<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DOES CIVILIZATION OWE A DEBT TO BEER?</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="24169"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARCHEOLOGY AND ANTHROPOLOGY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KATZ, SOLOMON H (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARRIS, MARVIN (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870324T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1D81F3CF937A15750C0A961948260" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DOES CIVILIZATION OWE A DEBT TO BEER?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: PHILADELPHIA, March 23 -</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: PHILADELPHIA, March 23 -</p>
        <p>PHILADELPHIA, March 23 -</p>
        <p>Why, 10,000 years or so ago, did people first settle down and go to all the trouble of sowing, cultivating and reaping crops? The question has long tantalized anthropologists and archeologists because once its answer is clear, they will know what sparked the long transformation of humans from wandering hunters into literate city dwellers.</p>
        <p>Beer did it, argues an anthropologist at the University of Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>The event that ''primed the pump,'' according to this new hypothesis, was the accidental discovery by prehistoric humans that wild wheat and barley soaked in water to make gruel, if left out in the open air, did not spoil. Instead, natural yeast in the air converted it to a dark, bubbling brew that made whoever drank it feel good. On top of that, the brew made people robust; at the time, it was second only to animal protein as a nutritional source.</p>
        <p>This combination of mood-altering and nutritional properties would have been incentive enough to cause neolithic hunter-gatherers in the Near East to begin cultivating the grains, Dr. Solomon H. Katz contends in an article published this month in Expedition, the journal of the Museum of Archeology/Anthropology at the University of Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>''My argument,'' Dr. Katz said in an interview, ''is that the initial discovery of a stable way to produce alcohol provided enormous motivation for continuing to go out and collect these seeds and try to get them to do better.'' The argument is buttressed, Dr. Katz wrote in his article, by the fact that ''almost invariably, individuals and societies appear to invest enormous amounts of effort and even risk'' in the pursuit of mind-altering foods and beverages.</p>
        <p>Strong motivation would have been required to break away from the hunting-gathering way of life, according to one view among archeologists, because - contrary to myth - hunting and gathering provided a higher and more reliable standard of living, with less work, than the onerous and often chancy pursuit of agriculture.</p>
        <p>Over the last two decades, specialists on the neolithic world have generally favored environmental and ecological explanations for the birth of agriculture. For instance, it has been commonly held that population increases forced neolithic peoples to search for ways to expand the food supply. But now, some scholars are beginning to doubt this explanation and are giving more weight to cultural factors. Dr. Katz's specialty is the study of the development of cuisine, broadly defined, as one such cultural factor.</p>
        <p>While Dr. Katz's beer hypothesis is likely to attract interest, skepticism is already being expressed. ''I would say it's an ingredient in the mix of causal factors,'' said Dr. Marvin Harris, an anthropologist at the University of Florida who is a theorist on cultural evolution, ''but I wouldn't want to put a kind of prime-mover status'' on it.</p>
        <p>What might have happened, said Dr. Harris, is that after the game animals of the late Pleistocene disappeared and deprived humans of their major source of food, people began combing the environment for anything that would sustain life. ''So what do you do with several tons of wild seeds you've just harvested?'' he asked. ''You settle down in a village and protect it. Meanwhile, the animals are coming closer to the stands of grain, and then there's a gradual transition over to domestication'' of both plants and animals. There is probably a ''symbiotic relationship'' between domestication of the two, he said.</p>
        <p>''There are plenty of plausible alternatives,'' he said. The process probably had its ''alcoholic aspect,'' he said, but ''the whole thing is a package.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Katz argues that grain-derived alcohol was the critical element. In many cultures, he says, the use of alcohol has been made so central to social and religious practice that any disruption of its supply would be seen as a serious problem. In the Near East, where agriculture and village life first appeared, the need to solve this problem could well have accounted for the transition from hunting and gathering, he said.</p>
        <p>The discovery of brewing could have happened quite easily, according to the anthropologist. First, he says, wheat and barley were soaked in water to make gruel. Some of the grains accidentally sprouted; and when tasted, were found to be sweet. For this reason they were saved, and eventually natural yeast in the air mixed with the watery gruel to produce a solution with perhaps 3 to 5 percent alcohol.</p>
        <p>The archeological record so far provides no direct evidence that beer-making prompted the cultivation of grain, Dr. Katz said. But, he wrote in his article, the beer hypothesis is compatible with one aspect of the record that has puzzled archeologists. At early neolithic village sites where stone tools used for cultivation were found, very few carbonized grain seeds were in evidence. Had they been more plentiful, it would have indicated that grain was used in the baking of bread, as is commonly believed. Since beer making does not require exposing grains to fire, he writes,''It could be an everyday activity and yet produce not a single carbonized seed.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, he said, narrow-necked storage vessels of the kind needed to promote carbonation have been found dating back to the beginnings of neolithic times. ''This vessel is so common through the world that it's incredible,'' he said. ''Every time you have one of these narrow necks, you know you've got something that's keeping the air and the oxygen outside and the carbon dioxide inside.'' The presence of carbon dioxide helped keep the brew acidic, in turn protecting it from the development of toxic qualities that can otherwise occur.</p>
        <p>By the time the neolithic village culture of the Near East had evolved into the city-states of Sumeria some 5,000 years ago, he said, beer-drinking had been raised to a high status. The world's oldest recipe, written on Sumerian tablets, is for beer. Another tablet contains a hymn to the beer goddess, Ninkasi.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
