<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY: TUESDAY, APRIL 14, 1987</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="30077"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DD1E3BF937A25757C0A961948260" item-length="1051" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY: TUESDAY, APRIL 14, 1987</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International A2-15</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International A2-15</p>
        <p>International A2-15</p>
        <p>In Moscow, George P. Shultz met with the Soviet Foreign Minister, Eduard A. Shevardnadze, for more than seven hours, including an unscheduled evening session. Page A1</p>
        <p>Mr. Shultz attended a Passover seder in Moscow for about 50 Jews who are seeking to emigrate. The seder was held at the residence of the American Ambassador. A1</p>
        <p>An agreement for a summit meeting between President Reagan and Mikhail S. Gorbachev is likely to be reached during Mr. Shultz's discussions in Moscow, White House officials said. A15</p>
        <p>Marine sergeants are deeply stung by various charges of espionage and rules violations against four marines. They expressed anger at the press for what they called the maligning of the Corps. A1</p>
        <p>South Africa's Government retreated from a complete ban on protests against detention without trial, saying the ban would not cover religious services. Church leaders vowed to go further in defying the decree. A1</p>
        <p>South Korea blamed the opposition for the suspension of constitutional debate ordered by President Chun Doo Hwan. The police tightened restrictions on one of the leaders, Kim Dae Jung. A3</p>
        <p>Korea's cancellation of a dialogue with opposition leaders creates a quandary for United States policy makers, officials said. They regard President Chun's announcement as a discouraging development. A3  News analysis: The Pope's visit to South America made apparent that he is a believer in the power of signs. Throughout the trip, the Pope used gestures and buzzwords to indicate his views on human rights controversies. A10</p>
        <p>Rajiv Gandhi faces a political crisis as the result of the recent forced resignation of the Indian Defense Minister. The event underscored internal divisions in the Prime Minister's Congress Party. A2</p>
        <p>In rice fields of Italy, the waters are troubled</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Israeli army kills Palestinian</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Palestinians meet to end rift</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Israeli corruption charges</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Terror group reported in India</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Qaddafi facing unhappy country</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Sandinistas test autonomy in east province</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>National A16-19, A23</p>
        <p>Housing officials are concerned that over the next decade more than half a million low- and moderate-income families may be ousted from federally subsidized apartments built in the 1960's and 1970's. A1</p>
        <p>American travel to Europe is expected to increase sharply this year despite the large decline in the value of the dollar, which raises the price of a vacation. A1</p>
        <p>Texaco's stock price fell in heavy trading as the large oil company tried to soothe the frazzled nerves of investors, lenders, suppliers and business partners in the wake of its bankruptcy filing on Sunday. D1</p>
        <p>Gary Hart will run for President, the former Senator from Colorado formally announced. Mr. Hart said he would run for the Democratic nomination because, ''I want America to do better and move forward.'' A16</p>
        <p>Complaints against airlines from consumers nearly doubled in March from the same time a year ago, and increased by 52 percent in the first three months of 1987, Federal government figures show. A16</p>
        <p>Delays at the Atlanta airport are very much on the minds of travelers and Federal officials. Hartsfield International has the worst rate of delays of any airport in the nation, a Federal report says. A16</p>
        <p>The work of Thomas Hart Benton, the Kansas City, Mo. artist, was celebrated by 1,000 admirers. Paintings by Mr. Benton, who died in 1975, were hung at one of the city's oldest inns, the type of place he said he preferred to art museums. A16</p>
        <p>Amy Carter testified at her trial on charges of disorderly conduct. She said she occupied a college building and blocked a road to prevent worse crimes by the Central Intelligence Agency. A17</p>
        <p>The discovery of a fossilized skull estimated to be 2.5 million years old led paleontologists to try to redraw humanity's family tree, but they disagree on how to do it. C1  Doctor testifies for Hinckley</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>The jet engine is 50 years old</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Army curbs Bradley vehicle</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>California moves against exclusive clubs</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>New president for Dartmouth</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Washington Talk A20</p>
        <p>Hart and rivals: Unconventional  Texaco: The capital shrugs  Regional B1-4, B6, B9</p>
        <p>Women are less likely to be hired by the New York City Fire Department because of a Federal appeals court decision, experts said. It weakened the impact of another decision that led the Fire Department to hire its first women. A1</p>
        <p>Six states will file a suit on acid rain to force the Federal Government to curb the air pollution that causes the environmental problem. It will charge that the Government has not enforced the Clean Air Act. B2</p>
        <p>Driver training for police recruits had weaknesses in the past, and the Police Academy is trying to impose tougher standards. Now the program is longer and includes a defensive driving course. B1</p>
        <p>Immigration officials are preparing for the estimated 750,000 illegal aliens in the area who will seek to legalize their status under the new Federal Immigration Law that takes effect May 5. B3  Prisoners will be issued condoms upon release from municipal jails, and homosexual prisoners will receive them upon request, officials said. The initiatives are part of an AIDS education effort. B6</p>
        <p>State lawmakers blocked funds for the Health Department's efforts to enforce new smoking regulations because they believe the rules were adopted illegally by the state's Public Health Council, officials said. B2</p>
        <p>Wedtech sues 2 auditors</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Titanic memorial tomorrow</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Discovery of ''brown tide'' roots</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Ex-M.T.A. chief accused of fraud</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Pact reached on hospital</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Landmark designations slowed in New York City</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Koch says city ready to run concrete plant</p>
        <p>B4</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
