<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DEMOCRATS TRADE GOWING REMARKS</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="61219"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1988</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GOVERNORS' ASSN, DEMOCRATIC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DIONNE, E J JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BABBITT, BRUCE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUKAKIS, MICHAEL S (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GEPHARDT, RICHARD A (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHROEDER, PATRICIA (REP)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, ALBERT JR (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BIDEN, JOSEPH R JR (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMON, PAUL (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JACKSON, JESSE L (REV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLANCHARD, JAMES J (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Richard A Gephardt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE6D7153FF933A05754C0A961948260" item-length="890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DEMOCRATS TRADE GOWING REMARKS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By E. J. DIONNE Jr., Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DIONNE, E J JR</byline>
      <dateline>MACKINAC ISLAND, Mich., July 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: On an island of unworldly peacefulness where cars are banned and the horse and buggy vies with the bicycle as the means of transportation, eight Democratic Presidential candidates told Democratic governors today how they would lead their party to victory and the nation into the 21st century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: On an island of unworldly peacefulness where cars are banned and the horse and buggy vies with the bicycle as the means of transportation, eight Democratic Presidential candidates told Democratic governors today how they would lead their party to victory and the nation into the 21st century.</p>
        <p>On an island of unworldly peacefulness where cars are banned and the horse and buggy vies with the bicycle as the means of transportation, eight Democratic Presidential candidates told Democratic governors today how they would lead their party to victory and the nation into the 21st century.</p>
        <p>For a party well-noted for fractiousness, the talk was nearly as ethereal as the island itself, a haven of mansions, whitewashed houses and cedar groves in the pale blue straits where Lake Huron meets Lake Michigan.</p>
        <p>Governors and candidates, who got together here at a meeting of the Democratic Governors' Association, vied with one another to make the most glowing comments about their party and their counterparts. Governor Cuomo of New York may have gone farthest, describing the Democratic Presidential field as ''the best ever assembled'' and ''an embarrassment of riches.''</p>
        <p>But reality presses in, even on Mackinac Island, and Bruce Babbitt, the former Governor of Arizona, called the party back to the matters of budget deficits and hard choices. Sales Tax Is Favored</p>
        <p>Mr. Babbitt told the governors that the time had come to end ''the conspiracy of silence'' around the Federal budget deficit and to talk of awful things, like raising taxes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Babbitt's choice is for what he refers to as a ''consumption tax,'' essentially a national sales tax. He called for a 5 percent rate that he said would raise $40 billion to $50 billion a year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Babbitt, who will detail his proposal in a speech in Washington on Thursday, said the tax would be designed in a way that would limit its impact on people with lower income. He would do this either by exempting certain basic items, including health care, housing and food, or by refunding payments to lower-income people, rebates they would apply for on their income tax returns.</p>
        <p>After that, the reality of political competition pressed in, too. While praising Mr. Babbitt as forthright, three of his adversaries immediately came out against the tax. They were Gov. Michael S. Dukakis of Massachusetts and Representatives Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri and Patricia Schroeder of Colorado. Senator Albert Gore Jr. of Tennessee said he was generally against consumption taxes but wanted to study Mr. Babbitt's proposal further.</p>
        <p>Two other candidates, Senator Joseph R. Biden Jr. of Delaware and Senator Paul Simon of Illinois, departed before they could be questioned, Mr. Biden before the meeting even ended. Risks Cited by Jackson</p>
        <p>The Rev. Jesse Jackson took a philosophical view in not commenting on Mr. Babbitt's plan. ''Different candidates have to take the risks they must take as part of the struggle to win national identity,'' Mr. Jackson said. ''That's part of the primary process.'' The visit here, though, was no risk at all for anyone, and it produced a pleasant interlude in the political struggle. For more than three hours the candidates were closeted with 19 governors at the Grand Hotel, a splendid relic of 19th-century wealth.</p>
        <p>The meeting was closed to the press - Gov. James J. Blanchard of Michigan, who arranged the retreat, said this promoted honest discussion - but afterward the participants talked a lot about what went on.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blanchard said the main goal was to enlist the power of incumbent Democratic governors behind the eventual Presidential nominee and to get the party's candidates to listen to the advice of proved election winners before it was too late. Mr. Dukakis noted that Democratic Presidential candidates usually consulted governors after the national convention, ''when there's not time to talk, to think, to listen and to reflect.''</p>
        <p>One of the concrete suggestions made at the meeting was offered by Mr. Cuomo. Noting that the party was often divided by regional issues, he suggested that he and Gov. Bill Clinton of Arkansas work together to formulate solutions to these problems. Both Governors were looked upon by many people as Presidential candidates but declined to run. Clinton Suggests Topics</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said after the meeting that he hoped he and Mr. Cuomo would get together and listed three areas where they might begin: a tax on imported oil, acid rain, and requirements that employers provide health insurance.</p>
        <p>In the meeting, Mr. Clinton warned his fellow Democrats not to make dismissive statements about the current candidates. As the sort of comments to avoid he cited two frequently heard statements: that Mr. Dukakis could not win because is he is of Greek descent or that Mr. Gore was not ''a real Southerner.'' He said such statements would ''trivialize the process'' and ''demean candidates.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo said after the meeting that he had warned the Democrats about the dangers of balancing the Federal budget, which he said might throw the country into recession and force draconian cuts in programs. ''How can you do it immediately?'' Mr. Cuomo said he told the governors. ''That would savage everything - social programs, defense.''</p>
        <p>According to the participants, the meeting ended after Mr. Jackson said the party needed not only ''numbers,'' but also ''feeling.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Blanchard, struggling to end the meeting, sought words to express his agreement with Mr. Jackson.</p>
        <p>''Why don't you just say 'Amen,' Governor?'' Mr. Jackson suggested, and Mr. Blanchard did. And thus ended the meeting.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
