<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY: FRIDAY, JULY 31, 1987</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="61448"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2DB1339F932A05754C0A961948260" item-length="1089" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY: FRIDAY, JULY 31, 1987</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International A2-10  Donald T. Regan testified that President Reagan felt he had been repeatedly ''snookered'' by Iranians into believing that continued arms sales would lead to the release of more American hostages. Page A1  President Reagan told aides to protect American hostages in Lebanon by limiting disclosure and instead make statements that pointed up inaccuracies in press accounts, according to notes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International A2-10  Donald T. Regan testified that President Reagan felt he had been repeatedly ''snookered'' by Iranians into believing that continued arms sales would lead to the release of more American hostages. Page A1  President Reagan told aides to protect American hostages in Lebanon by limiting disclosure and instead make statements that pointed up inaccuracies in press accounts, according to notes.</p>
        <p>International A2-10  Donald T. Regan testified that President Reagan felt he had been repeatedly ''snookered'' by Iranians into believing that continued arms sales would lead to the release of more American hostages. Page A1  President Reagan told aides to protect American hostages in Lebanon by limiting disclosure and instead make statements that pointed up inaccuracies in press accounts, according to notes. A10  India said peacekeepers will stay in northern Sri Lanka until New Delhi decides their mission has been completed. Sri Lanka had said the Indian contingent would report to the local commander. A1  A bomb exploded in Johannesburg outside a military barracks. The blast wounded 70 people, including several soldiers, and caused extensive damage to surrounding buildings. A6  A U.S. helicopter crashed into the Persian Gulf, killing one man and leaving three missing, military officials said. The copter was not under attack, and officials offered no explanation for the accident. A3  The Kremlin accused U.S. diplomats of fomenting demonstrations by Cri-mean Tatars. Several hundred Tatars have staged demonstrations in Moscow seeking to return to Crimea, from which they were deported by Stalin in 1944. A3  Kenneth L. Adelman is resigning as director of the Arms Control and Disarmament Agency. He expressed satisfaction that Washington and Moscow were moving toward a ban on medium-range and shorter-range arms. A3  Britain's top court barred the press from reporting the memoirs of Peter Wright, a retired intelligence agent, even though his book is available in London, fresh from an American publisher. A1  Mexican plane crashes; 39 die  A3  U.S. reconsiders Panama aid  A3  London journal  A4  Israeli proposes ouster of Arabs  A5  National A12-13, B6-8, B20  Abortion counseling would be barred from Federal funding in family planning clinics under new rules proposed by President Reagan. Mr. Reagan has repeatedly failed to win Congressional approval of measures to ban abortions. A1  The abortion rules proposed by President Reagan could severely limit the services provided by more than 4,000 clinics that receive Federal funds, according to family planning professionals. B8  Newly found natural antibiotics first detected in frogs apparently kill a wide variety of bacteria, fungi, parasites and possibly viruses. The antibiotics hold promise of treating many human infections. A1  Foreign investors are helping to push American stock market indexes to historic highs, according to traders and experts. They credited not only the Japanese, but also Europeans and Australians. A1  Leading indicators rose in June for the fifth consecutive month, the Commerce Department reported. The gain of eight-tenths of 1 percent was slightly higher than had been generally expected. D1  The nation's poverty rate eased last year to 13.6 percent, the lowest level since President Reagan took office, the Census Bureau reported. A bureau official acknowledged a rise in income inequality. A12  The President will be hospitalized today to have a skin cancer removed from the tip of his nose, the White House said. Experts say such cancers are almost never life-threatenting and are easy to cure by cutting away the cancerous skin. A1  Testing for the AIDS virus would be greatly expanded on a voluntary basis with strict civil rights guarantees under legislation introduced by Congressional leaders, backed by many major health groups. A12  A new spending cut mechanism for the budget balancing law that could put off major decisions on the deficit and tax increases until after the 1988 elections has been endorsed by Senate Democratic and Republican leaders. A12  The fabled King Ranch is struggling through one of the toughest eras in its 134-year history. The vast South Texas ranch has laid off or given early retirement to more than half of its employees. A1  Washington Talk B6  M.I.A.'s and the politics of hope  Acid rain lobby stirs debate  Byrd assails Reagan's stance  A12  Minutes with Kemp without Kemp  B7  Computers replace coziness for Republicans in Iowa  B7  Significance seen in Guam disease  B20  Regional B1-5  New York's biggest crack ring was broken, officials said. A Federal indictment named 29 people, including a 26-year-old Dominican identified as the leader. The authorities said the group distributed up to 10,000 vials of crack a day, primarily in Washington Heights and the Bronx. B1  Oxygen levels are dangerously low in several parts of western Long Island Sound and constitute a serious threat to the region's fishing industry, according to scientists and environmental offficials. B2  A labor leader will serve as a temporary ''observer'' on the board of the Metropolitan Transportation Authority until Governor Cuomo appoints a permanent member. Labor leaders said Sonny Hall would be the observer because Mr. Cuomo refused to appoint another leader, Victor Gotbaum, to the seat. B3  A bill to enhance jury service by raising the daily pay to $15 and doubling to four years the time between summonses had been endorsed by court officials but was vetoed by Governor Cuomo as too costly. B3  Sharply higher garbage disposal fees in the 22 municipalities in Essex County, N.J., were approved by state regulators. An official said the soaring charges represented a major emergency. B2  A jury cited hopeless deadlock on charges that three reputed Mafia figures had slain a police detective on a Queens street. After nine days of deliberation the jury foreman said the vote was 9 to 3 for acquittal. B1  B3  O'Connor defends AIDS role  A12  In Manhattan, panhandlers sometimes seem ubiquitous  B1  Solitude lapse for spurned statue  B1  176 apparent food poisonings at municipal hospital  B3  Feminists file Baby M brief  B3  Man triumphs over monkey  B3</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
