<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Storage of Propane in Blast May Have Broken the Law</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="58877"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PROPANE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXPLOSIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOROUGH PARK (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BROOKLYN (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDMAN, ARI L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Explosions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2D71F3AF931A15754C0A961948260" item-length="817" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Storage of Propane in Blast May Have Broken the Law</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ARI L. GOLDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDMAN, ARI L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The propane that exploded yesterday in a basement in Brooklyn, causing the collapse of several buildings and the loss of four lives, was apparently stored illegally, fire and gas officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The propane that exploded yesterday in a basement in Brooklyn, causing the collapse of several buildings and the loss of four lives, was apparently stored illegally, fire and gas officials said.</p>
        <p>The propane that exploded yesterday in a basement in Brooklyn, causing the collapse of several buildings and the loss of four lives, was apparently stored illegally, fire and gas officials said.</p>
        <p>Under the regulations of the Department of Buildings, propane cannot be stored in a basement.</p>
        <p>''The floors of such rooms'' that are used for the storage of propane ''shall not be located below ground level,'' according to Directive No. 6 of 1974 of the building department.</p>
        <p>According to the Fire Department, yesterday's explosion occurred when delivery men accidentally dropped a 20-pound container of propane as it was being taken to the basement of a plumbing supplies store in the Borough Park section. The propane fell down the stairs and went crashing into propane tanks already stored in the basement, the officials said. Questions of Compliance</p>
        <p>Witnesses said that the tank, which holds gas under pressure, was leaking as it fell. The explosion, experts speculated, might have occurred from a spark caused by the friction from the fall or from the exposure of the gas to an electric light in the basement. An electrical spark was needed because the dropping of a tank by itself would not cause an explosion, the experts said.</p>
        <p>''On the face of it, it would seem that there is some question as to whether there was compliance with the law in this case,'' said William M. Feehan, assistant bureau chief of fire prevention for the New York City Fire Department.</p>
        <p>Chief Feehan said that an investigation was under way to determine whether the plumbing company complied with additional regulations governing propane, including the requirement that the buyer have city permits.</p>
        <p>Propane, also known as liquid petroleum gas, is one of the most versatile of fossil fuels. ''It can do everything that natural gas can do but it has the added advantage of being portable,'' according to Carol McAdam, a spokeswoman for the National L.P. Gas Association.</p>
        <p>Because of its portability, propane is widely used in rural areas that do not have public utility service. A popular use is to run heaters and appliances in mobile homes. #15 Billion Gallons Used In suburban areas, propane is especially popular for firing outdoor barbeque grills. According to the L.P. Gas Association, those grills are growing in popularity, with more than 3 million sold last year.</p>
        <p>The gas also has numerous commercial uses. Plumbers use it to repair lead pipes and roofers use it to melt tar. It is also a popular fuel for fork lifts.</p>
        <p>Although not usually associated with New York City, propane is common at construction sites and at street fairs, where it is used to fire grills.</p>
        <p>Propane supplies 3 to 4 percent of the nation's energy needs. More than 15 billion gallons of it are used each year.</p>
        <p>Ms. McAdam said that the association ''prides itself on its safety record,'' adding that users should not be alarmed at the Brooklyn accident.</p>
        <p>''Like any fuel, improper or illegal use, such as in this instance, can lead to accidents,'' she said. Dangerous Leakage Possible</p>
        <p>In December 1983 in Buffalo, illegally stored propane was the cause of an explosion and fire that killed 6 people, including 5 firefighters, and injured more than 70 others.</p>
        <p>One common problem with outdoor grills is that users paint over the gas tanks, often hiding any corrosion that might take place in the metal shell. This can lead to dangerous leakage. Ms. McAdam said a booklet on the safe use of outdoor grills is available free from the association, which is in Oak Brook, Ill. The telephone number is (312) 573-4800.</p>
        <p>Ms. McAdam said that the New York City code that prohibits the storage of propane below ground level is consistent with recommendations of the American National Standards Institute, a national advisory board. Numerous Restrictions</p>
        <p>At the fire scene yesterday, at 18th Avenue and 50th Street, Police Commissioner Benjamin Ward said: ''We don't really know what started it. We think it was a propane tank. We don't know yet if there was a violation. The fire marshals will probably spend all night determining that.''</p>
        <p>The New York City regulations governing the use of propane are lengthy. In addition to the prohibition of storing the gas below ground level, there are numerous restrictions on storing it indoors. Many companies store propane in outdoor areas.</p>
        <p>For example, the regulations require that the room where the propane is stored must be used for propane storage only and must have heavy fire resistant walls, floor, ceiling and doors. The building in which it is housed must also be able to withstand an explosion by having breakable glass that can relieve the pressure in the event of an accident. In addition, all lights and switches should be ''explosion proof.''</p>
        <p>A sign must be posted with letters at least 2 inches high saying: ''Danger L.P. gas. Keep fire or flame away. No smoking.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
