<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FREE WILL IS OUR ONLY CHOICE</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="66353"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAWES, ELIZABETH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PARKIN, FRANK</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MIND AND BODY SHOP, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">REVIEW</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFD61E38F935A2575BC0A961948260" item-length="1081" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FREE WILL IS OUR ONLY CHOICE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH HAWES; Elizabeth Hawes, who writes frequently on cultural affairs, is at work on a book about the early history of the luxury apartment in New York City.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAWES, ELIZABETH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  THE MIND AND BODY SHOP  By Frank Parkin 221 pp. New York: Atheneum. $14.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  THE MIND AND BODY SHOP  By Frank Parkin 221 pp. New York: Atheneum. $14.95.</p>
        <p>THE MIND AND BODY SHOP  By Frank Parkin 221 pp. New York: Atheneum. $14.95.</p>
        <p>THE second novel by Frank Parkin, ''The Mind and Body Shop,'' is a black comedy that aspires to be a mordant social satire. Its energy is spent in witty observation rather than sustained message or narrative drive. It is restless and ruthless, but ultimately so chipper that one surmises that a serious professor of political thought - Mr. Parkin is a tutor in politics and fellow of Magdalen College, Oxford University, and the author of four books on political science -has sought comic relief by indulging in high-minded high jinks.</p>
        <p>As in ''Krippendorf's Tribe,'' his well-received first novel, Mr. Parkin's strengths lie in his wordplay, his metaphors, his significant effects: ''He laughed at the back of his throat, giving off a sound like one Jackson Pollock being scraped across the surface of another.'' His eye and tongue are sharp, and his every sentence supplies a striking distortion, or projection, of reality. Under the guise of a portrait of the modern English university, he takes on the decay of modern society, and with what amounts to a checklist of contemporary ills, from aerosol spray paint to mobile vasectomy vans and fingernail clippings in the Parmesan cheese, he annotates a diabolical version of modern life. '' [ The students ]  were like cockroaches in the central heating. Crammed in among the steaming bodies he felt more strongly than ever that the very concept of student had become outdated.''</p>
        <p>From time to time, as if to monitor a reader's vision, Mr. Parkin raises his head to scan the horizon, where the honeysuckle is shriveled, the new homes -on streets named for the Pre-Raphaelites - are laid between the nuclear waste disposal plant and the army firing range, and the ''sun flicker [ s ]  intermittently behind a bank of cloud, like a lightbulb in a faulty socket.'' The dense accumulation of detail is potentially hilarious, and yet the very surfeit of riches ultimately obstructs the vision promised by the acuity of perception and the facility of the prose. That Mr. Parkin's modern university is indistinguishable from the shallow and desensitized society outside its walls is both the point and the problem of the book.</p>
        <p>The setting at the university is Orwellian. In the opening scene of the book, as the vice chancellor, formerly a sales representative for Consolidated Tractor Fuels, makes his way from his moped to his wall-bars to exercise, acid rain is falling on the campus; on the library, which flies the flag of its current corporate sponsor; on lecture theaters guarded by coin-operated turnstiles; on the Khomeini Center for the Propagation of Islam, a white-marble mosque that has effectively supplanted the Ivory Tower. Professors, in quest of profit, glory and customer satisfaction, are in service to military despots, the Mafia and genetic engineers; neurotic students steal food, attempt suicide and pursue courses in social and economic forecasting, catering, cosmetic surgery and the martial arts; venerable collections of books are sold off to a university in Texas.</p>
        <p>Beyond the traditional term markings of Michaelmas, Lent and Trinity, the only remnant of the comfortable old backwater of scholarship and learning is shuffling 62-year-old Douglas Hambro, professor of metaphysical philosophy, whose flagging department is the book's focus of concern. The Mind and Body Shop of the title is a last-ditch attempt to revive this lone outpost of the humanities, where in collaboration with the Bangkok Pleasure Palace, courses like Spinoza in the Jacuzzi, Schopenhauer in the Shopping Hour and Kierkegaard-a-GoGo are offered - where thesis and antithesis merge into a synthesis, and spirit unites with matter. HAMBRO is an old-fashioned fool in a world of modern fools, and his distress is mute. He takes refuge from academic anarchy in his outhouse, where he has enshrined his Orwell memorabilia and ''the precarious world of order and meaning,'' and he fashions his life after Orwell's, marrying a charwoman (to transcend the class barrier), starving in Paris and, in the end - smiling, as jaunty as ''a volunteer marching to the front in a just cause'' -abandoning the university for a flophouse. He is a sad and bathetic figure, too remote to evoke real sympathy, too shadowy to support a reader's ready outrage.</p>
        <p>Perhaps it is the introduction of Orwell onto the scene - Orwell with his deeply felt experience and his insistent message - that ultimately causes disappointment by raising the hope of deliverance. ''The Mind and Body Shop'' provides an uncomfortable madcap vision. Like most good satire, it seems to be born of virtue, intended to civilize a dull and insensitive world. But finally it chooses to entertain rather than disturb or reform. For all its bleakness of scene and frequent prurience of humor, it is almost chirpy. If there is a message, it is delivered by Hambro's enterprising petty-thief father-in-law, who says, as he embarks on a new career in philosophy, ''What I reckon is . . . that we got to accept the argument for Free Will because we got no other choice.'' Hambro, in parting, asks, ''Wasn't it Merleau-Ponty who said that whatever happened to philosophy today would happen to the world tomorrow?''  Orwell's Sister's Kitty's Dish</p>
        <p>He sighed with contentment as he made himself comfortable in the rickety bentwood chair that had once belonged to George Orwell during his Hampstead period. Humming quietly to himself he took out his pipe and scraped the bowl over the chipped saucer that Orwell had also used as an ashtray while typing the final draft of 1984. Block-mounted photographs covered one entire wall: Orwell as a boy of three in naval uniform; Orwell feeding his goat; Orwell talking into a BBC microphone; Orwell's chest X-ray; Orwell's dog on Southwold beach; Orwell's sister; Orwell's sister's cat; Orwell's sister's cat's feeding bowl. Each photograph was neatly labelled and numbered according to a code. . . .</p>
        <p>Hambro reached for his index cards and proceeded to write detailed entries for the three most recent acquisitions to his collection of memorabilia. These were a dummy packet of gravy powder from Orwell's grocery shop in Wallington, the red and black ribbon on which Orwell had typed the final version of A Clergyman's Daughter, and a size twelve and a half army boot that Orwell had probably worn on the Aragon front. - From ''The Mind and Body Shop.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
