<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY: SATURDAY, DECEMBER 19, 1987</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="103054"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4DE113EF93AA25751C1A961948260" item-length="1062" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY: SATURDAY, DECEMBER 19, 1987</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL 3-8  Press freedom in Britain eroded because of legal actions against newspapers and broadcasters in 1987, in the view of journalists, civil libertarians and some politicians. Page 1  In Seoul, militant protesters, denouncing South Korea's presidential election as fraudulent, skirmished with riot policemen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL 3-8  Press freedom in Britain eroded because of legal actions against newspapers and broadcasters in 1987, in the view of journalists, civil libertarians and some politicians. Page 1  In Seoul, militant protesters, denouncing South Korea's presidential election as fraudulent, skirmished with riot policemen.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL 3-8  Press freedom in Britain eroded because of legal actions against newspapers and broadcasters in 1987, in the view of journalists, civil libertarians and some politicians. Page 1  In Seoul, militant protesters, denouncing South Korea's presidential election as fraudulent, skirmished with riot policemen. But most middle-class Koreans seemed prepared to accept the election results. 8  News analysis: Washington gambled by endorsing the legitimacy of Wednesday's election results in South Korea, but the odds appear to be in Washington's favor. 8  Corazon Aquino signed an order dropping Gregorio Honasan, a coup leader, from the military. Her action marks a low point for one of the heroes of the revolt that ousted Ferdinand E. Marcos. 4  Three Palestinians were shot dead by the Israeli Army as widespread violence again swept through the occupied Gaza Strip. The clashes were a blow to hopes that a reinforced troop presence would end the violence. 3  Kenya ousted two diplomats from Uganda, ordering them to leave the country within 24 hours, four days after growing tensions between the East African neighbors erupted in a gun battle between Ugandan and Kenyan security forces along their border. 6  Man in the News: Milos Jakes, the man named General Secretary of the Czechoslovak Communist Party on Thursday, is believed by the Czechoslovaks to have impeccable qualifications. His selection proved to be no surpise. 8  Paraguay's oldest political prisoner completed a 25-year jail term but he was not immediately set free. The prisoner, Napoleon Ortigoza Gomez, has been in solitary confinement since 1962. 6  U.S. expelling Russian at.N.  3  Karachi journal: The bride wore white  4  Navy's electronic ''spotter'' ship is near the Persian Gulf  6  NATIONAL 10, 28, 32-33  Texaco and Pennzoil have agreed in principle to settle their tumultuous legal dispute for $3 billion, a lawyer for Texaco said. The agreement will be the centerpiece of a $5.5 billion plan to extricate Texaco from bankruptcy. 1  Ivan F. Boesky was sentenced to three years in prison for conspiring to falsify stock trading records. Mr. Boesky, once one of the financial world's most powerful speculators, has become a symbol of Wall Street's excesses. 1  Stock prices rallied sharply, regaining all the ground lost in Thursday's sharp selloff and extending Wall Street's rally to two weeks. The Dow Jones industrial average jumped 50.90 points to close at 1,975.30. 1  President Reagan threatened to veto the bill needed to put this year's budget compromise into effect if it does not contain support that he considers ''adequate'' to sustain the contras into February. 1  A Congressman was reprimanded by the House of Representatives. The Congressman, Austin J. Murphy of Pennsylvania, was found to have violated House rules by having someone vote for him twice in 1978. 10  In an AIDS policy for the military, officials said they will remove personnel infected with the virus from sensitive, stressful jobs because of evidence that the virus can impair mental function, even in people who show no symptoms. 1  Iowa's Democratic headquarters has become a one-stop shop providing campaign services to all the party's candidates. The party is cashing in on the demand created by the Presidential nominating caucuses. 10  Seeking to cut the defense budget, the headquarters of military commanders around the world will be streamlined and their staffs reduced, Secretary of Defense Frank C. Carlucci has told the commanders. 33  The 'hole' in the ozone layer over Antarctica remained weeks longer than usual this year along with a mass of extremely cold air, scientists reported. They said that they could give no explanation for the events. 33  College presidents wives: From helpmate to colleague 10  Russians plan two missions to explore Mars 28  Bush is hoping to cut damage in arms memo 32  Massachusetts reaches accord on health bill 32  Deaver prosecutor asks tougher conflict laws 32  Congress united on one goal: the rush to adjourn 33  REGIONAL 29-32  Hospitalization of Joyce Brown, a 40-year-old homeless woman whose case has become a test of the city's powers to remove disturbed homeless people from the streets, was upheld in an appeals court. 1  Emergency rooms are being closed and ambulances diverted to less crowded hospitals due to overcrowding in New York City hospitals, officials said. ''There has been a huge increase in diversions,'' one official said. 29  The police violated guidelines when undercover officers of the New York City Police Department attended meetings of a civil rights organization, officials said. 29  Garbage collection in New Jersey is suddenly in upheaval in the heavily populated northern part of the state more than 10 years after it set out to close landfills and force its counties to draft plans for disposing of their trash. 29  Two boutiques discriminated against black men by denying them entrance or by treating them differently from white men, the New York City Human Rights Commission charged. The boutiques are on the Upper East Side. 29  In the schools chancellor search, the list of candidates for the post in the New York City school system has been narrowed to eight names, according to people familiar with the screening process. 31  The battle over the future of Lilco and its $5 billion Shoreham nuclear power plant took a decisive turn as state officials, Lilco officials and their investment bankers met as a group for the first time. 30  A former Mafia leader was sentenced to 25 years in prison for a 1980 conviction on extortion charges. The former leader, Alphonse (Allie Boy) Persico, had been a fugitive seven years, until his arrest last month. 31  Christmas scenes at Brooklyn home stand out 29  Two in Yonkers quit city posts 30  Dinkins seeks special inquiry 31  Howard Beach jury deliberates for a ninth day 31  Neediest Cases 32</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
