<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deaver Prosecutor Assails Administration Action</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="86835"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERJURY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIALS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRANKLIN, BEN A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEAVER, MICHAEL K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEYMOUR, WHITNEY NORTH JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEEDC1239F934A15753C1A961948260" item-length="642" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deaver Prosecutor Assails Administration Action</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN A. FRANKLIN, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRANKLIN, BEN A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The special prosecutor in the perjury trial of Michael K. Deaver accused the Reagan Administration today of seeking ''improperly to influence the outcome'' of the case.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The special prosecutor in the perjury trial of Michael K. Deaver accused the Reagan Administration today of seeking ''improperly to influence the outcome'' of the case.</p>
        <p>The special prosecutor in the perjury trial of Michael K. Deaver accused the Reagan Administration today of seeking ''improperly to influence the outcome'' of the case.</p>
        <p>The trial of Mr. Deaver, a former deputy White House chief of staff and a close friend of the President and Nancy Reagan, is set to open Tuesday, and jury selection was completed today in Federal District Court here.</p>
        <p>The charge by the special prosecutor, Whitney North Seymour Jr., came in connection with his efforts to gain the testimony of Canada's Ambassador to the United States, Allan E. Gotlieb. Mr. Deaver set up a lobbying firm after he left the White House in 1985, and a charge against him is that he lied about his actions in behalf of Canada regarding American policy on acid rain. Collusion Is Charged</p>
        <p>The Canadian Government has refused to allow Mr. Gotlieb to be subpoenaed for the trial. Mr. Seymour, in private communications with a lawyer representing Canada, has asked Ottawa to reconsider, and the Justice Department has objected to his action outside regular diplomatic channels.</p>
        <p>In papers filed this morning with the court here, Mr. Seymour charged that the Justice Department had ''teamed up with'' Mr. Deaver's defense counsel ''to stage an attack on the independent counsel.'' Mr. Seymour said the episode ''reconfirms the wisdom of separating the conduct of prosecutions of high Government officials from the Administration in power.''</p>
        <p>A Justice Department lawyer, David Anderson, asked District Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson today to ''instruct'' Mr. Seymour to refrain from ''making threats'' that were ''a danger to relations with our closest ally.'' Mr. Anderson and Herbert J. Miller, Mr. Deaver's lead counsel, quoted a letter from Mr. Seymour to Stuart Pierson, a lawyer representing Canada, as saying that Ambassador Gotlieb's unwillingness to testify would force the prosecutor to ''place much more emphasis on the unlawful acts of Mr. Deaver'' in his promotion of Canadian interests. Administration Is Disappointed</p>
        <p>But Judge Jackson, saying that the Ambassador would not be subpoenaed against his will, ruled that Mr. Seymour's ''Canadian overture'' was proper and ''was not an attempt to coerce Canada.''</p>
        <p>A Justice Department spokeswoman, Amy Brown, said later that the Administration was ''disappointed'' that the court had not ordered Mr. Seymour to conduct any future communications with the Canadians ''through proper diplomatic channels'' at the State Department. But she said the department was ''pleased'' that Judge Jackson had ''reiterated that the Canadian Ambassador is protected by diplomatic immunity.''</p>
        <p>The Justice Department said it would have no comment on a demand by Mr. Seymour that Pat Korten, a department spokesman, retract an earlier assertion that the independent prosecutor had ''violated Justice Department reguations'' by having direct contact with Canadians. Open Jury Selection</p>
        <p>Judge Jackson also denied today a motion by Mr. to dismiss the part of the Deaver indictment, one of five counts of lying under oath, that relates to Mr. Deaver's acid rain activities as a paid lobbyist for the Canadians. The 16 jurors - seven men and nine women, including four alternates - were selected over a period of a week in open court after Judge Jackson's attempt to screen jurors in secret was barred by a higher court. Newsgathering agencies argued successfully before the Federal Court of Appeals here that the jury selection must take place in open court.</p>
        <p>The Judge said late today that the final pretrial issue would be whether, or to what extent, the prosecutor can inform the jurors that Mr. Deaver may have committed ''other crimes'' - the influence peddling with which he is not formally charged, but about which he is accused of lying to a House subcommittee and a Federal grand jury.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
