<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crowding the Seashore on Every Coast</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="64397"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="IDEAS &amp; TRENDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEACHES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUPREME COURT (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LINDSEY, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5D91E3AF93AA3575BC0A961948260" item-length="1181" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crowding the Seashore on Every Coast</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT LINDSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LINDSEY, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ON shrinking beaches, the crowds are thicker than they used to be. More than half of America's population lives within 50 miles of the ocean or Great Lakes, and that proportion is rising quickly. And despite erosion, pollution and proliferating condos, each year more people go to the beach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ON shrinking beaches, the crowds are thicker than they used to be. More than half of America's population lives within 50 miles of the ocean or Great Lakes, and that proportion is rising quickly. And despite erosion, pollution and proliferating condos, each year more people go to the beach.</p>
        <p>ON shrinking beaches, the crowds are thicker than they used to be. More than half of America's population lives within 50 miles of the ocean or Great Lakes, and that proportion is rising quickly. And despite erosion, pollution and proliferating condos, each year more people go to the beach.</p>
        <p>That can be difficult, however. In most coastal states the public owns the beach from the water's edge to the high-tide mark, but getting there, or staking out a piece of dry sand, is another matter. To those on the inside looking out, whoever owns the beachfront owns the ocean. Property owners and municipalities, unsettled by the summer crowds, generally budge only when they have to. And, increasingly, to provide facilities for outsiders, locally run beaches charge admission fees.</p>
        <p>As basic principles of private property and public trust clash, most states are favoring the public. Florida has acquired 22 miles of sandy beachfront since 1982, and has set aside $5.5 million to acquire paths to the water through private property. In New Jersey, municipal beaches can no longer turn away nonresidents. California's Coastal Commission, although it was brushed back recently by the Supreme Court, has opened rights of way to many beaches near private homes.</p>
        <p>All efforts are frustrated by the erosion of almost every mile of coastline, from the narrowing barrier islands of the Atlantic to Louisiana, which is losing 100 acres a day, to California, where miles of bluff have crumbled into the ocean. The process, a consequence of rising sea levels, is hastened by overdevelopment.</p>
        <p>But the tide of people is rising, too. Five state beaches in Massachusetts had 970,000 visitors in 1976, 2.7 million in 1986. In that period attendance at Florida state parks, most of them on the beach, rose about 40 percent and would have been higher if the parks did not turn away visitors. Connecticut state beaches have also been turning people away this year.</p>
        <p>Making more room for the crowds makes economic and political sense for most states. The following reports describe what several of them are doing.  MIGRATION CLOSES IN  California's Open Beaches Feeling the Strain</p>
        <p>CALIFORNIANS have unlimited access to hundreds of miles of beaches, including the sandy front yards of multimillion-dollar beachfront homes. There are open spaces that would cause envy on the East Coast, but even California is encountering limits.</p>
        <p>California, with more than 27 million people, illustrates the pressures building on the nation's beaches. Along its 1,100 miles of coast there are long stretches of sand, especially in lightly populated central and northern parts of the state, where people can laze in virtual isolation. But here in Los Angeles County, even with more than 30 miles of county beaches, and in San Diego, population growth is making it harder and harder to find a private space on the beach.</p>
        <p>''By the year 2000, almost 80 percent of the people will be living within 50 miles of the coast,'' said Gary Magnuson, director of the Coastal States Organization, a Washington-based association of governors from shoreline states. ''And as more and more people move to the coast there's going to be more and more pressure for public access to the beaches.''</p>
        <p>In California, few legal controversies over access arose until recently because the coast, like Oregon's and Washington's, has remained largely open. Most of its more than 100 state and 25 local beaches are free.</p>
        <p>The California Constitution, enacted more than 130 years ago, declared that private property owners could not prevent access to navigable waters ''whenever it is required for any public purpose.'' In 1972, voters passed a law establishing the California Coastal Commission to enforce that and other coastal-protection measures.</p>
        <p>The commission has opened to the public dozens of miles of beaches that were previously difficult or impossible to reach. In many cases, it has done so by requiring property owners to allow the public to cross their property as a condition of permitting construction or remodeling of buildings on the beach. The United States Supreme Court struck down one such permit condition recently, but the decision is expected to have limited effect.</p>
        <p>Notwithstanding that decision, many experts see legislative and judicial trends moving in the direction that the West Coast states took from the beginning.</p>
        <p>''In a global, national sense, the prospects are getting better for beach access,'' said Michael L. Fischer, executive director of the Sierra Club in San Francisco. ''The trend is inexorable,'' agreed Donald Neuwirth, a San Francisco consultant on waterfront planning who helped design California's coastal access rules. The Texas Example</p>
        <p>Mr. Fischer and Mr. Neuwirth said state or local governments in Florida, Texas, North Carolina and several other states had lowered barriers to use of their beaches. ''In many ways, Texas, which passed an open beaches act that makes beaches a public right of way, is the best in the country when it comes to providing access,'' Mr. Fischer said.</p>
        <p>California's efforts appeared to suffer a setback with the Supreme Court decision in June. The 5-to-4 decision overturned a state court's ruling permitting the Coastal Commission to require the buyers of a beachfront lot in Ventura County, James and Marilyn Nollan, to donate an easement running parallel to the shore to permit direct passage between two neighboring public beaches. The easement was a condition for allowing the couple to build a larger house, which the commission contended would interfere with ''visual access'' to the beach.</p>
        <p>In their appeal, the Nollans' attorney, Ronald E. Zumbrun, said the state was trying to ''acquire property for itself without compensation as a payoff for the issuance of a permit.'' And the Supreme Court declared that California's beach access policy may ''be a good idea,'' but said that if the state ''wants an easement across the Nollans' property, it must pay for it.''</p>
        <p>It is not clear what effect the decision will have, since the Court did not foreclose further demands for easements but held only that the one sought from the Nollans did not serve the asserted public purpose of preserving ''psychological'' and ''visual'' access. Some planning experts say that the Coastal Commission's demand was an egregious violation of the Fifth Amendment prohibition of the taking of property without compensation, and that reasonable efforts to expand beach access, particularly those that compensate the owners, should be acceptable.</p>
        <p>Mr. Neuwirth said that while the decision did not appear to create new impediments to such efforts, ''I think some weak-kneed politicians will use it as an excuse to walk away from the coast.''</p>
        <p>A far greater problem, suggested Mr. Magnuson of the Coastal States Organization, would be the increasing traffic, litter, crime and safety problems generated by more intense use of the nation's limited shoreline. ''These resources,'' he said, ''won't be able to withstand the pressure unless they are managed well.''  IDEAS &amp; TRENDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
