<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MUSEUMS, IN SHIFT, AIM AT ILLITERACY IN SCIENCE</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="47" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="19735"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSEUMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870308T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE6DE153CF93BA35750C0A961948260" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MUSEUMS, IN SHIFT, AIM AT ILLITERACY IN SCIENCE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, March 76</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The life-sized tyrannosaurus can stay, but the 7-year-old computer exhibit and the energy and communications displays, all considered outmoded, have to go, say curators at the Boston Museum of Science who are trying to bring their exhibits up to date.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The life-sized tyrannosaurus can stay, but the 7-year-old computer exhibit and the energy and communications displays, all considered outmoded, have to go, say curators at the Boston Museum of Science who are trying to bring their exhibits up to date.</p>
        <p>The life-sized tyrannosaurus can stay, but the 7-year-old computer exhibit and the energy and communications displays, all considered outmoded, have to go, say curators at the Boston Museum of Science who are trying to bring their exhibits up to date.</p>
        <p>Museum officials say such modernizations are not simply reflections of advances in technology. More important to them is what researchers have described as a pervasive lack of ''science literacy'' among adults, especially teachers. The officials say this type of illiteracy compels the museum to act more as an educator than as a showcase for the most up-to-date scientific gadgetry.</p>
        <p>''Children lose their interest in science by the time they're in the eighth grade,'' said Roger L. Nichols, director of the Boston Science Museum. As a result, he said, most adults who shunned science in school cannot develop informed opinions about nuclear power, acid rain, and space-based weaponry.</p>
        <p>''More and more of our real policy issues in society are scientific in nature,'' Dr. Nichols said. ''They are going to be decided at the ballot box by people who don't understand them.'' Popularity Is Soaring</p>
        <p>Despite estimates by researchers that less than 10 percent of adults know what DNA and radiation are and can distinguish astonomy from astrology, science museums across the country are booming. At the Boston Museum of Science, attendance has soared to a million in 1986 from 800,000 in 1982, and the endowment has tripled in five years to $15 million. The Chicago Museum of Science and Industry, the nation's largest science museum, attracted almost four million people last year, and had its highest attendance ever in the first two months of this year.</p>
        <p>The Chicago museum attributes its rise in popularity to the addition last July of a new wing, the Henry Crown Space Center, whose gigantic domed Omnimax Theater shows larger than life projections of astronauts walking on the moon or pitchers hurling fastballs that seem sure to hit the viewer. The Boston museum is following this lead, and will open its new $24 million wing, complete with Omnimax Theater, on March 21.</p>
        <p>The new wing is the museum's latest effort to teach science through entertainment. According to Dr. Nichols, the museum has concentrated its money and efforts on spectacular shows and exhibits at the expense of more mundane permanent displays in order to attract the public to science. The Scientific Players</p>
        <p>Most recently, the Boston museum has collaborated with seven other science museums on a series of traveling exhibits that will make three-month stops at each museum. The last exhibit featured life-size moving dinosaurs; the current one, on robotics, demonstrates robots that play tic-tac-toe and read aloud.</p>
        <p>As the museum improves and expands its exhibits, museum officials are trying to assure that visitors understand what they see. According to Mary Jane Dodge, a project director, the museum has hired three full-time actors to perform scientifically related plays in the museum's new wing. The museum hopes to have at least 100 other employees who will wander among the displays explaining scientific issues and performing demonstrations, such as dipping a rose in liquid nitrogen and then shattering the petals like glass.</p>
        <p>Dr. Nichols said the museum's 35 roving exhibitors were as crucial to the museum's future as its permanent collection. ''It's unlikely we will do backflips to put more bells and whistles on the exhibits,'' he said. ''It's more likely we will put more people in the exhibit hall who say, 'Can I tell you about these parasol ants?' ''</p>
        <p>He said the museum's most valuable exhibits might be its live animals. ''Children are led into an interest in science through natural history,'' he said. To encourage children, especially girls, to pursue careers in science, the museum holds weekend sleepovers in its cavernous exhibit halls. Few Adults Well-Informed</p>
        <p>Charles H. Howarth, executive director of the Sci-Tech Center, a science museum scheduled to open in 1990 in Liberty State Park in New Jersey, said science museums were one of the few sources of science education for adults. He cited a 1983 study by John Miller, a professor at Northern Illinois University, that termed 93 percent of adults scientifically illiterate, and noted that while 48 percent of adults in the survey described themselves as very interested in science and technology, only 14 percent described themselves as well informed about these issues.</p>
        <p>Mr. Howarth said science museums could have ''an impact out of proportion to their size'' through educational programs for children and for teachers. Dr. Nichols said the Boston Museum of Science trained 2,300 teachers last year and reached 80 school systems through its educational programs, which, he added, have a more lasting value than anything inside the museum.</p>
        <p>''Unlike the Museum of Fine Arts, where if you spend half a million dollars on a painting and choose well, it grows more valuable over time, the science museum exhibits depreciate in value,'' Dr. Nichols said. ''It is in the nature of science to become obsolete.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
