<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>About New York; Falling Behind On the Latest List Of Urban Plagues</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="24480"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COCKROACHES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RATINGS AND RATING SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HOUSTON (TEX)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">DALLAS (TEX)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SAN ANTONIO (TEX)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GEIST, WILLIAM E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ABOUT NEW YORK</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Dallas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/San Antonio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Houston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7DA1530F936A15750C0A961948260" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>About New York; Falling Behind On the Latest List Of Urban Plagues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM E. GEIST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GEIST, WILLIAM E</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: After recently placing a lowly 14th in the latest ''serious crime'' ranking by the F.B.I. of the country's 25 biggest cities, New York suffered yet another damaging blow to its image yesterday, showing up a measly 12th on a list of America's most roach-infested cities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: After recently placing a lowly 14th in the latest ''serious crime'' ranking by the F.B.I. of the country's 25 biggest cities, New York suffered yet another damaging blow to its image yesterday, showing up a measly 12th on a list of America's most roach-infested cities.</p>
        <p>After recently placing a lowly 14th in the latest ''serious crime'' ranking by the F.B.I. of the country's 25 biggest cities, New York suffered yet another damaging blow to its image yesterday, showing up a measly 12th on a list of America's most roach-infested cities.</p>
        <p>It was the Sun Belt stealing our thunder again. Dallas had ranked No. 1 on the ''serious crime'' list, and yesterday Houston, Dallas and San Antonio finished a startling 1-2-3 in the roach rankings.</p>
        <p>''New York is lucky to even be on the list,'' said Dr. Betty Lane Faber, who conducts roach research at the American Museum of Natural History, noting further that no other Northern cities had made the list, which is based on per capita household-insecticide sales figures.</p>
        <p>''Sad to say, but we just don't have anywhere near the roach infestations of Houston, Miami, New Orleans and the others,'' Ms. Faber said.</p>
        <p>$ ? * * *  Still, the news arrived as a blow to some New Yorkers in attendance at a pesticide manufacturer's news conference, people who consider the roach the unofficial mascot of the city.</p>
        <p>''Any figures on rats?'' one dejected observer asked.</p>
        <p>''No one will ever touch us in litter,'' another said.</p>
        <p>So why does the smell of roach spray hang over the city at this time of year like cherry blossoms in Washington and honeysuckle in Savannah?</p>
        <p>''New Yorkers are just so anthropomorphic,'' Ms. Faber said. ''They don't know anything about nature, and when they see a bug, they freak out.''</p>
        <p>She knows people who have placed two inches of boric-acid crystals over the entire floor of their apartments to try and get rid of roaches. A friend of hers tied a tarantula to the bathtub for roach patrolling. Ms. Faber noted that having rats and mice helped, because they were natural enemies of the roach.</p>
        <p>The news conference was to have been held at the Harvard Club, but was switched to the New York Hilton ''when the Harvard Club got a little squeamish about TV cameras and bugs,'' a public-relations agent said.</p>
        <p>Every so often an insecticide manufacturer, accompanied by entomologists and a cadre of public-relations agents, invades New York to announce an ultimate solution to the roach problem. The roaches, which have been around 350 million years, seem to get a big kick out of it.</p>
        <p>''There are probably more roaches in New York now than there were 10 years ago,'' said Ms. Faber.</p>
        <p>Cockroaches are used to being bugged by humans. They have adapted in a variety of ways, from developing resistance to insecticides to learning to hide in places not sprayed - computer terminals, smoke alarms and Mr. Coffees - and developing the ability to taste poison without ingesting it.</p>
        <p>But there was cause for far more serious concern than New York's image, the panel of entomologists said.</p>
        <p>If you were thinking that perhaps all you had to worry about these days was radon, acid rain, sexually transmitted diseases, liability-insurance rates, corruption, nuclear winter, the Iran arms affair, cholesterol and third-generation nuclear weapons, guess again.</p>
        <p>$ ? * * *</p>
        <p>The panel, hired by Black Flag, said the entire East Coast might soon be infested with -move over killer bees - a new arrival, the flying Asian cockroach, Blatella asiana.</p>
        <p>Dr. Richard Patterson of the Insects Affecting Man and Animal Research Laboratory of the United States Department of Agriculture said the roaches were only in the Tampa, Fla., area right now. But he showed a videotape of automobiles and campers, which could carry the fast-breeding roaches up the coast. How serious is this threat?  Well, this may be tantamount to shouting, ''Fire!'' in a crowded theater, but let's just say you can forget about Nicaragua for the moment. We could lose Disney World! Mickey, Minnie, Goofy, the whole thing.</p>
        <p>''The roaches are already affecting tourism,'' Mr. Patterson said. ''The Tampa Chamber of Commerce is receiving 1,000 to 2,000 calls per week about the roaches - many of the calls from people canceling reservations. Disney World is receiving calls and is extremely concerned.''</p>
        <p>''People are afraid they'll carry them home,'' he said, noting that a pair of roaches can generate 400,000 descendants a year.</p>
        <p>Luckily for mankind, there is a remedy, the entomologists said - Roach Ender, a new product manufactured by Black Flag that ''locks them in permanent adolescence.''</p>
        <p>When a problem such as this is presented to the public, there is usually a remedy to buy. Sometimes the remedy even comes first.  ''Some roaches actually make nice pets,'' said Ms. Faber, pulling a box containing four huge roaches from her pocket as reporters stepped back. The roaches in her house that she does not care for, however, she steps on. ''Very effective,'' she noted.  ''Pets?'' Dr. Carl Djerassi, a scientist on the panel, asked. ''That's an angle we had not thought to capitalize upon.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
