<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WINE TALK</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="67497"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">AUSTRALIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">REMY MARTIN LTD</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDBERG, HOWARD G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7DD1330F93AA2575BC0A961948260" item-length="1144" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WINE TALK</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Howard G. Goldberg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDBERG, HOWARD G</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE French, who should know better, are exporting a wine labeled ''nouveau'' that they make in Australia. Did they forget that English is the country's language?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE French, who should know better, are exporting a wine labeled ''nouveau'' that they make in Australia. Did they forget that English is the country's language?</p>
        <p>THE French, who should know better, are exporting a wine labeled ''nouveau'' that they make in Australia. Did they forget that English is the country's language?</p>
        <p>The product, with the brand name Kindilan - an aboriginal word meaning ''joyful and young'' - is obviously intended to exploit the French Beaujolais nouveau vogue.</p>
        <p>Although its label declares ''South Australian Origin Guaranteed,'' the wine looks like Beaujolais nouveau, almost smells like it, tastes somewhat like it and, like Beaujolais nouveau, is best drunk slightly chilled. The product carries a 1987 vintage date.</p>
        <p>It is surprising that Remy Martin, which owns the Quelltaler Estate, producer of the appealing, flavorsome red Kindilan, couples the word ''nouveau'' with the phrase ''South Australian'' on the bottle.</p>
        <p>What's wrong with the plain English ''new wine''? The Italians properly call their exported versions of the light, fresh, early-drinking potion ''novello'' and Latin American producers, ''nuevo.''</p>
        <p>This seemingly small complaint addresses an issue of intellectual integrity. The French-owned Remy Martin's use of ''nouveau'' is ironic, because France has long chafed, legitimately, at the chutzpah of Americans' misappropriation of ''champagne'' on bottles that should be labeled ''sparkling wine.''</p>
        <p>As Christian Bizot, president of Bollinger, a leading Champagne house, said last week over lunch, this use of ''champagne'' on wine that is ''miles away from the high-quality wine of the Champagne district'' debases the image of the unique French product.</p>
        <p>Besides, Remy Martin owns two Champagne houses, Krug and Charles Heidsieck. Wouldn't Remy Martin howl if a top-grade California distiller marketed a ''Napa Valley Cognac''? Quite carefully, Remy Martin's wholly owned RMS, a Napa distillery, calls its product California Alambic Brandy.</p>
        <p>As an advocate of regionalism at a time when table wines are veering toward a regimented international style - too many chardonnays seem born alike - I wish Remy Martin had used label language that would help consumers keep wine cultures straight.</p>
        <p>American wine growers are no less guilty of misusing ''nouveau'' as a commercial ploy. Fortunately, American producers are phasing out their longstanding misuse of ''burgundy,'' ''chablis,'' ''chianti'' and ''rhine'' on wines that bear as much resemblance to French, Italian and West German wines as Classic Comics bear to the classics.</p>
        <p>These generic terms have largely been replaced by varietal labels; that is, many wines are identified by their grapes. Other table wines are being given proprietary (brand) names, especially at the premium level.</p>
        <p>It is not common to find any 87's whatsoever on shelves in the United States, since '87 grapes are still developing their personalities on Northern Hemisphere vines.</p>
        <p>Australia, of course, is in the Southern Hemisphere, which has summer - hence, a March vintage - when we have winter.</p>
        <p>This cosmology partly explains why the Australian ''nouveau'' has reached New York City even before French wineries have hired public-relations companies to churn out vintage-of-the-century hype for their Beaujolais and Beaujolais-Villages nouveaux, which will not arrive in America until late November.</p>
        <p>It doesn't explain everything, however. Something else does: money.</p>
        <p>French wine growers long ago learned the value of funneling a torrent of the young, fruity - indeed, charming, if unfinished - wine to Paris, London, New York and Honolulu four to six weeks after the harvest. It generates a counterflow of money that helps pay off the year's debts while the rest of the vintage matures in casks until spring.</p>
        <p>Both state-of-the-art technology and the Beaujolais region's vinification method, called carbonic maceration, are turning up on every hill and vale that a vine can call home.</p>
        <p>Under this technique, which is also known as whole-berry fermentation, flavor and color are extracted through the enzymatic breakdown of grapes placed uncrushed in an airless tank filled with carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>All vintners - Italian, North American, Latin American and Australian - understand the cash-flow appeal of the popular, easy-drinking beverage, which rarely has eight months' staying power. Now what's next - Japanese saki nouveau?</p>
        <p>Don't get me wrong. I adore the stuff and usually am among the first on line when Beaujolais-Villages nouveau - some producers call theirs ''primeur'' - turns up just before Thanksgiving.</p>
        <p>The wine lubricates gaiety, the hoopla is harmless and my adjective account is overdrawn by the fourth word. Nothing quite resembles the sheer Lolita-like beauty of the Beaujolais region's gamay grape at its juicy best, as it was in '85.</p>
        <p>I must say that the Kindilan blend ($4.99 at Sherry-Lehmann) - consisting of 65 percent shiraz, 18 percent merlot and 17 percent cabernet franc grapes - offers concentrated depth of flavor and the pizazz of a semi-sophisticated wine intended for refreshing August and September drinking.</p>
        <p>But I must also say that the nouveau craze has gone too far. I began to suspect so when I came across an '86 Maui nouveau, a Hawaiian wine. Tedeschi Vineyards produced it from carnelian grapes harvested in July on a volcano at Ulupalakua.</p>
        <p>Apparently, some French interests also think it has got out of hand. The other day, the mail brought a newsletter from the Union Interprofessionnelle des Vins du Beaujolais, a trade association of Beaujolais producers and shippers. It reports that the French have been hoist with their own petard.</p>
        <p>''The 'primeur' phenomenon has so great an impact that it is prejudicial to knowledge of the other Beaujolais wines, with a resulting denial of their richness and diversity,'' the newsletter said. ''It is therefore very difficult for the traditional Beaujolais and Beaujolais-Villages to find a market sector after the primeur period.''</p>
        <p>''This is a complete paradox,'' it went on. ''In fact, the Beaujolais primeur should be a sample of the vintage: the sales catalyst. But so great is its impact that it plays the opposite role, engulfing and dominating the Beaujolais image and reducing it to only the image of the primeur.''</p>
        <p>Critics of the quick-buck nouveau movement have long maintained that the annual river of nouveau drains too much from the lake of vintage-dated regular Beaujolais-Villages, especially in a good year.</p>
        <p>For consumers who do not have a bottomless thirst for Beaujolais, of which there are, alas, legions, early drinking gluts the taste buds. Sadly, they miss out on the lovely, aromatic, fuller-bodied wines from villages with such alluring names as Saint-Amour, Fleurie, Chiroubles, Moulin-a-Vent and Julienas.</p>
        <p>In any case, nouveau-quaffing is philosophically antithetical to the spirit of these deeper wines. As an old Beaujolais proverb says, ''One should never trust a man who drinks his Julienas in one swallow.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
