<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pilots Fly Over the Pole Into Heart of Ozone Mystery</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="76551"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTICA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHRISTIAN, SHIRLEY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4D9143CF931A1575AC0A961948260" item-length="1148" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pilots Fly Over the Pole Into Heart of Ozone Mystery</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHIRLEY CHRISTIAN, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHRISTIAN, SHIRLEY</byline>
      <dateline>PUNTA ARENAS, Chile, Sept. 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: From this windswept city on the Strait of Magellan, two American research planes are flying regularly into uncharted territory over the Antarctic, seeking an explanation for the hole in the earth's protective ozone layer that appears for about two months each spring.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: From this windswept city on the Strait of Magellan, two American research planes are flying regularly into uncharted territory over the Antarctic, seeking an explanation for the hole in the earth's protective ozone layer that appears for about two months each spring.</p>
        <p>From this windswept city on the Strait of Magellan, two American research planes are flying regularly into uncharted territory over the Antarctic, seeking an explanation for the hole in the earth's protective ozone layer that appears for about two months each spring.</p>
        <p>The seasonal thinning of ozone in the upper atmosphere, which protects plants, animals and people from the dangerous effects of the sun's ultraviolet rays, was discovered in 1979 by British researchers. It has caused deep alarm among scientists who are trying to determine whether man-made chemicals or natural processes are the cause.</p>
        <p>Among possible man-made causes, the chief suspects are chlorofluorocarbons, chemicals used in refrigeration, aerosol sprays and other products. These can destroy ozone when they reach the upper atmosphere. Dozens of nations last week signed a treaty in Montreal intended to halt and then roll back global use of the chemicals.</p>
        <p>The investigators here declined to draw conclusions yet about their work, but they said each flight has produced new information about the atmosphere, notably that it is colder and windier above the Antarctic than it is at any other place airplanes have flown.</p>
        <p>One of the planes, a DC-8 equipped as a flying laboratory, has made what project leaders say was the first known flight directly over the South Pole. The other plane is a high altitude ER-2, similar to U-2 reconnaissance craft.</p>
        <p>The flights began Aug. 17. The data brought back by the two planes are being analyzed by dozens of scientists and engineers in laboratories set up by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration in a hangar of the Chilean Air Force.</p>
        <p>The ER-2 flies into the upper part of the ozone hole at altitudes up to 67,000 feet, and the DC-8 flies at 30,000 to 35,000 feet. Each is expected to complete 12 flights by the time the investigation ends Sept. 28. Findings Eagerly Awaited</p>
        <p>The investigators will make their first public report on Sept. 30. Detailed findings for use by other scientists are not expected to be available until the middle of next year.</p>
        <p>Scientists, industries, environmentalists and government policy makers around the world are eagerly awaiting the findings. The study is expected to have an impact on the debate over the continuing use of chlorofluorocarbons in industrial and consumer products.</p>
        <p>The treaty signed last week would freeze the use of chlorofluorocarbons at last year's level by 1989 and reduce it by half in the next decade. A cap was put on future production of halons, another class of ozone-destroying chemicals, as well.</p>
        <p>If these chemicals are found responsible for the Antarctic ozone hole, experts said, pressure will grow to curb their use more drastically. Concerns About Cancer</p>
        <p>The United States banned the use of aerosol sprays containing chlorofluorocarbons in 1978, but the chemicals continue to be used in air-conditioning and refrigeration. Most other countries do not restrict their use.</p>
        <p>Scientists first became concerned that chlorofluorocarbons could deplete the ozone layer in the early 1970's. Should a significant thinning of the ozone occur, experts predict, the resulting increase in ultraviolet radiation will cause a substantial rise in skin cancer and eye cataracts and damage aquatic and terrestrial ecosystems.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robert T. Watson, an atmospheric chemist for NASA who is in charge of the program, said it was conceivable that the ozone hole, detected in 1979, was a natural phenomenon, perhaps caused by the dynamics of the Antarctic's climate and occurring periodically, but he said the evidence pointing to the chemical cause was stronger.</p>
        <p>Research conducted last year at McMurdo Station in the Antarctic supported the theory of a chemical cause, with returning scientists reporting high levels of chlorine in the polar atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Some of the scientists in the project indicated in interviews that they would have preferred to wait until next year to come here in order to prepare better for their investigation. Dr. Watson, while conceding that he sped up the schedule partly because of mounting political pressure over the chlorofluorocarbon issue, said there were important scientific reasons for hurrying.</p>
        <p>''If the hole turns out to be caused by human factors,'' he said, ''time could be of the essence.''</p>
        <p>While warning against alarmist theories, he pointed out that the ozone hole has grown by 50 percent since 1979. When it is open, Dr. Watson said, the hole, the area of extreme depletion, covers an area twice as large as the United States. He said disturbances in the the ozone layer were probably now occurring as far north as Santiago and Buenos Aires in South America and the southern edge of Australia and New Zealand. The thinning is worst near the center of Antarctica itself, and has grown more severe over time.</p>
        <p>Setting up this investigation, scientists here said, required them to move very fast and to do complicated research. They praised the cooperation they received from the Chilean Air Force, which has given the investigators free use of its base 12 miles north of Punta Arenas. Exploring Uncharted Territory</p>
        <p>About 170 people, including scientists, engineers, maintenance crews and managers, have taken part in the project. About one-fourth have already left Punta Arenas. Besides NASA, they come from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, the National Science Foundation, Harvard University, the Universities of Denver and Washington and other organizations.</p>
        <p>Dr. Watson said the two research aircraft have been going into ''absolutely uncharted territory'' on their flights, which go into the Antarctic over the Palmer Peninsula. He said the DC-8 had flown directly over the South Pole at 35,000 feet, while military and commercial planes regularly flying over the Antarctic avoid the pole itself because of the distances involved and the dangerous winds.</p>
        <p>He also said the ER-2 has flown higher over the Antarctic than any other plane.</p>
        <p>Pilots and investigators said they had measured temperatures of 80 to 90 degrees below zero centigrade (about 120 degrees below zero Fahrenheit) on the flights and winds up to 100 knots.</p>
        <p>Jim Barrilleaux, one of four retired United States Air Force pilots who have taken turns flying the single-seat ER-2, said he had also flown over the Arctic, which was warmer and less windy. He said he had never before flown in winds equal to those over the Antarctic.</p>
        <p>Each plane is equipped with a vast array of highly advanced sampling and measuring equipment. The mostly automated ER-2 has a number of coin-sized portholes, small wires and other protruding devices that gather particles and other samplings from the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The DC-8, a modified passenger plane equipped as a series of laboratories for this mission, carries a number of scientists who work while the plane is in the air.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
