<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Pollution Hounds Get Ready to Pounce</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="72318"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEUTSCH, CLAUDIA H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4D91330F935A3575AC0A961948260" item-length="2777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Pollution Hounds Get Ready to Pounce</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA H. DEUTSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DEUTSCH, CLAUDIA H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: UNTIL last month, the Inland Steel Company thought its air pollution problems were over. The air quality monitors scattered around its East Chicago, Ind., plant hadn't registered a violation of emissions standards since 1981. And, as far as Inland executives could tell, no one near the plant had complained about air quality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: UNTIL last month, the Inland Steel Company thought its air pollution problems were over. The air quality monitors scattered around its East Chicago, Ind., plant hadn't registered a violation of emissions standards since 1981. And, as far as Inland executives could tell, no one near the plant had complained about air quality.</p>
        <p>UNTIL last month, the Inland Steel Company thought its air pollution problems were over. The air quality monitors scattered around its East Chicago, Ind., plant hadn't registered a violation of emissions standards since 1981. And, as far as Inland executives could tell, no one near the plant had complained about air quality.</p>
        <p>But Inland and other companies in the heavily industrialized Lake County, Ind., region are in for a fresh spate of regulations, anyway. Unlike last decade's air pollution control rules, which aimed to clean up air that was obviously dirty, the new rules will focus on making sure that air stays clean.</p>
        <p>Indiana, like many other states, has run a computerized worst-case scenario - a what-if model that assumes that all plants are operating at full capacity, and that winds are spreading pollutants but not dispersing them. According to that model, the Lake County plants are environmental bad actors that must reduce their emissions of sulfur dioxide, and probably of total suspended particulate (the regulatory term for dust and soot) and other pollutants as well.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't make much sense,'' said Stefan P. Shoup, Inland's senior staff engineer for technological services and chairman of the Lake County Attainment Task Force, a local industry group for handling environmental matters. ''The modeling has gotten too conservative. This kind of control is not scientifically justified.'' After several years in which industrial air pollution was virtually a non-issue in Washington, Congress, the Environmental Protection Agency and the states are cracking down on industry in general, and on the steel and utility industry in particular.</p>
        <p>Indeed, it is almost as though a slumbering giant has awakened and is stretching all its limbs. The Senate is marking up a bill that would force the E.P.A. to control more hazardous pollutants. The E.P.A. in July passed a rule about microscopic dust in the air that it had been talking about for almost 12 years. Many of the states, meanwhile, are making their own pollution control rules more stringent.</p>
        <p>The flurry of activity has come about for a variety of reasons. More sophisticated technology and computer software are enabling regulators to pinpoint exactly what is in the air and where it comes from. Several states have missed their deadlines this year for reducing levels of ozone and carbon monoxide in the air, and environmental officials are trying to defuse the negative publicity that this has generated by assuming a get-tough stance. Moreover, mobile source emissions - official parlance for pollution from automobiles - have proved almost impossible to reduce without banning private cars from polluted areas. Few mayors or governors want to do that.</p>
        <p>Politically, basic industries are a more tempting target than cars. Ever since December 1984, when toxic gas from a Union Carbide Corporation plant killed more than 2,500 people in Bhopal, India, the political climate has been ripe for new restrictions on industrial emissions. The proposed rules are not onerous enough to drive any healthy company out of business, so few jobs are in danger.</p>
        <p>Still, compliance could lead to higher prices, further damaging American industry's competitive stance. Steel executives have warned that if pollution control rules make it impossible to make coke or slab steel economically in this country, they will buy these materials overseas. But most members of Congress, although they do not say so for the record, are more concerned about keeping high technology and service industries competitive than they are about manufacturing and process industries.</p>
        <p>THE result is that across the country, basic industry is gearing up for new rules. The Electric Power Research Institute, the utility industry's technology arm, just dedicated a test center to finding better ways to clean up the emissions from burning high-sulfur coal. It is also looking at ways to make sulfur dioxide scrubbers more efficient.</p>
        <p>''Acid rain goes through peaks and valleys of public consciousness,'' said Kurt E. Yeager, vice president of the Institute's coal combustion systems division. ''Now it's at a peak.''</p>
        <p>Steel industry executives, meanwhile, are dreading the spread of what-if modeling. ''We're afraid the states will use conservative modeling to put in safety factor upon safety factor,'' said William J. Riley, manager of environmental compliance at the Bethlehem Steel Corporation.</p>
        <p>''I don't think the steel industry is a major problem as far as air pollution goes,'' said Earle F. Young, vice president of environment and energy for the American Iron and Steel Institute. ''But some states will put new rules on it because it's big and it's visible.''</p>
        <p>The resurgence of interest in air pollution control stands in sharp contrast to the record of the last seven years. Political, not scientific, considerations took the heat off industrial air pollution during most of the current Administration.</p>
        <p>Indeed, industry was under heavy regulatory scrutiny throughout the prior decade. The Clean Air Act of 1970 empowered the E.P.A. to set limits on the amount of particulate matter, sulfur dioxide, and other ''criteria'' pollutants - common pollutants generated from driving cars, burning coal, making steel and other basic industrial processes -that could be found in the ambient air. Once the E.P.A. set such a rule for a particular pollutant, it required states to provide State Implementation Plans to show how they would attain acceptable concentrations of that pollutant.</p>
        <p>In the late 1970's Congress did its part to help by insisting that automobiles use lead-free gasoline and be equipped with catalytic converters. The states and regional E.P.A. administrators took on local industry.</p>
        <p>But for much of this decade, the E.P.A. has been beset by upheaval. In 1982 Congress began an investigation of charges that the E.P.A. was mishandling, for political reasons, a $1.6 billion toxic waste cleanup fund. Before that investigation had been completed, E.P.A. administrator Anne M. Gorsuch became the highest executive branch official to be cited for contempt of Congress, for refusing to provide subpoenaed documents; Rita M. Lavelle, head of the E.P.A.'s toxics program, was jailed for contempt, and 21 political appointees to the agency were fired. Amidst all the turmoil, the demoralized agency relaxed its vigilance on the states.</p>
        <p>''The E.P.A. has permitted the states to adopt industrial pollution rules that are too lenient,'' said David Hawkins, senior staff attorney of the Natural Resources Defense Council, a Washington group with a reputation for litigiousness on environmental matters. ''Anywhere from 70 percent to 90 percent of plants comply with the rules, but the air is still dirty. The rules are not stringent enough.''</p>
        <p>Privately, Federal regulators agree. ''We were beset with intra-agency politics, and we just stopped requiring states to provide attainment demonstration,'' conceded an E.P.A. enforcement official who requested anonymity. ''Since we have not pressured the states, the states have not pressured industry.''</p>
        <p>With the pressure off, industry stopped spending a lot on pollution control technology. Research-Cottrell Inc.'s Engineered Products and Systems Group, a major supplier of air pollution control equipment, saw industrial orders drop by two-thirds in the last four years, compared to what they were in the late 1970's.</p>
        <p>''Maintaining and rebuilding existing equipment has become 40 percent of our business,'' said Jerome E. Schnee, the group's president. ''It was just 20 percent five years ago.''</p>
        <p>But now the E.P.A. is bearing down again. Last week, it charged Bethlehem with violating rules at three plants. And E.P.A. officials are taking fresh looks at other companies' plants, too. ''We've developed some pretty sophisticated techniques for capturing and analyzing air samples,'' said Steve Rothblatt, chief of the air and radiation branch of E.P.A.'s Region 5, which includes major pockets of industry in the Midwest. ''We've found that in urban areas about half of emissions are from automobiles. So industry is half the problem.''</p>
        <p>''Companies have made major progress toward cleaning up,'' added Larry F. Kertcher, chief of air compliance in Region 5. ''But they still have a distance to go.''</p>
        <p>OF all large American industries, steel has perhaps the most at stake in the renewed emphasis on pollution controls. Historically, it is the industry that fought hardest - and, in some ways, most unsuccessfully - against them (see box).</p>
        <p>Steelmaking is an inherently dirty and energy-intensive process. Most steel plants are dotted with huge piles of coal that can send coal dust blowing into the air with every breeze. Processing coal into coke liberates tons of trace metals, hydrocarbons, soot and other pollutants. Transporting molten iron and steel around the plant also generates fumes, often red-tinged from airborn rust.</p>
        <p>But the E.P.A. has been fairly cooperative with the industry in orchestrating methods of compliance. For example, it has allowed some plants to pretend that they operated under a huge bubble, and to measure the total quantity of pollution gathered under that bubble rather than the quantity emitted by individual stacks. Practically speaking, that meant that if a steel plant could reduce total suspended particulate by watering down coal piles to prevent dust from flying around, it might avoid expensive equipment to get the last few particles out of a furnace smokestack.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. has also allowed companies to buy and sell pollution ''credits'' in areas with relatively high air quality. If a company shut down a plant that was emitting a certain amount of particulate, for example, it could sell the right to emit that same amount to another company in the area. That enabled some companies to expand without meeting stringent new-source pollution rules.</p>
        <p>Still, steel industry insiders insist that the industry cannot cope now with a fresh slew of pollution control laws. Most steel companies have been drowning in red ink for much of the 1980's. And most have already exhausted the inexpensive routes to controlling pollution. They have paved their roads and installed sprinkler systems over their coal piles. Some - Armco's Middletown, Ohio, plant is an example - have used landscaping as a control methodology, planting trees as landbased breakwaters to keep waves of pollutants from dispersing.</p>
        <p>Meeting pending regulations will require more sophisticated methods. Last month, for example, the E.P.A. promulgated its long-awaited PM10 standard, which mandates that states devise SIP's for airborn particles no bigger than 10 micrometers, or about a tenth the diameter of a human hair. The slightest tear or crack in pollution control equipment would let such fine particulate through, so the standard would mean increased maintenance costs. And it most probably will mean a need for more control equipment on smokestacks. ''Withough question, the PM10 standard will be a huge stimulant to sales,'' said Mr. Schnee of Research-Cottrell.</p>
        <p>Congress is also prodding the E.P.A. to step up regulation of toxic pollutants. In 17 years, the agency has designated only seven such pollutants, and Congress has lost patience. The Senate is discussing a bill that would require the E.P.A. to identify and regulate 50 hazardous air pollutants over the next three years.</p>
        <p>Already, steel companies are budgeting for new controls on benzene, one of the seven designated hazardous pollutants. Benzene is generated by facilities used to capture and recycle the byproducts of coke ovens. Most scientists expect that lead, zinc and manganese, which are found in iron ore and coal, as well as chromium and nickel, which are ingredients in stainless steel, will show up on the new hazardous pollutant list.</p>
        <p>''We'd have to retrofit our plants to take those metals out, and that means redoing everything we've done so far,'' said Bruce A. Steiner, environmental manager at Armco, which has spent $420 million on air and water pollution control equipment since 1960. ''The risk to individuals does not warrant the cost of control.''</p>
        <p>INDEED, unlike the 1970's, when steel executives tried to sway Congress with arguments about competitiveness, today the industry is arguing on the basis of science. ''Things become toxic because the law says they are,'' said Mr. Riley of Bethlehem. ''Too many analyses fail to check whether substances enter the environment in a way that can do harm. Your car's bumper has chrome in it, but do you call it a hazardous bumper?''</p>
        <p>Pending acid rain legislation may yet be the biggest thorn for the steel industry. Congress's primary aim is to stop electric utilities from generating the sulfur compounds that can lead to acid rain. But some of the proposed legislation also deals with nitrogen oxide, which is generally formed during any high-temperature process, including steel making. And even if the law as passed deals only with utilities and sulfur, it would probably mean a wave of utility rate increases. Armco's Mr. Steiner guesses that, if proposed legislation goes through, his company's utility bills will go up by $15 million to $20 million annually, meaning ''an additional cost of $3 to $4 a ton of steel.''</p>
        <p>For now, Mr. Steiner and most of his colleagues are remaining calm. The E.P.A. has been notoriously slow in forcing states to come up with new SIP's, and E.P.A. insiders say privately that it is unlikely that any steel company will be asked to do much in less than three years.</p>
        <p>And laws can change by then. Armco, for one, has budgeted just $25 million through 1992 for new air pollution control equipment, an amount the company, despite recent financial problems, can well afford. That budget is predicated on the demise of some of the more onerous provisions of pending legislation.</p>
        <p>''I think Congress will realize they do not need Draconian measures,'' Mr. Steiner says. And if it doesn't? ''Maybe we'll find less energy-intensive processes for making stainless steel, and maybe we'll buy coke from Germany and slabs from Korea. Faced with high enough expenditures, you look at all the options.''  COMPLIANCE: NOT SO COSTLY</p>
        <p>ALL companies were affected by tightened emissions regulations throughout the 1970's. But in many ways, steel was hardest hit. While electric utilities, refineries, and other polluters passed at least part of their costs of compliance to their customers, steel companies did not have that option. Competition from Japan was keeping steel prices down, while plastic and aluminum were making inroads into steel markets.</p>
        <p>In 1975, the American Iron and Steel Institute commissioned the Arthur D. Little Company to assess the economic impact of environmental regulation on the steel industry. The consulting firm predicted that the steel industry would have to spend between $12 billion and $14 billion on pollution control equipment to meet air and water quality rules by 1983. It also predicted that the cost of maintaining and operating pollution control equipment would add $25 to $30 a ton to the cost of making steel by 1983.</p>
        <p>Industry executives used those figures to lobby for a relaxation of environmental rules. Without relief, they argued, steel companies would have to close numerous plants and eliminate thousands of jobs.</p>
        <p>Congress turned a relatively deaf ear to the industry's pleas. And, in fact, the A.D. Little predictions turned out to be wrong. The Institute's own figures show that steel companies have spent a total of $6.1 billion on air and water pollution control from 1951 through 1986. Of that figure, $3.8 billion went to air pollution control. Maintenance costs are not as high as the Little study suggested, either. Armco Steel spends about $15 a ton of steel to maintain and operate pollution control equipment; other steel companies quote similar figures. The largest proportion of that goes to fuel and electricity for powering pollution control equipment. But much of it also goes to stemming so-called fugitive emissions - coal dust, leaks from coke oven doors, and such.</p>
        <p>''Coke ovens tend to be fine when they're first built,'' explained Bruce A. Steiner, Armco's environmental manager. ''But they are operated continuously, and they develop cracks as they age.''</p>
        <p>Over all, industry insiders concede that they overreacted to the first round of pollution control rules. ''None of the steel plants that have been shut down to date have attributed the shutdowns to requirements for pollution control,'' said Earle F. Young, an executive with the Iron and Steel Institute.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
