<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.P.A. FINDS LAKES OF WEST ARE FREE OF ACID RAIN</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="3967"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEEDC113BF935A25752C0A961948260" item-length="604" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.P.A. FINDS LAKES OF WEST ARE FREE OF ACID RAIN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A survey made public today by the Environmental Protection Agency found that no lakes in mountainous areas of the Western United States were currently polluted by acid rain but that a large number were potentially susceptible.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A survey made public today by the Environmental Protection Agency found that no lakes in mountainous areas of the Western United States were currently polluted by acid rain but that a large number were potentially susceptible.</p>
        <p>A survey made public today by the Environmental Protection Agency found that no lakes in mountainous areas of the Western United States were currently polluted by acid rain but that a large number were potentially susceptible.</p>
        <p>The survey, a one-time sampling of 719 lakes done in the fall of 1985, found that there was little industrial pollution affecting the lakes now. But it found that about two-thirds of the lakes had very little chemical capacity to neutralize any acid rain that might fall into them.</p>
        <p>The results are likely to be cited by both proponents and opponents of legislation to provide a nationwide program to control acid rain. One such legislative proposal was introduced earlier this month by Senator Robert T. Stafford, Republican of Vermont, and a similar bill is scheduled to be announced Friday by Senator George J. Mitchell, Democrat of Maine. Ingredients of Acid Rain</p>
        <p>Acid rain is pollution made up chiefly of oxides of sulfur and nitrogen from power plants, smelters, vehicles and other sources, that change chemically as they travel through the atmosphere and fall to earth as acidic rain, snow, fog or dry particles. Acid rain has been found to destroy aquatic life in some fresh water bodies in the East and to damage buildings. It may also be affecting forests, crops and, possibly, human health.</p>
        <p>A previous E.P.A. survey of Eastern lakes found that roughly 10 percent were polluted by acid rain while 50 percent were sensitive to acidity, particularly in the Northeast and Southeast.</p>
        <p>There are 10,393 lakes in the Western areas covered by the latest survey. E.P.A. officials said today that the lakes, many of which are in wilderness areas and national parks, are among the most sensitive in the world because of the absence of minerals to neutralize acidity.</p>
        <p>The officials said, however, that the amount of sulfur being deposited on these lakes was currently going down rather than up, largely because of the recent closing of a number of large metal smelters in the West. Results Are Questioned</p>
        <p>They added that the survey was not designed to show the effect of nitrogen oxides or to discover short-term episodes of acid pollution.</p>
        <p>But the agency said, ''The report data suggests that chronic regional lake acidification has not occurred in the mountainous areas of the West.''</p>
        <p>Mohamed El-Ashry, a senior associate of the World Resources Insitute, a Washington research and policy group, questioned the conclusion, saying, ''A one-shot deal does not justify a conclusion of no acidification or chronic affect.''</p>
        <p>''They conducted the survey in the fall but the critical time of year is during the spring snow melt when there is an acid pulse that impacts on aquatic life,'' he said. Difficulty of Spring Survey</p>
        <p>Officials of the environmental agency said that the survey was not taken in the spring because it was difficult to time the melting of the snow and because the lakes were in areas that were hard to reach and unsafe at that time of year.</p>
        <p>Michael Oppenheimer, an atmospheric physicist with the Environmental Defense Fund, emphasized that the survey showed the extreme sensitivity of the Western lakes. He said that while sulfur pollution might be going down in that area now, it was an area of rapid economic development where acid rain was likely to increase in the future.</p>
        <p>Deborah Sheiman, resource specialist for the Natural Resources Defense Fund, said the sensitivity of the lakes showed the need for acting now to protect them from acid rain even though none were now acidic.</p>
        <p>''You don't call the doctor after the patient is dead,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
