<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AT LONG LAST, A DRIVE TO RESTORE CITY HALL'S HISTORIC IMAGE</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="8722"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="ABOUT PHILADELPHIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PHILADELPHIA (PA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDA1138F932A05752C0A961948260" item-length="922" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AT LONG LAST, A DRIVE TO RESTORE CITY HALL'S HISTORIC IMAGE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, Jan. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Some Philadelphians think it is as magnificent and important a building as there is in town. This is high tribute in a city that likes to think of itself as the country's foremost museum of living architecture. Others think it is an outrageously busy-looking relic of the Victorian era.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Some Philadelphians think it is as magnificent and important a building as there is in town. This is high tribute in a city that likes to think of itself as the country's foremost museum of living architecture. Others think it is an outrageously busy-looking relic of the Victorian era.</p>
        <p>Some Philadelphians think it is as magnificent and important a building as there is in town. This is high tribute in a city that likes to think of itself as the country's foremost museum of living architecture. Others think it is an outrageously busy-looking relic of the Victorian era.</p>
        <p>But no one can ignore City Hall, the physical and civic heart of Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>Ninety classical statues by Alexander Milne Calder, grandfather of Alexander Stirling Calder, the mobile designer, look down from the granite facade of the eight-story, block-square building, generally considered one of the finest examples of the 19th-century Beaux-Arts and Second Empire styles of design.</p>
        <p>Human face masks and snarling lions glower from what local architectural experts say is the largest municipal building (more than 14 acres of floor space) in the country. Ornate columns by the scores decorate the four exterior walls. Floral carvings abound. Blocky mansard roofs reach toward the sky. Gingerbread is everywhere. Depending on one's point of view, the building is either richly scaled and intimately conceived, or hopelessly cluttered.</p>
        <p>Crowning all is Calder's 37-foot bronze statue of William Penn, believed to be the largest single piece of sculpture on any building in the world, standing atop a 548-foot tower that is believed to be the world's tallest masonry structure without a steel frame. It is visible for miles, the most vivid of reminders of what city this is.</p>
        <p>But both Billy Penn (as Philadelphians call him) and City Hall have fallen on hard times, literally and figuratively. As scandals plague the city's polity and monumental difficulties beset its government, City Hall is crumbling.</p>
        <p>Cracks have appeared. Chunks of stone, including keystones, have fallen off. The building's foundation has settled, and no one is sure how secure it is. As the building deteriorates, some of its public spaces have become public urinals. The cast-iron part of the tower on which the Penn statue stands has been weakened and twisted by nearly a century of wind, heat, sandblasting and acid rain.</p>
        <p>The statue itself is corroding. The city founder's face looks scarred and dirty. There are questions about the structural integrity of his bronze body. And he is not even visible any more, shrouded in the scaffolding used by those who are trying to assess the damage and determine what to do about it.</p>
        <p>Not a few citizens have noted the symbolism in this. ''A lot of the morale of the city is reflected in the condition of our public buildings,'' said Leslie Gallery, the executive director of the city's Foundation for Architecture. ''The building of City Hall has to represent the spirit of Philadelphia, and what's there now is somewhat depressing.''</p>
        <p>A start has been made in the opposite direction, however. An officially sanctioned citizens' committee recently kicked off a public campaign to raise $1.2 million for restoring the Penn statue in time for the celebration here next Sept. 17 marking the 200th anniversary of the signing of the Constitution.</p>
        <p>The drive began with modest fanfare when Julius Erving, the Philadelphia 76ers basketball star known as Doctor J who has put down roots as a Philadelphian and become active in civic affairs, was introduced as the campaign's chairman. ''I don't mind looking up to a guy like William Penn,'' he said. The president of the citizens' group is Herbert Olivieri, who is known as the city's cheese-steak king. There is no more Philadelphian trifecta than Billy Penn, Doctor J and Herb Olivieri, and hopes are high that it will be a winner.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, there has been considerable civic embarrassment over the shroud of scaffolding around the statue and its supporting tower. It has been there for nearly two years now, while the city government has struggled to get the restoration work under way. Bids have twice been received for the tower work, and although the latest one, $17.6 million, was lower than the first, it is still three times more than what the City Council has appropriated for the job.</p>
        <p>Beyond that, the task of putting the main building back into top condition is estimated to cost $30 million. The foundation must be stabilized, engineers say, to keep the structure from shifting. Marble must be replaced and the finish restored to reseal the building and keep moisture from aggravating the damage.</p>
        <p>It took 30 years, from 1871 to 1901, to build City Hall. How long it will take to restore it to its original grandeur is anyone's guess. Much of the grandeur remains, not least in the Calder statues of figures representing the seasons, continents, arts and science that are considered a major collection of art works in their own right.</p>
        <p>With its courtyards and open spaces (now mostly walled off by chain-link fences), the building ''has the potential to be the living room of the city,'' said Ms. Gallery, ''the place where all people in the city feel comfortable in coming together.''</p>
        <p>Her organization has been enlisted by the city government to hold a design competition for a renovation of the building's first floor.</p>
        <p>Every weekday buses bearing prisoners pull up to the building and discharge defendants into the courts there. In 1990 the courts are scheduled to move to a new criminal justice center. That, coinciding with the need to repair the building, is seen by Ms. Gallery as creating ''an opportunity to look at how the entire building is used in terms of its space planning.</p>
        <p>''The building,'' she said, ''is at an important crossroads.''  ABOUT PHILADELPHIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
