<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NATURAL GAS WELL IS BELIEVED FOUND</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="23449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SWEDEN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, THOMAS (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, WALTER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870322T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7D71638F931A15750C0A961948260" item-length="871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NATURAL GAS WELL IS BELIEVED FOUND</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER SULLIVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The bottom has, in effect, dropped out of a hole drilled 19,950 feet into the floor of a meteorite crater in Sweden, allowing 900 barrels of drilling lubricant to vanish into the earth's interior, and Dr. Thomas Gold of Cornell University believes the lubricant fell into a large reservoir of natural gas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The bottom has, in effect, dropped out of a hole drilled 19,950 feet into the floor of a meteorite crater in Sweden, allowing 900 barrels of drilling lubricant to vanish into the earth's interior, and Dr. Thomas Gold of Cornell University believes the lubricant fell into a large reservoir of natural gas.</p>
        <p>The bottom has, in effect, dropped out of a hole drilled 19,950 feet into the floor of a meteorite crater in Sweden, allowing 900 barrels of drilling lubricant to vanish into the earth's interior, and Dr. Thomas Gold of Cornell University believes the lubricant fell into a large reservoir of natural gas.</p>
        <p>If that is confirmed, he said at a meeting in Manhattan last week, it would support his theory that vast amounts of natural gas, chiefly methane, lie deeply hidden in the earth.</p>
        <p>He has argued for more than a decade that natural gas and oil are derived from material that fell from the sky in the final stages of the earth's formation. The conventional view is that they originated from the fossil remains of living organisms.</p>
        <p>And his theory is rejected by most other experts, but because other unorthodox views held by Dr. Gold have eventually been vindicated, some scientists have urged that his theory about the gas not be dismissed out of hand. If he is correct, they say the world's fuel resources would be vastly greater than they are assumed to be. No Evidence of Fossils</p>
        <p>If Sweden's deep well, in the giant crater 150 miles northwest of Stockholm, has struck a methane reservoir, some geologists say the Gold hypothesis will be strengthened. The hole has been drilled into granite where there is no evidence of fossil remains. Skeptics suggest that the source of the methane could be more deeply buried biological material.</p>
        <p>A thick, heavy fluid was circulated down the drill pipe to lubricate the drill and return to the surface, to flush out chips of rock. The lubricant's weight also prevents the hole from collapsing, About three weeks ago, Dr. Gold said, the rate of penetration of the crater bottom suddenly increased fivefold. Then the drilling lubricant, or ''driling mud,'' dropped into the well and the drill jammed. Before the drill reached the 19,950-foot level, it had been boring through rock that was cemented together, although it had apparently been fragmented by the impact of a huge meteorite in the distant past. But at that level the drill reached a looser formation. A Hint in Less Dense Material</p>
        <p>Gravity measurements had indicated a deep-lying deposit of less dense material, which Dr. Gold had predicted might be a more porous deposit that could be a gas reservoir. He says he believes such a reservoir swallowed the drilling mud. There are oil seepages around the rim of the 44-mile-wide crater, he said, and farmers use methane escaping from their wells to heat their homes.</p>
        <p>He believes the source of that gas may be the hypothesized reservoir. Efforts are being made to retrieve the drill stem, Dr. Gold said at the meeting last week, and an attempt will be made to drill a few hundred feet deeper to determine what gas is there.</p>
        <p>The Manhattan meeting was organized by the brokerage house of Eberstadt Fleming Inc., to inform its clients of the project in Sweden, because vindication of the Gold hypothesis would have far-reaching implications for energy-related industries.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gold suggests that abundant methane, a major constituent of natural gas, makes its way near the surface wherever the earth's crust is deeply fractured. Such locations would include the sites where large meteorites struck and the regions behind curved arcs of volcanic islands, where the sea floor plunges into the earth's interior. Soviet Project's Results</p>
        <p>A well drilled more than 40,000 feet into the Kola Peninsula on the Arctic coast of the Soviet Union, the deepest penetration of the earth so far, has produced results reminiscent of those in the Swedish well. According to Yevgeny A. Kozlovsky, the Soviet Minister of Geology, such gases as methane and carbon dioxide, as well as various hydrocarbons, were encountered at all levels.</p>
        <p>Beginning at a depth of 15,000 feet, the Soviet drill cut for more than two miles into rock that had apparently been fractured by hydraulic action, making it less dense and three to four times more porous than the overlying formation. In an article in the magazine Scientific American, Dr. Kozlovsky reported that microscopic fossils in the region, dating back ''hundreds of millions of years,'' indicated that the gas released was partly biological in origin.</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Gold's hypothesis, once the planets were largely formed, they generated enough gravity to alter the orbits of comets and asteroids, bringing close to the Earth those that had formed on the Solar System's frigid outskirts. Many of the meteorites that struck the Earth in that early period were probably carbonaceous chondrites, a class of meteorites rich in hydrocarbons and other organic material.</p>
        <p>Soviet scientists have suggested that the two moons of Mars may be such carbon-containing objects. Such objects that fell to earth in its final formative stages, Gold says, would now form a layer 100 miles to 200 miles beneath the surface.</p>
        <p>The overlying rock was formed from volcanic activity and other processes, and only where it is ruptured can gas from the buried organic layer rise higher, Dr. Gold said. Where it does, seepage of methane into peat bogs has depleted the bogs' oxygen, preventing decay and permitting the formation of coal, he added.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
