<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>REPORT FEARS OVER-EXPLOITATION OF ANTARCTIC MARINE RESOURCES</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="20825"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISHING, COMMERCIAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">POLAND</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, WALTER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870312T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEED6163CF931A25750C0A961948260" item-length="854" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>REPORT FEARS OVER-EXPLOITATION OF ANTARCTIC MARINE RESOURCES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER SULLIVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Despite an international effort to avert over-exploitation of Antarctic marine resources, heavy commercial fishing, particularly by Soviet vessels, appears to have radically depleted some species, according to a newly completed American-Polish survey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Despite an international effort to avert over-exploitation of Antarctic marine resources, heavy commercial fishing, particularly by Soviet vessels, appears to have radically depleted some species, according to a newly completed American-Polish survey.</p>
        <p>Despite an international effort to avert over-exploitation of Antarctic marine resources, heavy commercial fishing, particularly by Soviet vessels, appears to have radically depleted some species, according to a newly completed American-Polish survey.</p>
        <p>The three-month study, which ended Feb. 22, was performed from the Polish research vessel Professor Siedliecki, chartered on behalf of the National Marine Fisheries Service of the United States. Scientists from that agency and its Polish counterpart assessed the impact of harvesting fish and krill, a tiny plankton-eating shrimp that provide food for seals, fish, penguins, whales and many other Antarctic species.</p>
        <p>Scientists also looked for signs that plankton are being damaged by ultraviolet radiation from the sun, which is reaching the sea surface because of a giant hole in the protective ozone layer of the stratosphere over the South Pole region. The scientists attempted to see how deeply such radiation penetrates Antarctic waters and hope to assess plankton's vulnerability to ultraviolet radiation. An International Effort</p>
        <p>The cruise was part of an international effort to piece together the elaborate interdependencies characteristic of Antarctic life. The recently begun study is scheduled to last 10 years. As maritime nations have closed offshore zones to foreign fishing, countries formerly dependent on such zones, including the Soviet Union, Poland and East Germany, have turned to Antarctica. Vessels from Japan are also fishing there, as well vessels from countries closer to Antarctica, such as Chile.</p>
        <p>According to the National Marine Fisheries Service, an agency of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, groups of 6 to 12 Soviet trawlers were sighted from the Professor Siedliecki in December.</p>
        <p>The Soviet Union participates in the 19-nation Commission for the Conservation of Antarctic Marine Living Resources. It was among the first to accept limitations on net design proposed by France for waters off the Kerguelen Islands, in the Indian Ocean, which are claimed by France. The large-mesh nets allow immature fish to escape. The limits are now widely accepted by other nations.</p>
        <p>But the Russians have resisted further fishing limitations, arguing that there was no convincing evidence of serious depletion. Lack of Study Funds Cited</p>
        <p>Bruce Mannheim, staff scientist of the Environmental Defense Fund in Washington, said in an interview that accumulation of such evidence has been hampered by lack of Federal money for the research.</p>
        <p>The research ''is absolutely essential if the United States is to have any hand in controlling the Soviet harvesting of Antarctic marine species,'' he said. Congress appropriated $2 million for this fiscal year, making it possible to charter the Polish ship. Federal officials hope that an American vessel can be allocated to the project for the next Antarctic summer, coinciding with northern winter.</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Kenneth Sherman of the National Marine Fisheries Service laboratories in Narragansett, R.I., the new survey has confirmed a West German report of abrupt drops in three species of cod-like notothenia in waters off South Georgia, an island in the South Atlantic near Antarctica. The population is only one-tenth what it was in 1982, said Dr. Sherman, chief scientist of the Antarctic Marine Living Resources Program.</p>
        <p>Assessing trends in the krill propulation has proved surprisingly difficult, he said. They become extremely concentrated at certain times and places and greatly depleted in other periods. Dr. Sherman, in a telephone interview last week, said that in 1981 a ''mind-boggling superswarm'' containing an estimated 1.5 million metric tons was observed around Elephant Island, north of the Antarctic Peninsula. Sonar Device Provides Data</p>
        <p>This year, according to Dr. Sherman, an intensive survey of that area found the krill only one-third as abundant. Estimates of krill abundance are largely based on data collected by a sonar device towed astern. The krill produce an echo distinctly different from that of other species, he said. The observations are periodically verified by net hauls.</p>
        <p>Assessing factors affecting the abundance of krill is complicated by the roles of such marine mammals as whales and crabeater seals. The latter, which inhabit the drifting pack ice that surrounds Antarctica, are now thought to eat more krill than all the whale species of Antarctica combined.</p>
        <p>A treaty for the protection of Antarctic seals allows them to be harvested for research purposes and the Soviet Union recently notified other adherents to the treaty that it was killing a number of crabeater seals under that provision. Whaling is now outlawed in Antarctica, Dr. Sherman said.</p>
        <p>Among nations whose ships are currently, or have recently, participating in the 10-year study are Britain, Chile, France, East and West Germany, South Africa and Spain, as well as the Soviet Union and the United States. The Soviet Union has agreed to allow scientific observers to ride its fishing ships, Dr. Sherman said, but the scientists have not yet done so.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
