<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Award Made To Professor For Cell Study</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="71" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="83791"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOLOGY AND BIOCHEMISTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PROTEINS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AWARDS, DECORATIONS AND HONORS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROCKEFELLER UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLOBEL, GUNTER (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TELTSCH, KATHLEEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Proteins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEEDA143AF93BA25753C1A961948260" item-length="725" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Award Made To Professor For Cell Study</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHLEEN TELTSCH, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TELTSCH, KATHLEEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Columbia University's prestigious Horowitz Prize has been awarded to Dr. Gunter Blobel, a cell biologist at the Rockefeller University. The $22,000 prize is given annually by Columbia for outstanding research in biology or biochemistry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Columbia University's prestigious Horowitz Prize has been awarded to Dr. Gunter Blobel, a cell biologist at the Rockefeller University. The $22,000 prize is given annually by Columbia for outstanding research in biology or biochemistry.</p>
        <p>Columbia University's prestigious Horowitz Prize has been awarded to Dr. Gunter Blobel, a cell biologist at the Rockefeller University. The $22,000 prize is given annually by Columbia for outstanding research in biology or biochemistry.</p>
        <p>The Horowitz awards have come to be regarded as frequent indicators of international recognition because more than half the recipients have gone on to win a Nobel Prize. The awards were created by a bequest in honor of the daughter of Dr. Samuel David Gross, a 19th-century Philadelphia surgeon. Winners are selected by a committee at Columbia University's College of Physicians and Surgeons.</p>
        <p>Dr. Blobel, who is 51 years old and has been a professor at Rockefeller since 1976, was honored for his contributions in unraveling the complex mechanism in which proteins are processed in the cell.</p>
        <p>The biologist and his wife were traveling in Europe when Columbia's selection was announced last week.</p>
        <p>Dr. Qais Al-Awqati, the selection committee chairman, said Dr. Blobel's findings were ''analagous to locating a zip code for the delivery of a letter -only in this case, the letters are proteins that are made in one place in the cell and carried elsewhere.''  COUNTERPOINT FOR WOMEN</p>
        <p>When photographs were published of the bicentennial celebration of the Constitution in Philadelphia last month, a group of feminists objected, saying the pictures lacked one major element: women.</p>
        <p>''Look at the picture of President Reagan and more than a hundred participants on stage in front of Independence Hall and you will not see one female,'' said Lynn Yeakel, executive director of Women's Way, which describes itself as the country's first local fund-raising organization created to encourage financial support for feminist issues and services helping women and girls. There are 29 other autonomous groups around the country with the same goal.</p>
        <p>Women's Way is celebrating its 10th anniversary in Philadelphia with a conference, to open Nov. 8, which was also organized as part of the 200th anniversary of the Constitution. The planners have picked as their theme, ''The Unfinished Agenda: Women's Future Under the Constitution.'' They intend to examine such questions as economic equity and violence against women. They will also be talking about what they regard as the relatively small share of philanthropy directed to programs for women and girls, which Ms. Yeakel estimated at 4 percent of all philanthropy.</p>
        <p>''We want our meetings to be a sobering counterpoint to the pageantry, parades and balloons of last month's festivities,'' Ms. Yeakel said. ''We expect 600 delegates from the 50 states. And we hope men will want to come.''</p>
        <p>Women's Way is at 125 South Ninth Street, Philadelphia, 19107.  3 SCIENTISTS HONORED</p>
        <p>Two scientists and an educator will each receive a $50,000 award for ''pioneer achievement'' from the Charles A. Dana Foundation of New York.</p>
        <p>One scientific award honors F. Sherwood Rowland, of the Department of Chemistry at the University of California at Irvine, for research and public advocacy aimed at preventing depletion of the earth's ozone layer, which shields plant and animal life from the harmful ultraviolet rays of the sun.</p>
        <p>A second award in the field of health was made to Dr. Alexander D. Langmuir for ground-breaking work in developing techniques of public health surveillance against such diseases as malaria. Dr. Langmuir, who is 77 and retired, was for 21 years chief epidemiologist at the Federal Centers for Disease Control, and he persuaded health workers in this country to adopt a system for rapid reporting and response to disease.</p>
        <p>Another Dana award, in the field of higher education, will go to Philip Uri Treisman, a faculty member at the University of California at Berkeley, for creating a mathematics workshop program that has improved the performance of minority-group students in freshman mathematics.</p>
        <p>The Dana Foundation also made two special awards for lifetime contributions, one to Mary W. Lasker, president of the Albert and Mary Lasker Foundation, for her contributions over almost half a century to the field of health, and a second award to James R. Killian Jr., former president and chairman of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. He was honored for his contributions over more than 60 years to the field of higher education.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
