<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Talking While the Acid Rains</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="28194"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MULRONEY, BRIAN (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEED8113DF934A35757C0A961948260" item-length="590" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Talking While the Acid Rains</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: When Prime Minister Brian Mulroney of Canada first met President Reagan in 1985, the President promised to study acid rain and the three million tons of pollutants the United States disgorges north to Canada each year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: When Prime Minister Brian Mulroney of Canada first met President Reagan in 1985, the President promised to study acid rain and the three million tons of pollutants the United States disgorges north to Canada each year.</p>
        <p>When Prime Minister Brian Mulroney of Canada first met President Reagan in 1985, the President promised to study acid rain and the three million tons of pollutants the United States disgorges north to Canada each year.</p>
        <p>At their next meeting in 1986, after the promised study confirmed that indeed, acid rain is a serious problem and that ''the potential for long-term socioeconomic costs is high,'' Mr. Reagan sidestepped doing anything about it but promised to allot more funds to study control techniques.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reagan didn't follow through on even that promise. But at their third meeting this week he proposed a new plan: He would fulfill his last year's promise of more study funds, and ''consider'' a treaty on acid rain.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Mulroney contemplates the 14,000 acid-dead lakes in eastern Canada, the 13 blighted salmon-bearing rivers in Nova Scotia and the stands of dying sugar maples in Quebec, he must begin to wish that Mr. Reagan would stop making promises and start opening his eyes.</p>
        <p>In his refusal to start reducing acid rain, Mr. Reagan stands in fast-dwindling company. The states of Massachusetts, Michigan, Minnesota, New Hampshire, New York and Wisconsin all recently resolved to order reductions in the waste gases that cause acid rain. So have many countries in Europe. The provinces of Ontario and Quebec have launched ambitious control programs.</p>
        <p>None of these costly programs were undertaken lightly. But the evidence is so overwhelming that only the chief polluters and the White House advocate another study in place of immediate action.</p>
        <p>Blue-ribbon scientific committees now see a clear causal chain between waste gases spewed from coal-burning power plants, like those in the Middle West, and dead fish in lakes hundreds of miles away in the Northeast United States and Canada. The sulfur and nitrogen oxides travel far from their source, forming sulfuric and nitric acids in rain or when deposited as gases. The acids slowly poison lakes and streams, especially in regions whose soils cannot neutralize them. At a certain stage of acidity, fish and water plants die.</p>
        <p>Dead fish are only the most visible symptom of acid rain, a weak but insidious poison that probably now affects the ecology of the whole Eastern Seaboard in myriad unseen ways. Acid rain and gases corrode buildings and injure lungs. Acid rain may well be a factor in the widespread death and slower growth of trees along the Appalachian range. Ozone is another probable contributor, and curtailing emissions of nitrogen oxides would cut back ozone as well as acid rain.</p>
        <p>As the picture becomes steadily clearer, scientific groups have urged that action against acid rain begin now, without waiting for the last details to be worked out. To protect lakes, the tonnage of sulfur emissions must be roughly halved, and nitrogen oxides also reduced, at a cost of about $5 billion a year. Such reductions would also lessen damage to forests, human health, buildings and visibility.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mulroney had to act gratified at the President's pledge to consider action. Considering his abrupt loss of popularity in Canada, the Prime Minister could do no less. But a pledge is a pledge; action is action.</p>
        <p>The cutbacks and costs would fall most heavily on the worst polluters, like the power plants of the Ohio River Basin that inject their gases up through tall stacks and export their wastes eastward. While their foot-dragging is tolerated, the drizzle of poison adds to a steadily mounting burden. While Mr. Reagan roams, land and water burn.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
