<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="52866"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRASS, GUNTER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">RAT, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2D71539F93AA15755C0A961948260" item-length="1051" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Christopher Lehmann-Haupt</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE RAT. By Gunter Grass. Translated from the German by Ralph Manheim. 371 pages. Helen and Kurt Wolff/Harcourt Brace Jovanovich. $17.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE RAT. By Gunter Grass. Translated from the German by Ralph Manheim. 371 pages. Helen and Kurt Wolff/Harcourt Brace Jovanovich. $17.95.</p>
        <p>THE RAT. By Gunter Grass. Translated from the German by Ralph Manheim. 371 pages. Helen and Kurt Wolff/Harcourt Brace Jovanovich. $17.95.</p>
        <p>''THE RAT'' is Gunter Grass's most substantial novel since ''The Flounder'' was published nearly a decade ago. In fact, the title character of that earlier book - who of course traces his lineage to the talking fish in the brothers Grimm fairy tale ''The Fisherman and His Wife'' - shows up in ''The Rat.''</p>
        <p>A barge called ''The New Ilsebill'' (after the overambitious wife in the fairy tale) is chugging around the Baltic Sea ''overmanned with five women'' who knit and knit, ''clicking needles against the flow of time.'' Their ostensible mission is to measure the density of the jellyfish infesting the fishing grounds and beaches of the western Baltic. (''Of course it's known in advance that the findings will be catastrophic.'') But their real purpose is to locate the submerged city of Vineta, ''offshore from the mouth of the Peene,'' once ruled by a gynecocracy. On the way, off the coast of Denmark, one of the women summons up the Flounder, who has repented his male chauvinism and speaks only to women now. He tells her that ''the end is near.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, back in West Germany, Oskar Matzerath, the dwarf protagonist of Mr. Grass's great first novel, ''The Tin Drum,'' is preparing a visit to his (and Mr. Grass's) birthplace, Danzig, now Gdansk, Poland, to celebrate the 107th birthday of his grandmother, Anna Koljaiczek. Oskar, nearly 60, is balding and has prostate troubles, but heads a successful video firm called Post Futurum whose project it is to package the future. As he prepares for his trip to Gdansk, he is completing a film in which ''the Grimm Brothers'' and their fairy tale characters take over the Bonn Government (''All power to the fairy tales!'') and try to save the dying forests of Germany.</p>
        <p>Oskar's projects on the future are narratively twinned with the work of Malskat, the painter on the past. Malskat has fooled all West Germany with his Gothic paintings on the ceiling of St. Mary's Church in Lubeck. For doing so, the narrator of ''The Rat'' designates him, along with Konrad Adenauer and Walter Ulbricht, one of the three great forgers of the ''phony fifties.''</p>
        <p>''The political forgeries are given the name of Republic; the murals are called the miracle of Lubeck. True, on this side and that side, and in the vaulting of the choir loft, swastikas are chiseled away; true, on this side and that side a message, on the one hand democratic, on the other communist, is spooned out like pudding, but yesterday's screams are long heard behind the new facades; however carefully the cellars are sealed, the smell of corpses cannot be hidden. . . . But the fraud is successful! On either side the defeated, who only a short while ago were begging for indulgence, have curried favor with the victor power.''</p>
        <p>Do all these plot developments sound impossibly jumbled and confusing? They aren't. The narrative is seamlessly welded together and lent power by a brown rat that the author has been given for Christmas. Sometimes the two of them listen to the Third Program - ''in the morning, lectures, Educational Radio for All, festive Baroque music, news at intervals, Report on the Media; then later, Echo of the Day, more Baroque music, this time religious'' - and dream of reason.</p>
        <p>More often, the narrator dreams of the ''She-rat,'' who recounts for him the history of her species. It is one of survival, because rats have learned what humans couldn't. Just as rats once survived being excluded from Noah's ark, by digging into the ground before the rains came, they have recently survived the end of mankind, which the rats themselves precipitated by messing up ''the Protector Powers'' computer systems.</p>
        <p>In the post-human era, they have survived religious contention, the conflict of the rat-nations, and even the coming of the rat-people (or Watsoncricks, after the discoverers of the helical structure of DNA), who had beautiful blue eyes, Nordic manners and a tendency to march in disciplined formation. Still, the rats dream of mankind. They miss people. Which is why the She-rat has chosen to imagine the narrator circling the Earth in a space capsule, the only explanation for his own survival.</p>
        <p>Is it a bore that Mr. Grass continues to complain about and satirize the cold war, mutual deterrence, nuclear arms, radioactive fallout, art-loving neutron bombs, acid rain, the death of Germany's forests, overpopulation, starvation, the maldistribution of surplus foods, the importation of Turkish labor, the ecological imbalance of the Baltic Sea, ''Nicaragua and more Nicaragua'' and ''the Dotard of the West, known for his homespun wit,'' as if nobody had ever worried about such things before. It's a bore to the degree that such bellyaching suffuses ''The Rat,'' and since that degree is considerable, this novel is not up to such major works as ''The Tin Drum,'' ''Dog Years'' or ''The Flounder.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Grass is too exuberant to remain a bore for long, as he continues to wreak the mischief of Till Eulenspiegel on German literature. Some of his nightmare scenes make your hair stand on end. His rewriting of ''The Pied Piper of Hamelin'' as a parable of punk is inspired. (It was not the rats but the children the good burghers really wanted to be rid of.) And reading his prose, as always superbly translated by Ralph Manheim, is like being wakened from the sleep of reason by acid rain. The leader of the bargewomen sings, after their cruise is over and their knitting ended because their yarn has run out:  In the search for differences be tween man and animal,  love is often mentioned as  a faculty peculiar to man.  Meant here is not  love of one's fellows, which is more  frequent  among animals than among men,  but that of Tristan and Isolde  and other exemplary couples  which even among swans  is inconceivable. . . .  No nightingale or lark, only man  loves at all costs, in and out of sea son, to the point of madness  and beyond the grave.  As we know, lovers would even like  to eat each other up.  That is true, dearest: at once, bones  and all.  But first - to a lute accompani ment - let us roast  a juicy loin of pork and eat it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
