<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>VOLCANO IN OCEAN ASTOUNDS SCIENTISTS</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="14954"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANOGRAPHY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VOLCANOES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAWAII</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SCRIPPS INSTITUTION OF OCEANOGRAPHY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SCIENCE FOUNDATION, NATIONAL (NSF)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLAKESLEE, SANDRA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARMON, CRAIG (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFD6143BF933A15751C0A961948260" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>VOLCANO IN OCEAN ASTOUNDS SCIENTISTS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANDRA BLAKESLEE, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BLAKESLEE, SANDRA</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Feb. 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A team of oceanographers has piloted a small submarine into the eye of an underwater volcano near Hawaii and reports finding a strange new world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A team of oceanographers has piloted a small submarine into the eye of an underwater volcano near Hawaii and reports finding a strange new world.</p>
        <p>A team of oceanographers has piloted a small submarine into the eye of an underwater volcano near Hawaii and reports finding a strange new world.</p>
        <p>''There were beautiful red terraces,'' Dr. Harmon Craig said, ''and shimmering water all around.'' Dr. Craig, a marine chemist at the Scripps Institution of Oceanography in La Jolla, Calif., said entering the volcano Loihi this week ''was like coming upon a fairy castle or seeing an abstract painting by Miro or Picasso.''</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in the crater were strange fish, possibly a new species or even a new genus. The fish were two feet long, with huge mouths, sharp fangs, blue eyes and front legs, Dr. Craig said, adding, ''We grabbed one and brought it back.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Craig's specimen, a female, died soon after it was brought to the surface. It was frozen and will be examined at Scripps. It Wasn't What They Expected</p>
        <p>These discoveries, conducted as part of an exploration program financed by the National Science Foundation, were unexpected, Dr. Craig said yesterday in a telephone interview from Hawaii. They came as the research submersible Alvin made a series of dives 30 miles south of the big Island of Hawaii. Dr. Harmon said it was the first time that anyone had visited an active underwater volcano.</p>
        <p>Dr. Craig said he and his colleagues had expected to find features like those at other vents, places where hot water or molten material from inside the earth reaches the ocean floor. But he said, ''Every notion we had as to what we would find was wrong.''</p>
        <p>''Just when you think you understand everything,'' he said, ''you have another surprise.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Craig has spent the last few years exploring vents found along parts of the Pacific Ocean floor, including a vast ridge, deep trenches and weak points in the rigid oceanic plate where molten rock from the earth's mantle can pour through. Such ''hot spots'' sometimes form underwater volcanoes that can breach the water's surface to become an island. As the plate drifts over it, the hot spot can give rise to a chain of islands. Loihi Remains Underwater</p>
        <p>Such was the case with the Hawaiian islands, formed one by one by the same hot spot, now 30 miles south of Kilahuea Volcano, which is still active. The hot spot is forming a new volcano, still under water, which is Loihi.</p>
        <p>Loihi's crater lies 3,000 feet below the ocean surface. It is three miles long and two miles wide, Dr. Craig said. Two small pits with sheer walls are inside the larger crater. Geolgists estimate that Loihi last erupted a few thousand years ago.</p>
        <p>When vents were discovered at hot spots and along the mid-ocean ridge several years ago, scientists found colonies of giant clams, mussels and tube worms.</p>
        <p>Studies indicated that Loihi had hot water vents, Dr. Craig said, and the scientists expected to find ''350-degree water, clams, mussels and worms.''</p>
        <p>The first few dives, he said, covered miles. ''We saw nothing but gray, black sands, grayish plains and uninteresting terrain,'' he said. 'A Bright Pastel Red'</p>
        <p>Then, on the fourth dive, the submarine came upon a small pinnacle covering a few hundred yards, carpeted with terraces of ''a fluffy material about five to six inches thick,'' Dr. Craig said. ''It was a bright pastel red, with all those little white mouths.'' The scientists think the red material may be a bacterial growth, but they do not know what the white material is or what would be inside the holes. Nearby, he continued, hexagonal columns of basalt had fallen, making the scene ''like a medieval castle in ruins with a beautiful red tapestry before your eyes.''</p>
        <p>Everything was shimmering, he said, because of hot water supersaturated with carbon dioxide. The gas was coming out the volcanic rocks, which Dr. Craig said ''fizz when you hit them.'' Water samples brought to the surface bubbled like champagne, he said. The shimmering water appeared to be flowing down the terraces, he said, perhaps because of currents.</p>
        <p>The red and white material, Dr. Craig said, ''broke off when we tapped it.'' Samples are being sent to several laboratories. 'The Ugliest Fish' Ever Seen</p>
        <p>There were few living creatures inside the volcano except for the fish. ''It is the ugliest fish you've ever seen, mostly mouth and jaws,'' said Dr. Craig. ''It sits there with its jaws propped open, running water through its mouth as fast as it can.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Craig said the fish had been tentatively named Nierenbergia in honor of Scripps's director emeritus, Prof. William A. Nierenberg, who is known for his loquaciousness.</p>
        <p>''It is better than being named after other things I can think of,'' Dr. Nierenberg said by phone. ''I am glad that Harmon Craig thinks that, while I'm gone, I'm not forgotten.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
