<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEW EVIDENCE IN DEMISE OF DINOSAUR</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="38626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PALEONTOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DINOSAURS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3DB173DF93AA35756C0A961948260" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEW EVIDENCE IN DEMISE OF DINOSAUR</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Geologists have found strong new evidence to support the theory that a huge asteroid or comet collided with the Earth 65 million years ago and could have been responsible for mass extinctions of life, including the demise of the dinosaurs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Geologists have found strong new evidence to support the theory that a huge asteroid or comet collided with the Earth 65 million years ago and could have been responsible for mass extinctions of life, including the demise of the dinosaurs.</p>
        <p>Geologists have found strong new evidence to support the theory that a huge asteroid or comet collided with the Earth 65 million years ago and could have been responsible for mass extinctions of life, including the demise of the dinosaurs.</p>
        <p>In a report yesterday in the journal Science, the geologists said that microscopic particles of quartz found in 65-million-year-old sediments around the world contained structural cracks associated with a single cataclysmic impact. The fracture patterns in the quartz, they said, appeared to rule out an alternative theory involving widespread volcanic eruptions as a cause of the extinctions.</p>
        <p>The scientists said the ''shocked quartz'' crystals were found in eight widely separated places, from Europe to New Zealand, indicating a global phenomenon. The crystals were embedded in the same sediment layers that contain abnormally high amounts of iridium, a metal that is rare on Earth but relatively common in asteroids and comets. The clay sediments were laid down at the time of the mass extinction. Iridium Called the Key</p>
        <p>It was the discovery of these high levels of iridium in the 1970's that inspired the theory that an extraterrestrial body crashed into the Earth, scattering dusty debris that enveloped the globe and turned day into night for months. The global darkness brought a destructive chill and death to countless species of plants and animals. The same period of extinctions saw the end of the dinosaurs' 160 million-year reign on Earth.</p>
        <p>The controversial theory was first proposed in 1980 by Walter Alvarez, a professor of geology at the University of California at Berkeley, and his Nobel Prize-winning father, Luis Alvarez, the physicist. Subsequent findings have confirmed the iridium anomaly, although the direct link between an impact and the extinctions is disputed.</p>
        <p>But in their new report, Bruce F. Bohor, Peter J. Modreski and Eugene E. Foord, researchers of the United States Geological Survey in Denver, concluded: ''These characteristic features of shocked quartz at several sites worldwide confirm that an impact event at the Cretaceous-Tertiary boundary distributed ejecta products in an earth-girdling dust cloud, as postulated by the Alvarez impact hypothesis.''</p>
        <p>The Cretaceous-Tertiary boundary they referred to is the layer of sediment laid down at the end of the Cretaceous geologic period and the beginning of the subsequent Tertiary era. This was the time, 65 million years ago, of the most recent of five mass extinctions of life. Only after the dinosaurs and other dominant reptiles passed from the scene did mammals begin to emerge as a dominant life form.</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Bohor, an asteroid or comet six miles wide that struck the Earth at 45,000 miles an hour, as calculated by the Alvarezes, could have blasted debris high enough into the atmosphere to account for the worldwide distribution of shock quartz.</p>
        <p>Because the largest of the quartz grains were found in Montana, and the smaller ones in more distant places, Dr. Bohor speculated that the impact occurred in the Northern Hemisphere, probably in North America. Volcanic Theorists Unswayed</p>
        <p>The microscopic fractures in the quartz were the type that could be produced only by sudden impacts exceeding 1.3 million pounds per square inch, the geologists reported. Dr. Bohor said the patterns were distinct from the type that would have resulted from the lesser pressures of volcanic eruptions.</p>
        <p>The leading proponents of the volcanic theory, Charles B. Officer and Charles L. Drake of Dartmouth College, said they were not ready to concede defeat. They had noted that the Earth was undergoing extensive volcanic activity at the time of the mass extinction and much of the excess iridium could have come from deep inside the Earth through the eruptions.</p>
        <p>Most paleontologists, although they might agree that an asteroid or comet disrupted the world, tend to attribute the demise of the dinosaurs to a complex set of many environmental factors, including the falling sea levels and cooler climate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
