<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Home Remedies</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19871115T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="77904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADON GAS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GILBERT, SUSAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5DC1038F934A1575AC0A961948260" item-length="3861" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Home Remedies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Susan Gilbert: Susan Gilbert is a freelance writer who lives in New York City.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GILBERT, SUSAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: WHEN BEN OLEWINE DECIDED to build a house in Fairfield County, Conn., he wanted to avoid using a material that, in his New York City apartment, had literally made him sick. ''My eyes were constantly irritated and I kept sneezing, getting congested and feeling nauseous,'' recalls Mr. Olewine, a marketing consultant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: WHEN BEN OLEWINE DECIDED to build a house in Fairfield County, Conn., he wanted to avoid using a material that, in his New York City apartment, had literally made him sick. ''My eyes were constantly irritated and I kept sneezing, getting congested and feeling nauseous,'' recalls Mr. Olewine, a marketing consultant.</p>
        <p>WHEN BEN OLEWINE DECIDED to build a house in Fairfield County, Conn., he wanted to avoid using a material that, in his New York City apartment, had literally made him sick. ''My eyes were constantly irritated and I kept sneezing, getting congested and feeling nauseous,'' recalls Mr. Olewine, a marketing consultant. ''One guest ended up being sick for two weeks.''</p>
        <p>Sniffing through the apartment, Mr. Olewine traced the problem to one of the bedrooms: ''I took everything out of the room until I was left with just the carpet and the wall covering. I put my nose to the carpet and didn't sneeze. Then I put my nose to the wall and sneezed like crazy.'' Mr. Olewine soon learned that he was sensitive to the formaldehyde in the wall covering's adhesive.</p>
        <p>Such severe reactions to formaldehyde made Mr. Olewine and his wife, Denise, think about other dangerous chemicals often found in homes - toxic fumes from paints and wood finishes, lead in the water, asbestos. To keep substances like these to the minimum, the Olewines hired Paul Bierman-Lytle, a Connecticut architect and contractor who has earned as much acclaim for his designs as for his use of unconventional nontoxic or low-toxic materials: formaldehyde-free particleboards and wallpaper glue, insulation made of cork, and wood finishes made of beeswax. His pristine constructions - there are only a handful in the country - cost about 20 percent more than conventionally built houses, but to the Olewines it was worth it. ''I really notice a difference,'' says Mr. Olewine. ''No sneezing, no nausea.''</p>
        <p>The Olewines' concern over their environment may be extreme, but it is by no means unwarranted. The Environmental Protection Agency estimates that indoor air pollutants cause as many as 6,000 cancer deaths each year and that radon causes an additional 20,000.</p>
        <p>''People get hysterical at the thought of hazardous waste sites,'' says Dr. John Spengler, a professor of environmental health at the Harvard University School of Public Health. ''But studies show that your risk of getting cancer from exposure to chemicals in the water, paint stripper and other solvents found in your home is greater than your risk from exposure to the same chemicals in a hazardous waste site. And these findings don't just apply to extremely polluted houses.''</p>
        <p>In response to increased awareness about in-door pollutants, a constellation of products and services have emerged in recent years to help homeowners and apartment dwellers identify, measure and remove harmful substances. Pollution control has ballooned into a billion-dollar-a-year business, and as more and more firms enter the field, environmental experts are warning consumers to beware of charlatans. In most states, lists of qualified companies can be obtained from either the department of environmental protection or the department of health.</p>
        <p>The United States Senate is considering whether the Federal government should protect the quality of the air inside private homes. But for the time being, the decision to confront household pollution is up to each individual. In most cases, people can clear the air and water in their homes easily and without spending a fortune.  ASBESTOS</p>
        <p>ASBESTOS WOULD BE A WONDER material if it weren't also highly carcinogenic. This fibrous mineral has been used to insulate walls and heating pipes, to soundproof rooms, to fireproof walls and fireplaces, to strengthen vinyl floors and joint compounds and to give many paints their texture. About one-quarter of the houses and apartment buildings constructed or remodeled between 1920 and 1970 contain asbestos.</p>
        <p>Asbestos poses a health hazard only if fibers are released into the air. But anything from pulling up old linoleum to putting in a new bathroom can make asbestos crack or disintegrate. If the fibers are inhaled, they can cause cancer of the lung, stomach and chest lining, as well as asbestosis, a lung disease that is usually fatal. Tobacco and asbestos are a particularly deadly combination. According to the American Lung Association, prolonged exposure to asbestos almost doubles the likelihood that a smoker will develop lung cancer.</p>
        <p>Since the 1970's, the Federal government has prohibited the use of asbestos in insulation, fire retardants, soundproofing materials and joint compounds, and it is considering a ban on asbestos in all consumer products. Meanwhile, 33 states have passed laws of their own. New York City has the toughest local regulation, which requires that owners of apartment buildings have them checked for asbestos before doing any major renovation, construction or demolition; they are also required to submit plans for either containing or removing the asbestos.</p>
        <p>The United States Consumer Products Safety Commission (C.P.S.C), an independent agency that works with the E.P.A., has compiled a list of E.P.A.-certified detection companies. For a free copy, write to Asbestos List, United States Consumer Products Safety Commission, Washington, D.C. 20207. The cost of inspection ranges from $500 to $2,000, depending on the size of your home. If the inspection shows there is asbestos, don't assume you must get rid of it. Asbestos insulation around heating pipes, for example, can be contained by wrapping the pipes with duct tape.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. recommends that asbestos be removed if it is in poor condition or if you are planning to do construction or renovation. If possible, hire a licensed asbestos removal company. Although the E.P.A. does not issue licenses, 22 states now do, up from only four states three years ago. New Jersey is the only state in the New York metropolitan area that has a licensing program, but New York State will start one in December. Most companies charge between $10 and $35 a square foot to scrape paint containing asbestos from walls, and between $15 and $35 a linear foot to remove asbestos insulation from heating pipes.</p>
        <p>If asbestos removal companies are not licensed in your area, use a firm with a track record. Many fly-by-night companies are trying to cash in on this booming business, says Michael Stahl, director of the E.P.A.'s asbestos program. These companies often do not remove the asbestos properly or clean up afterward, which may actually increase the number of fibers in the air.  RADON</p>
        <p>RADON, A RADIOACTIVE GAS, IS the second leading cause of lung cancer in the United States, after cigarette smoking. When you breathe in radon, it becomes trapped in your lungs and assaults them with radiation. A 10-year-old who has lived since birth in a house with high radon levels is four times as likely to develop lung cancer as an adult than a child who has not been consistently exposed.</p>
        <p>Radon is produced by the decay of uranium in soil and rocks. As far as scientists know, it is not a health hazard outdoors; it becomes a problem only when it accumulates in an enclosed area. Radon enters houses through drainpipes or cracks in foundations and concrete basement floors. Because some groundwater and aquifers are laced with the gas, it is also present in tap water.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. estimates that 10 percent of the houses in the United States are polluted with potentially life-threatening levels of radon - enough to cause lung cancer in 3 out of 100 people exposed to it for most of their lives. It is not uncommon to find one house riddled with radon, while its next-door neighbor is free of the gas. Scientists cannot explain this, but they suspect it has something to do with differences in ventilation and even in a house's orientation to the prevailing winds. In Pennsylvania and New Jersey, two states with unusually high radon levels, people routinely pay to have houses tested before deciding whether to buy them.</p>
        <p>Most companies that perform radon tests offer several different kinds. The E.P.A. recommends starting with the fastest, least expensive test. This involves leaving a small canister filled with charcoal, which absorbs radon, in the basement for several days, then returning it to the company for analysis. The test costs between $10 and $50. State radiation offices provide lists of companies that the E.P.A. has approved for measuring radon.</p>
        <p>Test results are given in a measurement called picocuries. If the test shows more than four picocuries per liter of air, the E.P.A. suggests checking several other rooms in the house. If these measurements exceed four picocuries when averaged together, you should take remedial action.</p>
        <p>The first step most radon abatement companies will recommend is to seal cracks in foundation walls and concrete basement floors, which generally costs between $300 and $500. But according to Michael Mardis, chief of the radon mitigation, protection and quality assurance branch of the E.P.A., ''just sealing the cracks rarely reduces radon levels.''</p>
        <p>In most cases it is necessary to install a special ventilation system, at a cost of $1,000 to $5,000. Although these systems can eliminate as much as 99 percent of the radon in a house, Mr. Mardis notes that their effectiveness depends on the house's construction. For example, one ventilation system, which draws radon from basement walls and expels it outside, works only if the walls are made of cinder blocks.</p>
        <p>State environment or health departments have lists of companies qualified to remedy radon pollution. In New York State, call 800-342-3722; in New Jersey, 800-648-0394, and in Connecticut, 203-566-8167. Two free booklets - ''Radon Reduction Methods: A Homeowner's Guide'' and ''A Citizen's Guide to Radon: What It Is and What to Do About It''-are also available from these offices.  FORMALDEHYDE</p>
        <p>IT IS ALMOST IMPOSSIBLE TO avoid formaldehyde gas. It's in the resins used to make most particleboard, plywood and wood paneling; the foam in urea formaldehyde insulation; the sizing applied to upholstery and drapes; the adhesives used with carpeting and wallpaper; the ''permanent press'' resin in clothes; the germ killer in toothpaste - and the ink in the dollar bills that pay for all these things.</p>
        <p>Formaldehyde has been used in construction and manufacturing for more than 100 years, but only in the last decade have studies linked the gas to nasal cancer in laboratory animals. Formaldehyde fumes can also cause chronic respiratory problems, dizziness, rashes, lethargy and nausea.</p>
        <p>Materials containing formaldehyde emit the highest levels of gas when they are new, but they continue to release vapors for years. New houses and mobile homes have the highest formaldehyde levels - enough, in some cases, to cause long-term health problems, according to a report released this summer by the Department of Energy.</p>
        <p>The 3-M Corporation makes the only device that people can use to measure the ambient formaldehyde levels in their homes. The device is a canister containing filter paper that has been chemically treated to react with formaldehyde. The canister should be left in any room for eight hours, then mailed to 3-M for analysis. The company will tell you whether the amount of formaldehyde in the room exceeds the limit that the Federal government has established as safe for work places. The canisters, which cost $49.95 each, can be ordered from 3-M Monitors, A.F.S., P.O. Box 10752, White Bear Lake, Minn. 55110 (612-426-0691).</p>
        <p>The best way to minimize the formaldehyde in your home is to avoid buying products that contain the gas. Look for the low-formaldehyde or formaldehyde-free wood boards and adhesives that have come on the market in recent years.</p>
        <p>There are also two simple strategies for reducing the amount of formalde-hyde already in your home. One is to apply an epoxy sealer to particleboard, fiberboard and plywood to keep these materials from emitting the gas. The other is to buy some house plants. Research by NASA has shown that the leaves of philodendrons, spider plants and other common house plants absorb formaldehyde. According to Dr. Bill Wolverton, senior research scientist at NASA, ''About 15 to 20 plants should completely remove the formaldehyde from an 1,800-square-foot house.''  WATER POLLUTANTS</p>
        <p>LAST YEAR, 2 PERCENT OF THE country's community water supplies posed a significant risk to human health, according to the E.P.A. One-quarter violated the agency's regulations for maintaining drinking water quality. And environmental groups charge that those regulations are lax -the E.P.A. sets limits on only 30 pollutants, even though the 1986 amendment to the Safe Drinking Water Act requires standards for 83.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. estimates that 38 million Americans drink water tainted with unsafe levels of lead, which causes hypertension in adults, learning disabilities in children, neurological damage in fetuses and miscarriages. The agency has proposed cutting by half the amount of lead allowed in drinking water, but this alone would do little to address the problem. Most lead gets into water as it passes through the pipes in your town or even your house, yet Federal laws require that water be tested only in reservoirs, water towers and other places where it is stored.</p>
        <p>Several carcinogens are also present in much of the country's drinking water. ''The carcinogens we are most concerned about are radon and the byproducts of chlorine, which is used to disinfect water,'' says Lawrence Jensen, the E.P.A.'s assistant administrator for water. Despite the presence of carcinogens, research suggests that most tap water is relatively safe. According to a study published this year in Science, one quart of chlorinated tap water is less carcinogenic than, among other things, one raw mushroom.</p>
        <p>Many local water suppliers will test tap water for contaminants, sometimes without charge. There are also commercial water-testing laboratories. The largest of these, WaterTest, provides home testing kits and laboratory analyses that cost from $29.95 for measuring bacteria levels to $104.95 for detecting carcinogens. Contact WaterTest Corporation, P.O. Box 6360, Manchester, N.H. 03108-6360 (800-426-8378).</p>
        <p>If you have questions about your water, call the E.P.A.'s toll-free number (800-426-4791). To lower the lead content of your water, the E.P.A. recommends running the cold water from each faucet for about two minutes every morning to flush out water that has been sitting in the pipes all night, accumulating lead. WaterTest considers this a waste of time and water. ''Sometimes lead content actually goes up,'' says Jeff Vaughn, the company's public relations manager.</p>
        <p>Many of the agency's other suggestions are less controversial. Always use cold tap water for cooking, since hot water strips pipes of more lead. And let your water supplier know if you have any complaints about your drinking water. ''Water companies can reduce lead content by more than half by treating the water to make it less corrosive,'' says Jeanne Briskin, an E.P.A. chemist.</p>
        <p>Significant amounts of lead and many other pollutants can be eliminated from tap water with purifiers available at hardware stores and retailers that specialize in water treatment devices. There are three kinds of purifiers. Reverse osmosis devices and distillers remove lead and other metals as well as microbes, and activated carbon filters absorb chlorine byproducts and radon. Since none of the purifiers acts on the entire spectrum of contaminants, you should have your water tested so you can choose the most appropriate one.</p>
        <p>The best purifiers treat all the water in your house. They cost between $500 and $1,500, and yearly maintenance can be as high as $100. Less expensive units are available for individual faucets. The National Sanitation Foundation, an independent research organization, has compiled a list of the most effective purifiers. For a copy of the list, write to Nancy Culotta at the foundation, 3475 Plymouth Road, Ann Arbor, Mich. 48106.  HOUSEHOLD CHEMICALS</p>
        <p>MANY PRODUCTS THAT CLEAN, beautify and fumigate house and garden can also cause serious illnesses. Some of the same toxic chemicals discharged by factories and cars are used in paints, paint thinners, cleaners and other products. These chemicals -often found in higher concentrations inside a house than outside - have been linked to cancer and respiratory ailments as well as nausea and dizziness. Ammonia, for example, can inflame the respiratory tract, and some doctors advise asthmatics to avoid using any cleaners that contain it.</p>
        <p>There are about 50,000 pesticides on the market, and greater quantities are strewn on residential lawns and gardens than on farms. Four of the most widely used chemicals - 2,4-D, benomyl, chlorothalonil and glyphosate -have been linked to cancer and reproductive problems.</p>
        <p>No pesticide has caused more public furor in recent years than chlordane, the most widely used termite-killing chemical in the country. Studies have linked chlordane to cancer, neurological disorders and miscarriages.This summer, the sole manufacturer of chlordane took it and a similar chemical called heptachlor off the market, though exterminators can continue using the supplies stored in their warehouses.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. estimates that 3 out of 1,000 people exposed to chlordane or heptachlor in their homes may develop cancer, but doesn't consider this health risk great enough to warrant banning the pesticides. New York and Minnesota disagree and prohibit the use of both chlordane and heptachlor; Massachusetts has banned chlordane.</p>
        <p>The best way to minimize exposure to toxic household chemicals is to use safer alternatives - water-based paints that do not contain petrochemicals, beeswax floor cleaners and waxes, paint thinners made from plant oils and a class of termiticides called permethrins, which are not carcinogenic. Other nontoxic pesticides are available in many hardware stores. If you have questions about pesticides, write to the National Coalition Against the Misuse of Pesticides, 530 7th Street, S.E., Washington, D.C. 20003.</p>
        <p>Whenever you use paints, paint thinners or cleaners, make sure there is plenty of ventilation - either from open windows or exhaust fans. Store used cans of paint and paint thinner in an outdoor shed or detached garage. If you don't have an outdoor storage area, discard the cans. ''If you store them in the basement and find that six months later the cans are empty,'' says Dr. John Spengler of Harvard, ''just think about where the vapors have gone.''  COMBUSTION GASES</p>
        <p>ANY APPLIANCE THAT BURNS fuel discharges byproducts of combustion such as carbon dioxide. If these gases build up in your house, they can cause chronic bronchitis, headaches, dizziness, nausea and fatigue.</p>
        <p>All local building codes require that gas furnaces be fitted with pipes to vent their exhaust outdoors, but many codes do not cover other gas appliances. ''Local building codes for ventilation are geared to achieve minimum levels of comfort,'' says Dr. Spengler, ''not safety.''</p>
        <p>Gas appliances that are not working properly churn out excessive amounts of carbon dioxide. And wood-burning stoves by their very nature discharge smoke that contains carcinogenic hydrocarbons. ''It's like having a car running in the middle of your living room,'' says Dr. Robert McLellan, director of environmental and occupational health at the Gesell Institute for Human Development in New Haven. He explains that wood stoves expel more smoke indoors than fireplaces because they burn the wood more slowly. ''You can decrease the indoor pollution from your wood stove,'' he says, ''by opening the damper so the wood burns faster.''</p>
        <p>The first step in decreasing the fumes given off by gas appliances is to have them serviced regularly. Furnaces should be inspected and chimneys cleared of debris in the fall. The Gas Research Institute suggests that you periodically check your gas range by examining the pilot light and the flames from the burners. They should be blue; if they are yellow, the range is releasing too much carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>''I advise everyone with a gas range to buy a ventilation hood that vents the gas outside,'' says Dr. McLellan, who recently started a company that inspects houses for pollution. ''Most of the hood fans that come with ranges do nothing but filter grease and recirculate polluted air.'' Outdoor ventilation systems for gas ranges cost between $200 and $800, depending on how far the appliances are from an exterior wall.</p>
        <p>Anyone in the market for a new range should consider an electric range or one that runs on gas but is ignited by an electric spark. Spark ignition, according to the Gas Research Institute, cuts fuel consumption - and the amount of combustion gases released - by one-third.</p>
        <p>Dr. McLellan has a final warning about gas ovens: ''This may seem too obvious to mention, but never use your oven to heat your house. You can asphyxiate yourself with carbon dioxide.''  ALLERGENS</p>
        <p>ONE OUT OF EVERY SIX AMER-icans is allergic to something, and all the allergens that make you sneeze and itch outdoors find their way indoors. ''You carry pollen inside on your clothes or in your hair,'' says Dr. McLellan. ''And it blows indoors when you open your windows.''</p>
        <p>There are dozens of air-cleaning devices on the market, and some of them do an excellent job of filtering pollen as well as dust, smoke and animal fur. Although the models designed to sit on a desk or table are too small to be very useful, the larger units can remove as much as 75 percent of the particles floating in a 120-square-foot room in just half an hour. These units range in price from $100 to $450.</p>
        <p>The best air cleaners use a fan to draw in dirty air and circulate clean air. One type, called an electrostatic precipitator, contains electrodes that give particles a positive electrical charge. The particles are then magnetically attracted to negatively charged plates. Negative ion generators work according to a similar principle. Another type of air cleaner uses a so-called high-efficiency particulate filter made of a fine Fiberglas mesh to snare airborne particles.</p>
        <p>The Association of Home Appliance Manufacturers (A.H.A.M.), a trade organization, has rated several air cleaners. For a list of the ratings, send a self-addressed stamped envelope to A.H.A.M., Room Air Cleaner Program, 20 North Wacker Drive, Chicago, Ill. 60606.</p>
        <p>No air purifier is a substitute for cleaning your house. But even if you dust and mop every day, allergens inevitably collect inside humidifiers, dehumidifiers and air-conditioners. And these appliances inevitably blow the allergens back at you. So it is important to clean humidifiers and drain dehumidifiers once a week, and to have air-conditioning units serviced, and their filters cleaned, every spring.</p>
        <p>If you develop an allergic reaction to your dog or cat, but can't bear to give it away, Dr. McLellan advises that the pet be kept out of the bedroom and brushed outdoors by someone who is not allergic - once a week throughout the summer and less frequently during the rest of the year. People with allergies who don't have a dog or cat, however, should not look for trouble. ''I used to suggest that these people get turtles, until I found out that they carry salmonella,'' says Dr. McLellan. ''Now I recommend goldfish.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 15, 1987, Sunday, Late City Final Edition</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 15, 1987, Sunday, Late City Final Edition</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
