<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Hunt for Better Coal Plants</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="80658"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOMERSET (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ELECTRIC POWER RESEARCH INSTITUTE (EPRI)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1D91730F934A35753C1A961948260" item-length="907" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Hunt for Better Coal Plants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>SOMERSET, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The coal-burning electricity plant here, about 45 miles northeast of Buffalo, is considered ''state of the art.'' Federal regulators and environmental activists agree that the plant meets pollution standards for air and water.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The coal-burning electricity plant here, about 45 miles northeast of Buffalo, is considered ''state of the art.'' Federal regulators and environmental activists agree that the plant meets pollution standards for air and water.</p>
        <p>The coal-burning electricity plant here, about 45 miles northeast of Buffalo, is considered ''state of the art.'' Federal regulators and environmental activists agree that the plant meets pollution standards for air and water.</p>
        <p>But that achievement comes at a price. Utility executives point out that the pollution control equipment cost $350 million and that it consumes millions of kilowatt-hours of electricity a year. Moreover, it takes up a quarter-mile strip between the boiler and the stack, space that would simply not be available at old urban power plants.</p>
        <p>The challenge now is to produce energy from high-sulfur coal just as cleanly, but at a much lower cost. The electric power industry, coal producers and government are hoping that a $45 million research center, opened next to the plant here earlier this year, can find answers. Importance of the Research</p>
        <p>The research is crucial because two-thirds of the electricity produced in this country is generated with coal, and 30 percent of the plants use high-sulfur coal, the type found in northern Appalachia, according to the Electric Power Research Institute, a utility group. (An older research station, Arapahoe, in Denver, performs research on Western coal, which is much lower in sulfur but presents ash emission problems.) In plants built to meet current standards using Eastern high-sulfur coal, one-third of the capital cost goes into pollution control, and running that equipment typically consumes 3 percent to 5 percent of the plant's power output.</p>
        <p>Finding ways to lower the cost of pollution control for coal could be a boon not only to the coal industry but to energy consumers. ''Coal is a bargain, at least as it leaves the mine,'' said B.R. Brown, president and chief executive officer of the Consolidation Coal Company, a co-sponsor of the new research center.</p>
        <p>The center, which will cost $20 million to run over the next 10 years, was formed by the Electric Power Research Institute, with help from not only Consolidation but Somerset's owner, the New York State Electric and Gas Corpora-tion, and the Federal and New York State governments.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, present methods of burning coal cleanly are expensive. According to the Department of Energy, $60 billion has been spent since 1970 to control pollution at coal plants. In part that is because Federal law requires that plants with boilers ordered after September 1978, including the Somerset plant, be built to reduce sulfur emissions by 70 percent to 90 percent.</p>
        <p>The utility industry favors some technologies that would remove sulfur from flue gases at a lower cost per ton but do a less complete job than the technology in use at Somerset. Such steps could be combined with washing the coal before burning, allowing utilities to use a ''mix and match'' strategy to meet pollution requirements, according to Stuart M. Dalton, who manages the desulfurization research being conducted by the electric power institute. Environmentalists' View</p>
        <p>While environmentalists do not object to the industry looking for ways to clean up plants more cheaply, they insist that existing methods are not unacceptably expensive. ''What you are dealing with is a desire by the industry to further reduce costs from what are already acceptable cost levels in our view,'' said David G. Hawkins, a senior attorney with the Natural Resources Defense Council and a former assistant administrator for air programs in the Environmental Protection Agency under President Carter.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists also say that some of the research here is focused on less thorough cleanup systems. The industry is ''finding ways to do half the job for a quarter of the price,'' Mr. Hawkins said.</p>
        <p>The environmentalists point out that some of these less potent methods are being studied for installation in older plants under proposals to control acid rain, and they argue that these methods are not effective enough.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hawkins said that West Germany, for one, agrees with the view that clean energy with current technology is worth the price. West Germany decided in 1983 to require all coal plants to use existing anti-pollution technology and that the equipment would be fully installed by the end of this year. Basic Research Needed</p>
        <p>The problems being researched at the center illustrate how much remains to be done to refine the technology. Some of the experiments are as basic as improving the recipes for acid-scrubbing systems by varying the fineness of the limestone used to neutralize the sulfur dioxide. Another question is whether the end product is cleaner if the system that removes particles is installed ahead of the acid-scrubber or behind it. Other experiments will methodically vary temperatures, pressures and the ratio of gas to scrubbing material to find the best mix.</p>
        <p>The control equipment has two key goals. The first is to reduce the amount of pollution going up the stack in the form of sulfur oxides, nitrogen oxides and particulates. The second is to collect the pollutants in an environmentally benign form. For example, one system produces calcium sulfate, which is gypsum that can be sold for commercial use.</p>
        <p>An overriding problem is that all coal is not alike. It varies widely in sulfur content, energy potential and other chemical characteristics. And because each coal-burning plant is designed to use only a small range of coals, existing scrubbers must be custom built.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
