<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CANADIANS SCOLD BUSH OVER TRADE AND ACID RAIN</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="6049"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURNS, JOHN F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MULRONEY, BRIAN (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1D81E31F931A15752C0A961948260" item-length="860" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CANADIANS SCOLD BUSH OVER TRADE AND ACID RAIN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BURNS, JOHN F</byline>
      <dateline>OTTAWA, Jan. 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Canadian officials, in an unusually fractious mood, met today with Vice President Bush today and demanded that the Reagan Administration make greater efforts to fulfill commitments on trade, acid rain and other issues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Canadian officials, in an unusually fractious mood, met today with Vice President Bush today and demanded that the Reagan Administration make greater efforts to fulfill commitments on trade, acid rain and other issues.</p>
        <p>Canadian officials, in an unusually fractious mood, met today with Vice President Bush today and demanded that the Reagan Administration make greater efforts to fulfill commitments on trade, acid rain and other issues.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Bush standing beside him, Prime Minister Brian Mulroney complained of American indifference to Canada in terms that have long been common in Canadian politics but are rarely used, at least in public, when top United States officials are visiting.</p>
        <p>''The biggest trading partner of the United States is not West Germany or Japan, it's right here, by a long shot,'' Mr. Mulroney said. ''And the Government of Canada, and Canadians, don't want to be on anybody's back burner, or taken for granted at any time.''</p>
        <p>Moments later, the Prime Minister, having described himself as a friend of the United States who did not share his political opponents' propensity to ''throw verbal hand grenades'' at Washington, lashed out anew at United States efforts to reduce acid rain.</p>
        <p>The Government here has described the United States Administration's $287 million budget appropriation for 1987-88 (mainly for the development of clean coal-burning technology) as a breach of an agreement signed by President Reagan and Mr. Mulroney.</p>
        <p>Asked whether he considered the United States expenditures to be consistent with the undertaking of a five-year, $5 billion technology development program by United States Government and industry that Mr. Reagan made in Washington last May, Mr. Mulroney replied: ''Absolutely not. There's a lot more that they can do. I'm from Missouri, and I'm going to believe this when I see the cash.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, accompanied by Treasury Secretary James A. Baker, spent barely five hours here on a trip that was arranged last week at the request of Mr. Mulroney. With his Government's popularity slipping badly in public opinion polls, the Canadian leader used the occasion to present a new image as a man prepared to speak toughly to the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mulroney, a former executive with a United States-owned iron ore company, made his mark early in his 28-month tenure with friendliness toward the United States that went beyond the more cautious approach characteristic of previous Canadian leaders.</p>
        <p>Lately, this appeared to become a political liability as issues that are top priorities here, but of lesser concern in Washington - mainly trade, acid rain and Canadian sovereignty claims in the Arctic - produced a series of disputes and disappointments for the Canadians. With Mr. Mulroney struggling simultaneously against a new corruption scandal in his administration, his advisers saw the Bush meeting as an opportunity to recoup.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, expressionless as Mr. Mulroney spoke with reporters, then made remarks that appeared to recognize the political implications of the meeting for the Canadian.</p>
        <p>The Vice President said that of all the United States' foreign relationships, ''this one has got to rank as the most important.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush offered no immediate concessions, saying his purpose in coming had been to ''listen'' to the Canadians and to offer an American view. But he said that he would be conveying Mr. Mulroney's concerns to President Reagan when the two meet at the White House tomorrow, ''and between Secretary Baker and I, I hope that we will have some suggestions that will cope with some of the problems.''</p>
        <p>A major Canadian complaint at the meeting was that the United States has been paying insufficient attention to Mr. Mulroney's most risky political initiative, the effort begun last year to negotiate a ''free trade'' deal with the United States.</p>
        <p>Because the deal would involve trading lower tariffs on Canada's heavily protected industries for wider access to United States markets, Mr. Mulroney has been vulnerable to charges by labor groups and other opponents at home that he is gambling with Canadian jobs and ''sovereignty.''</p>
        <p>Lately, his problems have been compounded by a series of retaliatory tariffs and restrictions imposed by the United States on major Canadian exports, notably softwood lumber.</p>
        <p>The Prime Minister's appeal to Mr. Bush today was for Washington to follow Canada's lead and give the trade talks the ''highest priority.'' The absence of this he described as ''sort of strange'' given the extent of trade between the two countries, which sees $150 billion worth of merchandise crossing the border each year. By pressing the talks to a successful conclusion, he said, the United States would give the world a model of how to liberalize trade.</p>
        <p>In reply, Mr. Bush alluded to the protectionist mood in Congress and the problems it was posing. FREE TRADE DISCUSSED</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON, Jan. 21 - Mr. Bush said aboard his plane returning to Washington that he discussed with Mr. Mulroney ways to speed talks with Canada on freer trade between the two countries.</p>
        <p>The United States has already said it hoped to meet a deadline this September for forwarding a free trade pact to Congress. But the Ottawa Government, which has laid great stress on the importance of such a pact, has been concerned that the Reagan Administration will let the timetable slide.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
