<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FINE FRENCH FARE: SEARCH NO MORE</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="21901"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANT REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SOIR, LE (BAYPORT, NY, RESTAURANT)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STARKEY, JOANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5D9113EF936A25750C0A961948260" item-length="893" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FINE FRENCH FARE: SEARCH NO MORE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STARKEY, JOANNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: LE SOIR in Bayport is the dream everyone hopes to find: an attractive little French restaurant serving good food at reasonable prices. It is not a secret, though, for Le Soir has been in business for 10 years and has a large following.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: LE SOIR in Bayport is the dream everyone hopes to find: an attractive little French restaurant serving good food at reasonable prices. It is not a secret, though, for Le Soir has been in business for 10 years and has a large following.</p>
        <p>LE SOIR in Bayport is the dream everyone hopes to find: an attractive little French restaurant serving good food at reasonable prices. It is not a secret, though, for Le Soir has been in business for 10 years and has a large following.</p>
        <p>You might question the use of the word reasonable when the average entree price is $15. But that price includes both soup and salad and, with careful ordering, an excellent French meal here need not break the budget. The included soup and salad are both excellent.</p>
        <p>The soups that we tried, a cream of winter vegetable and a creamy but light pea soup, were first rate. The house salad includes leaf lettuce, watercress, endive and radicchio in a creamy vinaigrette that is a perfect blend of flavors.</p>
        <p>For those not counting pennies, there are some fine a la carte appetizer choices. The clams casino were tiny, tender and delicious. The oysters mignonette featured a red-wine vinegar sauce with shallots and cracked pepper. The house pate, served with a grainy French mustard, and the fish pate, with its saffron sauce, were both winners. The baked onion soup was as good as it gets.</p>
        <p>Other recommended appetizers include superior versions of classic dishes: escargots in a delicious garlicky snail butter; a beautifully presented artichoke with the choke removed, served either hot with melted butter or at room temperature with a tangy Dijon mustard vinaigrette; coquilles St.-Jacques, consisting of tiny sweet scallops in a tasty cream sauce lightly glazed with cheese, and lively pimento-flecked marinated mushrooms.</p>
        <p>Only the steamed mussels and the fish soup au gratin were disappointing. The sauce on the mussels was of dunking quality, but the mussels were small and a few were sandy. The fish soup was a thick brown bisque of undetermined taste. One diner at our table thought it was a strange-tasting onion soup until we reminded him that he had ordered fish bisque. Bread is another disappointment. It is standard commercial French bread.</p>
        <p>Diners will find old favorites among the entree choices: a crisp-skinned duck in orange sauce, a hearty boeuf bourguignon, tender, pink roast rack of lamb, a buttery filet mignon with a fine bearnaise sauce, a large juicy pepper steak, a perfectly cooked cod steak with tarragon butter, a stellar version of veal francaise, and meltingly tender frogs' legs in garlic butter.</p>
        <p>Less classic, but equally good, were the sauteed salmon in a cracked black pepper sauce, the properly pink calf's liver in a raspberry vinegar sauce and the rack of veal, which in reality was a thick, delicious veal chop. Only the chewy lobster in whisky sauce was less than enjoyable.</p>
        <p>Even the tightest penny pincher should not skip dessert. I tried them all and none were found wanting. Chocolate lovers will find a superassertive chocolate mousse and a decadently rich chocolate ganache cake. A wonderfully creamy cheesecake, a tangy apple and rhubarb cobbler and a lovely, light strawberry tart were other favorites.</p>
        <p>Le Soir has a formidable wine list of nearly 100 choices. While prices range widely from $12 to $85, the average bottle costs about $17 or $18. This is a thoughtfully constructed compilation of wines that includes some interesting and unusual French, California and Long Island vineyards. A number of the bottles on the list are young, however, and, while drinkable, are not yet near their peak.</p>
        <p>On busy weekend nights, the service staff, which is generally competent, gets a bit overwhelmed by the crowds and the tight quarters. The look of the restaurant is cozy French country, but cozy can be too chummy on a crowded night. The tables in the center of the room place the diner either on top of the people at the next table or in the path of the scurrying staff. Tables along the walls are comfortable and preferable.</p>
        <p>Away from the action at the center of the room, diners can relax and enjoy the simple yet attractive dining room. Black and white antique drawings adorn the white stuccoed and half-timbered walls. One wall has been replaced by glass, creating a sense of airiness and space. The greenhouse effect and the large green plants soften the black and white decor.In the adjoining room is a small jewel of a bar: the perfect place to have a drink, smell the lovely cooking aromas and anticipate the great French meal to come.</p>
        <p>A three-course meal with wine, tax and tip averages $25 a person. If you choose an a la carte appetizer and dessert, add $10 to the average.</p>
        <p>Le Soir has been closed for winter vacation and will reopen Wednesday.  LE SOIR  Very Good</p>
        <p>825 Montauk Highway, Bayport. 472-9090.</p>
        <p>Atmosphere: Cozy, country French.</p>
        <p>Service: Competent.</p>
        <p>Recommended dishes: House salad, clams casino, oysters mignonette, house pate, fish pate, onion soup, duck in orange sauce, filet mignon, veal francaise, frogs' legs, salmon in black pepper sauce, calf's liver, cod steak with tarragon butter, rack of veal, all desserts.</p>
        <p>Price range: Appetizers $3.95 to $8.25, entrees (includes soup and salad) $13.95 to $19.75.</p>
        <p>Credit cards: Visa and American Express.</p>
        <p>Hours: 5 to 10 P.M. Tuesday through Sunday.</p>
        <p>Reservations: Recommended.  Ratings:  Poor  Satisfactory  Good  Very good  Excellent  Extraordinary</p>
        <p>These ratings are based on the reviewer's reaction to food and price in relation to comparable establishments.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
