<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Surviving in the Cold: Strategies Revealed in New Studies</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="101956"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEASONS AND MONTHS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MIGRATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HIBERNATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRODY, JANE E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COURTIN, GIRARD (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARCHAND, PETER J (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Migration</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hibernation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DF123BF936A25751C1A961948260" item-length="1676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Surviving in the Cold: Strategies Revealed in New Studies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE E. BRODY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRODY, JANE E</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: AS winter grips the fields and forests of the north, life seems to be put on hold. The trees have lost their leaves, the food factories that nourish them and provide sustenance and shelter for birds and insects. Adult insects die, leaving eggs and larvae in protected nooks and crannies to start the next generation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: AS winter grips the fields and forests of the north, life seems to be put on hold. The trees have lost their leaves, the food factories that nourish them and provide sustenance and shelter for birds and insects. Adult insects die, leaving eggs and larvae in protected nooks and crannies to start the next generation.</p>
        <p>AS winter grips the fields and forests of the north, life seems to be put on hold. The trees have lost their leaves, the food factories that nourish them and provide sustenance and shelter for birds and insects. Adult insects die, leaving eggs and larvae in protected nooks and crannies to start the next generation. Birds and marine mammals migrate to warmer climes. Bears, woodchucks, mice and squirrels escape into hibernation.</p>
        <p>But, as a small group of cold-loving biologists are demonstrating, the barren torpor of winter is only an illusion. Life, sometimes very active life, persists winterlong - under the ground, under the ice, under the snow, on top of the snow and in the air. Through a remarkable series of adaptations, few of which are fully understood, plants and animals that might otherwise freeze or starve to death manage to survive and in some cases thrive all winter, even when their usual food supply lies dead or buried under snow and the temperature of the air falls way below zero.</p>
        <p>One insect, the snow scorpionfly, one quarter inch long with legs like stilts to keep its body off the snow, has chosen the predator-free wintertime for its mating season. On days when bright sun warms the snow so that their feet are unlikely to freeze, male and female scorpionflies climb perhaps three feet through the snowpack, meet on the surface, mate and then descend back to the moss beneath the snow before the sun sets.</p>
        <p>''What cue tells the scorpionfly when to come up and when to go down is a mystery we're still trying to decipher,'' said Girard Courtin, winter ecologist at Laurentian University in Sudbury, Ontario. Dr. Courtin describes winter ecology as ''a labor of love.'' ''Some of us may be masochists, but we all love it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>These researchers are finding that of the three basic strategies for surviving the rigors of winter - migrating, hibernating and developing resistance - the last is by far the most common.</p>
        <p>''Migration and hibernation are very costly strategies,'' observed Dr. Peter J. Marchand, ecologist at the Mountain Research Station near Boulder, Colo. ''It takes an enormous amount of energy to migrate over land, so only birds and aquatic animals can do it efficiently. As for hibernation, it is mainly used at midlatitudes; there aren't many areas in the far north where an animal can safely sleep through the winter without freezing or running out of stored energy.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Marchand, author of a newly published book on winter ecology, ''Life in the Cold'' (University Press of New England), pointed out that most animals and all plants must ''stick it out'' all winter and have evolved various mechanisms for keeping warm.</p>
        <p>Some animals that are normally solitary huddle together, with as many as 20 flying squirrels crammed into a section of a hollow tree or three or four species of snakes intertwined in a rock den. Voles and deer mice build communal nests and tunnels under the insulating blanket of snow; even in air temperatures as low as 10 degrees Fahrenheit Dr. Marchand reported, measurements over a two-week period in January showed that temperatures hovered around 32 degrees Fahrenheit where a deep snowpack, acting as an insulating blanket, met the ground. In these nests, temperatures often reach 50 degrees.</p>
        <p>Some warm-blooded animals, especially small birds, enter a nightly torpor, reducing their body temperature to limit heat loss to the cold night air.</p>
        <p>But many other winter-active animals have evolved elaborate mechanisms to generate or save heat. As Dr. Marchard noted, some small birds that do not fly south, such as goldfinches and redpolls, grow more feathers in winter and fluff them out in the cold for added insulation.</p>
        <p>But this is not enough to fend off the fierce winter cold. To maintain their body temperature and remain warm enough to fly, some birds must shiver almost continuously to generate extra body heat. Cynthia Carey and Richard L. Marsh showed that goldfinches acclimatized to winter can produce 5.5 times as much heat as usual by shivering.</p>
        <p>For animals with appendages exposed to the cold, such as the legs of ducks or the tails of beavers, an interlaced network of blood vessels acts as a heat exchanger to block excessive loss of heat to the environment. In the exposed extremities, surface veins constrict, shunting blood toward the center; there, the warmth of arterial blood is transferred to the cooler blood in adjacent veins. This keeps the extremities cool but preserves the animal's core temperature. A beaver may lose 25 percent of its body heat through its tail in summer, but it loses only 2 percent in winter. Antifreeze for Plants</p>
        <p>Plants, too, have evolved antifreeze techniques. Evergreens, for example, keep the cells in their leaves from freezing and bursting by transfering water in the cells to the spaces between cells. Ice crystals form outside the cells and press in cell membranes, but the fluid within cells is now more concentrated and thus more resistant to freezing.</p>
        <p>Dr. Marchand pointed out that, contrary to popular belief, the hardest winter days for evergreen plants are the ones people like best: sunny and calm. At these times the plants are at risk of death from dessication because their dark-colored leaves warm up, more of their stored water turns to vapor, and they lose moisture to the colder and drier surrounding air. Wind, however, cools the leaves and diminishes water loss, he said.</p>
        <p>''From a plant's perspective, winter is an extended drought, and maintaining a favorable water balance is critical to a plant's survival,'' Dr. Marchand said.</p>
        <p>He and his fellow winter ecologists have also questioned some long-held beliefs about why animals grow bigger in the north or turn white in winter. Winter white may be important not so much as a camouflage (especially since winter enemies are few) as a means of increasing insulation, Dr. Marchand said. He explained that without the pigment, melanin, in fur and feathers, there are more air spaces within the hairs and feathers and thus greater insulation.</p>
        <p>The arctic fox, for example, has no enemies, but its luxurious white coat insulates it far better than does the fur of other animals with an equally thick coat.</p>
        <p>And, Dr. Marchard suggested, larger body size among northerly members of a species, such as fishers and martens, may be the accidental result of decreased competition for food in the north, rather than a specific adaptation to reduce heat loss or to store extra energy for winter. For example, one study showed that the size of the shorttail weasel increases northward only after its ranger extends beyond that of its closest competitor, the longtail weasel. The Shrew's Tactics</p>
        <p>One of the most successful winter survivors is the smallest of mammals, the shrew, according to detailed studies by Dr. Joseph Merritt, director of the Powdermill Nature Reserve in Rector, Pa. If there was ever a hyperactive animal, the shrew is it. The largest North American shrew, the short-tailed shrew, weighing as much as two 25-cent coins, has a heart rate of 760 beats a minute (70 is normal for people) and respiration rate of 164 breaths a minute.</p>
        <p>Dr. Merritt, who has been studying this bite-sized creature by telemetry, reports that it lives alone all winter in an underground nest and races through an elaborate system of tunnels, feeding on insect larvae and pupae and occasionally dipping into its hoard of stored live prey. This shrew has a venomous bite that immobilizes prey, keeping it fresh for days as an emergency ration. The tiny mammal protects its cache by defecating and urinating on it, which discourages other potential diners.</p>
        <p>But the shrew's main winter survival tactic, Dr. Merritt's studies have shown, is a layer of so-called brown fat accumulated each winter over the shoulder blades. Brown fat acts like a furnace or heating blanket. When the hypothalamus, a tiny gland at the base of the brain, is cued by cold, it triggers the release of a hormone, norepinephrine, which in turn acts on lipase, an enzyme that catalyzes the breakdown of fat molecules in brown fat. This breakdown releases heat, which warms the animal. Then, as the animal eats, it replenishes its store of brown fat.</p>
        <p>''The short-tailed shrew is such an effective winter survivor that it actually gains weight during winter,'' Dr. Merritt said. By capturing shrews periodically through the Appalachian winter and measuring their metabolic capacity, Dr. Merritt has shown that their brown fat reaches its maximum heat-generating capabilities in mid-January, when the outside temperatures are coldest. Benefits of Snow</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Courtin, the hardest time for winter-active animals is now, before the ground is covered by a thick insulating blanket of snow. ''When it rains, the animals get wet and cold and many perish,'' he said. ''A few, like the meadow vole, dig into underground burrows and then shift their nests to the soil surface once it's covered by a snowpack.''</p>
        <p>The students of winter ecology agree that many more questions than answers remain as to how plants and animals make it through the ''wrathful nipping cold'' of winter, as Shakespeare put it. Dr. Courtin, for example, is now studying wintergreen, a tiny woodland plant with shiny evergreen leaves and bright red berries. He wonders: ''Do the tissues freeze? If not, why not? Do they photosynthesize beneath the snow? There's good evidence that they do accumulate starch in spring when still covered by several feet of crystalline snow.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Marchand wonders about carbon dioxide accumulation under the snowpack as a result of continuous respiration and decay of plant matter and the breathing of subnivean (under the snow) animals. He notes that there are often many vertical tunnels in the snowpack that for decades were thought to be ventilation shafts for subnivean animals. But one of his students showed in growth chamber studies that animals suffered no adverse effects from carbon dioxide levels far higher than those ever found under the snow.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
