<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Waste Not, We Must Want Not Incineration, but Planning</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="62418"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND OPINION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BARGES AND SCOWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">VEERAVAGU, PONNAMPALAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDE1231F931A3575BC0A961948260" item-length="1025" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Waste Not, We Must Want Not Incineration, but Planning</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PONNAMPALAM VEERAVAGU; Ponnampalam Veeravagu is an associate professor of life sciences at the New York Institute of Technology in Old Westbury.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VEERAVAGU, PONNAMPALAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE only waves that Islip's vagabond garbage barge, Mobro, now appears to be making are political - waves of recrimination between state and local officials.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE only waves that Islip's vagabond garbage barge, Mobro, now appears to be making are political - waves of recrimination between state and local officials.</p>
        <p>THE only waves that Islip's vagabond garbage barge, Mobro, now appears to be making are political - waves of recrimination between state and local officials.</p>
        <p>Certainly there is plenty of blame to go around at both levels for this particular fiasco. But on the larger issue of waste disposal there can be little question that the major failure has been the state's, for, in the long term, the only resolution of this issue will come from state and Federal initiatives.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, Mobro seems to have stimulated some new thinking at the state level. If that turns out to be the case, the barge will have served a useful purpose.</p>
        <p>Since 1983, when legislation banned the opening of new landfills on Long Island or the expansion of existing ones, the State Department of Environmental Conservation has promoted garbage-to-energy incinerators as the alternative to landfills. From the very beginning, this proposed solution has been opposed by community groups and environmentalists, who correctly see incineration not as a solution but as a potential cause of even more serious environmental problems.</p>
        <p>The critics have been quick to point out that incineration will release dioxin and related toxic chemicals into the atmosphere and will produce an ash that, if only one-fourth the weight of the original garbage, will contain toxic metals and other harmful substances in more concentrated form.</p>
        <p>What the state has come to realize is that landfilling this ash poses as many problems as landfilling Mobro's cargo. The 11 incinerators the state has suggested for Long Island would produce enough ash in two days to fill a barge the size of Mobro, and the state has made little progress in arranging for ways to dispose of it. A proposed site in Yaphank in the Town of Brookhaven has raised intense local opposition, and the option of shipping the garbage has been much diminished not only by Islip's folly but by the great expense other towns have incurred in shipping waste to private dumps.</p>
        <p>As environmental awareness continues to spread across the country, Long Island's ability to ship out its garbage is likely to diminish even further.</p>
        <p>With awareness of these problems sinking in, the state recently took several steps in the right direction. In its 1987 waste management report, issued last winter, the Department of Environmental Conservation advocates the recycling of 50 percent of garbage statewide by 1997. Locally it is requiring each Long Island town seeking approval for a garbage-to-energy plant to submit a plan for recycling part of its waste stream. Recycling will reduce the amount of garbage to be burned, the size and cost of incinerators and the amount of ash produced.</p>
        <p>While encouraging, these initiatives only represent first steps. Individual towns on their own cannot make a significant impact on the day-to-day waste stream. The recycling program of the Town of Islip, initiated in 1982, is the best on the Island and yet has resulted in a waste-stream reduction of only about 8 percent. If recycling is to reach the goal of 50 percent, the state must abandon the approach of ''hometown does it, state regulates it'' and become an active partner in working toward solutions. As long as garbage disposal involved little more than digging in the hole in the ground, towns did not require help from higher levels of government. But when a town has to observe strict environmental requirements and find reliable markets for its recycled products, garbage disposal becomes a qualitatively different responsibility, one beyond the financial, technological and administrative capabilities of towns.</p>
        <p>The time has arrived for New York to establish a statewide authority with the task of Reduce use and avoid disposable products. leading and coordinating the efforts of the towns and counties.</p>
        <p>Beyond putting its own house in order, the state should provide leadership at the regional and national levels in dealing with the solid-waste problem. Ultimately garbage reduction will have to be approached from the production end as well as from the consumer end, and here only a national effort will be effective.</p>
        <p>Our society can take a lesson from Western Europe, where recycling is a widely accepted practice but where the supply of recyclables continues to outrun the market for them; as a result, several countries have begun to think in terms of a more basic approach to the waste problem, at the production end.</p>
        <p>There is a parallel between the acid rain problem and the garbage problem. The causes of acid rain do not rest with the Northeastern states where the rain falls but with the Midwestern states that burn coal containing sulfur. Similarly, the causes of the garbage problem lie in the manufacturing centers that flood the country with disposable products made of nonbiodegradable materials and marketed with excessive packaging.</p>
        <p>With a standard of living not much higher than West Germany's, the United States produces more than seven times the waste per capita. This adds up to 150 million tons of garbage annually, not counting industrial waste, enough to fill Islip's vagabond barge 50,000 times over. Any long-range solution of the garbage crisis must incorporate plans to reduce use per person and to substitute re-usable products for disposable ones.</p>
        <p>How can this be done? Measures long advocated by environmentalists include limiting the use of nonbiodegradable plastics, banning nonreturnable containers, placing a tax on throwaway items and taxing household goods and cars with short lifetimes. Individual states can have only limited effectiveness in carrying out such policies. The need is for Federal regulation, for uniform policies that prevent manufacturers from evading regulation by moving from one part of the country to another or by moving abroad.</p>
        <p>Public officials from Long Island and the rest of the state hopefully can provide leadership in moving an economy based on buy-use-discard to one based on buy-use-repair-re-use-recycle. Mobro has provided ample material for cartoonists and late-night talk shows; how nice if, in addition, it proved a catalyst for much-needed initiatives.</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND OPINION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
