<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HOMEOWNERS DISCOVER TOUGH RULE ON 'POINTS'</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="YOUR TAXES: A GUIDE TO PREPARING 1986 RETURNS - Sixth of 11 Articles" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="15953"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCOME TAX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KLOTT, GARY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3DA1131F930A15751C0A961948260" item-length="1487" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HOMEOWNERS DISCOVER TOUGH RULE ON 'POINTS'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GARY KLOTT, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KLOTT, GARY</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Around this time of year, renters tend to evince jealous sentiments toward homeowners who have bought into the American dream, and the treasure chest of tax deductions that go along with it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Around this time of year, renters tend to evince jealous sentiments toward homeowners who have bought into the American dream, and the treasure chest of tax deductions that go along with it.</p>
        <p>Around this time of year, renters tend to evince jealous sentiments toward homeowners who have bought into the American dream, and the treasure chest of tax deductions that go along with it.</p>
        <p>Homeowners, however, will discover in filling out their 1986 returns that the tax benefits, while still sizable, are not quite as abundant as they used to be.</p>
        <p>For the many Americans who refinanced their homes last year, the Internal Revenue Service has issued tough new guidelines on deducting ''points,'' which will mean hundreds or even thousands of dollars less in write-offs on 1986 returns.</p>
        <p>And homeowners who installed storm windows, insulation or other energy-saving device will find they are no longer rewarded with a tax break for their conservation efforts.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, taxpayers will still find considerable tax savings around the house, from the mortgage interest and property taxes they pay on their Manhattan co-op or Southampton summer home to write-offs for their home offices and the cost of hiring household help to look after their children while they are off at work. Even renters can partake of similar tax benefits for home offices and household help.</p>
        <p>Although the Tax Reform Act of 1986 imposes some new limitations on homeowner tax benefits - most notably mortgage interest and home offices - none of the changes applies to 1986 returns.</p>
        <p>But an edict by the revenue service, issued while Congress was busy drafting the new tax law, will have a direct bearing on 1986 returns.</p>
        <p>The I.R.S. ruling spelled out how points paid in connection with a refinancing could be written off. Points are a one-time, up-front fee that lenders routinely charge for making home loans. They are no small item, normally running 2 to 4 percent of the principal amount of the loan.</p>
        <p>Under the new guidelines, deductions for points paid in a refinancing have to be spread out over the life of the loan. The I.R.S. said the only time points could be fully deducted in the year paid is when the mortgage loan proceeds are used directly to purchase a principal residence or make improvements.</p>
        <p>The I.R.S. contended that the ruling, which came in the form of a three-paragraph announcement, was merely reinforcing its longstanding position. But the ruling surprised many tax professionals and stunned hundreds of thousands of homeowners who refinanced their homes last year to take advantage of the decline in interest rates. The ruling was in sharp contrast to what had been common practice in deducting points. Previous Approach Noted</p>
        <p>''I'd say 99 percent of people in America deducted points all at once,'' said Richard A. Sprayregen, a partner at Kenneth Leventhal &amp; Company, an accounting firm specializing in real estate.</p>
        <p>''The position taken by the I.R.S. has provided new fertile ground for controversy,'' said Richard J. Stricof, a tax partner at the accounting firm of Seidman &amp; Seidman. He said the I.R.S. position is likely to be challenged in the courts. But for now, he cautioned, taxpayers who choose to fully deduct points paid in a refinancing risk penalties in the face of the I.R.S. opinion.</p>
        <p>The ruling will make a big difference in the amount of deductions homeowners can claim on their 1986 return.</p>
        <p>For example, assume a homeowner paid $2,400 in points. If the mortgage was used to buy a principal residence, the full $2,400 could be deducted for the year when it was paid. The same would be true if the mortgage was used to finance a home improvement.</p>
        <p>But if the $2,400 was paid to refinance an existing mortgage with, say, a new 20-year home loan at lower interest, the points would have to be written off in equal installments over the 20-year life of the loan. In this case, only $120 could be deducted each year. A Special Line for Points</p>
        <p>Points also have a more prominent position on tax return forms now than they did in past years. On 1986 returns, points are no longer lumped in together with mortgage interest; instead, points now have to be reported on a separate line.</p>
        <p>Renters, as well as homeowners, will also be disappointed to find that the tax credits for installing energy-saving items in the home have passed into extinction. The residential energy credit, worth up to $300, expired at the end of 1985 and Congress decided not to revive it. The renewable energy credit - worth up to $4,000 for the installation of solar water heaters, windmills and other renewable energy devices - had the same fate.</p>
        <p>Working parents, however, are still eligible for a tax break for hiring household help to take care of their younger children or a disabled dependent while they are off at work or looking for a job. Eligible expenses cover care of a child under age 15 or a physically or mentally incapacitated spouse or other dependent of any age.</p>
        <p>This ''child and dependent care credit'' can help subsidize the cost of hiring a maid, a butler, a housekeeper, a cook or a baby sitter. Only chauffeurs and gardeners are considered ineligible as child caretakers - as far as the credit is concerned. Payments to a Relative</p>
        <p>Even payments made to a relative, such as a mother-in-law, are eligible, unless the relative is someone who can be claimed as a dependent on the taxpayer's return.</p>
        <p>Outside the home, expenses eligible for the credit include day care, nursery school and summer camp. Also eligible are boarding school costs except for tuition.</p>
        <p>Depending on the family's income, the credit is worth 20 to 30 percent of the first $2,400 in expenses for care of one dependent, or $4,800 for the care of two or more dependents.</p>
        <p>Taxpayers who have set up an office in their home often try to find a way to justify writing off the room as a business expense. For those who meet the stringent guidelines, the rewards can be substantial. Renters get to deduct a proportionate share of their rent and utilities. Homeowners can claim deductions for depreciation, utilities and other expenses attributable to the room.</p>
        <p>Self-employed individuals who work out of their home have little problem qualifying. But employees have a tough time meeting the guidelines unless they have a sideline business. The common excuse that a home office is needed to do paperwork brought home at night from the office is usually insufficient. Dual I.R.S. Requirement</p>
        <p>Under the guidelines, the designated office space has to be used both regularly and exclusively as a home office. This exclusivity requirement does not rule out offices that occupy only a portion of a room, such as the corner of a studio apartment. But the space designated as a home office cannot be used for any other purpose. Consequently, an artist who uses his living room for painting during the day and for entertainment at night will not qualify for a deduction.</p>
        <p>In addition, the guidelines require that the home office be either a ''principal place of business'' or a place to ''meet or deal'' with customers or clients. This is where employees usually run aground. They normally fail the first test, since their principal place of business is almost always considered their office at work. And they usually fail the alternate test since the courts have repeatedly held that meeting or dealing with clients means physically meeting them at the home office. ''You can't just sit on the telephone with them,'' said Mr. Stricof.</p>
        <p>Even if one of those requirements is met, the employee still has to be able to prove that the home office was solely for the ''convenience of the employer'' and not merely a place that the employee finds more comfortable and convenient to work in after hours. An Office Outside Home</p>
        <p>Self-employed people, including those with sideline businesses, usually have no trouble meeting the principal-place-of-business test if they operate the business out of their home. But if they have an office or shop outside the home where most of their business is conducted, they run into the same problem meeting this requirement as employees do.</p>
        <p>The courts have made exceptions. Last year, a Wisconsin couple who owned a self-service laundry won their battle with the I.R.S. after an appeals court agreed that the home office was justified since there was no adequate space to work on administrative matters at the laundry. The court noted that the wife spent ''most of her time in the home office and performed what may be her most important functions as a manager there.''</p>
        <p>In the past, a similar court victory was won by a professor at the City University of New York. The court noted that the professor spent most of his time working in his home office because his office at the university was inadequate for research and writing. And a few Metropolitan Opera musicians were allowed to deduct their home offices on grounds that they spent more time practicing at home than performing at Lincoln Center, where no practice space was made available.  Next: Personal retirement plans.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
