<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLDWIDE PACT SOUGHT ON OZONE</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="14863"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN ECONOMIC COMMUNITY (EEC) (COMMON MARKET)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1D81330F93AA25751C0A961948260" item-length="786" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLDWIDE PACT SOUGHT ON OZONE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Members of Congress called today for an international agreement to protect the earth's ozone shield and voiced support for newly proposed legislation to gradually eliminate Americans' use of chemicals that destroy atmospheric ozone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Members of Congress called today for an international agreement to protect the earth's ozone shield and voiced support for newly proposed legislation to gradually eliminate Americans' use of chemicals that destroy atmospheric ozone.</p>
        <p>Members of Congress called today for an international agreement to protect the earth's ozone shield and voiced support for newly proposed legislation to gradually eliminate Americans' use of chemicals that destroy atmospheric ozone.</p>
        <p>Ozone in the upper atmosphere shields the surface of the earth from cancer-causing ultraviolet radiation from the sun. There has been mounting scientific consensus that the atmospheric ozone is being destroyed by chlorofluorocarbons, chemicals used in refrigerants, packaging, foams and aerosol propellants, and several other man-made chemicals.</p>
        <p>At a news conference on Capitol Hill today, Senators and Congressmen from both political parties said they would push a Congressional resolution to support the President in forthcoming negotiations in Vienna aimed at protecting the ozone shield.</p>
        <p>Representatives of the industrial nations will meet in the Austrian capital Feb. 23-27 in an attempt to reach an agreement to freeze current production levels of chlorofluorcarbons and to end their use over time. The United States made such a proposal at a meeting in Geneva in December but, while some consensus was reached on the nature of the problem, no agreement was made on further action.</p>
        <p>Today members of Congress charged that the European Community, Japan, and the Soviet Union were dragging their feet on an international agreement to protect the ozone shield in order to serve their own narrow economic self-interest.</p>
        <p>Senator Timothy E. Wirth, Democrat of Colorado, said at the news conference that a Congressional resolution would send ''a signal to the European Comminity and Japan that the U.S. Congress views the threat of ozone depletion as a very serious threat to the global environment. The risks of inaction are enormous.''</p>
        <p>Separate but similar bills to to regulate chemicals that deplete the ozone layer were introduced today by Senator John H. Chafee, Republican of Rhode Island, and Max Baucus, Democrat of Montana. Both bills would gradually eliminate within six to eight years 95 percent of the chlorofluorocarbons that cause the most destruction, as well as two kinds of chemicals that react with ozone, both halogens containing bromine.</p>
        <p>The bills would freeze production of the chemicals at current production levels starting in one year and would also bar all imports of products containing or made with chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>Senator Chafee said that ozone depletion and the related problem of the warming of the earth's surface because of the buildup of carbon monoxide and other gases in the atmosphere were ''monumental problems with a doomsday effect.''</p>
        <p>Warnings about the dangers of chlorofluorcarbons were first raised more than a decade ago by Pofessor F. Sherwood Rowland and Dr. Mario J. Molina, scientists at the University of California in Irvine. In the the late 1970's use of these chemicals was barred by the United States, Canada, Sweden and Norway for most aerosol propellants such as those used in deodorants. But other countries did not follow suit and, in the meantime, the use of the chemicals in other applications grew rapidly.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, appearance of a mysterious ''hole'' in the ozone layer over Antarctica each spring, a hole the size of the United States, has prompted new fears about the impact of ozone depletion.</p>
        <p>Increased ultraviolet radiation reaching the earth's surface through the thinning ozone shield can cause lead to skin cancer and other health problems in humans and also damage crops and forests.</p>
        <p>Representative Henry A. Waxman, Democrat of California, said today that a recent Environmental Protection Agency draft report predicted that ozone depletion would lead to 40 million additional skin cancer cases and 800,000 additional cancer deaths in the next 88 years.</p>
        <p>Lee M. Thomas, administrator of the environmental agency, which is taking the lead on the ozone issue, said today he welcomed the Congressional support for an international agreement. ''It strengthens the United States position that immediate worldwide actions are necessary to reduce emissions into the atmosphere of chemicals suspected of depleting the ozone layer. While our current understanding of all the factors involved is less than complete, the potential consequences are too great to delay action.''</p>
        <p>Richard E. Ayres, a lawyer with the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental group, said that the bills to bar chlorofluorocarbons ''are a strong response to the environmental ''threat of ozone depletion.''</p>
        <p>Another environmental group, Friends of the Earth, today announced a consumer campaign to alert the public about products such as styrofoam packaging that are made with products that harm the ozone layer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
