<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Concern for Rain Forest Has Begun to Blossom</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="82415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRODY, JANE E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7DD113EF930A25753C1A961948260" item-length="1506" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Concern for Rain Forest Has Begun to Blossom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE E. BRODY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRODY, JANE E</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE movement to save the richest ecosystem in the world - the tropical rain forest - is making slow but certain progress as forest dwellers and local activists join with international conservation groups to halt projects that would destroy these wet jungles along with the diverse human cultures they sustain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE movement to save the richest ecosystem in the world - the tropical rain forest - is making slow but certain progress as forest dwellers and local activists join with international conservation groups to halt projects that would destroy these wet jungles along with the diverse human cultures they sustain.</p>
        <p>THE movement to save the richest ecosystem in the world - the tropical rain forest - is making slow but certain progress as forest dwellers and local activists join with international conservation groups to halt projects that would destroy these wet jungles along with the diverse human cultures they sustain.</p>
        <p>Several tropical countries have taken the first steps to actively preserve parcels of rain forest, which are now disappearing at an unprecedented rate of 50 to 100 acres a minute. A few, such as Costa Rica, have put large portions of their forests under protection. Even Brazil, home to a third of the world's rain forests and where an area of forest the size of Connecticut is still cut down each year, is establishing nature reserves and has a growing conservation movement. And over the last decade or so, local conservation groups dedicated to protecting wild species have begun to gain a voice in many different tropical countries, from Malaysia to the Philippines to Ecuador.</p>
        <p>The World Bank, the biggest single lender for development projects in the third world, is notorious among conservationists for underwriting schemes that damage rain forests. But now, pushed by private groups and the American Government, the bank says it has begun to rethink its policies and is increasing the number of ecologists on its staff.</p>
        <p>These first glimmers of optimism in what until now has been a bleak picture were evident in interviews with participants in a conference on tropical rain forests to be held later this week at Hunter College in New York. Ivan Ussach, vice president of the New York Rain Forest Alliance, a citizens' educational group that is the coordinating sponsor of the conference, said that while New York City is far from rain forests, it is a center of financial interests that have been fostering their destruction.</p>
        <p>The spread of agriculture, uncontrolled logging and other developments have already reduced rain forests in Latin America, Africa and Asia to less than half their original area. In interviews last week, the conference participants predicted that unless something dramatic is done to reshape rain forest management throughout the world, this essentially nonrenewable resource will be reduced by another 20 to 40 percent from the current level by the turn of the century.</p>
        <p>Because mature rain forest takes centuries to grow back - assuming the soils are not permanently damaged - experts say it is more akin to a nonrenewable than a renewable resource.</p>
        <p>A growing worldwide network of environmental activists and concerned scientists hopes to crystallize public concern and devise ways for stemming the destruction.</p>
        <p>''We can all be very upbeat about the fact that things are beginning to resonate.'' said Dr. Thomas E. Lovejoy, executive vice president of the World Wildlife Fund. ''The growing concern about rain forests in this country is mirrored by an increasing environmental consciousness in countries like Brazil, where there are now 300 conservation organizations as against fewer than 10 a decade ago.'' But at the same time, he added, ''We can be downbeat about the fact that the scale of the problem is far greater than the scope of present solutions.''</p>
        <p>''What's happening now is very exciting,'' said Randall Hayes, director of the Rainforest Action Network, an environmental group based in San Francisco. ''We are evolving a functional global network of activists both in the northern industrialized countries and in third-world countries who want to keep the forested areas.''</p>
        <p>Groups of local citizens are taking aggressive action in Southeast Asia as well as in South America. For example, the Penan, a hunting and gathering tribe in Borneo, have been blockading a logging road since failing to get protection for their rain forest through the Malaysian Government. And several tribes in Southeast Asia have formed the Indigenous Peoples Network, working with the Asia-Pacific Peoples Environmental Network to begin fighting against projects that harm their interests in the forest. Review of Policies Sought</p>
        <p>Beyond setting aside reserves, experts say, governments of tropical countries need to reassess broader development policies if pressures on rain forests are to ease. Curbing rapid population growth is one need. Beyond this, critics say, governments mistakenly see rain forest lands as a ''safety valve,'' where farm workers or laborers displaced by mechanization or poor economic management can be resettled. But in many cases, the lands cannot sustain farming and the end results are devastated forests and soils and more poverty.</p>
        <p>Often, experts say, small-scale projects can be devised that improve the lives of local people without undermining the ecosystem. For example, Bruce Rich, an attorney for the Environmental Defense Fund in Washington, said the native rubber tappers in Brazil, whose survival is threatened by rain forest destruction, have united in opposition and suggested alternative development plans that would exploit the forest without destroying it.</p>
        <p>Policies in the rich countries, too, are under scrutiny. Mr. Hayes believes that ''there's more to be done in the United States to save the rain forest than in countries like Brazil because a lot of American tax dollars and American companies are financing destructive rain forest projects.'' After a consumer boycott of Burger King beef spearheaded by the network along with other environmental groups last summer the huge fast-food chain announced it would stop importing beef from Costa Rica, where cattle ranches are expanding on land cut from rain forest.</p>
        <p>In another worldwide effort, several United Nations agencies, national forestry departments and private groups, coordinated by the World Resources Institute in Washington, have developed a Tropical Forestry Action Plan. The aim is to raise awareness among governments of policy changes needed to protect forests and to direct more funds toward conservation and reforestation, Search for Incentives In addition to urging aid agencies to pay more attention to the environmental consequences of their loans, conservation groups are searching for new incentives for forest protection. In an innovative approach that activists hope can be duplicated, Bolivia agreed last summer to create a 3.7-million acre rain forest reserve in exchange for forgiveness of $650,000 of its external debt. Conservation International, a private group in Washington, purchased the debt at a discounted price of $100,000 from banks that have little hope of otherwise collecting on the loans to Bolivia.</p>
        <p>The rain forest preservation effort marks a change in the conservation movement over all from concern about popular individual species such as pandas and leopards to a focus on whole environments, the loss of which would be far more threatening to human welfare.</p>
        <p>Scientists studying the global role of rain forests point to such vital contributions to humanity as these:</p>
        <p>* Rain forests are the source of countless thousands of useful plants and animals, many of which have not yet been exploited or even discovered. While rain forests cover some 6 to 7 percent of the earth's land mass, they house 40 to 50 percent of all living species, making rain forests biologically the richest environments on earth. One-quarter of the prescription drugs used in the United States, including potent cancer and cardiac medications, were originally derived from or inspired by rain forest plants.</p>
        <p>* Cultures indigenous to the rain forests are believed to harbor a wealth of information about hundreds of medicinal plants and animal products that are as yet unknown to medical science. As Jon Tinker, president of The Panos Institute, a London-based research group, put it: ''You don't have to lose the people themselves to lose this knowledge. All you have to do is destroy the social structure that fosters transmission of this oral information.''</p>
        <p>* Many important crop plants, such as corn, originated in tropical rain forest areas, where wild parent plants still serve as a source of genes that confer pest resistance and other economically important characteristics. There are also hundreds of as yet unexploited edible plants that could one day be cultivated.</p>
        <p>* Rain forests play a critical role in modulating global climates. By releasing all the carbon locked up in the massive trees of the tropics, rain forest destruction would increase atmospheric carbon dioxide, which acts like a greenhouse to trap solar energy in the atmosphere. Together with the rise in carbon dioxide from industrial activity, this would accentuate the expected global warming that could speed desertification in the tropics and subtropics and cause flooding of coastal cities and loss of farmland in the temperate zones.</p>
        <p>To those who say rain forest destruction is necessary to support rapidly expanding populations in third world countries, environmental experts point out that many rain forest soils are not suitable for sustained agricultural development.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
