<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kew's Faceted Conservatory Is Home to 10 Microclimates</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="96540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DESIGN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">KEW GARDENS (LONDON)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONDON (ENG)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILSON, GORDON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMMONS, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HALE, SHEILA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7DD123EF935A15752C1A961948260" item-length="1041" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kew's Faceted Conservatory Is Home to 10 Microclimates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHEILA HALE, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HALE, SHEILA</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Nov. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The gale that ripped across southern England on Oct. 16 hit Kew Gardens in west London just before 4 A.M. By sunrise the magnificent 300-acre garden was scarcely recognizable. About 1,000 trees had been destroyed or badly damaged.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The gale that ripped across southern England on Oct. 16 hit Kew Gardens in west London just before 4 A.M. By sunrise the magnificent 300-acre garden was scarcely recognizable. About 1,000 trees had been destroyed or badly damaged.</p>
        <p>The gale that ripped across southern England on Oct. 16 hit Kew Gardens in west London just before 4 A.M. By sunrise the magnificent 300-acre garden was scarcely recognizable. About 1,000 trees had been destroyed or badly damaged.</p>
        <p>Most of these trees were more than 100 years old, but Kew's horticultural curator, John Simmons, took some comfort in the knowledge that the precious contents of the garden's greenhouses survived the storm unharmed.</p>
        <p>The newest and largest of the greenhouses, the Princess of Wales Conservatory, was finished last summer. It contains about 15,000 rare and exotic specimens, most of which are unable to tolerate even a few minutes of exposure to the English climate. They were previously housed in temporary structures that might have been shattered during the storm. But the sturdy, low-profile design of the new greenhouse was like a fortress against the exceptionally high winds.</p>
        <p>There is no greenhouse in the world quite like this high-tech structure, which has been attracting crowds since it was officially opened by Princess Diana in July. It was designed by the architect Gordon Wilson in consultation with Mr. Simmons, who had been planning it since 1972.</p>
        <p>The exterior looks like a Cubist interpretation of a giant faceted diamond partly sunk in the ground. Inside, the exotic specimens flourish in the immense space of 48,337 square feet, or 1.1 acres. Visitors can walk through 10 computer-controlled climates, from the intense humidity of a South American mangrove swamp to the arid heat of the Namib desert in southwest Africa to the cool damp of a North American plateau.</p>
        <p>In the center of the greenhouse are giant Amazon waterlilies, which are visible from many levels of the building. They grow from seed each year with leaves more than six feet across that are strong enough to support a baby. From southwest Africa is the primitive Welwitschia mirabilis, with leaves that resemble discarded snakeskin; in a steady soil temperature of 75 degrees Fahrenheit, it can live for 2,000 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simmons's favorite insectivore is the Heliamphora, which is from Venezuela. A Dali-like landscape of giant cactuses grows in the south-facing end of the greenhouse. At the north end is a hill covered with endearing tree ferns, their furry trunks spotted like deer.</p>
        <p>Scattered throughout the collections are some 2,000 species that are threatened with extinction in their native countries by land clearance.</p>
        <p>One of the aims of the plantings, Mr. Simmons said, is to protect the plants from genetic interference so that pure specimens can survive and be scientifically investigated.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilson, who specializes in laboratory buildings, said that his greenhouse was ''a scientific institution as well as a public garden.'' Having visited and studied conservatories all over the world, he said that his greenhouse was ''unique, because it meets the special needs of Kew's unequaled collection of herbacious plants.''</p>
        <p>''The conservatory is a very uncommon building type,'' he added, ''There are not many of them anywhere and they are separated by long time spans. So architects of conservatories often find themselves re-inventing the wheel. It isn't easy to learn from the mistakes of others.''</p>
        <p>To address the problem, Mr. Wilson first built a prototype of a section of the greenhouse, which has been left standing and is used as a subsidiary greenhouse. ''We learned from our mistakes on the prototype and the construction of the main conservatory went quite smoothly,'' he said.</p>
        <p>His greenhouse has been hailed by some as an architectural masterpiece. Arthur Hellier wrote in The Financial Times that it was ''a fabulous assemblage of planes.''</p>
        <p>Sir Geoffrey Jellicoe, a prominent landscape architect, called it ''absolutely splendid.''</p>
        <p>''It fits so well into the landscape,'' he said. ''The geometry is so good.''</p>
        <p>But Richard Rogers, a British architect who confesses that he has only seen photographs, described it as heavy and unrefined. ''I wonder whatever happened to the great tradition of featherweight structures that are glazed,'' he said. He compared the greenhouse, unfavorably, to Kew's two elegant Victorian greenhouses, Decimus Burton's lofty, curvilinear Palm House of 1848, which is now being restored, and the rectangular Temperate House of 1862.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilson, however, said that Burton, who was in his own day a pioneer of greenhouse engineering, would have approved of his design. ''It echoes the straight and angled shapes of traditional green houses,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''The plants love it,'' Mr. Simmons said. ''It is really very, very satisfying to see the house doing what it was supposed to do.''</p>
        <p>The public loves it too, which is something of a triumph in a country so deeply conservative in its architectural tastes. One of the unusual features of the greenhouse is its irregular landscaping and curving paths that encourage visitors to wander freely, to explore or sit or draw. ''We have been saturated with people since we opened,'' Mr. Simmons said. ''Fortunately, people are good for plants, which thrive on the carbon dioxide we breathe out.''</p>
        <p>The Princess of Wales Greenhouse cost $:4.78 million, or nearly $8,600,000, and is expected to last a century.</p>
        <p>The exterior glass is angled to take maximum advantage of the little amount of sun the English climate provides. Computers are programmed to assure that no heat is wasted and to save labor costs; the building is operated with a staff of only five or six. If the main gas or electricity supply had been cut off on the night of the storm, the central computer would have automatically switched on emergency power.</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Wilson, Mr. Simmons has seen all of the major conservatories of Europe and America. He remains fascinated by their enduring appeal. ''Glass houses were popular in the 18th century, and they are still just as popular,'' he said. ''It may be because you don't just look at the plants, you enter their environment, or, in our case 10 different environments.''</p>
        <p>''It's a bit like time travel,'' he said. ''You step out of a grim English day into the insufferable heat of a jungle.''</p>
        <p>A century from now, when Kew is restored to its former splendor, even more astonishing greenhouses may stand.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
