<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Hot Ticket Is Round Trip, to or From Moscow</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="91177"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="WASHINGTON TALK: SOVIET-AMERICAN RELATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GAMAREKIAN, BARBARA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON TALK PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DE1F3EF93AA35752C1A961948260" item-length="1376" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Hot Ticket Is Round Trip, to or From Moscow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA GAMAREKIAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GAMAREKIAN, BARBARA</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Dr. Zara Khetagurova and Tamara Abova, members of a delegation of Soviet women traveling from Moscow to the United States, suffered an indignity familiar to many an American traveler: They were bumped from their Aeroflot flight, on which they had been booked for six weeks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Dr. Zara Khetagurova and Tamara Abova, members of a delegation of Soviet women traveling from Moscow to the United States, suffered an indignity familiar to many an American traveler: They were bumped from their Aeroflot flight, on which they had been booked for six weeks.</p>
        <p>Dr. Zara Khetagurova and Tamara Abova, members of a delegation of Soviet women traveling from Moscow to the United States, suffered an indignity familiar to many an American traveler: They were bumped from their Aeroflot flight, on which they had been booked for six weeks.</p>
        <p>''So many Soviet people are visiting America that our airport could not cope with this number, so that is why we arrived a day early with the help of Belgian airlines,'' said Miss Abova, a senior researcher at the Soviet Union's Academy of Sciences. Her Washington itinerary, which included meeting with such people as Supreme Court Justice Sandra Day O'Connor and Senator Nancy Landon Kassebaum, Republican of Kansas - had been arranged by the American Association of University Women.</p>
        <p>Suddenly it seems that everyone -politicians, rock stars, students, scientists, environmentalists, educators and astronauts - is making the Moscow-Washington commute. Even thoroughbred horses are getting into the act. Gjatsk, a 3-year-old colt, the first Soviet horse to compete in this country since 1966, ran in the 36th Washington, D.C., International on Oct. 31.</p>
        <p>And it has become equally trendy for Americans to travel to the Soviet Union. Six Congressional wives departed Washington in early October, leading a delegation, Peace Links, to Tashkent, Tbilisi and Leningrad. Peace Links, a national disarmament group founded by Betty Bumpers, wife of Senator Dale Bumpers, Democrat of Arkansas, played host last year to about 40 Soviet women visiting in this country. Politicians, Athletes, Musicians</p>
        <p>Governor Cuomo of New York, Billy Joel and his rock group, an organization called Athletes for Peace and students from Phillips Academy in Andover, Mass., who spent five weeks there, are among recent visitors to the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>At Harvard University, three Soviet officials participated recently in a retrospective look at the Cuban missile crisis with such onetime adversaries from the Kennedy years as Robert S. McNamara and McGeorge Bundy. Members of the Soviet Ministry of Education met with members of the World Wildlife Fund in Washington. And Soviet environmentalists were at the World Resource Institute here to discuss the climactic changes known as the ''greenhouse effect,'' the global warming trend caused by the accumulation of carbon dioxide and manmade gases in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Stephen H. Rhinesmith, who directs the United States Information Agency office that was established to oversee the cultural and educational exchange agreement signed two years ago in Geneva by President Reagan and Mikhail S. Gorbachev, considers the increase in trans-Atlantic visits a communications breakthrough.</p>
        <p>''We are now working with over 200 Soviet organizations,'' he said. ''But the real news is that there are significantly different kinds of activities going on that we have never seen before.'' In this category he mentioned seminars conducted by satellite, the exchange of high school students and citizens' exchange programs like the one last summer in Chautauqua, N.Y., involving 190 Soviet citizens living with American families. The Trend Is Up</p>
        <p>In 1985, the year before the Geneva accords, 50,000 Americans traveled to the Soviet Union and 3,000 Soviet visitors came to this country. Dr. Rhinesmith anticipates that this year more than 100,000 Americans will go to the Soviet Union, with some 10,000 Russians heading in this direction.</p>
        <p>Keeping track of all these comings and goings is the Institute for Soviet American Relations, established in 1983 by Harriett Crosby, a former teacher with a master's degree in psychiatry, and Nancy A. Graham, a former Peace Corps official.</p>
        <p>''In the early 1980's, you were considered a weirdo if you were interested in the Soviet Union. Now it is considered the 'in' thing to do,'' said Miss Crosby, who has made 16 trips there.</p>
        <p>Isar, as the organization is called, grew out of a survey Mrs. Graham made of all the organizations and groups involved in Soviet-American relations. Started in a Kitchen</p>
        <p>''We discovered there was no coordination of all these groups, and so we became sort of a networking body collecting and distributing information about what was going on, not only in exchanges but all kinds of activities that relate to American-Soviet relations,'' Miss Crosby explained. The two women, now operating out of an office near Dupont Circle, originally worked out of the kitchen of a house in Washington that Miss Crosby had rented from Arthur and Donna Hartman, longtime friends who were posted in Moscow when Mr. Hartman was United States Ambassador there.</p>
        <p>The first issue of Isar's journal, ''Surviving Together,'' which reports every four months on Soviet-American joint projects and exchanges as well as on trade, legislation, public education programs and news coverage, consisted of just 12 pages. The most recent issue extended to 102 pages, with 30 pages of reporting on exchanges and joint projects alone. The journal has a circulation of 3,500.  ''I know these people,'' said Aleksandr P. Potemkin, cultural attache at the Soviet Embassy, which receives 20 copies of the journal. ''I think they do very useful work.''</p>
        <p>''One of our jobs is to keep track of exchanges,'' said Dr. Rhinesmith, ''but every time 'Surviving Together' comes out we find we only know about 30 percent of what is going on. It is a tremendous resource.'' Cultivating Contacts</p>
        <p>Isar also publishes a directory of all the American organizations involved with the Soviet Union, and Dr. Rhinesmith said he has given his Soviet colleagues copies to enable them to get a better idea of the multitude of American organizations with which they are working.</p>
        <p>Because of their Washington contacts and their first-hand acquaintance with a number of Russians, Miss Crosby and Mrs. Graham at times serve as a back channel for the Soviet visitor, setting up meetings with National Security Council staff people and on Capitol Hill, sometimes with a small dinner party at the Grahams' Georgetown home and on other occasions a quiet luncheon where people can talk off the record.</p>
        <p>''We are able to sort of work behind the scenes when it is mutually beneficial,'' said Miss Crosby. ''We will arrange meetings that we think would be constructive with people in the Administration and with Congress.''</p>
        <p>The volume of travel between the two countries declined when the United States severed official cultural and educational ties after the 1979 Soviet intervention in Afghanistan. Privately sponsored exchanges continued to take place, but they were arranged without official United States Government blessing. Sputnik Anniversary Marked</p>
        <p>John Marks, a former Foreign Service officer who was co-author with Victor Marchetti of the best seller ''The CIA and the Cult of Intelligence,'' now heads Search for Common Ground, an organization that looks for innovative ways in which Washington and Moscow can cooperate.</p>
        <p>''I used to specialize in throwing monkey wrenches into the system; now I am into the politics of building,'' said Mr. Marks, who recently traveled to Moscow from Washington with 75 Americans to mark the 30th anniversary of Sputnik.</p>
        <p>He attributes the growing number of Soviet-American exchanges to ''the extraordinary frustration among people who want to do something about what is the most important issue facing the country.''</p>
        <p>''When the government wasn't moving,'' he said, ''citizens felt it was something they could do. It is one way in which citizens can get involved -to connect with people on a human level. I have no illusions that this sort of thing changes government policy, but it certainly beats sitting back and complaining.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Rhinesmith is confident that future political disagreements will not stop the flow of people and ideas.</p>
        <p>''Both governments are working very hard to see that this people-to- people movement continues to grow in spite of the inevitable political strains and ups and downs of the relationship,'' he said. ''We are not in the business of trying to demonstrate that we are all the same. We are extremely different societies, but if we undertand those differences we will be better able to carry on a dialogue about where we have common areas of agreement.''  WASHINGTON TALK: SOVIET-AMERICAN RELATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
