<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Washington Talk: Single-Issue Lobbying; Caustic Debate on Acid Rain Letter</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="61676"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOBBYING AND LOBBYISTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ACID RAIN, CITIZENS FOR SENSIBLE CONTROL OF</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK PUBLIC INTEREST RESEARCH GROUP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service"></object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON TALK PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDC1530F932A05754C0A961948260" item-length="804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Washington Talk: Single-Issue Lobbying; Caustic Debate on Acid Rain Letter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The letterhead says the appeal is from ''Citizens for Sensible Control of Acid Rain.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The letterhead says the appeal is from ''Citizens for Sensible Control of Acid Rain.''</p>
        <p>The letterhead says the appeal is from ''Citizens for Sensible Control of Acid Rain.''</p>
        <p>Sent to thousands of households, it warns that Congress is considering acid rain legislation ''that would cost $110 billion'' and ''would mean up to 30 percent higher electric bills.'' Recipients are urged to write their legislators in Congress to vote it down.</p>
        <p>As far as another lobbying group here is concerned, that is misleading, for Citizens for Sensible Control of Acid Rain is not a citizens group, at least not in the grassroots sense. The effort is financed by power and coal companies, which contribute to the pollution that causes acid rain, and other businesses that oppose the legislation. And that has outraged the U.S. Public Interest Research Group, which takes an opposite view on the acid rain bill. Standard Practice</p>
        <p>The organizing of lobbying groups is standard practice in the capital. A spokesman for the Federal Election Commission said there were 1,044 registered committees organized around a single issue or ideology. He said it was often impossible to tell a group's position from its name. Similarly, Harland Williams, president of the national chapter of the Public Relations Society of America, said that Citizens for Sensible Control of Acid Rain sounded like ''legitimate advocacy'' and that such practices were not unusual.</p>
        <p>Like many lobbying campaigns, the acid rain group is run by a public relations executive in Washington, in this case Thomas L. Buckmaster. Mr. Buckmaster maintains that his organization generates letters from citizens so it is a citizens group.</p>
        <p>But some others in the business of lobbying on specific issues say they find such lobbying questionable. The head of one large public relations concern here, who asked not to be identified, said he had organized ''a number of'' what he called ''phony coalitions'' but no longer did so because he found it ''personally disturbing.''</p>
        <p>To the U.S. Public Interest Research Group, which describes itself as a nonpartisan, nonprofit consumer and environmental advocacy group, the activities of the acid rain group are disturbing indeed.</p>
        <p>Since the industry group was formed in 1983, it has spent $4 million sending 800,000 letters to citizens, according to the Public Interest Research Group. Alexandra Allen, a Public Interest Research Group lawyer, said none of the letters mentioned that sponsors of Citizens for Sensible Control of Acid Rain had a vested interest in the acid rain issue.</p>
        <p>The group's stationery has been changed this year to include a line at the bottom saying that financing was provided by electric, coal and manufacturing companies.</p>
        <p>''As Congress considers acid rain legislation this year,'' Ms. Allen said, ''we hope that every member is fully aware that Citizens for Sensible Control of Acid Rain is in fact an industry lobby masquerading as a citizens organization.''</p>
        <p>Representative James J. Florio, Democrat of New Jersey, agrees there is confusion. He said a constituent who sent him a letter generated by the acid rain group had not realized it was an industry effort. The group ''purports to be disinterested but clearly it is not,'' Mr. Florio said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Buckmaster, the executive director of Citizens for Sensible Control of Acid Rain, takes exception to the notion that the effort is deceptive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Buckmaster, who runs the operation out of the Washington office of Fleishman Hillard Inc., a St. Louis public relations concern, said: ''We have been and will continue to be candid about who we are, where our funding comes from and what the purpose of the organization is.''</p>
        <p>He said 135,000 people - ''citizen volunteers'' he called them - had written letters as a result of the campaign.</p>
        <p>''Form letter or not,'' he added, ''each letter was signed by an individual citizen who has taken time to read our letter, decided it accurately reflects their point of view and took the extraordinary step of signing their name and sending to their elected representative.'' 'Nitpicking'?  The acid rain legislation would require coal-burning power plants to install special equipment or use expensive low-sulphur coal so as to reduce their releases of the pollutants that are suspected of causing acid rain.</p>
        <p>Ms. Allen said the contention in the letters that the legislation would cost $110 billion and raise electric rates by up to 30 percent was a worst-case estimate over 20 years based on a trade group's figures. She said Congress's Office of Technology Assessment had estimated residential electric rates would rise 2 to 3 percent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Buckmaster called this ''nitpicking.'' He also wondered how much money the Public Interest Research Group had spent on lobbying for the bill.</p>
        <p>The answer, provided by Ms. Allen, is about $40,000 since 1983, mostly for staff salaries and a newsletter.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
