<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Link Brazil's Forests to Debt Relief</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="58695"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LATIN AMERICA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRAZIL</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MULLEN, KEVIN T</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HALPIN, PETER T</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROCKEFELLER, DAVID</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DF1330F932A15754C0A961948260" item-length="580" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Link Brazil's Forests to Debt Relief</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Let's Not Write Off Latin America'' by David Rockefeller (Op-Ed, July 5) bristles with wisdom. It also demands creative solutions to ease the debt burden of Latin American countries, Brazil in particular.</p>
        <p>Brazil is in deep economic trouble, with inflation climbing upward of 1,000 percent a year. Brazil's decision to suspend interest payments on its international debt a few months ago caused a furor in banking circles worldwide. Yet we can no more afford to write off Brazil financially than we can afford to ignore the impending ecological folly taking place in Brazil's Amazon Basin: the rapid destruction of the last great tropical rain forest on the planet.</p>
        <p>The coincidence of these two actions - interest-payment suspension and forest destruction - inspires a strategy to alleviate both problems simultaneously. Mr. Rockefeller lays out the justification for continued lending to Brazil and other Latin countries. But why not negotiate for concessions of value to the world in exchange for temporary financial relief?</p>
        <p>The Brazilian Amazon Basin, the largest ecosystem on earth, is fast disappearing because of excessive cutting at an annual loss rate in thousands of square miles. The 2.7 million square miles of tropical forest will be gone within two generations.</p>
        <p>The forest acts as a major buffer against carbon dioxide buildup, helping to inhibit the ominous ''greenhouse effect,'' a planetary time bomb. The forest also acts as a global weather stabilizer. Proably most important, the Amazon Basin, with its vast population of some half million to two million animal and plant species, equivalent to 20 percent of all the species on earth, could hold the key to many of the diseases afflicting mankind, should it survive long enough to be studied adequately. After all, most of our medicines were originally derived from plants and animals.</p>
        <p>A nation struggling to meet debt obligations cannot afford the luxuries of preservation activities. National and international financial institutions based in the United States should negotiate a five-year suspension of Brazilian interest payments as part of a larger plan to provide Brazil with the credit to become financially healthy. Should the loss of interest be overwhelming for some of the United States-based debt holders, the Federal Reserve can monetize the interest debt or Congress can devise legislative financial relief. Neither action will cause an inflationary ripple. Call it all smart foreign aid!</p>
        <p>A second part of the plan requires that Brazil work with the United States Government and appropriate national and international ecological organizations to develop a system of wildernesses, parks, wildlife refuges, sustainable-yield forests, farms and grazing areas in the Amazon Basin similar to what has been accomplished in the United States. This exchange affords the World Bank an opportunity to make amends for the adverse ecological impacts of its past Brazilian projects.</p>
        <p>Some critics, maybe Brazilians themselves, will call this plan a form of imperialism or paternalism from the North. We think it amounts to assisting a neighbor in trouble. Helping Brazil to safeguard its national assets while healing its economy can only benefit us all. KEVIN T. MULLEN  PETER T. HALPIN  Vienna, Va., July 7, 1987  The writers are, respectively, a former committee director with the Council on Environmental Quality and vice president of the World Resources Company.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
