<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY: SATURDAY, JUNE 27, 1987</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="52323"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1DB1631F934A15755C0A961948260" item-length="1107" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY: SATURDAY, JUNE 27, 1987</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International 2-5, 28  Mikhail Gorbachev's economic plans won backing from the Communist Party Central Committee, and three of his allies were elected to full membership on the Politburo. It was a major show of Mr. Gorbachev's political strength. Page 1  News analysis: Soviet politics and policy have taken a startling turn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International 2-5, 28  Mikhail Gorbachev's economic plans won backing from the Communist Party Central Committee, and three of his allies were elected to full membership on the Politburo. It was a major show of Mr. Gorbachev's political strength. Page 1  News analysis: Soviet politics and policy have taken a startling turn.</p>
        <p>International 2-5, 28  Mikhail Gorbachev's economic plans won backing from the Communist Party Central Committee, and three of his allies were elected to full membership on the Politburo. It was a major show of Mr. Gorbachev's political strength. Page 1  News analysis: Soviet politics and policy have taken a startling turn. Mr. Gorbachev has laid to rest any doubt about whether he sides with the self-styled radicals who have pushed to quicken the pace of economic change. He is with them. 1  Man in the News: A. N. Yakovlev's promotion to the Politburo is the latest by Mr. Gorbachev of a man in his own mold. Mr. Yakovlev is an exponent of increased openness who is adroit in dealing with the West.  5  In Seoul, riot policemen struggled but ultimately managed to retain control of the city's streets against tens of thousands of anti-Government protesters. The clashes were the most ferocious in a week. 1  The South Korean protesters's goal is freedom, supporters said. In the Seoul neighborhood of Yongdungpo, the ferment of recent weeks has drawn the interest and emotions of many working-class residents. 3  A U.S. official expressed optimism about the situation in South Korea, saying President Chun Doo Hwan was amenable to changes. The State Department official, Gaston J. Sigur Jr., conferred with Mr. Chun this week. 3  William J. Casey repeatedly misled the House Intelligence Committee about the secret arms sales to Iran and the supply operation for the Nicaraguan rebels in one of his final appearances before the panel, a transcript shows. 1  OPEC is close to an agreement on a production quota for the second half of the year that is lower than originally projected. The apparent agreement is a victory for Iran, which wants to maximize prices, and a defeat for Saudi Arabia. 35  The trade status of Rumania was suspended. The Senate voted to suspend most-favored-nation trade status to the country for six months to protest Rumanian policies on human rights and emigration. 5  In a skirmish on arms control, the Democratic leadership in the House of Representatives retreated, as it agreed to drop two key provisions from the supplemental budget for 1987. 2  U.S. chides Greece on terrorists  4  Zakinthos journal  4  U.S.-Spain talks on bases recess  4  Beirut kidnappers identified  4  50 killed in Philippine air crash  28  Japanese quits whale group  28  National 6, 12-14, 32-33  Justice Lewis F. Powell Jr. retired from the Supreme Court for reasons of age and health. His surprise announcement set the stage for what is certain to be a bitter, politically charged Senate confirmation battle. 1  A successor will be named quickly for Justice Powell in the hope of finding a candidate who tips the ideological balance on key issues without generating a protracted confirmation fight with the Senate, officials said. 1  Justice Powell sat at the center of an often polarized Supreme Court for a decade and a half. The Court's balancer and compromiser, he is creating, through retirement, a particular void, in tone as well as substance.  32  In a victory for property owners, the Supreme Court, in a 5-to-4 decision, sharply limited the power of governments to force landowners to surrender ownership rights without them compensation. 33  The President had polyps removed from his colon at a medical checkup. White House officials said the two small polyps appeared to be noncancerous, but the results of pathology tests are not expected to be available until Monday. 1  The JWT Group will be purchased by a much smaller British marketing company. The purchase of theworld's fourth largest advertising company by the WPP Group is the industry's first unsolicited acquisition.  35  Jack Kemp's focus on minorities has been among the hallmarks of his Presidential campaign. He has called for his party to reach out to voters who are black, Hispanic, poor or members of other disadvantaged groups. 14  A Republican strategy to recapture the political initiative appears to be emerging. In a speech, the chairman of the Republican National Committee used the strategy, which focuses attention on Democratic tax and spending proposals. 14  A twin-engine cargo plane crashed three miles short of Boston's Logan Airport in a residential neighborhood, killing the pilot and setting off a nine-alarm fire, which gutted three buildings and seven cars. 6  Louisiana political challengers tone down ads  6  Indian and Eskimo births rising  12  House votes $350 million to combat acid rain  14  Regional 29-31  General outlines for an ethics code for New York State political leaders and a system of regular outside audits of all parts of state government have been agreed on by Governor Cuomo and legislative leaders, the Governor said. 29  42 subway newsstands may close unless contracts can be settled, the Metropolitan Transportation Authority said. An agreement with Kapoor Brothers Inc. is being terminated because the company owed back rent and fees. 31  Honors for District 4 schools in East Harlem have come from the White House, the MacArthur Foundation, and to the students, whose test scores were up yet again. ''This has been the best year the district has ever had,'' one official said. 29  A 'special independent investigator' was called for by New York State Assembly Republicans to look into allegations of improper business dealings by the executive director of the Thruway Authority, Alexander A. Levine. 30  Sale of Queens Farms Dairy's assets in New York City to John Labatt Ltd., the Canadian beer and food conglomerate, was announced by Labatt officials. 29  A law to protect freshwater wetlands in New Jersey has been agreed on by Governor Kean and legislative leaders. The agreement paves the way for the Governor to lift his moratorium on wetlands development. 29  In the Bess Myerson inquiry, the United States Attorney in Manhattan, Rudolph W. Giuliani, objected to the disclosure of secret testimony and other materials concerning the former New York City Cultural Affairs Commissioner. 31  Hotel suite named for Gleason  12  Death sentence in Connecticut  30  Kaufman to become senior judge  31  Convicted ex-judge assailed  31  Criminal to get psychiatric test  31</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
