<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MAIL-ORDER CATALOGUES THAT AID A CAUSE</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="44" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="104861"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAIL ORDER COMPANIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CATALOGUES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HINDS, MICHAEL DECOURCY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mail Order Companies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2DF153FF935A15751C1A961948260" item-length="1436" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MAIL-ORDER CATALOGUES THAT AID A CAUSE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michael deCourcy Hinds</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HINDS, MICHAEL DECOURCY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: You can buy cashews at the corner market, or you can buy them from an alternative mail-order company and help Honduran farmers, replenish wastelands and provide children with schoolbooks. All for $5 a pound, postage paid and satisfaction guaranteed from Pueblo to People, a nonprofit mail-order house that supports health, literacy and community projects in poor countries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: You can buy cashews at the corner market, or you can buy them from an alternative mail-order company and help Honduran farmers, replenish wastelands and provide children with schoolbooks. All for $5 a pound, postage paid and satisfaction guaranteed from Pueblo to People, a nonprofit mail-order house that supports health, literacy and community projects in poor countries.</p>
        <p>You can buy cashews at the corner market, or you can buy them from an alternative mail-order company and help Honduran farmers, replenish wastelands and provide children with schoolbooks. All for $5 a pound, postage paid and satisfaction guaranteed from Pueblo to People, a nonprofit mail-order house that supports health, literacy and community projects in poor countries.</p>
        <p>''We're not looking for a profit for ourselves,'' said Pueblo's mail-order coordinator, Jimmy Pryor, who like every other member of the organization in Houston, takes home a salary of $900 a month. He said that more than 40 percent of the income from their cashew sales is returned to the farmers. The organization provided technical assistance in developing the cashew-growing project and, since 1982, has marketed the nuts through its catalogue, which carries 24 pages of food, handcrafts and clothing.</p>
        <p>There are over 100 ''alternative'' mail-order companies, as they call themselves. The alternative they offer the consumer may seem intriguing now, amid all the year-end appeals from causes and charities. No Tax Deductions</p>
        <p>These mail-order houses do not portray themselves as charities, and purchases from them do not qualify for tax deductions. But people who use their catalogues to buy goods and services can support a wide range of social causes.</p>
        <p>By keeping labor and overhead low, the organizations say they are able to invest a significant portion of their income in their projects. The causes - as varied as education, the environemtn and employment - tend to have broad appeal. Some products, including Nicaraguan coffee and T-shirts with anti-apartheid slogans, have a narrower political orientation.</p>
        <p>These companies occupy a small corner in the $50-billion-a-year mail-order business, generating revenues of $50 million to $100 million. But they have created a niche since the 60's.</p>
        <p>Today, marketing products linked to causes is big business. Credit card companies have made the concept popular with what they call affinity cards, which spin off $8 to $12 a year each in contributions to schools, clubs and nonprofit groups. Using Computer Power</p>
        <p>But most of the alternative operations are nonprofit, often collectively owned and operated. Manya re politically liberal; a few have ties to religious groups. Some trace their roots to the original alternative source-book, Stewart Brand's ''Whole Earth Catalog.'' (Some conservative organizations sell products through the mail, but most cater to members.) The business has come a long way in two decades. Low-cost computers have made it easier to compile mailing list, process orders and keep track of inventory. The field even has its own marketing consultant, Niche Marketing Services, which was founded last year in Vermont.</p>
        <p>Its president, Alan Newman, said: ''I think a lot of people would rather support the planet by buying products from a group that will put the profits into a third world or environmental causes, rather than buying from Sears, which will create more shopping centers with the profits.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the companies themselves have become more appealing. ''If you go back three years,'' Mr. Newman said, ''their promotional materials and packaging were so poor nobody would have bought unless they totally supported the cause. Now, with good presentations, we're finding we can use more and more of the mainstream mailing lists.''</p>
        <p>But the alternative houses are dependent mainly on lists provided by other nonprofit organizations. Those interested in receiving catalogues should write or call the organizations. Last year, about 100 of these companies sent out about a million catalogues, compared with 12 billion sent out by the 8,500 conventional mail-order companies.</p>
        <p>The catalogues are an alternative product themselves, often generously laced with philosophy. And if you browse through enough of them, you may well find a product you want that serves a cuase you support.</p>
        <p>Jubilee Crafts sells a $9 woven purse that helps Guatemalan refugees, and wild rice that American Indians harvest from their canoes, at $5 for eight ounces. Equal Exchange sells Nicaraguan coffee processed in Canada ($28 for five pounds) to support farmers and to protest Reagan policies toward the Sandinistas.</p>
        <p>For environmentalists, there are organic lawn supplies from Gardeners Supply, recycled paper from the Earth Care Paper Company, energy-saving refrigerators and recorded whale music from Renew America. Wildlife enthusiasts can buy cosmetics developed without tests on animals from My Brother's Keeper.</p>
        <p>Co-op America, an umbrella organization for alternative companies, publishes five 80-page mail-order catalogues each year, promoting about 250 products. Its 37,000 members, who pay $15 a year, also receive a quarterly on social issues called Building Economic Alternatives.</p>
        <p>About 4,500 members have purchased life and health insurance through the organization, and others have invested about $2 million in banks and mutual fund associated with the group.</p>
        <p>''The purpose of Co-op America is to change the way people do business in a way that is more consistent with their values and ideals,'' said Paul Freundlich, who founded the nonprofit organization in Washington five years ago. Catalogue sales have been increasing by about 50 percent year, with sales expected to total $1 million in 1988.</p>
        <p>Gardeners Supply, in Burlington, Vt., had $8 million in sales this year, making it one of the most successful alternative mail-order companies. Will Raap, active in organizing community gardens in blighted areas, started the company in 1982. ''I am a businessman,'' he said. ''I think the world wants companies with a broader perspective than just selling stuff.''</p>
        <p>At first the company sold only specialized gardening equipment for physically handicapped people. But to survive, it quickly broadened its product line to include a wide assortment of labor-saving tools and organic supplies. Its $42.50 Easy Kneeler, for example, imported from England, is a small light bench, which, upside down, become a padded platform to kneel on for weeding.</p>
        <p>While complaints abound in the profit-making mail-order industry, nonprofit companies have a good reputation. ''Complaints against nonprofit organizations are quite rare,'' said Candace Von Salzen, speaking for the Council of Better Business Bureaus. Consumers with compalints should write the council at 1515 Wilson Boulevard, Arlington, Va. 22209.</p>
        <p>Selling products by mail is, to some nonprofit organizations, a survival mechanism. The solar Lobby, which helped persuade the Carter Administration and Congress to allow tax credits for the use of solar energy equipment, has evolved into the Fund for Renewable Energy and the Environment.</p>
        <p>Among dozens of solar and energy-saving products featured in its 27-page Renew America catalogue is a Sun Frost refrigerator, a highly efficient machine that uses 80 percent less electricity than conventional models. The $1,560 price tag is high for a 12-cubic-foot refrigerator, but it is supposed to save $3,000 in electric bills over its 20-year life.</p>
        <p>''American refrigerators consume as much electricity each year as is produced by 17 large nuclear power plants,'' the catalogue states. ''If everyone bought a Sun Frost, we could eliminate 14 of those plants and still keep our food fresh.'' Some Companies and Their Products</p>
        <p>Here is a sampling of alternative mail-order businesses. Keep in mind that requesting one or two catalogues may prompt other mailings, because companies share lists. Catalogues are free unless otherwise stated.</p>
        <p>Co-op America, umbrella group for many causes 126 Intervale Road, Burlington, Vt. 05401 $1 for catalogue Clothing, crafts, toys, books, financial services Earth Care Paper Company, recycling group 325 Beech Lane, Harbor Springs, Mich. 49740 Paper and stationery products Gardeners Supply, an environmental group 126 Intervale Road, Burlington, Vt. 05401 Gardening tools, organic products Jubilee Crafts, human rights activists 300 West Apsley Street, Philadelphia, Pa. 19144 $1 for catalogue Imported clothing, blankets, artwork, crafts My Brother's Keeper, animal rights activists PO Box 1769, Richmond, Ind. 47375 Cosmetics Pueblo to People, aids developing countries 1616 Montrose Boulevard., Houston, Tex. 77006 Furniture, clothing, crafts, nuts WSA Community Pharmacy, active in health education 341 State Street Madison, Wis. 53703 Organic and herbal products Renew American Project, supporters of renewable energy 1001 Connecticut Avenue NW, Suite 638, Washington, D.C. 20036 Energy-saving products</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
