<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Theory on Oceans of Venus</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="105545"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="SCIENCE WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VENUS (PLANET)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KASTINGS, JAMES (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Venus (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871229T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7D91538F93AA15751C1A961948260" item-length="300" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Theory on Oceans of Venus</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: UNTIL scientists learned of the extremely high temperature of Venus, the conventional view of the planet was of an ocean-covered body, perhaps inhabited by exotic sea creatures. Then it was confirmed by spacecraft that the surface temperature was 800 degrees Fahrenheit, hot enough to melt zinc, and that the atmosphere, which is 100 times heavier than that of the</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: UNTIL scientists learned of the extremely high temperature of Venus, the conventional view of the planet was of an ocean-covered body, perhaps inhabited by exotic sea creatures. Then it was confirmed by spacecraft that the surface temperature was 800 degrees Fahrenheit, hot enough to melt zinc, and that the atmosphere, which is 100 times heavier than that of the</p>
        <p>UNTIL scientists learned of the extremely high temperature of Venus, the conventional view of the planet was of an ocean-covered body, perhaps inhabited by exotic sea creatures. Then it was confirmed by spacecraft that the surface temperature was 800 degrees Fahrenheit, hot enough to melt zinc, and that the atmosphere, which is 100 times heavier than that of the Earth, was largely composed of carbon dioxide and clouds of almost pure sulfuric acid.</p>
        <p>It was argued that the high temperature was caused by the carbon dioxide acting like the glass of a greenhouse, but in a ''runaway greenhouse effect,'' making it so hot that all water would evaporate.</p>
        <p>Now Dr. James Kasting and two other space scientists argue that, based on analogies with Earth and Mars, Venus must have had up to 1,000 times as much water as can be accounted for in this manner, since the planet is entirely dry.</p>
        <p>Instead they propose a ''wet greenhouse theory,'' speculating that the planet went through a period of several hundred million years in which it had an ocean. Because of the planet's nearness to the Sun and the heat-trapping effect of carbon dioxide in the air, they theorize, the ocean temperature rose to 200 or 300 degrees Fahrenheit but was kept from boiling by relatively high atmospheric pressure.</p>
        <p>Under this model, the water evaporated and became dissociated by sunlight into its constituents. The lightweight hydrogen diffused into space, the oxygen remained, and the ocean, possibly with the aid of life, converted the carbon dioxide into carbonates.</p>
        <p>Another of the three authors of the study, Dr. James B. Pollack, proposed as early as 1970 that Venus had an ocean. The third author was Dr. Tom Ackerman. All are associated with the space agency's Ames Research Center in Mountain View, Calif.</p>
        <p>SCIENCE WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
