<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WHAT WILL IT TAKE TO UNSETTLE A CARIBOU?</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="33960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="A CLASSIC ENVIRONMENTAL DEBATE: DRILLING FOR OIL IN AN ARTIC REFUGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXPLORATION OF RESOURCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC PROPERTY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WILDERNESS AREAS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALASKA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARCTIC NATIONAL WILDLIFE REFUGE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERIOR, DEPARTMENT OF THE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCCLURE, JAMES A (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">UDALL, MORRIS K (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska/Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exploration of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wilderness Areas</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1D91F3DF935A15757C0A961948260" item-length="1663" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WHAT WILL IT TAKE TO UNSETTLE A CARIBOU?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: INTERIOR SECRETARY DONALD P. HODEL last week set the stage for a classic legislative battle, by recommending that the entire 1.5 million-acre coastal plain within the 19.5 million-acre Arctic National Wildlife Refuge in Alaska be opened to oil development.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: INTERIOR SECRETARY DONALD P. HODEL last week set the stage for a classic legislative battle, by recommending that the entire 1.5 million-acre coastal plain within the 19.5 million-acre Arctic National Wildlife Refuge in Alaska be opened to oil development.</p>
        <p>INTERIOR SECRETARY DONALD P. HODEL last week set the stage for a classic legislative battle, by recommending that the entire 1.5 million-acre coastal plain within the 19.5 million-acre Arctic National Wildlife Refuge in Alaska be opened to oil development.</p>
        <p>According to the Interior Department, there is about a one-in-five chance that a major oil field lies beneath the permafrost. But if one does exist, the department says, it contains between 600 million and 9.2 billion barrels of oil. Such an oil discovery will be needed soon, Mr. Hodel contends, to relieve the nation of its dangerous reliance on foreign sources.</p>
        <p>Conservationists and their allies say the Hodel decision threatens a delicate and irreplaceable natural area with permanent, perhaps fatal damage for the sake of a short-term oil supply. The proposed drilling area, the only extension in Alaska of the Interior Plains of North America, lies in the calving areas of a great migratory herd of caribou.</p>
        <p>Congress must now decide whether to adopt Mr. Hodel's proposal, to modify it or to bar all development activity within the refuge. Philip Shabecoff, a reporter in the Washington Bureau of The New York Times, asked two legislators who will play important roles in the Congressional debate where the national interest lies in this issue.</p>
        <p>Senator James A. McClure of Idaho, ranking Republican on the Senate Energy and Natural Resources Committee, is a supporter of the Administration plan to open the refuge, 100 miles east of the giant Prudhoe Bay oil field, to exploration. Representative Morris K. Udall, Democrat of Arizona, is chairman of the House Interior Committee and author of legislation that would turn the entire refuge into a wilderness area protected from development.</p>
        <p>Excerpts from the interviews follow.  McCLURE: EXPLORATION NEED NOT CAUSE HARM</p>
        <p>Question. Most people agree that the national interest requires both the development of domestic energy supplies and the conservation of rare and pristine natural environments. But the two goals often seem to collide. How would you strike a balance in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge?</p>
        <p>Answer. Remember that a wildlife refuge is created to preserve the wildlife. It is not exclusively to maintain the status quo on natural conditions.</p>
        <p>We need to keep in mind the reason for which the wildlife refuge was created so that we can keep foremost in our minds that the wildlife species, including the natural fauna and biota, be protected to the maximum extent possible. We need to draw the parallel that oil and gas exploration has been permitted in other wildlife refuges across the country.</p>
        <p>The Audubon Society acquired lands for a refuge and had permitted exploration within that refuge (the Rainey Wildlife Refuge in Abbeville, La.) to create money which would allow them to do other preservation work. They also struck a balance.</p>
        <p>Q. The biologists in the United States Fish and Wildlife Service, and Canadian biologists, say the environment in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge is unlike that of other refuges, that survival in it is difficult and that the migratory Porcupine caribou herd particularly might suffer. Is oil production compatible with preserving that wildlife? A. First I'll give you a short answer: Yes. Secondly, there was a key word in your comment - you said ''might,'' ''might cause damage.'' The same sort of comments were made with respect to Prudhoe Bay development, and the caribou herd at Prudhoe Bay has increased.</p>
        <p>Q. What about the argument that going after oil in such a sensitive frontier area is a 'Drain America First' policy that will use up the nation's remaining onshore resources and lead to dependency later on?</p>
        <p>A. Dependence isn't just a possibility for our future, it is an immediate reality. The 1973 oil embargo caused a great deal of difficulty. The 1979 marginal shortage has created a large part of the economic chaos that we're still recovering from.</p>
        <p>We don't have to speculate. While the world is in a better condition today than it was in 1979, we're rapidly approaching the position where we again will have free-world vulnerability to the economic effects of marginal shortage of an essential commodity.</p>
        <p>Q. Critics also say that the Administration is ignoring other possibilities, such as developing alternative fuels, and that we are going into the wildlife refuge when we could save the amount of oil it is going to produce simply by driving slowly and making our appliances more efficient.</p>
        <p>A. A balanced energy policy is absolutely essential, and that does mean conservation, it does mean alternative fuels. But it also means that we must recognize the competitive nature of the world, and that competition involves the economics of production. That means you cannot, in the United States, pay a price that is disproportionate to that which is paid in other countries or we'll lose our economic competitiveness. All the alternative fuels have to meet a test not only of technology but of economics.</p>
        <p>Some critics say: 'Don't drill that oil, burn our coal.' We have an acid rain problem. We have an even greater unknown with respect to the carbon dioxide questions, damage to the ozone layer. We are still testing. But we shouldn't automatically assume that since we're the OPEC of coal we can automatically shift to the combustion of coal.</p>
        <p>Q. It's also been said that one of the reasons the Administration is moving so fast to open up the entire coastal plain to oil development is that it wants to move as many of the resources on public land to the private sector before 1988.</p>
        <p>A. I don't see a great rush. I believe it was in 1979 or 1980 that Congress mandated that this study be done, and the Congress mandated that it be done in five years. The Administration is behind the schedule that Congress established. Q. What is your prognosis on the debate? A. It is a sensitive issue. My guess is it will be a close issue, decided by a very few votes.  UDALL: RISKS TO WILDLIFE ARE HIGH</p>
        <p>Question. How would you strike a balance between energy needs and conservation in a place like the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge?</p>
        <p>Answer. I think you've got to come down here on the side of protection. I know this is often said about areas in contention. But this is a very exceptional place. It ought to be the very last place we drill, when we're really down and out.</p>
        <p>In 1980, when we passed the Alaska Lands Bill, the industry wanted Petroleum Reserve 4, the naval reserve, which is much bigger and covers several hundred miles of the Arctic coastline. We made a bargain, that the refuge is the most important, and we'd even turn loose Pet 4. They found nothing, and now they're back and want the wildlife refuge. Q. What is so special about it? A. It depends on your values. When you've got the largest caribou herd - there's nothing like it left in the world, including the Soviet Union and Siberia. The buffalo is essentially extinct, and the caribou perform some of the same functions in the northland that the buffalo did here. And you've got the musk ox, and an immense variety of plants and animals. You run real risks in making the intrusions that drilling involves.</p>
        <p>Q. Does the refuge serve any purpose, except for a handful of rich tourists every year?</p>
        <p>A. Oh, it's a very special place and serves as scientific, philosophic protection for a great number of rare mammals and birds and life of all kinds.</p>
        <p>It's very interesting to scientists. There are few places like this left in the world. This is as fragile a place as you can find.</p>
        <p>Q. Interior Secretary Hodel said the prospects for a major oil strike are better in the refuge than any place else in the country onshore and that the United States will need domestic reserves badly by the end of the century if it is not to become dependent on OPEC. Isn't that aspect even more important to the country than the biologic aspects of the refuge?</p>
        <p>A. Well, yes and no. As long as we can get the oil from other places at reasonable prices, it makes no sense to drill our supplies and pump them out and have our wells dry and then be looking to the oil-producing nations.</p>
        <p>Q. The Administration maintains that the record of the oil industry in the Arctic shows that it does not do serious damage to the wildlife.</p>
        <p>A. I don't think they're just making up those arguments. It's a judgment call. I think experience isn't all that conclusive yet.</p>
        <p>We've had 15 years or so with Prudhoe and we came out pretty good. The people who talked about ecological disaster have been proven wrong. But 15 years isn't very long in terms of something as fragile and precious as this Northern Slope.</p>
        <p>Q. Does not the legislation you have introduced, to turn the refuge into a wilderness that cannot be developed, shut us off from getting the oil in case there is a national need for it?</p>
        <p>A. Not with me it doesn't. If the day comes when we're facing shortages, we're going to have to do some things we wouldn't like to have to do.</p>
        <p>They call this a lock-up. But what happens is we're saying this is a preferred resource.We'll go there last and not fast. It's a lock-up, but Congress has the key.</p>
        <p>Q. Proponents of drilling say that by keeping the refuge out of bounds now, the damage will be far greater in an emergency because then we'll have to get that oil in a hurry.</p>
        <p>A. That's an old argument: Quick and dirty will be the way to go. I don't believe it. We've learned so much about how to produce oil that I think if that great day comes when we have to do it, we'll do it in a reasonable fashion, and we'll have the benefit of all the experience of the last couple of decades in places like Prudhoe. Q. What do you expect to happen in Congress? A. We're just in the opening rounds, and people are sparring and trying to figure where to go. It's possible that some kind of compromise arrangement can be made, although I don't see too much willingness right now to make a compromise. But I've seen it happen before.</p>
        <p>A CLASSIC ENVIRONMENTAL DEBATE: DRILLING FOR OIL IN AN ARTIC REFUGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
