<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gym Classes Teaching How the Body Works</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="99094"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PHYSICAL EDUCATION AND TRAINING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMITT, ERIC</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Physical Education and Training</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7DF173DF936A35751C1A961948260" item-length="1214" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gym Classes Teaching How the Body Works</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMITT, ERIC</byline>
      <dateline>MINEOLA, L.I., Dec. 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In the gymnasium at the Jackson Avenue Elementary School, 8-year-olds ran through a human circulatory system on the parquet floor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In the gymnasium at the Jackson Avenue Elementary School, 8-year-olds ran through a human circulatory system on the parquet floor.</p>
        <p>In the gymnasium at the Jackson Avenue Elementary School, 8-year-olds ran through a human circulatory system on the parquet floor.</p>
        <p>Pretending they were blood cells, they grabbed oxygen molecules (bean bags) from a bucket, raced through the heart chambers (red and blue Hula-Hoops) and completed the circuit by exchanging the oxygen for carbon dioxide (crumpled waste paper). Their warm-up finished, the panting pupils checked their pulse rates.</p>
        <p>Watching them, Kathleen Kern, the school's physical education teacher, said, ''You can't teach kids about aerobic fitness until they understand the circulatory system.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Kern's class here reflects a trend in physical education across the country in which children are playing fewer competitive games in class while being taught more about their bodies and basic athletic skills intended to promote lifelong fitness.</p>
        <p>The changes, coming when educators have expressed concern over the flabby physical condition of America's youth, stress participation and self-improvement - using nontraditional activities from juggling to square dancing - over the urge to win.</p>
        <p>''We don't want to put them in a competitive framework at an early age where their little egos can't handle it,'' said Barbara Southwick, a physical education teacher in Centereach, L.I., and a former president of the New York Association for Health, Physical Education, Recreation and Dance. ''We're trying to build children's self-esteem, not a top-of-the-rope club.''</p>
        <p>And with time for gym squeezed in many schools because of budget cuts and pressure to pack in more academic subjects, educators say that if they cannot get their pupils into shape in two 30-minute classes a week, the new emphasis at least teaches them how to keep fit on their own.</p>
        <p>''I'm not teaching kids how to play soccer or basketball,'' Ms. Southwick said. ''I'm teaching them the basics of good form in running, jumping and throwing, and letting the students apply that to any activity they enjoy.''</p>
        <p>Under the new programs, educators say that students develop better coordination, teamwork and appreciation for fitness.</p>
        <p>John Foley, director of physical education in the Three Village School District in Setauket, L.I., said, ''I see a great deal more enthusiasm and fewer disciplinary problems.''</p>
        <p>Children still play traditional playground games like kickball and dodgeball, but teachers are using a host of alternatives to improve endurance, strength, flexibility and eye-hand coordination, including these activities:</p>
        <p>* At Hagan Elementary School in Poughkeepsie, N.Y., first- and second-graders learn volleyball skills by playing a beginner's game with balloons.</p>
        <p>* Kindergartners at Greenbrook Elementary School in South Brunswick, N.J., practice teamwork and throwing skills in games using foam balls and Frisbees.</p>
        <p>* Students at William S. Hart High School in Newhall, Calif., are given aerobic activity homework, including such sports as racquetball, skiing, surfing or skateboarding, to make physical activity a part of their lives away from school.</p>
        <p>''The bottom line is that children have to learn, but we want to make physical fitness fun,'' said Steve Carbone, president of the physical education teachers association in Suffolk County. New Emphasis on Old Ideas</p>
        <p>The new emphasis has grown out of research and classroom experiments by teachers across the country, from Adelphi University here on Long Island to the University of Arizona in the West. Its advocates say their ideas are not new. But where these instructors once practiced their different methods in relative obscurity, they are now leaders of a movement propelled in part by the adult fitness craze and parents' demands that their children shape up, too.</p>
        <p>Last year, for example, New York State issued the first new statewide syllabus for elementary school physical education since the 1930's. The new guidelines emphasize rhythm and dance, outdoor living skills and physical conditioning.</p>
        <p>Beginning in 1986, California has required students in grades 5, 7 and 10 to take written tests on physical fitness. ''We felt it was important for students to understand fitness so they would maintain it for a lifetime,'' said Dr. Betty Hennessy, a consultant for physical education with the California Department of Education. ''We're getting away from the children just playing follow the leader and doing what the teacher says.''</p>
        <p>Michael C. Willie, director of New York's pupil health and fitness programs of the State Department of Health, said, ''There's a spirit of trying to provide a variety of noncompetitive activities that children might engage in all their lives.''</p>
        <p>Under the new programs, which vary widely from school to school and are still in the early stages in many districts, competitiveness is tempered. Teams are called groups, scorekeeping is discouraged and instruction takes priority. How Much Competition?  At what age should children be exposed to competitive sports has been a subject of continuing debate as long as Little League and Pop Warner football have been around.</p>
        <p>Ash Hayes, executive director of the President's Council on Physical Fitness and Sports in Washington, said, ''I'd hope we'd never see any significant downplaying of competition. It'd be a great disservice to our kids. Competition goes on through life.'' Teachers, however, say that by teaching fundamental movements and athletic skills to young children, not just games, they are preparing them for more advanced team play when older.</p>
        <p>''I teach how the body moves, where it moves, what it can do and why,'' said Jean Geyer, a physical education teacher at Brook Avenue School in Bay Shore, L.I. Pupils Learn Muscle Groups</p>
        <p>As children learn more about movement, they also learn which muscles make them go.</p>
        <p>In Mrs. Kern's class, for example, a child does not do a pushup, he ''exercises his pectoralis major and triceps.'' By the fifth grade, children at Jackson Avenue School can name, identify and describe the function of 13 major muscles, she said.</p>
        <p>Two hindrances to the growth of this trend result from a shortage of certified gym teachers and the brief time that they have to spend with children.</p>
        <p>''Most physical-education programs don't have enough time to build fitness,'' said Janis Bozowksi, who teaches pupils at Greenbrook Elementary in South Brunswick twice a week for 30 or 40 minutes.</p>
        <p>Only four states, New York, New Jersey, Illinois and California, require that all students, from kindergarten through 12th grade, take physical education, and only Illinois requires that they take it five days a week.</p>
        <p>New York State requires that elementary pupils receive 120 minutes of physical education a week. State and local officials say that most districts are lucky to reach half the requirement.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, where the requirement is 150 minutes a week, and in Connecticut, which recommends 60 to 100 minutes a week for its youngest pupils, the situation is similar.</p>
        <p>Even with the time they now have, teachers say they have noticed encouraging signs from their students.</p>
        <p>''In the short-term, this is making kids feel good about participating in activities,'' Mrs. Geyer said. ''In the long-term, hopefully we'll get their level of fitness up to a more acceptable level.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
