<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TOUCHING THE 19th-CENTURY ADIRONDACKS</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="41378"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKS AND OTHER RECREATION AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CAMPS AND CAMPING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ADIRONDACK STATE PARK</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, ANN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Camps and Camping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7D7123EF934A25756C0A961948260" item-length="2321" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TOUCHING THE 19th-CENTURY ADIRONDACKS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN GOODMAN; ANN GOODMAN is associate editor of Securities International, a new McGraw-Hill newsletter.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, ANN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ''The Sunday Rock was the rock everybody passed on their way into the park, on their way into the Adirondack wilderness back in the old days. Once they passed that rock, Sunday could be Wednesday, Tuesday could be Saturday. You lost account of time. It didn't matter, because once you were in the woods, you were on a different time, in a different frame of mind, everything.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ''The Sunday Rock was the rock everybody passed on their way into the park, on their way into the Adirondack wilderness back in the old days. Once they passed that rock, Sunday could be Wednesday, Tuesday could be Saturday. You lost account of time. It didn't matter, because once you were in the woods, you were on a different time, in a different frame of mind, everything.</p>
        <p>''The Sunday Rock was the rock everybody passed on their way into the park, on their way into the Adirondack wilderness back in the old days. Once they passed that rock, Sunday could be Wednesday, Tuesday could be Saturday. You lost account of time. It didn't matter, because once you were in the woods, you were on a different time, in a different frame of mind, everything. That rock became known as the Sunday Rock, because when you went in, it was always Sunday, and when you came out, it was always Sunday.''</p>
        <p>As we sat around a crackling campfire, stars gleaming overhead and beasts whispering and wailing in the dark forest, this Adirondack tale, told by our guide, captured the mood of the wilderness. After two days of rowing and trekking, we had lost track of time and other intrusions of the tamed world.</p>
        <p>My friend and I had hired a guide to escort us for three days in the Adirondack Park, six million acres of waterways and wooded mountains 300 miles north of New York City. A third of the area is protected by an 1885 New York law stating that the acreage be kept forever as wild forest land. We were to traverse the park's sprawling St. Regis Wilderness Canoe Area, closed to motor vehicles, by foot and canoe, and set up camp at a pond where we could swim and fish. We would also learn the legends and lore of the Adirondack Mountains.</p>
        <p>The pain of roughing it was eased by our guide, Joseph Patrick Hackett, 31 years old. He grew up hunting, fishing and camping near the small village of Elizabethtown, 25 miles south of Lake Placid, where our trip was to begin. While still a child, he had longed to become a guide, joining a profession that has been carried on in the area for a century and a half. Although far younger than the grizzled guide of imagination, Mr. Hackett has a saucy glint in his eye and a knack for banter that links him to his predecessors.</p>
        <p>The first Adirondack guides of the early 1800's were trappers, Indians and loggers who led explorers and adventurers into the wilderness. By the end of the century, guides were accompanying wealthy tourists, whom they called ''sports,'' into the woods to hunt, fish and enjoy the outdoors. The guide earned his pay by rowing his sport through lakes and rivers, hauling wooden pack baskets and the guide boat - a canoe with oars - over portages, staking out fishing holes, setting up camp and fixing meals. Part of the guide's stock in trade was stories, often describing his own heroic exploits in the wilds. These yarns have been fused into the local lore, each embellished by decades of retelling. ''You can believe about half of what an Adirondack guide tells you, and you can't be too sure of that,'' Mr. Hackett said of the rascals who blazed the trail. In five years he has helped to rekindle guiding, which was nearly extinguished as the automobile allowed tourists to probe the back country on their own.</p>
        <p>Early Saturday morning, Mr. Hackett met us at our motel in Lake Placid. We had brought only our camping clothes and sleeping bags. He was to provide the rest - backpacks, tents, lanterns, utensils, food, fishing tackle and guide boats. My backpack weighed 20 pounds, my friend's 40. The mighty Mr. Hackett lugged an 80-pound pack and a 60-pound pack basket of food. In our car, we followed his jeep, two canoes on top, 25 miles northwest, past Saranac Lake where we stopped to buy a $3.50 license to allow us to fish for three days. Upper St. Regis Lake was our port of entry into the St. Regis wilderness. It was a gray morning, and it started to drizzle as we got out of the cars and began to load the boats. We put on our waterproof trousers and jackets, which, along with a flashlight that we also brought, proved to be the biggest boon to our weekend.</p>
        <p>The light rain lent a mystery to the mountains, shrouding them in steamy vapor. We rowed across the lake, blooming with purple arrowhead flowers. Guide and gear were in one boat, my friend and I lagged behind in the other. By the time we reached the first portage, Mr. Hackett had already hauled his 50-pound boat and its contents 100 yards to the next lake. He helped us to do the same. Then we navigated through a narrow channel of muddy black water, aptly named Bog Pond. Mr. Hackett shouted advice on how best to handle the oars to move the boat ahead or back. We crossed a second portage to Bear Pond, whose 50 acres of clear blue water seemed more typical of the Mediterranean than the Adironacks, where tannin from the trees often darkens lakes. This was to be our home for three days. I had to steer the boat to shore, and as I clumsily worked at it, a loon with perfect timing chortled from the woods.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hackett staked out our campsite, in use since the last century, on the 50-foot cliff overlooking the water. It was still drizzling as he swiftly helped us pitch the tents and string a hammock between two trees. He unpacked a large tarpaulin, which, roped to four trees near the campfire, served to cover our kitchen and dining and living rooms. Almost immediately, we huddled underneath to shelter from a sudden downpour. Rain is the camper's woe, for which the Adirondack guide's all-weather cure is a story.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hackett recounted the tale of Teddy Roosevelt's ride to his Inaugural. ''Roosevelt was staying at the posh Tahawus Club near Mount Marcy, at 5,344 feet the park's highest peak. He was atop the mountain when McKinley was shot. Roosevelt was hauled down the mountain and back to the club, only to hear that the President had recovered. The next day, Roosevelt was on his way back up the mountain when word arrived that McKinley had died. The country needed a President, so that evening Roosevelt, assisted by a number of guides, trekked down the mountain. By the time they reached the bottom, it was nearly midnight, but Teddy insisted on traveling another 15 miles to the nearest railroad station where he could catch the train to Buffalo.</p>
        <p>''He asked for volunteers to go with him, but no guide dared travel in the pitch black night. Only one, Mike Cronin, agreed to accompany the next President, and they flew down to the train in North Creek. Afterward, Cronin became a celebrity, and tourists came to hear his tale.''</p>
        <p>Each time Cronin recounted the story, he embellished it, Mr. Hackett explained, how they came around the corners with their wagon on two wheels, and the horses were frothin' and Roosevelt was shakin' and they made this mad dash in the middle of the night. When it was over, he'd say, ''You know, I just so happen to have left four of the horseshoes from that team of eight horses, and I'll sell 'em to you!'' They say in his lifetime he sold 400.</p>
        <p>Teddy Roosevelt may have had his way in the woods, but generally the guide is supreme. The paying sport, perhaps a big cheese back home, is reduced to a city bumpkin. We obediently followed Mr. Hackett about once the rain had stopped. He showed us a nearby pond built up by beavers and a whole tree they had chiseled apart with their teeth. After hiking back to camp, we set out on a canoe tour deeper into the wilderness. Our guide rowed us through two spring-fed lakes carved out by glaciers. We seemed to glide over St. Regis Pond, a 300-acre lake speckled with islands and encircled by mountains. Far inside the wilderness, we easily heard our oars splash over the water, a black mirror reflecting peaks and trees.</p>
        <p>That evening Mr. Hackett built a fire from pine needles, hemlock boughs and fragrant cedar logs still moist from the day's rain. We helped him prepare the meal of macaroni and cheese. He washed the dishes. Ever since one of Mr. Hackett's clients ripped up a pack basket to use as dry kindling, he said, he has preferred to take most of the responsibility around the camp. After dinner, we sat around the campfire and shooed mice from the marshmallows. The basket of food was hung by a makeshift pulley on a bough six feet up, well out of reach of chipmunks and bears. No sooner were we tucked into our sleeping bags than we heard a suspicious rustling and then a definitive thud. We bolted out to find raccoons rifling through the provisions in the basket, which they had brought to the ground by chewing the rope. We used a longer rope to raise the basket another six feet, and slept peacefully.</p>
        <p>Animals and birds were everywhere.</p>
        <p>We didn't see any eagles, still plentiful in the Adirondacks, but Mr. Hackett's Indian legend about one was almost as good.</p>
        <p>''One day the eagle was sitting in a big white pine, when along flew a bat. 'Is it true,' asked the bat, 'that you're the most powerful of flying creatures?' The eagle modestly answered that it was. The bat asked whether the eagle could fly higher than other creatures, and the eagle answered affirmatively. The bat asked if the eagle was swifter and more graceful than other creatures, and the eagle said he was. Then the bat asked the eagle to demonstrate how high he could fly and the eagle obliged.</p>
        <p>''As the eagle circled, the bat flew after him, clinging to his back. They flew higher and higher, until the eagle returned to the pine tree. The bat promptly flew back to the woods and bragged to all the animals that he had flown even higher than the eagle. The other animals were furious and scampered off to ask the eagle about it. When they heard that the bat had merely hitched a ride, they punished him. They cut off his wings so he could no longer fly. They gave him a long tail, so whenever he walked he would trip on it. And that's how we got the mouse.'' The next morning we were awakened by a bright sun, which spurred us to undertake an outing to St. Regis Mountain, at nearly 3,000 feet the highest peak in the wilderness area. Carrying only lunch, we moved in our canoes unencumbered as we backtracked over the waterways we had traced the day before. Sumptuous ''camps'' - summer homes of the rich - dot the shores of St. Regis Lake. We passed Topridge, an estate open to the public. From the canoe, we could see only a handful of the more than 50 buildings on its 200 acres.</p>
        <p>We docked our boat half a mile from the mountain trail, which was forged in the mid-1800's. The path, still muddy from rain, was bordered by slender silver beeches. We hiked over flat ground at first, but gradually the trail began to wind steeply up. We sweated profusely in the sun, eagerly taking a drink from a rushing mountain stream. The view from the summit was worth the exertion of our walk of three and a half miles on the upgrade. We could see all the ponds and lakes we had crossed by canoe, as well as our campsite. We celebrated with turkey and tomato sandwiches, and some stream water Mr. Hackett had collected along the way.</p>
        <p>That evening Mr. Hackett prepared steaks and corn on the cob and baked potatoes in the campfire. For this guide's sports, no ''eternal stew,'' a potpourri of backwoods edibles prepared by Noah John Rondeau, the ''tin can hermit,'' a guide who lived in the Cold River region in the early 1900's. He kept his food cool by storing it in buried metal garbage cans. Hollow logs housed his skillets and pots. But he was an unusual hermit in that he liked people, Mr. Hackett told us. One kitchen utensil he lacked was a percolator, the story continued, and when some important guests came to dinner, he asked if any of them had one. No one did. As Mr. Hackett retells it, ''Undaunted, Rondeau takes off his old hunting boot, pulls the toe of his sock, cuts it with a knife, makes a little pouch out of it, pours the coffee in it, ties a knot, drops it in the pot to percolate away. Needless to say, no one had any coffee that day.''</p>
        <p>The next day, our last in the wilderness, we broke camp early to be free to fish. Our lake was considered ''dead'' because acid rain, which has plagued the Adirondacks, had increased to the point that no fish were thought to live there. But Mr. Hackett said that good-sized fish could still be snared. He showed us how to troll by dragging our fishing lines behind the boat to imitate minnows. We novices basked in the sun while Mr. Hackett rowed us around. But no fish bit.</p>
        <p>As clouds gathered overhead, we lugged our gear down the cliff, sad at returning to the clatter of civilization. But we carried a bit of the woods with us. From our Adirondack guide we had learned that ''wilderness is a state of mind.''  INTO THE PARK</p>
        <p>Guiding has enjoyed something of a revival in the last five years. The New York State Outdoor Guides Association, formed in 1982, publishes a yearly list of licensed guides with phone numbers, addresses and their specialties. Send a check or money order for $1 made out to the association to Box 855, Saranac Lake, N.Y. 12983.</p>
        <p>Maps and brochures on areas in the Adirondacks are available, many of them free, from the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, Ray Brook, N.Y. 12977; phone, 518-891-1370. When writing, specify the area you are interested in.</p>
        <p>Joe Hackett operates the Tahawus Guide Service and Backcountry Outfitters on Route 86 in Ray Brook, N.Y. His mail address is Post Office Box 424, Lake Placid, N.Y. 12946, and phone, 518-891-4334. He offers hiking, canoeing and fishing trips April through October. It's good to book two months ahead. The fee is $135 a day for the first person, $60 for each additional person and this covers food and all equipment including canoes, fishing tackle, tents and backpacks. You need bring only sleeping bag, toiletries and clothing. You will want to take rainsuit, windbreaker, sturdy walking shoes and a sweater. Trips are tailored to the client's wishes.  Getting to Lake Placid</p>
        <p>By plane: Piedmont flies from Newark Airport and La Guardia Airport to Saranac Lake, which is a $15 cab ride from Lake Placid.</p>
        <p>By car from New York City: Take the Gov. Thomas E. Dewey Thruway, I-87 north to Albany, then continue on I-87, the Northway, to Exit 30. Continue 25 miles west on Route 73 to Lake Placid. - A. G.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
