<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY: WEDNESDAY, APRIL 8, 1987</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="28425"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7DF153EF93BA35757C0A961948260" item-length="991" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY: WEDNESDAY, APRIL 8, 1987</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International A3-18</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International A3-18</p>
        <p>International A3-18</p>
        <p>Rebuilding the embassy in Moscow will be considered by a high-level intelligence panel appointed by the President. The panel will study whether Soviet listening devices have compromised the embassy.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: Spying is accepted as part of the relationship between the United States and the Soviet Union, but American officials believe Moscow has had a distinct advantage in espionage activities in recent years.  A16</p>
        <p>Contra supporters raised millions more than contra leaders estimated they needed. Of the $83 million to $97 million raised between 1984 and 1986, over $20 million is unaccounted for, records show. A1</p>
        <p>The North Korean military threat that President Chun Doo Hwan of South Korea has used to justify crackdowns on critics of his repressive rule is real, American and South Korean officials say. A1  George Shultz will attend a seder with prominent Jewish dissidents in Moscow on Passover in an effort to dramatize the issue of Jewish emigration, the State Department's senior human rights official said. A17</p>
        <p>Helmut Kohl favors deployment of a new American short-range missile in West Germany and another system's modernization if there is a Soviet-American agreement abolishing European medium-range missiles, officials said. A18</p>
        <p>A new Philippine military policy against Communist rebels has created thousands of new refugees but has not yet brought the victories President Corazon C. Aquino called for. A9</p>
        <p>Syrian troops are ending a siege by Shiite Moslem militiamen that has gone on for five months in a Palestinian district in southern Beirut. Inhabitants cheered the soldiers moving into the Shatila district. A3</p>
        <p>NationaL A20-25, D30-32</p>
        <p>Paul Volcker cited economic risks, including recession, if the United States relies on further depreciation of the dollar to redress its trade deficit.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>States can limit Medicare fees under a Federal court ruling in Massachusetts, and while doctors assailed the decision, some experts said it would encourage other legislatures to follow suit. A1</p>
        <p>Private health plans often victimize the elderly with shady sales pitches and sometimes inadequate care, a Senate report said, recommending the Reagan Administration should not promote the plans for now. D31</p>
        <p>Harold Washington was re-elected Mayor of Chicago, defeating Democratic archrival Edward R. Vrdolyak and becoming the first Chicago Mayor to win re-election since the Richard J. Daley. A20</p>
        <p>Nancy Pelosi led in early returns in an election in California to fill the seat of the late Representative Sara Burton. However, the margin seemed to indicate the likelihood of a runoff, election officials said. A21  An acid rain proposal was assailed by some Members of Congress and environmental groups, who called the President's offer to consider a treaty with Canada another tactic to delay enforcing pollution controls. A14</p>
        <p>News analysis: Deficit reduction required by the Federal budget-balancing law appears to be doing well in this year's deliberations. This is a change from last year, when the law's letter and spirit were often ignored.  A23</p>
        <p>The Pentagon is secretly planning a blueprint showing how defenses against nuclear missiles could be deployed in space in the mid-1990's, two senators opposing the plan said.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>PAC's are playing a growing role in financing elections. Political action committees accounted for more than one-third of the $227 million collected by House candidates last year, a new  News Analysis: The Texaco ruling bya unanimous Supreme Court Monday masked sharp conflict within the Court on various issues in the case. The six separate opinions show that different concerns motivated the Justices. D1  Texaco won an injunction preventing the Pennzoil Company from seizing any assets until after a hearing next Monday. The ruling allows the company to continue business activities following the Supreme Court's decision. D5</p>
        <p>Older drivers view their licenses as passports to freedom and independence, but debates about age and traffic safety are taking place in homes and statehouses across the country.  C1</p>
        <p>Washington Talk B6</p>
        <p>Durenberger and his troubles  Friends raising money for North and Poindexter  Regional B1-5, B7</p>
        <p>Stricter ethics rules for politicians were approved overwhelmingly by members of the State Legislature. The vote came as weeks of tension over corruption investigations seemed to boil over in anger. A1</p>
        <p>At least 10 people may have died when a bridge on the Gov. Thomas E. Dewey Thruway collapsed Sunday and sent their vehicles tumbling into a flooded creek 40 miles northwest of Albany, officials now believe. B1</p>
        <p>Debate over all-male clubs has been intensified by city efforts to force them to admit women. The debate focuses on fundamental Constitutional principles, fine points of law and tradition in a changing world. B1</p>
        <p>News analysis: The Baby M decision has concerned a number of legal scholars who worry that the judge may not have followed state law in ordering what he recognized as ''an extraordinary judicial remedy.'' B2  Closer monitoring of physicians and hospitals is penetrating the medical world's clinical secrets, health officials say. Investigations are finding misconduct and incompetence that officials said might have previously been glossed over. B3</p>
        <p>The AIDS fight is focusing on addicts to intravenous drugs as the battle against the disease's spread moves from the laboratories and lecterns to the stoops and shooting galleries in New York City's most scarred neighborhoods. B1</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
