<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE TONIC EFFECTS OF WATER, WHETHER IN A POND OR A FOUNTAIN</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="20746"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="THE GARDENER'S EYE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, HUGH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870312T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4DE133AF931A25750C0A961948260" item-length="1146" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE TONIC EFFECTS OF WATER, WHETHER IN A POND OR A FOUNTAIN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HUGH JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSON, HUGH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THERE are two kinds of water in gardens: the kind that looks easy (it runs or lies in a natural or apparently natural hollow in the ground), and the kind that is clearly making an effort. Ponds, streams, rills, lakes and cascades all belong in category one. Category two applies to pools, to hard-edged containers, to any water in a situation where it is obviously constrained by art, or, most emphatically, to fountains.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THERE are two kinds of water in gardens: the kind that looks easy (it runs or lies in a natural or apparently natural hollow in the ground), and the kind that is clearly making an effort. Ponds, streams, rills, lakes and cascades all belong in category one. Category two applies to pools, to hard-edged containers, to any water in a situation where it is obviously constrained by art, or, most emphatically, to fountains.</p>
        <p>THERE are two kinds of water in gardens: the kind that looks easy (it runs or lies in a natural or apparently natural hollow in the ground), and the kind that is clearly making an effort. Ponds, streams, rills, lakes and cascades all belong in category one. Category two applies to pools, to hard-edged containers, to any water in a situation where it is obviously constrained by art, or, most emphatically, to fountains. Fountains are the antithesis of water's natural behavior. Versailles is full of them for that very reason. They are the hydraulic equivalent of fireworks.</p>
        <p>Either kind of water can be a major attraction and center of attention in a garden. It is said that water in movement - whether downward as in waterfalls, upward as in fountains or sideways as in breaking waves -charges the air with negative ions. These negative ions are supposed to have a tonic effect on the brain, the opposite effect to that of hot, dry winds, which irritate and depress (admittedly, it is hard to see how this theory applies to rain or drizzle).</p>
        <p>However the scientists may see it, I know that I am uplifted by cataracts and inspired by fountains, and I have no objection to a day by the sea. Even a placid piece of water in a garden, reflecting the sky, gives me quite disproportionate satisfaction. A garden without water in some shape or form is like a house without windows.</p>
        <p>The scale of the waterworks is not important except in relation to the size of the garden. A tiny yard (as the Japanese well know) can be transformed by a mere thread of water falling into a hollow stone. A very small electric pump, turning over perhaps a gallon a minute, can produce a respectable little cascade.</p>
        <p>If rocks masquerading as mountains is your style of gardening, recirculating the water in a bathtub-size pond is enough to create a dollhouse of a wilderness - not to be scorned in a city dweller's life.</p>
        <p>I would not advocate this style, though, for the uninvolved. If you know no plant names and shrink from dirt under your fingernails, you were ordained to be a fountain person. I prescribe for you a tank with architectural, not picturesque, pretensions. The same little pump will furnish a very pretty plume of water going up, and you may install a pair of goldfish to flash like dropped earrings as you peer at your reflection.</p>
        <p>The catch with either course is that water needs management. Just to keep a swimming pool looking clean and appetizing takes constant applications of chemicals and energy. Water is full of life, of microscopic plants and animals, of minerals and gases. Left to its own devices, this wildlife rapidly turns clear water into potage du jour. The gardener's business is to keep it sweet, which is not easy. I have seven separate ponds or pools of quite different character in my garden. Some work well; others are frequently murky or worse.</p>
        <p>Each presents a different problem, as it does a different pleasure: the carp in one stirring up the mud from the bottom; in another, an ineradicable mass of algae in spring. Even if my success rate is nothing to boast about, I am trying to achieve a balanced ecosystem, an equilibrium between the producers and consumers among the population of the water.</p>
        <p>Water plants are the producers of oxygen, using the energy in sunlight to convert carbon dioxide into the sugars they need for growth. Oxygen is the waste product they breathe out, but it is the breath of life to the consuming element: the fishes, newts, tadpoles and insects, not to mention bacteria and other microscopic fry. The fish and the rest, like you and I, in turn exhale carbon dioxide to the benefit of the plants.</p>
        <p>Note the need for sunlight. Water plants come in many forms, from the wispy weeds that trail deep in the flow of a stream to water hyacinths that float, and from the tiny algae that appear as a mere olive cloud to the glossy green disks of leaves that erupt from the depths where a waterlily grows.</p>
        <p>Looking at a pond as you would a landscape, the waterlilies are trees. They thrust their leaves up highest and cast shade on everything below. Little will grow in a pond where lily leaves cover the surface. With scant oxygen it will be a poor pond for fish, too. Better to clear away half the lilies and introduce plants that thrive on the bottom or in the middle depths. Anacharis (elodea or Canada waterweed) and cabomba (Carolina fanwort) are two such submerged plants, according to Charles Thomas, president of Lilypons Water Gardens in Lilypons, Md.</p>
        <p>A pond deeply shaded by overhanging trees is almost as damaging, since the fallen leaves, decomposing in the water, consume oxygen and can give off gases noxious to fish.</p>
        <p>Pond or pool, naturalistic or formal, the golden rule is to be consistent. If you adopt the naturalistic course, let water do only what would come naturally. Give it a hollow in the ground. Shape it irregularly. Do not construct the margin so that the earth immediately next to the water is dry. True ponds have boggy brinks, or at least enough moisture at their edges to support marsh marigolds and primulas. You can make provision for wet ground with little beds of soil inside the waterproof structure.</p>
        <p>What should the water-holding shell be made of? Some advocate heavy plastic or rubber sheeting. My preference is concrete, at least four inches thick and reinforced with wire mesh.</p>
        <p>Plastic or rubber is easier and cheaper to lay but also easy to puncture. And the unnatural-looking margin is almost impossible to hide. A glimpse of weathered concrete can be mistaken for a bank of rock or clay, but shiny black sheeting bears no resemblance to anything in nature.</p>
        <p>My favorite pond is one I built after studying Japanese gardens in books. It is kidney-shaped, about 30 feet by 10 feet at the narrowest, lying below a 7-foot bank. Against the bank I built a cascade of weathered limestone that incorporates an upper pool the size of a washbasin. Water from a spring (a mere trickle, but perpetual) drops a foot or so into the upper pool, then bounces and slides down a rocky gully, divides in two where it reaches a projecting ledge, and splashes 3 feet vertically to the pond below.</p>
        <p>A yellow waterlily is planted in a pocket in the bottom that I made when pouring the concrete. One bank is shaded by a shrubby willow; here grow hostas and ferns. The sunny side has just a clump of wide-faced purple Iris kaempferi.</p>
        <p>Five hundred tiny fish flicker in close formation, destined never to grow to be more than a snack for the herons. At the far side the concrete brink forms a dam, disguised by rocks, to let the water trickle on, via a buried pipeline, to another pond.</p>
        <p>This is where you will find me late on a still evening in June, my ears tuned to the harmony of the upper and the lower falls, my eyes adjusted in the twilight to pick out the sumptuous globes of the sleeping lily.</p>
        <p>THE GARDENER'S EYE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
