<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DEAVER PLEADS NOT GUILTY TO U.S. PERJURY CHARGES</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="24923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOBBYING AND LOBBYISTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERJURY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">TOLCHIN, MARTIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEAVER, MICHAEL K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1D81F3DF934A15750C0A961948260" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DEAVER PLEADS NOT GUILTY TO U.S. PERJURY CHARGES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARTIN TOLCHIN, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TOLCHIN, MARTIN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Michael K. Deaver, who left the White House to form a lobbying concern, pleaded not guilty to perjury charges today at his arraignment in Federal District Court.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Michael K. Deaver, who left the White House to form a lobbying concern, pleaded not guilty to perjury charges today at his arraignment in Federal District Court.</p>
        <p>Michael K. Deaver, who left the White House to form a lobbying concern, pleaded not guilty to perjury charges today at his arraignment in Federal District Court.</p>
        <p>Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson set the trial for June 8.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver, the former White House deputy chief of staff, is to be the first person tried under the Ethics In Government Act of 1978, which authorized the appointment of a special prosecutor when a top official is accused of wrongdoing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver, who was released today on his own recognizance, took a taxi to the field office of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, where he was photographed and fingerprinted, according to his attorney. Indicted on March 18</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver was indicted March 18 on five counts of perjury that charged him with lying to both a grand jury and Congress, in connection with investigations of alleged violations of laws prohibiting conflicts of interest.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver and his attorney, Herbert J. Miller, stood before Judge Jackson at the arraignment, which took three minutes. ''How do you plead?'' the judge asked.</p>
        <p>''I am not guilty, your honor,'' Mr. Deaver replied in a firm, strong voice.</p>
        <p>The judge said, ''Defendant is to be released on his personal recognizance, with no conditions, unless there is objection from the Government.''</p>
        <p>''No objection,'' said Whitney North Seymour Jr., the court-appointed special prosecutor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver left the courtroom in a brisk stride, shaking hands with reporters and telling each of them, ''It's nice to see you.''</p>
        <p>''I have no comment to make this morning,'' Mr. Deaver said before leaving in a taxi.</p>
        <p>Judge Jackson, who will preside over the trial, set April 20 for hearing defense motions. The judge was appointed to the court by President Reagan in 1982. Constitutional Challenge</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller said that he would renew a challenge by Mr. Deaver to the constitutionality of the law establishing the special prosecutor, with the official title of independent counsel. Randall J. Turk, Mr. Deaver's co-counsel, said Mr. Deaver would also contest the indictment on numerous other grounds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver had sought unsuccessfully to block his indictment by contending that the law violated the constitutional doctrine of separation of powers because it gave the court-appointed special prosecutor powers vested in the executive branch. Judge Jackson held March 11 that ''the constitutionality of the act will likely be upheld,'' rejecting Mr. Deaver's effort to block the indictment. The judge also found Mr. Deaver's motion premature, adding, ''Once indicted, he may move to dismiss the charges prior to trial.''</p>
        <p>Judge Jackson was subsequently upheld by the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia, and the indictment was returned hours after Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist rejected Mr. Deaver's last-minute effort to block it, noting that courts had traditionally been unwilling to interfere with criminal investigations. Ethics Law Bars Contacts</p>
        <p>The 1978 law bars senior Federal officials from lobbying anyone at their former agencies within one year after leaving the Government and from lobbying any department within two years on an issue in which they had direct responsibility. The law carries a lifetime ban against lobbying their former agencies on any matter in which they were ''personally and substantially'' involved while working for the government.</p>
        <p>Legal experts consider the law vague, and note that those who seek to exert political influence seldom leave traces of their activities. Moreover, in the case of Mr. Deaver, although he has acknowledged lobbying officials in the Office of Management and Budget and the National Security Council, the White House has maintained that those offices were separate and distinct from the White House for lobbying purposes.</p>
        <p>Two of the counts against Mr. Deaver charge that he lied to a House Energy and Commerce subcommittee investigating the conflict-of-interest charges. One count charges that Mr. Deaver lied when he said that he had done nothing to assist a representative of the Korean Government in obtaining a 1985 meeting with Mr. Reagan to deliver a letter on trade issues. A second count charged that he lied when he denied contacting anyone in the West Wing of the White House regarding his lobbying.</p>
        <p>The indictment also charged that he lied in his appearance before the grand jury last June when he said he had not participated in any White House discussion of acid rain until March 6, 1985. The indictment also charged that Mr. Deaver perjured himself when he denied making contact with any Government official on behalf of Trans World Airlines. The last count accused Mr. Deaver of lying when he denied speaking to anyone outside the Treasury Department in his representation of Smith Barney, which was seeking tax breaks for the Government of Puerto Rico.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
