<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>JUDGE BARS INDICTMENT OF DEAVER TO MULL CONSTITUTIONAL CHALLENGE</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="16874"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOBBYING AND LOBBYISTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERJURY</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSE COMMITTEE ON ENERGY AND COMMERCE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TOLCHIN, MARTIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEYMOUR, WHITNEY NORTH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEAVER, MICHAEL K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JACKSON, THOMAS PENFIELD (JUDGE)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4DA1131F935A15751C0A961948260" item-length="1068" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>JUDGE BARS INDICTMENT OF DEAVER TO MULL CONSTITUTIONAL CHALLENGE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARTIN TOLCHIN, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TOLCHIN, MARTIN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A special prosecutor said today that he would ask a Federal grand jury to indict Michael K. Deaver, the former White House deputy chief of staff, on four counts of perjury. But a Federal district judge temporarily barred any indictments after Mr. Deaver's lawyers challenged the constitutionality of the law authorizing appointment of special prosecutors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A special prosecutor said today that he would ask a Federal grand jury to indict Michael K. Deaver, the former White House deputy chief of staff, on four counts of perjury. But a Federal district judge temporarily barred any indictments after Mr. Deaver's lawyers challenged the constitutionality of the law authorizing appointment of special prosecutors.</p>
        <p>A special prosecutor said today that he would ask a Federal grand jury to indict Michael K. Deaver, the former White House deputy chief of staff, on four counts of perjury. But a Federal district judge temporarily barred any indictments after Mr. Deaver's lawyers challenged the constitutionality of the law authorizing appointment of special prosecutors.</p>
        <p>The prosecutor, Whitney North Seymour, said he would ask the grand jury to indict Mr. Deaver on charges that he lied last May in testimony before a House Energy and Commerce subcommittee and also lied to a Federal grand jury on three different matters. The grand jury has been investigating conflict-of-interest charges arising from Mr. Deaver's lobbying activities.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver's counsel argued in Federal District Court in a lawuit filed today that the 1978 law permitting the appointment of special prosecutors violated the constitutional doctrine of separation of powers. 'No Irreparable Harm'</p>
        <p>Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson issued an emergency order temporarily barring Mr. Seymour from pressing the case, saying that ''no irreparable harm'' would occur from a brief delay. He set March 11 for a hearing on the constitutional challenge.</p>
        <p>The challenge came a day after attorneys for Lt. Col. Oliver L. North, a former aide to the National Security Council, filed a similar challenge against the appointment of Lawrence E. Walsh as a special prosecutor. Mr. Walsh was appointed by a three-judge Federal panel to investigate the sale of arms to Iran by the United States and the diversion of the profits to the Nicaraguan rebels.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver's lawyers submitted a copy of Colonel North's brief along with with their own 42-page challenge to the statute. It was not clear whether Mr. North and Mr. Deaver had coordinated their actions in advance.</p>
        <p>Judge Jackson said Mr. Deaver ''has raised substantial questions as to the constitutionality of the Independent Counsel provisions of the Ethics in Government Act.'' The judge also said that ''a brief delay'' was justified because ''the grand jury's term is not imminently to end.''</p>
        <p>''No evidence is in danger of being lost,'' the judge said. ''No statute of limitations is about to expire. The plaintiff Deaver is not likely to flee the jurisdiction.''</p>
        <p>The judge's action came hours before the grand jury was expected to indict Mr. Deaver, a close friend of President Reagan and his wife, Nancy. Mr. Seymour's actions in pressing the indictments were praised by both Republicans and Democrats in Congress.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver's lawyers argued that Mr. Seymour, who was appointed last May by a three-judge Federal court, sought to ''usurp'' prosecutorial powers that the Constitution had vested in the executive branch.</p>
        <p>''The judge's decision speaks for itself,'' Herbert J. Miller, one of Mr. Deaver's attorneys, said on leaving the courthouse. ''The constitutional issues are very important.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller, asked why he had waited until the indictments appeared imminent before challenging the constitutionality of the law, replied, ''We wanted to make sure we had a real concern about what would happen.'' Deaver Asked for Prosecutor</p>
        <p>In opposing the delay in the Deaver case, Mr. Seymour predicted in a court session, ''The grand jury is going to allege that he lied the very first time he came to them.'' He noted that Mr. Deaver had petitioned the Justice Department to seek the appointment of an independent counsel.</p>
        <p>''Now, all of a sudden, when he sees that gamble is lost,'' Mr. Seymour continued, Mr. Deaver ''is talking about coming in and claiming irreparable harm'' from an indictment. ''It's only now he has faced up to the fact that it's not coming out the way he wanted it to,'' Mr. Seymour said.</p>
        <p>The House subcommittee had focused on Mr. Deaver's lobbying on behalf of the Canadian Government for an agreement with the United States on acid rain. The committee asked the independent counsel to explore charges that Mr. Deaver had lied in committee testimony.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour was given the broader task of investigating several of Mr. Deaver's enterprises to determine whether he violated ethics laws that restrict lobbying by former Government officials. Under those laws former high-ranking officials are forbidden to lobby their old agencies for a year after leaving Government. They also cannot lobby any department for two years on an issue in which they had direct responsibility, and they are permanently barred from lobbying on an issue in which they were involved ''personally and substantially.''</p>
        <p>Last month, Mr. Seymour asked the Federal court to extend his jurisdiction to include allegations of perjury and obstruction of justice. In his description today of the perjury indictment he hoped to obtain against Mr. Deaver, Mr. Seymour did not accuse Mr. Deaver of violating the ethics laws.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller acknowledged that there was no case law to bolster his contention that Mr. Seymour lacked constitutional authority to prosecute Mr. Deaver. ''The constitutionality of this statute has not been challenged as such in this situation,'' Mr. Miller said.</p>
        <p>Steven R. Ross, counsel to the Clerk of the House of Representatives, which seeks to uphold the statute, said the claim by both Mr. Deaver and Colonel North was ''not frivolous.'' And a number of prominent legal specialists agreed today that the lawsuits filed by Mr. Deaver and Colonel North would offer a strong constitutional challenge to the appointment of special prosecutors.</p>
        <p>Other constitutional experts predicted, however, that the courts would be unwilling to overturn the special prosecutor statute in this politically charged case.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ross noted that the executive branch must set in motion the machinery that leads to the appointment of special prosecutors.</p>
        <p>''The Attorney General must petition for appointment of an independent counsel,'' he said. ''Without his application, nothing would have happened.''</p>
        <p>Attorney General Edwin Meese 3d asked that an independent counsel be appointed to investigate Mr. Deaver's representation of Canada in seeking an acid rain agreement, and his efforts to seek Federal tax code changes that benefited Puerto Rico. The Attorney General also asked that the independent counsel be permitted to review other matters that had evoked Congressional concern, including Mr. Deaver's representation of the Daewoo Corporation, a large South Korean steel company.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
