<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DEAVER ACTS TO UPSET INDICTMENT, DEPICTING PROSECUTOR AS VINDICTIVE</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="32217"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERJURY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHENON, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEAVER, MICHAEL K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEYMOUR, WHITNEY NORTH JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5DD1F39F932A15757C0A961948260" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DEAVER ACTS TO UPSET INDICTMENT, DEPICTING PROSECUTOR AS VINDICTIVE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHENON, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHENON, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Michael K. Deaver, the former White House aide indicted on charges of perjury, today accused the special prosecutor in his case of ''prosecutorial vindictiveness'' and of intentionally distorting truthful testimony.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Michael K. Deaver, the former White House aide indicted on charges of perjury, today accused the special prosecutor in his case of ''prosecutorial vindictiveness'' and of intentionally distorting truthful testimony.</p>
        <p>Michael K. Deaver, the former White House aide indicted on charges of perjury, today accused the special prosecutor in his case of ''prosecutorial vindictiveness'' and of intentionally distorting truthful testimony.</p>
        <p>As part of a package of court motions intended to overturn the indictment, Mr. Deaver suggested that the special prosecutor, Whitney North Seymour Jr., had added a fifth perjury count to the indictment because he was angry over a court challenge to his authority.</p>
        <p>Last February Mr. Seymour said publicly that he planned to seek a four-count perjury indictment against Mr. Deaver, who has been accused of lying under oath to Congress and to a grand jury about his lobbying activities after leaving the White House.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver then filed suit, challenging Mr. Seymour's constitutional authority in the case. When the suit was dismissed last month, a Federal grand jury brought an indictment against Mr. Deaver, the former White House chief of staff, accusing him of five counts of perjury. Move to Dismiss Charge</p>
        <p>''Mr. Seymour thus 'upped the ante' against Mr. Deaver after Mr. Deaver exercised his legal rights to challenge the propriety of Mr. Seymour's investigation,'' Mr. Deaver's lawyers said in a court motion requesting the dismissal of the fifth perjury count.</p>
        <p>The decision to include the extra count, the motion said, ''raises the unseemly specter of prosecutorial vindictiveness and requires the vindictively added count to be dismissed by this court.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour has not disclosed why he added the fifth perjury count and would not answer questions today. Prosecutors have not disclosed which of the five counts was added at the end of the investigation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver is scheduled to go on trial in Federal District Court here in June.</p>
        <p>In the series of court motions today, Mr. Deaver asked that the trial be moved out of Washington because of prejudicial pretrial publicity.</p>
        <p>Another motion reasserted Mr. Deaver's challenge to the constitutionality of the inquiry by Mr. Seymour. The inquiry by a court-appointed special prosecutor, he said, infringed on the law-enforcement powers vested in the executive branch by the Constitution.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver also charged in the court papers that Mr. Seymour had deliberately omitted references to truthful statements that Mr. Deaver made about his role in White House policy on Canada and the issue of acid rain.</p>
        <p>In the indictment, Mr. Deaver was accused of lying to the grand jury when he denied discussing the acid rain issue until a meeting at the White House on March 6, 1985. The indictment said Mr. Deaver attended six White House meetings before that date at which acid rain was discussed.</p>
        <p>In fact, the defense motion said, Mr. Deaver ''did not deny that acid rain was discussed on those occasions. He merely testified that if it was, he had no recollection of the discussion or of having participated in it.'' Distortion of Testimony Charged</p>
        <p>Yet this portion of Mr. Deaver's testimony was not mentioned in the indictment. The defense motion today charged that Mr. Seymour had made unfair and incomplete use of Mr. Deaver's testimony. This ''calculated omission,'' it said, ''constitutes an impermissible distortion of the true nature and extent of his testimony on those subjects.'' It added, ''There is no perjury if answers claimed to be false were taken out of context.''</p>
        <p>In other motions, the defense lawyers contended that Mr. Seymour's investigation went beyond the mandate set by the three-judge panel that selected him last year.</p>
        <p>Charges in the indictment that Mr. Deaver made false statements about lobbying for Trans World Airlines and the Government of South Korea were not covered in the court mandate, the lawyers said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver, who has pleaded not guilty, came under investigation by the grand jury because of allegations that he had violated Federal ethics laws that limit lobbying activities by former Government officials. He was never charged with violations of those laws. Instead, he was accused of lying about his lobbying business.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
