<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN BRONX, EVERYONE KNOWS HOW TO SPEND THE CITY'S MONEY</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="41248"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRONX (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3D7153CF934A25756C0A961948260" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN BRONX, EVERYONE KNOWS HOW TO SPEND THE CITY'S MONEY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The testimony had not even begun. City Councilman Michael DeMarco was explaining the rules for the public hearing in the Bronx on New York City's proposed $22.7 billion budget: The speaking time would be five minutes for elected officials and heads of agencies, two minutes for everyone else.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The testimony had not even begun. City Councilman Michael DeMarco was explaining the rules for the public hearing in the Bronx on New York City's proposed $22.7 billion budget: The speaking time would be five minutes for elected officials and heads of agencies, two minutes for everyone else.</p>
        <p>The testimony had not even begun. City Councilman Michael DeMarco was explaining the rules for the public hearing in the Bronx on New York City's proposed $22.7 billion budget: The speaking time would be five minutes for elected officials and heads of agencies, two minutes for everyone else.</p>
        <p>''Hey, that's ridiculous,'' shouted a woman at the rear of the hall. ''We've always gotten three minutes before.''</p>
        <p>Cries of ''I agree, I agree!'' and ''Amen!'' from many of the rest of the scheduled speakers who were, officially, 119 in number, urged the woman on.</p>
        <p>''Miss, I don't know who you are,'' shouted Mr. DeMarco, grabbing Borough President Fernando Ferrer's gavel and rapping for order, ''but you are very impolite. You interrupted me.'' At this, one of the annual meetings that the City Council and the Board of Estimate hold to hear comments from the public on the Mayor's proposed budget, almost everyone in the Bronx - or his representative - had a better idea on how the city should spend its money. Race Against Time</p>
        <p>The Italian Big Sisters were there. So was the Baychester Library Association, the Institute for the Puerto Rican Hispanic Elderly, the Bronx Choral Society, the North Wind Under Sea Institute and a group called the Fund for Animals, which sought an allocation for its birth-control campaign for cats and dogs.</p>
        <p>Speaker after speaker stepped to the microphone in the middle of the granite-columned Veterans' Memorial Hall of the Bronx County Courthouse and read rapidly through speeches, trying to reach the end before the timekeeper's bell went off.</p>
        <p>''I will be brief,'' said a representative of a teachers' union. ''I have no choice.''</p>
        <p>The comments - to Mr. Ferrer, City Council members from the Bronx, and representatives of the Mayor and the other four Borough Presidents - included the following:</p>
        <p>On parks - ''We'd suffocate in carbon dioxide if plants didn't convert it to oxygen,'' said Theresa Lato of the Bronx Council for Environmental Quality. ''Parks are not a luxury but a necessity.''</p>
        <p>On playgrounds - ''Elizabeth Barrett Browning Intermediate School doesn't have one,'' said one speaker.</p>
        <p>On libraries - ''This is a special year,'' noted Nathalia Lange, who was speaking for the Bronx Library Council. ''By Presidential proclamation it is the Year of the Reader.''</p>
        <p>On sewers and street repairs for the Wakefield section of the Bronx - ''I am not handing out a prepared text,'' said the woman advocating them, ''because I hope to burn in your conscience what I have to say here.'' 'People's Right of Petition'</p>
        <p>The hearing seemed part a contest in oratory, part an exercise in letting off steam and part of an old-fashioned demonstration of what Mr. Ferrer called ''the people's right of petition.''</p>
        <p>Many of the speakers said they lobbied the politicians all the time and had already made known their concerns.</p>
        <p>''But you have to repeat, repeat, repeat,'' said James Vacca, district manager of Community Board 10 in the northern Bronx.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vacca, who is 32 years old, said he had come to the Bronx hearing every year since a teacher encouraged him, at 13, to speak up for better bus service for junior high school students in the Pelham Bay section. He got it, he said.</p>
        <p>The woman who got into the shouting match over time limits was the chairwoman of Community Board 12, Elvira Wyart. She told a reporter after her speech, ''I wouldn't say this is fun, but it is an opportunity to influence people.'' She had prevailed on the time question: Mr. DeMarco said speakers would still get three minutes this year, but they would get only two minutes next year. Unfilled Potholes</p>
        <p>Mrs. Wyart, who wore on her coat a gold cockroach pin, given to her by her husband after her frequent exhortations to officials that we ''stamp out drug dealers just like cockroaches,'' used her time to lament all the things the city was not getting done.</p>
        <p>''Twenty-two point seven billion dollars and we can't even get the Little League fields repaired,'' she said in a rhetorical flourish that drew cheers and whistles from the audience. ''Twenty-two point seven billion dollars and we can't even get the potholes filled.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ferrer said in an interview that the hearing was ''an important part of the budget process.'' The Council and the Board of Estimate must finish their modifications and vote on the budget before June 30. The public hearings are held in each borough and there is also an additional hearing open to everyone in the city.</p>
        <p>A former city councilman who became Borough President after Stanley Simon resigned in March shortly before being indicted on corruption charges, Mr. Ferrer said he planned to ''make this into something serious.''</p>
        <p>''When you see me turn around and whisper something to somebody,'' he continued, ''that's me asking an aide, 'Hey, let's have a report on what this speaker is talking about.' ''</p>
        <p>But even Mr. Ferrer, new on the job and clearly benefiting from an air of goodwill on the part of community leaders, became impatient with some of the speakers.</p>
        <p>''Could you wrap it up now,'' he said to one man who was at least 45 seconds over the limit with no end to his speech in sight. ''You know, just conclude.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
