<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE INDEPENDENT STYLE OF DEAVER'S PROSECUTOR</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="47589"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOBBYING AND LOBBYISTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">AYRES, B DRUMMOND AYRES JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEYMOUR, WHITNEY NORTH JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEAVER, MICHAEL K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOTLIEB, ALLAN (AMB)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOTLIEB, SONDRA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEED9123DF93BA35755C0A961948260" item-length="1381" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE INDEPENDENT STYLE OF DEAVER'S PROSECUTOR</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By B. DRUMMOND AYRES Jr., Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">AYRES, B DRUMMOND AYRES JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Every year on July 4, Whitney North Seymour Jr. gathers the dozen or so other members of his family on Cape Cod. One by one, each reads a sentence or a paragraph from the Declaration of Independence. Then, after each reading, the entire clan joins in a discussion of the meaning and significance of that section of the document.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Every year on July 4, Whitney North Seymour Jr. gathers the dozen or so other members of his family on Cape Cod. One by one, each reads a sentence or a paragraph from the Declaration of Independence. Then, after each reading, the entire clan joins in a discussion of the meaning and significance of that section of the document.</p>
        <p>Every year on July 4, Whitney North Seymour Jr. gathers the dozen or so other members of his family on Cape Cod. One by one, each reads a sentence or a paragraph from the Declaration of Independence. Then, after each reading, the entire clan joins in a discussion of the meaning and significance of that section of the document.</p>
        <p>If this seems an unusual and poignant way for an American family to mark July 4, it is nonetheless thoroughly in keeping with the character of Whitney North Seymour Jr., the 63-year-old New York lawyer who is the special prosecutor investigating influence-peddling allegations against Michael K. Deaver, the former deputy White House chief of staff.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour is of the establishment, scion of a prominent Manhattan family of moderate Republicans and big-client lawyers, graduate of Princeton and Yale, member of the Century Club and the Players, Episcopalian.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Seymour - Mike to his friends - comes across as pious and stuffy to some, he strikes many others as a man rightly living life, utterly honest, committed to the public good, interested, engaged. ''The essential character of Mike Seymour is that he is straight as an arrow, fiercely independent,'' says Edward M. Shaw, a close friend and fellow New York lawyer. Subpoena Across the Border</p>
        <p>The other day, Mr. Seymour decided to subpoena the Canadian Ambassador and his wife in the Deaver case, seemingly heedless of the furor it would stir over diplomatic immunity, not only in Canada but also at the State Department and in the American legal establishment. He said the Canadian Government, which had received some advice from Mr. Deaver on the touchy cross-border subject of acid rain, was being ''duplicitous'' and did not want the investigation to proceed.</p>
        <p>The Canadians shot back that Mr. Seymour was ''irresponsible.''</p>
        <p>The State Department said he was creating international ''friction.''</p>
        <p>And close friends and supporters, who have always considered Mr. Seymour to be a competent litigator, worried that he had badly misjudged the situation or was on a desperate fishing expedition, trying hard, but clumsily, to bolster a case in which he has managed to obtain perjury indictments against Mr. Deaver but not the crucial conflict-of-interest indictments. Unlisted Office Telephone</p>
        <p>None of this moved Mr. Seymour, who before taking on the Deaver assignment was best known for his investigations into rackets, police corruption and narcotics in the 1960's and 1970's, first as an assistant United States attorney for the Southern District of New York, then as a special counsel, then as the United States Attorney. He is, after all, the same man who, after being named independent counsel in the Deaver case, began by refusing to list any office address or telephone number.</p>
        <p>Anyone who really needed to reach him, including informers, would find a way, he seemed to be saying. He characteristically refused to explain his rationale.</p>
        <p>As for the press, which he has always kept at arm's distance, it seemed that reporters could have their day in court, when and if Mr. Deaver went to court. But again, Mr. Seymour refused to explain his reasons for not discussing the case, even as the din of negative editorials and columnists' comments grew louder.</p>
        <p>Actually, his record is clear on press matters. And the other day, the din having died down somewhat, he reiterated his views in a rare interview. 'A Little Bit Strange'</p>
        <p>There is a ''terrible risk'' of disservice to a defendant, he said, if a prosecutor talks about a case before it can unfold in court. ''When a case comes to trial,'' he added, ''that is where the stories for the press come from.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour's general reticence to talk to the press or to otherwise explain himself gives pause even to some of his supporters. His refusal to list an office address or telephone number for his Deaver investigation office is ''a little bit strange,'' in the view of Richard Ben-Veniste, a Washington lawyer who once worked as an assistant United States attorney for Mr. Seymour.</p>
        <p>And to Mr. Shaw, Mr. Seymour's consistent refusal to talk to reporters about cases opens him to ''fair criticism'' that ''there are times when he is pursuing that conviction that he is more closed-mouth than he needs to be.''</p>
        <p>Some of the force for that conviction seems to come from Mr. Seymour's view that courts are ''the stable force'' in life and that there is little to equal the importance or satisfaction of working in them as a prosecutor, particularly as a United States Attorney. ''The position of U.S. Attorney,'' he contends, ''is the finest public service position that exists. U.S. Attorneys carry the responsibility that the law is firmly enforced, but with compassion and consideration.'' Campaigns for Public Office</p>
        <p>However Mr. Seymour views courts and prosecuting, Mr. Deaver's lawyer finds Mr. Seymour lacking in prosecutorial skills. ''This is nothing short of outrageous,'' the attorney, Herbert J. Miller Jr., said the other day of Mr. Seymour's handling of the Deaver investigation. ''It is not the type of conduct you'd expect from any prosecutor.''</p>
        <p>For all his love for the courtroom, Mr. Seymour has deviated several times and run for political office, failing in attempts to win a seat in the New York Assembly and in the United States House and Senate, but succeeding in winning a term in the New York State Senate, in 1966-68. Political analysts in New York say his success has been limited, in good part, because he tends to come across as a stiff, even dour, candidate.</p>
        <p>During his run for the United States Senate in 1982, a campaign he describes as ''a foolish stab,'' Mr. Seymour was arrested and charged with disorderly conduct when he deliberately attempted to distribute campaign literature at a fairground in Altamont after fair officials contended that such activity was unlawful. Mr. Seymour, never one to duck a crusade, managed to get the charge dropped, hailing the dismissal as a ''red-letter day for the democratic process.'' Convicted and Fined $17</p>
        <p>The incident was not his first personal tiff with the law or his first crusade against it. Once, while driving through Arizona with his family on a vacation to the Southwest, he was given a ticket for parking too close to the highway.</p>
        <p>He disputed the charge, demanded an immediate trial, represented himself and, in short order, was convicted and fined $17. He demanded an immediate appeal, but was told that the earliest date he could have was in two months, when, of course, he would be back in New York, a costly 2,000 miles away. He dropped his appeal, but not the case. Instead, he wrote a long, highly critical travel article on it for The New York Times.</p>
        <p>Five years ago, he parted ways with the prestigious New York law firm of Simpson Thacher &amp; Bartlett after a 33-year affiliation, much of it during the time when his father, Whitney North Seymour Sr., was a major partner.</p>
        <p>Big firms were losing their way, he contended, becoming too impersonal and bureaucratic and concentrating more on making money than rendering service.</p>
        <p>He and another refugee from a big firm, Peter Megargee Brown, found their independence by setting up a two-man firm, calling it a ''country'' firm in the middle of the big city. They hoped to make a good living. But they also aimed to ''render service,'' particularly to those who could not afford to pay, like the hard-pressed grocer down on the corner who gave them two bottles of Irish whisky when, after many hard hours, they got him his small share of a relative's estate. A Publisher Himself</p>
        <p>For all his pulling and tugging with the press through the years, Mr. Seymour is himself a publisher, a hobby that goes back to his childhood in Greenwich Village, when he used a toy printing press to periodically produce The Garden Chatter, a neighboorhood newspaper that he distributed in a nearby park. The press run? ''Oh, about 25 copies.''</p>
        <p>Today, through a family-run enterprise called Lime Rock Press, he and his wife, Catryna Ten Eyck, and his two daughters, Tryntje Van Ness and Gabriel North, publish miniature books, some of them little more than a couple of inches square.</p>
        <p>''I know all about the First Amendment and freedom of the press,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
