<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Britain's TV for Children</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="60626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="ABOUT EDUCATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BRITISH BROADCASTING CORP (BBC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HECHINGER, FRED M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOME, ANNA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ABOUT EDUCATION (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3D61F31F93BA15754C0A961948260" item-length="1100" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Britain's TV for Children</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRED M. HECHINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HECHINGER, FRED M</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: COMPARED with American programming, British television is a children's paradise. But broadcasters and educators are worried that it might turn into a paradise lost if the Thatcher Government's plans to deregulate the industry materialize.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: COMPARED with American programming, British television is a children's paradise. But broadcasters and educators are worried that it might turn into a paradise lost if the Thatcher Government's plans to deregulate the industry materialize.</p>
        <p>COMPARED with American programming, British television is a children's paradise. But broadcasters and educators are worried that it might turn into a paradise lost if the Thatcher Government's plans to deregulate the industry materialize.</p>
        <p>The American experience feeds such pessimism because deregulation has allowed broadcasters to blur the line between children's shows and commercials. American commercial television has virtually abandoned children's programming, except for what has come to be known as the Saturday morning ''cartoon ghetto.'' Many of these programs feature characters based on toys and serve as marketing tools for toy makers. Public television is virtually alone in serving America's children.</p>
        <p>But Anna Home, who presides over BBC's children's section, remains confident that children's programming in Britain will not suffer. ''We are still going up rather than down,'' she said. She added that BBC alone, not counting commercial programs on Independent Television (ITV), broadcast about 800 hours a year to children, including programs from 4 to 6 in the afternoon.</p>
        <p>Every weekday at about 5 o'clock, BBC broadcasts a 10- to 15-minute news roundup for children.</p>
        <p>A half-hour program for preschoolers at 10 A.M. has been on the air for about 20 years. On a recent morning, the preschool program started with an American Charlie Brown cartoon, appropriately dealing with the children's experiences in summer camp. Feminists would be pleased to know that the girls defeated the boys in every contest from swimming to arm wrestling. It was followed by a segment that let children have a look at another country, in this case the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>The next day, the announcer said, there would be a story of one boy's fight against acid rain.</p>
        <p>Programs appear geared to urban audiences - working-class speech patterns of performers attest to that. The shows also like occasionally to take children to the countryside. In one recent program, children were shown learning to milk a very docile cow.</p>
        <p>On Saturday mornings, BBC entertains children from 8:30 to noon, including two hours of live programs and the rest cartoons, 25 percent of them imports from the United States.</p>
        <p>One particularly popular children's soap opera, ''Grange Hill,'' is set in an inner-city state school and deals with the daily lives of its students. The half-hour program has been on the air more than 10 years for a daily half-hour in the late afternoon.</p>
        <p>A relatively new show that is watched regularly by parents and children at 7:30 P.M. on Tuesdays and Thursdays, and in rebroadcasts on Sunday afternoons, is ''EastEnders,'' set at Albert Square in a working-class section of London's East End. It has become Britain's No. 1 program, Ms. Home says. Recent research has shown that 20 percent to 25 percent of all children between the ages of 4 and 15 watch it. The program, dealing with the lives of people in their homes and shops, is a sort of grown-up version of Sesame Street, without the muppets.</p>
        <p>Except for cartoons, I doubt whether many British programs for young children would travel across the Atlantic. British programmers say the pace of American shows is too hectic. That is why the BBC turned down Sesame Street years ago. The programs I sampled here seemed slow and relaxed. They appealed to me, but I wondered if they would hold the attention of American children raised on action-packed fare.</p>
        <p>''Our shows are slower, more British,'' Ms. Home said. ''I sometimes think they're a little too British. I'd like them a little faster, but not like Sesame Street.''</p>
        <p>''Don't misunderstand,'' she went on. ''Sesame Street has had an enormous influence worldwide, especially in its technique.''</p>
        <p>British children watch less television and their viewing is more tightly controlled by adults, she added.</p>
        <p>Ms. Home said BBC did not make documentaries for children or teen-agers. ''We do problems within dramas.''</p>
        <p>A recent segment of ''Grange Hill'' used a drug theme, showing how a high school student got addicted to heroin, and how he got off.</p>
        <p>What about direct teaching, such as in the American science program ''3-2-1 Contact,'' produced by the Children's Television Workshop, creator of Sesame Street? ''Too educational,'' said Ms. Home. ''The characters are too all-American squeaky-clean.''</p>
        <p>But she added: ''We are currently making a science show. It will be a mixture of looking at what children are doing and some short science fiction dramas written by serious science fiction writers. We'll look at the achievements of science in the past and prospects for the future.''</p>
        <p>In buying shows from America, Ms. Home says: ''I look at the quality of the program, and up to now it's been O.K. But I'm getting worried because the toy manufacturers in the United States are pushing toys into the programs. That would be unacceptable.''</p>
        <p>Despite her general optimism, Ms. Home does worry about the future. Children's programs, she points out, are not as profitable for the commercial broadcasters as adult shows. At present, ITV is required to do a certain number of children's programs. Deregulation may change this. If children's programming in the commercial sector declines, there could be greater financial pressure on BBC to fill the void.</p>
        <p>Drama is very expensive, Ms. Home said. ''People ask whether it is really important to spend so much money for 8- to 13-year-olds,'' she said. ''I'm fighting the battle all the time.'' Still, she is hopeful because ''the tradition of public service programming is strong here.''</p>
        <p>Other observers see potential deregulation as a more serious threat. At present, commercial broadcasters are periodically relicensed on the basis of a prospectus that includes a commitment to public service, such as children's programming. A ''worst case scenario,'' says Stuart Maclure, editor of The Times of London's Educational Supplement, expects relicensing to be replaced by auctions that would give channels to the highest bidders. Much more money might be made if the public service requirements give way to a free broadcasting market.</p>
        <p>If that happens, pessimists warn, BBC might suffer. At present, BBC is financed through users' fees collected from every household with a television set. If the government were to reduce those fees, it could drive BBC out of entertainment and dramatic productions, giving it exclusive responsibility for public service, but with inadequate financing.</p>
        <p>If this were to happen, children's programming, in which Britain has long pioneered, could face policies of the kind that have devastated it in the United States.</p>
        <p>ABOUT EDUCATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
