<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A GUPPY BOOM IN AGE OF AQUARIUMS</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="74643"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="GIBSONTON JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FLORIDA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GIBSONTON (FLA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORDHEIMER, JON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2D6143CF936A2575AC0A961948260" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A GUPPY BOOM IN AGE OF AQUARIUMS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jon Nordheimer, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NORDHEIMER, JON</byline>
      <dateline>GIBSONTON, Fla.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Those upwardly mobile young professionals whose nickname rhymes with guppies are helping create a booming market for the tropical fish and other species, and the biggest beneficiary is this town on the eastern shore of Tampa Bay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Those upwardly mobile young professionals whose nickname rhymes with guppies are helping create a booming market for the tropical fish and other species, and the biggest beneficiary is this town on the eastern shore of Tampa Bay.</p>
        <p>Those upwardly mobile young professionals whose nickname rhymes with guppies are helping create a booming market for the tropical fish and other species, and the biggest beneficiary is this town on the eastern shore of Tampa Bay.</p>
        <p>Hemmed in by their apartments and lacking yards for much larger pets, these urban dwellers are propelling sales of such bowl dwellers as shovelnose catfish, loach weather dojos and the ever-popular guppies, many of which are raised or shipped from Gibsonton.</p>
        <p>Gibsonton is a curious setting for the center of tropical fish farming in this country. With phosphate plants belching yellow smoke, the town has attracted attention in the past as the winter home of circus sideshow people and, more recently, as a breeding ground for an Asian flying cockroach.</p>
        <p>Fields here and in other communities around Tampa Bay are pitted with ponds arranged in orderly rows that from the air look like giant Post Office mailslots dug out of the green earth. Together they produce millions of freshwater tropical fish for aquariums.</p>
        <p>''We've come a long way from the days when the industry was represented by a goldfish in a bowl on a tabletop,'' says Elwyn Segrest, a good-humored Mississippian who once operated a pet shop before he got into tropical fish farming, Florida's fastest growing agricultural business.</p>
        <p>Some medical authorities say that people need pets to help reduce the tension of city life, and the loneliness. Pet fish, they say, are great to come home to in an empty apartment and they help reduce stress and lower blood pressure. Look at all the fish tanks in dentists' waiting rooms.</p>
        <p>Pet fish represent the second biggest hobby in America, behind photography, and it is estimated that 5 to 10 percent of the population keeps some species of fish in an aquarium at home or office. The surge of interest has created a demand for exotic and more expensive species to mix in a tank with the more commonplace guppies, neon tetras and swordtails that are the mainstays of pet shop aquariums and the quart bowls lining the back walls of a K-Mart.</p>
        <p>Mr. Segrest's operation, Segrest Farms, ships fish directly to pet shops, packaging them in water-filled plastic bags given a burst of pure oxygen. Across town, Tim Hennessy, who with his wife and brother owns Ekk Will Tropical Fish Farms, ships only to wholesalers. His hatchery alone sends four million tropical fish a month in 50-ton shipments out of Tampa International Airport. Every week the airport handles 15,000 to 20,000 boxes of pet fish.</p>
        <p>Florida agricultural officials estimate that fresh fish production in the state jumped 30 percent last year and another large gain is expected this year when all the figures are compiled.</p>
        <p>''Fish are good pets,'' Mr. Hennessy is quick to point out. ''There's no messes on the carpet and they won't keep you and the neighbors up barking all night.''</p>
        <p>The United States imports more pet fish than it produces, but of the domestic crop, 90 percent of the tropical fish are hatched in Florida around Tampa. Saltwater reef fish are more prized than freshwater varieties, for brilliance of color as well as other aesthetic considerations. But nearly all have to be captured in native seas, a process that drives up the price and causes greater mortality in shipping because the fish must endure more handling and stress for longer periods of time.One out of five arrive dead or mortally stricken.</p>
        <p>Freshwater fish fare better. Mr. Hennessy, who holds a college degree in ocean engineering and a master's degree in business administration, says more than 99 percent of the fish he ships arrive alive.</p>
        <p>Each fish shipper has his own technique to enhance survival during shipments that sometimes cover two or three days. Basically, the key is to sedate the fish by injecting into the packaged bags of water chemicals like benzocaine and carbon dioxide, which slow down respiration, defecation and movement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Segrest goes a step further, favoring a tranquilizer that has the effect of knockout drops. ''I like to ship 'em belly up,'' he says, a condition that at times causes outraged pet store owners to telephone him and complain that all his fish arrived dead. ''I tell them to retrieve them out of the garbage can and put them in a tank. They'll revive in a matter of minutes and be 100 percent healthy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hennessy recalls that his hatchery once referred to the medication as ''dope'' until an air freight handler at the Atlanta airport, overhearing the reference, stole a carton thinking he had intercepted a box of marijuana.</p>
        <p>Another handler, trying to be helpful, noted the freshwater fish label and stored the shipment in a freezer overnight when a flight was delayed so the fish wouldn't spoil.</p>
        <p>GIBSONTON JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
