<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY: MONDAY, APRIL 6, 1987</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="27869"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5D61038F935A35757C0A961948260" item-length="1051" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY: MONDAY, APRIL 6, 1987</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-11, B10</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-11, B10</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-11, B10</p>
        <p>The South Korean underground nurtures a passionate belief in democracy and the reunification of North and South Korea. Its conduct over the next year could shape South Korean politics for many years. Page A1</p>
        <p>Nearly one year after Chernobyl suffered a nuclear disaster, only one fireman who faced spewing radiation to fight the blaze has survived to tell the tale, emerging as the foremost symbol of the struggle against the rogue reactor. A1</p>
        <p>Mikhail S. Gorbachev put off a visit to Czechoslovakia until late in the week because of a ''slight cold.'' The announcement set off ripples of conjecture. The Soviet leader was expected to arrive in Prague today. A6</p>
        <p>Tass reported a failed space project. The Soviet Government official press agency said an unmanned, 11-ton space research module, called Kvant, failed to link up with the orbiting Mir laboratory. B10</p>
        <p>President Reagan arrived in Ottawa on a cold and rainy day for his third summit meeting with Prime Minister Brian Mulroney and, as it happened, encountered a chilly reception on the subject of acid rain. A5</p>
        <p>The Pope heard an archbishop's cry against Chile's ''culture of death.'' Archbishop Jose Manuel Santos Ascarza, at a mass in Concepcion, complained of terrorism by both the military Government and its opposition.  A3</p>
        <p>In Chile, the use of violence by the opposition has become the subject of disagreement. The dispute has been heightened by the clashes that marred Pope John Paul II's visit.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Pakistan is anticipating pressure -both military and psychological -from Kabul and Moscow that could result from heavy fighting that is expected in the next few months between Soviet forces and Afghan guerrilla armies. A9  A ferry tragedy is a Dover tragedy, as the disaster at Zeebrugge, Belgium, has proved. Dover, in southeast England, is Europe's leading ferry port, but some worry about its dependence on one industry. D8</p>
        <p>A global television news program, Planet 3, could be appearing weekly on television stations from Peoria to Prague by next spring, according to the British-American partnership that is trying to find the money to begin it. B10</p>
        <p>Attempts to reopen Beirut's airport this weekend have turned into a national controversy and heightened tensions between Moslems and Christians. The international airport has been closed for two months. A8</p>
        <p>National A12, B8-11</p>
        <p>Illegal aliens working on farms helping to harvest fruit, vegetables and ''other perishable commodities'' such as Christmas trees and tobacco, could be offered legal status under plans being made by the Reagan Administration. A1  A shift in Texas's economic realities can be heard, suddenly, in talk of an income tax to replace the gusher of oil and gas revenues that has gone dry. In the past, politicians have avoided suggesting such a tax. A12</p>
        <p>A runoff mayoral election in Dallas will be held on April 18, since the Mayor Pro Tem, Annette Strauss, failed to gain a majority of the vote on Saturday in her bid to become the first female elected mayor. B9</p>
        <p>Those who shaped the Constitution were the focus of discussion as 2,200 historians gathered to examine the document's meaning. Mostly, the spotlight shone on rebels and dissenters who worked to expand its protections. A12  Mainstream Republicans and evangelical Christians are struggling for power in the South Carolina G.O.P., underscoring the rising tension between followers of Vice President Bush and those of the Rev. Pat Robertson, who are an important voting constituency. B9  An offer to buy United Airlines from the Allegis Corporation for $4.5 billion in cash, subordinated notes and assumed debt was made by the airline's pilots' union. D1</p>
        <p>More independent films are winning acclaim in Hollywood. A decade ago, about 10 Oscar nominations a year were won by movies released by independents or second-tier Hollywood studios. The total this year was 36.</p>
        <p>C11</p>
        <p>Tests performed at chemical fire</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON TALK B8</p>
        <p>Dr. Koop defends his crusades  Regional B1-7, B14</p>
        <p>A bridge collapsed on the Thruway in Fort Hunter, N.Y, pitching at least two cars and a truck into a swollen creek. It was not known immediately how many people might have been injured. A1</p>
        <p>The bridge had been rehabilitated five years ago and was last inspected in April 1986, when the 31-year-old structure was found to be in good condition, a state official said. A1  Fallen bridge to affect truckers</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Connecticut tragedy is recalled</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Inquiries into state payroll abuses have focused attention on the extent of the intimate - and possibly illegal - relationship between party politics and public funds in the state Capitol.  A1</p>
        <p>Of people who use soup kitchens, more than 40 percent survive on one meal or less a day, according to a private study, which also found that most of those eligible for government benefits are not getting them. B1</p>
        <p>A man in a deportation case is expected to go before the United States Supreme Court today. The fate ofKarl Linnas, who is accused of being a Nazi war criminal, will ultimately be decided by Attorney General Edwin Meese 3d. B6  An office-entertainment center is planned on 12 blocks between Pennsylvania Station and the Hudson River. Gulf and Western Inc. and Olympia &amp; York are reported close to agreement on the project. B1</p>
        <p>Lyn Nofziger will refuse to testify about the $780,000 he has received as a lobbyist for the Long Island Lighting Company, he told a Senate subcommittee, adding that he plans to invoke the Fifth Amendment. B3</p>
        <p>A 'nuclear curriculum' for students in grades kindergarten through 12 has been developed at East Meadow School District in Long Island to encourage learning about nuclear energy, nuclear war and related issues.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Group to help Prospect Park</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>Koch planning condominiums in Queens</p>
        <p>B14</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
