<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CANADIANS COMPLAIN REAGAN RENEGES ON ACID RAIN FUNDS</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="2908"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MULRONEY, BRIAN (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURNS, JOHN F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5DB1E39F931A25752C0A961948260" item-length="651" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CANADIANS COMPLAIN REAGAN RENEGES ON ACID RAIN FUNDS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BURNS, JOHN F</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, Jan. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Less than a year after President Reagan and Prime Minister Brian Mulroney signed an accord on a joint approach to the problem of acid rain, officials here have begun questioning whether the United States is serious about tackling an issue that has sensitive political overtones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Less than a year after President Reagan and Prime Minister Brian Mulroney signed an accord on a joint approach to the problem of acid rain, officials here have begun questioning whether the United States is serious about tackling an issue that has sensitive political overtones.</p>
        <p>Less than a year after President Reagan and Prime Minister Brian Mulroney signed an accord on a joint approach to the problem of acid rain, officials here have begun questioning whether the United States is serious about tackling an issue that has sensitive political overtones.</p>
        <p>New criticism has been spurred by the allocation of less than $300 million to acid rain research in Mr. Reagan's $1,024 billion budget for fiscal 1988, much of it money that was committed before the two Governments agreed on a stepped-up environmental program last year.</p>
        <p>In Canada, where official studies have attributed 50 percent of environmental damage from rain-borne pollutants to American industries, the allocation has been widely criticized as undercutting the agreement reached by Mr. Reagan and Mr. Mulroney at a meeting in Quebec City last March.</p>
        <p>In turn, Mr. Mulroney has come under fresh attack for his handling of relations with the United States, which opponents have frequently described as insufficiently assertive. $5 Billion Plan Was Agreed On At the meeting in Quebec City, the two leaders accepted recommendations for a five-year, $5 billion program by governments and industries on both sides of the border that would develop new technologies to fight acid rain.</p>
        <p>At the time, critics here said that Mr. Mulroney had accepted a nebulous commitment to further research when what was needed was an immediate crackdown on smokestack industries.</p>
        <p>On learning of the Reagan budget allocation, Mr. Mulroney's chief aide for pollution matters, Environment Minister Thomas McMillan, told reporters that the Government would have to reassess its approach.</p>
        <p>Mr. McMillan was quoted as saying that Mr. Reagan's approach to the acid rain issue seemed to be ''theological,'' meaning not practical, and one that ''doesn't get us anywhere'' - much what the Government's critics have been saying all along. Closer Examination of Budget</p>
        <p>Mr. McMillan said he would reserve final judgment until officials had made a closer examination of the budget, which allocates the largest part of the acid rain money, $199 million, to the Department of Energy's program to develop cleaner ways of burning coal.</p>
        <p>Acid rain occurs when oxides of sulfur or nitrogen from the burning of fossil fuels combine with moisture in the atmosphere. Through chemical reactions, nitric or sulfuric acid is formed and falls to earth in rain, sleet, snow or mist. It can also fall in dry form.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, other political commentators have advised the Government here to recognize that it was duped in the 1986 accord.</p>
        <p>''The President has donned the blinkers he wore before last year's meeting,'' The Globe and Mail of Toronto said in an editorial. ''Clearly, there will be no real progress on acid rain until Mr. Reagan is put out to pasture.'' Tighter Emission Laws Sought</p>
        <p>Michael Perley, executive coordinator of the Canadian Coalition on Acid Rain, said Ottawa should return to its insistence, before Mr. Mulroney, that tighter emission laws be adopted by the United States.</p>
        <p>For the Government, the criticism comes at an inopportune time. Perhaps more than at any time in the last 20 years, political debate in Canada is centering on relations with the United States, with mounting charges from the opposition parties that Mr. Mulroney's Conservatives are leading the country into an unhealthy dependence on the good will of officials in Washington.</p>
        <p>Already there are strong signs that relations with the United States will play a central role in the next election, expected in 1988.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mulroney, whose standing in public-opinion polls has plummeted since winning a landslide in the 1984 vote that ousted the Liberal Government, is on the defensive on a variety of United States-Canada issues. Opposition leaders have taken to describing the Prime Minister as weak and credulous in his dealings with Washington.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
