<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A DOCTOR IN THE HOUSE: DIAGNOSING THE SOURCES OF DANGER</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="23909"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAZARDOUS AND TOXIC SUBSTANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADON GAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASBESTOS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW HAVEN (CONN)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">GESELL INSTITUTE FOR HUMAN DEVELOPMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PERCOSKI, BETSY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCLELLAN, ROBERT K (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SPECTOR, PAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/New Haven</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asbestos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870322T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7D61630F931A15750C0A961948260" item-length="1482" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A DOCTOR IN THE HOUSE: DIAGNOSING THE SOURCES OF DANGER</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BETSY PERCOSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PERCOSKI, BETSY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: JANE CROSS, her husband, Paul Spector, and their newborn daughter, Jessie, moved into a house on Goodrich Avenue in a quiet residential New Haven neighborhood last fall. From the outside, the house looked indestructible. Built of brick with slate covering the roof and the upper part of the second floor, the house resembles an English country cottage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: JANE CROSS, her husband, Paul Spector, and their newborn daughter, Jessie, moved into a house on Goodrich Avenue in a quiet residential New Haven neighborhood last fall. From the outside, the house looked indestructible. Built of brick with slate covering the roof and the upper part of the second floor, the house resembles an English country cottage.</p>
        <p>JANE CROSS, her husband, Paul Spector, and their newborn daughter, Jessie, moved into a house on Goodrich Avenue in a quiet residential New Haven neighborhood last fall. From the outside, the house looked indestructible. Built of brick with slate covering the roof and the upper part of the second floor, the house resembles an English country cottage.</p>
        <p>The house had been vacant for nearly two years, but was well cared for by the previous owners, said Dr. Cross. Painting, refinishing floors and making minor improvements were part of the couple's plan for their new home. They have now discovered that their circa 1920 house may have some built-in problems.</p>
        <p>Shortly after they moved in, a friend suggested to them that the insultation wrapped around water pipes throughout the basement and garage might be made of asbestos. Dr. Cross, a pediatrician, was aware of the danger of respiratory damage and the potential carcinogenic effects of asbestos. She and her husband decided to call Dr. Robert K. McLellan, an environmental-health expert at the Gesell Institute for Human Development in New Haven and an assistant clinical professor of occupational medicine at the Yale School of Medicine.</p>
        <p>Dr. McLellan has gone into the house call business, giving checkups to the houses while the owners stand by and watch. He started the service last December as an outgrowth of his practice in occupation and environmental health combined with family medicine.</p>
        <p>''I would see people here in my office who were chronically ill, and I realized that for medical reasons it was important to see where they were living,'' said Dr. McLellan. He said he is interested in the effect of environmental hazards on people. Most studies of these kinds of hazards have been confined to the workplace, he said. In the case of Dr. Cross and Mr. Spector, there was no history of chronic illness, but on a recent visit to their house, Dr. McLellan found a number of potentially hazardous conditions.</p>
        <p>He began the two-hour visit by taking a family history. Dr. Cross, who works part time, and Mr. Spector, a psychotherapist who has his office at home, both spend a large part of each day in their house. The more time spent in a house that has toxic hazards increases the potential for harm, said Dr. McLellan.</p>
        <p>Safe levels of exposure to many hazards are based on a worker's exposure to the substance, said Dr. McLellan. ''Levels are designed for healthy people exposed to material 40 hours a week, not 365 days a year and sometimes up to 24 hours a day,'' he said. At greatest risk are elderly people, pregnant women and children. The elderly are likely to spend more time indoors, children have lower tolerances for many substances and pregnant women risk passing toxicity to their unborn child, he said.</p>
        <p>After hearing no specific health complaints from Dr. Cross and Mr. Spector, Dr. McLellan began his inspection in the basement, an area often containing the most problems, he noted. This house was no exception.</p>
        <p>Asbestos, in the form of insulation, covered water lines. Painted white and in good condition, the asbestos could safely be left in place if it were not cut or disturbed in any way, Dr. McLellan said. Since the basement was not part of the family's living space, the hazard as it existed was minimal.</p>
        <p>However, recent work by a plumber had left asbestos filaments scattered on the floor. Dr. McLellan advised that the small particles could be safely removed with a wet mop. ''And then throw the mop away,'' he added. Sweeping or vacuuming would expose the person doing the work to the possibility of inhaling asbestos. Any break in the insulation that exposed asbestos to the air should be sealed with duct tape, he advised.</p>
        <p>''There is no safe threshold for asbestos,'' said Dr. McLellan. The State Department of Health Services considers anything more than 0.01 fibers per cubic centimeter in the air dangerous. The Environmental Protection Agency has not yet determined levels of safety of asbestos.</p>
        <p>When Dr. McLellan tests areas that may contain asbestos, he wears a disposable paper suit and mask. The procedure involves spraying a small area with water and scraping away a portion of the material for a test sample. The ''injury'' is then resealed with duct tape, he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. McLellan had recommended removing asbestos from the garage during his consultation, which was two months before his inspection. The work was performed by a company that specializes in asbestos removal, Dr. Cross said. ''They came in wearing outfits that looked like space suits, with masks,'' she said. ''They sealed off the garage from the house with sheets of plastic while they worked.'' The work, she said, cost $1,400.</p>
        <p>There are about 15 companies in the state who do such work. The Health Services Department has been trying to get legislation proposed to require licensing and training of companies that remove asbestos, according to Gregory Bonadies, an environmental official in the preventable diseases section of the department. Costs for work done in the home range from $1,500 to $2,500. The department offers to the public the names of contractors that meet qualifications for removing asbestos from state buildings.</p>
        <p>Dr. McLellan gave the house was given a clean bill of health for another potential health hazard - radon, which causes lung cancer. Radon meters, consisting of a thin plastic film that is left exposed to the air in the basement, showed no levels of radon. The Environmental Protection Agency has determined that anything more than four picocuries per liter in the air is dangerous.</p>
        <p>Radon is a colorless, odorless gas that filters into houses through basements. It can be present in water as well as air, but the greatest health risk comes from breathing it.</p>
        <p>''All the evidence to date shows we don't have reliable predictors of where radon will be a problem,'' said Dr. McLellan. For that reason, he said, it would not be unreasonable for every homeowner to have the air monitored for radon.</p>
        <p>Although the air in their house was free of radon, the New Haven family was being exposed to other air pollutants. Dr. McLellan found a damper system for the furnace that could allow combustion gases such as carbon dioxide, nitrogen dioxide and sulfur dioxide to be distributed through the house. He recommended a system that would bring fresh air from outside to eliminate the problem. Combustion gases, he said, irritate a person's respiratory system.</p>
        <p>A similar problem was found in the kitchen. Basements usually have the most problems, but kitchens can run a close second. Here he found an unvented gas-cooking stove that gave off the same kind of gases found in the basement.</p>
        <p>His tour of the kitchen included looking through household cleaning material stored in the cabinet under the sink. Common household cleaners present a toxic hazard to children.</p>
        <p>''When it comes to children, I don't even trust lucks for these kinds of materials,'' he said. This family rated fairly well, with an aerosol can of oven cleaner as the greatest danger. He recommended the cleaner be brought to a toxic-waste collection site.</p>
        <p>The inspection includes examination of the air-exchange devices such as furnaces, air-conditioning, humidifying or dehumidifying devices. He checks the area outside the house and asks about materials used on lawn and shrubbery. Water, if not from a public-water supply, is tested. If there is lead pipe, or extensive lead solder, the water is tested for lead.</p>
        <p>Furnishings are inspected as well. New furniture, rugs and wall coverings give off gases from volatile organic compounds such as formaldehyde, zylene and toluene. Foam-filled couches, bedding and pillows can harbor mold that triggers allergic reactions.</p>
        <p>The range of medical problems caused by environmental hazards in the home is far-reaching. They range from respiratory ailments, most commonly found in poorly ventilated buildings, such as irritated eye, nose and throat to more unusual complaints of ear infections, asthma and bronchitis. Dr. McLellan listed symptoms such as fatigue, headaches, inattentiveness and dermatitis as possible reactions to an unhealthy environment.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most dangerous are chronic and delayed reaction problems. Neurological damage from lead exposure, and the risk of cancer from exposure to radon, asbestos and chemicals in a water supply are among the problems Dr. McLellan said he hopes to eliminate with his house calls, which he and his staff make throughout the state. He said the evaluation makes the most sense for those with specific health concerns, but may be helpful for people who are worried about their houses.</p>
        <p>A consultation and evaluation cost of $200, and special testing - which includes tests of water from private wells - indicated from the consultation is billed separately. It is, the doctor said, ''good preventive health care.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
