<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Calvinism and the New Cigarette</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="77864"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">RJR NABISCO INC</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFD61438F934A1575AC0A961948260" item-length="497" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Calvinism and the New Cigarette</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Should smokers be allowed a less dangerous way to feed their nicotine addiction? Reactions from medical authorities to RJR Nabisco's virtually smokeless cigarette have ranged from skepticism to outright hostility. Antismoking groups are almost certain to challenge the company's right to market it without</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Should smokers be allowed a less dangerous way to feed their nicotine addiction? Reactions from medical authorities to RJR Nabisco's virtually smokeless cigarette have ranged from skepticism to outright hostility. Antismoking groups are almost certain to challenge the company's right to market it without</p>
        <p>Should smokers be allowed a less dangerous way to feed their nicotine addiction? Reactions from medical authorities to RJR Nabisco's virtually smokeless cigarette have ranged from skepticism to outright hostility. Antismoking groups are almost certain to challenge the company's right to market it without Government approval.</p>
        <p>It's easy to sympathize with the challengers, who fear that the new product will reduce smokers' incentives to quit. Quitting, after all, is the surest way to eliminate smoking's mortal risks. But there's another side to the argument: many addicts can't break the habit, even if stern Calvinists insist they must, and for them the low-smoke cigarette may be the soundest way to lessen the risks.</p>
        <p>Ordinary cigarette smoke contains nicotine and other chemicals that cause cancer and irreversible lung damage, and exacerbate heart disease. RJR's new product burns pure charcoal rather than tobacco, producing mostly carbon dioxide and water vapor. The smoker draws the relatively clean smoke through tobacco, a ''flavor capsule'' containing tobacco extract and flavorings and a filter made from tobacco. What the smoker inhales contains a dose of nicotine but no tobacco ''tar.''</p>
        <p>Nicotine and carbon monoxide from the burning charcoal put the smoker at higher risk of heart disease. The flavorings, not yet identified, may also prove carcinogenic. But the absence of tar probably reduces the danger of cancer and emphysema. The virtual absence of ash and secondary smoke should make the product less offensive and dangerous to nonsmokers. And the clever design of the cigarette should make it far less likely that a careless smoker will start a fire.</p>
        <p>These advantages pose a dilemma for Americans who dream of a smoke-free society.</p>
        <p>After decades of campaigning, smokers are on the defensive, smoking is in decline and the rights of nonsmokers are finally being recognized. A less dangerous cigarette could slow, perhap even reverse, these welcome, healthy trends. On the other hand, barring the sale of the new RJR product would condemn hard-core nicotine addicts and those who breathe their secondary smoke to the greater hazards of conventional cigarettes.</p>
        <p>Such dilemmas are not new to public health policy. The liberal use of antibiotics reduces the risk of bacterial infections in patients suffering from viral diseases, but encourages the spread of bacterial strains that are more resistant to drug treatment.</p>
        <p>Expedited approval of new prescription drugs can save lives, but increases the risk of belated discovery of grave side effects. Giving clean needles to heroin addicts could slow the spread of AIDS and hepatitis, but may encourage experimentation with drugs.</p>
        <p>In the case of the safer cigarette, it's not clear how to balance the interests. What is clear is that the competing interests exist, and that moralistic opposition to anything labeled tobacco cannot substitute for reasoned debate on how best to reduce nicotine addiction.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
