<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FLORIDA KEY DEER: ADAPTING OR DYING</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="43144"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FLORIDA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORDHEIMER, JON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDC143AF930A15756C0A961948260" item-length="856" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FLORIDA KEY DEER: ADAPTING OR DYING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON NORDHEIMER, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NORDHEIMER, JON</byline>
      <dateline>BIG PINE KEY, Fla.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Blondie and Skinny Minnie came first, scenting the air at the edge of the asphalt before crossing the street to the shade of Peg Riepe's beloved fig tree. Other buff-colored does follow, moving cautiously along a neighborhood street like house cats out for a stroll.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Blondie and Skinny Minnie came first, scenting the air at the edge of the asphalt before crossing the street to the shade of Peg Riepe's beloved fig tree. Other buff-colored does follow, moving cautiously along a neighborhood street like house cats out for a stroll.</p>
        <p>Blondie and Skinny Minnie came first, scenting the air at the edge of the asphalt before crossing the street to the shade of Peg Riepe's beloved fig tree. Other buff-colored does follow, moving cautiously along a neighborhood street like house cats out for a stroll.</p>
        <p>Instinctive caution mark deer, but it is not a reliable tool for the Florida Key deer, which is on the endangered species list. The herd of small white-tail deer, protected in the National Key Deer Refuge, which covers several islands along the lower Florida Keys, is dwindling under the pressures of encroaching civilization.</p>
        <p>Residential subdivisions on the edges of the refuge hold powerful attractions. Luscious ornamental plants can be nibbled. Garbage can lids can be dislodged by large wet noses. A carrot can be cadged with a flick of long-lashed eyelids.</p>
        <p>But some people have dogs. Worse, they have automobiles, and cars take a terrible toll of the Key deer, wiping out 20 percent of the herd every year, far more than are run down and killed by neighborhood dog packs. Deer Fell to 40 in 1954</p>
        <p>The refuge was created in 1954 after the deer population fell to 40 animals. By 1976, protected from hunters and land developers who had pre-empted and, in many cases, destroyed the small number of freshwater sources on the small islands ringed by the sea, the herd had grown to more than 400.</p>
        <p>Now the deer population has fallen to no more than 300, according to Deborah Holle, the refuge manager.</p>
        <p>Seventeen of the deer, which as adults reach a height of only 27 inches at the shoulder, have been killed by cars so far this year, including several pregnant does, according to Ms. Holle. Six others have died from other causes; three were brought down by dogs.</p>
        <p>''Let one dog get blood in his eye and the others will join in and chase down a deer and eat their insides out,'' said Mrs. Riepe, a resident of a subdivision on Big Pine Key, the largest of the 17 islands included in the refuge. ''Their screams are pitiful.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Riepe, a Big Pine resident for 17 years, fumes at what she calls the ''arrogance'' of newcomers who consider the deer a neighborhood pest that chew up their front yards.</p>
        <p>''Humans must learn they have moved into the deer's world, not the deer into theirs,'' she said one bright afternoon as the does nested in her yard, hopeful that Mrs. Riepe would violate the refuge's regulations that prohibit the feeding of a carrot.</p>
        <p>''I'm happy to share my banana tree or eggfruit tree or guava tree with them,'' she said. ''I figure the bottom of the tree as far as they can reach belongs to them and the top to us.''</p>
        <p>The land bridge that was wiped out 12 centuries ago by the rising sea has been replaced by U.S. 1, the Overseas Highway that runs 100 miles from the tip of the Florida peninsula down to Key West. Winter tourist traffic is so congested on the two-mile stretch of U.S. 1 where it crosses Big Pine Key that local residents want a parallel road to make moving around the small island easier. Deer-Lovers Favor New Road</p>
        <p>''Even people who love the deer feel they need this road and rationalize that if the herd drops to 200 or 150 it won't be too high a price to pay,'' Ms. Holle said. ''But the smaller a herd gets the smaller the gene pool gets and once you lose the genetic mix you get animals more susceptible to disease.</p>
        <p>''If we continue having 60 deer a year killed out of 300 we are already into no-growth. Any higher toll reduces the herd.''</p>
        <p>Lack of a large range and few freshwater supplies have probably promoted a natural selection that favored a small animal weighing no more than 55 or 60 pounds at maturity, less than one-third the bulk of a male buck in the northeastern United States.</p>
        <p>A fawn stays with a doe until rutting season when dominant bucks run off yearling males. Seeking new ranges, the yearlings test the frontiers of civilization, coming out of the mangrove-covered back country on Big Pine Key, where two-thirds of the herd lives, only to meet disaster on U.S. 1.</p>
        <p>''They're so naive and dumb, especially the little bucks,'' Ms. Holle said. ''If this new road goes through we'll look back on it in 10 years and say it was the beginning of the end for the Key deer, I'm afraid.''</p>
        <p>On Mrs. Riepe's street, in the shade of buttonwood and fig trees, the deer cannot contemplate an unhappy fate. Even Skinny Minnie, the name given to one of the does who survived a vicious dog attack a few years ago, looks serene on a gentle afternoon despite the severe throat wounds that left her unable to control a tongue that lolls slackly from a corner of her mouth.</p>
        <p>Her body, like that of Blondie, the dominant female, is thick with a fawn about to be born, and when her time comes she and the other does will give birth in some rough thicket far from the driveways and mailboxes.</p>
        <p>Sometime in the summer, when the rains come, they will emerge, tentatively at first, followed by the splinter-legged fawns, sniffing their way to Mrs. Riepe's trees, which will then be heavy with fruit, claiming their bottom half of the bounty, showing off their fawns, and perhaps cadging a carrot or two.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
