<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HISTORIC POWER PLANT REBORN AT THE GREAT FALLS IN PATERSON</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="53164"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HYDROELECTRIC POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PATERSON (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT FALLS (PASSAIC RIVER, NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NARVAEZ, ALFONSO A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydroelectric Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDB153AF933A05755C0A961948260" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HISTORIC POWER PLANT REBORN AT THE GREAT FALLS IN PATERSON</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALFONSO A. NARVAEZ, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NARVAEZ, ALFONSO A</byline>
      <dateline>PATERSON, N.J., June 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In 1791, Alexander Hamilton, the first Secretary of the Treasury of the fledgling United States of America, came here and decided to use the power of the Passaic River and its 70-foot drop over the Great Falls to develop the nation's first manufacturing center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In 1791, Alexander Hamilton, the first Secretary of the Treasury of the fledgling United States of America, came here and decided to use the power of the Passaic River and its 70-foot drop over the Great Falls to develop the nation's first manufacturing center.</p>
        <p>In 1791, Alexander Hamilton, the first Secretary of the Treasury of the fledgling United States of America, came here and decided to use the power of the Passaic River and its 70-foot drop over the Great Falls to develop the nation's first manufacturing center.</p>
        <p>He helped found the Society for Establishing Useful Manufactures, which sought to break the country's dependence on English manufacturing. It built canals and raceways to channel the river's force, and dozens of mills and factories powered by water wheels were built here and flourished for almost 100 years.</p>
        <p>This morning, with a statue of Hamilton overlooking the scene - along with dozens of schoolchildren and other spectators - government officials rededicated a refurbished hydroelectric generating plant meant to help ease the nation's dependence on foreign oil.</p>
        <p>''This is a very historic site,'' said John Tropalian, project manager for the $15 million Great Falls Hydroelectric Station. ''This is where the nation's economic base got started.'' Dormant Nearly 20 Years</p>
        <p>The plant, dormant for almost 20 years, can now generate up to 11,000 kilowatts of electricity, about one-third of the Paterson area's electricity needs. It was the oil crisis of the 1970's that gave rise to plans to rebuild the power plant, financed with a $1.3 million grant from the Federal Department of Energy and about $13 million in loans and private investments.</p>
        <p>Walter E. Leach, vice president of Independent Hydro Developers, the company that refurbished and will operate the plant, said the generating station was one of seven such plants already built. Another is under construction.</p>
        <p>The three 3,650-kilowatt generators, built by Allis-Chalmers, are installed in a structure built in 1914 to house electric generators capable of turning out 5,000 kilowatts of electricity. That generating plant was operated from 1914 to 1969, when the low cost of fossil fuels and the high cost of replacing aging equipment forced it to close.</p>
        <p>The electricity being produced is being sold to the Public Service Electric and Gas Company for transmission throughout North Jersey. Frederick R. Di Santi, senior vice president of the utility, called the plant ''a welcome addition to our system.'' He said the utility was paying about 6 cents for each kilowatt-hour of energy from the plant. Residential customers of the utility pay about 11 cents a kilowatt-hour at summer rates. Expanding Natural Resources</p>
        <p>State Senator Frank X. Graves Jr., a Democrat who is also Mayor of Paterson, hailed the restoration of the plant. ''We are rededicating ourselves to the principles our country was founded upon,'' he said. ''We are taking our natural resources and expanding them. And we can still enjoy what America is all about, the beauty of the falls.''</p>
        <p>Representative Robert A. Roe, Democrat of New Jersey, who said he fished in the river at the base of the falls as a boy, said the debate over protection for oil tankers in the Persian Gulf highlighted the fact that energy supplies remained one of the most crucial issues facing the nation.</p>
        <p>United States Senator Frank R. Lautenberg, a New Jersey Democrat who also grew up in the area, said Paterson was ''a representation of what America is all about,'' combining factories and a mix of immigrant groups to develop the economic base of the country.</p>
        <p>The hydroelectric plant, which is in the Great Falls Historic District, has been operating under test conditions since early this year. Today, because of the low level of the river, only one turbine was working.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
