<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MUSHROOM FARM REVIVED</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="11646"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSHROOMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW ENGLAND STATES (US)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FRANKLIN MUSHROOM FARM</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAMILTON, ROBERT A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MEYA, WILHELM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mushrooms</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5D91331F93BA35751C0A961948260" item-length="1262" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MUSHROOM FARM REVIVED</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert A. Hamilton</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAMILTON, ROBERT A</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: WHEN the Ralston Purina Corporation sold its mushroom farm in Franklin four years ago, it said it was getting out of the business because the Northeast market was oversupplied.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: WHEN the Ralston Purina Corporation sold its mushroom farm in Franklin four years ago, it said it was getting out of the business because the Northeast market was oversupplied.</p>
        <p>WHEN the Ralston Purina Corporation sold its mushroom farm in Franklin four years ago, it said it was getting out of the business because the Northeast market was oversupplied.</p>
        <p>But the group of local business people who took the plant over have carved out their own market, and in the process tripled production and more than doubled employment at the farm.</p>
        <p>Purina's problem, said Wilhelm W. Meya, the plant manager and one of the new owners, was that it canned a lot of its product, and shipped much of what was left to the Middle West. The company has its headquarters in St. Louis.</p>
        <p>''You're not going to make it unless you can sell your mushrooms on the fresh market,'' Mr. Meya said.</p>
        <p>The State Agriculture Commissioner, Kenneth B. Andersen, said his department often uses the mushroom farm as an example of how, with the proper management, farming can be viable in Connecticut.</p>
        <p>''There are good examples of the entrepreneurial spirit that has hit a lot of home runs in Connecticut,'' Mr. Andersen said. ''Everyone has been surprised at how well they've done.''</p>
        <p>Franklin Mushroom Farms is the only mushroom farm in the state, and the only one of its size in New England. And, said Mr. Meya, the market for Connecticut-grown mushrooms is just beginning to take off.</p>
        <p>''Per capita consumption of mushrooms in this country is still very low compared with a lot of other countries,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Americans each eat an average of 2.8 pounds of mushrooms a year, compared with 5.7 pounds in Canada and 6.8 pounds in Great Britain, Mr. Meya said.</p>
        <p>The mushroom farm, a sprawling seven-acre factory off Route 32 in the northern tip of the rural town of Franklin, was built in 1978 by Purina at a cost of $16 million.</p>
        <p>When Purina shipped most of its production to the Middle West, however, it had to compete with fresher, locally-grown mushrooms. Many of the mushrooms at that time also went into processing, but that sector of the business has since been dominated by Taiwan and China. Between 1978, when Purina opened the plant, and 1981, when the company put the farm up for sale, imports soared from 17,000 pounds to 27.4 million annually, and domestic producers say they cannot compete with the cheaper imports.</p>
        <p>In November of 1982, Purina cut production to 120,000 pounds a week, a third of the plant's capacity, and laid off half its 300 employees, then announced the plant was for sale.</p>
        <p>In early 1983, the plant was sold to a group of local businessmen, including Milton Jacobson, a lawyer from Norwich, Peter Matthews of Mystic, a financier, and Mr. Meya, a native of Austria who ran his family's mushroom farm there before coming to this country to take a job with Purina.</p>
        <p>Under the proper conditions, Mr. Meya said, a mushroom will double in size every day, and be market size a week from the time the mushrooms begin to show as tiny dots in the compost beds. But maintaining the proper conditions is difficult, requiring a lot of knowledge of mushrooms and a lot of expensive monitoring equipment, he added.</p>
        <p>Temperature and humidity, and the level of carbon dioxide and oxygen, must be carefully balanced. Conditions in each of the 45 growing rooms at the plant are controlled separately, to accommodate different growing needs during the various phases of growth.</p>
        <p>To avoid contamination, the plant is pressurized by fans blowing air into the building through a system of microfilters, so if there is an air leak in the building, air flows out, not in.</p>
        <p>Employment has climbed from 150 to 380 workers, and the plant produces 360,000 pounds of mushrooms a week, making it ''one of the most productive farms in all North America, when you compare pounds produced to man hours,'' Mr. Meya said.</p>
        <p>The reason for the turnaround has to do in part with the price the group paid for the plant, $2.4 million, versus the $16 million cost Purina incurred building it.</p>
        <p>But while the low initial price helped the company's profitability, Mr. Meya said, the success also is due to the fact that a small company is more suited to the running of an agricultural enterprise.</p>
        <p>''A large corporate structure likes to have pretty precise five-year forecasting,'' Mr. Meya said. But that is impossible with the mushroom, or any horticultural product, he said, because of the vagaries of weather, changing consumer tastes and other unpredictable factors that can cause a major market swing.</p>
        <p>The mushroom farm has also raised wages and increased benefits for its workers. ''They've got one of the best packages, maybe the best package, of any farm in the state,'' said Mr. Andersen.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meya said that to survive in the mushroom business, ''you have to produce at low cost, with high quality. And the product can only be improved if the morale and commitment of the work force is increased.''</p>
        <p>Turnover, which was running in excess of 10 percent a month under Purina, has dropped to almost nothing, he said.</p>
        <p>''We have a very stable work force, and the longer they're here, the better they know their jobs, and the better the product they turn out,'' Mr. Meya said.</p>
        <p>The farm also helped create a local market for the mushrooms. Mr. Meya convinced several supermarket chains to sell the mushrooms, and the farm sent food experts to the supermarkets to give demonstrations to shoppers on how to use the mushrooms in cooking or salads.</p>
        <p>The farm printed and distributed thousands of copies of ''Mushroom Facts,'' which give information on the fungus's nutritional value. Mushrooms have only 20 calories a cup, contain all nine amino acids essential for humans, have twice the protein content of asparagus and cabbage, and are a good source of vitamins B1, B2 and niacin.</p>
        <p>The fact that mushrooms are nutritional and low in calories has helped their sales in the health-conscious Northeast, Mr. Meya said.</p>
        <p>Franklin Mushroom Farms has also introduced some new mushrooms, such as oyster mushrooms, which have a flavor like wild mushrooms and are meatier than the popular white mushrooms, and shiitake mushrooms - a brown, capped fungus that has a woody taste and dense texture.</p>
        <p>Before long, Mr. Meya said, the farm will be selling crimini, an Italian mushroom with more flavor than the button mushroom.</p>
        <p>''The American consumer is getting more and more sophisiticated,'' Mr. Meya said. Americans ''travel more, see more, taste more, and when they come back to this country they want the same things.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Andersen said the state is ''always trying to retool our agricultural markets to aim at those new, up and coming markets, and the mushroom farm has set a shining example of how to do that.''</p>
        <p>Despite developing a better market for fresh mushrooms in Connecticut and surrounding states, however, the market is highly seasonal, so there are times when as much as 30 percent of the stock is surplus.</p>
        <p>Rather than can those mushrooms and compete with the lower-priced imports, the mushroom farm sells them flash blanched and frozen, a process in which they retain most of their nutrients and taste, or marinated, two styles that have become very popular among consumers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meya said he would like to see mushroom growers band together to push their products the way milk producers, raisin growers and other farm groups have.</p>
        <p>To that end, he has convinced 14 mushrooms farms representing 35 percent of national production to join the National Mushroom Growers Association, based in Chicago, to do cooperative marketing.</p>
        <p>''If the whole industry would be more serious and put more money behind it,'' Mr. Meya said, ''I think the whole industry would be in better shape.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
