<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Year Congress Stopped</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="103969"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0D7133DF931A15751C1A961948260" item-length="434" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Year Congress Stopped</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The first session of the 100th Congress raises the real possibility that one of these years, the national legislature may not simply adjourn for Christmas but actually grind to a halt. Consider the lawmakers' performance in the last few days. They had to pass a law to keep the Government functioning while they battled one more day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The first session of the 100th Congress raises the real possibility that one of these years, the national legislature may not simply adjourn for Christmas but actually grind to a halt. Consider the lawmakers' performance in the last few days. They had to pass a law to keep the Government functioning while they battled one more day.</p>
        <p>The first session of the 100th Congress raises the real possibility that one of these years, the national legislature may not simply adjourn for Christmas but actually grind to a halt. Consider the lawmakers' performance in the last few days. They had to pass a law to keep the Government functioning while they battled one more day. The next day they had to do it again.</p>
        <p>The session now ending will be remembered for its riveting televised inquiry into the Iran-contra scandal and hearings on Judge Robert Bork's nomination to the Supreme Court. The nation was well served by both. But when it came to legislating, the legislators seemed paralyzed. Even on the most critical task of the year, cutting the Federal budget deficit, the best they could do was to keep it from growing still bigger. Other priorities just collapsed.</p>
        <p>The Democrats controlled both houses this year, for the first time since 1980, with substantial majorities in each. Their leaders promised a return to caring government and fiscal responsibility. What emerged was partisan government and fiscal recklessness to match that of the President. It was a year of posturing and paralysis.</p>
        <p>Deficit reduction always hurts; no politician yearns to cut spending or raise taxes. But America's economic stability - indeed, the world's - depends in major part on substantial cuts in the mega-deficits wrought by President Reagan's fixation on cutting revenue while raising defense spending. The failure to make an adequate dent this year is all the more inexcusable given the stock market plunge in October. How loud must a warning be for Washington to hear it? The final money bills proceeded as if there had been no alarm at all. President and Congress alike still only pretend concern.</p>
        <p>After deficit reduction, this year's supposed priority was a foreign trade bill. The prolonged budget stalemate preoccupied key members of both houses, so a reconciliation of protectionist Senate and House bills was postponed to next year. A badly needed housing bill, the first in seven years, was killed by the Senate, and other important legislation just stalled - including welfare reform, a plan for catastrophic-illness health insurance and a program to deal with acid rain.</p>
        <p>There's no reason to think that the 1988 session will do better. The only cheerful prospect is that it will be shorter. Were it not for Christmas, this year's battles might rage on. Next year, with an election in November, the members are likely to hurry to get done in time for something that really matters - getting re-elected to do the jobs they aren't doing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
