<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ANSWERS TO QUIZ</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="50" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="4280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">QUESTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEED7153CF934A25752C0A961948260" item-length="278" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ANSWERS TO QUIZ</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Questions appear on page 12. 1. Hans-Dietrich Genscher is the Foreign Minister of West Germany. 2. 4. 3. Staff members of The New Yorker asked Robert A. Gottleib, editor in chief of Alfred A. Knopf, to withdraw his recent acceptance of the editorship of the magazine. 4. The Meadowlands area of New Jersey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Questions appear on page 12. 1. Hans-Dietrich Genscher is the Foreign Minister of West Germany. 2. 4. 3. Staff members of The New Yorker asked Robert A. Gottleib, editor in chief of Alfred A. Knopf, to withdraw his recent acceptance of the editorship of the magazine. 4. The Meadowlands area of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Questions appear on page 12. 1. Hans-Dietrich Genscher is the Foreign Minister of West Germany. 2. 4. 3. Staff members of The New Yorker asked Robert A. Gottleib, editor in chief of Alfred A. Knopf, to withdraw his recent acceptance of the editorship of the magazine. 4. The Meadowlands area of New Jersey. 5. The board of CBS Inc. unanimously elected William S. Paley as chairman and Laurence A. Tisch as president and chief executive. Both men held the positions on a temporary basis since September, when they teamed up to oust Thomas H. Wyman, who had held all three positions. 6. The Polish leader, Gen. Wojciech Jaruzelski. 7. More likely. 8. Liberia. 9. Queen Elizabeth II's youngest son, Prince Edward, quit the Royal Marines, breaking a century-old tradition of British princes' serving tours of duty in the armed forces. 10. Washington Square Park. 11. Pregnant women were banned after a study found a sharply higher incidence of miscarriages among workers who produce computer chips. 12. Prenatal brain abnormalities. 13. Najib, the Afghan leader, appealed for support for a cease-fire with Moscow. 14. The title of press secretary will continue to be held by James S. Brady, who was disabled in the 1981 assassination attempt on President Reagan. 15. ''The Bell Jar,'' by Sylvia Plath. 16. Japan. 17. Lewis Lloyd and Mitchell Wiggins of the Houston Rockets were expelled after testing positive for cocaine. 18. It is hoped that the lower dollar will bring some improvement to the nation's trade deficit. 19. A statement by Jewish leaders in the United States that criticized several aspects of his Middle East trip. 20. Ring Lardner Jr. 21. Acid rain.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
