<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stage: By Durang, 'Laughing Wild'</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="92096"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RICH, FRANK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DURANG, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LAUGHING WILD (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEED7163EF931A25752C1A961948260" item-length="1060" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stage: By Durang, 'Laughing Wild'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK RICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RICH, FRANK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: JACKIE MASON puts theatergoers in a laughing mood by reassuring them that they will get no ''theater'' in his show - just jokes, lots of them, that circumscribe the world according to the comedian at center stage. Although Christopher Durang's new comedy at Playwrights Horizons is mostly in the form of stand-up monologues and might also be titled ''The World According to Me!,'' the laughter does not come nearly so easily.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: JACKIE MASON puts theatergoers in a laughing mood by reassuring them that they will get no ''theater'' in his show - just jokes, lots of them, that circumscribe the world according to the comedian at center stage. Although Christopher Durang's new comedy at Playwrights Horizons is mostly in the form of stand-up monologues and might also be titled ''The World According to Me!,'' the laughter does not come nearly so easily.</p>
        <p>JACKIE MASON puts theatergoers in a laughing mood by reassuring them that they will get no ''theater'' in his show - just jokes, lots of them, that circumscribe the world according to the comedian at center stage. Although Christopher Durang's new comedy at Playwrights Horizons is mostly in the form of stand-up monologues and might also be titled ''The World According to Me!,'' the laughter does not come nearly so easily. Mr. Durang, as funny a writer as Mr. Mason or nearly anyone else, is determined to give us his free-associative comic riffs in the more pretentious form of A Play. The evening's actual title, ''Laughing Wild,'' is a reference to Samuel Beckett's ''Happy Days'' - and, Mr. Durang's past ribbing of Beckett notwithstanding, that is not necessarily a joke.</p>
        <p>In Act I, two characters known only as Woman and Man appear successively - and in vaguely ''Endgame''-like surroundings - to address the audience on the subject of life. The woman, a chic and mesmerizing figure in the performance of E. Katherine Kerr, says she is a sometime Creedmore patient, but her madness often seems a function of the same pet peeves that inform so many New York comedy-club routines - surly taxi drivers, street musicians, talk-show hosts like Sally Jessy Raphael. When Mr. Durang, playing the man, delivers his monologue, the comic targets become even more reassuringly familiar, at least to fans of the writer's previous work. He asks the audience, much as his characters once demanded of Sister Mary Ignatius, how an ostensibly just God would allow the nuclear catastrophe at Chernobyl and the persecution of homosexuals.</p>
        <p>At their liveliest, the monologues offer splenetic laughter, imaginatively induced. Mr. Durang remains a master at framing metaphysical conundrums in the terms of pop-culture kitsch. Ms. Kerr's entire existential terror is at one point telescoped into a fantasy about what might happen to the poor soul who found himself a partner to a self-promoting Dr. Ruth Westheimer on the television game show ''Password.'' (And you can be sure that Mr. Durang, a stickler for satirical detail, knows the actual ''Password'' rules as well as he does the catechism.) When, in his monologue, the playwright patiently tries to apply Old Testament logic to the derivation of AIDS, the black humor achieves a mean political edge that is absent in the play's more juvenile shock effects, such as its wisecracks about Mother Teresa, and in its pro forma, if trendy, one-liners about Westway, nuclear waste and the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Among the other jokes, the smartest probe subjects as varied as Strindberg, alliteratively named television stars, the decorative esthetics of semen and the piety of Tony Award winners. But the humor is not continuous, as it was when Mr. Durang and Sigourney Weaver did their free-wheeling stand-up revue ''Das Lusitania Songspiel.'' In the interests of theater, the diverse topics of ''Laughing Wild'' are yoked together by the invocation of larger themes, and finally the characters are brought together, too, for a second act whose hilarious high points are revealingly executed by the designers, Thomas Lynch (sets) and William Ivey Long (costumes), rather than the performers.</p>
        <p>Given the speed and polish of Ron Lagomarsino's staging, the ostensibly unifying trappings would carry us from laugh to laugh if they had real emotional, dramatic or intellectual weight. Because they don't, they slow the evening down instead. Like the protagonists in so many past Durang plays, the characters of ''Laughing Wild'' are trying to dispose of their underlying ontological rage -whether aimed at God, parents or authority figures of church and state -so they can relieve their anxiety and resume living with some modicum of hope. This time their methods of self-purgation are far from gripping.</p>
        <p>The woman at first takes a cue from Winnie in ''Happy Days'' by ''laughing wild amid severest woe'' - she breaks periodically into startling guffaws recalling the whinnies of the ''Equus''-fixated psychiatrist in Mr. Durang's ''Beyond Therapy.'' The man, who presents himself as a proselytizing lecturer, initially purports to have suppressed his ''negative'' feelings by subscribing to an est-like ''personality workshop.'' When the woman and man meet in a phantasmagoric series of sloppily overlapping dreams in Act II, they defray more of their anger with guns (another tired Durang ploy) before finding true peace in a sentimental denouement worthy of ''Barefoot in the Park,'' or perhaps the Shirley MacLaine spiritual manifestos that the author otherwise mocks.</p>
        <p>According to the Playbill, Mr. Durang wrote ''Laughing Wild'' for Ms. Kerr, and one can see why. This actress delivers her most hostile lines (''I wish I'd been killed when I was a fetus'') with a savage, taunting bark that might make Elaine Stritch seem like a Pollyanna. Ms. Kerr also enjoys riding Mr. Durang's lightning-fast transitions in tone to create the Sister Maryesque aura of danger exuded by a crazy woman who retains her intelligence and wit. That her descents into tearfully ''sad longing'' are convincing yet unmoving says much about how unearned they are in the script.</p>
        <p>Mr. Durang's own acting does not serve his writing so ably. When, in the man's Act I monologue, he announces that he has changed his life through positive thinking, the playwright's winking delivery makes it clear that he is even less convinced by what he's saying than his self-doubting character is. The performance has the air of a put-on, which adds another level of archness to a work that itself seems like an elaborate put-on intended to justify the theatricality of a hit-and-miss collection of comedy routines. If Mr. Durang had only written more jokes and fewer rationalizations for them, the audience would be laughing much too hard to ask or care whether ''Laughing Wild'' is a play.  Self-Purgation</p>
        <p>LAUGHING WILD, by Christopher Durang; directed by Ron Lagomarsino; set design by Thomas Lynch; costume design by William Ivey Long; lighting design by Arden Fingerhut; sound design by Stan Metelits; production manager, Carl Mulert; production stage manager, M. A. Howard. Presented by Playwrights Horizons, Andre Bishop, artistic director; Paul S. Daniels, executive director. At 416 West 42d Street.  WITH: E. Katherine Kerr and Mr. Durang</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
