<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TOY GUNS: A REAL AND GROWING PROBLEM FOR POLICE</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="6997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TOYS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIREARMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BISHOP, KATHERINE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE6D8133FF936A15752C0A961948260" item-length="1153" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TOY GUNS: A REAL AND GROWING PROBLEM FOR POLICE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHERINE BISHOP, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BISHOP, KATHERINE</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO Jan. 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Just after midnight over the school holidays last month, three San Francisco police officers responded to a silent alarm indicating that someone had entered a local high school. A few minutes later a 15-year-old high school student lay dying in a darkened hallway, shot by one of the officers, who had seen the youth pointing a gun at him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Just after midnight over the school holidays last month, three San Francisco police officers responded to a silent alarm indicating that someone had entered a local high school. A few minutes later a 15-year-old high school student lay dying in a darkened hallway, shot by one of the officers, who had seen the youth pointing a gun at him.</p>
        <p>Just after midnight over the school holidays last month, three San Francisco police officers responded to a silent alarm indicating that someone had entered a local high school. A few minutes later a 15-year-old high school student lay dying in a darkened hallway, shot by one of the officers, who had seen the youth pointing a gun at him.</p>
        <p>What the teen-ager was armed with turned out to be a pellet gun that was also a highly realistic reproduction of a .357 Magnum Colt Python pistol.</p>
        <p>The gun, which is capable of shooting small pointed lead pellets powered by a carbon dioxide cartridge, was one of the more powerful such guns and could have caused an injury if the pellet struck someone in the face or eye, the police said. But it was not nearly so powerful as the .357 Magnum, one of the deadliest of pistols. A New Generation of Toy Guns</p>
        <p>While it is illegal to sell or possess a pellet gun in San Francisco, such guns, as well as toy guns, have been used in crimes for years. But now a new generation of nonlethal guns that closely resemble real pistols and submachine guns is causing rising alarm among law-enforcement officials.</p>
        <p>The incident last month, which apparently involved stealing from the school's vending machines, is still under investigation. It is the most recent in what the police say are a growing number of incidents involving look-alike guns that cannot readily be distinguished from the real thing, even by experienced police officers.</p>
        <p>In New York City, about a dozen such look-alike guns have been recovered annually since 1984 in incidents involving assaults on police officers alone, a Police Department spokesman said.</p>
        <p>Often the use of such guns is associated not with the commission of a crime but with a prank, horseplay or thoughtless brandishing in public. Bright Yellow Paint Proposed</p>
        <p>For example, earlier this month police officers in Santa Cruz, Calif., fired at a man brandishing what turned out to be a toy pistol, and officers are increasingly stopping people carrying such guns, Deputy Police Chief Steven Belcher said.</p>
        <p>In Virginia, Judge Robert T. S. Colby of State District Court has begun a campaign aimed at passage of a state law that would require all reproductions of guns to be painted bright yellow. Judge Colby said he began the action because in the last month he had three cases involving look-alike guns, which the toy industry calls replica guns.</p>
        <p>In one case, a police officer nearly shot a young man who pointed what appeared to be a .22-caliber Luger at him. When the man was subdued, he was found to be carrying a plastic toy pistol.</p>
        <p>''I see it as a gigantic problem.'' Judge Colby said. ''We're going to kill innocent people and absolutely jeopardize officers' lives.''</p>
        <p>''We're very much aware that it is a national problem,'' said Jerald Vaugh, executive director of the International Association of Chiefs of Police, which is based in Alexandria, Va. He said that ''the toy is treated exactly as the real thing'' when police officers are called in such incidents, adding, ''It's a potential disaster waiting to happen.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Vaugh mentioned a recent incident in Washington in which a man was seen entering a bank with what appeared to be a Uzi submachine gun. It turned out to be a cap-firing toy that had been taken to work by a bank employee as an office prank.</p>
        <p>Although no one was injured, Mr. Vaugh said the incident ''could have resulted in a tragic outcome.''</p>
        <p>While most look-alike guns are made in Japan, some water guns that resemble submachine guns are produced in the United States.</p>
        <p>Jodi Levin, a spokesman for the Toy Manufacturers of America, a trade organization representing 240 manufacturers responsible for 90 percent of retail toy sales nationwide, said the group had no policy on look-alike guns. Military Assault Weapons</p>
        <p>Police Chief Joseph D. McNamara of San Jose, Calif., said the problem was exacerbated by the fact that realistic-looking reproductions and toys had become increasingly popular at the same time that a proliferation of military assault weapons used by drug dealers, in addition to acts of random violence, had heightened the apprehensiveness of the public and the police.</p>
        <p>Eighteen months ago a toy Uzi submachine gun figured in an incident in Larkspur, Calif., 15 miles north of here. Security guards at a shopping center called the police when they saw a young man who they said was carrying a Uzi. Police officials confiscated the toy from its 18-year-old owner.</p>
        <p>Michael Murray, manager of Games and Things, a store that sells toys for adults where the $175 toy Uzi was purchased, said the gun was a popular ''adult make-believe item.''</p>
        <p>He said the store had a policy against selling such guns to minors. Since the incident, he added, adults who purchased the guns are cautioned against brandishing them in public.</p>
        <p>And labels now warn buyers that the toy guns may be mistaken for a real gun, Mr. Murray said, One company that has dropped the toy Uzi but continues to sell other toy guns is Sharper Image, a San Francisco-based chain selling high-quality merchandise for business executives through 29 retail outlets around the country. In addition, it has a monthly catalogue that is sent to three million people.</p>
        <p>Richard Thalheimer, the company's president, said the stores sold hundreds of cap-firing toy Uzis every month, but the item was removed from the catalogue last September after the company received letters from ''an intelligent and vocal minority'' of catalogue readers opposed to its sale. 'Exactly Like a Real Uzi'</p>
        <p>The toy, which could be purchased in a kit or fully assembled, was advertised as having metal parts ''exactly like a real Uzi'' to simulate the feel and sound of the real thing. The advertisement said, ''Even a battle-tested Israeli soldier might mistake this new Uzi replica for the real gun.''</p>
        <p>Asked who purchased such toys, Mr. Thalheimer said they ''appealed to an extreme type of customer a little overly gun happy'' and to people ''who appreciate the history of firearms.''</p>
        <p>Sharper Image has also sold the Water Warrior, a water gun made to look like an M-16 automatic rifle, and now sells a similar toy modeled after a Baretta submachine gun. Mr. Thalheimer said the chances were slim that it could be mistaken for a real gun.</p>
        <p>But in an incident in Los Angeles last year, a 14-year-old boy shooting a water ''machine gun'' off the roof of a downtown building brought police officers with guns drawn.</p>
        <p>Art Agnos, a California Assemblyman from San Francisco, said he recently began asking toy manufacturers for ideas to solve the problem. He said he became interested when he carried a toy water rifle to a committee meeting to demonstrate a point he was trying to make in favor of the outlawing of military assault weapons.</p>
        <p>''The members of the Ways and Means Committee of the State Legislature thought it was real,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
