<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HINTS OF MORE CLOUDINESS SPUR GLOBAL STUDY</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="53109"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLOUDS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GLEICK, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, STEPHEN H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEEDD1F3BF933A05755C0A961948260" item-length="1330" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HINTS OF MORE CLOUDINESS SPUR GLOBAL STUDY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES GLEICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GLEICK, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: AS human activity accelerates a global warming of the atmosphere, some scientists are beginning to suspect that the earth may already be responding with a built-in safety mechanism of its own: clouds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: AS human activity accelerates a global warming of the atmosphere, some scientists are beginning to suspect that the earth may already be responding with a built-in safety mechanism of its own: clouds.</p>
        <p>AS human activity accelerates a global warming of the atmosphere, some scientists are beginning to suspect that the earth may already be responding with a built-in safety mechanism of its own: clouds.</p>
        <p>Scientists in the United States and Britain calculate that the globe could be regulating its temperature through a ''planetary thermostat,'' an intricate feedback loop involving atmospheric gases, oceanic plankton and the formation of clouds.</p>
        <p>Wispy and volatile as they are, clouds have been a notoriously elusive piece of the climate puzzle, even in an era of satellites monitoring the entire globe. By reflecting sunlight before it can warm the earth's surface, they strongly influence the global balance of incoming and outgoing heat.</p>
        <p>''The clouds are the shades - they're the blinds,'' said Stephen Schneider, a climate specialist at the National Center for Atmospheric Research. ''It's a very, very difficult thing to monitor because it's so highly variable. Yet I can't think of a more important variable if you want to know what the climate's doing, other than the thermometer itself.''</p>
        <p>Because reliable cloud measurements are scarce, scientific agencies worldwide are stepping up the pace of an international series of cloud experiments.</p>
        <p>American researchers yesterday began a program to analyze low-level sea clouds off the coast of California with a combination of satellites, aircraft and earthbound observers. Europeans are starting an International Cirrus Experiment to study higher-altitude clouds, and the Japanese will begin a complementary program early next year.</p>
        <p>''We know that mankind is busy perturbing the system,'' said William Rossow of the Goddard Institute for Space Studies in New York, which is coordinating data from the long-term International Satellite Cloud Climatology Project. ''What we don't know is how big the response is going to be.''</p>
        <p>Although the data are fragmentary and far from conclusive, some isolate pieces of research already suggest a growing cloudiness of the kind that could alter climate patterns, darkening skies and dampening spirits. One new survey of records from 45 American cities finds evidence that all but one grew cloudier in the second half of this century.</p>
        <p>A variety of regional studies had found increasing cloudiness, but the survey of 45 cities is the first to uncover a nationwide trend. It was carried out by William L. Seaver of Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University and James E. Lee of the Mitre Corporation, a nonprofit research group in McLean, Va.</p>
        <p>They used data collected by National Weather Service observers, trained to look at the sky and write down a percentage of cloud cover. From 1900 to 1936, the Department of Agriculture compiled statistics on cloudless days each month for different cities, and the Virginia researchers compared that data with the period since 1950. 'The Question Now Is Why'</p>
        <p>Only Fort Worth, Tex., had more cloudless days, 7.5 a month instead of 7.4. The 44 other cities had fewer; New York, for example, had 3.7, compared with 4.5 in the first part of the century. Why Fort Worth bucked the trend, no one knows.</p>
        <p>The cloudless-day figures are a one-dimensional way of measuring a complicated phenomenon - they say nothing, for example, about total cloud area, or total reflectivity. And the researchers do not know whether the trend is steady or highly variable. But so far the survey is the only nationwide record of cloudiness over a period of more than a few years.</p>
        <p>''Nobody had tried to tackle it from a total U.S. perspective,'' Dr. Seaver said. ''The question now is why and how it's come about.''</p>
        <p>The researchers and other climatologists have speculated about such influences as industrial pollution and exhaust from aircraft - both sources of particles that can promote the formation of cloud droplets.</p>
        <p>Other scientists, however, have focused on the earth's warming as they become increasingly concerned about the greenhouse effect, the trapping of energy by carbon dioxide and a variety of manmade gases building up in the atmosphere. The dynamics of the greenhouse effect are much modeled and little understood.</p>
        <p>Atmospheric scientists using computers to predict climate trends have rarely succeeded in taking account of the role of life itself. That was the goal of the researchers who put forward the new feedback idea in the journal Nature: Robert J. Charlson and Stephen G. Warren of the University of Washington, Meinrat O. Andreae of Florida State University, and James E. Lovelock of the Coombe Mill Experimental Station in Launceston, England.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lovelock is the author of the Gaia hypothesis, the theory that life on earth has collaborated over billions of years to establish and maintain the conditions needed for its existence. The Gaia hypothesis - sometimes tinged with mystical notions of purposefulness - is scientifically controversial, but it has called attention to the ways organisms as small as bacteria can cause changes in climate on a global scale.</p>
        <p>''Even if the whole Gaia hypothesis is totally wrong, it has brought forward some very useful thinking about how the whole system is woven together,'' Dr. Charlson said. ''It is clear that the factors that control climate are more complex than the modelers have heretofore believed.''</p>
        <p>The key actors in the new feedback calculations are tiny plankton -algae floating in vast numbers near the ocean surface. The researchers believe, although it has not been clearly established, that warmth may encourage the plankton's growth. Formation of Particles</p>
        <p>The plankton emit a sulfurous gas, dimethylsulfide. When it reaches the atmosphere, it reacts with oxygen to form aerosols, particles in the air. The particles, according to the new hypothesis, serve as seeds for cloud droplets, which then reflect the sun's radiation back out to space.</p>
        <p>Clouds form when upwelling air expands and cools, increasing the relative humidity. If particles are present to act as seeds, the excess moisture condenses around them as cloud droplets.</p>
        <p>''Global climate is quite sensitive to the population of these particles,'' Dr. Charlson said. ''I believe that we have identified an important missing piece of the overall climate puzzle.''</p>
        <p>Whether the planet contains its own means of slowing a warming trend that humanity has begun remains far from certain. The researchers acknowledge that no data on the area or reflectivity of the global cloud cover are available to test any theory about long-term cloud trends. This is a gap that the international satellite programs hope to fill.</p>
        <p>One problem is that clouds are persistently three-dimensional and layered, making quantitative measurements quite tricky. ''The satellite perspective only gives you a top-down view,'' said James Coakley of the National Center for Atmospheric Research, who is working on the California field experiment that got under way yesterday. ''We're only now learning how to interpret the satellite data, but there's been a big blossoming of activity in this area.''</p>
        <p>Most photographs of cloud cover taken by satellites are composed of picture elements three to six miles, which means that the satellites cannot tell whether clouds are solid or broken up on smaller scales. The field experiment is meant to provide resolution on the order of 100 feet. 'The Basic Dilemma'</p>
        <p>The relationship of droplet size to reflectivity is another variable that is hard to pin down. And clouds, especially when they are deep and thick, also serve as a blanket, holding in infrared radiation that would otherwise escape. Climatologists need to calculate that secondary warming effect along with the primary cooling effect.</p>
        <p>''If you just look at a cloud, you see rapid time variations and very complex spatial structures,'' Dr. Rossow said. ''We don't know how to add up to the larger scale of the atmospheric climate system all of that inhomogeneity and variability. That's the basic dilemma.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
