<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEITHER LIQUID NOR GAS, ODD SUBSTANCES FIND USES</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="41917"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMISTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUPERCRITICAL FLUIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5DD1331F93AA25756C0A961948260" item-length="1527" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEITHER LIQUID NOR GAS, ODD SUBSTANCES FIND USES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A BIZARRE form of matter distinct from the solids, liquids and gases that make up the everyday world may soon lead to radical improvements in products as varied as plastics and potato chips, scientists predict.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A BIZARRE form of matter distinct from the solids, liquids and gases that make up the everyday world may soon lead to radical improvements in products as varied as plastics and potato chips, scientists predict.</p>
        <p>A BIZARRE form of matter distinct from the solids, liquids and gases that make up the everyday world may soon lead to radical improvements in products as varied as plastics and potato chips, scientists predict.</p>
        <p>Among the prospects are oil-free potato chips that even dieters can eat, tastier decaffeinated coffee, odorless fish oil and new ways of analyzing chemicals without destroying unstable molecules.</p>
        <p>The class of matter, called supercritical fluid, was discovered in 1822 by the French scientist Charles Cagniard de la Tour. Only recently, however, have scientists and engineers recognized important uses to which supercritical fluids may be put. In January, Americans got their first taste of a food product manufactured using a supercritical fluid, when a new type of caffeine-free coffee went on the market. Supercritical fluids are likely to figure soon in the production of chemicals, pharmaceuticals and other foods. They are already applied in an important type of chemical analysis called chromatography.</p>
        <p>Most substances are solids at low temperatures, liquids at intermediate temperatures and gases at high temperatures. With increasing temperature, water, for example, changes from crystalline ice to liquid water to steam. But when a substance is subjected to a sufficiently high pressure and temperature, it is converted into something that does not ordinarily exist on the surface of the earth: a supercritical fluid, intermediate in its properties between a liquid and a gas. (Supercritical fluids probably exist deep in the earth's interior and on some large planets.) Like a gas, a supercritical fluid expands to fill its container and permeate everything in the container. But like a liquid, a supercritical fluid can dissolve solids, including even such substances as salt. By very carefully controlling the composition, pressure and temperature of a supercritical fluid in which some solid is immersed, a skillful chemist can extract a single component from the solid without dissolving the rest of it.</p>
        <p>At the University of Maine at Orono, Erdogan Kiran, a professor of chemical engineering, has designed a special high-pressure chamber in which the strange behavior of supercritical fluids is directly visible. The apparatus is made of thick steel capable of withstanding pressures up to 1,000 times that of the atmosphere, or roughly 500 times the pressure of air in an automobile tire. The test chamber, Dr. Kiran said in an interview, is fitted with windows made of half-inch-thick blocks of colorless synthetic sapphire, one of the hardest materials known. 'A Wonderful Thing to Watch'</p>
        <p>Using the pressure cell, Dr. Kiran's group has experimented with dissolving such plastics as polystyrene in supercritical fluids.</p>
        <p>''It's a wonderful thing to watch,'' he said in an interview. ''You can see a chunk of styrene inside the cell when you begin, but as you increase the temperature and pressure of the invisible supercritical fluid in the cell, the appearance of the plastic changes. The visible outline of the chunk disappears, and the supercritical fluid in which the plastic is dissolving turns brilliant colors - reds and yellows, for the most part.</p>
        <p>''When the temperature and pressure are lowered to allow the supercritical fluid to revert to an ordinary gas, the plastic dissolved in it reappears in the form of particles so fine that the gas turns dense, opaque black in color,'' he said. The particles eventually precipitate out.</p>
        <p>The object of Dr. Kiran's research is to discover a practical and cheap method for dissolving and separating the main components of wood - cellulose, hemicellulose and lignin. Such a process would not only benefit pulp and paper producers but would also produce the chemicals essential to making the polymer materials used for plastic implements and textiles. Success would have such far-reaching industrial consequences that Dr. Kiran's project became the first ''high-risk high-return innovative research program'' ever financed by the National Science Foundation.</p>
        <p>''Our success in this research effort,'' Dr. Kiran said, ''has the potential of revolutionizing the whole pulp and paper industry and opening up new directions in polymer science and chemical processing.'' Solvents for Many Applications</p>
        <p>Many substances, including water itself (which becomes a supercritical fluid at temperatures above 705 degrees Fahrenheit and pressures above 218 atmospheres) can be used as supercritical solvents. But at very high temperatures many chemical molecules break down, and researchers must pick a supercritical fluid that will not destroy the molecules it is intended to dissolve. Supercritical water is hot enough to set fire to paper or wood.</p>
        <p>A more practical solvent for many applications is supercritical fluid carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>At room temperature and pressure, carbon dioxide is a common gas; it is a waste product exhaled by all animals. At atmospheric pressure, carbon dioxide becomes a solid (dry ice) when chilled below minus 109 degrees Fahrenheit. At a temperature of minus 134 degrees and a pressure 5.1 times that of the atmosphere, carbon dioxide is at its so-called ''triple point'' a state at which the solid, liquid and gaseous forms of the substance can coexist in equilibrium.</p>
        <p>But at a temperature of 88 degrees Fahrenheit and a pressure of 73 atmospheres, carbon dioxide becomes a supercritical fluid capable of dissolving a variety of chemicals, including the white crystalline substance known as caffeine. This fact has been turned to profit by coffee producers; raw, moist coffee beans are immersed in supercritical fluid carbon dioxide which penetrates the beans, dissolving and extracting the caffeine. When the supercritical fluid is pumped away, the coffee beans are left free of both caffeine and solvent residue, since residual carbon dioxide, a gas at ordinary temperatures and pressures, immediately disperses. Decaffeination Process</p>
        <p>Supercritical carbon dioxide decaffeination is the basis of a process invented in West Germany for the Kaffee-HAG company, which was acquired in 1979 by the General Foods Corporation. Since the beginning of this year, General Foods' Sanka brand coffee has been decaffeinated in West Germany using supercritical fluid carbon dioxide as the extracting solvent. The decaffeinated raw beans are shipped to the United States for roasting and further processing.</p>
        <p>Unlike water and other common solvents, supercritical carbon dioxide fluid dissolves only caffeine from the coffee, leaving largely undissolved the chemicals that give coffee its characteristic flavor and smell; these are left to the consumer to extract from the grounds using hot water. General Foods contends that major advantages of the method are that it is economical, it preserves the taste of regular coffee and it leaves no solvent residue. In addition, animals studies have implicated one of the chemical solvents traditionally used to decaffeinate coffee, methylene chloride, as a carcinogen at high doses.</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Kiran, who participated in a recent symposium in West Germany on applications of supercritical technology, several food products will soon be treated with supercritical fluids. Japanese manufacturers, for example, have built an experimental plant for treating fish oil with supercritical fluids to remove odors and flavors, he said. Other entrepreneurs are thinking about deodorizing vegetable oils using supercritical solvents.</p>
        <p>''There is a proposal,'' Dr. Kiran said, ''to use supercritical fluids to extract cooking oil from potato chips. That would leave a crisp, oil-free chip. Supercritical solvents will also be useful for manufacturing hormones and other biological chemicals and pharmaceuticals that must be exceptionally pure.'' Analytical Uses</p>
        <p>Milton L. Lee, a professor of chemistry at Brigham Young University at Provo, Utah, believes that supercritical fluids also have an important future in the laboratory itself as solvents used in chromatographic chemical analysis.</p>
        <p>In chromatographic analysis, the substance to be analyzed is dispersed in a gas or liquid and forced through a thin tube packed with an absorbent material. The larger molecules in the unknown substance pass through the packed tube more slowly than the smaller molecules, and this difference in speeds spreads out the various chemical components so that they can be measured separately.</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Lee, supercritical fluids have begun to replace conventional gases and liquids in some applications of chromatographic chemical analysis. The use of supercritical fluids as analytical solvents, he said, avoids breaking down unstable molecules that would be destroyed by conventional analysis. The technique works especially well in analyses for certain antibiotics, pesticides, narcotics and organic poisons.</p>
        <p>''Although supercritical fluids have been known for a long time,'' he said, ''the expense and difficulty of building high-pressure equipment to handle them has impeded their scientific and industrial exploitation. But it seems that supercritical fluid technology is now rapidly coming of age.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
