<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Incinerator Project Is a Divisive Issue in Vermont</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="67" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="97461"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCINERATORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUTLAND (VT)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">VERMONT</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">VICON RESOURCE RECOVERY SYSTEMS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, SALLY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0D8103DF93AA15752C1A961948260" item-length="1114" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Incinerator Project Is a Divisive Issue in Vermont</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SALLY JOHNSON, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSON, SALLY</byline>
      <dateline>RUTLAND, Vt., Nov. 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The idea seemed seductively simple five years ago. The City of Rutland and neighboring towns would pool their garbage and burn it in a huge incinerator, producing electricity. The garbage, which had been threatening to overflow landfills, would be gone and the electricity would be cheap.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The idea seemed seductively simple five years ago. The City of Rutland and neighboring towns would pool their garbage and burn it in a huge incinerator, producing electricity. The garbage, which had been threatening to overflow landfills, would be gone and the electricity would be cheap.</p>
        <p>The idea seemed seductively simple five years ago. The City of Rutland and neighboring towns would pool their garbage and burn it in a huge incinerator, producing electricity. The garbage, which had been threatening to overflow landfills, would be gone and the electricity would be cheap.</p>
        <p>A lot has happened in those five years. At first many people in Rutland backed the project. Now, some citizens and politicians have changed their minds, and the issue has caused political and personal divisions.</p>
        <p>''I thought it sounded wonderful,'' recalled Patricia Donnelly, a Rutland City alderman who was once an enthusiastic supporter of the proposal and now opposes it. ''They told us we would be able to get rid of our garbage by burning it for $16.50 a ton for the next 26 years. I wondered why nobody had thought of it before.'' Physicist Has Faith</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Wennberg, the new Mayor of Rutland, won his first campaign last spring, in large part because of his support for the plant. The Mayor said his training as a physicist enabled him to study the evidence and conclude that ''the health-related concerns are unfounded.''</p>
        <p>What worries him more, he said, is ''what will happen without the plant.''</p>
        <p>''Our landfill will close in May 1988,'' he said. ''In my view, we had better get this plant on line.''</p>
        <p>The waste-to-energy plant, built and owned by Vicon Resource Recovery Systems of Butler, N.J., is scheduled for a late December start, at least two years behind the original date and $12.5 million over the original budget of $22 million. Requirements Added</p>
        <p>As late as last Tuesday, the Vermont Public Service Board, which regulates utilities, was adding new requirements to the permit that Vicon needs to operate the plant.</p>
        <p>Vicon, which has been testing the incinerator since mid-October, has not yet received permission to bury the toxic ash in a landfill it owns in Sunderland, a town in southern Vermont.</p>
        <p>Residents there oppose the ash dump on the ground that it may pollute a nearby trout stream, the Battenkill. Many fishermen are also concerned. Nor has Vicon received a final decision from the Public Service Board as to how much it will be allowed to charge for the electricity it produces. Contract Sparks Disagreements</p>
        <p>In addition, the company faces a possible challenge over the issue of ''tipping fees,'' the per-ton amount it charges communities to burn their waste. Under a contract approved in 1982, the 24 towns that make up the Rutland County Solid Waste District would pay a tipping fee of $16.50.</p>
        <p>However, Vicon now says it may have to charge as much as $40 per ton because of the costs created by delays in the project and because of more stringent environmental requirements now.</p>
        <p>Opponents of the incinerator contend that costs could go even higher than $40 a ton, and some say it was never made clear that the costs could rise above $16.50. Some opponents are petitioning for a new vote on the contract for the communities in the Solid Waste District. Pressure From Japanese Bank</p>
        <p>Furthermore, both sides acknowledge that Vicon, which has contracts with 33 other towns, is under pressure from the Industrial Bank of Japan to find new sources of financing and quickly repay the construction loan of $35 million.</p>
        <p>''The Industrial Bank of Japan has been waiting for its money twice as long as it intended to,'' said Alan George, the Rutland lawyer representing Vicon. ''I.B.J. is not in the mortgage-lending business. It wants its money out.''</p>
        <p>Resistance, which evolved gradually, stems from fears of potential health hazards, hazards Mrs. Donnelly said were never adequately explained in the beginning. She said she was dismayed to learn that, in the first air-quality permit it issued, the state was willing to ease its requirements if Vicon felt they would be too costly. That permit has since been amended.</p>
        <p>David Dickinson, a farmer who lives one mile downstream of the plant, is worried that Vicon may release contaminated water into the municipal sewer system, or into Otter Creek, which flows through his 300-acre dairy farm, providing water for his dairy herd. Assurances Unconvincing</p>
        <p>''I'm worried about heavy metals like lead, cadmium, zinc, mercury and copper,'' Mr. Dickinson said, adding that he is also concerned about organic pollutants. ''Vicon has been denying it right along, but we're not sure.'' A recent report prepared for the Environmental Protection Agency by private consultants stated that incinerator ash can contain lead, cadmium, dioxin and other toxic substances.</p>
        <p>One of the contingencies in the Public Service Board order issued Tuesday was that Vicon submit engineering reports on its storm drain system.</p>
        <p>Other neighbors have been concerned about air pollutants during incineration, which takes place at temperatures of up to 1,900 degrees. Responding to public pressure, the state has added a number of requirements, including more frequent monitoring and new emission controls, particularly on acid gas, sulfur dioxide, carbon dioxide and nitrous oxide.</p>
        <p>Vicon says the fears are unfounded, that its furnace design is the best in the business and the company has a good track record. 'All Over the World'</p>
        <p>''Vicon is building these plants all over the world,'' Mr. George said. ''There are five or six in existence and another dozen under construction. There has been some citizen opposition, but nothing like this.''</p>
        <p>On the other hand, Meredith Wright, a lawyer for the Environmental Law Project of the Vermont Law School, said the opponents have reason to worry.</p>
        <p>''Any incinerator is a high-tech operation with a lot of working parts,'' said Mr. Wright, who has been helping opponents prepare their case. ''If all parts operate as designed, we hope this new permit will be sufficiently protective. The concern is that some parts won't work as designed. This is a very complex system.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wennberg asserted that the state has paid too much attention to the ''fanatical and shrill attacks by the opposition, in the face of overwhelming evidence to the contrary.'' 'I Am Astounded'</p>
        <p>''The state's performance, by and large, has been atrocious,'' he said. ''I am astounded at the state's inability to deal with the issue.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Donnelly, now a dedicated opponent of the Vicon plant, said the controversy has taken its toll on her.</p>
        <p>''My position has not been politically popular,'' she said. ''I've put up with incredible ridicule for my stand. But we need to know certain things. What's going to happen in 15 years? What will happen to the children who grow up next door to the plant? Those questions have never been answered, and it scares the hell out of me.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
