<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kingsville Journal; Two Woodsmen Do Their Best On the Range</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="71126"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOOD AND WOOD PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">KINGSVILLE (TEX)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">REINHOLD, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PREWITT, JIM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FELKER, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wood and Wood Products</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3D81630F931A3575AC0A961948260" item-length="712" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kingsville Journal; Two Woodsmen Do Their Best On the Range</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT REINHOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REINHOLD, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>KINGSVILLE, Tex.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Its wood may be fine for grilling seafood and wild game in fashionable New York restaurants, but the mesquite tree is the scourge of south Texas. The gnarled, thorny tree, with roots of more than 50 feet, sucks valuable water from the dry range, and ranchers and farmers spend millions to rip it out and burn it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Its wood may be fine for grilling seafood and wild game in fashionable New York restaurants, but the mesquite tree is the scourge of south Texas. The gnarled, thorny tree, with roots of more than 50 feet, sucks valuable water from the dry range, and ranchers and farmers spend millions to rip it out and burn it.</p>
        <p>Its wood may be fine for grilling seafood and wild game in fashionable New York restaurants, but the mesquite tree is the scourge of south Texas. The gnarled, thorny tree, with roots of more than 50 feet, sucks valuable water from the dry range, and ranchers and farmers spend millions to rip it out and burn it.</p>
        <p>But where others see a nuisance, Jim Prewitt sees opportunity. The rich mesquite wood, he says, makes a fine mahogany-like hardwood. It is excellent for furniture, flooring, plaques and toys. A dreamer, Mr. Prewitt envisions a lumber industry on the flat south Texas plain. The ranchers think the sun has touched him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Prewitt, a mathematics teacher in his 50's, is a certified eccentric by south Texas standards. A part-time vegetarian who once converted his Toyota to run on an electric generator powered by a windmill, he is building what he calls an ''experimental dwelling'' under a geodesic dome on the edge of this town, which is home to the fabled King Ranch. His building materials include the concrete blocks discarded when King Street, which runs through the center of Kingsville, was repaved.</p>
        <p>Mr. Prewitt preaches the gospel of re-use and renewable energy, and praises the ''social organization'' of bees. His calling card is a Texas original:</p>
        <p>Alternative Energy Sources Sawmill-Electric Car Woods-Bees-Math Near the dome, Mr. Prewitt has built a sawmill and a kiln. He pays ranchers to haul their bigger mesquite logs there. He slices the logs with an antique buzz saw and then trims the boards into salable lumber. He says they bring $3 to $6 a foot, depending on quality.</p>
        <p>The problem, though, is an unreliable supply. ''This not being a logging community, everybody's been a little tentative about realizing they could bring logs in and I'd pay for it,'' Mr. Prewitt said. ''Ranchers are interested in eradicating mesquite, not growing it.''</p>
        <p>Still, some local business people see a potential new industry in a region affected by depressed oil and cattle prices. Dick Messbarger, the energetic manager of the Kingsville Chamber of Commerce, has encouraged Mr. Prewitt, though he complains that the lumberman - who says he is ''a couple of thousand ahead'' so far - is not interested enough in profits.</p>
        <p>Across town, Peter Felker, a plant physiologist at Texas A &amp; I University, is mounting a more scientific crusade for mesquite. Through cloning, he is trying to breed a thornless, straighter mesquite that grows fast and resists cold weather.</p>
        <p>After nearly a decade of research, Mr. Felker has developed a technique to propagate the improved varieties with cuttings from the South American species. He sees markets for the wood and, more important, for mesquite as decorative plants.</p>
        <p>The biggest hurdle, the scientist says, is that Southwest range interests have convinced the Government that mesquite should be eradicated, not cultivated. The Department of Agriculture has classified mesquite as a noxious weed and sponsors several eradication programs that have enlisted south Texas farmers.</p>
        <p>''We have been fighting this since 1978,'' Mr. Felker said, contending that the dense stands should be selectively cleared, gradually replanted with superior gene types and managed for lumber, as is done in the North with walnut.</p>
        <p>Mr. Felker and two local investors, Marty and Otis West, have formed a company, Plantclone Inc., to patent the propagation technique and market the improved mesquite. They envision growing as many as 25,000 trees a year and selling most of them to nurseries.</p>
        <p>''This is just the beginning,'' Mr. Felker said. ''Now is the time to look at new crops for new business niches. We haven't paid any attention to our native plant resources, and I think horticulture has tremendous potential in south Texas.''</p>
        <p>He and Mr. Prewitt are organizing a mesquite furniture business in Kingsville, and they recently took several prototypes of mesquite tables to the Dallas Furniture Mart.</p>
        <p>''We're trying to get a lot of orders,'' Mr. Felker said, ''so people in town can build a lot of tables and consume a lot of lumber, which will pull the demand for logs in the field, which will allow the rancher to get some return. Right now Prewitt is buying trees from ranchers. But who's going to buy the lumber from him?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
