<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deaver's Client Tells of Business Call From Plane</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="94776"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERJURY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOBBYING AND LOBBYISTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRANKLIN, BEN A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEAVER, MICHAEL K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (MRS)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1D9173BF933A15752C1A961948260" item-length="642" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deaver's Client Tells of Business Call From Plane</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN A. FRANKLIN, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRANKLIN, BEN A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Three months after he left his post as White House deputy chief of staff in 1985 to become a private lobbyist, Michael K. Deaver apparently used the radio telephone on Nancy Reagan's official airplane to conduct his consulting business, witnesses at Mr. Deaver's perjury trial said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Three months after he left his post as White House deputy chief of staff in 1985 to become a private lobbyist, Michael K. Deaver apparently used the radio telephone on Nancy Reagan's official airplane to conduct his consulting business, witnesses at Mr. Deaver's perjury trial said today.</p>
        <p>Three months after he left his post as White House deputy chief of staff in 1985 to become a private lobbyist, Michael K. Deaver apparently used the radio telephone on Nancy Reagan's official airplane to conduct his consulting business, witnesses at Mr. Deaver's perjury trial said today.</p>
        <p>The testimony came as the trial resumed after a week's recess to allow Mr. Deaver to recuperate from kidney stone surgery.</p>
        <p>William H. Timbers Jr., a vice president of Smith Barney, Harris Upham &amp; Company, testified that in August 1985 the Mr. Deaver left a telephone message instructing him to dial ''a special number at the White House.'' He was then to use the code word ''Foxtrot'' to have a call put through to Mr. Deaver. Broaden Consulting Contract</p>
        <p>Mr. Timbers told the jury that after being warned by a White House operator that he would talking on an ''unsecure line,'' Mr. Deaver answered amid ''a sound I identified as that of an airplane.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Timbers said he had earlier asked Mr. Deaver to broaden his consulting contract with Smith Barney to include lobbying ''on the minimum wage issue in Puerto Rico.'' In the telephone call Mr. Deaver agreed ''that he could work on a new project,'' Mr. Timbers testified.</p>
        <p>''He said this is not a secure telephone line,'' Mr. Timbers said. ''We should talk about this another time.'' The conversation ended. Mr. Deaver left the White House in May 1985 to form Michael K. Deaver and Associates, a Washington consulting firm. Smith Barney, the firm's first client, had a $250,000-a-year contract.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver has been charged with lying to a Congressional subcommittee and to a Federal grand jury investigating whether he violated ethics laws by representing clients on issues he dealt with when he was in the Government.</p>
        <p>According to Mary Ann Fackelman-Miner, a White House photographer, the plane was taking Mrs. Reagan to Boston for an appearance in her anti-drug campaign. Ms. Fackelman-Miner, who was on the plane, said Mr. Deaver and his wife, Carolyn, longtime friends of the President and Mrs. Reagan, traveled with Mrs. Reagan to Boston and then to Martha's Vineyard for an overnight visit.</p>
        <p>She identified ''Foxtrot'' as Mrs. Reagan's code word when she travels.</p>
        <p>Smith Barney signed its original contract with Mr. Deaver a week after he left the White House. The company hoped to gain support from the Reagan Administration for a tax provision that would benefit mainland companies investing in manufacturing plants in Puerto Rico.</p>
        <p>Reading from a memo he wrote to his superiors at Smith Barney on May 22, 1985, Mr. Timbers said he had recommended Mr. Deaver as a lobbyist on the tax matter because ''the final decision will be the President's.'' The memo said that Mr. Deaver had told him he had made ''quiet inquiries'' and could help.</p>
        <p>Also today prosecutors continued in their efforts to link Mr. Deaver to decisions made before he left the White House regarding complaints by Canada that the United States was doing too little to curb acid rain.</p>
        <p>After leaving the White House, Mr. Deaver signed a $100,000-a-year contract with the Government of Canada to obtain better treatment for it on curbing acid rain. In his sworn testimony before the grand jury and the Congressional subcommittee, Mr. Deaver asserted that he had had no role at the White House on the acid rain issue until just before a United States-Canada summit meeting on March 17, 1985.</p>
        <p>But today Patrick J. Buchanan, a former White House speech writer, testified that Mr. Deaver ''spoke up'' on acid rain in February of that year. Mr. Buchanan said that at one meeting Mr. Deaver voiced support for appointing envoys on the issue, a suggestion that David Stockman, then the director of the of Management and Budget, opposed as leading to high costs.</p>
        <p>''David Stockman went ballistic, as they say,'' Mr. Buchanan said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
