<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge in Deaver Case Quashes Subpoena for Envoy</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="51390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERJURY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JACKSON, THOMAS PENFIELD (JUDGE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOTLIEB, ALLAN (AMB)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEAVER, MICHAEL K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDA143CF930A15755C0A961948260" item-length="594" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge in Deaver Case Quashes Subpoena for Envoy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A Federal district judge here ruled today that Allan Gotlieb, the Canadian Ambassador to the United States, could not be compelled to testify at the perjury trial of Michael K. Deaver, a former White House aide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A Federal district judge here ruled today that Allan Gotlieb, the Canadian Ambassador to the United States, could not be compelled to testify at the perjury trial of Michael K. Deaver, a former White House aide.</p>
        <p>A Federal district judge here ruled today that Allan Gotlieb, the Canadian Ambassador to the United States, could not be compelled to testify at the perjury trial of Michael K. Deaver, a former White House aide.</p>
        <p>Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson denied a motion by Whitney North Seymour, the independent counsel in the case, to force Mr. Gotlieb to testify and quashed the subpoena.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver is accused in a five-count indictment of lying to a grand jury and a House subcommittee about the extent of his involvement with the acid rain issue before he resigned as deputy White House chief of staff to become a lobbyist for Canada and other clients. At the time of his testimony, Mr. Deaver's lobbying business was being investigated for possible ethics law violations regarding his ties to the White House. A Diplomatic Dispute</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour said Mr. Gotlieb was the only witness who could prove that Mr. Deaver lied when he said he could not recall having lunch on Jan. 5, 1985, with the Ambassador and his wife, Sondra.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour touched off a diplomatic dispute last month when he sent a Federal agent to serve subpoenas on Mr. Gotlieb and his wife at the Canadian Embassy.</p>
        <p>Embassy officials refused to accept the subpoenas and later accused Mr. Seymour of violating international law by trying to serve them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour responded by accusing the Canadian Government of ''duplicitous'' behavior by cooperating with his investigation to satisfy political critics but ultimately refusing to provide crucial testimony in the case against Mr. Deaver.</p>
        <p>Judge Jackson rejected Mr. Seymour's contention that Canada had waived its diplomatic immunity by agreeing to answer written questions posed last year by Mr. Seymour. ''The Canadian note of July 1986 is neither expressly nor by any fair implication a commitment by Canada to subject its Ambassador, or any other of its diplomatic personnel, to the American judicial process in this case,'' the judge said. On Canada's Rights</p>
        <p>''It is clear from the diplomatic correspondence so far supplied to the court that Canada has relinquished nothing beyond its absolute right to have ignored Mr. Seymour and his investigation from the outset, and even that it parted with only to the extent of forwarding its diplomats' voluntary, unsigned, unsworn summary answers to the queries posed, through a diplomatic, not a judicial, medium,'' Judge Jackson said.</p>
        <p>The State Department objected to Mr. Seymour's efforts to serve Mr. Gotlieb with the subpoena, saying it violated international law.</p>
        <p>Before the ruling, David Anderson, a Justice Department attorney, argued that the United States had an obligation ''to see that Canadian diplomatic immunity is upheld.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Anderson said the Federal Government must protect diplomatic immunity to keep its envoys from being subpoenaed in foreign countries.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver is scheduled to go to trial July 13 on the perjury charges.</p>
        <p>Last week a Federal appeals court refused to consider Mr. Deaver's challenge to the constitutionality of the statute under which Mr. Seymour was appointed by a court to investigate and prosecute the case.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver's lawyers are expected to appeal that decision to the Supreme Court, an action that could further delay the trial, which originally was scheduled to begin June 8.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver, who sought the independent counsel's investigation last year, contends the Ethics in Government Act, which provides for the independent counsel, is unconstitutional because it violates the Constitution's doctrine of separation of powers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
