<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>POVERTY IS LINKED TO HARM TO LAND</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="84638"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ZIMBABWE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENT AND DEVELOPMENT, WORLD COMMISSION ON</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PAUL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GANDHI, RAJIV (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MUGABE, ROBERT (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2DF1531F933A15753C1A961948260" item-length="559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>POVERTY IS LINKED TO HARM TO LAND</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, N.Y., Oct. 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Two prominent leaders from different parts of the developing world warned today that poverty is encouraging their people to destroy the natural environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Two prominent leaders from different parts of the developing world warned today that poverty is encouraging their people to destroy the natural environment.</p>
        <p>Two prominent leaders from different parts of the developing world warned today that poverty is encouraging their people to destroy the natural environment.</p>
        <p>But they argued that more economic assistance, not new restrictions on development aid, offers the best way to preserve tropical forests, stop the spread of deserts and prevent further damage to the developing world's environment.</p>
        <p>The warning and the plea for help came from Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi of India and Prime Minister Robert Mugabe of Zimbabwe. Mr. Mugabe is the chairman of the Nonaligned Movement, a major grouping of developing countries. Mr. Gandhi is a former chairman of the movement.</p>
        <p>Their remarks came in speeches to the General Assembly during a debate on the report of the World Commission on Environment and Development. The report was written by the commission under its chairman, Prime Minister Gro Harlem Brundtland of Norway. 'Sustainable Development'</p>
        <p>The report called for ''sustainable development'' and urged that in the future governments and institutions that aid development, like the World Bank, should insure that projects are compatible with environmental concerns.</p>
        <p>Many developing countries have expressed concern over the emphasis the commission put on the need for ''sustainable development.'' They contend that the richer Western nations are now seeking to make respect for the environment a new condition for aiding the developing world, futher slowing the flow of financial assistance they receive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gandhi and Mr. Mugabe said that rich and poor countries alike often allow economic changes that harm the world's natural resources and appear unsustainable in the long run.</p>
        <p>They agreed that forests are disappearing at an unacceptable rate in much of the developing world, that deserts are spreading because poor countries are condoning unsustainable patterns of agriculture, and that water resources are being damaged.</p>
        <p>But they also said that industrialized countries are responsible for acid rain and the danger of a rise in global temperatures through damage to the ozone layer from industrial emissions. 'Exploit Natural Resources'</p>
        <p>The two leaders said that poverty often forces people in poor nations to live in ways that permanently damage the environment.</p>
        <p>''The compulsions of development and limitations of financial resources tempt many developing countries to exploit their natural resources beyond endurance, ignoring environmental safeguards,'' Mr. Gandhi said.</p>
        <p>'' Those who are poor and hungry will destroy their immediate environment in order to survive,'''' Prime Minister Mugabe said. ''They will cut down their forest. Their livestock will overgraze the grasslands. And in growing numbers they will crowd into congested cities. They will overuse marginal land.''</p>
        <p>The answer, both men said, was for Western industrial countries to do more to assist the economic development of the poorer nations so their people do not need to live in ways that damage their land.</p>
        <p>''What is needed,'' Mr. Mugabe said, ''is the injection of more resources to enable the developing countries to formulate development programs that have environmental safeguards.''</p>
        <p>The two leaders also called for the West to open its markets to exports from poorer nations and grant more generous relief to poor countries heavily in debt.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
