<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY: TUESDAY, JANUARY 13, 1987</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="3302"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4DD173CF930A25752C0A961948260" item-length="924" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY: TUESDAY, JANUARY 13, 1987</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: International</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: International</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>No criticism of Israel was intended, the United States has assured Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir, when the White House disclosed documents last week describing Israel's involvement in the decision to sell arms to Iran.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>Responsibility for the Iran 'mistake' is something that President Reagan cannot escape, asserted the top Republican on the Senate intelligence committee, William S. Cohen of Maine.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>News analysis: Israel's link to Iran arms deals has been suggested by White House disclosures indicating that Israel promised that with one sale of arms to Teheran, all American hostages would be released.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Iraq said it had driven Iran back from much of the border region it had overrun in its new offensive near the city of Basra, while Iran said its troops had withstood three counterattacks in ''pitched battles.''</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>A drugs, arms and terrorism link is noted in a United Nations report that says a variety of illicit activities are masterminded by international criminal organizations, sometimes threatening national security.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>A Chinese scientist was dismissed as the Communist Party moved to reassert control over intellectuals with liberal views. The scientist had become a hero among thousands of student demonstrators last month.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Max M. Kampelman was appointed by the President to be counselor of the State Department as he continues in his role as an arms control negotiator.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Gen. Wojciech Jaruzelski, in Rome, began his first official visit to the West since he imposed martial law in Poland five years ago. His agenda included reducing Poland's diplomatic and economic isolation.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>The Premier of Bavaria's ambitions are uncertain, but many wonder whether Franz Josef Strauss could end up in Bonn as Vice Chancellor, after the election Jan. 25.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Ring Lardner Jr., back in Moscow 53 years after his last visit, toured the Kremlin with his wife. It has been four decades since his association with Communism fractured his career as a screenwriter.</p>
        <p>C17</p>
        <p>Shultz meets Nigerian leaders</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>National</p>
        <p>A16-20, B7, B20, D26</p>
        <p>Caspar W. Weinberger endorsed the preliminary deployment of an initial defense against ballistic missiles, provided that it would serve as a cornerstone for a nationwide shield against nuclear missiles.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Less money for energy conservation and renewable energy programs and more funds for military programs are outlined in the Energy Department's budget request, a Congressional study says.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>1986 was a very safe year to fly, a turnaround from 1985, according to official figures showing that large and medium-sized passenger planes flown by this country's airlines were not involved in a fatal crash.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Senate hearings on health care began, chaired by Edward M. Kennedy. Having lacked the majority party spotlight for six years, Democrats are now seizing the initiative on social issues.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Hard times have come to the West, according to economists and political leaders who say the region now faces declining population growth, persistent problems in important industries and growing apprehension about the future.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A new editor of the New Yorker magazine, for years a magnet for the country's leading writers, will succeed William Shawn on March 1. Robert A. Gottlieb, president of Alfred A. Knopf, will be only the third editor in 62 years.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Man in the News: Marlin Fitzwater will become President Reagan's new chief spokesman on Feb. 2, replacing Larry Speakes.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Conrail engines could have halted in time to avoid a collision with an Am trak train last week even if the engineer never saw a disputed track signal, speed tests conducted yesterday by the National Transporation Safety Board indicated.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>A small-town editor received threats after moving to and starting a crusade in McCormick, S.C. The sheriff is now in jail and a new election will be today, but his paper is up for sale.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Omaha's mayor fights for his job. Voters will decide today whether Mayor Michael Boyle will be recalled and replaced. Some say his erratic behavior justifies an ouster.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Verifying U.S. and Soviet compliance with nuclear testing limits should be far more comprehensive than has been proposed by the White House, secret documents show that Government intelligence officials say.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>New inquiry on Walker spy ring</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Justices to rule on liability</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Dollar hits 6-year low</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Washington Talk</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>I.R.S. redraws tax forms for '87 Congress mulls a highway bill  Regional</p>
        <p>B1-5</p>
        <p>Governor Cuomo conferred with John J. Santucci, the Queens District Attorney, to discuss turning the Howard Beach racial case over to a special prosecutor, and both gave signals that they would be prepared to do so.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Religious leaders met at City Hall to condemn the Howard Beach attack in the third such gathering that Mayor Koch has held to discourage racism in the city. More than 50 leaders participated.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Spectators interrupted the trial of an officer who fatally shot an elderly woman during an eviction in the Bronx. As the officer's lawyer was making an opening statement, shouts of ''liar'' and ''cover-up'' halted the trial briefly.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>An AIDS victim may wed in St. Patrick's Cathedral, renewing civil vows with his wife. Cardinal O'Connor reversed the decision of the rector of the Cathedral who had denied the couple's request.</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>Kean seeks welfare changes</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Renovation for Bryant Park</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>B5</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
