<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clean Air Needs a Federal Gorilla</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="98849"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOG</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5D71238F937A35751C1A961948260" item-length="497" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clean Air Needs a Federal Gorilla</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Seventeen years after passage of the Clean Air Act, 80 million Americans still live with unhealthy amounts of smog and ozone. The plan was to control ozone pollution by the end of this year, but last month the Environmental Protection Agency announced yet another extension and the waiver of penalties for all but a few cities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Seventeen years after passage of the Clean Air Act, 80 million Americans still live with unhealthy amounts of smog and ozone. The plan was to control ozone pollution by the end of this year, but last month the Environmental Protection Agency announced yet another extension and the waiver of penalties for all but a few cities.</p>
        <p>Seventeen years after passage of the Clean Air Act, 80 million Americans still live with unhealthy amounts of smog and ozone. The plan was to control ozone pollution by the end of this year, but last month the Environmental Protection Agency announced yet another extension and the waiver of penalties for all but a few cities. The House's overwhelming refusal yesterday to roll back the Clean Air Act's deadlines an additional 19 months sends a clear signal through the fog: Breathable air deserves a higher priority.</p>
        <p>There has been progress against most of the pollutants targeted by the Clean Air Act, but ozone has proved particularly intractable. In the stratosphere, the ozone layer protects life below. At ground level, the gas, even in minute amounts, harms the lungs; scar tissue can accumulate and impair breathing. In the New York metropolitan region, ozone has soared beyond the E.P.A. safety standard an average 31 days a year.</p>
        <p>Control of ozone depends on cutting back emissions of the airborne organic chemicals, like those contained in gasoline fumes, that aid in its formation. Controls on vehicles and major industrial sources have reduced organic emissions considerably over the last decade, but not enough.</p>
        <p>Further reductions must now come from many small sources, like gas stations. They may require ''extremely harsh, some might say heroic, lifestyle-changing measures,'' like gasoline rationing or alternate drive days, warns E.P.A. Administrator Lee Thomas. The agency can impose awesome sanctions against states that fail to reduce air pollution. It can halt construction or cut off Federal aid for highways and sewage treatment. But fearful of provoking public outcry, E.P.A. is reluctant to mandate major ozone reductions. Hence Mr. Thomas promises to withhold sanctions if states merely devise plans to reduce ozone.</p>
        <p>But the rate of reduction required in these plans - a mere 3 percent a year - delays the goal of smog-free air for 10 or 15 more years. The public will probably stomach far stronger measures than E.P.A. thinks. Many state environmental officials wish Mr. Thomas would act more like a ''gorilla in the closet,'' says William Becker of the State and Territorial Air Pollution Program Administrators. The agency could do that by mandating fewer volatile chemicals in gasoline, oil-based paint, solvents and deodorants, and requiring fume controls when gas is pumped at gas stations.</p>
        <p>Impatient with E.P.A.'s efforts, New York, New Jersey and six New England states decided recently to require fewer volatile chemicals in gasoline sold in summer months. The agency has proposed a similar rule, but it won't be instituted in time to affect gas sales next summer. New York and New Jersey will require fume controls at gas stations, but only at court insistence.</p>
        <p>Until Washington sets higher standards and faster goals, the states will lag in achieving safe and smog-free air. Mr. Thomas needs to thump his chest much more convincingly.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
