<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Protecting the Chesapeake's Striped Bass</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="97511"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASS (FISH)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHESAPEAKE BAY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRYANT, NELSON</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">OUTDOORS (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2D71F3DF93AA15752C1A961948260" item-length="1111" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Protecting the Chesapeake's Striped Bass</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nelson Bryant</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRYANT, NELSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ALTHOUGH there has been an improvement in the spawning of striped bass in many of the rivers entering Chesapeake Bay, the Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission announced earlier this fall that it would continue its current recommendation for a 33-inch minimum-length limit for migratory coastal stocks of the species.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ALTHOUGH there has been an improvement in the spawning of striped bass in many of the rivers entering Chesapeake Bay, the Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission announced earlier this fall that it would continue its current recommendation for a 33-inch minimum-length limit for migratory coastal stocks of the species.</p>
        <p>ALTHOUGH there has been an improvement in the spawning of striped bass in many of the rivers entering Chesapeake Bay, the Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission announced earlier this fall that it would continue its current recommendation for a 33-inch minimum-length limit for migratory coastal stocks of the species.</p>
        <p>Historically, most of the bass that range up and down the Northeast coast have been of Chesapeake Bay origin. Several years ago, these coastal stocks dwindled alarmingly. The intent of the regulation is to keep fishing pressure off female stripers from the Chesapeake, beginning with those spawned in the spring of 1982.</p>
        <p>The regulation will presumably remain in effect until the young-of-the-year, or juvenile, index of stripers in Maryland's portion of the bay reaches a three-year running average of 8.0. (This index, derived from annual net samples in given areas, is a measuring tool. It exceeded 30.0 in 1970, a banner year, but 8.0, the approximate average over a period of more than 30 years, is believed to be high enough for adequate recruitment of new stocks.) This spring, the index was 4.8. In 1986, it was 4.1; in 1985, 2.9. The index was 8.4 in 1982, after being 1.9 in 1980 and 1.2 in 1981, which is why those spawned in 1982 are being given special protection.</p>
        <p>Various causes for the procreative failure of the Chesapeake's stripers have been cited, among them pollution - including acid rain and agricultural runoff - and overfishing by both sport and commercial interests. The one readily available course of action for those whose job it is to protect the species was to curtail fishing mortality drastically. With this in mind, the coastal states from Maine to North Carolina were asked to reduce their catch of the 1982 vintage of female stripers until 95 percent of them had had a chance to spawn.</p>
        <p>The states responded to this in various ways. Maryland set the pace with a total moratorium. During the season just past, restrictions in these states ranged from a total ban on both possession and sale to permitting anglers to take one striper a day 33 or more inches long, and also allowing limited commercial fishery for bass of that size.</p>
        <p>Biologists have generally agreed that most female stripers become mature between ages 4 and 6, 22 to 37 inches long, but recent data suggest that some may not spawn until their eighth year, when they would be about 39 inches long. A 33-inch female would weigh about 24 pounds; a 39-incher about 35 pounds. The males rarely exceed 25 pounds. Because males are always smaller than females after the second year of their lives, minimum-length restrictions protect greater numbers of the former.</p>
        <p>New York State's striper regulations, which include a total ban on sale of the species regardless of origin, take the Hudson River's production of the species into account. Substantial numbers of striped bass spawn in the Hudson River, and this year the juvenile index for Hudson stripers was the highest since the assessment program was launched in 1979, twice the long-term average.</p>
        <p>In marine waters, New York allows an angler to keep one striper a day, 33 or more inches long. In the Hudson above the George Washington Bridge, the daily angling limit is one fish at least 18 inches long. The open season for stripers in the marine district is May 8-Nov. 30; in the Hudson, March 16-Nov. 30.</p>
        <p>The reason for New York's no-sale restriction is that significant numbers of striped bass in the Hudson River and in the state's coastal waters were found to be contaminated with polychlorinated biphenyls (PCB's) above the level deemed fit for human consumption by the Food and Drug Administration. One thus has the rather bizarre situation in which PCB pollution of the Hudson has afforded the fish a greater degree of protection than they would have otherwise been given. (The effect of PCB's on the fish themselves is not clear, although research has indicated that stripers spawned in the Hudson may not, at least in the first few months of their lives, be able to swim as rapidly as those in less-contaminated waters.) In New York State and elsewhere, commercial fishing interests have sought a relaxation of the no-sale ban. A bill introduced in the New York Legislature early this year - it later died in committee - would have allowed a limited commercial fishery for small striped bass in the state's marine waters, there being evidence indicating that those fish may have average PCB concentrations below the F.D.A. standard of two parts per million.</p>
        <p>One of the difficulties in allowing such a fishery was whether the harvesting of small bass in coastal waters - even though most might be of Hudson origin - could be reconciled with the 33-inch minimum-length requirement.</p>
        <p>This year, the striped bass's reproductive success was unusually high in some of the rivers in Virginia that feed into the Chesapeake Bay. In the James River, it was 10 times the long-term average. On the other hand, very few juvenile fish were found in Maryland's rivers at the head of the bay, an area that once produced many stripers.</p>
        <p>Even under optimum conditions, only minuscule numbers of the eggs deposited by female striped bass in their spawning runs survive to the juvenile stage. If this were not so, there would soon be a surfeit of the species, for a single large female produces millions of eggs. Sometimes, striper production dwindles because not enough females reach the spawning grounds. According to some observers, this is what happened at the head of Chesapeake Bay this year. At other times, even though great numbers of eggs are released, few of them survive beyond the larval stage. Pulses of acidic water moving down a stream can decimate larval stripers.</p>
        <p>Over the decades, fishery biologists have observed what they call dominant year classes in striped bass productivity, years - as in 1970 in the Chesapeake - in which the survival rate is extraordinarily high. No single adequate explanation has been found for this, but when it does occur, it seems to be a widespread phenomenon.</p>
        <p>These natural cycles complicate the task of those who would devise a successful management plan for striped bass. Although pollution has undoubtedly contributed to the decline of the East Coast's migratory stocks of the species, attrition from this source cannot be measured with any degree of accuracy.</p>
        <p>According to Randy Carlson, assistant director of the Massachusetts Division of Marine Fisheries, ''There is a lot of support growing for the argument that a very substantial part of the striper's difficulties is the direct result of overfishing, and I tend to agree with this.''  OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
