<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All 12 Candidates Debate In First TV Appearance</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="98366"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1988</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEBATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service"></org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL BROADCASTING CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DIONNE, E J JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOLE, ROBERT J (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DU PONT, PIERRE S 4TH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAIG, ALEXANDER M JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KEMP, JACK F (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROBERTSON, MARION G (PAT) (REV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROKAW, TOM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMON, PAUL (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JACKSON, JESSE L (REV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, ALBERT JR (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GEPHARDT, RICHARD A (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUKAKIS, MICHAEL S (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BABBITT, BRUCE E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Richard A Gephardt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDF1F3AF931A35751C1A961948260" item-length="1669" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All 12 Candidates Debate In First TV Appearance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By E. J. DIONNE, Jr., Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DIONNE, E J JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Twelve Presidential candidates brought a foretaste of the 1988 general election campaign into the nation's living rooms tonight with a debate that emphasized party differences on foreign policy far more than distinctions among individual candidates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Twelve Presidential candidates brought a foretaste of the 1988 general election campaign into the nation's living rooms tonight with a debate that emphasized party differences on foreign policy far more than distinctions among individual candidates.</p>
        <p>Twelve Presidential candidates brought a foretaste of the 1988 general election campaign into the nation's living rooms tonight with a debate that emphasized party differences on foreign policy far more than distinctions among individual candidates.</p>
        <p>The six Democrats began a two-hour debate broadcast by NBC News by denouncing the Republicans for failing to support President Reagan's decision to sign a treaty on intermediate-range nuclear weapons with the Soviet Union, chiding them for opposing a treaty supported by a Republican President.</p>
        <p>''It is nothing short of appalling that five of the six Republican candidates refuse to support the new arms control agreement,'' said Senator Albert Gore Jr. of Tennessee, one of the Democrats. A Defense by Bush</p>
        <p>The six Republican candidates vehemently attacked the Democrats for their stands on the Soviet Union and Central America and domestic spending. But five of them questioned the arms treaty. Only Vice President Bush vigorously defended the pact - and like the Democrats, he took his foes to task for not backing the President.</p>
        <p>The Republican candidates treated Mr. Bush - who, nationwide, is far ahead of his rivals in the polls - somewhat more gently than they had in a debate in Houston earlier this fall. But former Secretary of State Alexander M. Haig Jr. pointedly asked Mr. Bush what he had said or done about the Iran-Contra arms deal. ''Were you in the cockpit, or were you on an economy ride in the back of the plane?'' Mr. Haig asked.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush dodged the question, saying the Reagan Administration had sought to correct the mistakes the arms deal brought to light, and when Mr. Haig demanded an example, the Vice President smiled and said ''Time's up.''</p>
        <p>The Democrats, who sparred among themselves so gently on foreign policy that they seemed to have agreed to a cease-fire treaty of their own, turned sharply against each other when matters turned to domestic policy.</p>
        <p>They were particularly tough on Senator Paul Simon of Illinois, who has taken the lead in most polls in Iowa, which will begin the nominating process with its caucuses Feb. 8.</p>
        <p>Representative Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri said Mr. Simon had offered an economic program that ''smacks of Reaganomics.''</p>
        <p>''Paul, you're not a pay-as-you-go Democrat, you are a promise-as-you-go Democrat,'' Mr. Gephardt said. ''Simonomics is really Reaganomics with a bow tie.''</p>
        <p>Bruce Babbitt, former Governor of Arizona, who has been more specific than any of the other Democratic candidates in proposals for tax increases and spending cuts, including taxing Social Security benefits for the affluent, accused all of his rivals of ''flimflam.''</p>
        <p>''It's time to live up to this budget deficit and tell the American people what they need to know,'' he said. Rising to his feet, Mr. Babbitt declared that he was standing up ''to say it's time we raise taxes.''</p>
        <p>Glancing at his seated rivals, Mr. Babbitt shook his head and said, ''There are not a lot of profiles in courage here.'' Noncandidate Is Star</p>
        <p>The debate, held at the John F. Kennedy Center here, turned out to be a far more vigorous encounter than many politicians had expected, and the candidates made clear that a number of substantive questions divide them.</p>
        <p>Still, the program also immediately showed the extent to which the candidates were operating under the rules of network television, not politicians. The clear star of the show, and the dominant figure, was NBC's Tom Brokaw. As the candidates stood dutifully on two sides of a large blue square on stage at the start of the program, Mr. Brokaw introduced them in alphabetical order - Democrats first, Republicans second.</p>
        <p>Then, before a candidate spoke a word, Mr. Brokaw cut to commercials. And when the program came back, Mr. Brokaw stepped up to each candidate, pacing the stage like a ringmaster, to confront each with queries. At times, the camera showed Mr. Brokaw towering over the candidates, walking up to the railing that separated him from them and interrogating them in the tones of a young prosecutor.</p>
        <p>It was the first time all twelve candidates had appeared together, although the debate was really two debates. The Democrats sparred on foreign policy for the first half hour, and the Republicans followed suit in the next half hour segment. Then the Democrates came back for 30 minutes on domestic policy, followed by the Republicans. A Cozy Group?  The Democrats - Mr. Gephardt, Mr. Simon, Mr. Babbitt, Mr. Gore, Gov. Michael S. Dukakis of Massachusetts and The Rev. Jesse Jackson - were so gentle with each other during the discussion on foreign policy that Mr. Brokaw at one point questioned whether they were opponents or just ''a cozy group.''</p>
        <p>The Republicans - Mr. Bush, Mr. Haig, the Senate minority leader, Bob Dole, Representative Jack Kemp of upstate New York, Pat Robertson and former Gov. Pete du Pont of Delaware - played rougher with each other at the start, although they eased off later.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush proudly declared himself a supporter of the intermediate-range missile treaty.</p>
        <p>''I think we ought to go ahead and sign this treaty,'' Mr. Bush said. He scolded his opponents for failing to support an agreement that involved ''banning an entire generation of intermediate nuclear forces.''</p>
        <p>''The good thing about this treaty is that it's a major breakthrough in verification,'' Mr. Bush said. ''People said you'd never get this kind of verification and now we have it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Haig, who has vigorously opposed the treaty, seemed to soften his position. ''It's too late to scuttle what's already happened,'' he said. But he said he still thought the United States should seek ''some absolute preconditions,'' including changes in Soviet policy toward human rights.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole continued to hedge on the agreement. ''I'm happy the President's signing it and I applaud him for it,'' Mr. Dole said. But he said the Senate had a right and responsibility to ratify the treaty and suggested he might support Senate-added reservations.</p>
        <p>''We can improve the treaty for the President,'' Mr. Dole said. ''I've never let the President down yet, but I have a right to read and study.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kemp, Mr. Robertson and Mr. du Pont criticized the treaty.</p>
        <p>''It's a bad treaty for the United States,'' said Mr. du Pont. ''I would always entrust freedom to the ingenuity of the American people before I would entrust it to the integrity of the Soviet Union.''</p>
        <p>The Republicans vigorously denounced the Democrats for their opposition to military aid to the Nicaraguan Contras.</p>
        <p>''What we need to do is to keep the pressure on the Marxist Sandinistas,'' Mr. Dole said. ''I don't see any of the Democrats suggesting there's even any problem.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Robertson said he would sooner ''believe in the Great Pumpkin or the tooth fairy'' than to believe that a Communist regime would voluntarily leave power. He added that the Democrats had abandoned their past support for a vigorously anti-Communist foreign policy.</p>
        <p>''In the old days, with Truman and Kennedy, the Democrats stood for freedom,'' Mr. Robertson said. Now, he said the Democrats often supported policies of ''appeasement.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kemp condemned the Democrats for failing to live up to President Kennedy's pledge to ''pay any price and bear any burden'' to ''insure the survival and the success of freedom.''</p>
        <p>''They will not even pay the price of human freedom in this hemisphere,'' Mr. Kemp said.  In the first half hour, dedicated to the Democrats' views on foreign policy, the Democrats attacked the Reagan Administration but hardly each other.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gephardt asked Mr. Simon what he would do to bring to heel the Administration's ''rogue foreign policy'' with regard to the Iran-Contra affair.</p>
        <p>Mr. Babbitt suggested to Mr. Gephardt that the Administration had failed to take up the suggestion by the Soviet leader, Mikhail S. Gorbachev, who said on American television that environmental matters should be a subject of summit discussion. Among other things, Mr. Gephardt responded, ''the President has not dealt with the acid rain issue.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore set that amiable tone from the moment of his opening statement. when he responded to a suggestion from Mr. Brokaw, the moderator, who said that the Senator's criticism of fellow Democrats on military issues would give the Republicans an opportuntiy to charge all of them with being ''soft on defense.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore did concede there were differences among Democrats - in earlier debates, he had highlighted them - saying he was the only one of them who ''support the mission in the Persian Gulf of keeping the sea lanes open and stand up to the Ayatollah Khomeini.'' Jackson on the Gulf</p>
        <p>Mr. Jackson said Mr. Gore was ''misrepresenting the truth about the Persian Gulf,'' and said he was committed to ''keeping the sea lanes open,'' but with the cooperation and more active participation of other nations, notably Japan, through the United Nations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Babbitt also took up the gauntlet against the Administration when he posed his question to Mr. Gore: ''What policy is it that you are supporting in the Persian Gulf.''</p>
        <p>The Administration, Mr. Babbitt said, was ''sending soldiers of fortune with cakes and Bibles, offering the ayatollah support to overthrow the Iraqis. Then the next day, supporting the Iraqis. Then the Iraqis fire a missile and sink an Americna ship, and the President responds to the Iraqi attack by threatening a pre-emptive strike against the Iranians.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Babbitt said the entire policy led him to ask the question: ''Who's on first?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gephardt and Mr. Gore engaged in one of the toughest exchanges of the evening.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore challenged Mr. Gephardt for the latter's vote in favor of the tax cut program put forward by President Reagan in 1981.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gephardt barely defended the vote, but turned the question around and asked Mr. Gore: ''Are you for repealing it and for voting to raise taxes on middle income people?''</p>
        <p>Neither Mr. Gephardt nor Mr. Gore were satisfied with the other's answer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
