<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Longer Merely Voices In the Russian Wilderness</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="105111"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HISTORIC BUILDINGS AND SITES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KELLER, BILL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEEDE113CF934A15751C1A961948260" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Longer Merely Voices In the Russian Wilderness</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL KELLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KELLER, BILL</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IN the Armenian capital of Yerevan, angry citizens have forced local officials to promise that a chemical plant blamed for high rates of cancer and birth defects will be relocated. In the town of Kirishi, in western Russia, a band of citizens led by a local postman shut down a plant manufacturing synthetic additives for livestock feed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IN the Armenian capital of Yerevan, angry citizens have forced local officials to promise that a chemical plant blamed for high rates of cancer and birth defects will be relocated. In the town of Kirishi, in western Russia, a band of citizens led by a local postman shut down a plant manufacturing synthetic additives for livestock feed.</p>
        <p>IN the Armenian capital of Yerevan, angry citizens have forced local officials to promise that a chemical plant blamed for high rates of cancer and birth defects will be relocated. In the town of Kirishi, in western Russia, a band of citizens led by a local postman shut down a plant manufacturing synthetic additives for livestock feed. In Moscow, in the face of student protests, the authorities have abandoned plans to demolish several old buildings.</p>
        <p>These are heady times for Russia's environmentalists. Officially and unofficially, concern has blossomed for the icy lakes percolating with industrial wastes, the historic buildings razed to make way for cement high-rises, the city air choked with the effluents of progress.</p>
        <p>Even where environmentalists have failed in their immediate goals, they have pressed the limits of citizen activism, openly challenging projects that have the imprimatur of the Communist Party and Government ministries and treading on ground that was once closed to debate. Some groups have even begun to question the wisdom of the Soviet nuclear power program.</p>
        <p>The first successes were scored by an influential few. When the Government announced in August 1986 that it was dropping plans to divert two Siberian rivers for irrigation, primary credit went to Russian writers like Vasily Belov and Valentin Rasputin, who campaigned against the project because it threatened to flood large swaths of the primeval landscape in which these writers find the mystic roots of Russianness. The cultural elite has undertaken similar campaigns to defend Leo Tolstoy's homestead and Siberia's Lake Baikal from industrial pollution.</p>
        <p>But environmentalism has begun to develop a potent grass-roots following, taking on some of the character of the conservation movements of the West. Environmentalists thus find themselves in the forefront of what Mikhail S. Gorbachev, the Soviet leader, calls ''democratization.''</p>
        <p>The Soviet movement reflects genuine concern about the hangover of hasty industrialization. But it has also profited from a convergence of political developments, including the worldwide outcry over the explosion in April 1986 at the Chernobyl nuclear power plant.</p>
        <p>''They say that one thorn of experience is worth more than a whole forest of instructions,'' Mr. Gorbachev wrote in Pravda in September. ''For us, Chernobyl became such a thorn.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, the grandiose development projects of the Khrushchev and Brezhnev eras have fallen from favor. Such symbols of socialist gung-ho as the still-uncompleted Baikal-to-Amur Siberian railroad or the river diversion projects are now eschewed in favor of what Mr. Gorbachev calls ''intensive'' development, which means upgrading existing facilities with newer, more efficient technology.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gorbachev has also discovered that the environment fits neatly into his foreign-policy theme of an interdependent world. The Soviet leader now routinely mentions acid rain or the ozone layer in his speeches as an illustration of the problems the superpowers might solve together - if only they would disarm.</p>
        <p>It may be that Mr. Gorbachev's supporters in the leadership feel that the environment is safe ground for the nurturing of the popular initiative they need to shake off the pervasive lethargy of Soviet society. Local Opposition</p>
        <p>Local officials do not always see it that way. In Leningrad, the busiest hub of unofficial environmentalism, leaders of Spaseniye (Salvation), a popular preservation group, and Delta, a tiny group organized to battle a flood control project, have been harassed and criticized in the local press, even as the national newspaper Izvestia has written sympathetically of them.</p>
        <p>Like any group that shows a sign of life in this society, environmentalists face attempts to steer them into official channels. Komsomol, the youth arm of the Communist Party, which once dutifully mobilized around titanic development projects, has lately fastened on the environment as a popular organizing theme. Last June the Soviet Peace Committee, the slick official organization responsible for mustering ''spontaneous'' rallies against American militarism, announced that its next venture in activism would be an environmental group. In Moscow, co-optation is the sincerest form of flattery.</p>
        <p>These are not the only forces that sense the selling power of conservation. The group Pamyat (Memory), a Russian nationalist organization with a wide streak of anti-Semitism and xenophobia in its ranks, presents itself as a group to protect monuments of Russian history and culture.</p>
        <p>The environmentalists' most formidable obstacle is probably the momentum of the builder bureaucracy itself. No sooner had the Siberian river project been pronounced dead than it resurfaced in the form of a continuing study.</p>
        <p>''The official mentality here is like the Army Corps of Engineers,'' said one American official, recalling the sometimes nemesis of American environmentalists. ''Every time they see a river, they want to pave it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
