<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS SUMMARY: WEDNESDAY, APRIL 29, 1987</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="35233"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BUSINESS DIGEST (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5D6173DF93AA15757C0A961948260" item-length="675" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS SUMMARY: WEDNESDAY, APRIL 29, 1987</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  The Economy</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  The Economy</p>
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>Skepticism is growing about Treasury Secretary Baker's policies. Until two months ago, Mr. Baker could point to noteworthy achievements, but evidence of deterioration is showing up everywhere - in the sinking dollar, rising interest rates, growing inflation and a slowing of the world economy. He is also losing influence in Congress and the Administration.  [ Page A1. ]</p>
        <p>House Speaker Wright shifted his stand on a rescue package for the F.S.L.I.C. In an embarrassing reversal, Mr. Wright said he now favored a much larger bailout of the agency, acknowledging that the thrift industry's woes were worse than he had realized.  [ D1. ] Markets</p>
        <p>The Fed has moved to tighten monetary policy, most economists and market analysts now maintain. The experts noted that the central bank had presided over a rise in the important Federal funds rate and conspicuously failed to take routine action to prevent it from rising further on Monday.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Stocks closed slightly higher, ending a four-day slide. The Dow Jones industrial average eked out a 1.42-point gain, closing at 2,231.96. A firmer dollar and falling rates helped.  [ D12. ]</p>
        <p>The dollar was up a bit in light trading, but dealers were unimpressed, largely because the market turned back efforts to push the currency through two key resistance levels.  [ D18. ]</p>
        <p>Prices of most live-cattle and pork futures rose. Soybean futures also advanced.  [ D18. ] Companies</p>
        <p>British Petroleum and Standard Oil agreed on a $7.82 billion price for the purchase of 45 percent of Standard Oil that B.P. does not yet own. The deal will make British Petroleum the world's third-largest oil company. It also provides for the settlement of shareholder suits challenging B.P.'s lower offer of $7.4 billion.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>USX reported a loss and Bethlehem Steel posted a profit. USX's results reflected a labor-related plant shutdown that ended in February. Bethlehem's profit resulted from plant improvements, reduced costs and higher prices as well as USX's absence from the market.  [ D1. ]  Three oil companies -Occidental, Pennzoil and Chevron - posted quarterly results that were hurt by lower oil prices.  [ D5. ]</p>
        <p>A Merrill Lynch unit expects a suit from the Haft family relating to the takeover fight for Supermarkets General.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>The two committees monitoring Texaco during its bankruptcy proceedings chose a representative of Metropolitan Life to head one panel and those of Pennzoil and Tenneco to head the second.  [ D5. ]</p>
        <p>J. C. Penney will relocate its headquarters in Dallas, consultants say. The move, affecting 4,000 employees, would be the latest in a renewed corporate exodus from Manhattan.  [ A1. ]</p>
        <p>Apple plans to spin off a software company that will develop, publish and sell programs for Apple personal computers.  [ D5. ] International</p>
        <p>A new Brazilian finance minister was named by President Jose Sarney after four days of intense political consultations. The new minister, Luiz Carlos Bresser Pereira, is an economist with vast business experience.  [ D1. ] Technology</p>
        <p>The application of biotechnology to forestry is the mission of several U.S. laboratories. Using cloning and gene-splicing techniques, California researchers are trying to produce trees that grow faster or are resistant to disease, insects or acid rain.  [ D10. ]</p>
        <p>The ETA-10 may soon be the world's most powerful computer. The supercomputer, made by ETA Systems, processes information so rapidly that it must be dunked in liquid nitrogen to prevent components from melting. Advances.  [ D10. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>The yen-dollar exchange rate is dividing the Administration as it prepares for the Nakasone talks. The issue is whether the U.S. should help support the dollar or let market forces decide the currency's value. Leonard Silk. Economic Scene.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>The frenzied action in the silver markets on Monday will not soon be forgotten by traders. Some analysts linked the turbulence to a steep rise in margins, or good-faith deposits. Market Place.  [ D12. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
