<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Canada Assails New Bid to Have Envoy Testify in Deaver Case</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="82612"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERJURY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHENON, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEYMOUR, WHITNEY NORTH JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEAVER, MICHAEL K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DB1738F937A25753C1A961948260" item-length="791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Canada Assails New Bid to Have Envoy Testify in Deaver Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHENON, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHENON, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Government of Canada said today that it was the victim of ''shocking and extraordinary'' efforts at ''intimidation'' by the special prosecutor in the perjury case against Michael K. Deaver.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Government of Canada said today that it was the victim of ''shocking and extraordinary'' efforts at ''intimidation'' by the special prosecutor in the perjury case against Michael K. Deaver.</p>
        <p>The Government of Canada said today that it was the victim of ''shocking and extraordinary'' efforts at ''intimidation'' by the special prosecutor in the perjury case against Michael K. Deaver.</p>
        <p>In a statement released in Washington, the Canadian Secretary of State, Joe Clark, said the special prosecutor, Whitney North Seymour Jr., had made a new and ''outrageous'' attempt to obtain testimony from the Canadian Ambassador to the United States at Mr. Deaver's trial.</p>
        <p>The State Department immediately joined with Canada in protesting a letter of Oct. 2 from Mr. Seymour to a lawyer for the Canadian Embassy.</p>
        <p>In the one-page letter, which was made public today by the embassy, Mr. Seymour warned that unless Ambassador Allan E. Gotlieb testified at Mr. Deaver's trial, prosecutors would be ''forced'' to ''place much greater emphasis at the trial on the unlawful acts engaged in by Deaver when he was working for the Canadian Government.'' One of Five Counts</p>
        <p>Last May, Mr. Seymour attempted to subpoena the Ambassador and his wife, Sondra; Mr. Deaver is accused of lying under oath about his dealings with Canadian issues, specifically the issue of acid rain, before he left the White House in 1985. This is one count of a five-count indictment.</p>
        <p>A Federal judge later ruled that the Ambassador and Mrs. Gotlieb could not be forced to testify. At the time the State Department and Canada accused Mr. Seymour of violating international agreements governing diplomatic immunity. Mr. Deaver's trial is scheduled to begin next Monday.</p>
        <p>In its formal statement today, the Canadian Embassy said it ''wishes to protest in the strongest terms against this attempted intimidation of the government of a sovereign state exercising its sovereign rights under international law.''</p>
        <p>It continued, ''Mr. Seymour clearly expects that by threatening to 'convict' Canada of nonexistent offenses in the publicity surrounding a trial in which Canada is not a party, he will succeed in intimidating the Government of Canada and compel it to give up its rights under international law.''</p>
        <p>In a short telephone conversation, Mr. Seymour would not comment on the new Canadian protest. ''I look forward to reading about it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In a letter today to the Justice Department, the State Department's legal adviser, Abraham Sofaer, sided with Canada against Mr. Seymour, whose role as a special prosecutor allows him to operate independent of the Reagan Administration. Effort Called Disturbing</p>
        <p>Mr. Sofaer said that Mr. Seymour's renewed effort to obtain testimony from the Ambassador was ''disturbing'' and had caused ''considerable embarrassment to both the governments of the United States and Canada.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour's attempts to secure testimony from Ambassador Gotlieb have strained Canadian-American relations and led to repeated protests from the Canadian Government.</p>
        <p>The Reagan Administration has been embarrassed by its inability to restrain Mr. Seymour, who, under the 1978 special prosecutor law, is answerable to almost no one. It was unclear what pressure, if any, the Justice Department could bring on Mr. Seymour as a result of Mr. Sofaer's letter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour has said previously that Ambassador Gotlieb was a ''key prosecution witness'' against Mr. Deaver, who left his post as White House Deputy Chief of Staff to become a highly paid Washington lobbyist and public relations consultant.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour is accused of committing perjury when he said under oath that he could not remember several White House meetings involving pollutants released into the atmosphere by American factories, which Canada asserts are falling in that country as acid rain. After leaving the White House, Mr. Deaver obtained a contract from the Canadian Government. Lobbying Is Not Involved</p>
        <p>In its letter of protest today to the State Department, the Canadian Embassy noted that the charges against Mr. Deaver do not directly involve his lobbying contract with Canada.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Seymour now proposes to conduct the trial so as to focus on 'the unlawful acts engaged in by Deaver when he was working for the Canadian Government,' even though Mr. Deaver does not stand accused of any such acts,'' the letter said. ''The real object of his proposed shift of emphasis appears to lie elsewhere.''</p>
        <p>Under international law, diplomats cannot be compelled to testify in a foreign trial unless immunity is waived by their Government. In the Deaver case, Canada has refused to waive the immunity shared by Ambassador Gotlieb and his wife.</p>
        <p>In his statement today, Mr. Clark, the Secretary of State for External Affairs, said that Mr. Seymour's new letter was an attempt ''to intimidate the Government of Canada into relinquishing its sovereign rights.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
