<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brooklyn Refuse Plan Raises Broad Concerns</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="46" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="93208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCINERATORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND CLAIMS AGAINST GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BROOKLYN (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NEUFFER, ELIZABETH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDB163EF936A25752C1A961948260" item-length="1017" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brooklyn Refuse Plan Raises Broad Concerns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH NEUFFER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NEUFFER, ELIZABETH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Almost a decade ago, New York City officials proposed a series of waste-to-energy incinerators. The first was to be built in the Brooklyn Navy Yard by 1984. Today, construction has yet to begin, delayed by strident community opposition, a lawsuit and changing environmental regulations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Almost a decade ago, New York City officials proposed a series of waste-to-energy incinerators. The first was to be built in the Brooklyn Navy Yard by 1984. Today, construction has yet to begin, delayed by strident community opposition, a lawsuit and changing environmental regulations.</p>
        <p>Almost a decade ago, New York City officials proposed a series of waste-to-energy incinerators. The first was to be built in the Brooklyn Navy Yard by 1984. Today, construction has yet to begin, delayed by strident community opposition, a lawsuit and changing environmental regulations.</p>
        <p>While the proposal, still fought by environmentalists and nearby residents, inches through a state hearing process that already has taken more than six months, the city's garbage crisis is worsening. New York's last large landfill, Fresh Kills on Staten Island, could be closed in 1997, leaving no place to dispose of the 27,000 tons of garbage that New Yorkers produce each day.</p>
        <p>At issue in the debate over the Brooklyn Navy Yard are questions being repeated around the country. Does incineration release toxic chemicals into the air at levels that pose a threat to human health? Should the ash from incinerators be classified as hazardous waste, and stored with protective measures? Is incineration the solution to the garbage crisis - or is recycling, or some combination?</p>
        <p>In the late 1970's, when city officials first proposed that an incinerator be built in each borough, waste-to-energy plants seemed the epitome of environmental foresight. But controversy quickly developed. Pressure From Residents</p>
        <p>The Board of Estimate, under pressure from Brooklyn residents, at first opposed the Navy Yard plant. But in 1985, after debate that produced mounds of scientific studies and divided the city's environmental community, the board narrowly approved the Brooklyn incinerator and plans to build four incinerators.</p>
        <p>State hearings were delayed more than a year by a lawsuit brought by environmentalists. Today the incinerator still needs permits from the state and the Federal Environmental Protection Agency, and city officials doubt it will be operating much before 1992.</p>
        <p>Over the years designs for the 15-story, approximately $400 million incinerator have evolved in reaction to changing environmental laws and public concern.</p>
        <p>The plant planned by the contractor, Wheelabrator-Fryer-Environmental Systems Inc., is a so-called mass-burn plant, designed to burn waste of all kinds at a temperature of 1,800 degrees Fahrenheit, said Jim Meyer, a policy analyst for the Department of Sanitation. Pumping Air</p>
        <p>Plants like that use furnaces, called combustors, that burn a steady stream of garbage. The waste - metals, glass, ceramics and all - is moved down steps in an inclined grate as air is pumped through it to speed burning.</p>
        <p>The hot gases from the burning garbage heat water in the walls and at the top of the combustor, generating low pressure steam for heating or high pressure steam for electric generating. Public utilities are required to buy this electricity.</p>
        <p>Early environmental arguments over incinerator pollution centered on the control of flue gases and dust. In the absence of Federal air pollution standards for garbage incinerators, states have established limits on pollutants such as carbon monoxide and the unburned hydrocarbons that contribute to acid rain.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. announced that no new plants would be licensed in the future without state-of-the-art air pollution technology, which includes dry scrubbers that bathe combustor smoke in an alkaline dust to neutralize acids, and then captures the dust in fabric filters known as a bag house. Cutting Dioxin Levels</p>
        <p>Many say that the dry scrubber-bag house system has gone far to reducing the emission of dioxins, which are highly toxic to laboratory animals.</p>
        <p>This system, combinedwith high temperatures, would make the risk posed to the public from dioxins emitted by the Brooklyn plant ''well below levels of risk generally accepted in society,'' said Paul Casowitz, the deputy sanitation commissioner.</p>
        <p>But many environmentalists say that even the reduced levels of dioxin are too high.They note that there are no Federal standards for dioxin emissions. At the same time, debate continues over the best way to handle fly ash and bottom ash.</p>
        <p>Under the worst conditions, city officials say, the dioxins emitted from its smokestack would cause 1 to 3 additional cancer cases per million people exposed over a 70-year period.</p>
        <p>But many environmentalists and nearby residents sharply disagree. They are concerned that the plant, the first in the country to be built in such a densely populated area, would emit dioxin at harmful levels. The Recycling Option</p>
        <p>Dr. Barry Commoner, the director of the Center for the Biology of Natural Systems at Queens College, argues that studies reveal that dioxins can be formed when the hot gases reach the cooler smokestack. In addition, studies done by the center calculate the risk of cancer to nearby residents is 29 cases of cancer per million people exposed over a 70-year period.</p>
        <p>With so many questions raised about the byproducts created by burning garbage, there are many who argue that recycling, not incineration, is the answer.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists charge that the city is not committed to recycling.</p>
        <p>''To the city, recycling is an afterthought,'' said Bonnie Fine Kauffman, a lawyer for Brooklyn residents opposed to the plant.</p>
        <p>But the city's Department of Sanitation disputes that full-scale recycling can be achieved in New York City. They hope only to recycle 15 percent of the city's waste, through a curbside recycling project that began on an experimental basis last year.</p>
        <p>Now, as the Brooklyn Navy Yard incinerator is taking shape in the absence of Federal regulations on dioxin, and controversy over the disposal of the ash, state and city officials say they are concerned they will arrive at a consensus about the plant only to have to amend it to comply with Federal regulations in the future.</p>
        <p>And for environmentalists, the continuing debate over the Brooklyn Navy Yard will shape the future of incineration.</p>
        <p>''It will be an important plant that others will look to as a model'' said Michael Herz, a lawyer for the Environmental Defense Fund. ''The outcome of this proceeding is critical for the course of waste energy in New York State.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
