<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Science Watch; Clue on Comet Impact</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="99945"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG ADDICTION AND ABUSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TESTS AND TESTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAIR</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PSYCHEMEDICS CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSTON, ARCH C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hair</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEED91739F93BA35751C1A961948260" item-length="657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Science Watch; Clue on Comet Impact</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: TINY black magnetic spherules found in 65-million-year-old sediments are believed to be strong additional evidence that a massive asteroid or comet struck the earth at that time, and they also could help scientists find the impact point, geophysicists at the University of Minnesota report.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: TINY black magnetic spherules found in 65-million-year-old sediments are believed to be strong additional evidence that a massive asteroid or comet struck the earth at that time, and they also could help scientists find the impact point, geophysicists at the University of Minnesota report.</p>
        <p>TINY black magnetic spherules found in 65-million-year-old sediments are believed to be strong additional evidence that a massive asteroid or comet struck the earth at that time, and they also could help scientists find the impact point, geophysicists at the University of Minnesota report.</p>
        <p>The spherules were determined to be responsible for the unusually strong magnetic properties of clays laid down at the time of the mass extinctions at the end of the Cretaceous geological period, 65 million years ago. These magnetic characteristics have been detected in sediments in Italy and also in cores from the floor of the Pacific Ocean.</p>
        <p>In a report in the November issue of Geophysical Research Letters, Horst-Ulrich Worm and Subir K. Banerjee said an anaylsis of the magnetic minerals showed them to be ferrites with properties unlike those found in volcanic ash. This was ''an important finding,'' the scientists said, because it called into question the proposed alternative theory that volcanic eruptions, not extraterrestrial impacts, led to the global catastrophe that included the extinction of the dinosaurs.</p>
        <p>The analysis also led the scientists to conclude that the impact occurred in the oceanic crust.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the relatively large size of the spherules, compared with the usual dust particles from impacts and volcanic eruptions, indicated that they would have been too heavy to have traveled far from the impact site, the Minnesota geophysicists said. Finding the site or sites of the impact would be a major step toward resolving the controversy over whether an asteroid or comet impact contributed to the mass extinctions.  Ice and Earthquakes</p>
        <p>The ice sheets of Greenland and Antarctica appear to be smothering potential earthquakes, applying a vast weight that clamps underground faults together.</p>
        <p>Worldwide detection of shock waves over the last generation has shown that the polar regions have surprisingly little seismic activity. No large earthquake has ever been recorded in the interior of Greenland or Antarctica.</p>
        <p>New calculations by Arch C. Johnston, director of the Center for Earthquake Research at Memphis State University, suggest that the intense pressure from the ice is suppressing the seismic slippage that produces earthquakes.</p>
        <p>''The great weight can actually make it more difficult for faults to slip or fail,'' Dr. Johnston said yesterday. His study appears in the journal Nature.</p>
        <p>A second effect may also be at work, he said. By sealing off the rock from sources of water, the ice caps reduce the pressure of water flowing through pores and cracks in the rock. Such underground fluid pressure can encourage earthquakes, acting as a lubricant for faults.</p>
        <p>In effect, the ice caps make the underground pores drier. That, too, may discourage earthquakes. Dr. Johnston noted that two other earthquake-free regions are the arid Sahara Desert and the Arabian peninsula.  Keats's Incriminating Hair</p>
        <p>Great issues can hang on hair and fingernails, clinical and forensic chemists have reported.</p>
        <p>It has long been known that substances entering the body are absorbed by hair and fingernails, thereby leaving a long-term record of their presence. A company in Santa Monica, Calif., the Psychemedics Corporation, has begun to apply this fact to a new form of testing for the use of addictive drugs. The company says that its sensitive test, called radioimmunoassay, almost infallibly reveals lifetime patterns of drug use.</p>
        <p>A comparable method was used some years ago in analyzing a few strands of the hair of John Keats. The consumptive 19th-century poet was found to have been a heavy user of opium toward the end of his life.</p>
        <p>Psychemedics says its new method recently showed that a truck driver had been dismissed on the basis of false evidence of heroin use. The evidence had been obtained from a standard urine test, and the driver's union commissioned an independent analysis of his hair.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
