<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ozone Hole Raising Concern for Scientists' Safety</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="87215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTICA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SENATE COMMITTEE ON ENVIRONMENT AND PUBLIC WORKS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, WALTER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4DF113AF93BA15753C1A961948260" item-length="674" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ozone Hole Raising Concern for Scientists' Safety</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER SULLIVAN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, WALTER</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The atmosphere's protective ozone layer is so depleted over Antarctica in the springtime that there is cause for concern about the safety of scientists and support personnel there, researchers said at a Senate hearing today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The atmosphere's protective ozone layer is so depleted over Antarctica in the springtime that there is cause for concern about the safety of scientists and support personnel there, researchers said at a Senate hearing today.</p>
        <p>The atmosphere's protective ozone layer is so depleted over Antarctica in the springtime that there is cause for concern about the safety of scientists and support personnel there, researchers said at a Senate hearing today.</p>
        <p>If the seasonal ''hole'' in the ozone layer continues to expand, they said, it could threaten inhabitants of southernmost South America.</p>
        <p>Dr. Peter E. Wilkniss, director of polar programs at the National Science Foundation, told the panel he was concerned ''for the health and safety of our people.'' He said the foundation was discussing the threat with officials from Chile and Argentina.</p>
        <p>In the stratosphere, ozone, a form of oxygen, absorbs most of the ultraviolet radiation from the sun, which can cause sunburn and skin cancer and which can be lethal to many life forms. There is wide agreement that declines in atmospheric ozone are linked to the release of chlorofluorocarbons, chemicals used in aerosols, refrigeration and a variety of other applications.</p>
        <p>Normally, ultraviolet radiation that gets through the ozone is partly absorbed in the lower atmosphere, but this is less true in Antarctica, where the air is exceptionally clear. Explorers there have had to cope with sunburn since long before the period of ozone depletion. High Levels of Chemical</p>
        <p>The ozone hole forms over Antarctica in September and October, which is springtime in the Southern Hemisphere. On Sept. 30 scientists reported observations from space and long-range aircraft indicating that the hole was even larger this year than last. Today experts from the science foundation described more recent observations from the ground at McMurdo Sound, in Antarctica, showing levels of chlorine monoxide in the lower stratosphere there to be 100 times greater than those elsewhere.</p>
        <p>The chlorine monoxide is believed to have come from the breakdown of chlorofluorocarbons. The chlorine is assumed to be responsible for much of the ozone breakdown.</p>
        <p>Although an international agreement to reduce the production of chlorofluorocarbons was reached Sept. 16 in Montreal, some specialists testifying today before panels of the Senate Committee on Environment and Public Works described the constraints as inadequate.</p>
        <p>Because of uncertainty about the Antarctic ozone hole, delegates at the Montreal meeting ''were instructed not to consider the Antarctic phenomenon in their deliberations,'' Dr. Michael B. McElroy of Harvard University said today. ''The situation has now changed,'' he said. ''The chemistry responsible for the enormous drop in ozone over Antarctica is distinct.'' He said it differed from the process believed to deplete the ozone elsewhere. The situation, he added, ''requires an appropriately radical response.'' Some scientists have proposed a total halt in the production of chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>Dr. McElroy is chairman of Harvard's department of earth and planetary sciences. His explanation for the ozone hole, based on laboratory tests, involves ''chemistry of a most unusual character'' in which, in the extreme cold of the Antarctic stratosphere, nitric acid and water form crystals that drop out of the atmosphere as nitric acid ice, he said.</p>
        <p>This sets the stage for reactions in which chlorine, released from the chlorofluorocarbons, acts as a catalyst to break down the ozone, he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. F. Sherwood Rowland of the University of California at Irvine, who warned of the ozone danger in the early 1970's, pointed out that atmospheric measurements from the ground in Switzerland, South Dakota and Maine all show moderate ozone depletion in spring or late winter. Its cause, he said, may be similar to that for the precipitous South Pole depletion, even though those sites are not polar.</p>
        <p>It would be ''very risky, foolhardy,'' he added, to assume that the process at work in Antarctica could not spread into temperate latitudes.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mack McFarland of E.I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company, a chlorofluorocarbon producer, said it was unlikely that the process at work over Antarctica could occur elsewhere.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
