<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PLANNING FORESTS FROM LAB CULTURES</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="35217"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOTECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GENETIC ENGINEERING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">POLLACK, ANDREW</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biotechnology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4DC173DF93AA15757C0A961948260" item-length="1036" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PLANNING FORESTS FROM LAB CULTURES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">POLLACK, ANDREW</byline>
      <dateline>DAVIS, Calif.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IN a laboratory here, tall redwoods from little test tubes grow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IN a laboratory here, tall redwoods from little test tubes grow.</p>
        <p>IN a laboratory here, tall redwoods from little test tubes grow.</p>
        <p>The laboratory, run by Prof. Don J. Durzan of the University of California at Davis, is one of an increasing number of university and industrial facilities trying to apply the techniques of biotechnology to forestry.</p>
        <p>They are trying to mass-produce clones of trees from cells growing in laboratory cultures. They are also beginning to introduce new traits into trees using recombinant DNA technology, also known as gene splicing.</p>
        <p>The goal of such work is to produce trees that grow faster or are resistant to disease, insects or acid rain. Lumber companies tend to cut the best trees first and are under pressure to replenish stocks as fast as they remove them. Trees take decades to reach maturity, so there can be a big payoff in breeding better trees or in reducing the time before trees can be harvested.</p>
        <p>Paper companies would like to have trees that are rich in cellulose, thereby producing more paper and less waste products. ''The most exciting thing would be to alter the way a tree is put together,'' said Ronald Dinus, director of forest biology at the Institute of Paper Chemistry, an industry-sponsored research center in Appleton, Wis.</p>
        <p>The same genetic techniques could also be applied to fruit trees, but with the opposite goal: to produce trees with almost no wood. ''We're trying to get fruit, not wood,'' said Professor Durzan. ''Why should we have to have ladders to collect the fruit? Why should we have to prune?''</p>
        <p>Foresters have tried to produce better trees in the past using conventional breeding, but the task has been far more difficult than for agricultural crops and animals. A new generation of corn can be grown each year, but trees might take 20 years or more to mature and produce the seeds for the next generation. Seeds Are Imprecise</p>
        <p>Seeds are also somewhat imprecise. Instead of passing on a desired trait from one parent, they might pass on an undesired trait from the other parent. Once a desirable tree is found, it also might not produce enough seeds to quickly restock the forest.</p>
        <p>So foresters are relying more on cloning. With this technique, genetic copies of a desirable tree can be made in large quantities.</p>
        <p>Much of clonal forestry has been pioneered abroad, according to William J. Libby, professor of forestry and genetics at the University of California at Berkeley. Scandinavians have cloned Norwegian spruce, and New Zealanders Monterey pine. The Ontario Ministry of Forests has a huge cloned forest of European poplars.</p>
        <p>In the United States, the Weyerhaeuser Company uses cloning for ornamental trees in its nursery business and has a huge pilot project aimed at cloning trees for timber. The Simpson Timber Company in northern California is cloning coast redwoods.</p>
        <p>Cloning has been done for years by taking a cutting from a tree and rooting it. But this technique does not work well with some conifers, the softwood trees like pine that are most important for the lumber industry. Newer Techniques</p>
        <p>A newer technique, known as micropropogation, allows shoots to be generated from the tissues of trees in cultures. This method is in use by some forest companies.</p>
        <p>A still newer experimental technique, known as somatic embryogenesis, can create multiple embryos from a mass of cells. The embryos can be encapsulated in a gel and stored as artificial seeds.</p>
        <p>Since the cells can be rapidly multiplied in culture, this technique, pioneered at Davis and a few other labs, could lead to mass production of desirable trees. ''It looks like that is the way of the future in terms of mass cloning of conifers,'' said Paul Webb, chief scientist at Agrogen Biotechnologies, a forest genetics company in Vancouver, British Columbia. ''You can have hundreds of thousands of embryos in a one-liter flask.''</p>
        <p>Such cell culture techniques can also make it faster and easier to screen trees for desired traits. ''We can test 10 million cells rather than 10 million trees to look for disease resistance,'' Dr. Durzan said. Using Genetic Engineering</p>
        <p>The ability to grow numerous plants from a single cell also paves the way for the use of genetic engineering in trees. Scientists can implant genes for desired traits into a tree cell and then grow one or more trees from that cell.</p>
        <p>So far, this has been done on an experimental basis only. The United States Forest Service and Calgene, a plant biotechnology company in Davis, have produced poplar trees resistant to a herbicide by implanting a gene for such resistance into tissue of the tree.</p>
        <p>Forest biotechnology, sometimes dubbed ''forestry in a flask,'' still faces numerous obstacles. Scientists still can't dependably get whole trees to grow from cells or from embryos.</p>
        <p>The process is also still too expensive for widespread use. Some researchers think it will be five years before cell cultures and genetic engineering are used in trees, and then only for ornamental trees that sell for high prices. There are also environmental risks. A forest of cloned trees could lack genetic diversity, so that a disease that kills one tree would kill them all. Knowledge About Forest Genetics</p>
        <p>Another barrier is lack of knowledge of the genetics of forest trees, which have been studied less extensively than agricultural crops.</p>
        <p>''With many of our important food plants, we know where the important genes are,'' said Stanley Krugman, director of timber management research for the United States. Forest Service. ''No important gene has ever been isolated from a tree.''</p>
        <p>The first genes implanted into trees, therefore, will come from other organisms, such as bacteria. Several companies are experimenting with implanting genes from a bacterium that produces a natural toxin. Trees with such a gene might be able to produce their own insecticide.</p>
        <p>In Dr. Durzan's lab, the gene responsible for a firefly's glow has been inserted into cells of fir and pine trees, although the researchers have not yet succeeded in growing complete trees from such cells. While the work is only for research purposes, Dr. Durzan joked that the implications could be far-reaching: In the future Christmas trees might come with their own lights.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
