<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Australian Dining Treat: Fresh Salmon From Tasmania</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="101670"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="FARE OF THE COUNTRY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALMON</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">TASMANIA (AUSTRALIA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AUSTRALIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PERLEZ, JANE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Tasmania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7DD1030F930A25751C1A961948260" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Australian Dining Treat: Fresh Salmon From Tasmania</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ; JANE PERLEZ is a reporter on the metropolitan staff of The Times.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PERLEZ, JANE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: UNTIL the last decade or so, a hefty slab of meat - at lunch, sometimes at breakfast and almost always at dinner - was the staple of the Australian diet. A meat pie, oozing with tomato sauce, was the closest thing to a national dish. Even cafes selling fish and chips still boast signs saying, ''Fish and grills,'' as if to say that fish is too light for the hearty</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: UNTIL the last decade or so, a hefty slab of meat - at lunch, sometimes at breakfast and almost always at dinner - was the staple of the Australian diet. A meat pie, oozing with tomato sauce, was the closest thing to a national dish. Even cafes selling fish and chips still boast signs saying, ''Fish and grills,'' as if to say that fish is too light for the hearty</p>
        <p>UNTIL the last decade or so, a hefty slab of meat - at lunch, sometimes at breakfast and almost always at dinner - was the staple of the Australian diet. A meat pie, oozing with tomato sauce, was the closest thing to a national dish. Even cafes selling fish and chips still boast signs saying, ''Fish and grills,'' as if to say that fish is too light for the hearty Aussie appetite.</p>
        <p>This predilection for meat still exists, but fish - and there are plenty of varieties in a nation surrounded by water - has been encroaching on the Australian palate. Last year, as if to show how sophisticated the taste for fish had become, Australians were treated to their first fresh Atlantic salmon. It was not flown in on ice but specially bred at salmon farms in the cool waters off the eastern coast of Tasmania, the densely forested island state just south of the Australian mainland. Tasmania is closer to the Antarctic than California is to New York, but it is still an easy flight to the rest of Australia. Very quickly, Tasmanian Atlantic salmon became the gastronomic hit of the summer season, served in smart restaurants in Sydney, Melbourne and Hobart and to first-class passengers on Qantas flights.</p>
        <p>At one of the farms in Dover on Esperance Bay, a eucalyptus tree-fringed inlet 80 miles south of Hobart, Chris Smith, a former government fisheries researcher turned salmon farmer, has built 20 floating net pens that sit in the bay like a cluster of swimming pools. It is in these nets that the fish, descendants of Nova Scotia salmon imported in the 1960's to an Australian lake as sport fish, grow to eight pounds. Mr. Smith feels triumphant that the salmon, after several years of testing for disease in their new environment, have been transplanted so successfully to southern waters. So far the main difficulty faced by the infant industry has been scavenging seals - one farmer lost all his stock to seals.</p>
        <p>The Australian salmon eating season starts in October, when Mr. Smith and his 6 full-time and 20 seasonal workers start harvesting. The fish are pulled from their pens by a scoop at the end of a crane, anesthetized with carbon dioxide and then gutted in a large shed on the water's edge. They are chilled, packed in boxes, hauled by truck over the dirt road out of the farm and up the 80 miles to Hobart, where some are offered by a few local restaurants. The bulk is sent by air to Sydney and Melbourne, where restaurant customers often eat salmon caught 1,000 miles away that morning. Last year's season, the first for Tasmanian Atlantic salmon, finished in March with Mr. Smith's farm sold out and restaurants clamoring for more.</p>
        <p>With the success of Mr. Smith's farm and several others like his, Tasmania, suffering a stagnant economy, saw a bright new economic future. In Sydney, where eating at restaurants has been elevated to a sport almost as popular as surfing and sailing, food critics heaped praise on the new fish. And at the bustling Sydney fish market, where Sydneysiders shop on Saturday mornings for prawns, oysters and lobsters for weekend dinner parties, the salmon was scooped up despite its price, which was the equivalent of about 13 American dollars a pound. Japanese restaurants rushed to serve it as sashimi and sushi.</p>
        <p>''It was the first time Australians had fresh salmon,'' said Peter Bowyer, headwaiter at Beppi's, a popular Sydney place. ''The food writers hailed it as the miracle of the year.''</p>
        <p>At Beppi's the salmon is prepared three ways. ''We grill it with lemon and butter,'' said Mr. Bowyer. ''Or we serve it poached in a tamarillo hollandaise. The tamarillo is a red-seeded fruit from New Zealand, slightly sour. Or we pan fry it with tomato and basil. Consumer-wise the grilled is the most popular. Taste-wise the poached is better. But in Sydney they tend to think of poached food as being for invalids. In fact, when it is poached it is very delicate.''</p>
        <p>The salmon is served with Australian white wines: a sauvignon blanc or a fume blanc aged in wood from South Australia.</p>
        <p>At the Blue Water Grill, a restaurant with splendid views over Bondi Beach, about 15 minutes from downtown Sydney, the chef, Neil Perry, is a little more adventurous. He prepares two appetizers with the salmon. For one he sugar cures a filet overnight and serves it with a toasted brioche, mascaparone cheese and fried capers. For another, he combines shiitake mushrooms that have been lightly cooked in olive oil with Bermuda onions marinated in lime and puts thin, raw slices of salmon in the mixture. ''The flavor is delicate,'' said Mr. Perry. ''The salmon is superb raw.'' As a main course Mr. Perry char-grills the salmon and serves it with pesto and a fresh tomato sauce.</p>
        <p>In Hobart's premier fish restaurant, Mure's, a tiny colonial house with the feeling of a New England inn, what has now become the local fish is preferred plain.</p>
        <p>''We serve it simply so as not to kill the taste or kill the texture,'' said George Mure, the owner. ''We poach the filets in a court bouillon and serve them with hollandaise sauce and asparagus. With salmon cutlets we grill them and add a herb butter that sinks into the fish.''</p>
        <p>Tasmania has two small vineyards, Moorilla and Piper's Brook, both of which produce Rieslings that Mr. Mure suggests with the salmon.</p>
        <p>Tasmanian waters produce wide varieties of fish, one of which, the stripey trumpet, a meaty fish with considerable oil, is found in only one other place: off the South Island of New Zealand. Tasmania is also known for excellent lobster that comes into season about the same time as the home-grown salmon. But for the second summer-eating season, and for many to come, Australians who have only ever tasted fresh salmon on overseas trips, will be luxuriating in a fish they thought only others could have.</p>
        <p>FARE OF THE COUNTRY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
