<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Aiding Salmon Conservation</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="92132"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISHING, SPORT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SALMON FEDERATION, ATLANTIC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRYANT, NELSON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Faroe Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4DC153EF931A25752C1A961948260" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Aiding Salmon Conservation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nelson Bryant</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRYANT, NELSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IF you'd enjoy good food and a chance to chat with some of this country's most dedicated Atlantic salmon anglers and conservationists, you should plan to attend the Atlantic Salmon Federation's annual dinner at the Plaza Hotel, 59th Street and Fifth Avenue, Nov. 19.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IF you'd enjoy good food and a chance to chat with some of this country's most dedicated Atlantic salmon anglers and conservationists, you should plan to attend the Atlantic Salmon Federation's annual dinner at the Plaza Hotel, 59th Street and Fifth Avenue, Nov. 19.</p>
        <p>IF you'd enjoy good food and a chance to chat with some of this country's most dedicated Atlantic salmon anglers and conservationists, you should plan to attend the Atlantic Salmon Federation's annual dinner at the Plaza Hotel, 59th Street and Fifth Avenue, Nov. 19.</p>
        <p>Your attendance will also assist the effort to aid and protect what many regard as the world's foremost game and food fish. With branches in this country and Canada, the Federation is the largest and most prestigious salmon conservation organization in the world.</p>
        <p>The dinner - a single ticket is $95 - also includes an auction and raffle and a cocktail reception featuring smoked salmon. Raffle and auction items include limited edition sporting prints by the late Ogden Pleissner and other well-known artists, a leaping salmon sculpted in wood, and prime-time angling on major salmon streams in New Brunswick, Quebec and Iceland.</p>
        <p>For more information and reservations, call Chase Reynolds at (617) 356-0717.</p>
        <p>The Atlantic salmon's habits have made it a subject of international concern. Spawned in clear, cold streams in North America, the United Kingdom, Iceland and many European countries, the young fish descend to the ocean to grow and mature before returning to their natal waters to spawn. Ideally, the fish would only be harvested in the rivers of their origin. For many years, however, salmon have been taken by commercial netters as they move along the coast to their home streams, and in the mid-1960's, an open-ocean drift net fishery for them developed off Greenland. UNTIL that time, little was known about the salmon's wanderings at sea. It is now known that salmon taken in that fishery are mainly of North American and European origin, while most of those similarly caught in the Norwegian Sea and off the Faroe Islands come from European streams. Because it is indiscriminate, this high seas commercial fishery can result in a single stream's stocks being decimated.</p>
        <p>Although salmon once swarmed up the major rivers of New England to spawn, dams blocked their passage. Early in this century, Maine was the only state that had any fish returning. A salmon restoration effort was begun on the Connecticut River in 1967. This has included building fish passage facilities at dams. The last such facility to be completed was at the Wilder, Vt., hydroelectric dam, a few miles south of Hanover, N.H., and salmon have already passed that point. A similar restoration is under way on the Merrimack River.</p>
        <p>In the past decade, the catch of salmon spending more than one year at sea has been declining. Commercial fishing - both high seas and along the shore - disease, poaching, deforestation, pollution, including acid rain, have all played a part in this.</p>
        <p>Although they are the same species, the salmon from each river are distinct strains. One simplistic example of this would be that, in general, salmon spawned in deep, broad rivers tend to be large and heavy-bodied, while those from smaller, shallower and faster waters tend to be smaller and slimmer. When native fish are no longer available to begin a restoration effort on a given river, biologists can only choose offspring of brood stock from a river that is similar to the one scheduled for stocking, and hope for the best. WHEN the first mature fish of such a stocking return, they become what may be regarded as the brood stock of a native strain. However, one of the difficulties is that several years must pass before enough returnees are available to provide eggs and milt for substantial hatchery production, and subsequent introduction, of that strain.</p>
        <p>There is no commercial harvesting of Atlantic salmon in the United States, and during the past few years, Canada has severely restricted such activity, in some instances cutting it off entirely. This has included a program in which commercial fishermen are reimbursed for surrendering their licenses. This reflects a growing awareness on the part of Canadian officials that a salmon in an angler's canoe is worth many times more to the general economy than one in a commercial fisherman's net. Canada has also limited the recreational catch. In New Brunswick, for example, an angler may keep only two grilse a day, 10 a season. A grilse is a small - about 4 pounds -early-returning salmon, usually a male.</p>
        <p>Some champions of the salmon believe that salmon aquaculture may help save wild stocks. Worldwide landings of wild Atlantic salmon have averaged 10,000 metric tons annually in recent years; 60,000 metric tons of farmed salmon were produced in 1986, and 150,000 metric tons are predicted for 1990.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
