<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When the Jungle Turns to Wasteland</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="15703"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="LOST WILDERNESS: THE WARNINGS GROW LOUDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDE113EF931A15751C0A961948260" item-length="1160" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When the Jungle Turns to Wasteland</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: FROM New York's Columbus Avenue to the world's tropical forests, the life and death of trees occupied the attention of many scientists at the annual meeting of the American Association for the Advancement of Science last week in Chicago. They assessed the effects of acid rain in the Adirondacks, issued dire updates on the spread of deserts in sub-Saharan Africa and discussed the benefits of agroforestry, the practice of growing crops side by side with nitrogen-fixing trees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: FROM New York's Columbus Avenue to the world's tropical forests, the life and death of trees occupied the attention of many scientists at the annual meeting of the American Association for the Advancement of Science last week in Chicago. They assessed the effects of acid rain in the Adirondacks, issued dire updates on the spread of deserts in sub-Saharan Africa and discussed the benefits of agroforestry, the practice of growing crops side by side with nitrogen-fixing trees.</p>
        <p>FROM New York's Columbus Avenue to the world's tropical forests, the life and death of trees occupied the attention of many scientists at the annual meeting of the American Association for the Advancement of Science last week in Chicago. They assessed the effects of acid rain in the Adirondacks, issued dire updates on the spread of deserts in sub-Saharan Africa and discussed the benefits of agroforestry, the practice of growing crops side by side with nitrogen-fixing trees. The keynote speaker, Peter H. Raven, argued that one of the world's most pressing problems is the destruction of tropical forests and its effect on climate, biological diversity and human well-being. Following are excerpts from the conference.  A BIOLOGICAL CATASTROPHE</p>
        <p>In the late 1970's, the United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization estimated that about 40,000 square miles of tropical forest were being cut every year. If that were still the rate of clear cutting, all the tropical evergreen forest would be gone in about 60 years. On the other hand, the F.A.O. estimates assumed no population growth or other increased pressures on the forest whereas in fact populations are growing rapidly and other pressures are increasing also. So that's an unreal expectation and 60 years must be taken as much too much an overestimate.</p>
        <p>Logging destroys about 20,000 square miles of tropical evergreen forest, an area about the size of West Virginia, every year.</p>
        <p>The clearing of tropical forests for pastures affects an area about half the size of that which is logged. The growing imports of beef from Mexico and Central America in the past 25 years, for example, have been the major factor in the loss of about half the forests of southern Mexico and Central America. And the net effect has been to keep the price of an average hamburger in the United States about a nickel less than it would have been otherwise. . . .</p>
        <p>Deforestation contributes relatively substantially to carbon dioxide in the atmosphere. Cutting the forests of South America on a wide scale, it is calculated, would precipitate a regional temperature rise of 3 to 5 degrees centigrade which would extend the dry season and speed the destruction of any forests that are left, including those in biological reserves, while greatly disrupting the agriculture of the fertile parts of South America and perhaps farther afield. . . .</p>
        <p>The most serious long-term global problem that results from deforestation, however, will be the loss of a major proportion of biological diversity on earth. The extinction rates are about a thousand times the level of the last tens of millions of years. Whether you look on that loss as tragic from a scientific, esthetic or moral standpoint or because of the opportunities being lost that will affect human destiny, it is unquestionably the one problem we are participating in now that will have the most lasting consequences.</p>
        <p>Since the forests where about 2.2 million species of organisms minimum occur will be reduced to less than a tenth of their total extent over the next 15 years, we may assume that over a million species or a quarter of the total biological diversity on earth are at risk of extinction during the next 15 to 20 years or so.  - PETER H. RAVEN, director of the Missouri Botanical Garden and professor of botany at Washington University.  PRIMATES ARE ENDANGERED</p>
        <p>The mountain gorilla is only one of many primates threatened with extinction. Of some 200 recognized varieties in the world, over half are currently in some jeopardy. . . . The most ubiquitous pressure facing wild primate populations comes from the destruction of their habitats. Over 90 percent of all primates inhabit the tropical forests of Asia, Africa and Central and South America. Just five countries - Brazil, Zaire, Cameroon, Madagascar and Indonesia - support 75 percent of all primate species. . . .</p>
        <p>With the expansion of agriculture, a lethal cycle begins in which the primate loses: as their natural habitat is destroyed and crops are planted, some primates become agricultural pests, placing them in direct conflict with humans.</p>
        <p>Even where primates do not interfere with human settlements, their populations are threatened as their forests are cut. Species that have highly specialized diets cannot adapt. Populations are often isolated from one another in areas too small to support viable groups. After several generations, their reproductive rates suffer as inbreeding depression sets in. Even in relatively large forest tracts where selective logging is the predominant threat, important primate food species are removed or damaged.  - KAREN B. STRIER, lecturer in anthropology at Harvard University, at a panel on the legacy of Dian Fossey, the gorilla expert who was murdered in Rwanda in December 1985.  TAKING THE HEAT IN NEW YORK</p>
        <p>Much is expected of street trees, yet little is known about their physiological responses to the urban habitat. It is estimated, however, that of the 1,000 or so street trees planted in New York City each spring half will die within 10 years. At approximately $300 per tree, this premature death is a sizable investment in plants that will never reach adult size. . . . Foremost among the above-ground ways in which the city causes stress in street trees is reradiated heat from buildings, asphalt, car tops and concrete. Air pollution is often cited as a problem for plant growth; however, this depends on the air drainage patterns of a particular location. In New York City, it is rare to see field symptoms of air pollution whereas in Los Angeles it is more common.</p>
        <p>By looking at the data from one sampling period in August 1983, many striking patterns can be seen. On both sides of Columbus Avenue, the temperature rose higher and the relative humidity fell lower than the official report in Central Park just a few blocks away. In fact conditions have been recorded for the west side of the street that would be more likely to be found in the desert Southwest than in a maritime Northeastern city. . . .</p>
        <p>The traditional approach of choosing a tree only for form and seasonal interest must broaden to include drought, salt, heat and other stress tolerances. Trees planted in groups in slightly raised beds would shade each other from heat and wind while allowing for a greater esthetic impact. These less formal plantings could utilize species now commonly thought of as unsuitable for street trees because they don't have the required ''lollypop'' shape, that is, one trunk with symmetrical branches on top. Many of the so-called junk or weedy trees and shrubs, such as Russian olive, alder, white mulberry and the ailanthus,may be better able to withstand environmental stress than our common street trees, such as the little leaf linden.  - NINA BAssuk, associate professor of horticultural physiology and director of the Urban Horticulture Institute, Cornell University.</p>
        <p>LOST WILDERNESS: THE WARNINGS GROW LOUDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
