<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Threat of Plastic Trash defies Technological Solution</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="72310"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="IDEAS &amp; TRENDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLASTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEED71230F935A3575AC0A961948260" item-length="1085" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Threat of Plastic Trash defies Technological Solution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ONCE almost synonymous with cheap flimsiness, plastic has become respectable. Synthetic polymer resins still go into disposable cups, hamburger boxes and party favors, but lately they are also the stuff of motorcycle sprockets, tank armor and rocket engines. The plastic helmets and daggers used by today's soldiers are not only lighter and stronger than their steel counterparts, but they will remain in mint condition for centuries, to the possible delight of future archeologists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ONCE almost synonymous with cheap flimsiness, plastic has become respectable. Synthetic polymer resins still go into disposable cups, hamburger boxes and party favors, but lately they are also the stuff of motorcycle sprockets, tank armor and rocket engines. The plastic helmets and daggers used by today's soldiers are not only lighter and stronger than their steel counterparts, but they will remain in mint condition for centuries, to the possible delight of future archeologists.</p>
        <p>ONCE almost synonymous with cheap flimsiness, plastic has become respectable. Synthetic polymer resins still go into disposable cups, hamburger boxes and party favors, but lately they are also the stuff of motorcycle sprockets, tank armor and rocket engines. The plastic helmets and daggers used by today's soldiers are not only lighter and stronger than their steel counterparts, but they will remain in mint condition for centuries, to the possible delight of future archeologists.</p>
        <p>But the very durability of plastic has conferred a curse: Our indestructible garbage is killing wildlife and threatening to choke human communities on their own waste. Many garbage dumps are bloated beyond their capacity to expand, and one of the few points on which environmentalists and the plastics industry seem to agree is that a day of reckoning is not far off.</p>
        <p>By 1990, roughly half the cities in the United States will have run out of landfill space, says Worldwatch Institute, an environmental research organization. The renowned garbage barge from Islip, L.I., sailed as far south as Belize in search of a dumping ground. Last week, after 162 days, disposal finally began. An incinerator in Brooklyn is reducing 3,100 tons of solid waste - including, no doubt, a great deal of plastic - to 400 tons of ash.</p>
        <p>The sheer volume of plastic production is almost beyond belief - more than 20 million tons a year in the United States alone. By 1976, the cubic volume of plastic manufactured in the United States had surpassed that of steel, copper and aluminum combined. Abroad, scarcely a third world nation is without a petrochemical plant churning out polyethylene and other plastics.</p>
        <p>The trouble is that most plastic objects don't rust, rot, dissolve or evaporate. Worldwatch estimates that 8 percent of the solid waste pouring into American landfills is plastic likely to take up to five centuries to degrade. The National Academy of Sciences has estimated that commercial fishing fleets each year dump at least 52 million pounds of packaging material into the sea and lose some 300 million pounds of indestructible plastic fishing lines and nets. The resulting annual death toll, experts say, is one to two million sea birds, 100,000 sea mammals (including whales and seals with intestinal blockages caused by plastic bags) and countless fish. The Marine Sciences Research Center at Stony Brook, L.I., has estimated that 30 percent of the fish in the world's oceans have tiny pieces of plastic in their stomachs that interfere with digestion.</p>
        <p>About 30 states now require degradable plastic in the six-ring connectors used to bundle canned and bottled drinks. Discarded carelessly, these connectors become deadly snares for birds and small animals. According to Dr. Donald E. Hudgin, president of Princeton Polymer Laboratories in New Jersey, degradable connectors begin to crumble after only three or four weeks' exposure to the sun. A similarly exposed connector made of ordinary polyethylene might survive for 400 years or more. Environmental Chemistry</p>
        <p>Since degradable forms of plastic exist, why are they not more commonly used in such disposable products as trash bags and food wrappers?</p>
        <p>One reason is that only a limited degree of degradability can be built into common plastics. A typical polymer consists of chains of molecules, each of which may contain hundreds of thousands of atoms. Bacteria cannot attack such relatively gigantic structures unless they are broken into fragments less than 1,000 atoms long. Most polymer chains are unlikely to break down on their own, so biological decay is stymied.</p>
        <p>In principle, chemists know how to make plastic that is vulnerable to attack by bacteria and other living organisms. Such biodegradable polymers, some made from waste products of the dairy industry, could include polyglycolic acid and polycaprolactone. For the time being, though, such novel plastics would be far too expensive to market on a large scale, industrial chemists say. And, having been purposely made vulnerable, they might prove unreliable. Experts say the chances are remote that anyone will find a practical way to use enzymes or bacteria to break up the molecular chains in such common plastics as polyethylene, polystyrene, polyvinyl chloride and polypropylene.</p>
        <p>In the case of the six-ring connectors, scientists rely instead on the sun. When carbon monoxide is chemically inserted into a polymer chain, the effect is to replace a strong link with one weak enough to be broken by ultraviolet light. Plastic made from such a photodegradable polymer soon begins to fall apart in sunlight.</p>
        <p>While photodegradable plastics can help with the litter problem, they do nothing for plastic already buried in landfills. Moreover, they are relatively expensive. According to Dr. Hudgin, a typical degradable plastic costs about $2 a pound, while ordinary polyethylene costs only about 50 cents a pound.</p>
        <p>The key to solving the problem, say the plastic makers, is to stop dumping and start burning. Carl Kamena of Dow Chemical, which makes the ubiquitous Styrofoam, asserts that the fuel value of waste plastic is about the same as that of oil. When burned some plastics generate hydrochloric and other acids that would have to be removed from smoke with the use of expensive chemical scrubbers. ''But considering that the cost of landfill disposal has risen from $4 a ton to $100 a ton in some parts of the country, incineration looks attractive, even when it must include the cost of scrubbing,'' he said. Although environmentalists generally oppose adding another burden of pollutants to the atmosphere, most acknowledge that nearly any solution to the garbage problem will involve trade-offs.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, laws aimed at curbing the flood of plastic proliferate.</p>
        <p>Suffolk County on Long Island is considering legislation that would ban plastic packaging of hamburgers and other fast foods. Similar bills are pending in California and Michigan.</p>
        <p>Several Congressmen, including Representative James J. Howard, a New Jersey Democrat, are pressing to curb plastic dumping. Italy has enacted a law to make nondegradable plastic bags illegal starting in 1991.</p>
        <p>In the long run, environmentalists and many scientists say, the solution to the plastic glut, along with parallel problems posed by nuclear reactor waste, atmospheric carbon dioxide and all the other destructive effluvia of human activity, will depend not on technological breakthroughs, but on collective self-discipline.</p>
        <p>IDEAS &amp; TRENDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
