<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMRY: WEDNESDAY, FEBRUARY 4, 1987</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="10125"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2D91338F937A35751C0A961948260" item-length="950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMRY: WEDNESDAY, FEBRUARY 4, 1987</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International A2-A9  Brezhnev's son-in-law is being held in Moscow after his arrest on corruption charges, a Foreign Ministry spokesman said. The son-in-law was a top Interior Ministry official until 1984. Page A1  In a deal for Awacs radar planes in 1981, King Fahd and other Saudi Arabian officials agreed to aid anti-Communist guerrilla groups, U.S.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International A2-A9  Brezhnev's son-in-law is being held in Moscow after his arrest on corruption charges, a Foreign Ministry spokesman said. The son-in-law was a top Interior Ministry official until 1984. Page A1  In a deal for Awacs radar planes in 1981, King Fahd and other Saudi Arabian officials agreed to aid anti-Communist guerrilla groups, U.S.</p>
        <p>International A2-A9  Brezhnev's son-in-law is being held in Moscow after his arrest on corruption charges, a Foreign Ministry spokesman said. The son-in-law was a top Interior Ministry official until 1984. Page A1  In a deal for Awacs radar planes in 1981, King Fahd and other Saudi Arabian officials agreed to aid anti-Communist guerrilla groups, U.S. officials said. A1  Western journalists in Iran recently observed a regime that has subdued virtually all opposition outside its ranks but that suffers increasingly volatile internal rivalries. A1  Iraq is unlikely to reverse damage -military, political and psychological - that Iran has wrought in its latest offensive despite Baghdad's superior air and firepower, experts say. A6  Attempts to win the release of an American journalist detained in Iran are being undertaken by governments friendly to both the United States and Iran, American officials and diplomatic sources said. A3 Hearings to confirm Robert Gates, the newly nominated Director of Central Intelligence, will not be an occasion for a full-scale public review of the agency's role in the Iran-contra affair, a Senator said. A7  Military analysis: Seizures in Beirut of hostages have prompted a refining of contingency plans for retaliatory air strikes against terrorist camps in the Middle East, Pentagon sources said. A3  Mr. Reagan weighed Pentagon plans for the early deployment of a partial ''Star Wars'' system in a meeting with senior members of his Administration, and reportedly no decision was made. A2  Salvador's soul is in small towns that cover the countryside. The long civil war in which more than 60,000 people have been killed has ground the peasants in these dust-filled hamlets very small. A4  A party shake-up in Vietnam was the result of pressure from grass-roots Communist organizations, according to a Western diplomat based in Hanoi whose impressions were supported by American scholars. A8 NATIONAL A12-21, D24  Wider use of an AIDS test is being considered by Federal health officials, they said. The plan would include testing all applicants for marriage licenses and patients who enter hospitals. A1  The House overrode a veto of a bill aimed at cleaning up the nation's water at a cost of $20 billion. The Senate is expected to take up the measure today, and Democratic leaders predicted a similar override. A1  180 U.S. farms disappear each day, victims of consolidation, changing economics, poor management, bad luck, high interest rates, low crop prices, emotional and financial despair or some of each. A1  U.S. trade figures may be deceiving because it will take more than currency adjustments to close the record $169.8 billion gap between what America bought from abroad in 1986 and what it was able to sell. A1  The House deferred a vote on raises for lawmakers and other Federal officials until after the raises were to take effect, at 12:01 this morning. The vote will thus be either meaningless or the first step in a legal battle to rescind the raises. A13  An amendment on speed limits that would allows states to raise the limit on rural interstate highways to 65 miles an hour was approved by the Senate, 65 to 33. A12  Patrick J. Buchanan will resign from his post as White House communications director effective March 1, he announced. He is the latest hard-line conservative to depart as President Reagan begins his final two years in office. A19  Acid rain poses a serious threat to human health that is too significant to defer protective action, according to representatives of major public health groups who addressed a Congressional panel. A12  Fort Worth is an 'In' place, according to W, the international fashion and society publication that publishes an annual list of such things. But its residents are not overly impressed by the honor. A12  The hallmarks of a great palate, creating a splendid new dish, spicing a familiar one to perfection or savoring another's cooking, are within reach of all who dare, leading chefs and researchers say. C1  WASHINGTON TALK A20  Cooperation on Iran inquiries  In the halls, artists come and go REGIONAL B1-6, B24  Payoffs to 20 government officials were reported to Federal investigators by the men who paid them, former top executives of the Wedtech Corporation, a South Bronx military contractor. A1  New evidence from Howard Beach indicates that white youths chased Michael Griffith onto the Belt Parkway, where he was killed by a car on the night of Dec. 19-20, law-enforcement sources say. A1  765 police officers were promoted to the rank of sergeant, more than three and a half years after they were tested for eligibility and after months of litigation over the exam. B1  Promotions end frustration B6  G.M. will stay in North Tarrytown, N.Y., to assemble a new fiberglass-body mini-van at its plant there, the company announced, insuring production and thousands of jobs well into the 1990's. B2  Fewer public school dropouts were reported in New York City in the 1985-86 school year. The city's dropout rate now stands at 30.7 percent, down from 35.3 percent, the Board of Education said. B1  A cost-saving plan for theaters that aims to lower the cost of producing shows will be put to the test tomorrow night when the musical revue ''Stardust'' begins performances at the Biltmore. C21  Dr. Stern testifies on Baby M B2  State U. approves sports plan B2  Jersey mayors seek aid B3  Gotti witness admits lying B4  New dispute on M.T.A. plan B5  Neediest Cases B6</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
