<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST: THURSDAY, SEPTEMBER 17, 1987</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="75220"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BUSINESS DIGEST (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4DF103BF934A2575AC0A961948260" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST: THURSDAY, SEPTEMBER 17, 1987</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  THE ECONOMY</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  THE ECONOMY</p>
        <p>THE ECONOMY</p>
        <p>A bill to protect the domestic textile and clothing industries from import competition was passed by the House. But the 263-to-156 margin would not be wide enough to override President Reagan's promised veto. The bill would restrict the import growth for a wide range of consumer products, and it is seen as a barometer of sentiment for a tougher trade posture. [ Page D1. ]</p>
        <p>Commercial banks could acquire healthy savings institutions, not just those in financial trouble, under a plan that the Federal Reserve Board will consider. If adopted, the move could result in extensive further consolidation of the banking industry. [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Representative Dingell has powerful supporters in his effort to stop legislation that would permit the nation's commercial banks to sell farm loans to the investing public through a Government-backed secondary market. [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>A Pentagon plan for weapons procurement laws was resisted by the White House budget office and will probably not be sent to Congress, officials say. The plan had been put forth by Richard Godwin, the Under Secretary of Defense who resigned this week. [ D6. ]</p>
        <p>Business inventories rose 0.2 percent in July as total business sales remained essentially unchanged. [ D14. ]</p>
        <p>The nation's industry operated at 81 percent of capacity in August, the first time it has been that high since November 1984. [ D4. ] MARKETS</p>
        <p>Stock prices plummeted for a second day, falling 36.39 points, to 2,530.19, as volume was sharply higher, at 195.7 million. Most of the decline occurred in the last hour and was attributed to arbitrage-related selling of stocks and buying of index futures. [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Treasury bond prices ended slightly higher for the day after tumbling in the morning.  [ D24. ]  Yields for C.D.'s and money market accounts and mutual funds were moderately to sharply higher for the third straight week. [ D23. ]</p>
        <p>The dollar finished higher against most currencies in New York, after having mixed results in Europe. Gold prices slipped 75 cents an ounce, to $458, in late New York trading. [ D26. ]</p>
        <p>Cotton futures advanced the daily limit on a report of a tight supply of certificated cotton for filling October contracts. [ D26. ] COMPANIES</p>
        <p>Ames Department Stores does not expect to end its problem of extraordinarily high levels of disappearing merchandise quickly. Ames recently disclosed that a $4.2 million shortage had reduced its net income, and its stock dropped sharply. [ D19. ]</p>
        <p>MCA plans to build a theme park near either Paris or the Spanish coast for more than $500 million. The company is determined to challenge Disney's dominance of the theme-park business. [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>Managers will buy Bozell, Jacobs, Kenyon &amp; Eckhardt from Lorimar Telepictures for $143.2 million. The ad agency's sale had been expected since June. [ D27. ]</p>
        <p>Asher B. Edelman said he sold part of his Foster Wheeler stake in a deliberate attempt to confuse people who might have inside information on the deal. [ D8. ] INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>Delegates from rich and poor nations agreed to freeze and later roll back their consumption of widely used chemicals that destroy ozone molecules in the upper atmosphere.  [ A1. ]  The accord is expected to touch off a race to develop chemical alternatives that are not hazardous to the earth's ozone layer. [ A12. ]</p>
        <p>Britain's Midland Bank will accept raw materials from Peru as payment of part of the $160 million it is owed. It is the first time since the debt crisis began in 1982 that a commercial bank has agreed to accept commodities instead of cash. [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>North Korea has apparently agreed to begin repaying its Western creditors, less than a month after formally defaulting. [ D18. ] TODAY'S COLUMNS</p>
        <p>The bailout of First City of Texas breaks precedent by seeking money from the private sector and by employing a ''collecting bank'' to hold First City's problem loans. Talking Deals. [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>Investors who buy inital public offerings, but dump them back into the market within days, can cause price declines and big headaches for the lead underwriters. Market Place. [ D14. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
