<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EX-CHAIRMEN AND NOT LOVING IT</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="11764"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="WASHINGTON TALK: CONGRESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONGRESSIONAL COMMITTEES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONGRESS (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">REPUBLICAN PARTY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOWD, MAUREEN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON TALK PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4DA1E3AF93AA35751C0A961948260" item-length="1054" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EX-CHAIRMEN AND NOT LOVING IT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DOWD, MAUREEN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Power corrupts, Adlai Stevenson once drily observed, but lack of power corrupts absolutely.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Power corrupts, Adlai Stevenson once drily observed, but lack of power corrupts absolutely.</p>
        <p>Power corrupts, Adlai Stevenson once drily observed, but lack of power corrupts absolutely.</p>
        <p>With the Democrats gleefully in control of the Senate, Republican legislators are suffering from that worst of Washington maladies - pernicious power loss.</p>
        <p>Once chairmen of committees and subcommittees, once the arbiters of the agenda and the masters of all they surveyed, they have been stripped of their gavels and demoted to ranking members or, worse, mere members.</p>
        <p>''Anyone around here who's saying 'It's all a relief' and 'Isn't it neat that I don't have to worry about being chairman anymore' is just not being truthful,'' said Senator Pete V. Domenici, the New Mexico Republican who was transformed from an obscure, rumpled legislator to a national, rumpled leader when he became chairman of the Budget Committee in 1981. 'A Little Bit of Apprehension'</p>
        <p>''There's still a little bit of apprehension about what it's like to be in the minority again after so long,'' he said.</p>
        <p>There are many indignities associated with this change in status, not the least of which is that the Democrats take over the side of the U-shaped committee tables with the best angle for the television cameras that record many hearings.</p>
        <p>The Republicans move to the side with the hot television lights, whirring camera noise and an angle that offers, as Senator John C. Danforth, Republican of Missouri, puts it, ''a nice shot of the back of the human head.''</p>
        <p>''With my face,'' he noted wryly, ''this may be one of the few benefits to being in the minority.''</p>
        <p>Senator Danforth, who has stepped down after two years as chairman of the Commerce Committee, was quickly reminded of the limitations of the minority by an incident over Harry S. Truman's desk. A Bequest Is Undone</p>
        <p>The desk was bequeathed to him at the end of the last session by his close friend Thomas F. Eagleton, Democrat of Missouri, who was retiring.</p>
        <p>Last week, however, Mr. Danforth read in the newspapers that a freshman Senator, Barbara A. Mikulski, Democrat of Maryland, had been assigned to sit at the Truman desk and was interpreting this as a sign from above that she should continue her ''feisty'' style.</p>
        <p>Senator Danforth immediately tried to reclaim the desk. But the office of the Sergeant at Arms, in charge of such logistics, is a patronage job that is now under the control of the Democrats.</p>
        <p>''If I were in the majority I would just put the grab on the desk,'' Mr. Danforth said, smiling ruefully at this lost droit du seigneur. ''But now there are all these elaborate negotiations involving staff people and so on.''</p>
        <p>Senator Danforth, who is an heir to the Ralston-Purina fortune, is not the sort to be intoxicated by power. And like some others who have lost majority power, he is mostly philosophical about it.</p>
        <p>''All things considered, I'd rather be in the majority,'' he said, his lanky form draped comfortably over a couch in his office. ''But I don't think that I have been reduced to a lump.'' 'A Mixed Blessing'</p>
        <p>In fact, he says, there are distinct advantages. ''The job of chairman is a mixed blessing,'' he said. ''It gives you control of an agenda so that you can mark up bills and focus on matters that are of specific interest to you. But the job also consists of presiding over long hearings and making sure that a lot of miscellaneous legislation gets enacted that you have no particular interest in.''</p>
        <p>As chairman of the Commerce Committee, Senator Danforth found himself caught in a net of issues about marine life when he would have preferred to focus on trade policy and transportation safety.</p>
        <p>''Sure, I like whales and purpoises, but there are just not that many in my state,'' he said. ''And we had jurisdiction over fish, but the fish we talked about were salmon. In my state, fish means largemouth bass and catfish.''</p>
        <p>Now that he is the ranking minority member of the committee instead of the chairman, he does not have to sit through testimony from a two-page list of witnesses in hearings.</p>
        <p>''I have chaired Commerce Committee meetings that have started at 9:30 in the morning and gone on till 10 at night,'' he said. ''It's kind of nice to look at your witness list and say, 'Oh, well, I'd like to hear the first and second witnesses today but not the 23d and 24th.' ''</p>
        <p>''When you're the chairman of the committee,'' he said, ''you certainly can get some things done, but you also have to spend a lot of time holding people's hands.''</p>
        <p>Some former committee chairmen are missing the fraternity atmosphere they had enjoyed with the President and his aides. 'That Will Be a Void'</p>
        <p>For the six years that his party controlled the Senate, President Reagan could call in the chairmen of key committees, and it would be a Grand Old Party get-together.</p>
        <p>Senator Domenici, sounding wistful, recalled: ''I used to be able to meet with the President and express my views about the fiscal matters in front of people all in my own party. If we still don't get to do it every now and then, that will be a void, because we had pretty freewheeling conferences, contrary to what people think. And we didn't always agree, and we did it right there in front of each other. I'm sure I'll miss that.''</p>
        <p>Senator Robert T. Stafford of Vermont said he was proud of completing most of the agenda he set for himself as chairman of the Committee on the Environment and Public Works, but he wished he could have stayed ''on the tiller instead of tending the mainsheet'' for two more years - ''in order to have a final shot at getting an acid rain bill through the Senate.'' The Matter of Health</p>
        <p>He said being a committee chairman was not necessarily good for one's health - a point on which Senator Domenici, who resumed chain smoking in 1983 at the height of his attempts to hammer out a budget compromise, would agree.</p>
        <p>''In the last two years,'' said Senator Stafford, ''I pushed myself harder than I should have, and I've done my health no particular good.''</p>
        <p>Now, however, he will be able to leave all that pushing to his successor, Quentin N. Burdick of North Dakota, and spend more time sneaking away to go boating on his 55-foot cabin cruiser, Full Moon.</p>
        <p>''I think that this year, some further inspection of the ecology of the Chesapeake Bay is in order,'' said the ranking member of the environment committee.</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON TALK: CONGRESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
