<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deaver Prosecutor Asks Tougher Conflict Laws</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="102966"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOBBYING AND LOBBYISTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEAVER, MICHAEL K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEYMOUR, WHITNEY NORTH JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TOLCHIN, MARTIN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ETHICS IN GOVERNMENT ACT OF 1978</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE6DE123FF93AA25751C1A961948260" item-length="715" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deaver Prosecutor Asks Tougher Conflict Laws</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARTIN TOLCHIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TOLCHIN, MARTIN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Whitney North Seymour Jr. today proposed to Congress a major overhaul of the nation's laws on conflict of interest as the White House assailed his criticism of the Administration's ethical standards.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Whitney North Seymour Jr. today proposed to Congress a major overhaul of the nation's laws on conflict of interest as the White House assailed his criticism of the Administration's ethical standards.</p>
        <p>Whitney North Seymour Jr. today proposed to Congress a major overhaul of the nation's laws on conflict of interest as the White House assailed his criticism of the Administration's ethical standards.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour, the independent prosecutor who earlier this week won a perjury conviction against Michael K. Deaver, the White House aide who became a lobbyist, proposed removing legislative ambiguities to make the Ethics in Government Act more easily enforceable and to create clear, firm standards of conduct for former senior Administration officials.</p>
        <p>One proposal would ban all communications by former senior employees that are intended to influence their former agencies. This would include ''social'' and ''informational'' contacts now permitted by law.</p>
        <p>''After a year and a half of investigative and prosecutive activity, it is the conclusion of this office that the present Ethics in Government Act is essentially unenforceable, and its protection of the public is illusory,'' Mr. Seymour said in a letter to members of the House and Senate judiciary committees. Rodino Promises Attention</p>
        <p>Representative Peter W. Rodino Jr., a New Jersey Democrat who is chairman of the House Judiciary committee, said Mr. Seymour's recommendations would be ''considered carefully.'' He agreed that ''there certainly is evidence that the current laws on ethics need to be clarified and strengthened'' while recognizing the constitutional rights of former employees and the government's need to attract persons of high quality.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Marlin Fitzwater, the White House spokesman, assailed Mr. Seymour's charges Thursday that the Administration had turned a blind eye to unethical practices. Mr. Seymour had declared that ''the problem is too much 'loose' money and too little concern in Washington about ethics in government,'' problems which he called ''a function of leadership.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fitzwater called Mr. Seymour's remarks ''an insult to the people of Washington.''</p>
        <p>''They are an insult to government civil servants, as well as political leaders throughout the country,'' Mr. Fitzwater said. Shultz Is Defended</p>
        <p>Mr. Fitzwater defended Secretary of State George P. Shultz, whose testimony in behalf of Mr. Deaver was assailed by Mr. Seymour as symptomatic of the present level of White House leadership.</p>
        <p>''I find it outrageous that he would find it wrong for one friend to feel sorry for the hardships of another friend, and he is totally out of line,'' Mr. Fitzwater said of Mr. Seymour's criticism of Mr. Shultz.</p>
        <p>Legal experts had speculated that Mr. Seymour brought charges of perjury rather than conflict of interest because he considered the ethics law so riddled with ambiguities that it was unenforceable. The Senate Judiciary Committee last July approved tightening the law, in legislation pending before the Senate, but Mr. Seymour would go considerably further. The House Judiciary committee held hearings on the conflict-of-interest laws earlier this year.</p>
        <p>''The only real restraint the statute creates is obstruction of prosecutors with murky definitions and meaningless exemptions which have converted the law into a quagmire of potential reasonable doubt,'' Mr. Seymour said. Time Limits Vary</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour's proposals would strengthen the prohibitions against former senior officials who are banned from seeking to influence Government officials for various periods of time. They are now subject to a one-year prohibition against seeking to influence their former agencies, a two-year prohibition against seeking to influence officials on any matters that were pending when they left and a lifetime prohibition against seeking to influence on matters in which they were ''personally and substantially'' involved.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour proposed a ban on personal communications transmitted through assistants or emissaries, on behalf of former senior employees. The evidence indicated that the Deaver firm's contacts were often made by his associates.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour also proposed prohibiting the use of diplomatic immunity to block an investigation. That was an obvious reference to his inability to obtain the testimony of Canadian officials concerning allegations that Mr. Deaver had worked on their behalf for a United States-Canada agreement on acid rain.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
