<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ENVOY SUBPOENAED FOR DEAVER TRIAL</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="44123"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERJURY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOBBYING AND LOBBYISTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTRACTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">STATE, DEPARTMENT OF</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHENON, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOTLIEB, ALLAN (AMB)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEAVER, MICHAEL K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE6DF1538F934A15756C0A961948260" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ENVOY SUBPOENAED FOR DEAVER TRIAL</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHENON, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHENON, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Canadian Government said tonight that its Ambassador to Washington had been subpoenaed to testify at the perjury trial of Michael K. Deaver, the former White House aide, but would refuse to appear.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Canadian Government said tonight that its Ambassador to Washington had been subpoenaed to testify at the perjury trial of Michael K. Deaver, the former White House aide, but would refuse to appear.</p>
        <p>The Canadian Government said tonight that its Ambassador to Washington had been subpoenaed to testify at the perjury trial of Michael K. Deaver, the former White House aide, but would refuse to appear.</p>
        <p>In a statement, the Government said its decision was based on ''longstanding and important principles which govern the conduct of relations between two sovereign states.''</p>
        <p>Allan E. Gotlieb, the Canadian Ambassador to the United States, has extensive knowledge of the $105,000 lobbying contract provided to Mr. Deaver by the Canadian Government. State Department Backs Canada</p>
        <p>A Canadian official who asked not to be identified said the State Department was supporting Canada in its assertion that Ambassador Gotlieb could not be compelled to testify at the Deaver trial.</p>
        <p>It was unclear how important Mr. Gotlieb's testimony would be, although officials said he had already provided valuable information to prosecutors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver has been accused of lying under oath to Congress and a Federal grand jury about his lobbying activities, including his dealings with Canada on the issue of acid rain.</p>
        <p>One legal source said Whitney North Seymour Jr., the special prosecutor in the case, intended to take the Ambassador to court to force him to testify at the trial, which is scheduled to begin next month.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour, the source said, has argued that Mr. Gotlieb must testify to verify allegations against Mr. Deaver. The Constitution provides criminal defendants with the right to confront prosecution witnesses through cross-examination.</p>
        <p>In a statement issued by the Canadian Embassy, Canada said Mr. Seymour was ''asking the Government to break normal diplomatic practice.'' Waiver Called 'Unprecedented'</p>
        <p>Under diplomatic accords, the statement said, ''foreign diplomatic personnel are not obliged to testify in judicial proceedings and will not do so without an expressed waiver from the sending country.''</p>
        <p>The statement said that ''such a waiver would be unprecedented for Canada in a matter such as the Deaver trial, just as it would be unprecedented for the United States to grant a waiver in similar circumstances.''</p>
        <p>Under a 1985 contract, Mr. Deaver was reportedly paid $105,000 by the Canadian Government to lobby for efforts to control acid rain and on trade.</p>
        <p>Last year, while the grand jury investigation continued, Mr. Deaver announced that to spare further embarrassment to Canada, he would not renew the contract.</p>
        <p>Canada has denied that future job opportunities were discussed with Mr. Deaver while he worked for President Reagan as the deputy White House chief of staff, but the fact that the lobbying contract was signed within days of his departure from the White House has raised suspicions.</p>
        <p>The fourth count of the five-count indictment against Mr. Deaver deals with Canada and the acid rain issue. According to the indictment, Mr. Deaver committed perjury when he told a grand jury last June that he could not recall participating in White House meetings on the acid rain issue until March 6, 1985. Selection of Special Envoy</p>
        <p>Prosecutors said he had been present at six meetings before then at which acid rain was discussed.</p>
        <p>The indictment charges that Mr. Deaver also lied when he told the grand jury that he had not participated in the selection of Drew Lewis, the former Secretary of Transportation, as the Presidential envoy on the acid rain issue in 1985. In fact, the indictment said, Mr. Deaver ''actively supported the idea of appointing a special envoy from the moment the idea was first proposed on Dec. 17, 1984,'' and ''actively supported the President's selection of Drew Lewis.''</p>
        <p>The indictment also accused Mr. Deaver of lying about a lunch with Mr. Gotlieb in early 1985 to discuss relations between the two governments.</p>
        <p>A Canadian official who asked not to be identified said Abraham D. Sofaer, the State Department's legal adviser, had written to Mr. Seymour ''within the last 24 hours'' and said he ''totally supported the Canadian legal view on this issue.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
