<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CANADA WANTS OFF THE BACK BURNER</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="25277"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURNS, JOHN F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MULRONEY, BRIAN (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870329T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDC1739F93AA15750C0A961948260" item-length="708" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CANADA WANTS OFF THE BACK BURNER</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BURNS, JOHN F</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: WHEN Vice President Bush visited Prime Minister Brian Mulroney in Ottawa in January, more than one Canadian newspaper columnist pointed out that Mr. Bush had dressed for the bitter cold in a short, unlined raincoat. It was a symbolic detail for many Canadians, who often complain that American leaders are woefully ill-informed about their northern neighbor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: WHEN Vice President Bush visited Prime Minister Brian Mulroney in Ottawa in January, more than one Canadian newspaper columnist pointed out that Mr. Bush had dressed for the bitter cold in a short, unlined raincoat. It was a symbolic detail for many Canadians, who often complain that American leaders are woefully ill-informed about their northern neighbor.</p>
        <p>WHEN Vice President Bush visited Prime Minister Brian Mulroney in Ottawa in January, more than one Canadian newspaper columnist pointed out that Mr. Bush had dressed for the bitter cold in a short, unlined raincoat. It was a symbolic detail for many Canadians, who often complain that American leaders are woefully ill-informed about their northern neighbor.</p>
        <p>That sensitivity will no doubt be even more acute next Sunday when President Reagan is in Ottawa for the annual meeting between the two heads of state. Mr. Mulroney warned Mr. Bush that Canada was tired of being on Washington's ''back burner'' and that he would watch for signs that Canada's concerns were being taken more seriously.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reagan has tried to answer Mr. Mulroney's challenge by announcing that he would seek $2.5 billion for acid rain research over the next five years. But Mr. Mulroney's critics called the plan cosmetic, saying that Mr. Reagan was only making good on a pledge he made a year ago and subsequently abandoned.</p>
        <p>The Canadians argue that only quick action, not more research, will reduce the pollution from coal-burning plants in the Ohio Valley that reacts in the atmosphere and returns to earth in the form of acid precipitation. Experts say United States emissions are responsible for killing lakes and forests in eastern Canada.</p>
        <p>An inability to persuade the Reagan Administration to impose mandatory emission controls is seen here as only one example of Ottawa's lack of influence in Washington.</p>
        <p>A common complaint is that Britain, West Germany and Japan exercise greater leverage on the issues that matter to them, although Canada is America's leading trading partner and the two countries have a broad bilateral relationship.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mulroney's problems with Washington are only part of deeper troubles at home. A sequence of Cabinet resignations and dismissals has fueled doubts about the probity of some people swept into office in the Conservative Party's 1984 landslide victory over the Liberal Party. The 47-year-old Prime Minister began his mandate by saying that the Conservatives had been shut out of the advantages of public life for too long. But patronage appointments and contracts for the party's friends as well as skulduggery that has resulted in a number of criminal investigations have raised questions.</p>
        <p>But in the long run, whether or not the Government succeeds in reviving its popularity - the Conservatives' support was 24 percent in a recent Gallup poll, compared with 41 percent for the Liberals - is likely to depend at least as much on the course of relations with the United States. Already, there are predictions that the election expected in 1989 could turn out to be a referendum on attitudes toward the United States.</p>
        <p>From the outset Mr. Mulroney declared that he would take a more accommodating attitude toward Washington than did former Prime Minister Pierre Elliott Trudeau, whose prickly intellectual ways irritated several American Presidents. Calculating that more could ''be gained from cooperation than confrontation,'' Mr. Mulroney launched the most ambitious attempt since World War II to redefine the relationship.</p>
        <p>The centerpiece has been negotiations for a ''free trade'' pact that would eliminate tariffs and other economic barriers. After months of stalemate, those discussions recently picked up, and lately there has been talk of a preliminary pact as early as June. But it appears the accord may skirt some tricky issues, including the right of the United States to use its ''countervail'' mechanisms to impose punitive duties against Canadian goods judged to have been unfairly subsidized.</p>
        <p>Some Canadians, including recent immigrants from Asia and Latin America, say they would be happy to see closer integration of the two nations. But many more, opinion polls show, find the idea unappealing, or worse. Several prominent figures have responded to Mr. Mulroney's campaign with warnings about Canada's being ''taken over'' by the United States.</p>
        <p>For the critics, a satisfactory relationship would begin with the assurance that the Washington takes Canada seriously. It is for that, as much as for details on free trade or acid rain, that they will be watching Mr. Reagan closely next weekend.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
