<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. STEP IN DEAVER CASE ANGERS CANADA</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="44772"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOBBYING AND LOBBYISTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURNS, JOHN F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEAVER, MICHAEL K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOTLIEB, ALLEN E (AMB)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOTLIEB, ALLEN E (MRS)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1DD1539F933A05756C0A961948260" item-length="731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. STEP IN DEAVER CASE ANGERS CANADA</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BURNS, JOHN F</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, May 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The attempt by the special prosecutor in the Michael K. Deaver case to compel Canada's Ambassador to the United States and his wife to testify in Mr. Deaver's trial has angered the Canadian Government, which had hoped that the diplomatic and political ramifications of its involvement with Mr. Deaver were at an end.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The attempt by the special prosecutor in the Michael K. Deaver case to compel Canada's Ambassador to the United States and his wife to testify in Mr. Deaver's trial has angered the Canadian Government, which had hoped that the diplomatic and political ramifications of its involvement with Mr. Deaver were at an end.</p>
        <p>The attempt by the special prosecutor in the Michael K. Deaver case to compel Canada's Ambassador to the United States and his wife to testify in Mr. Deaver's trial has angered the Canadian Government, which had hoped that the diplomatic and political ramifications of its involvement with Mr. Deaver were at an end.</p>
        <p>The political storm that burst when Mr. Deaver's $105,000 contract with Canada became public last year subsided rapidly after a House of Commons committee held an inconclusive hearing on the affair. But after process servers arrived at the Canadian Embassy in Washington earlier this week with subpoenas for the Ambassador, Allen E. Gotlieb, and for his wife, Sondra, the issue was thrust onto the public agenda once more.</p>
        <p>In the House of Commons, there have been renewed questions about the propriety of hiring Mr. Deaver to assist Canada in its effort to obtain United States controls on acid rain. But on the narrower issue of the Gotlieb subpoenas there has been virtually no dissent, with opposition politicians backing the Government's stand that the Ambassador and his wife are protected by diplomatic immunity from any requirement to appear in court. State Dept. Supports Stand</p>
        <p>The Government's stand was outlined in two forcefully worded statements by the External Affairs Minister, Joe Clark, and was supported by the State Department, which sent lawyers to court in Washington Thursday to argue against the subpoenas. In Ottawa, a senior official in Prime Minister Brian Mulroney's office, Bruce Phillips, said today that no legal maneuvering by the special prosecutor, Whitney North Seymour Jr., would have any effect.</p>
        <p>''They're not going to be in court, no matter what,'' said Mr. Phillips, who served until recently as minister for public affairs in the Canadian Embassy in Washington.</p>
        <p>Mr. Phillips, who is now director of communications for Mr. Mulroney, said the Government was particularly incensed by Mr. Seymour's statement that Canada was guilty of ''duplicitous behavior.'' In fact, Mr. Phillips said, the truth was exactly the reverse, since Mr. Seymour had been told at the outset of his contacts with the embassy last year that there was no question of Mr. Gotlieb's waiving his diplomatic immunity.</p>
        <p>''I don't know, maybe he feels he has a weak case, and that's why he's coming down the pike with a totally different approach, and a totally different tone, than he employed last year,'' Mr. Phillips said, referring to Mr. Seymour. Planning Strategy</p>
        <p>Mr. Phillips said the embassy had planned its strategy in the Deaver affair with care from the onset of its contacts with Mr. Seymour last summer. The Canadian official, who took part in discussions at the embassy at the time, said it had been made clear to Mr. Seymour that the embassy's cooperation - in the form of written answers provided by Mr. Gotlieb to written questions from Mr. Seymour - in no way constituted a waiver of Mr. Gotlieb's diplomatic immunity.</p>
        <p>''As a responsible and friendly neighbor, it was our view that it would not be seemly for Canada not to cooperate with a legal inquiry in the United States,'' Mr. Phillips said. ''But right from the outset the No. 1 question for us was how to do that without eroding our sovereignty. We explained to Mr. Seymour that we were not going to cooperate at the expense of losing our diplomatic immunity. No country would do that, least of all the United States.'' 'Breach of Faith'</p>
        <p>At the External Affairs Ministry, officials said that the first they had heard of Mr. Seymour's plan to get the Gotliebs to testify was when the process servers arrived at the embassy on Tuesday. It was this peremptoriness, as well as what Canadian officials say they consider a ''breach of faith'' after the cooperation with Mr. Seymour last summer, that explained the angry tone of Mr. Clark's public statements on the affair this week, the officials said.</p>
        <p>Among opposition politicians, there has been a suspicion that some of the Government's anger derived from its chagrin at seeing an embarrassing issue revived. A legislator for the opposition Liberal Party, John Nunziata, used the controversy over the subpoenas to renew a demand in the House of Commons that Mr. Gotlieb be brought back to testify before the External Affairs Committee on the contract with Mr. Deaver. Mr. Clark refused that demand last summer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
