<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Environment As a Diplomatic Issue</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="104487"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="WASHINGTON TALK: STATE DEPARTMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">STATE, DEPARTMENT OF</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NEGROPONTE, JOHN D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON TALK PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5DA123BF936A15751C1A961948260" item-length="1054" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Environment As a Diplomatic Issue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Just after an international protocol to protect the earth's ozone shield was signed in Montreal in September, Secretary of State George P. Shultz telephoned Assistant Secretary John D. Negroponte to compliment him on ''an important diplomatic triumph for the United States.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Just after an international protocol to protect the earth's ozone shield was signed in Montreal in September, Secretary of State George P. Shultz telephoned Assistant Secretary John D. Negroponte to compliment him on ''an important diplomatic triumph for the United States.''</p>
        <p>Just after an international protocol to protect the earth's ozone shield was signed in Montreal in September, Secretary of State George P. Shultz telephoned Assistant Secretary John D. Negroponte to compliment him on ''an important diplomatic triumph for the United States.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Negroponte, then the head of the department's Bureau of Oceans and International Environmental and Scientific Affairs, the accolade was especially sweet.</p>
        <p>The bureau, for many years a little-known, neglected and in some respects unloved backwater, was imposed on an unreceptive State Department by Congress in 1974. Until recently the bureau had about as much power in influencing national policy as a lame-duck freshman member of Congress from the minority party.</p>
        <p>But when Mr. Negroponte became head of the bureau in 1986, he determined, he recalled in an interview, to make it ''relevant within the Department of State.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Negroponte has now left the bureau, to become deputy director of the National Security Council. But in his tenure, environmental affairs and the bureau itself moved from the backwater toward the mainstream of the nation's diplomacy.</p>
        <p>In part, the bureau's increased activity and influence can be attributed to the aggressive leadership of Mr. Negroponte, a career diplomat. At the same time, environmental issues such as acid rain or the putative destruction of the earth's ozone shield by manmade chemicals have become increasingly recognized as pressing international problems affecting economic, national security and public health matters. These issues would have thrust themselves onto the State Department agenda no matter who was in office.</p>
        <p>The latest sign that environmental issues are taking on a significant role in international relations came in the communique signed by President Reagan and Mikhail S. Gorbachev, the Soviet leader, at the end of their summit here this month. The communique included a pledge of cooperation on dealing with the global climatic warming trend attributed to the ''greenhouse effect.''</p>
        <p>In this changing diplomatic era, the oceans and environment bureau has shown over the past few years that ''we could accomplish useful things for our foreign policy,'' Mr. Negroponte said. A List of Achievements</p>
        <p>Among the achievements in his watch at the bureau, he listed these:</p>
        <p>* The Montreal protocol, in which all the industrial countries and many developing countries agreed to limit production of manmade chemicals that are believed to be destroying the earth's protective shield. The State Department played a major role not only in getting other nations to agree to the protocol but also in persuading the Reagan Administration to accept controls on industrial production.</p>
        <p>* Agreements with Canada and Mexico dealing with pollution that crosses international borders. Mr. Negroponte acknowledged, however, that the United States has not resolved its differences with Canada over acid rain.</p>
        <p>* The resumption of an agreement with the Soviet Union for cooperation in space research. The cooperation had been broken off since the Russians intervened in Afghanistan in 1979.</p>
        <p>* A treaty with 14 Pacific island states giving American tuna fleets access to their fisheries. This issue has been a source of ''serious bilateral friction'' with many of those states, Mr. Negroponte said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Negroponte, a tall, husky man of 48, who was Ambassador to Honduras before taking on the oceans and environment bureau, said that in recent years ''environmental concerns are starting to be internalized in institutions such as the State Department and the Agency for International Development.'' 'A Whole Range of Issues'</p>
        <p>''No one,'' he said, ''is seriously questioning any more factoring in environmental considerations on a whole range of issues where previously they might have been controversial.''</p>
        <p>Richard E. Benedick, who as deputy assistant Secretary of State negotiated the Montreal protocol for the United States, said the oceans bureau ''has become one of the most important parts of the State Department.''</p>
        <p>''This is the diplomacy of the future,'' said Mr. Benedick, who is now on temporary assignment to the Conservation Foundation, a private research group. United States relations with other counties, he explained, now involve science and environmental issues as well as traditional aspects of foreign policy.</p>
        <p>Richard J. Smith, Mr. Negroponte's principal deputy, has taken over as acting head of the bureau. A search is under way for a permanent successor.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists give Mr. Negroponte and the bureau of oceans and environment somewhat mixed reviews.</p>
        <p>Craig Van Note, executive director of Monitor, a consortium of conservation and animal protection groups, said that while Mr. Negroponte has been in charge of the bureau, ''he has indeed addressed many global ecological issues and given them some weight in the State Department.''</p>
        <p>''It was about time,'' he added, ''that State had someone good in that position with enough influence and interest in these issues to put them on the front burner.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Van Note also said, ''Where it has come down to specific environmental conflicts such as the whaling issue or the problem of marine mammals caught in tuna fishing drift nets, John has been less than supportive.''</p>
        <p>He said Mr. Negroponte often sought to compromise with Japan and other nations with vested economic interests on these issues. For example, by not supporting sanctions against Japan and by ''actively encouraging Japan to continue whaling,'' he contended, Mr. Negroponte has hindered efforts to enforce an agreed-upon international moratorium on commercial whaling. 'Planetary in Scale'</p>
        <p>Rafe Pomerance, senior associate of the World Resources Institute, a Washington-based research and policy group, said the State Department's role in environmental issues has been growing ''as environmental issues assume a greater international character.''</p>
        <p>These issues are becoming increasingly internationalized, he said, because ''the scale of human activities is having an impact that is planetary in scale.''</p>
        <p>''Unilateral action to deal with these issues can still be beneficial, but it is no longer sufficient,'' Mr. Pomerance said. ''The consequences are much larger than those we have dealt with before.''  WASHINGTON TALK: STATE DEPARTMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
