<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Finding on Ozone 'Hole' Raises Concern</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="103013"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHANKLIN, JONATHAN D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4DD1E3FF93AA25751C1A961948260" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Finding on Ozone 'Hole' Raises Concern</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The winter mass of extremely cold air over Antarctica remained weeks longer than usual this year, along with the seasonal ''hole'' in the atmosphere's protective ozone layer, British and American scientists have reported.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The winter mass of extremely cold air over Antarctica remained weeks longer than usual this year, along with the seasonal ''hole'' in the atmosphere's protective ozone layer, British and American scientists have reported.</p>
        <p>The winter mass of extremely cold air over Antarctica remained weeks longer than usual this year, along with the seasonal ''hole'' in the atmosphere's protective ozone layer, British and American scientists have reported.</p>
        <p>The scientists said in interviews today and Thursday that they could give no definitive explanation for the events. It might simply be a quirk in the weather, some of them said. But several said they were worried about the possible implications for both climate change and the earth's protective ozone shield.</p>
        <p>Scientists have previously reported that atmospheric ozone over the Antarctic fell this year to the lowest levels recorded in the several years since measurements of the seasonal thinning began. Some speculated that the extremely low ozone level itself directly contributed to the extended cold weather because there was little ozone in the atmosphere to absorb the sun's warmth.. Late Breakup of Cold Air</p>
        <p>In the past the cold air mass over Antarctica in its winter has tended to break up by early to mid-November, in the Antarctic spring. At that point the ozone levels climb back toward normal too. But measurements taken by American scientists at the South Pole found that the breakup did not begin this year until Nov. 29 or 30. Scientists of the British Antarctic survey, who took measurements at Halley Bay, 1,000 miles from the pole, where ozone levels are often lowest, found the usual warming had only begun to move within the past three or four days.</p>
        <p>Scientists from both countries said the warming of the air mass had been delayed in the past, but that this year the breakup was at least two weeks later than in any Antarctic springtime since monitoring began in 1957.</p>
        <p>Jonathan D. Shanklin, a scientist with the British Antarctic survey who was among the first to observe the ''hole'' of depleted ozone in the Anatractic atmoshere, said that on Dec. 3 the measured ozone level was about a third lower than the previous year. It was, he said, ''by far the lowest'' ozone readings ever made on that date. Ultraviolet Radiation</p>
        <p>Atmospheric ozone, a form of oxygen, protects the earth's surface from harmful ultraviolet radiation from the sun that can cause skin cancer and other health problems in humans and other life on earth. Recent evidence has indicated that the man-made chemicals have played an important role in creating the seasonal ozone hole over the South polar region.</p>
        <p>Several of the scientists, including F. Sherwood Rowland, who first proposed in the early 1970's that atmospheric ozone could be destroyed by chlorine chemicals, suggested that the extended duration of the cold air mass was directly related to the low ozone levels. Because there was so much less ozone to absorb heat from the sun, the air over Antarctica was warming up more slowly, the scientists said.</p>
        <p>Ralph J. Cicerone, director of the National Science Foundation's National Center for Atmospheric Research in Boulder, Colo., said the duration of the ozone-poor air mass could be dangerous for organisms in Antarctica. When the ozone first begins to disappear late in the polar winter, the sun is very low on the horizon and little ultraviolet radiation penetrates the earth. But with the ozone hole remaining until late in the Antarctic spring, the sun is higher and much more radiation can penetrate the thin atmospheric shield, Dr. Cicerone explained.</p>
        <p>The Antarctic is rich in animal life, such as krill, a crustacean on which other marine life feeds, that plays an important part in the global food chain. Changes in Climate Feared</p>
        <p>Mr. Shanklin of the British Antarctic Survey, interviewed by telephone in Cambridge, England, said the temperature measured at Halley Bay was still at minus 60 degrees centigrade on Dec. 10, much colder than at that date in the past. He said the long duration of the frigid air mass in the Antarctic was likely to produce variations in ''short-term weather systems and long-term climate changes'' in the Southern Hemisphere.</p>
        <p>''The problem is that we really don't know enough about the atmosphere to predict what this is going to do,'' Mr. Shanklin said. He added, however, that from now on those who try to predict climate patterns ''are going to have to put the ozone hole into their models.'' 'These Thngs Are Unknowable'</p>
        <p>Arlen J. Krueger, an atmospheric scientist for the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, cautioned that the extended duration of the ozone hole might simply be a variation from normal patterns and would not necessarily reoccur.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
