<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BYRD OPPOSES LEGISLATION TO CURB POLLUTION THAT CAUSES ACID RAIN</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="28509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BYRD, ROBERT C (SEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1DA1739F93AA35757C0A961948260" item-length="512" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BYRD OPPOSES LEGISLATION TO CURB POLLUTION THAT CAUSES ACID RAIN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Robert C. Byrd, the Senate Democratic leader, said today that ''acid rain is not an emergency'' and denounced legislation proposed to control the sources of the pollution that causes it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Robert C. Byrd, the Senate Democratic leader, said today that ''acid rain is not an emergency'' and denounced legislation proposed to control the sources of the pollution that causes it.</p>
        <p>Robert C. Byrd, the Senate Democratic leader, said today that ''acid rain is not an emergency'' and denounced legislation proposed to control the sources of the pollution that causes it.</p>
        <p>Because of Senator Byrd's ability to influence legislation, his opposition could substantially reduce Congressional prospects for action to control acid rain.</p>
        <p>But lawmakers who have already introduced legislation to curb sources of acid rain said they would continue to press for passage of their bills.</p>
        <p>In a speech on the Senate floor today, Mr. Byrd said he applauded President Reagan's statement in Ottawa on Monday that he would consider a proposal by Prime Minister Brian Mulroney that Canada and the United States negotiate a ''bilateral accord'' controlling acid rain, which is destroying lakes, fish and forests in Canada and the Northeastern United States. 'Major Sacrifice' for U.S.  But the majority leader asserted that the United States was already doing more to deal with the acid rain problem than Canada, and added, ''Canada would like us to require a major sacrifice in the livelihoods of millions of our citizens to improve environmental quality for Canada.''</p>
        <p>Senator Byrd represents West Virginia, a coal-producing state that would be strongly affected by efforts to control pollution from coal-burning power stations, a major source of acid rain. West Virginia, which produces much coal with a high sulfur content, would, it is believed, lose sales to states burning low-sulfur coal.</p>
        <p>While he said he was ''deeply concerned about the environment,'' Mr. Byrd added: ''I am also deeply concerned about job stability and the welfare of communities in states such as mine. I worry about the competitiveness of our energy-intensive industries and about the electric bills that residential, commercial and industrial consumers must pay.''</p>
        <p>The Senator said a bill he introduced would provide $3.5 billion in matching grants to the states to help pay for cleaner coal-burning methods and would achieve ''a broad set of energy and environmental goals'' without causing economic disruption. Stafford Defends His Bill</p>
        <p>Senator Robert T. Stafford, a Vermont Republican who is the author of legislation that would require substantial reductions in sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide pollution, the chief components of acid rain, said he would continue to press for passage of his bill.</p>
        <p>''Everyone who speaks in defense of polluters always claims controlling that pollution will cost money and jobs,'' Senator Stafford said, adding, ''Those defenders of pollution never talk about the cost of injury to health and the environment.''</p>
        <p>Senator George J. Mitchell of Maine, author of another bill that would reduce the pollution that causes acid rain, said he intended to deal with the problems raised by Senator Byrd. But Mr. Mitchell, a Democrat, also said he disagreed with Mr. Byrd's contention that the only reason for acid rain controls was to help Canadians.</p>
        <p>''The principal reason is to help Americans,'' Senator Mitchell said. ''We will press forward.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
