<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Certain and Ominous Effects of Ozone Loss</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="48671"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HODEL, DONALD P (SEC)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7D71731F930A25755C0A961948260" item-length="353" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Certain and Ominous Effects of Ozone Loss</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Interior Secretary Donald Hodel's recommendation regarding the depletion of stratospheric ozone -that people could wear more sunglasses, hats and suntan lotion - is absurd and deserving of ridicule (''Through Rose-Colored Sunglasses,'' editorial, May 31). Yet the fact that the opposition to an inter-national freeze on the production of ozone-destroying chemicals is both woefully misinformed and powerful makes this is no laugh-ing matter.</p>
        <p>Your editorial may actually mislead by touching only briefly on the far-reaching implications of ozone loss, referring to one Environmental Protection Agency study. Numerous tests have been carried out, both in controlled environments and in the field, resulting in many conclusions that are far from ''uncertain.''</p>
        <p>Research has shown that an increase in the earth's exposure to ultraviolet-B rays has unequivocal negative implications. Humans would not only be afflicted by melanoma (skin cancer) at a higher rate, but human immunological systems can be adversely affected.</p>
        <p>Most plants (including crops, of course) which have received higher doses of UV-B rays display signs of stunted growth, less leaf area and an inhibition of the photosynthetic process. Extensive research has also demonstrated that even smaller changes in UV-B radiation drastically affect marine life.</p>
        <p>Beyond these effects, there are strong indications that an increase in the level of UV-B rays will contribute to altering the entire planet's climate, conceivably producing a ''greenhouse effect,'' which also carries severe implications.</p>
        <p>The hole in the ozone discovered over Antarctica is now roughly the size of the continental United States, and probably growing. Scientists are still debating the cause; most explanations focus on the chemicals we pump into the air.</p>
        <p>We must remember that the destruction of stratospheric ozone is not only irreversible: no one gains and we can all lose. The issue must be presented to the public responsibly and in detail, with emphasis on the finality of this potential catas-trophe. ALEXANDRA SMITH  Washington, June 1, 1987</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
