<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Forestry Group Seeks Tougher Pollution Controls</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="95417"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FORESTRY ASSN, AMERICAN</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7D9143EF931A15752C1A961948260" item-length="671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Forestry Group Seeks Tougher Pollution Controls</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The American Forestry Association says acid rain and other air pollution are harming the nation's forests and has called on Congress to act to strengthen controls on the pollutants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The American Forestry Association says acid rain and other air pollution are harming the nation's forests and has called on Congress to act to strengthen controls on the pollutants.</p>
        <p>The American Forestry Association says acid rain and other air pollution are harming the nation's forests and has called on Congress to act to strengthen controls on the pollutants.</p>
        <p>The association, a private nonprofit conservation group whose members include professional foresters, scientists and others concerned with forest issues, thus becomes the first national forestry organization to call for immediate Federal action to clamp down on air pollution.</p>
        <p>Professional forestry groups and the timber industry have been saying there was not enough evidence to justify expensive and restrictive new antipollution measures.</p>
        <p>But the document issued Thursday by the forestry assocation said it now appeared that a variety of pollutants, including ozone, or smog, airborne sulfur, excessive nitrogen, toxic aluminum and other metals, along with acid rain, were combining with natural stresses and contributing to the decline of a number of tree species in American forests, particularly in the East.</p>
        <p>''Given the importance of forest, aquatic and terrestrial resources to the health and well-being of the nation, the American Forestry Assocation believes that the risks and costs associated with further delaying additional pollution controls now seems to outweight the risks and costs associated with action,'' the document said.</p>
        <p>The association called for Congress to amend the Clean Air Act to impose stronger controls on emissions of sulfur, nitrogen oxides, hydrocarbons and toxic metals by industry, motor vehicles and other sources.</p>
        <p>The document said that ozone, the major compotent of smog, had been proved to damage and kill Eastern white pine and to cause damage and death to white fir, ponderosa pine and some other species. Acid air pollution, together with excessive nitrogen fertilization, aluminum and natural stresses, such as drought and insects, were given as the possible causes for the decline of spruce at high elevations in the Appalachians.</p>
        <p>The paper also noted that it was now ''widely acknowledged'' that acid rain had killed life in lakes and other fresh water over wide areas and that air pollution, particularly ozone, had caused haze in the forests, thereby diminishing their recreational value. Acid rain is sulfur and nitrogen, much of it from coal-fired power plants, that changes chemically in the atmosphere and falls as acidic rain, snow, fog or dry particles.</p>
        <p>John A. Thorner, environmental counsel of the National Forest Products Association, which represents the timber and wood products industries, said that the forestry association's document acknowledged that air pollution had not been conclusively proved to be a cause of damage to forests.</p>
        <p>''We see no convincing evidence that further controlling air pollution on a national scale will improve the health of the forests,'' Mr. Thorner said. ''We do see risks in acting.''</p>
        <p>He said these risks included wasting money and having people assume that once new controls were added the risks to the forests had ended.</p>
        <p>Many of the companies that belong to the industry association are involved in the manafacture of paper and paper products and are heavy users of electricity. Controls to lower the pollutants that cause acid rain would raise the cost of electric power. The Reagan Adminstration opposes new legislation to control acid rain and other air pollution on grounds that such controls would cost a lot of money and produce uncertain benefits, if any. A report issued earlier this year by a interagency group formed to study acid rain found that there was no immediate threat to the forests from pollution. The report was heavily criticized by scientists outside the Government.</p>
        <p>The forestry association's report and recommendations were hailed by Susan Buffone, director of the National Clean Air Coalition, an alliance of environmental and public health groups, as ''a courageous announcement favoring revitalization of the Clean Air Act and enactment of a package of comprehensive amendments to strengthen this law.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
