<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OZONE AGREEMENT IS HAILED AS A FIRST STEP IN COOPERATION</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="37422"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS ENVIRONMENT PROGRAM</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2DD1130F936A35756C0A961948260" item-length="1090" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OZONE AGREEMENT IS HAILED AS A FIRST STEP IN COOPERATION</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: While negotiations in Geneva last week ended with only a tentative step toward ridding the atmosphere of the chemicals that are depleting the earth's ozone shield, they displayed a degree of international foresight on the environment that had been no more than an elusive goal in recent decades. The negotiations also represented a dramatic success for a United</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: While negotiations in Geneva last week ended with only a tentative step toward ridding the atmosphere of the chemicals that are depleting the earth's ozone shield, they displayed a degree of international foresight on the environment that had been no more than an elusive goal in recent decades. The negotiations also represented a dramatic success for a United</p>
        <p>While negotiations in Geneva last week ended with only a tentative step toward ridding the atmosphere of the chemicals that are depleting the earth's ozone shield, they displayed a degree of international foresight on the environment that had been no more than an elusive goal in recent decades. The negotiations also represented a dramatic success for a United Nations environmental agency that many experts had all but written off as ineffective.</p>
        <p>The negotiations, held under the auspices of the United Nations Environment Program, produced a tentative agreement to freeze production of chlorofluorocarbons at 1986 levels starting in 1990 and to cut production of the chemicals, which scientific evidence indicates are depleting ozone in the upper atmosphere, by 20 percent two years later. The accord also called for an additional 30 percent cut in production of the chemicals, but left open when, and even if, that reduction would be achieved.</p>
        <p>Conservation groups here greeted the tentative agreement with restrained enthusiasm. They called the agreement a step forward but said it remained to be seen whether producing nations would go the additional distance needed to protect the ozone.</p>
        <p>However, Administration officials contended, and even the conservationists agreed, that the ozone accord could signal the beginning of a new era of international cooperation in coming to grips with a wide variety of global concerns, including the warming of the earth's atmosphere, the destruction of tropical rain forests and the trade in toxic substances.</p>
        <p>The United States' chief negotiator at the Geneva talks, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State Richard E. Benedick, said today: ''The agreement on ozone is really a landmark because it is the first time the international community is taking hold of an environmental problem before it happens.'' Heretofore, there has been little display of international will to deal with global environmental threats. Many observers had also wondered whether any effective structure existed for bringing sovereign nations together to address such problems.</p>
        <p>If the Geneva agreement is signed, it would require sovereign nations to reduce their production of chlorofluorocarbons, a valuable economic commodity, in order to deal with a problem that science has identified as potentially very serious but which has yet to have any significant impact.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, there was wide agreement that the United Nations Environment Program, led by its executive director, Mustafa K. Tolba of Egypt, played a key role in achieving the tentative agreement and that the U.N. body could be the much-needed forum for dealing with other pressing environmental problems in the future.</p>
        <p>That there would be any agreement at all to limit production of chlorofluorocarbons could not have been predicted five years ago or even last year, when the European Economic Community and Japan expressed strong reservations. But mounting scientific evidence, including findings that a widening ''hole'' in the ozone over Antarctica may be caused by chlorine produced by human activity, has led to an increasingly serious view of the issue.</p>
        <p>Ozone in the atmosphere shields the earth's surface from ultraviolet radiation from the sun. Such radiation has been found to be a cause of skin cancer and to produce other health problems as well as to damage crops and forests. Questions Still Linger</p>
        <p>In Geneva, Mr. Tolba said he would call an emergency meeting at which governments could consider stronger actions if new evidence showed that the Antarctic ozone hole was continuing to widen rapidly.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists complained today that the provisions of the tentative agreement would not by themselves be adequate to end the threat to the ozone. David Wirth of the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental group, said that a scientific consensus indicated that an 85 percent reduction from current production levels would be needed to prevent any further increase in chlorofluorocarbons in the atmosphere but that the only commitment among the partipants in Geneva was for a 20 percent reduction. He noted that the negotiators had left open the possibility that the additional 30 percent reduction would only go into effect if the signatories to the treaty agreed to do so by majority vote.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wirth also said that an effective agreement would only take effect if the United States continued to press hard for one but he added that ''hostile right-wing forces within the Administration are trying to sabotage it.''</p>
        <p>Michael Oppenheimer, a scientist with the Environmental Defense Fund, another private group, said the agreement was not specific about a long-term goal of getting most ozone-destroying chemicals out of the atmosphere and had no schedule for reaching the goal of a 95 percent cutback in production of the chemicals as proposed by the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>''We have to get the world on the road of cleaning itself of these chemicals,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Oppenheimer also said: ''If progress on this protocol continues and the governments work out the details, it will be a signal event - a watershed in human history. We seem to be on the threshhold of a global atmospheric agreement for the first time.'' 'Vehicle Is There'</p>
        <p>Stating that the ozone agreement could be a precedent for other agreements, such as one to deal with the warming of the earth's atmosphere that is expected to result from the buildup of carbon dioxide and other gases, the environmentalists said: ''The vehicle is there. We should get on board and ride it as far as it will go.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Benedick of the State Department said ''a great deal of credit'' for the success of the Geneva negotiations must go to the United Nations Environmental Program and Dr. Tolba. Fitzhugh Green, Associate Administrator of the E.P.A. for international activities, said that the United Nations group could continue to play ''a very positive and helpful role.''</p>
        <p>The Geneva accord, Mr. Green said, ''shows that the environmental movement is coming of age. This is a chance for the entire world community to take action to protect the ozone.''</p>
        <p>The Reagan Administration, however, is again seeking to reduce the United States contribution to the United Nations Environmental Program. This year it is proposing to provide $4.8 million to the group, down from $6.8 million the previous year and down from the $10 million a year that the was provided by the United States each year until the Reagan Administration took office.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
