<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Haven Hospital Widens Uses of Laser</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="64587"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURGERY AND SURGEONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LASERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOSPITALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ST RAPHAEL'S HOSPITAL (NEW HAVEN, CONN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAMILTON, ROBERT A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Laser (Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission of Radiation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEEDE1E30F93AA3575BC0A961948260" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Haven Hospital Widens Uses of Laser</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT A. HAMILTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAMILTON, ROBERT A</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A NEW HAVEN hospital is one of five sites in the country experimenting with expanded use of the YAG laser, and doctors there say the initial results show the laser holds a lot of hope for people who need delicate ear, nose and throat surgery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A NEW HAVEN hospital is one of five sites in the country experimenting with expanded use of the YAG laser, and doctors there say the initial results show the laser holds a lot of hope for people who need delicate ear, nose and throat surgery.</p>
        <p>A NEW HAVEN hospital is one of five sites in the country experimenting with expanded use of the YAG laser, and doctors there say the initial results show the laser holds a lot of hope for people who need delicate ear, nose and throat surgery.</p>
        <p>''It seems to work much better than any of the other lasers we have,'' said Dr. Gerald W. Peskin, chairman of the department of surgery at the Hospital of St. Raphael, where the tests are being conducted.</p>
        <p>Dr. K. J. Lee, chief of the hospital's section of otolaryngology, said one patient, a 57-year-old man, had a hot cup of coffee two hours after having a tongue cancer removed. He said that in another case, an 18-year-old boy went home two hours after a tonsillectomy, which would have normally taken a couple of days for recovery.</p>
        <p>''Maybe these patients had very high thresholds of pain,'' Dr. Lee said. ''To be fair, so we're not being sensationalistic, we want to do 100 or 200 procedures over the next two years.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Ernest D. Moritz, chairman of the department of medicine, said the YAG has been used for more than 100 operations in the last two years at St. Raphael, for operations below the neck, as approved by the Food and Drug Administration.</p>
        <p>''There have been situations where people have been referred to us because the tumor was life threatening and there was absolutely no other way to operate on it,'' Dr. Moritz said.</p>
        <p>In addition to eliminating the bleeding normally associated with an operation, Dr. Moritz said, the YAG lowers the risk of infection. Because the actual laser beam is delivered by a piece of fiber-optic cable thinner than the lead in a pencil, it can be worked into an area inaccessible to a scalpel or the more commonly used Carbon Dioxide laser.</p>
        <p>''There are people for whom nothing else can be done, who can be helped by the YAG,'' Dr. Moritz said.</p>
        <p>The YAG is one of three lasers in use in hospitals and clinics.The other two are the Argon and the Carbon Dioxide lasers. YAG is an acronymn for yttrium-aluminum-garnet, a crystal that forms the laser beam.</p>
        <p>The YAG has been used for many years for eye, gastrointestinal, and pulmonary operations, but until this year ear, nose and throat specialists have been barred from using it.</p>
        <p>The Argon laser, which is attracted to the color red, is now commonly used to remove a birthmark referred to as a port wine stain.The Carbon Dioxide laser has a very narrow, intense beam of light, and is used as a scalpel. But the Carbon Dioxide laser must be transmitted through steel cable that makes it unwieldy.</p>
        <p>The YAG has a more diffuse beam, without the precision of a Carbon Dioxide laser, but it can stop bleeding quickly. There is almost no post-surgical swelling when a YAG is used, so a tonsillectomy on an adult, for example, typically a very painful procedure, is not as uncomfortable.</p>
        <p>There is also some indication that the intense heat of the YAG, which vaporizes offending cells, may help prevent the recurrence of tumors.</p>
        <p>St. Raphael, which opened its laser center 12 years ago, was among the first hospitals in Connecticut to obtain the $100,000 YAG laser two years ago, and is the only hospital in the state to be involved in the Food and Drug Administration's tests of the YAG on ear, nose and throat procedures.</p>
        <p>Dr. Moritz said a reasons the agency has not approved widespread use of the YAG on ear, nose and throat procedures is that the laser's effect on the sensitive tissue in those areas had to be fully documented before experiments could begin.</p>
        <p>He added that operations above the neck are more dangerous than those below it because of the proximity to vital air passages that can be accidentally blocked and can lead to a patient's death. But the YAG's ability to instantly coagulate blood, which Dr. Lee called ''a quirk of physics,'' makes it the instrument of choice for some of the delicate procedures above the neck.</p>
        <p>Operations on tongue lesions, for example, are typically accompanied by profuse bleeding, ''but with the two tongue procedures we've done so far, there was not a drop of blood,'' Dr. Lee said. Other patients have congenital defects that cause them to have severe nose bleeds, Dr. Lee said, and the YAG can be used to treat the symptoms and for preventive measures.</p>
        <p>Dr. Moritz said because the YAG is so easily manipulated it can be worked into position to operate on bronchial obstructions that a year ago would have been inoperable. Removing tumors and plaque from blood vessels without a major loss of blood is also made possible by threading the YAG into the vessel and attacking the tumor or buildup from within.</p>
        <p>Dr. Moritz said one disadvantage to the clinical trials of the YAG is that by the time a patient is referred, he will often have an advanced tumor that is inoperable with traditional surgery, and that patient is at greater risk.</p>
        <p>The YAG is not the answer to all surgical procedures, Dr. Lee said. ''If we can take a mole out as well with a scalpel, why use the YAG?'' Dr. Lee said.</p>
        <p>But there a lot of instances where the YAG will be useful, the doctors say. ''We're still not sure of all it can do,'' Dr. Peskin said. ''I think the use will broaden as more and more people see how effective it is.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
