<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Now, the Environment According to N. Dakota</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="2090"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="WASHINGTON TALK: CONGRESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONGRESS (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SENATE COMMITTEE ON ENVIRONMENT AND PUBLIC WORKS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURDICK, QUENTIN N (SEN)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON TALK PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEED8133DF93AA35752C0A961948260" item-length="953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Now, the Environment According to N. Dakota</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As a college football player at the University of Minnesota, Quentin N. Burdick went relatively unnoticed. He was a blocking back, clearing the way for Bronko Nagurski, the great running back.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As a college football player at the University of Minnesota, Quentin N. Burdick went relatively unnoticed. He was a blocking back, clearing the way for Bronko Nagurski, the great running back.</p>
        <p>As a college football player at the University of Minnesota, Quentin N. Burdick went relatively unnoticed. He was a blocking back, clearing the way for Bronko Nagurski, the great running back.</p>
        <p>Much the same can be said of Mr. Burdick's role as a United States Senator for the past 26 years. The jovial, gentlemanly Democrat from North Dakota has quietly and effectively served the interests of his native state. But he has never been chairman of a full Congressional committee, no major law bears his name, and he has conducted no headline-grabbing investigative hearings.</p>
        <p>In short, Quentin Burdick is not a household name.</p>
        <p>But now, with the Democrats back in control of the Senate, Mr. Burdick has become chairman of the Senate Environment and Public Works Committee, a very busy, highly visible panel that deals with a broad spectrum of issues, many of which, like acid rain and toxic waste, tend to arouse strong passions. As a result, he is in the limelight.</p>
        <p>Early indications are that Mr. Burdick's low-key style will not change. But the environment committee's priorities and the way it goes about its business will apparently shift substantially under his leadership. A Western Perspective</p>
        <p>For one thing, Senator Burdick, who is 78 years old, brings a distinctly Western perspective to his job, a change from recent years when the chairmen of the environment committee were Senator Robert T. Stafford, a Republican from Vermont, and, before him, Senator Jennings Randolph, a Democrat from West Virginia. Because of this perspective, the two highest items on the Burdick committee agenda are legislation for the Federal highway program and the Clean Water Act.</p>
        <p>''We want to take care of those two problems right away,'' he said recently. ''Roads is almost the top priority right now,'' he said, adding that it was ''absolutely incredible'' that Congress did not pass legislation last year permitting a continuance of Federal highway funds to the states. Many states are now running out of money for road building, he said.</p>
        <p>''Nothing is more important to North Dakota than the challenge of communications - roads for getting grain to the mills,'' Senator Burdick declared. Responsibility for the highway program ''is the heart of the committee in my books,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As for clean water, ''no resource is more dear in the West,'' he said. The House, by 406 to 8, voted today to renew the Clean Water Act, adopting a bill identical to the one killed by President Reagan with a pocket veto in November. Mr. Burdick said he expected the Senate to pass the legislation on Monday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reagan said the $18 billion for sewage treatment facilities in the legislation was too much money and has proposed an alternative for $12 billion in sewer funds.</p>
        <p>Senator Burdick's North Dakota view of the world also influences his thinking about acid rain legislation, which is likely to be a key environmental issue in the 100th Congress. ''My approach,'' he said, ''is taking care of the problem where it exists, not doing it all over the country.''</p>
        <p>''North Dakota is clean; Ohio and Pennsylvania and other places in the East is where they have problems,'' he contended, saying of power plants in his home state, ''We've already introduced scrubbers in North Dakota, and they have added 25 percent in costs to our rate payers.'' He said he did not favor legislation of the kind introduced in the House last year that would require financial support from all 50 states for controlling the pollution that produces acidic rain.</p>
        <p>Senator Burdick is also disposed to delegate authority. The environment committee's subcommittees, now headed by Senators George J. Mitchell of Maine, Daniel Patrick Moynihan of New York, Frank R. Lautenberg of New Jersey and Max Baucus of Montana, will have more autonomy than in recent years, he said.</p>
        <p>''I'll be there watching, but the way you get things done is to give these guys responsibility,'' he said. ''They know what they are doing.''</p>
        <p>Senator Mitchell said the new committee chairman ''is a very fine man and will do a good job.''</p>
        <p>''He is unusual among senators in that he doesn't talk a lot or give long speeches. That accounts for his popularity among North Dakotans.''</p>
        <p>Senator Mitchell also said he expected Senator Burdick to continue the committee traditions of bipartisanship and commitment to protecting the environment that, he said, were faithfully observed while the Republicans controlled the Senate and the committee. A Family Tradition</p>
        <p>Senator Burdick continues his own family tradition of eminence in law and politics. His father, Usher L. Burdick, also a lawyer, served as North Dakota's Lieutenant Governor and then represented the state in Congress for 20 years.</p>
        <p>Quentin Northrup Burdick was born in Munich, N.D., June 19, 1908. He received his undergraduate and law degrees at the University of Minnesota. Today, he sometimes brags that he scored a touchdown every time he touched the ball as a running back in college. Then he confesses he carried the ball only once.</p>
        <p>When he talks about his accomplishments in Congress, one of the first things he mentions is his leading role in obtaining legislative authority for the big Garrison Diversion irrigation project in his part of the country. He also notes that he was chairman of the Agriculture Committee subcommittee on agricultural corporations, which he said was a key committee for North Dakota interests.</p>
        <p>As for never before heading a committee despite being in the Senate since 1960, he says simply that ''the ball bounces in strange ways.'' He says one of his North Dakota predecessors, Milton R. Young, served 34 years in the Senate without ever being named a committee chairman.</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON TALK: CONGRESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
