<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.P.A. SEEKS DELAY IN USING SANCTIONS OF POLLUTION LAW</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="94097"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SANCTIONS (ECONOMIC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOG</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON MONOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORTHEASTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDWESTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DB113DF93BA25752C1A961948260" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.P.A. SEEKS DELAY IN USING SANCTIONS OF POLLUTION LAW</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Environmental Protection Agency today proposed delaying economic sanctions against areas that will not meet a statutory Dec. 31 deadline for reducing smog and carbon monoxide levels. It would be the third major delay since 1977.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Environmental Protection Agency today proposed delaying economic sanctions against areas that will not meet a statutory Dec. 31 deadline for reducing smog and carbon monoxide levels. It would be the third major delay since 1977.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency today proposed delaying economic sanctions against areas that will not meet a statutory Dec. 31 deadline for reducing smog and carbon monoxide levels. It would be the third major delay since 1977.</p>
        <p>The latest plan was attacked by seven Northeastern states downwind from major sources of pollution, in the Midwest. The Northeastern representatives in Congress today called the plan illegal and a retreat from the national goal of clean air. The dispute is likely to go on for months and end up in the courts.</p>
        <p>Nearly 60 large metropolitan areas will not meet the deadline for reducing ozone, a major component of smog, and carbon monoxide to maximum levels set by the Clean Air Act. The law provides sanctions to be used against cities that do not meet the deadline, including a ban on construction of plants that are large sources of pollution and the withholding of Federal funds for highways, sewers and air pollution control. Clash Over the Proposal</p>
        <p>E.P.A. officials said that in the absence of Congressional action, the new policy was necessary to assure progress against air pollution without causing the serious economic disruptions likely to result from harsh economic sanctions. The officials said that the agency had authority to delay imposing sanctions for up to five years if cities were making an effort to control the pollution.</p>
        <p>But officials from the Northeastern states and other areas contended that the agency was removing incentives for meeting the law by easing the deadlines while failing to provide enough Federal authority and assistance for dealing with pollution. The states also complained that the Federal plan did not address the regional nature of the problem.</p>
        <p>Finally, the states fear that if the new Federal plan is not supported by statute, it will leave them vulnerable to lawsuits by citizens' organizations demanding attainment of the Clean Air Act standards.</p>
        <p>The Dec. 31 deadline for reaching reduced ozone and carbon monoxide levels is itself an extension of two previous deadlines, one set for 1982, the other for 1977. The state critics say the E.P.A. policy is largely a continuation of Federal tactics that have been unsuccessful before.</p>
        <p>The policy proposed today would go into effect next spring after a 60-day period of public comment. It would require states to prepare new plans under which cities would eventually meet the smog and carbon monoxide requirements. Those plans would also have to provide for a minimum annual reduction of of 3 percent for these pollutants. Delay on Construction Ban</p>
        <p>But the new policy would delay by at least three years the imposition of any construction ban in the noncomplying areas and would put off indefinitely using the other sanctions against cities that are making good-faith efforts to reach the air pollution goals.</p>
        <p>Lee M. Thomas, Administrator of the E.P.A., termed the new policy ''tough but reasonable'' and predicted that it would ''move cities steadily toward the attainment of the standards'' but avoid ''severe social and economic disruptions, at least in the near term.''</p>
        <p>Thomas C. Jorling, Commissioner of New York State's Department of Environmental Protection, who also spoke for the States of Connecticut, New Jersey, Massachusetts, Maine, Vermont and Rhode Island, called the plan ''misguided'' and said the Federal agency had no legislative authority to approve the delay.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jorling said at a news conference here that instead Congress must act to pass legislation that will require the ozone and carbon monoxide goals to be met and also to reach other clean air goals, such as reducing the pollution that causes acid rain.</p>
        <p>New legislation has been reported in the Senate and drafted in the House to revise and strengthen the Clean Air Act. Among the revisions would be stretched-out deadlines for attaining the smog and carbon monoxide standards. But it is unlikely such legislation would be completed this year.</p>
        <p>Conrad Simon of the E.P.A.'s New York regional office said that New York and New Jersey had not been able to comply fully with their own plans for meeting the air pollution standards. Court orders resulting from lawsuits filed by the Natural Resources Defense Council, he noted, have put the two states on schedules to reduce pollution. But he added that because of the serious local problems the two states face, including pollution coming from states to the south and west, both New York and New Jersey faced a difficult task in meeting the anti-pollution goals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jorling acknowledged that New York had not done all it could to comply with the law but said that it was moving forward. But he added that without Federal regulation of interstate air pollution, without more restrictions on motor vehicle emissions and without E.P.A. guidance on appropriate technology to curb pollution, the state would not be able to do the job. He said New York State and New York City were basically agreed on the inadequacy of the Federal plan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jorling said New York could support an extension of the Dec. 31 deadline to next July 1 to give Congress a chance to amend the law. He also said that New York intends to sue the E.P.A. to force action to clean up pollution upwind of the state. Unless such pollution from outside the state is reduced, he said, New York could not on its own meet the goals of the law.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
