<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is the Air Pure or Foul? Lichens Can Tell the Tale</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="67082"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SULFUR DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LICHEN (PLANT)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRODY, JANE E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3DC103FF93BA2575BC0A961948260" item-length="1668" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is the Air Pure or Foul? Lichens Can Tell the Tale</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE E. BRODY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRODY, JANE E</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: AT the turn of the century, when ''botanizing'' was a popular pastime, dozens of naturalists spent countless hours collecting and identifying lichens, unusual unions of algae and fungi forming picturesque plants that resemble neither ''parent.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: AT the turn of the century, when ''botanizing'' was a popular pastime, dozens of naturalists spent countless hours collecting and identifying lichens, unusual unions of algae and fungi forming picturesque plants that resemble neither ''parent.''</p>
        <p>AT the turn of the century, when ''botanizing'' was a popular pastime, dozens of naturalists spent countless hours collecting and identifying lichens, unusual unions of algae and fungi forming picturesque plants that resemble neither ''parent.''</p>
        <p>For those who took the trouble to notice these lowly but often colorful denizens of such diverse environments as forests, deserts and even Antarctic rocks, lichens long served as sources of food, dyes and drugs as well as esthetic enjoyment. Indeed, one form of lichen is believed to have been the ''manna from heaven'' that in the biblical account saved the Israelites from starvation in the desert. But for most of this century lichens have been largely ignored.</p>
        <p>Now, however, lichenologists have found an important new use for these biologic curiosities: as monitors of the havoc that human beings wreak on the environment. Despite lichens' extraordinary adaptability and ability to survive in all kinds of environmental extremes, they are acutely sensitive to a major industrial atmospheric pollutant, sulfur dioxide. (In the atmosphere, sulfur dioxide can be transformed into acid rain, which, surprisingly, does not damage lichens.) Airborne pollution accounts for the absence of lichens in the heart and usually the periphery of most major cities. Finding even one sickly lichen alive in an urban downtown, such as those Dr. Clifford Wetmore occasionally sees in St. Paul, is considered a sign of relative cleanliness.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wetmore, a University of Minnesota botanist who has devoted his career to this still largely mysterious organism, has spent the last five summers working in national parks throughout the country as what might be called a lichen epidemiologist. He has counted, collected and catalogued lichens, assessed their health status and analyzed the foreign elements that can contaminate their tissues.</p>
        <p>The information he has extracted from these silent monitors not only shows much about air pollution in the present and the recent past but also hints at potential problems that warrant close observation. And, according to Dr. Wetmore, the cost of using this biological monitoring technique is a mere fraction of what it would be to monitor just current pollution levels with instruments. For example, the three-month survey he conducted of lichens in Isle Royale National Park in Lake Superior cost just $13,000, he said, whereas merely setting up the monitoring equipment he recommended as a result of his findings cost $200,000.</p>
        <p>''Isle Royale is a pristine environment, and the National Park Service would like to keep it that way,'' Dr. Wetmore said in a recent interview. ''But from the lichen damage in certain areas, I can tell that some pollution is coming in, probably from Thunder Bay in Canada, where there is a paper plant and other industries and no scrubbers on the smokestacks.''</p>
        <p>By contrast, the lichens in Indiana Dunes, a national lakeshore near Gary, Ind., a city infamous for its pungent industrial odors, have suffered serious sulfur dioxide damage. When Dr. Wetmore compared his lichen collection with those of 1890's naturalists, he discovered that ''many species have been eliminated, and the ones that remain - only species tolerant to sulfur dioxide - are small, distorted and not fertile.'' He added that the lichens' tale of ''air quality degradation extends all the way to Warren Dunes in Michigan.'' Devastation in Ohio</p>
        <p>Equally devastated were the lichens in Cuyahoga Valley National Recreation Area, situated between the industrialized cities of Akron and Cleveland, the lichenologist reported. His study in 1985 found that ''81 percent of the 172 species reported to be living in the area before 1917 are now missing.''</p>
        <p>Even more important, Dr. Wetmore said, was the discovery that all the Cuyahoga Valley lichens containing blue-green algae were gone. These algae (which are actually a family of chlorophyll-containing bacteria) ''fix'' atmospheric nitrogen, turning it into a form that plants can use for nourishment. Lichens made up of blue-green algae are now recognized as major sources of nitrogen fertilizer in some areas, such as deserts and forests. Since the lichens that contain nitrogen-fixing blue-green algae are among those most sensitive to sulfur dioxide, this pollutant can cause long-range losses in fertility.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wetmore also performs elemental analyses on some of the lichens he collects. Since lichens incorporate minerals and other elements from the environment into their tissues, they can reveal the presence of nonlethal levels of such ''pollutants'' as copper, zinc, lead and sulfur. Prospectors might even use lichens to pinpoint the location of minable minerals, he said.</p>
        <p>In Cuyahoga Valley, the elemental analysis revealed elevated levels of automotive pollutants in the lichens in one part of the park and industrial minerals in the lichens elsewhere. Chernobyl's Effects</p>
        <p>Compared with instrument monitoring or assessing lichen damage directly, Dr. Wetmore explained, ''elemental analysis is a much more sensitive way to look at air pollution, because living lichens accumulate pollutants in the air and, by magnifying low-level contamininants, can serve as harbingers of future problems.''</p>
        <p>Lichens are long-lived, surviving for perhaps half a century, and when they become contaminated the effect can be devastating for decades. For example, as a result of the Chernobyl nuclear accident last year, the lichens that reindeer and caribou rely on for winter food are now contaminated with radioactivity. This has forced the slaughter of reindeer herds in Scandinavia, severely disrupting the lives of Lapp herders.</p>
        <p>Even the early lichenologists recognized the unusual nature of lichens as reflecting a symbiotic relationship between an alga and a fungus. Though it has long been thought that both partners benefit from their association, recent studies by one expert suggest that a lichen results from a parasitic attack on the alga by the fungus.</p>
        <p>This expert is Dr. Vernon Ahmadjian of Clark University in Worcester, Mass., co-author with Surindar Paracer of ''Symbiosis: An Introduction to Biological Associations'' (University Press of New England, 1986). Dr. Ahmadjian explains that symbiosis refers merely to two organisms that share the same living space. The relationship can be one of mutualism, in which each organism benefits from the union; parasitism, in which one is benefited but the other harmed, or commensalism, in which one is benefited and the other neither benefited nor harmed.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ahmadjian, who mastered the technique of splitting the lichen into its component parts, growing the partners separately and then reuniting them, said his research suggested that most lichens reflect a ''controlled parasitism'' in which the fungus invades the alga, killing many of the algal cells and forcing the surviving cells to release food to sustain the fungus. This idea was first proposed in 1867 to the Swiss Naturalists' Club by Simon Schwendener, whose suggestion was soundly ridiculed by his scientific contemporaries.</p>
        <p>The fungus, Dr. Ahmadjian explained, makes up well over 90 percent of a lichen; its growth depends on the alga, which can produce food through photosynthesis. ''The fungus is clearly the dominant partner,'' he said. What the alga gets in return is a matter of considerable controversy. Some lichenologists say the fungus provides vitamins and a protective home for the alga. But according to Dr. Ahmadjian, ''To call this mutualism would be like saying that domestic cattle and humans have a mutualistic relationship just because we provide them with food and shelter before we slaughter them.'' Economic Implications</p>
        <p>Dr. Ahmadjian foresees yet another potential use for lichens: that of isolating the genes that allow lichens to live in strange environments and incorporating those genes into economically important plants.</p>
        <p>Typically, lichens like it where the environment is moist and sunny at least some of the time, although many species of lichens can tolerate extremes of heat or cold, wetness or dryness. When conditions that favor growth are absent, they simply lie dormant until their lot improves. Lichens can reproduce asexually by forming soredia, or globules of algal cells surrounded by fungal strands, and sexually with fungal spores, which may later join up with algae. Or pieces of a lichen can break off and start a new one. But the partners that form lichens are rarely found living independently in nature; rather, the alga-fungus marriage seems critical to their survival.</p>
        <p>Lichens grow on rocks, trees (typically on the moister north side), soil, picnic tables, abandoned cars and, in New Guinea, even on the backs of certain beetles. In the dry, barren valleys of Antarctica, they have been found inside rocks.</p>
        <p>Slowly, the acids and other compounds produced and released by lichens, as well as the mechanical force of lichen growth, can disintegrate rocks and wood and turn them into soil. Lichens also trap dust and pollen and can themselves disintegrate to gradually build up soil. Approximately half the 20,000 known species of lichens produce compounds with antibiotic properties, many of which are used medicinally by native populations.</p>
        <p>In form, these organisms vary from what might be likened to a bonsai forest of miniature trees to undulating disks and crusts that cling to rocks; some hang from trees like Spanish moss. The colors similarly vary: yellow, orange, red, green, brown, black, white and often combinations.</p>
        <p>As Dr. Wetmore's five-year contract with the National Park Service draws to a close - at the behest of Congress, the service plans to make other types of pollution assessments in the parks - he says he will miss his summers among these intriguing freaks of nature. To Dr. Wetmore, lichens are more than a life's work. ''They are an environmental treasure,'' he said, ''even if all they did was add to the beauty and diversity of our surroundings.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
