<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'A PARTICULARLY FRUSTRATING SITUATION'</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="99384"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="CONNECTICUT Q&amp;A: LEONARD J. BRUCKMAN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION, DEPARTMENT OF (CONN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAMILTON, ROBERT A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRUCKMAN, LEONARD J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4D7173DF935A35751C1A961948260" item-length="1511" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'A PARTICULARLY FRUSTRATING SITUATION'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT A. HAMILTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAMILTON, ROBERT A</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: LEONARD J. BRUCKMAN is the head of the air quality unit of the State Department of Environmental Protection. His department has been responding in recent weeks to Federal criticism of the ozone level in the state, which exceeds the 0.12 parts per million standard set in the 1970's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: LEONARD J. BRUCKMAN is the head of the air quality unit of the State Department of Environmental Protection. His department has been responding in recent weeks to Federal criticism of the ozone level in the state, which exceeds the 0.12 parts per million standard set in the 1970's.</p>
        <p>LEONARD J. BRUCKMAN is the head of the air quality unit of the State Department of Environmental Protection. His department has been responding in recent weeks to Federal criticism of the ozone level in the state, which exceeds the 0.12 parts per million standard set in the 1970's.</p>
        <p>The Federal Clean Air Act, which requires compliance with that standard, was supposed to expire at the end of this year, but because Connecticut and other states have not met the standard, the act is to be extended five years, with possible Federal sanctions for noncomplying states. The New England states, New York and New Jersey have formally protested the Federal policy. In his office in Hartford, where he oversees a staff of nearly 100 employees, Mr. Bruckman talked the other day about ozone. Following are some excerpts from the conversation.</p>
        <p>Q. What are the health effects of ozone?</p>
        <p>A. Ozone is the kind of generic name we give for photochemical smog in the summer. Ozone itself is a pulmonary irritant, so it can cause labored breathing or chest pains if you're asthmatic. But it really is an indicator of other things in the smog, the particulate organic compounds that can be carcinogenic.</p>
        <p>Q. At 0.12 parts per million, how dangerous is the ozone level now to Connecticut residents?</p>
        <p>A. It may not be the most dangerous air pollutant, but it affects, because of its regional nature, three million people. We have other compounds that might be more dangerous pound for pound, but they tend to be more localized. Dioxins, lead -those kind of things tend to be more associated with stationary sources. That makes it a serious pollutant because it affects a large number of people.</p>
        <p>Q. How is ozone produced?</p>
        <p>A. You don't emit ozone like you do sulfur dioxide. What you do is emit the ozone precursors, the hydrocarbons and nitrogen oxides, and then under the influence of temperature and sunlight, you get photochemical reactions that ultimately produce ozone, and that also produce some of these other particulate hydrocarbons.</p>
        <p>Q. What areas of the state tend to be the worst?</p>
        <p>A. As a general statement, on the days we experience the highest level it's because of the effect of the New York City plume, and the areas that tend to be the worst are areas in the area between New Haven and Hartford, and that's because it takes that much time for the chemistry. It takes so many hours to form ozone.</p>
        <p>The precursors that are emitted in the morning, by the time it cooks and reacts it's late afternoon and that air is between New Haven and Hartford. Sometimes it can slide east into the Groton area; it depends on the meteorology. But that doesn't mean the rest of the state isn't above the standard.</p>
        <p>Q. How much of Connecticut's ozone problem is due to sources outside the state, like New York City?</p>
        <p>A. If we shut down the entire state, there would be violations of the standard because of sources from outside the state. We're in a particularly frustrating situation. Until the Federal Government makes some of the source regions outside of the Northeast implement the control programs we've done, we're never going to get anywhere. There's a lack of leadership and willingness to implement control programs where the stuff is being generated. They have a real ''fix it where you measure it'' philosophy, instead of fixing it where it's created.</p>
        <p>Q. Is New York the only source of air pollutants coming into this region?</p>
        <p>A. No. There's two areas of problem. There's the interregional problem, the plume that comes in from New York City. That takes less than a day. Then we have extraregional, that comes in from 100 to 500 miles away. This air mass - maybe it starts out in the Midwest or the South - it moves across the United States like a big box, and everything is put into the box. Then it moves off the Atlantic Coast, and the circulation brings it into Connecticut. Those forest fires in Georgia that blanketed Connecticut with smoke a few weeks ago are a perfect example. That pollution wasn't coming from New York City. But with ozone you can't see the smoke. With acid rain you can't see the smoke.</p>
        <p>We need the Federal Government to control sources outside our region, otherwise it's a hopeless effort. Although New York and New Jersey and Massachusetts might not have done everything in their plans, they've done quite a bit. they've done a lot more than the people in the Midwest, the Atlantic States, and down South, and that's where we're really looking to get control programs into place.</p>
        <p>Q. How likely is the passage of a Federal control program?</p>
        <p>A. The Administration, at the Federal level, has not placed the environment as a high priority, and certainly they would perceive it as unpopular to go into a state where they're trying to pump up the economy and tell it it has to put in costly control programs which will have no real benefit locally but will benefit some other region of the country. That's the exact role for the Federal Government, to overcome the parochial stand of the state, but the likelihood of that happening is slim. The Environmental Protection Agency would just as soon not have to require these programs, they'd rather have Congress do it, and we're caught in the middle.</p>
        <p>Q. Will ozone return to a natural balance if the precursors are cleaned up or is the ozone here now something that will have to be cleaned up?</p>
        <p>A. It doesn't stay in the atmosphere. It's not something that has a long residency. It's not going to be zero; you'll always have some background ozone. In areas that are heavily forested you'll get some. Pine trees have compounds that can contribute to ozone formation. Ozone is an oxidizing agent, so it reacts with other compounds.</p>
        <p>Q. Scientists have asked for a ban on the use of chlorofluorocarbons, which deplete the ozone in the stratosphere. Is there any connection between the abundance of ozone in the atmosphere, and the shortage of ozone in the stratosphere?</p>
        <p>A. Absolutely no connection at all. That's a source of a lot of confusion. Ozone in the stratosphere is way up there screening out ultraviolet light which causes cancer. This ozone is down at the surface. It's strictly an air pollutant, an oxidizing agent indicative of other kinds of harmful compounds.</p>
        <p>Q. Connecticut's controversial auto emissions program - has that had a measurable impact on air quality?</p>
        <p>A. Our analysis indicates the control programs have reduced the violation of ozone on the days when air is fairly dead or there are light and variable winds. We think we have to do a little more, so we're looking at other control programs. But we're very close to what we feel is attainment on those days when we control our own destiny, and our inspection and maintenance is a cornerstone of our control program. It's probably the most significant of all our programs.</p>
        <p>Q. What effect will the program to reduce the volatility of gasoline sold in the state, which is intended to reduce gasoline vapors, have on price and performance?</p>
        <p>A. It's certainly going to affect price. The price is going to go up a couple, three cents at the most. It shouldn't affect driveability, performance, because it's only going to be required in the summer months. If you required that kind of gasoline in the winter, you might have a starting and performance problem.</p>
        <p>Q. Is Connecticut going to face any Federal sanctions for not meeting the clean air goals?</p>
        <p>A. The only sanction we might face is the construction moratorium on large pollution sources, but we don't have here the big hydrocarbon sources like an automobile assembly plant or that kind of thing. I don't think that would have much of an impact here. All the big sources are in the South and Midwest, so we get a double whammy: they leave here and we get their air pollution anyway. Not only have we done everything in our plan but we've gone beyond our plan, so we won't face any sanctions for failing to live up to our plan.</p>
        <p>Q. What other air quality programs is Connecticut working on currently?</p>
        <p>A. We've got the toxic control program. There's a list of 850 compounds that are hazardous. Right now it keys off the occupational standards, to limit risk while we develop more specific standards. Right now we're working on sulfuric acid; we're working on perchlorethylene and trichlorethylene, which are emissions of dry-cleaning operations, we're looking at a number of compounds.</p>
        <p>Q. Is this an attempt to get ahead of problems before they can develop into a serious hazard, such as the ozone problem?</p>
        <p>A. Yes, this is a prospective rather than a retrospective program. The way the toxic program is set up, it applies to existing facilities. Our dioxin program, for instance, doesn't only address new resource recovery facilities, those emission will apply to incinerators that don't have heat recovery, hospital incinerators, existing resource recovery facilities like Windham's, which we're retrofitting with control, or anything else that emits dioxin. It tries to get out in front of the issues rather than react to the issues.</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT Q&amp;A: LEONARD J. BRUCKMAN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
