<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SEARCHING FOR THE KEY TO SCIENCE LITERACY</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Survey of Education Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISKE, EDWARD B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE6D61230F937A35752C0A961948260" item-length="3801" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SEARCHING FOR THE KEY TO SCIENCE LITERACY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Edward B. Fiske</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FISKE, EDWARD B</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A PARADOX exists in the teaching of science in the United States. This nation produces far more Nobel Prize laureates in science than any other country in the world. The most talented foreigners flock to American universities to earn degrees in science and many elect to work and teach here. There is general confidence that</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A PARADOX exists in the teaching of science in the United States. This nation produces far more Nobel Prize laureates in science than any other country in the world. The most talented foreigners flock to American universities to earn degrees in science and many elect to work and teach here. There is general confidence that</p>
        <p>A PARADOX exists in the teaching of science in the United States. This nation produces far more Nobel Prize laureates in science than any other country in the world. The most talented foreigners flock to American universities to earn degrees in science and many elect to work and teach here. There is general confidence that American schools are continuing to produce enough professional scientists to maintain the nation's economic and military strength.</p>
        <p>Yet scientists and educators are increasingly concerned about what they perceive as a growing chasm between America's science ''haves'' and its ''have-nots.'' Citizens are routinely finding themselves facing decisions that require scientific judgments -from national policies on nuclear power and ''Star Wars'' to personal decisions about the risks of sexually transmitted diseases. But there is uneasiness that many Americans are ill equipped by their science educations to make such decisions intelligently.</p>
        <p>''Letting the experts run things is not appropriate for a democracy,'' says Robert Pollack, a molecular biologist and dean of Columbia College. ''American citizens have an obligation to understand things, and that means becoming scientifically literate.''</p>
        <p>The blame for low levels of scientific understanding is being increasingly laid at the door of the nation's schools. Last fall, Secretary of Education William J. Bennett issued a scathing indictment of the way science is taught in American classrooms, charging that it tends to consist either of the tedious transfer of facts from teacher to student or of a ''grab-bag of esoteric stunts.'' A 1983 report to the National Science Board, which sets policy for the federally supported National Science Foundation, put the problem just as bluntly: ''The nation that dramatically and boldly led the world into the age of technology is failing to provide its own children with the intellectual tools needed for the 21st century.''</p>
        <p>International comparisons consistently show that American students study less science and math than their counterparts in Japan, West Germany and other developed countries - and consequently know a lot less about it. This low achievement eventually translates into widespread ignorance about science among adults.</p>
        <p>Just how ignorant Americans may be about science was tested last year by Jon D. Miller, director of the Public Opinion Laboratory at Northern Illinois University. Mr. Miller interviewed 2,000 adults and found that more than two out of five agreed that ''Space shots have caused changes in our weather.'' A comparable proportion said that ''Some numbers are especially lucky for some people.'' More than a third of those interviewed also agreed that ''Science tends to break down people's ideas of right and wrong.'' To reverse the plunge into science illiteracy, educators have begun experimenting with new approaches to ''hands-on'' learning. In addition, leaders of the National Science Foundation and other governmental agencies have been pushing for new Federal programs to train science teachers and to rethink the kind of scientific education that Americans require. Such efforts are supported by many corporate leaders who are worried that their next generation of employees will not be prepared to deal with new discoveries and technologies that are changing their products, markets and operations. Echoes of Sputnik Fears - But With a Difference rrxhFor some Americans, much of the current concern over science illiteracy has echoes in the American reaction to Sputnik, the Soviet satellite that in 1957 was the first to be orbited in space. For more than a decade after Sputnik's launching, Congress underwrote a major effort to upgrade the quality of science teaching in the United States. Scientists were recruited to create a series of sophisticated high school curriculums in physics, chemistry and other subjects, and a whole generation of science teachers was trained through summer workshops and other crash programs.</p>
        <p>The post-Sputnik era differed in one fundamental respect from the current one. In the late 1950's the challenge facing the nation was to develop a cadre of scientists who could assure that the United States would remain militarily and economically competitive. Today there is little concern expressed about the nation's capacity to produce scientists. The field has intrinsic appeal to bright students, who are frequently identified at a young age. The best high schools offer first-rate science courses, and graduate fellowships are readily available to college science majors. Salaries in industry are competitive, and while scientists complain about cutbacks under the Reagan Administration, the level of scientific research remains high.</p>
        <p>''By and large we are getting the people we need,'' says Lewis Branscomb, who recently stepped down as chief scientist at the International Business Machines Corporation to teach at Harvard. ''But then you only need 20 percent of the high schools to produce them.''</p>
        <p>The problems with scientists relate not so much to numbers as to who they will be. Mr. Branscomb and others note that there is a major ''equity'' issue, since relatively few members of minority groups and women find their way into the ranks.</p>
        <p>According to the Department of Education, American undergraduates majoring in science has been declining. Science degrees as a proportion of all undergraduate degrees have dropped from 32 to 29 percent since the late 1960's. Even those students who do major in science tend to take premium salaries in industry upon graduation rather than go on to graduate schools. Consequently, a growing percentage of college teaching and research posts are held by foreigners.</p>
        <p>Although the flow of future Nobel Prize winners and other scientists seems assured, concern is rampant about the science illiteracy of the public, which must understand and manage what scientists develop. ''A democratic society cannot function in a technological age if a high proportion of its members are uninformed about what constitutes scientific evidence,'' says David A. Goslin, executive director for education at the National Academy of Sciences.</p>
        <p>Examples abound of scientific findings having an impact on social, political and personal judgments. A California court is now involved in the issue of whether it is safe to spray potato plants with genetically engineered bacteria in an effort to protect them from frost. Congress has been caught between the Reagan Administration's requests for funds for the Strategic Defense Initiative, popularly known as ''Star Wars,'' and the arguments of some scientists that the missile-defense system won't work. Many scientists believe that, because of excessive fears about the dangers of nuclear power plants, the United States will eventually find itself falling behind other countries.</p>
        <p>''It's important for people to understand that there are trade-offs involved in any kind of power,'' says George Bugliarello, president of Polytechnic University, in Brooklyn. ''The dangers of nuclear power are well known, but less known is the fact that coal causes acid rain.'' He notes that Vermont is now struggling with pollution problems resulting from extensive use of coal-burning stoves. ''It's fine to say that small is beautiful,'' Mr. Bugliarello says. ''But the scientifically literate person also recognizes the collective impact of many small actions.''</p>
        <p>Several scientists cite concern about AIDS as an example of how the level of scientific literacy affects public policy. In deciding whether to permit students with the disease to attend classes, school boards have had to assess evidence from scientists on whether it can be transmitted by casual contact.</p>
        <p>Scientists say that it is also important for the public to understand the limitations of science. Maxine F. Singer, a biochemist who is editor of The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, notes that when AIDS first emerged scientists knew virtually nothing about it. ''We've learned an astonishing amount in less than five years - more than we have ever learned about anything that quickly,'' she says. ''But there are people who say that all this money has been spent and we don't have a vaccine or a cure. They don't understand that we don't have a cure for any viral disease - measles, influenza, you name it. If we ever got a cure for AIDS, it would be incredible.'' Low Number of Courses In Science Is Deplored rrxhConcern about scientific illiteracy begins with the basic fact that American students simply don't study much science. Science Indicators, a biennial report to the National Science Foundation on the condition of science and technology, cites figures showing that less than half of all high school juniors and only a third of seniors take a science course. ''The tenth grade is the last time that most high school students in the United States are exposed to science,'' it declares. As a result, American high school students receive ''only one-half to one-third the exposure to science'' as their counterparts in other developed countries such as Japan, West Germany, East Germany and the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>Similar patterns exist with math. American students take an average of 2.7 years of math during their four years of high school; only two-thirds complete Algebra I and only half get through geometry.</p>
        <p>Virtually all high schools teach some science, but the range varies widely. A recent National Science Teachers Association survey found that of the nation's 24,000 high schools 7,000 offer no physics, 4,000 no chemistry and 2,000 no biology. American students do poorly on standardized tests of their scientific and mathematical knowledge. The National Assessment of Educational Progress, a federally supported project to measure student achievement, found consistent declines between 1969 and 1982 in the scientific knowledge of 9-, 13- and 17-year-olds. International comparisons of mathematical performance routinely put Americans at or near the bottom.</p>
        <p>The way science is taught at all levels also comes in for heavy criticism. Instruction in primary schools is portrayed as a haphazard affair in which ill-trained teachers seem to succeed primarily in conveying their own anxiety and negative attitudes about the subjects. Studies of high school science teaching report that most instruction comes in the form of lecturing by the teacher, usually straight out of a textbook that is probably out of date. The emphasis is on the conclusions of science, not the process, and priority is given to ''coverage'' - or getting through the textbook.</p>
        <p>''Most high school science courses are watered-down versions of introductory college courses,'' says Bill G. Aldridge, executive director of the National Science Teachers Association. ''This makes life easier for college professors, since they are teaching less new information, but it doesn't help the 93 percent of students who will never take a college science course and really need something else at the high school level.''</p>
        <p>As for the college courses, a task force formed by the National Science Board reported last April that they are marked by ''serious problems,'' notably that ''laboratory instruction, which is at the heart of science and engineering education, has deteriorated to the point where it is often uninspired, tedious and dull.''</p>
        <p>Running through all these criticisms is the feeling that what passes for science in American schools has little to do with what science is really all about. ''Science is not a list of facts and principles to learn by rote; it is a way of looking at the world and asking questions,'' says James Rutherford of the American Association for the Advancement of Science. ''How often do you see elementary school kids outside collecting leaves and bugs and then doing something with them?''</p>
        <p>High school textbooks, he observes, are replete with ''Latin names that kids learn and immediately forget,'' while labs have little to do with the way scientists work. ''Kids go in, set up some equipment, gather data and verify a predetermined conclusion -all in 45 minutes,'' he says. ''And verifying what Newton did 300 years ago is hardly science. Does anyone ever ask whether Newton might have got it wrong?'' Signs Indicate That More Students Are Being Challenged rrxhEfforts to change the situation have begun, largely as part of the broad national movement to improve the quality of instruction in American public schools in all basic subjects. According to the Education Commission of the States, 41 states have increased the number of science courses required for a high school diploma. In 10 states, including Connecticut, three full years of science study are now necessary for graduation; Connecticut previously required no science courses. New York now requires two science courses, up from one. New Jersey still requires one course.</p>
        <p>There are other encouraging signs. Science-oriented ''magnet'' schools are proliferating in Houston, Los Angeles and other cities and at least three states have, or soon will have, high schools modeled on such leaders as the Bronx High School of Science.</p>
        <p>The College Board reports that the number of students taking Advanced Placement courses in math and science has steadily increased, from 16,500 in 1965 to 99,200 last year, with the growth among female students triple that of males. ''These figures do not necessarily herald a renaissance in math and science education,'' cautions George Hanford, outgoing president of the board. ''But they do indicate that high schools are becoming more interested in challenging their college-bound students in these subjects.''</p>
        <p>Many critics argue that making students take more of the same old things is not enough. Some elementary schools have begun to address their own problems, particularly the lack of scientific training of teachers.</p>
        <p>At the Anne Beers Elementary School in Washington, for example, an abandoned wing has been turned over entirely to science instruction. Every day, classroom teachers escort their classes to the science facility, which includes two laboratories and a wealth of materials that students can manipulate. The wing is run by Gloria Tucker, who, with an assistant, helps teachers prepare their lessons and makes sure that laboratories and classrooms are set up with the right materials when the classes arrive.</p>
        <p>''I didn't particularly care about science,'' says Ruth Walls, a fifth-grade teacher. ''I was required to do science only two days a week, and I'd pretty much teach what I was interested in. Now I do it five days a week and follow a specific curriculum.'' Teachers say that the new system allows more integration of science with other subjects, such as having students write language-arts essays about scientific topics.</p>
        <p>Numerous high schools also have begun to put more emphasis on hands-on instruction. At the Benjamin N. Cardozo High School in Bayside, Queens, students can be seen creating static electricity that makes their hair stand on end or mixing colored lights as a means of studying reflection. ''We are in the business of getting kids to inquire,'' explains Bertram L. Linder, the school's principal.</p>
        <p>The approach seems to be paying off. Howard Sklanberg, a Cardozo senior, recalls an experience in his freshman biology course in which he heated yogurt samples on a microscope slide and watched the bacteria. ''I had just seen a commercial about how healthy yogurt was, and there were all these bacteria moving around,'' he says. His close encounter with the inner world of yogurt apparently had its intended effect, for the 17-year-old student is now hard at work on a paper on ''The Effect of Induced Microtubial Polymerization on the Extension of Dorsal Root Ganglia Neurites.''</p>
        <p>Some science educators, however, believe that a fundamental transformation must occur in the way science courses are organized in high schools. ''The usual sequence - first biology, then chemistry, then physics - is upside down,'' says Gerald Holton, a Harvard physicist and historian of science who was a member of the National Commission on Excellence in Education. ''You can't understand chemisty without basic physics, and you can't understand biology without knowing its chemical and physical base.'' High Schools Intensify Effort To Attract Quality Teachers rrxhOne major obstacle to creating a scientifically literate population, many educators maintain, is the lack of qualified high school teachers. For several years the National Science Teachers Association has been sounding an alarm on this issue, maintaining that nearly a third of science teachers are ''unqualified'' to teach and that there is a serious shortage of science and math teachers. In response, a number of states have initiated crash programs to attract science teachers through such incentives as forgiving student loans in return for several years of service in the classroom. The teachers' association has called for a new system of certifying science teachers for multiple assignments. ''We need persons trained in related disciplines, like physics, chemistry and mathematics,'' Mr. Aldridge says.  Yet with more states establishing tougher science requirements, the demand for science teachers is intensifying at a time when talented science and math students are being actively recruited by industry. Scientists have begun calling for a revival of the summer workshops, graduate fellowships and other successful teaching-development programs that were run by the National Science Foundation, the principal Federal agency in charge of scientific research and education, during the post-Sputnik era.</p>
        <p>But the role of the Federal Government in improving scientific literacy remains controversial. After Neil Armstrong landed on the moon in 1969, the nation seemed to turn its attention to other issues besides science programs. Many foundation programs were allowed to lapse, and when the Reagan Administration came into office in 1981 it sought further cutbacks. The Federal science education budget dropped from $75 million in 1981 to a low of $21 million in 1982, and that was double the Administration's request. In response to growing concern about the quality of American education, Congress has increased spending to $100 million, with further increases expected.</p>
        <p>Although sharply critical of the quality of science education in American schools, Secretary Bennett has resisted the arguments of those who say that the time has come for another expensive Federal effort similar to what occurred following Sputnik. He argues that major changes can be brought about not by spending large amounts of money on new curriculums or raising teacher salaries, but through fundamental but relatively inexpensive changes in teaching methods. ''As a 'hands-on' adventure guided by a knowledgeable teacher,'' he declares, ''science can sweep children up in the excitement of discovery.'' To those who say that good science requires expensive equipment, he suggests that local sources of funds are readily available. ''Here is a place where business, industry, science centers and universities can all help,'' he says. The Question Remains: What Do Students Need to Know? rrxhUnderlying these issues is the question of what a student needs to be taught about science to prepare him for his role as an intelligent citizen.</p>
        <p>In mathematics there appears to be a consensus. Math educators agree on the need to place more emphasis on problem-solving than on developing basic calculating skills. In New York, California and elsewhere, a major push is under way to replace the current high school pre-calculus progression of algebra and geometry with the ''integrated'' approach routine in European schools. This method shuns artificial distinctions between these subject areas and puts relatively more emphasis on statistics, probability and the so-called discrete mathematics basic to computers.</p>
        <p>When it comes to science, though, educators are still trying to think through what it means to be scientifically literate. The National Science Foundation, in an effort entitled ''Project Synthesis,'' has identified a ''cluster'' of goals, ranging from ''personal needs'' - how babies are created, elementary electricity and so forth - to the sort of information about ''societal issues'' that students will need to deal with as voters. Implicit in this effort is the idea that scientific literacy involves much more than knowledge of some conclusions that scientists have reached in the past. As the official description puts it, ''Science can be thought of as a body of ideas, a way of thinking and investigating, a community of workers engaged in a complex social enterprise, and as a powerful force affecting how we live.''</p>
        <p>The American Association for the Advancement of Science has also embarked on a major effort called Project 2061 (after the year Halley's Comet will next return) that will attempt to define what students need to know about science, develop curriculums and materials for teacher training and, finally, to put the new approach into effect in schools across the nation. As with Project Synthesis, however, practical results appear years away.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most innovative approach to scientific literacy is contained in a course entitled ''Theory and Practice of Science'' that Columbia University has been offering since 1981 as a way for nonscience majors to fulfill their science requirement. The goal is to convey to students the way in which scientists think and work by ''bringing the culture of science into the classroom.''</p>
        <p>Students begin with four weeks of math and are then taught enough science to be able to work their way through several important scientific works, such as Johann Gregor Mendel's pioneering 1866 paper on the cross-breeding of peas that helped lay the groundwork for the modern field of genetics. Students follow Mendel's thinking, including the questions he asked, his hypotheses, the design of his experiment, the data he gathered and how he transformed figures on the ratio of round and wrinkled peas into a theory of ''dominant'' and ''recessive'' genetic traits.</p>
        <p>Columbia's Dean Pollack stresses that science is not a series of conclusions but a way of thinking about the world. ''Science is essentially a structure for asking questions,'' he says, ''and every 5-year-old is a natural scientist because every 5-year-old is curious about the world.'' Schools at all levels have managed to squelch this natural enthusiasm, he says, but the need to find ways of reviving it is great.</p>
        <p>''For an individual, knowing how to ask the right questions is part of being educated,'' he says. ''For a democratic society, empowering people to do this is a fundamental responsibility.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
