<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Food Inspection Results</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="88" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="101458"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SANITATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HEALTH, DEPARTMENT OF (NYC)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFD91E3EF930A25751C1A961948260" item-length="1143" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Food Inspection Results</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The New York City Department of Health last week released a list of 34 food establishments cited for violating the health code.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The New York City Department of Health last week released a list of 34 food establishments cited for violating the health code.</p>
        <p>The New York City Department of Health last week released a list of 34 food establishments cited for violating the health code.</p>
        <p>In addition, it listed five restaurants that were allowed to reopen after correcting earlier violations and two that were closed for having failed to do so.</p>
        <p>The establishments are these:  VIOLATIONS  MANHATTAN  Blimpie's, 362 7th Ave. (30th St.). Flies in basement, old food and dust on basement floor, celiling tiles missing.  Caribbean Creole Restaurant, 852 Amsterdam Ave. (101th St.). Grease on range filters and exhaust fans, hole in kitchen floor, dirt on kitchen wall, peeling paint, mouse droppings, sink for rinsing dishes broken, boxes on kitchen floor.  Chelsea's, 176 7th Ave. (20th St.). No food-protection certificate, previous inspection report not available.  Cherry Blossom, 545 5th Ave. (44th St.). Mouse droppings in kithcen and storage room, flies.  Deli Express, 132 Delancey St. (Norfolk St.).</p>
        <p>Some food uncovered, previous inspection report unavailable, no soap in employee bathroom, dust on refrigerator fan, old flour on dough mixer, dirt and grease on floor, ceiling panels missing, mouse droppings on basement shelves, carbon dioxide canister not secured to basement wall, holes in basement floor, material stored directly on basement floor, no food-inspection certificate, no valid permit.  Gen Ling Restaurant, 165 Hester St. (Elizabeth St.). Grease on range hood and filters, exhaust system built improperly.  Giorgio's Pizza, 122 Chambers St. (Church St.).</p>
        <p>Old food on can opener, grease and old food on fan guards, some food uncovered, dirty dough container, some food too cool, dirt on floor.  King Fung Restaurant, 20 Elizabeth St. (Bayard St.). Old food and dust in refigerator, seams in cutting board, old food on slicing machine, old food on floor, rat droppings on basement floor and shelves, flies, no equipment to prevent formation of vacuum in basement sink.  Mambi III, 124 Dyckman St. (St. Nicholas Ave.). Holes in basement ceiling, uncapped sewer line, dishwashing equipment inadequate, some food at improper temperatures.  Las Mananitas Mexican Restaurant, 322 E. 14th St. Dishwashing equipment inadequate, old food on can opener, grooves in kitchen cutting table, reach-in refrigerator doors do not close properly.  McSherry's Tavern, 4944 Broadway (207th St.).</p>
        <p>Equipment for washing bar glasses inadequate, hole in floor, dirt on kitchen walls and basement storage shelves, grease on stove, shelves in refrigerator covered with old food and corroded, food stored improperly, no bulb guards in refrigerator, no food covers, leak under sink, material stored improperly, hot-water heater improperly vented.  Miss Kim's Deli, 12 Nassau St. (Wall St.). No valid permit, no guard on refrigerator bulbs.  North of the Border, 155 W. 46th St. No proper permit, wood floor under sink, skylight broken, hole in wall and in hot-water flue, leak in hot-water pipe.  Not Just Bagels, 217 E. 23d St. Rat droppings in basement.  Oakwood Cafe, 132 W. 31st St. Mouse droppings on stairs, goods stored improperly, no valid permit.  Oggie's Deli, 125 E. 41st St. Food containers uncovered and on floor, food at improper temperatures, mouse droppings, old food and grease on floor, boxes on floor.  Szechuan House, 92 7th Ave. S. (15th St.). Floor tiles missing, no test kit for chemicals in sanitizer.  Wimp's, 29 W. 125th St. No valid permit, some food uncovered, dust on floors and shelves, rear door not flush with floor.  BROOKLYN  Angelo's Pizza, 1 Tompkins Ave. (Flushing Ave.). Rat droppings, no extermination report available.  Camille's, 311 Henry St. (Atlantic Ave.). Milk crates as storage shelves, mouse droppings, holes in bathroom wall, leak in basement pipe.  Daily Wok Chinese Restaurant, Ave. I Flea Market (McDonald Ave.). No valid permit or food-protection certificate, no guard on ceiling light.  F &amp; M Bakery, 256 Broadway (S. 8th St.). No sink for washing hands, no two-compartment sink for pots, rat droppings, no extermination report available, fly strips above food preparation table, old food on refrigerator door, dust on shelves, dirt on floor, equipment on floor.  New Jade Chinese Restaurant, 1103 Kings Hwy. (Coney I. Ave.). Flies and roaches in basement, rinse water too cool, no sign warning employees to wash hands in bathroom, boxes on milk crates.  Nino's Napoli, 1712 Pitkin Ave. (Rockaway Ave.). No valid permit or no food-protection certificate.  Rex Seafood, 222 7th Ave. No valid permit, boxes on floor, grease on floor, rat droppings.  QUEENS  Amica Pizza, 24-06 34th Ave. Previous inspection report not available, no soap or paper towel in employees' bathroom, dirt and grease on basement floor, holes in ceiling, mouse droppings, no valid permit, roaches, ice-cream scoop stored improperly, inadequate extermination.  Cookie Express, 76-07 37th Ave. Mouse droppings, dirt on kitchen floor and walls, no screen on kitchen door, old food on refrigerator walls, glass door on display cabinet broken, no bathroom for customers, inadequate bathroom near food-preparation area, flypaper strips over preparation and storage areas, no protection certificate.  Lemonia Restaurant, 29-19 Broadway. Dirt on basement floor, holes in ceiling and walls, supplies on milk crates, mouse droppings on shelves and basement floor.  McDonald's, 250-01 Northern Blvd. Flies.  North Shore Diner, 196-20 Northern Blvd. Dirt on fan guards, some food left uncovered, some food too warm, refrigerator thermometers broken, hole in screen door, old food and grease on refrigerator shelves, toilet top broken, dirt and old food on kitchen floor, rinse water too cool, mouse droppings in basement.  Yuraku Restaurant, 192-20 Northern Blvd. Flies in kitchen, no kit for testing washing chemicals.  STATEN ISLAND  Cosmopolitan Lounge, 611 Bay St. (Canal St.).</p>
        <p>No valid permit, mouse droppings, inadequate extermination.  Frank's Luncheonette, 7001A Amboy Rd. (Page Ave.). Screen door broken, dust on ceiling fan, wall plaster broken, mold on refrigerator walls and ceiling, rust on refrigerator shelf, stove hood not working, water dripping from sink and dishwasher.  New Dinette, 187 Richmond Ave. (Kalver Pl.).</p>
        <p>Mouse droppings, no guards on kitchen lights, grease on exhaust hood.  REOPENED  MANHATTAN  Blimpie's, 83 Delancey St. (Orchard St.).  Danon on the Park, 432 Columbus Ave. (80th St.)  Little Italy, 208 W. 42d St.  Raoul's Restaurant, 180 Prince St. (Thompson St.).  QUEENS  Oasis Restaurant, 40-48 Main St.  CLOSED  MANHATTAN  Benny's of New York, 35 7th Ave. (12th St.).  QUEENS  Junction Pizza, 33-15 Junction Blvd.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
