<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Legacy of Ruin</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="99809"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARCHEOLOGY AND ANTHROPOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MONUMENTS AND MEMORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOCHSCHILD, ADAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEEDC1E3EF934A35751C1A961948260" item-length="592" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Legacy of Ruin</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Adam Hochschild; Adam Hochschild is the founder of Mother Jones magazine.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOCHSCHILD, ADAM</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: When I was a boy, I sometimes visited a house in upstate New York that was just across a fence from an old, overgrown, hillside cemetery. This graveyard was a beautiful place, shady on hot days, and I used to love playing there. Cemeteries are often intriguing to children, I think. They are sometimes our first brush with the mystery of death, and also with the power of memory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: When I was a boy, I sometimes visited a house in upstate New York that was just across a fence from an old, overgrown, hillside cemetery. This graveyard was a beautiful place, shady on hot days, and I used to love playing there. Cemeteries are often intriguing to children, I think. They are sometimes our first brush with the mystery of death, and also with the power of memory.</p>
        <p>When I was a boy, I sometimes visited a house in upstate New York that was just across a fence from an old, overgrown, hillside cemetery. This graveyard was a beautiful place, shady on hot days, and I used to love playing there. Cemeteries are often intriguing to children, I think. They are sometimes our first brush with the mystery of death, and also with the power of memory. In the dates on tombstones is contained the message that we all must die and the reassurance that a mark will be left, our names will be preserved. Some day other children may play on top of our bones and know whose they were.</p>
        <p>As I grew a little older, the dates on the gravestones had more meaning. I liked counting how long people had lived, figuring out how old they had been at the time of historical events I had read about, spotting the occasional birth date before 1800 and imagining the Civil War regiments that were named on veterans' tombstones. It was in this cemetery that I first grasped how hard life had been in ''the old days.'' So many graves were those of children. Often these bore the engraved phrases 19th century parents used to ease the pain of a small child's death: ''God has called this little lamb home.''</p>
        <p>On my vacation last summer, I wandered through that tiny cemetery for the first time in many years. I was shocked. Acid rain had streaked and eroded the lettering on the gravestones. Some you could barely still read, one or two not at all. In a few decades more, many graves will be marked only by featureless, corroded slabs of stone. Those buried below will be anonymous.</p>
        <p>There was another place I visited on the same vacation trip: an Atlantic beach on the coast of Morocco. Unlike a cemetery, a beach should be ever-changing, with the sand always sculpted into new shapes. But on this one too much was permanent. All manufactured things and almost all plastic: bottles, combs, broken toys, bits of fish net and the webs that hold six packs of beverage cans together.</p>
        <p>Some of this was left by vacationers, some washed ashore from ships at sea. Scientists tell us that most of this stuff will last for hundreds of years. It is not biodegradable. Besides fouling beaches all over the world, these products are taking a heavy toll of marine life - fish, lobsters and crabs that ingest the small things or get tangled up in the particularly lethal can webbing.</p>
        <p>The same beach was flecked everywhere with tiny tar balls. These sticky black lumps were the product of oil tankers illegally cleaning out empty tanks at sea. According to Moroccan friends, tankers are much more likely to do this when offshore from a country with a long coastline that is too poor to have a navy or coast guard to police the shipping lanes. Not wanting to get their feet covered with tar, most people walking on this beach wore plastic sandals. When worn out, lost or discarded, many of these, too, will become part of the beach's permanent plastic flora.</p>
        <p>What verdict do the images of that graveyard and that beach give on our society? What we are doing to our worldwide environment is not only altering the air we breathe and the food we eat; it is irrevocably altering or removing what we leave for people to remember us by centuries from now. From ruins like the Parthenon and the Colosseum we know a lot about the Greeks and the Romans. To figure us out, will future archeologists have to make do with plastic webbing and plastic sandals? For we've created a culture - the first in history - where the refuse lasts and the monuments dissolve.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
