<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hodel Blunders as He Squanders</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="39647"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RENTING AND LEASING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OFFSHORE EXPLORATION AND INSTALLATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARCTIC NATIONAL WILDLIFE REFUGE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALASKA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ATLANTIC OCEAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PACIFIC OCEAN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERIOR, DEPARTMENT OF THE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">OAKES, JOHN B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HODEL, DONALD P (SEC)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska/Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reserves (Natural Resources)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7D81131F931A25756C0A961948260" item-length="1437" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hodel Blunders as He Squanders</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John B. Oakes; John B. Oakes is former Editor of the Editorial Page of The New York Times.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">OAKES, JOHN B</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: If James G. Watt were still Secretary of the Interior, he couldn't have done much worse than Secretary Donald P. Hodel has done in recent weeks. Except for differences in decibel level, the two have faithfully followed the identical policy of squandering the nation's natural resources for presumed short-term gains.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: If James G. Watt were still Secretary of the Interior, he couldn't have done much worse than Secretary Donald P. Hodel has done in recent weeks. Except for differences in decibel level, the two have faithfully followed the identical policy of squandering the nation's natural resources for presumed short-term gains.</p>
        <p>If James G. Watt were still Secretary of the Interior, he couldn't have done much worse than Secretary Donald P. Hodel has done in recent weeks. Except for differences in decibel level, the two have faithfully followed the identical policy of squandering the nation's natural resources for presumed short-term gains.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hodel's two most recent violations of his trust are separate but related. The first was to throw open to oil extraction the entire coastal plain of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge in northeastern Alaska, the only place in North America where the complete range of Arctic ecosystems is still preserved intact.</p>
        <p>The second, a week later, was Mr. Hodel's decision to open for oil and gas leasing millions of acres of the most environmentally sensitive offshore areas along the Atlantic, Pacific and Alaska coasts.</p>
        <p>The Reagan-Watt-Hodel leasing program is not a sensible or orderly method of stretching out America's dwindling supply of this finite energy resource. It is, rather, a self-destroying crash program, as though the nation's life depended on draining America dry of all its oil reserves as quickly as possible.</p>
        <p>There are other and better ways of tackling the energy problem, but the Administration shows little interest in them. All of its emphasis is on extraction. None is on the far less costly and far more productive avenues of greater energy efficiency (especially in transportation, housing and manufacturing) and of alternative energy sources (especially solar). The discovery of new oil can hold off for only a few years at most the total depletion within the next several decades of domestic oil resources at present rates of consumption. The facts about the Arctic Refuge are straightforward, but what Mr. Hodel says about them is not. The key area that he would now open to oil exploitation is its huge coastal plain, comprising the only 100 miles of Alaska's 1,100-mile North Coast still fully protected from oil development. It is indispensable terrain for North America's largest herd of caribou, whose annual trek from the Canadian side of the border is one of the world's unique wildlife migrations. A request from the Canadian Government for continued protection of the herd was ignored.</p>
        <p>The Arctic coastal plain is also home to an immense variety of other animal and bird life of the tundra whose habitat - and therefore whose existence - would be irretrievably damaged by any kind of industrial incursion into a wilderness as fragile as this. Violation of this land of majestic silence would be an act of spiritual degradation. It should be contemplated only as a last resort.</p>
        <p>By the Government's own admission, the chances of finding any oil at all beneath the refuge in commercially exploitable volume are less than one in five. The department's mean estimate of the amount of oil available (on the 19 percent chance that any is available) would only be enough to meet America's energy needs for less than 200 days.</p>
        <p>Assistant Secretary William P. Horn speaks glibly of an oilfield potentially the size of neighboring Prudhoe Bay. The respected analyst Amory Lovins of the Rocky Mountain Institute points out that the overall possibility of such a strike is no more than 1 percent.</p>
        <p>To replicate the Prudhoe Bay complex is Mr. Hodel's goal. Prudhoe Bay is producing half as much air pollution as New York City. Water pollution from its oil spillage and toxic chemical waste is spreading out through the flat wetlands of the tundra. Even in the unlikely event that another Prudhoe Bay would in fact be discovered, it would, while it lasted, reduce America's dependence on foreign oil only from 40 to 30 percent.</p>
        <p>To enlist native Alaskan support for prospective oil development in the refuge, the Interior Department has been attempting to trade subsurface mineral rights in the area for lands held by native corporations in other parts of Alaska. The cynical idea is to induce the native Alaskan groups to add their pressure to the Government's own strenuous campaign to open the area to oil development, regardless of the effects on native culture and way of life. Not for the first time, the Government is engaged in the dirty business of corrupting native societies for a shabby purpose.</p>
        <p>Only Congress can save the situation now. A bill introduced by Morris K. Udall, the House Interior Committee's chairman, will do the job by turning the refuge into an officially designated wilderness area where there can be no mineral or any other kind of exploitation. In 1980, Mr. Udall, a father of the Alaska Lands Act, was forced to compromise on protection of the refuge to secure passage of the basic law. This time around, there can be no compromise. Secretary Hodel again showed his contempt for environmental values when he set a five-year schedule for offshore oil and gas leasing that would threaten some of the most crucially important fishery, wildlife and scenic areas on either coast.</p>
        <p>Advertised by the Interior Department as a compromise with environmentalists, this is no compromise at all. If it were, the outcome would have been different in the Bering Sea, for example. One of the world's richest fishing grounds, the sea is also one of the heaviest concentration areas for Alaska's exotic marine mammals and birds. It is up for grabs under the oil and gas leasing program.</p>
        <p>In what could have been a historic step in resolving conflicts between environmentalists and developers, representatives of conservation organizations, fishermen, native Alaskan groups and major oil companies - meeting under aegis of Robert Redford's Institute for Resource Management - negotiated a compromise agreement on Bering Sea areas to be excluded from oil and gas development.</p>
        <p>But it was not to be. Mr. Hodel has rejected the recommendations. He has included in the lease program some 32 million acres of the most environmentally sensitive areas off the Alaskan coast that the interested parties had agreed to exclude. So much for compromise.</p>
        <p>While recognizing a near-shore buffer zone along most of the Atlantic coast, the Hodel plan leaves unprotected the famed Georges Bank, a rich fishing ground off New England that one oil spill could annihilate. Most of the offshore deep water areas off the northern California and Northwest Pacific coasts that Mr. Hodel deferred from the leasing program are tracts in which the oil industry is not now particularly interested.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hodel triumphantly called his five-year leasing program ''the foundation of America's energy future.'' If America is to have an ''energy future,'' it will have to be based on a whole lot firmer foundation than this. The search for new sources of domestic oil at any cost is at best a temporary expedient, not a policy. A realistic energy policy would concentrate instead on development of alternative energy sources and on a serious program of promoting energy efficiency and fuel conservation.</p>
        <p>The Administration has consistently downgraded both these paths to energy independence. It has cut severely the already meager appropriations for research and development of alternative energy, especially solar. Late last year, President Reagan actually vetoed a bill (that has since become law) setting Federal energy efficiency standards for home appliances that have the endorsement of the industry itself.</p>
        <p>This new bill alone will save, before the end of the century, the energy equivalent of at least one billion barrels of oil, which could easily surpass the entire output of the projected Arctic Refuge development. A program to efficiently insulate America's housing stock would save within a few years much more than even the most optimistic production prospects of the refuge. Substitution of fuel-efficient cars for the current supply of ''gas guzzlers'' would do the same.</p>
        <p>But where is the national policy to achieve such goals? Everything the Administration does on this issue -from relaxing gas consumption standards and raising speed limits to belittling the search for renewable energy alternatives - moves in the opposite direction.</p>
        <p>The point is not that there should be no leasing or development of prospective oil-bearing lands, but that there is no reason to plunge into the relatively few areas where exploitation would do permanent and irreparable environmental harm with dubious and temporary economic results. There is a compelling national interest, however, in constructing a high-priority Federal program to develop both energy efficiency and alternative methods of energy production. That would be the creative pathway to an ''energy future'' for America.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
