<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY: MONDAY, MARCH 23, 1987</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="24025"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3DE173DF930A15750C0A961948260" item-length="997" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY: MONDAY, MARCH 23, 1987</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International A3-11</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International A3-11</p>
        <p>International A3-11</p>
        <p>Manila peace efforts have failed and the time has come for military victory over Communist insurgents and right-wing terrorists, President Corazon C. Aquino said at a graduation ceremony. Page A1</p>
        <p>Burma remains an exhausted nation 25 years after a coup that brought Ne Win to power and the anniversary was not celebrated with large festivities. A1</p>
        <p>U.S.-Japan trade friction may increase, as the Administration appears to be ready to impose sanctions against Japanese semiconductor manufacturers, Government and industry officials said. A1</p>
        <p>China's economic reform program, identified with Deng Xiaoping, would seem to be further eroded with the withdrawal of a plan to limit party involvement in the management of state-owned industries. A8</p>
        <p>A trial of four accused hijackers is expected to begin soon in Pakistan, Government officials said. They are charged in connection with the Pan Am hijacking last year in which 21 people were killed. A9</p>
        <p>Islamic fundamentalists in Lebanon appear to be gaining military strength in the south, leading to power struggles among Shiite Moslems there and increasing attacks on Israel's buffer force. A9</p>
        <p>Aiding farmers is so expensive for so many countries that the U.S. wants to put it at the top of the list of international economic issues to be negotiated this year, Administration officials said. A1</p>
        <p>In Nicaragua, health care and education are more accessible than before the Sandinistas took power. But serv- ices are often inadequate because there is not enough money and qualified professionals have fled. A10</p>
        <p>25 Chilean prisoners were tortured until they signed confessions implicating themselves in arms trafficking and an attempt to kill President Augusto Pinochet, according to documents filed by their lawyers. A3</p>
        <p>Barbuda residents feel neglected at the hands of their much more populous neighbor and partner in the two-island nation of Antigua-Barbuda. The main issue in an election Monday is eventual independence. A4</p>
        <p>Canada's demands to cut acid rain will not be met by the increased funds for research announced by the Reagan Administration last week, many Canadians outside the Government are saying. A10</p>
        <p>A Soviet arms expert accused the U.S. of opposing the removal of all Soviet and American medium-range missiles from Europe and said he had doubts that an accord on the issue could be signed. A11</p>
        <p>Leningrad is trailing Moscow in the Soviet cultural thaw as party officials move cautiously, waiting to be certain the signals from the Soviet leadership on the new openness are unmistakable. A11</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A12-16, B6</p>
        <p>Fewer people do drive appar-ently because of the widening public and legislative support for ever-tougher laws against drunken driving and tighter enforcement of existing regulations. A1</p>
        <p>Local laws are getting results</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Georgia's death-sentencing process is being challenged in the Supreme Court on the grounds that it discriminates against blacks. If the appeal is denied, the era of broad-based challenges to the death penalty may end.  A12</p>
        <p>Allergies are a political issue in the Southwest. Once considered a haven for the allergy-afflicted, southwestern desert cities now exceed many eastern and northern cities in pollen counts. A12</p>
        <p>Jesse Jackson may tone down his political style. He said he is aware of his ''image'' problem and is determined to keep himself from becom-ing an issue in his second Presidential bid. B6</p>
        <p>Marvin Kalb will be the first director of the Joan Shorenstein Barone Center on the Press, Politics and Public Policy at the John F. Kennedy School of Government at Harvard University. A13</p>
        <p>A 5,600-seat bingo hall opened Saturday at Big Cypress Seminole Indian Reservation in Florida. More than $1 million in cash and prizes were given away to those who came from as far away as Peru. A13</p>
        <p>Falwell hints short PTL term</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Roberts begins fast for funds</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Investigation of pilot dropped</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>Washington Talk</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Lehman's sea-war strategy is alive, but for how long?  Governmental Dept. of Trinkets  Regional B1-7</p>
        <p>Seven people died in a fire in a 35-story Harlem building. Three people jumped to their deaths from their 33d-story apartment. Fire officials said sprinklers apparently failed to function. A1</p>
        <p>Four officers save many lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>An effort to get mothers off welfare and into private jobs is still in its infancy, 17 months after New York state officials began the mandatory program. The results have been mixed at best. A1</p>
        <p>24 police officers will not be expelled from New York City's police labor union, Mayor Koch and union leaders said, citing the ''divisive impact'' the dispute was having on police morale.  B3</p>
        <p>Questions about deadly self-defense and the laws governing them remain more than two years after Bernhard H. Goetz pulled a pistol and shot four men on a downtown subway train.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Bergenfield is trying to find out why four teen-agers committed suicide, but residents say they will never really know why the four young people decided they could no longer bear to live. B1</p>
        <p>The dynamics of power in Albany have been significantly altered by Mel Miller in his first 10 weeks as Speaker of the State Assembly. He has made it clear that he is unwilling to defer to the Governor. B1</p>
        <p>News analysis: The New York City corruption scandals may be rooted in the fiscal crisis of the 1970's. The city's brush with bankruptcy reshaped its politics. B4</p>
        <p>Westchester Democrats form a group</p>
        <p>B3</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
