<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>30 Nations Meet on Rules to Protect Ozone Layer</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="16752"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATMOSPHERE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VIENNA (AUSTRIA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KAMM, HENRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Austria/Vienna</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDB133EF935A15751C0A961948260" item-length="659" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>30 Nations Meet on Rules to Protect Ozone Layer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY KAMM, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KAMM, HENRY</byline>
      <dateline>VIENNA, Feb. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Technical and legal experts from 30 countries are meeting at the United Nations center here to negotiate a set of rules to protect the atmosphere's vital ozone layer from industrial chemicals suspected of depleting it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Technical and legal experts from 30 countries are meeting at the United Nations center here to negotiate a set of rules to protect the atmosphere's vital ozone layer from industrial chemicals suspected of depleting it.</p>
        <p>Technical and legal experts from 30 countries are meeting at the United Nations center here to negotiate a set of rules to protect the atmosphere's vital ozone layer from industrial chemicals suspected of depleting it.</p>
        <p>Members of the American delegation, the prime mover for a far-reaching agreement, expressed a belief today that progress was being made in bridging the gap that has divided the industrial world into two camps.</p>
        <p>Going into the five-day meeting, which began Monday, nations largely sharing the American view - Canada, Sweden, Norway and Finland - favored a freeze on current production and use of a range of chlorofluorocarbons, known as CFC's, and halons and a gradual reduction of their use leading to a nearly total ban.</p>
        <p>The 12-nation European Community and Japan, however, favored a freeze only on production of some of the compounds and no phase-out until research provides further proof that these gases are diminishing the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>The atmospheric ozone band shields all forms of life on earth from harmful ultraviolet radiation. Depletion would lead to significant increases in skin cancer and possible rises in other illnesses, as well as reduced crop and fisheries yields, according to American studies.</p>
        <p>The compounds suspected of destroying atmospheric ozone are used in aerosol sprays, refrigerants, solvents, rigid-foam products and fire extinguishers. Because of the wide range of uses, restrictions placed on the compounds would affect industries whose production is worth billions of dollars.</p>
        <p>Indications that the West European attitude is becoming more open to considering a phase-out is producing some optimism in the camp of those favoring stringent restrictions. Bill L. Long, alternate head of the American delegation, by far the largest one here, attached particular significance to an addition to the position paper presented by the European Community. A Last-Minute Supplement</p>
        <p>In what was clearly a last-minute supplement to a six-point paper, a seventh paragraph for the first time raised a possibility that the 12-nation group was moving toward a long-term ban. After saying scientific knowledge so far did not justify ''total phasing out of CFC's,'' the paper continued:</p>
        <p>''Nevertheless, given the length of time needed for the first full review to be carried out and assessed, and before any subsequent reductions can be agreed and implemented, some reductions could be a desirable precautionary measure.'' This appeared to American participants as a move toward the American position that policymakers must act even before all scientific data are in if waiting might raise the problem to a magnitude beyond solution. Opponents of the compounds say the stability of the compounds is so great that once in the atmosphere they will continue to destroy ozone for as long as a century.</p>
        <p>The American view was expressed in an opening statement on Monday by the delegation leader, Richard E. Benedick. He warned against waiting too long and said: ''If we are to err in designing measures to protect the ozone layer, then let us, conscious of our responsibility to future generations, err on the side of caution.''</p>
        <p>Among those awaiting the results of the talks are members of the Senate and House of Representatives, who have introduced resolutions timed to influence the meeting with the threat of an American ban on the compounds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Benedick noted that several major producing countries had not signed or ratified a two-year-old convention to protect the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>In fact, a United Nations statement showed that none of the members of the European Community had made formal their ratification and that Spain, Portugal and Ireland had not even signed it and were not attending the meeting. Japan also has not signed but is attending.</p>
        <p>Participants said the Community attitude misrepresented the positions of some of its important members, because the 12 nations are bound to unanimity.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
