<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Answers To Quiz</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="36061"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2DE163AF931A35756C0A961948260" item-length="431" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Answers To Quiz</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: 1. The X-ray is of an Egyption bronze cat, one of the most popular sculptures at the museum, previously believed to date from around 300 B.C. It shows a porous form of bronze, virtually unknown for that period, and museum officials say the cat is probably a fake.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: 1. The X-ray is of an Egyption bronze cat, one of the most popular sculptures at the museum, previously believed to date from around 300 B.C. It shows a porous form of bronze, virtually unknown for that period, and museum officials say the cat is probably a fake.</p>
        <p>1. The X-ray is of an Egyption bronze cat, one of the most popular sculptures at the museum, previously believed to date from around 300 B.C. It shows a porous form of bronze, virtually unknown for that period, and museum officials say the cat is probably a fake.</p>
        <p>2. President Kurt Waldheim of Austria was commentng on a Justice Department decision to put him on a list of people barred from entering the United States because of his participation in the persecution of Jews as a lieutenant in the German Army in World War II.</p>
        <p>3. Carl R. Channell, a professional fund-raiser, pleaded guilty in Federal court to charges of conspiring to defraud the Government by raising tax-exempt funds to arm Nicaraguan rebels.</p>
        <p>4. It restores the Police Department to the staff levels it had before the fiscal crisis 12 years ago.</p>
        <p>5. Merrill Lynch &amp; Company said it was because bonds that it owned plummeted in value when interest rates surged.</p>
        <p>6. Bill Russell will coach the Sacramento Kings.</p>
        <p>7. Mr. Nakasone told President Reagan that the Bank of Japan would guide interest rates lower and Mr. Volcker testified on Capitol Hill that the Federal Reserve, the American central bank, had raised interest rates in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>8. The rules require that clean drinking water and sanitation facilities be provided on large farms to protect the health and safety of workers exposed to parasites and pesticides in the fields.</p>
        <p>9. In an unusual challenge to the Government, the newspaper ignored a court-ordered ban on reporting details of Mr. Wright's assertions that British intelligence agents plotted against Prime Minister Harold Wilson.</p>
        <p>10. It is an ambitious attempt to break up a large concentration of poor blacks and integrate them throughout the city.</p>
        <p>11. In a year when quarterbacks were not expected to arouse much interest, four, including Testaverde, were drafted in the first round.</p>
        <p>12. Watt proposed that the entire 1.4 billion-acre outer continental shelf be made available to the oil industry. This plan includes much of disputed waters but would defer lease sales for oil development on about 650 million acres.</p>
        <p>13. The long slide in farmland values appears to be ending as major agricultural lenders are beginning to sell much of the land they have taken over from troubled farmers.</p>
        <p>14. The United States-backed rebels who attacked a Government work crew.</p>
        <p>15. Nuclear war and acid rain.</p>
        <p>16. A 31-nation conference reached an agreement in principle to freeze and ultimately reduce production and consumption of chemicals thought to deplete the ozone.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
