<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seeking Methane In Bales of Trash</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="47926"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHANE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARBAGE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUTIS, PHILIP S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0D91F39F933A25755C0A961948260" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seeking Methane In Bales of Trash</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP S. GUTIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GUTIS, PHILIP S</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: LOWELL HARRELSON could be forgiven if he wanted to have nothing more to do with trash. For weeks he has been searching for a home for the 3,100 tons of garbage he owns, all in neat little bales aboard the garbage barge Mobro at anchor off the shore of Brooklyn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: LOWELL HARRELSON could be forgiven if he wanted to have nothing more to do with trash. For weeks he has been searching for a home for the 3,100 tons of garbage he owns, all in neat little bales aboard the garbage barge Mobro at anchor off the shore of Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>LOWELL HARRELSON could be forgiven if he wanted to have nothing more to do with trash. For weeks he has been searching for a home for the 3,100 tons of garbage he owns, all in neat little bales aboard the garbage barge Mobro at anchor off the shore of Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Harrelson remains undaunted about his original plan to use garbage - barge load after barge load of residential and business trash from the New York area - to produce methane gas for commercial energy uses.</p>
        <p>''I still believe,'' he said yesterday in a telephone interview, ''that someone, somewhere out in this whole, wild world, is going to say, 'O.K., Lowell, take a small plot of land and try out your idea.' ''</p>
        <p>His idea is that tightly compressed bales of garbage would be more efficient in producing methane gas than loosely packed trash in landfills. Experts in waste management are not so certain.</p>
        <p>The extraction of gas from conventional landfills is a proven, commercially feasible technology. Hundreds of companies nationwide capture methane - a byproduct of the decomposition of natural materials, such as foods and papers - and sell it.</p>
        <p>In New York, Brooklyn Union Gas, using methane produced at the Fresh Kills landfill on Staten Island, provides heating and cooking gas to 10,000 families.</p>
        <p>''Twenty-five new companies have sprung up in the last five years for the sole purpose of capturing the gas rights from old landfills,'' said Dr. Roger Carrier, vice president for engineering at the Chambers Development Company in Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>''These projects are so profitable, they do not need any new big bonding issues, and there are no noisy environmental hearings to survive,'' Dr. Carrier added. He describes his company as ''waste specialists'' involved in designing and running landfills.</p>
        <p>The process by which methane is produced is well known. Billions of microorganisms in effect eat decomposing trash and excrete a combination of carbon dioxide and methane.</p>
        <p>The question is whether a landfill packed with baled garbage will be a more efficient producer of methane than a landfill of trash from garbage trucks and flattened with bulldozers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harrelson, a building contractor who says he has studied methane gas production methods for more than 10 years, is convinced that baled garbage will be more effective.</p>
        <p>The trash is baled in hydraulic systems under pressure of several thousand pounds per square inch, powerful enough to mash a Mercury station wagon to the size of a coffee table.</p>
        <p>''When I saw the bales, I suddenly realized that there is the answer to all the questions in methane production,'' Mr. Harrelson said. ''I can get the high density in my landfill, and the bales can be easily transported.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Harrelson believes landfills are too loosely packed. It now takes too long to fill and cap a landfill, he said, and much of the methane is lost.</p>
        <p>Experts in waste management and disposal, however, are less certain.</p>
        <p>''There are reasons why baled garbage would be more efficient, and a very fundamental reason why it is not,'' said Dr. Raymond W. Regan, an associate professor of civil engineering at Pennsylvania State University.</p>
        <p>''The most fundamental problem,'' he said, ''is that by packing material together very tightly - about twice as compact as in a normal landfill -there would less air voids, and the bacteria that produce methane cannot operate unless they have oxygen.''</p>
        <p>Joan P. Siegal, supervisor of landfill services for GSF Energy Inc., which operates the methane production facility at the Fresh Kills landfill, said her company ''typically does not look for a landfill with a lot of bailed, dry refuse.''</p>
        <p>''It tends to have a much slower decay,'' she said, ''and would therefore take much longer to recover the methane.''</p>
        <p>E. Louis Wilkinson, regional manager for GSF Energy in New York, said that although the basics of methane production are fairly well understood, ''the variables and how well they interact are not as well understood.'' One of those variables is what happens when you bail garbage.</p>
        <p>''This is a relatively untested area,'' Mr. Wilkinson said, ''and everything is in the realm of possibilities. But right now we don't think bailed garbage provides for the ideal condition.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Carrier of Chambers Development said that landfills of bailed refuse could present a number of problems in producing methane.</p>
        <p>The first, he said, would be that water - which is critical to decomposition - might have trouble penetrating a tightly condensed bail. A related problem, he suggested, could be that the bales would be so strongly packed that they ''bridge,'' he said, meaning that there would be open spaces or voids between the bales.</p>
        <p>''With 2,000-pound bales,'' Dr. Carrier said, ''chances are that the water is going to run right through those passageways and never touch the center of the bale.''</p>
        <p>His suggestion: ''Run a tractor over them and crunch it in real good.''  BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
