<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crowding the Seashore on Every Coast</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="64400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="IDEAS &amp; TRENDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEACHES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUTIS, PHILIP S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0D91E3AF93AA3575BC0A961948260" item-length="602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crowding the Seashore on Every Coast</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Philip S. Gutis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GUTIS, PHILIP S</byline>
      <dateline>COLD SPRING HARBOR, L.I.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ON shrinking beaches, the crowds are thicker than they used to be. More than half of America's population lives within 50 miles of the ocean or Great Lakes, and that proportion is rising quickly. And despite erosion, pollution and proliferating condos, each year more people go to the beach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ON shrinking beaches, the crowds are thicker than they used to be. More than half of America's population lives within 50 miles of the ocean or Great Lakes, and that proportion is rising quickly. And despite erosion, pollution and proliferating condos, each year more people go to the beach.</p>
        <p>ON shrinking beaches, the crowds are thicker than they used to be. More than half of America's population lives within 50 miles of the ocean or Great Lakes, and that proportion is rising quickly. And despite erosion, pollution and proliferating condos, each year more people go to the beach.</p>
        <p>That can be difficult, however. In most coastal states the public owns the beach from the water's edge to the high-tide mark, but getting there, or staking out a piece of dry sand, is another matter. To those on the inside looking out, whoever owns the beachfront owns the ocean. Property owners and municipalities, unsettled by the summer crowds, generally budge only when they have to. And, increasingly, to provide facilities for outsiders, locally run beaches charge admission fees.</p>
        <p>As basic principles of private property and public trust clash, most states are favoring the public. Florida has acquired 22 miles of sandy beachfront since 1982, and has set aside $5.5 million to acquire paths to the water through private property. In New Jersey, municipal beaches can no longer turn away nonresidents. California's Coastal Commission, although it was brushed back recently by the Supreme Court, has opened rights of way to many beaches near private homes.</p>
        <p>All efforts are frustrated by the erosion of almost every mile of coastline, from the narrowing barrier islands of the Atlantic to Louisiana, which is losing 100 acres a day, to California, where miles of bluff have crumbled into the ocean. The process, a consequence of rising sea levels, is hastened by overdevelopment.</p>
        <p>But the tide of people is rising, too. Five state beaches in Massachusetts had 970,000 visitors in 1976, 2.7 million in 1986. In that period attendance at Florida state parks, most of them on the beach, rose about 40 percent and would have been higher if the parks did not turn away visitors. Connecticut state beaches have also been turning people away this year.</p>
        <p>Making more room for the crowds makes economic and political sense for most states. The following reports describe what several of them are doing.  LONG ISLAND: PERMITS ONLY</p>
        <p>Long Island, as its name would suggest, has no shortage of beaches.</p>
        <p>But it also has no shortage of rules regulating their use. For the most part, officials said, they are restricted to residents of the village, town or county that owns the beach.</p>
        <p>''The beaches on Long Island are accessible - if you are a resident,'' said Nancy K. Nugent, a coastal resource specialist in the New York Department of State's Division of Coastal Resources and Waterfront Revitalization. Federal and state beaches, including the Fire Island National Seashore and seven state parks, are open to all with small parking fees. But for the most part village and town beaches are not.</p>
        <p>If a municipality accepts Federal or state money for beach facilities, Ms. Nugent said, it must admit nonresidents. But it can charge them ''reasonable'' fees, she said, which can range up to $15 a car.</p>
        <p>Some communities in Connecticut, where the situation is much the same but the beaches more crowded, charge outsiders even more. Westport, for example, charges nonresidents $20 a car on weekends.</p>
        <p>In New York, the restrictions ''just haven't been questioned that much, as far as I know,'' Ms. Nugent said.</p>
        <p>Long Island accounts for most of New York's oceanfront, but Ms. Nugent said very few other beach communities in the state have residency requirements. New York City's beaches are free and open to all. And everywhere, people can walk along the wet-sand portion of the beach - if they can get to it.</p>
        <p>IDEAS &amp; TRENDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
