<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY: THURSDAY, APRIL 23, 1987</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="33172"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEEDA1531F930A15757C0A961948260" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY: THURSDAY, APRIL 23, 1987</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-15  Six black rail workers were killed and four police officers were seriously wounded in two clashes in South Africa, and 16,000 workers were dismissed for ignoring a deadline to end a strike. A1  Sri Lanka attacked bases of two Tamil guerrilla separatist groups in the north, killing 80 people, in reprisal for two terrorist bombings that killed at least 237 people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-15  Six black rail workers were killed and four police officers were seriously wounded in two clashes in South Africa, and 16,000 workers were dismissed for ignoring a deadline to end a strike. A1  Sri Lanka attacked bases of two Tamil guerrilla separatist groups in the north, killing 80 people, in reprisal for two terrorist bombings that killed at least 237 people.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-15  Six black rail workers were killed and four police officers were seriously wounded in two clashes in South Africa, and 16,000 workers were dismissed for ignoring a deadline to end a strike. A1  Sri Lanka attacked bases of two Tamil guerrilla separatist groups in the north, killing 80 people, in reprisal for two terrorist bombings that killed at least 237 people. A14  An ex-CIA official is a principal in the criminal investigation of the Iran-contra affair, the special prosecutor said. The former official, Thomas Clines, worked with Lieut. Col. Oliver L. North. A10  Iran has sentenced a U.S. engineer, Jon Pattis, to 10 years in prison, saying he had spied for the Central Intelligence Agency, Teheran officials announced. A11  Moscow's latest offer on short-range arms was criticized by a senior Washington official, Kenneth L. Adelman. He said the Kremlin had retreated from positions outlined in Moscow to Secretary of State George P. Shultz. A6  Washington can neutralize any electronic listening devices that might have been placed in the new United States Embassy in Moscow, according to Robert Lamb, the State Department's top security official. A7  Canadians deplore acid rain, which originates from smokestacks in the Ohio Valley and moves northeast to Ontario, where it kills fish and pushes entire lakes toward biological death. A4  Zoning plan threatens Savile Row A1  Argentina considers appeasing army A3  Peru's chief under fire as rebels gain A3  Palestinians harden policy A5  Eastern-bloc call for candor A8  Soviet press widens coverage A8  Warsaw accuses U.S. aide of spying A9  NATIONAL A16-24, B10-15  &gt;Death penalties are constitutional even when statistics indicate race is a major factor in the decisions to impose them, the Supreme Court ruled in upholding Georgia's capital punishment law, 5 to 4. A1  Pessimism over Star Wars has reportedly been expressed by key physicists. They said so many breakthroughs are required that it will take a decade or more to determine whether the program can be carried out. A1  The bond market is suffering its worst beating in nearly three years as thousands of investors are selling their holdings out of fear that the plummeting dollar will revive inflation. A1  107,000 schools would be inspected for asbestos, and administrators would be required to remove the carcinogen under new rules proposed by the Environmental Protection Agency. A1  A jury convicted Joe Hunt of murder in the death of Ronald Levin of Beverly Hills, Calif. The panel deliberated only two days in the five-month trial of Mr. Hunt, the leader of a group called the Billionaire Boys Club. A16  The N.B.A. is expanding by four franchises. The owners of the 23 existing teams unexpectedly voted unanimously to award franchises to two Florida cities, Miami and Orlando, as well as to Charlotte, N.C., and Minneapolis. A1  Welfare payments could be halted to a family that received a lump-sum personal injury award, the Supreme Court ruled. The 5-4 decision involves a major Federal-state welfare program, Aid to Families with Dependant Children. B11  The elderly fared far better than all other American population groups in their income gains in the first half of the 1980's, according to an analysis of Census Bureau statistics. C1  Report station dispute settled A6  Drug use declines in military A16  Families fear nuclear-waste test A16  F.A.A. to study controller errors A18  List of AIDS test-takers is lost A21  Researchers test Herpes vaccine A24  Panel denies waiver on Seabrook reactor A24  WASHINGTON TALK B10  The politics of arms control  Police memorial unveiled  REGIONAL B1-9  Residents are increasingly opposing New York City's attempts to open any centers residents fear would harm the character of their neighborhoods. Some officials call it a ''not in my backyard'' phenomenon. A1  Racial harassment occurred in a March 21 clash between several black and white students at Columbia College, according to administrators. They said they were disciplining an unnamed white student for verbal abuse. B2  A jail official upheld negotiations over force in defending correction officers' treatment of rebellious Rikers Island inmates last October. The official, Robert Kasanof, challenged a state report. B5  Governor Cuomo is endangering the independence of the New York State Public Service Commission by becoming directly involved in utility rate-making, the outgoing chairman of the panel charged. B1  Despite repeated flooding, residents of the Passaic and Pompton river plains are resisting government buyout offers. In a soaring real-estate market, sellers say they must leave the area for affordable housing. B1  The lynx will be reintroduced to New York by wildlife scientists about a century after it disappeared from the state. The scientists hope to establish a colony of about 70 of the shy, reclusive cats. B2  Inquiry clouding Goldin's future B1  Harlem River Houses still special B1  Special memories of the Dodgers B3  Two may shun ethics inquiry B3</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
