<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MUSIC: THE GEWANDHAUS ORCHESTRA</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="66" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="34095"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONCERTS AND RECITALS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GEWANDHAUS ORCHESTRA OF LEIPZIG</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLLAND, BERNARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DA113CF935A15757C0A961948260" item-length="568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MUSIC: THE GEWANDHAUS ORCHESTRA</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLLAND, BERNARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A NATIONAL style, curiously enough, often reveals itself through the work of outsiders. Thus anyone wanting to encapsulate the spirit of Leipzig's Gewandhaus Orchestra at Carnegie Hall Thursday night had only to hear them play American music.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A NATIONAL style, curiously enough, often reveals itself through the work of outsiders. Thus anyone wanting to encapsulate the spirit of Leipzig's Gewandhaus Orchestra at Carnegie Hall Thursday night had only to hear them play American music.</p>
        <p>A NATIONAL style, curiously enough, often reveals itself through the work of outsiders. Thus anyone wanting to encapsulate the spirit of Leipzig's Gewandhaus Orchestra at Carnegie Hall Thursday night had only to hear them play American music.</p>
        <p>The piece was Samuel Barber's ''Adagio for Strings,'' which these East German musicians under their conductor, Kurt Masur, managed to reconstitute in a Central European image. This was, in other words, a performance of dark seriousness, with heavy pressure on the bow and relentless aspirations toward profundity.</p>
        <p>Successful as the performance was on its own terms, Barber's music seemed nonetheless a little alien standing on its native ground at Carnegie Hall. Stripped away was, first of all, this music's entrancing ambiguity - the elements of tragedy rubbing against an almost childlike yearning. The ''Adagio for Strings'' incorporates that feeling of nostalgia, the reaching for a memory just beyond one's grasp, that makes the best of Charles Ives so moving. It is also a piece relying on a certain beauty of tone - a luxurious tint that both enhances and contradicts Barber's heart-on-sleeve sentiments.</p>
        <p>It was the kind of sound the Gewandhaus simply does not possess. Mr. Masur's orchestra has become a regular visitor in recent years and has been received with serious attention and friendly curiosity - especially for the distinctive primary colors of its wind sections. It is a style one hears seldom in the West these days.</p>
        <p>While familiarity with the Gewandhaus has certainly not bred contempt, it does call up reservations - about the harsh, slightly raw string tone and the not-always-reliable, not-always-articulate brass playing. By these standards, the Gewandhaus has trouble standing on an international level of quality that most American orchestras attain with ease. What makes these East Germans interesting, and perhaps valuable to listeners here, however, is their sober earnestness. Overwork induces periodic spasms of off-handedness among Western musicians, and the collective seriousness of the Gewandhaus, despite its limitations, is an admonishment to us all.</p>
        <p>Juxtaposing the Barber with Siegfried Matthus's Concerto for Timpani and Orchestra was a nice bit of diplomatic balance. Subtitled ''The Forest,'' the East Prussian's three-movement piece called to mind the storm sequence of Beethoven's ''Pastoral'' Symphony, but one updated into a kind of ecological tract. Gentle, verdant textures give way to ugly eruptions (dare one substitute acid rain for Beethoven's thunderbolts and downpour?) and then return at the end, in the composer's description, as ''a vision ardently desired.''</p>
        <p>The orchestral language is not remarkable, though the crossing meters in the last movement have a nice turbulent effect. Karl Mehlig played the solo part handsomely, and Mr. Matthus's writing for him has a subtle, dampened quality that wisely avoids the timpani's more grandiose properties.</p>
        <p>Also on the program was the Tchaikovsky Fifth Symphony - a piece already weary with overuse and played here with rugged force but not much beauty. One could also question Mr. Masur's very slow interpretation of the Andante markings in the first two movements. In both cases, Tchaikovsky, I think, wished to rescue the intensely Romantic from what is merely lugubrious and sentimental -states to which this performance came dangerously near.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
