<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. UNCERTAIN ON OZONE PACT</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="44711"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5DB1E3EF93AA15756C0A961948260" item-length="474" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. UNCERTAIN ON OZONE PACT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The United States may back away from a tentative international agreement to freeze and ultimately reduce production and consumption of chemicals believed to deplete the earth's protective covering of ozone, Administration officials said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The United States may back away from a tentative international agreement to freeze and ultimately reduce production and consumption of chemicals believed to deplete the earth's protective covering of ozone, Administration officials said today.</p>
        <p>The United States may back away from a tentative international agreement to freeze and ultimately reduce production and consumption of chemicals believed to deplete the earth's protective covering of ozone, Administration officials said today.</p>
        <p>''Our negotiating position is under review,'' said a White House spokesman, Albert R. Brashear.</p>
        <p>An Interior Department official commented that Secretary of the Interior Donald P. Hodel ''does not want the President boxed into an option that as of right now provides no assurance that other nations will go along.'' 'Secretary Is Very Concerned'</p>
        <p>''The Secretary is very concerned from a philosophical point of view that the President be given the opportunity to receive a full range of options on this issue,'' the Interior official added.</p>
        <p>The Washington Post reported in its Friday issue that the Administration is reconsidering its position taken at an international conference of 31 nations April 30 and weighing instead a public relations campaign to encourage the use of sunglasses and skin lotion.</p>
        <p>Administration officials tonight declined to comment on any options that might be taken up by the Cabinet council on domestic policy, which is reviewing the issue.</p>
        <p>''We do not comment on discussions within the domestic policy council,'' said Mr. Hodel's spokesman. Agreement in Geneva</p>
        <p>The April conference, which took place in Geneva, produced a tentative agreement to freeze production of chlorofluorocarbons at 1986 levels starting in 1990 and to cut production of the chemicals by 20 percent two years later. The agreement envisaged an additional 30 percent cut in production, but left the timing open.</p>
        <p>Chlorofluorocarbons are industrial chemicals that interact destructively with the stratospheric ozone layer that protects life from harmful ultraviolet radiation.</p>
        <p>The chemicals are used as solvents, propellants in aerosols, refrigerants, in plastic foams and in fire extinguishers.</p>
        <p>The United States and Canada banned the use of chlorofluorocarbons in aerosols in 1978, but they are still widely used in other applications. State Department View</p>
        <p>The Cabinet review is expected to pit Secretary Hodel against Secretary of State George P. Shultz. The State Department has been described as strongly opposed to altering the American position.</p>
        <p>The chief American negotiator in Geneva was Deputy Assistant Secretary of State Richard E. Benedick who described the April pact at the time as ''really a landmark.''</p>
        <p>In the past the nations of the European Community and Japan have expressed strong reservations about limiting production of the ozone-destroying chemicals.</p>
        <p>But reports that a widening ''hole'' in the ozone layer over Antartica may be caused by chlorofluorocarbons have focused growing international attention on curbing output of the chemicals.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
