<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deaver Found Guilty of Lying 3 Times Under Oath</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="102428"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERJURY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOBBYING AND LOBBYISTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS IN GOVERNMENT ACT (1978)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRANKLIN, BEN A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEAVER, MICHAEL K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (MRS)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JACKSON, THOMAS PENFIELD (JUDGE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILLER, HERBERT J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEYMOUR, WHITNEY NORTH JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DB1239F934A25751C1A961948260" item-length="1228" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deaver Found Guilty of Lying 3 Times Under Oath</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN A. FRANKLIN, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRANKLIN, BEN A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A Federal jury today found Michael K. Deaver, a longtime friend of President and Mrs. Reagan and a former senior member of their staff, guilty on three charges of lying under oath about using his influence with the White House as a highly paid lobbyist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A Federal jury today found Michael K. Deaver, a longtime friend of President and Mrs. Reagan and a former senior member of their staff, guilty on three charges of lying under oath about using his influence with the White House as a highly paid lobbyist.</p>
        <p>A Federal jury today found Michael K. Deaver, a longtime friend of President and Mrs. Reagan and a former senior member of their staff, guilty on three charges of lying under oath about using his influence with the White House as a highly paid lobbyist.</p>
        <p>After 27 hours of secret deliberations that started Friday, the jurors acquitted him of two other counts of perjury.</p>
        <p>Federal District Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson, who presided at the seven-week trial, said he would sentence Mr. Deaver Feb. 25. He allowed Mr. Deaver to remain free. The maximum punishment on the three charges, which is usually not imposed, would be 15 years in prison and fines totaling $22,000. 'In My Heart I Am Innocent'</p>
        <p>As the vedict was announced, Mr. Deaver, standing and facing the jury, turned and smiled gamely at his wife, Carolyn, and their daughter, Amanda, 17 years old, who sobbed on her mother's shoulder.</p>
        <p>Before television cameras outside the courthouse, Mr. Deaver said, ''I am obviously very disappointed, but at the same time I know in my heart that I am innocent.''</p>
        <p>His chief counsel, Herbert J. Miller, said he would appeal the conviction, a process that could take several years. As for the basis for an appeal, Mr. Miller said, ''You'll read it in my motion.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reagan, in a written statement, said he and his wife, Nancy, were sorry to learn of the verdict. Mr. Reagan said: ''He has been a longtime friend and has served with dedication. Beyond that I cannot comment further at this time since the decision will likely be appealed through our court system.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver, the deputy White House chief of staff from 1981 until May 1985, is the first person indicted under the provisions of the Ethics in Government Act of 1978 allowing for the appointment of special prosecutors, formally known as independent counsels. Six special prosecutors have investigated current or former high officials in the Reagan Administration.</p>
        <p>Whitney North Seymour Jr., the special prosecutor in the Deaver case, said in a statement, ''Today's verdict shows the American system of justice at its best.''</p>
        <p>A juror, Janice M. Hale, a supermarket employee, said, ''We just went by the evidence. It was quite clear.''</p>
        <p>The jury foreman, Barrington Bell Jr., said the jurors reached their verdict ''after very intense, and I mean intense, deliberations.''</p>
        <p>The jury found Mr. Deaver guilty of lying to a House subcommittee about his efforts to obtain a meeting with the President for a South Korean trade envoy, of falsely telling a Federal grand jury that he could not remember contacts he made on behalf of Trans World Airlines, and of telling the grand jury he could not remember his repeated efforts to help retain a Federal tax policy favorable to mainland manufactuers with factories in Puerto Rico.</p>
        <p>He was acquitted of falsely denying to a the House subcommittee that he had made contacts on behalf of other paying clients with seven present or former members of the White House staff and of another charge of falsely denying to a grand jury that he had been involved in the selection of an Administration envoy to Canada on the issue of acid rain. Deaver Did Not Testify</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver, 49, never took the witness stand. Indeed, in a calculated gamble, Mr. Miller declined to call any of the nearly 200 witnesses on the defense team's tentative pretrial list.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller, whose firm is Miller Cassidy Larroca &amp; Lewin, acknowledged to reporters today that the defense strategy ''might have been a mistake.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller, who was also a lawyer for former President Richard M. Nixon, asserted to the jury that the prosecution had ''totally failed'' to make its fundamental case.</p>
        <p>Under established criminal law in perjury cases, proof of an ''intent to deceive'' is required for conviction.</p>
        <p>Among its other effects, Mr. Miller's strategy in resting without calling defense witnessess prevented the jury from hearing evidence that Mr. Deaver's alcoholism might have clouded his memory. Alcohol abuse was a major element, well publicized in advance by his lawyers, in the rationale for Mr. Deaver's false statments, some of which were unchallenged by the defense.</p>
        <p>But Judge Jackson ruled last week that without the testimony of defense experts on the ''aberrational'' effects of alcoholism the jury was barred from considering alcoholism as a mitigating factor.</p>
        <p>The indictment accused Mr. Deaver of deliberately giving false sworn statements before a subcommittee of the House of Representatives and a Federal grand jury with the intent of concealing his conduct at Michael K. Deaver &amp; Associates Inc, the consulting concern, or lobbying business, he established after leaving the White House.</p>
        <p>South Korea paid the concern $475,000 a year. T.W.A. and the manufacturers with plants in Puerto Rico, as a group, each paid $250,000 a year.</p>
        <p>The jury was told by prosecutors that the lobbying concern took in $3.2 million in fees in its first year of operation. The trial testimony covered the concern's efforts to influence Government policy on behalf of foreign and corporate clients who paid more than half of the fees in that first year, $1.7 million. Another Case to Be Tried</p>
        <p>Next month, another special prosecutor is to try another former White House staff member, Lyn Nofziger, on charges of violating the lobbying restrictions of the Ethics in Government Act of 1978. The law bars, for two years, former senior Government officials from trying to influence policy decisions in the agency where they worked. Mr. Nofziger has pleaded not guilty.  In one of his most bitterly criticized decisions, the indictment sought by Mr. Seymour did not charge Mr. Deaver directly with lobbying law violations. It charged him instead with lying to the grand jury in an attempt to avoid charges of lobbying infractions.</p>
        <p>Over strenuous defense objections, pretrial rulings by Judge Jackson allowed the prosecution to present testimony about compromising lobbying activities by Mr. Deaver. The evidence was not presented as proof of violations of the lobby law.</p>
        <p>If any of the allegations of lobbying misconduct were true, the defense lawyers argued, the special prosecutor was ''derelict in his duty'' for not charging Mr. Deaver directly with violations of the ethics act. 'This Is the Whole Point'</p>
        <p>But in court last week, responding to Mr. Miller's complaint that Mr. Deaver was unjustly on trial for lawful lobbying activities, Mr. Seymour, finally lost his aplomb.</p>
        <p>''That is the whole point of this indictment,'' the prosecutor shouted. ''Mr. Deaver lied to the grand jury. He blocked the investigation.''</p>
        <p>The evidence admitted at trial of ''possible violations'' of the lobbying law by Mr. Deaver was designed to build an essential element for a perjury conviction - that the defendant had a motive for lying.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour argued that Mr. Deaver's ''intent to deceive'' was driven by his desire to preserve a profitable business from the scandals and to avoid bringing humiliation to the highly placed friends he had ''exploited,'' including President and Mrs. Reagan.</p>
        <p>The Deaver prosecution followed a familiar Washington pattern. In 1986, newspaper reports disclosing some of the clients signed by Mr. Deaver led to a Congressional investigation and then to a demand for the appointment of a special prosecutor. Mr. Deaver publicly joined in the call.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
