<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CONCERN GROWS ON REGION'S WATER</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="779"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHORTAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WELLS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PUTNAM COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MELVIN, TESSA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reserves (Natural Resources)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEED9143BF937A35752C0A961948260" item-length="1489" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CONCERN GROWS ON REGION'S WATER</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TESSA MELVIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MELVIN, TESSA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IN the coming year, attention is expected to be focused on the area's water supply, a natural resource that planners in the New York City region agree is limited and requires management if serious water shortages are to be avoided.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IN the coming year, attention is expected to be focused on the area's water supply, a natural resource that planners in the New York City region agree is limited and requires management if serious water shortages are to be avoided.</p>
        <p>IN the coming year, attention is expected to be focused on the area's water supply, a natural resource that planners in the New York City region agree is limited and requires management if serious water shortages are to be avoided.</p>
        <p>While concerned county residents are calling for regional and state cooperation to seek solutions, local, state and Federal agencies have become concerned about water quality and quantity regionwide and are attempting to formulate a comprehensive water policy.</p>
        <p>With few exceptions, Putnam County residents depend on private wells for fresh water, and some well-drillers, such as Henry M. Boyd of Carmel, have expressed concern that rapid development - with its blacktop, parking lots and central sewers - will cover so much of the natural landscape in Putnam County that rain cannot soak the ground and feed the wells.</p>
        <p>If wells no longer suffice to supply area needs, tapping into surface-water sources may not be easy. Although Putnam County is home to a large part of the New York City reservoir system and the lakes that feed it, the cost of hooking into that system and providing the filtration to insure water quality would be prohibitively expensive, Putnam County planners say.</p>
        <p>A series of reports mapping and assessing the local water resources and outlining strategies for insuring a supply well into the next century are due later this year from state agencies, a regional consortium and a Westchester County task force. The first of these reports, issued last year, indicated that the region's water quality and quantity are not guaranteed, and the next 13 years are leading to ''a century of limits'' in terms of water resources.</p>
        <p>The report, entitled ''Thirsty City - A Plan of Action for the New York City Water Supply,'' lists three major concerns about the reliability of a system on which 85 percent of Westchester communities depend, as do portions of 12 other counties around the state.</p>
        <p>Consumption is ''apparently out of control, with no adequate explanation,'' according to the report, a privately financed effort of the Citizens Union Foundation, a New York City-based organization that studies problems confronting urban areas and reports on them to the public. Hydrologists consulted in the study agreed that the system's ''safe yield'' - the amount that the 23 reservoirs feeding the New York City supply system can yield without going dry - is 1.2 billion gallons daily, but the New York City and Westchester ''draw'' has topped that figure in steadily increasing amounts over the last 18 years.</p>
        <p>A second concern cited by the authors of ''Thirsty City'' is the threat posed by urbanization and development. In the Croton reservoir, one of three major reservoir systems that supply the metropolitan area, the authors say ''water quality is already deteriorating.''</p>
        <p>New York City is scheduled to spend an estimated $400 million to construct its first major water supply treatment plant at the Jerome Park reservoir in the Bronx to cope with impurities in the Croton system.</p>
        <p>The authors are also concerned about the ''greenhouse effect,'' a global warming associated with the accumulation of carbon dioxide that scientists say could cause the ocean's level to rise, destroying groundwater aquifers and placing impossible demands on the reservoir system.</p>
        <p>Residents of Putnam County are concerned about the pace of urbanization and development that has caused the county's population to grow 13 percent in the last five years and an estimated 6 million square feet of office park space to be developed or proposed during the last two years. The 87,000 residents depend less on the New York City Croton reservoir system, which sprawls across large portions of their county, and more on private wells and lakes. Of the county's 87 water districts, only three are supplied by the reservoir system. Private water sources came first in this sparsely populated county, and remain traditional.</p>
        <p>Well-drillers such as Mr. Boyd, who digs about 300 wells a year, are kept busy piercing through the solid rock that underlies most of Putnam County searching for the seams and cracks that store ground water. The job is more difficult these days, Mr. Boyd said, because of ''lots of buildings, parking lots and roads'' that are covering the ground of the recharge areas into which rain should soak.</p>
        <p>''Much more of the runoff goes into the New York City reservoir system and not to our wells and lakes,'' Mr. Boyd said. He is worried about the future of Putnam County's water supply, and he added: ''Each area has to be evaluated and each acre evaluated to see how buildable it is or how valuable it is for water retention.''</p>
        <p>The United States Geological Survey is conducting just such a study in Putnam County in cooperation with the county's Department of Health. Well yields are being evaluated, and all groundwater aquifers mapped. The geological survey is conducting a similar study in Westchester, and, said Steven Wolcott, a hydrologist with the department, ''not much work of this kind has ever been done in the southern New York region.''</p>
        <p>But, he said, more agencies were becoming concerned about the region's water quality and supply. While refusing to speculate on the results of the study, Mr. Wolcott added: ''Whether this region is running low on water is a $2 million question. I won't say that we are, as that would cause alarm.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Boyd's concerns about the quantity of water available to Putnam County is not shared by county officials. ''Certainly there's more usage,'' John Karell, director of the division of environmental health for Putnam County, said recently, adding: ''Remember the drought last year. Groundwater may recover at a slower rate.'' Wells in Putnam have never been dug as deep as in other counties in the region, Mr. Karell said, adding, ''I want to review the U.S.G.S. data before I make any judgments.''</p>
        <p>Although Malcolm T. Beal Jr., vice president of a well-drilling concern in Brewster, also drills wells 100 feet deeper than he did 10 years ago, he said: ''There's more than an adequate supply of water. All the concern about quality and quantity of water in the county is overstated by those who want to limit development.''</p>
        <p>Later this year, special reports from agencies studying water problems in the state, the New York City region and Westchester County will be issued, each addressing some of the concerns raised in ''Thirsty City.'' Among these will be a second interim report issued by the Mayor's Intergovernmental Task Force on the New York City water supply needs, a panel representing the city and all the counties in the watershed areas. The group concluded last year that use in New York City and Westchester already exceeded the system's safe yield and that consumers would require an additional 200 to 300 million gallons a day by the year 2000. The group has been studying ways to increase that water supply and to assess demand by 2030.</p>
        <p>Salvatore A. Celona, director of the county's Water Agency, which represents Westchester in all water-related issues, is a member of that New York City task force, one established in 1985 in response to the drought. The current work of the intergovernmental task force, Mr. Celona said, represents an intelligent response to demands for growth in the region. ''This panel will allow us to use water wisely,'' Mr. Celona said, ''rather than allowing it to manage us.''</p>
        <p>Westchester County is developing its own internal water-management plan, Mr. Celona said, with the help of a water-management task force established by County Executive Andrew P. O'Rourke early last year. That group, which includes commissioners of planning, health and environmental facilities, is considering such questions as whether the county needs an agency to set guidelines for controling storm water runoff, and its report is due in September.</p>
        <p>Near the end of the year, a report will be issued detailing a systematic statewide approach to managing the state's water resources for present and future needs. Established by an act of the State Legislature in 1984, the Water Resources Management Strategy Program, using resources of the state's Health Department and its Department of Environmental Conservation, is looking at key facts about sources and supplies in 13 sub-regions of the state, examining policy issues, and is expected to recommend a strategy for providing an adequate water supply for the state's needs through the middle of the next century.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Putnam planners, drillers and residents continue to focus debate on the county's concerns about water, wells and development. One Putnam County planner, who asked to remain anonymous, said: ''The whole water issue is a kaleidoscope, and it's difficult to pinpoint where the real problems lie. This issue is not a 'Chicken Little-type thing.' The sky is not falling, but we are concerned, and we are studying the situation.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
