<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>REAGAN, CITING FOREIGN CHALLENGE, OUTLINES SUPERCONDUCTIVITY PLAN</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="60883"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRICITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUPERCONDUCTORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PATENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANTITRUST ACTIONS AND LAWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PHYSICS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GLEICK, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electricity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DE113AF93AA15754C0A961948260" item-length="1108" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>REAGAN, CITING FOREIGN CHALLENGE, OUTLINES SUPERCONDUCTIVITY PLAN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES GLEICK, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GLEICK, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Responding to the perception of a strong challenge from Japan and other countries, President Reagan announced a broad Federal program today to help American businesses translate the scientific promise of superconductivity into marketable technologies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Responding to the perception of a strong challenge from Japan and other countries, President Reagan announced a broad Federal program today to help American businesses translate the scientific promise of superconductivity into marketable technologies.</p>
        <p>Responding to the perception of a strong challenge from Japan and other countries, President Reagan announced a broad Federal program today to help American businesses translate the scientific promise of superconductivity into marketable technologies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reagan described it as an ''11-point Superconductivity Initiative,'' the points ranging from a new advisory panel of ''wise men'' to proposed legislation that would strengthen patent protection and relax antitrust rules.</p>
        <p>The plan includes establishing, at Government laboratories, four special centers for research into superconducting materials - substances that carry electric current without the slightest loss to resistance. Further, the military plans to spend $150 million in the next three years to speed potential applications in ships and weaponry. A Major Commitment</p>
        <p>''Science tells us that the breakthroughs in superconductivity bring us to the threshold of a new age,'' Mr. Reagan said at a Federal conference on the commercial applications of superconductivity. ''It is our task at this conference to herald in that new age with a rush.''</p>
        <p>Flanked by the Secretaries of State, Defense and Energy - and paying tribute to Secretary of Commerce Malcolm Baldridge, a scheduled speaker before his death in a rodeo accident Saturday - the President outlined what amounted to an extraordinary Government commitment to a breakthrough in pure science.</p>
        <p>The President's program comes eight months after the first announcement that physicists had discovered new superconducting materials.</p>
        <p>Past superconductors, already used to make powerful magnets in medical imaging machines and particle accelerators, only worked in extreme cold and required so much refrigeration that they were relegated to the realm of esoterica. The new materials become superconducting with much less cooling, opening the door to small, fast computers, frictionless levitating trains, extremely efficient electrical transmission lines and perhaps many other everyday applications.</p>
        <p>''The effects of all these discoveries will change the world in ways that we will all have to stretch our imaginations to conceive,'' said the White House Science Adviser, Dr. William R. Graham. Meeting the Competition</p>
        <p>A driving motivation for the initiative, Administration officials said, is the fear of well-coordinated foreign competition on a new high-technology battleground. Japan and the Soviet Union have set in motion national programs on superconductivity.</p>
        <p>''It's not so much a fear as a certain realization,'' Dr. Graham said in an interview. ''The Japanese will move very aggressively in this area. And where 20 years ago we had the luxury of moving in advanced technology at our own pace, today Japan and several other countries are very sophisticated technically and very strong competitors.''</p>
        <p>The legislative part of the President's program ties three proposals together in one bill under the rubric of superconductivity. Antitrust laws would be relaxed to make joint ventures easier for manufacturers; patent laws would be strengthened to allow companies to seek damages when imported products infringe patents and - the proposal likely to be most controversial - the Freedom of Information Act would be modified to allow Government laboratories to withhold commercially valuable scientific information.</p>
        <p>The Administration is also ordering the Patent and Trademark Office to speed up processing applications involving superconductivity. Other agencies are being asked to switch financing toward superconductivity research wherever possible. Concern About Military</p>
        <p>The President, continuing his series of public appearances during the Iran-contra hearings, spoke in an anecdotal, quotation-filled talk of ''an age of mind over matter.''</p>
        <p>He described the promise of the new superconductors as ''a quantum leap in energy efficiency that would bring with it many benefits, not least among them a reduced dependence on foreign oil, a cleaner environment and a stronger national economy.''</p>
        <p>Scientists expressed pleasure today at the fast-rising level of Administrative attention to superconductivity. Some, however, said they were concerned about the amount of financing to be channeled through the Department of Defense for military purposes.</p>
        <p>The conference that began today is intended to bring Government and industry officials together with scientists to discuss the future of applications in such areas as computing, transportation and commmunications. To the vocal annoyance of some scientists, the White House decided to exclude foreign participation.</p>
        <p>Dr. Graham, the President's Science Adviser, said that while he believes in international openness in science, ''We really wanted to have a meeting of our home team.'' Engineering Problems</p>
        <p>A frantic international research effort by thousands of physicists in recent months has brought an increasingly sharp sense of the engineering problems that will have to be overcome on the way from the laboratory to the marketplace.</p>
        <p>The materials are easy to make in small quantities. One physicist, Angelica Stacy of the University of California at Berkeley, spoke today of the ''Julia Child approach - some people are using coffee grinders and microwave ovens.'' But mass production brings difficulties, and the superconductors become unstable when exposed to moisture and carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Because the materials are brittle ceramics, the production of wire for magnets or transmission lines will also pose engineering difficulties, and the Department of Energy has set up a special wire-making project at the Argonne National Laboratory in Illinois.</p>
        <p>One reason for the Administration's concern about the road to commercial applications is the likelihood that the most rewarding technologies will require a long, sustained commitment of investment without the solace of immediate compensation on corporate balance sheets. Redirection of Financing</p>
        <p>''Other countries, particularly Japan, have shown that such commitment can produce spectacular results,'' said Erich Bloch, the head of the National Science Foundation. If American industry is not willing to look ahead more than a year or two at a time, he said, ''then others will reap the benefits of the insights that our laboratories have produced.''</p>
        <p>For now, at least, the initiative involves a redirection of money from other research rather than new financing, a White House aide said. And Federal officials took pains to say their policy would be guided by the President's belief that private enterprise must remain responsible for developing commercial products.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
