<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A RAGE THAT RISES WHEN THE TROUT GO BELLY UP</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="33005"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="MUSKOKA JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MUSKOKA LAKE (ONTARIO)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURNS, JOHN F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Ontario</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DB1F3FF930A15757C0A961948260" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A RAGE THAT RISES WHEN THE TROUT GO BELLY UP</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BURNS, JOHN F</byline>
      <dateline>MUSKOKA LAKE, Ontario, April 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Rolf Uhde gazed at the cirrus clouds scudding across the sky, harbinger of a spring rainstorm still about 12 hours away. Then he glanced back to the pond by his feet, its murky waters sliced by the shadowy traces of thousands of speckled trout.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Rolf Uhde gazed at the cirrus clouds scudding across the sky, harbinger of a spring rainstorm still about 12 hours away. Then he glanced back to the pond by his feet, its murky waters sliced by the shadowy traces of thousands of speckled trout.</p>
        <p>Rolf Uhde gazed at the cirrus clouds scudding across the sky, harbinger of a spring rainstorm still about 12 hours away. Then he glanced back to the pond by his feet, its murky waters sliced by the shadowy traces of thousands of speckled trout.</p>
        <p>''We'll be losing some of those beauties when the rains come,'' said Mr. Uhde, a 60-year-old fish farmer, fingering the stubble on his chin. ''When the storms blow in from the southwest, the readings around here go crazy. Then we find the fish floating on the pond, dead as a doornail.''</p>
        <p>In this resort district 100 miles north of Toronto, residents routinely test the lakes and streams after rain or snow. Often, they find a sudden sharp drop in levels of pH, indicating an increase in acidity, which can kill fish and push entire lakes toward biological death.</p>
        <p>The primary cause of acid rain in the Muskoka Lakes area is hundreds of miles away, beyond Canada's borders in industrial concentrations along the Ohio Valley. There, coal-burning power plants, smoke-belching steel mills and acrid petrochemical plants pump millions of tons of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide into the air each year. Chemically Transformed</p>
        <p>In the atmosphere, the pollutants mix with water vapor and are chemically transformed into acids, which eventually fall to earth in rain, snow, fog or dust. Large areas of the northeastern United States are polluted in this way, but much of the damage occurs across a stretch of eastern Canada that is 1,500 miles wide and at least 1,000 miles deep, along the path of the prevailing winds from the south.</p>
        <p>Canada has some house-cleaning of its own to do - about 1.2 million tons of Canadian sulfur dioxide reaches the United States each year, compared with 3.2 million tons that wafts into Canada from the United States. But Canadian officials say that their control program will meet the goal of a 50 percent cut from the flows across the border registered in 1980.</p>
        <p>At the worst-hit places in Canada like Muskoka, and in the maple-sugar region of Beauce, south of Quebec City, scientists have attributed 75 percent of the damage to industrial emissions that originate in the United States. Elsewhere, the United States contribution to Canada's acid rain problem is put at an average of 50 percent. A $20 Billion Problem</p>
        <p>All told, the Government agency that monitors pollution, Environment Canada, estimates that more than $20 billion in annual economic activity in Canada is at risk.</p>
        <p>As President Reagan discovered on his visit to Canada this month, fears of this kind raise strong feelings. Demonstrators drawn to Parliament Hill in Ottawa gave more attention to acid rain than to nuclear weapons. And whenever the President came within hailing distance of Canadian reporters, the only thing they wanted to know was what he intended to do about acid rain.</p>
        <p>Canada is seeking a pact that sets a schedule for a 50 percent reduction in flows across the border of sulfur dioxide, identified as the most damaging source of acid rain. The Canadians laid the domestic groundwork for the pact in 1985 by ordering a 50 percent cut over 10 years in the 1980 levels of sulfur dioxide emitted by the country's worst polluters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reagan has resisted mandatory emission cuts, saying they would cripple United States industry. Instead, he has backed a five-year, $5 billion program of research into cleaner ways of burning coal, with the costs to be equally shared by Government and industry.</p>
        <p>Faced with what is likely to be a long struggle, Prime Minister Brian Mulroney has been unusually blunt. ''We know the cause of acid rain, we know the consequences and we know the cure,'' he said in Quebec City shortly before Mr. Reagan's visit. ''The Government of Canada is firmly resolved to end the blight of acid rain, and expects the same genuine resolve from the United States.'' 'Incredible Selfishness'</p>
        <p>Some in Canada are even more vocal.</p>
        <p>''There is a widespread perception that Americans really don't give a damn if we have any forests, any fish or any lakes,'' said William Blaikie, a Member of Parliament for the left-wing New Democratic Party. ''The sense of an incredible selfishness on the part of the U.S. Government is going to have a fundamental effect on the way that Canadians think about the United States.'' Mr. Blaikie sits on a parliamentary committee that has studied acid rain.</p>
        <p>To make sure that its opinions are felt in Washington, the Government has recently said that it intends to work with American politicians sympathetic to Canada's concerns in an effort to create a groundswell for controls in Congress. 'Matter of Political Will'</p>
        <p>Patrick McTaggart-Cowan, one of the country's most distinguished scientists, who has retired to a 200-acre farm on the Muskoka River, spoke with quiet passion last month of his stunted cauliflower crop and of the chocolate-colored water in the farm's well - effects that Dr. McTaggart-Cowan, 75 years old, a former chairman of the Science Council of Canada, attributed to acid rain.</p>
        <p>Dr. McTaggart-Cowan, a physicist, dismissed the Reagan Administration's arguments that the scientific foundation for a multibillion-dollar acid rain control program was lacking. ''The science of all this is well known,'' he said. ''As far as I'm concerned it's been known since before World War II. So it's no longer a scientific problem, it's a matter of political will.''  MUSKOKA JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
