<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>House Rejects Long Delay of Clean Air Deadlines</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="98945"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7D91E30F937A35751C1A961948260" item-length="649" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>House Rejects Long Delay of Clean Air Deadlines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The House today overwhelmingly rejected an industry-backed drive to take the tough issues of air pollution and acid rain off Congress's agenda until at least 1989.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The House today overwhelmingly rejected an industry-backed drive to take the tough issues of air pollution and acid rain off Congress's agenda until at least 1989.</p>
        <p>The House today overwhelmingly rejected an industry-backed drive to take the tough issues of air pollution and acid rain off Congress's agenda until at least 1989.</p>
        <p>In two votes, the House rejected the industry proposal to extend by 19 months the Clean Air Act's deadline of Dec. 31 for reducing smog and carbon monoxide levels and then approved an extension of eight months.</p>
        <p>The 19-month extension was rejected by a vote of 257 to 162. The eight-month amendment was approved by voice vote a short time later, and supporters said it would force Congress to strengthen the Clean Air Act next year and perhaps begin an attack on the pollution that causes acid rain. A Consortium of Corporations</p>
        <p>Supporters of the short-term extension amendment, led by Representatives Silvio O. Conte, Republican of Massachusetts, and Henry A. Waxman, Democrat of California, said the 19-month amendment would have all but guaranteed that the 100th Congress would take no further action on air pollution.</p>
        <p>The defeat of the 19-month plan, offered by Representative John P. Murtha, a Pennsylvania Democrat, came less than a day after the Clean Air Working Group, a consortium of some of the nation's largest corporations and most powerful trade associations, predicted victory for the plan.</p>
        <p>''We've got the votes,'' said Ronald Sykes, a General Motors lobbyist active in the industry group.</p>
        <p>Lee M. Thomas, Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, has said that nearly 60 large metropolitan areas will not meet the Dec. 31 deadline for reducing ozone, a major component of smog, and carbon monoxide to maximum levels set by the Clean Air Act. The law provides sanctions to be used against cities that do not meet the deadline, including a ban on construction of plants that are large sources of pollution and the withholding of Federal funds for highways, sewers and air pollution control.</p>
        <p>Among the metropolitan areas that have not been able to comply fully with the air pollution standards are those in New York and New Jersey. 'Relief From Sanctions' Sought</p>
        <p>The industry group was lobbying hard for the Murtha amendment, which was supported by the Reagan Administration and by Representative John D. Dingell, a Michigan Democrat who is chairman of the House Energy and Commerce Committee.</p>
        <p>''We've been talking to a lot of members,'' said Jim Hamilton, a lobbyist for the USX Corporation, formerly United States Steel. ''We have been working with every member of the House who supports Murtha's amendment, and that includes John Dingell.''</p>
        <p>Although the industry group wants no changes in the Clean Air Act, Mr. Hamilton said it backed the Murtha amendment to ''provide communities with relief from sanctions'' for more than the eight months called for in the Conte amendment.</p>
        <p>But while industry lobbyists were expressing their concern for cities, the National League of Cities was urging the House to support the Conte-Waxman amendment and start revising the Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>David Gardiner, a lobbyist for the Sierra Club, a major environmental organization, called today's roll-call vote ''the most important environmental vote of 1987.'' ''Approval of the Murtha amendment would be an extraordinary admission by the 100th Congress that they are unwilling or incapable of protecting America's breathers from air pollution,'' he said. ''It means that Congress will do what the polluters want -nothing. Tens of millions of Americans will pay the price of that inaction with their health.''</p>
        <p>Senators were watching the House vote closely. The Senate Environment Committee has approved a comprehensive anti-pollution package that is still awaiting floor debate. Robert C. Byrd of West Virginia, the Senate majority leader, opposes its provisions to control acid rain.</p>
        <p>Mr. Byrd, Mr. Dingell and Mr. Murtha represent areas that depend on the coal, automobile or steel industries.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
