<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GORE, ENTERING 1988 RACE, PROJECTS 'NEW SOUTH' IMAGE</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="53256"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1988</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DIONNE, E J JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, ALBERT JR (SEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DC123DF933A05755C0A961948260" item-length="1199" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GORE, ENTERING 1988 RACE, PROJECTS 'NEW SOUTH' IMAGE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By E. J. DIONNE Jr., Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DIONNE, E J JR</byline>
      <dateline>CARTHAGE, Tenn., June 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Standing on the steps of a red brick courthouse in this venerable farm town that is misty with the imagery of the Old South, 39-year-old Senator Albert Gore Jr. today declared himself a Presidential candidate from ''the New South'' who is ''eager to help build a new America.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Standing on the steps of a red brick courthouse in this venerable farm town that is misty with the imagery of the Old South, 39-year-old Senator Albert Gore Jr. today declared himself a Presidential candidate from ''the New South'' who is ''eager to help build a new America.''</p>
        <p>Standing on the steps of a red brick courthouse in this venerable farm town that is misty with the imagery of the Old South, 39-year-old Senator Albert Gore Jr. today declared himself a Presidential candidate from ''the New South'' who is ''eager to help build a new America.''</p>
        <p>Before several thousand supporters who gathered along the main street of Mr. Gore's hometown (population 2,672), the youngest Democratic candidate for the Presidency promised to ''regenerate a sense of national purpose'' for ''a young and eager and restless nation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said the 1988 election should produce a President who could rival the Soviet leader Mikhail S. Gorbachev. Without mentioning him by name, he called the 56-year-old Mr. Gorbachev ''a leader who combines youthful energy and innovation with experience.''</p>
        <p>''The free world,'' Mr. Gore declared in a passage that drew some of the day's loudest cheers, ''urgently needs a leader who can match him, test him, bargain with him and make the most of this possibly historic opportunity for a safer, saner world.'' Grasping the Initiative</p>
        <p>Suggesting that the United States needed to regain the initiative, Mr. Gore went on: ''We as Americans have always captured the imagination of people all across the earth. This election offers a chance for the United States to once again demonstrate that we have the capacity for self-renewal that the rest of the world can only dream about.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, who would be the youngest President in American history if elected next year, brings to the Democratic race a careful moderation developed in ten and a half years in Congress - eight in the house, two and a half in the Senate - and from a lifetime of watching his father, former Senator Albert Gore Sr., who spent 32 years in Congress.</p>
        <p>The elder Mr. Gore virtually led the cheering today as he stood proudly behind his son on the courthouse steps in this town at the heart of the family's political base.</p>
        <p>Carthage and the surrounding area turned out in mass for a down-home political sendoff. Most of the stores shut down, many people took the day off from work, and 200 Democratic women baked thousands of cookies to keep the crowd happy under the hot sun. Pressing Southern Advantage</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore hopes to profit from the creation of ''Super Tuesday,'' March 8, 1988, when 20 states, many of them in the South, will elect delegates to the national convention.</p>
        <p>The only Southerner among the seven Democrats now in the race, Mr. Gore has seen his effort to consolidate support in the South stalled by speculation that Senator Sam Nunn of Georgia would enter the contest.</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Gore's own aides concede that he has not yet captured the imagination of the South. And Mr. Gore himself noted that some in politics have suggested that given his age he might have waited a few elections before runnng for President.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gore was unabashed today in offering himself not only as a Southerner, but as a young Southerner in tune with the region's changing political and social climate.</p>
        <p>''Here in Carthage, we are part of what is called the New South and we are eager to help build a new America,'' he said. ''Along with other Southerners, we eagerly anticipate the new and powerful role the South will play in selecting our Presidential nominee next year and in helping to determine what kind of America we will lead into the 21st century.''</p>
        <p>''I am not running as a Southern candidate,'' he said at another point, ''but as a national candidate from the South and proud of it.'' Science and the Military</p>
        <p>A man with an easy smile, Mr. Gore has staked out his turf in Congress on a variety of such esoteric issues as the depletion of the ozone layer around the earth, the regulation of organ transplants and genetic engineering.</p>
        <p>He also made himself a specialist on arms control and has been a leader, along with Representative Les Aspin of Wisconsin, of a centrist alliance that has sought alternatives both to President Reagan's policies and to those proposed by the Democratic Party's more dovish wing.</p>
        <p>The caution with which Mr. Gore approaches military questions was revealed in his address here today.</p>
        <p>In the prepared text, Mr. Gore's emphasis was on peace and the need to ''make nuclear war obsolete.''</p>
        <p>But when he gave the speech, Mr. Gore added passages that made clear he also stood for military preparedness. ''I served in Vietnam,'' he said, reading from the prepared text, and then added: ''I know the importance of protecting our national security.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore demonstrated the central role arms control will play in his campaign by focusing almost entirely on that subject in an address to an American Legion post in Manchester, N.H., where he flew after his announcement here.</p>
        <p>In the speech, released here, Mr. Gore promoted his proposal to replace multi-warhead missiles with mobile missiles that have only one warhead. This could form the basis for an arms control agreement that would reduce the risk of nuclear war by making it ''impossible for either the Soviet Union or the United States to gain any advantage whatsoever from a nuclear first strike.''</p>
        <p>On domestic issues, Mr. Gore placed himself squarely within the emerging Democratic consensus, emphasizing in his speech here the need to rebuild America's educational system, improve the training of its workers, provide better health care and child care and combat homelessness. He said the United States should stand for ''civil, equal and human rights.''</p>
        <p>On trade, he said he would ''combat unfair trade practices,'' but urged the nation to embrace ''perfectionism, not protectionism.'' Fame and Family</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, the father of four children, is married to a woman who may well be better known than he is.</p>
        <p>Mary Elizabeth Aitcheson Gore, 38, called Tipper, is a leader in the movement to call on the recording industry to exercise greater self-restraint and to clearly label rock songs and videos with explicit sexual or violent themes.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Gore has run into strong opposition from some rock stars, but she argues that she opposes censorship and likes rock music. Her concern, she says, is that young children are being exposed to songs that seem to glorify rape, sado-masochism and suicide. Her recent book, ''Raising PG Kids in an X-Rated Society,'' is selling well.</p>
        <p>Although well-liked in this town, Mr. Gore was born in Washington, and has a nearly perfect establishment upraising.</p>
        <p>He graduated from St. Alban's School, a prestigious private school in Washington, and with honors from Harvard. He attended divinity and then law school at Vanderbuilt University while he was working as a reporter and then editorial writer at The Nashville Tennessean. He abruptly entered politics in 1976, when Representative Joe Evins announced his retirement.</p>
        <p>The most moving moment in Mr. Gore's address here came after he noted his experience as a Vietnam veteran. ''I know there are better ways to resolve our differences than through war,'' he said. ''On the obelisk in front of me are the names of eight young soldiers from Carthage who paid the ultimate price in that conflict.'' Then, one by one, he read the names of the eight fallen heroes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
