<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>6 STATES IN NORTHEAST TO SUE U.S. OVER ACID RAIN</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="30006"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND CLAIMS AGAINST GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MASSACHUSETTS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MAINE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">VERMONT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDB143BF937A25757C0A961948260" item-length="856" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>6 STATES IN NORTHEAST TO SUE U.S. OVER ACID RAIN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Six Northeastern states, including New York, New Jersey and Connecticut, said today that they would sue the Federal Government to force it to curb the air pollution that causes acid rain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Six Northeastern states, including New York, New Jersey and Connecticut, said today that they would sue the Federal Government to force it to curb the air pollution that causes acid rain.</p>
        <p>Six Northeastern states, including New York, New Jersey and Connecticut, said today that they would sue the Federal Government to force it to curb the air pollution that causes acid rain.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit, which is being joined by national environmental groups, is to charge that the Federal Environmental Protection Agency has failed to carry out provisions of the Clean Air Act that require a reduction in pollution that impairs visibility in Federal parks and wilderness areas.</p>
        <p>The suit asserts that the pollutants that cause much of the reduced visibility in the Northeast are sulfates that come largely from coal-fired power plants in the Midwest. These sulfates are also believed to be a major source of the acid rain that has been found to have destroyed freshwater life in lakes in the United States and Canada. Widespread Forest Damage</p>
        <p>Current research shows that acid rain also damages building materials, may be harmful to human health and may play a role in causing widespread forest damage along the Eastern Seaboard and in Canada.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit would require the E.P.A. to publish rules requiring a curb on the pollution that causes the impaired visibility and to compel the polluting state to carry out those rules.</p>
        <p>The states sending the notices of intent to sue also included Massachusetts, Maine and Vermont, along with the Natural Resources Defense Council, the Environmental Defense Fund, the Conservation Law Foundation and the Sierra Club. A 'Very Complex' Problem</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the agency said the notice of intent to sue had not been received and thus no specific comments about the planned suit could be made.</p>
        <p>The spokesman, Christian Rice, said the E.P.A. had previously acted to curb pollution from specific, identifiable sources of pollution that impaired visibility. He added, however, that the problem of ''regional haze'' was a ''very complex and difficult problem.''</p>
        <p>When more information about the sources of regional visibility impairment and how to monitor them is available, he said, the agency will then be able to ''allocate control burdens in a rational way'' and take action.</p>
        <p>New York's Attorney General, Robert Abrams, said he and the attorneys general of the other states planning to sue the Federal Government were highly critical of President Reagan's proposal in Ottawa last week to spend $2.5 billion to develop technology for burning coal cleanly.</p>
        <p>''Using the Clean Air Act to order reductions in harmful emissions is a far more effective response to this environmental problem than the proposal to spend $2.5 million for new emission control technology,'' Mr. Abrams said. A 'Stalling Tactic'</p>
        <p>He said that the President's proposal ''is an expensive stalling tactic'' and that ''the technology is already available to drastically cut emissions which cause acid rain.''</p>
        <p>''If the President wishes to spend billions of dollars on the acid rain problem,'' Mr. Abrams said, ''he should figure out how the money could be used to accelerate, not retard, the installation of emission controls on the dirtiest Midwestern power plants.''</p>
        <p>This would be the fifth lawsuit filed by Northeastern states and environmental groups in recent years charging violations of the Clean Air Act by the Federal Government. One of the cases, contending that the Federal agency has failed to carry out a provision of the act requiring action to curb pollution that crosses international borders, is awaiting a decision by the Supreme Court on whether it will hear the state's appeal of a lower court's rejection of its charges.</p>
        <p>One pending lawsuit deals with what it calls the failure of the E.P.A. to curb air pollution crossing state boundaries, another with charges that the agency has not curbed the use of tall smokestacks to evade the requirements of the law. Still another would force the agency to revise the national air-quality standards to deal with acid rain, which they do not currently address. 'Partial Abatement'</p>
        <p>An assistant attorney general for New York, David Wooley, said in a telephone interview that if the E.P.A. required a reduction of the pollution that is harming visibility on a regional scale in the East, one side effect would be the ''partial abatement'' of acid rain.</p>
        <p>Several bills are now pending in Congress that would attack the acid rain problem head on by requiring substantial reductions in sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide emissions by power plants, factories and automobiles. These pollutants are changed chemically when carried through the atmosphere and fall to earth as acidic rain, snow, fog or dust.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wooley said, however, that visibility impairment was a significant problem in its own right. He said that visibility has worsened in the East since the 1950's and that the decline has been shown to correspond to a rise in atmospheric concentrations of sulfates and sulfur dioxide.</p>
        <p>A lawyer for the Sierra Club Legal Defense Fund, Howard Fox, said that ''regional haze is an insidious problem which effectively draws a curtain across the East's most cherished scenic vistas, preventing them from being enjoyed by the public.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
