<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOST ENERGY FUNDS FOR MILITARY USES</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="3225"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOLAR ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC WEAPONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE WEAPONS (STAR WARS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MISSILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENERGY, DEPARTMENT OF</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORDON, MICHAEL R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE6DA123DF930A25752C0A961948260" item-length="599" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOST ENERGY FUNDS FOR MILITARY USES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL R. GORDON, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GORDON, MICHAEL R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Energy Department's budget request would increase the share of agency funds that are spent on military programs while reducing funds for energy conservation and renewable energy programs, according to a Congressional study made public today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Energy Department's budget request would increase the share of agency funds that are spent on military programs while reducing funds for energy conservation and renewable energy programs, according to a Congressional study made public today.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department's budget request would increase the share of agency funds that are spent on military programs while reducing funds for energy conservation and renewable energy programs, according to a Congressional study made public today.</p>
        <p>Almost two-thirds of the department's budget is for military programs, according to the report. It said part of the budget for research on civilian projects was being used to finance programs for President Reagan's proposed defense against missiles, including a a nuclear reactor that would be sent into space to power parts of the ''Star Wars'' system.</p>
        <p>The Congressional analysis was released by Representative Edward J. Markey, Democrat of Massachusetts, a member of the Energy and Commerce Committee who is a critic of the Administration's missile shield plan. Increasing Devotion to Military</p>
        <p>The analysis shows that about 65 percent of the Energy Department's requested budget is for military programs, such as nuclear warheads and research on a ''Star Wars'' X-ray laser device that would be powered by a nuclear detonation.</p>
        <p>About 61 percent of the agency's 1987 budget was devoted to military programs, according to the study, while in 1981 military programs accounted for only 38 percent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Markey, who heads the Subcommittee on Energy Conservation and Power, asserted today that the Energy Department budget was becoming increasingly ''militarized.''</p>
        <p>While the budget for military programs would increase under the Energy Department's plan, spending for solar energy and renewable energy would be cut by 36 percent, according to the Congressional analysis. Spending on fossil energy research would be cut by 18 percent. Official Acknowledges Shift</p>
        <p>Under Secretary of Energy Joseph F. Salgado provided figures that were close to the committee's breakdown. The shift reflects the general priority that the Administration has placed on buying new generations of nuclear weapons, he said, adding that it also stems from the department's decision that the Government should concentrate on ''high risk'' research and development and should not spend a lot on some types of conservation programs.</p>
        <p>One issue raised by the Congressional report is whether the Department should finance some ''Star Wars'' programs in its civilian budget. Such programs include the SP-100 space-based reactor and research on other multimegawatt powerplants.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department noted that the SP-100 program was intended to develop a compact reactor that could serve civilian as well as military applications in the 1990's. Concern Over Nuclear Satellites</p>
        <p>Mr. Salgado said that the agency was justified in financing some of these programs in its civilian budget because they were initiated as nonmilitary programs and might have some civilian applications. ''I am told that they started out as civilian programs but it turned out that the only customer was the military,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Some members of Congress and interest groups have raised particular concerns about the Energy Department's space-based reactor program. They note that some nuclear-powered satellites have fallen out of orbit and maintain that the SP-100 program could present risks.</p>
        <p>According to the Congressional analysis, the Energy Department is seeking $8.2 billion in funds for military programs this year. This represents an increase of about $600 million and is more than double the amount the agency was spending when President Reagan took office.</p>
        <p>The overall Energy Deparment budget request is $12.6 billion, close to the current level of $12.5 billion.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
