<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOOD INSPECTION RESULTS</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="68" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="90821"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SANITATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1DA173FF93BA35752C1A961948260" item-length="1119" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOOD INSPECTION RESULTS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The New York City Department of Health last week released a list of 25 food establishments cited for violating the health code.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The New York City Department of Health last week released a list of 25 food establishments cited for violating the health code.</p>
        <p>The New York City Department of Health last week released a list of 25 food establishments cited for violating the health code.</p>
        <p>In addition, it listed seven restaurants that were allowed to reopen after correcting earlier violations and four that were closed for having failed to do so. The establishments are these:  VIOLATIONS  MANHATTAN  Allen's Deli, 1294 Madison Ave. (91st St.). Refrigerator littered with food, lightbulb unshielded, holes in basement wall and at junction of wall and floor, sink covered with dirt, supplies on basement floor, mouse droppings on basement shelves, inadequate extermination, flies.  American Pie, 434 Amsterdam Ave. (80th St.).</p>
        <p>Mouse droppings in basement, rust inside ice machine, dust on refrigerator fan, backflow equipment missing.  Brighton Fortune Villa Chinese Restaurant, 270 W. 38th St. Mouse droppings on shelves and floors in basement and kitchen, roaches and flies in basement and kitchen, food on kitchen floor, dirt and grease at junction of walls and floors, no protection certificate, food containers on top of food in refrigerator, holes in walls and floor in kitchen and bathroom.  Cathedral Cafe, 941 Amsterdam Ave. (106th St.). Flies in kitchen.  Chinatown Kite, 193 Centre St. (Hester St.). Operating without a valid permit or protection certificate, most recent inspection report unavailable, food under sink and on top of counter, food covered with towels, carbon dioxide container improperly fastened to wall, no hot water in sink in employees' bathroom, flies.  Colony Coffee Shop, 429 3d Ave. (29th St.). Debris at junction of floors and walls, grease on wall behind grill, no end caps on fluorescent refrigerator bulbs, dishwashing water too cool, sink blocked and dust on dishwashing equipment, operating without a valid permit, grease and food on stove top, grease and dust on fan vent over stove, temperature of some foods too high.  Hime of Japan, 1185 2d Ave. (62d St.). Grease on hood and top of broiler, old food and dirty dishes on counter, no sanitizing tablets at sink for washing bar glasses, no valid permit, self-inspection reports not kept.  Little Italy, 208 W. 42d St. Flies, mouse droppings on floors, inadequate extermination measures, inadequate lighting.  Midtown Deli Express, 204 E. 43d St. Operating without a valid permit, mouse droppings on storage floor, dirt on sides of stove and fryer.  Milon Restaurant, 93 1st Ave. (5th St.). Grease on wall near stove, no guard on lightbulb, uncooked food on cooked food in refrigerator, no screen in bathroom and near stove, mouse droppings on shelf, flies.  North Star Pub, 93 South St. (John St.). Dead roaches under pots and pans on kitchen shelf, dirt and litter in storage room, tiles missing from wall near kitchen table, rust and old food refrigerator rack, boxes stored on floor, mouse droppings in storage room.  Peter's Restaurant &amp; Deli, 1413 Madison Ave. (97th St.). Unused material in basement, flies in basement, vegetables on floor, bottom of side door not flush with floor, screen on storm door torn.  Rainbow, 735 Lexington Ave. (58th St.). Operating without a valid permit, no protection certificate, standing water on basement floor.  Sea World, 409 8th Ave. (30th St.). Mouse droppings on floor and shelves in storage room and service counter, grease and dust on shelves, no protection certificate, flies and roaches.  Vincent's, 119 Mott St. (Hester St.). Hole in basement ceiling, stairs in disrepair, dust on basement floor, dishwasher water too cool.  BROOKLYN  Circle's Cafe, 514 2d St. Operating without a valid permit, flies in kitchen, open seam on cutting board, food handlers not wearing hairnets.  Robert's Restaurant, 65 Washington St. (Front St.). Flies, inadequate extermination.  QUEENS  Assembly Restaurant, 45-46 Bell Blvd. Food uncovered, uncovered containers of food on top of one another, standing water in basement, no guard on lightbulb, no equipment to prevent backflow on hose, carbon dioxide tanks not secured, no signs in bathrooms warning employees to wash hands, and mouse droppings on basement floor.  Dani's Restaurant and Pizza, 81-28 Lefferts Blvd. Cat in basement, dirt and grease on stove hood, grooves on cutting board, old food on shelves, no fan guards in basement cheese freezer, dirt in refrigerator, no screen door on storage area entrance.  E &amp; R Restaurant, 3-11 27th Ave. Mouse droppings on storage-room floor and floor and shelves behind front counter, flies, loose wall covering, inaccessiible space under food-preparation table, drain from steam table incorrectly connected to waste line, counter display lights not covered, dirt on fan guards in display refrigerator, storage racks in some refrigerators covered with stale food and aluminum foil.  Kelly's Pub, 136-11 41st Ave. No food-protection certificate.  Pizza Hut, 253-11 Hillside Ave. Rust and food on can opener, operating without a protection certificate.  Sizzler, 95-25 Queens Blvd. Not enough chlorine in rinse water, floor tiles missing and standing water near dishwasher, holes in wall at dishwasher and janitor's closet, stale food on can opener, no guard over lightbulb in meat refrigerator, no equipment to prevent vacuum in hose, no valve on soda carbonator, cracked salad bowl used as ice scoop.  Szechuan Capital, 135-28 Roosevelt Ave. Dirt and grease at junctions of walls and floors, kitchen light improperly attached, food uncovered and stored on floor, some meats too warm, no lightbulb guard in refrigerator, food on refrigerator shelves, grease and food on can opener.  Tipico Dominicano, 103-10 39th Ave. Dirt and grease on exhaust fan, stale food and debris at junction of walls and floors, inadequate bathroom ventilation, uncovered meats stored in freezer, bottles on uncooked food in freezer, supplies on low skids and overturned milk cartons in basement, roaches in basement, no equipment to prevent formation of vacuum in sink hose.  REOPENED  MANHATTAN  McAnn's Restaurant and Bar, 692 3d Ave. (43d St.).  Gandhi Restaurant, 345 E. 6th St.  Hunan Hut, 143 E. 23d St.  Spanish Benevolent, 239 W. 14th St.  BRONX  Bartow Pizza, 2045A Bartow Ave. (DeReimer Ave.).  BROOKLYN  Cino's Restaurant, 243 De Kalb Ave. (Clermont Ave.).  QUEENS  Kim's Deli, 204-14 Hillside Ave.  CLOSED  MANHATTAN  Mobile commissary for street vendors, 410 W. 36th St.  El Tablaso de Valenzuela, 527 W. 160th St.  BRONX  Cafe Cappuccino, 1036 Morris Park Ave. (Paulding Ave.).  Tony's Pizza, 2137 Williamsbridge Rd. (Lydig Ave.).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
