<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Certain and Ominous Effects of Ozone Loss; Trouble in Antarctica</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="48665"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HODEL, DONALD P (SEC)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE2D71E39F930A25755C0A961948260" item-length="326" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Certain and Ominous Effects of Ozone Loss; Trouble in Antarctica</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your editorial accurately chronicled the shortsighted views of Interior Secretary Hodel and Presidential Science Adviser William Graham on the loss of the earth's protective ozone layer. What makes these officials' suggestions so ludicrous are the very serious impacts that the ozone hole could already be having on marine life in Antarctica.</p>
        <p>Last year, U.S. scientists confirmed that for a month every Antarctic spring, atmospheric ozone over Antarctica plunges by more than a third. Those observations have ominous implications, since the hole occurs when algae and other microflora bloom in the waters off the icy continent. The increased ultraviolet radiation that penetrates to the earth's surface could significantly affect these tiny planktonic creatures at the very base of the Antarctic food chain.</p>
        <p>Indeed, preliminary experiments already indicate that only slight increases in ultraviolet light can dramatically reduce Antarctic phytoplankton. Moreover, as the ozone hole has widened over Antarctica and has exposed the continent's waters to increased ultraviolet radiation, there has been a curious coincidental disappearance of krill. Krill, which feed on plankton, are the tiny, shrimp-like crustacea that serve as the major food source for whales, seals and penguins.</p>
        <p>It is now winter in Antarctica, and the sun won't shine there again until late July, but scientists have shed enough light on the ozone hole to know that it is likely caused by emissions from chlorofluorocarbons. The shortsighted solutions recently espoused by Hodel and Graham would not in any way limit these chemical emissions.</p>
        <p>Antarctica is far away, but it should not be out of mind, par-ticularly for Government officials who are charged with shaping the Administration's science policy and protecting our natural resources. BRUCE S. MANHEIM JR.  Scientist, Wildlife Program  Environmental Defense Fund  Washington, June 4, 1987</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
