<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Arctic to Arena</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="57289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="SCOUTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ARENA FOOTBALL LEAGUE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON COMMANDOS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALTON, CLARENCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEEDA1230F935A25754C0A961948260" item-length="337" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Arctic to Arena</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Last year, shortly after he graduated from Lehigh University with a degree in economics, Clarence Walton decided to forget football. He had been a 240-pound starter at nose guard for three years and had acquired a sense that football was a never-ending, time-consuming phenomenon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Last year, shortly after he graduated from Lehigh University with a degree in economics, Clarence Walton decided to forget football. He had been a 240-pound starter at nose guard for three years and had acquired a sense that football was a never-ending, time-consuming phenomenon.</p>
        <p>Last year, shortly after he graduated from Lehigh University with a degree in economics, Clarence Walton decided to forget football. He had been a 240-pound starter at nose guard for three years and had acquired a sense that football was a never-ending, time-consuming phenomenon.</p>
        <p>After reporting to free-agent tryout camps run by the New England Patriots and several Canadian Football League teams, but receiving no contract offers, Walton decided the fond memories of football definitely belonged in his past.</p>
        <p>He signed on with an Antarctic research program that spent August, September and October at a base on Ross Island. ''Scientists were studying the ozone layer over Antarctica,'' said Walton. ''I was a field assistant working in temperatures of 50-below zero.</p>
        <p>''It was interesting, seeing volcanos, ice caverns and penguins, but when it was dark for 20 hours a day, I thought a lot about football.''</p>
        <p>After his return, Walton worked as a financial planner in New York, then took a leave last spring after hearing about the new Arena Football League.</p>
        <p>After surviving a turnout of hundreds of candidates, he was assigned to play as a guard and defensive end with the Washington Commandos, one of four teams playing a six-game schedule this summer.</p>
        <p>''It's unbelieveably different from regular football,'' he said. ''You play offense and defense, so you're always doing something. Contact is hard and players sprint, not glide, and get thrashed against the boards. I've never felt so tired on a football field before.''</p>
        <p>Although making only $500 a week as a starter, Walton is again enchanted with football and plans to return to Arena football as long as the new sport thrives.</p>
        <p>''I know I can't ask for leaves of absence from business forever, but maybe I can work out a schedule that will let me play for three or four more seasons,'' he said. ''At the pace that this game is played, that would probably be about all that I could take, anyhow. Then I'll really forget football and get down to work.''  SCOUTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
