<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DEAVER JURY HEARS OF A PERJURY PLAN</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="100882"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERJURY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOBBYING AND LOBBYISTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRANKLIN, BEN A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEAVER, MICHAEL K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEYMOUR, WHITNEY NORTH JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (MRS)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE6DB1F3BF932A25751C1A961948260" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DEAVER JURY HEARS OF A PERJURY PLAN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN A. FRANKLIN, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRANKLIN, BEN A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The prosecutor told the jury at the perjury trial of Michael K. Deaver today that Mr. Deaver's exploitation of his 20-year friendship with Ronald and Nancy Reagan to enhance his lobbying business may have ''broken their hearts.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The prosecutor told the jury at the perjury trial of Michael K. Deaver today that Mr. Deaver's exploitation of his 20-year friendship with Ronald and Nancy Reagan to enhance his lobbying business may have ''broken their hearts.''</p>
        <p>The prosecutor told the jury at the perjury trial of Michael K. Deaver today that Mr. Deaver's exploitation of his 20-year friendship with Ronald and Nancy Reagan to enhance his lobbying business may have ''broken their hearts.''</p>
        <p>The defense, however, told the panel of 15 people, 12 of whom will begin deliberating the guilt or innocence of Mr. Deaver Friday in Federal District Court here, that the prosecution itself was guilty of ''oppression'' and trickery.</p>
        <p>Herbert J. Miller, the chief defense attorney, was rebuked by Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson after completing the defense's two-hour summation.</p>
        <p>''You knew that was improper,'' the judge told Mr. Miller, who had just told the jurors that he had ''the moral certainty'' that Mr. Deaver was innocent of one of the prosecution's accusations. In effect, it was a defense lawyer testifying. Alleged Perjury Plan Outlined</p>
        <p>The emotional linking of Mr. Deaver, a former White House chief of staff, with the President and Mrs. Reagan and Mr. Deaver's ''using of his relationship with them to entice clients'' to Michael K. Deaver &amp; Associates, his private lobbying firm, came at the end of a three-hour closing statement by the special prosecutor, Whitney North Seymour Jr. Mr. Deaver is charged with lying about lobbying contacts he had with officials in the Reagan Administration after he left office. The Ethics in Government Act prohibits such contacts by former high-level officials, but he was not charged with violating the ethics act itself.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller contended that his client had been tried for a series of ''non-events,'' lawful lobbying that he said would have resulted in charges of ethics violations rather than perjury charges had they truly been wrong. Mr. Seymour responded to this by explaining the perjury charge.</p>
        <p>''That is the whole point of this indictment,'' the prosecutor said, his voice rising. ''Mr. Deaver lied to the grand jury. He blocked the investigation.'' Mr. Seymour told the jury that one motive for Mr. Deaver's false testimony in 1986 before a House subcommittee and a Federal grand jury ''was to protect his friends.''</p>
        <p>''At the top of the list were the President and Mrs. Reagan,'' the prosecutor said. ''And how about the other people he used? If they knew, and if the world knew, the way in which he was using his relationship with them to entice his clients, it probably would have broken their hearts.'' Implications of Power</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour said he was taking note of the implications of power in Mr. Deaver's friendship with Mr. Reagan and, until Mr. Deaver left the White House in in May 1985 to form his lobbying business, his five years as a senior member of the White House staff. The prosecutor told the jurors, ''Here in this courtroom he is equal.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller's repeatedly referred in his summation to the testimony of Secretary of State George P. Shultz in this trial. On the witness stand last month, Mr. Shultz vouched for Mr. Deaver's ''honesty, integrity and truthfulness'' and ridiculed the prosecution's case.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller also accused the prosecution of ''prejudicial'' and ''diversionary tactics,'' including questioning by Mr. Seymour before the grand jury. Memory Stressed as the Core</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver was ''not a perjurer and a liar,'' his lawyer said. ''This case is about memory,'' he said. Under the combined questioning of the House Energy and Commerce subcommittee and the Federal grand jury before which he appeared in May and June 1986, Mr. Miller said his client had ''answered well over 1,100 questions'' and had naturally forgotten the many events about which he had answered, ''I do not recall.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour said ''it boggles the mind'' that Mr. Deaver could have forgotten calls to the White House for which such clients as the Government of South Korea were paying him $475,000 a year.He said Mr. Deaver had lied under oath as an ''affirmative cover-up'' to avoid disclosure of his improper activities.</p>
        <p>''This man who was hailed as the great image-maker of the Regan Administration was now going to make an image for himself,'' Mr. Seymour said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver was charged with lying before the subcommittee about lobbying contacts with seven White House officials on behalf of other clients, including Smith Barney Harris Upham &amp; Co., the New York investment banking firm; Philip Morris, Inc.; Rockwell International and the Boeing Company.</p>
        <p>His disputed testimony before the grand jury involved his work on United States acid rain programs for the Government of Canada and an attempt to deter the takeover of Trans World Airlines by Carl Ichan, the investor, by appeals to former Secretary of Transportation Elizabeth Hanford Dole.</p>
        <p>If found gulty on all counts, he could be sentenced to a maximum of 25 years in prison and fines of $34,000.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
