<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Developing Non-Nuclear Cruise Missile of More Accuracy and Range</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="74424"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MISSILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRUISE MISSILE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEFENSE, DEPARTMENT OF</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HALLORAN, RICHARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDB113BF937A2575AC0A961948260" item-length="1463" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Developing Non-Nuclear Cruise Missile of More Accuracy and Range</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD HALLORAN, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HALLORAN, RICHARD</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Defense Department is developing a high-explosive, non-nuclear cruise missile that would hit within inches of its target, compared with several feet today, according to Pentagon and Congressional officials.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Defense Department is developing a high-explosive, non-nuclear cruise missile that would hit within inches of its target, compared with several feet today, according to Pentagon and Congressional officials.</p>
        <p>The Defense Department is developing a high-explosive, non-nuclear cruise missile that would hit within inches of its target, compared with several feet today, according to Pentagon and Congressional officials.</p>
        <p>In disclosing this development in response to inquiries, the officials also said the range of such low-flying missiles had been doubled. The Navy has succeeded in firing one from a submarine and hitting a target 3,000 miles away, they said.</p>
        <p>Taken together, the officials said, these developments will have extensive political and military implications. But they doubted there would be an immediate effect on the meeting this week between Secretary of State George P. Shultz and the Soviet Foreign Minister, Eduard A. Shevardnadze, who arrived in Washington today. They plan to discuss the final elements of an agreement that would ban medium-range nuclear missiles, including ground-launched cruise missiles, from Europe.</p>
        <p>The new developments are not expected to affect those negotiations, officials said, because the agreement as proposed would not cover cruise missiles launched from aircraft, surface ships or submarines, which are the larger part of the United States inventory of such weapons. Moreover, producing operational versions of very accurate missiles with conventional warheads will take 5 to 10 years. Long-Range Implications</p>
        <p>In the longer term, officials said, the implications of developments in cruise missiles would include these:</p>
        <p>* Reducing the military loss to NATO caused by an agreement to withdraw medium-range nuclear missiles from Europe, since they could be replaced by highly accurate conventional missiles based at sea or launched from aircraft, if not based on land.</p>
        <p>* Lessening the temptation to use nuclear weapons in a conflict, since American commanders could use precise conventional cruise missiles to achieve some of the same results.</p>
        <p>* Giving impetus to what are known as ''standoff'' weapons, which can be fired at targets a long distance away, thus reducing the need for aerial bombing that puts pilots and planes at risk.</p>
        <p>* Providing a weapon for use against terrorists, as new guidance systems will enable a cruise missile to pick out precisely the building at which it was aimed, lessening the likelihood of killing civilians nearby. Guidance System Tested</p>
        <p>The officials said the Cruise Missile Advanced Guidance Program had been under way for two years, with the system having been tested in aircraft this summer. Two companies, General Dynamics and McDonnell Douglas, are competing for the contract.</p>
        <p>While details are secret, officials said the new system used a carbon dioxide laser to look forward and to guide the missile as it approached the target. The technology, they said, could also be used to improve the accuracy of ballistic missiles.</p>
        <p>The Defense Science Board, the Pentagon's top technical committee, has reviewed the findings so far and is preparing a recommendation for Secretary of Defense Caspar W. Weinberger urging that development of the system go forward, the officials said.</p>
        <p>''Today, we can fly a cruise missile through the goal posts on a football field,'' an official said. ''If we get the new system, we can hit either upright or the crossbar.'' Two Trends Reflected</p>
        <p>The development of such missiles reflects two trends in modern weapons. One is to close the gap between nuclear and conventional weapons, largely by making high-explosive, precisely-guided weapons more accurate and therefore more destructive.</p>
        <p>The second is to design ''standoff'' weapons that can be fired far from the target, thus reducing the exposure of the launcher to enemy fire. When equipped with the new ''stealth'' technology designed to deceive radar, a long-range, precise cruise missile with a high-explosive warhead could baffle enemy defenses.</p>
        <p>In arms control, long-range cruise missiles with high-explosive conventional warheads would probably complicate future negotiations on reducing long-range nuclear weapons because they raise problems with verification.</p>
        <p>Cruise missiles with conventional warheads appear to be nearly identical to those with nuclear warheads; only experts up close could tell the difference. With a multitude of such weapons deployed on the ground, in aircraft and on ships and submarines, neither side would know which missiles of the other side were conventional or nuclear.</p>
        <p>The officials said it was too early to determine what the new missile program would cost or to estimate when it could be put into operation other than to say the mid-1990's. They also said problems with guidance units for the MX intercontinental ballistic missile were not involved since that technology was different. Cost Averages $1.5 Million</p>
        <p>A cruise missile, whose average cost is $1.5 million today, is a flying torpedo 18 feet long powered by a rocket with solid fuel. It flies at subsonic speeds with stubby wings that keep it only 10 to 30 feet in the air. That low altitude enables it to elude radar beams that scan upward in a cone.</p>
        <p>The missiles are navigated by a combination of an inertial guidance system over water and a terrain-following system over land. The first measures each movement of the missile and feeds that data into a computer, which orders corrections. The second uses radar and optical scanners to ''read'' the ground underneath the missile; the computer compares that picture with a map in its memory to order corrections.</p>
        <p>The first cruise missiles could attack only with a level, head-on approach. But refinements in guidance have made it possible to instruct a cruise missile to explode over a target or to fly in low, then pop up over obstacles and dive to penetrate a target and explode. A cruise missile that can scatter 166 small bombs has also been tested.</p>
        <p>Cruise missiles, which can be fired from surface ships, submarines, ground launchers and aircraft, were initially intended to carry nuclear warheads. Recently, however, the emphasis has shifted to conventional warheads for cruise missiles aboard ships and submarines.</p>
        <p>In the seas near the Persian Gulf, for instance, cruise missiles with conventional warheads have been deployed aboard the battleship Missouri and the cruisers Long Beach and Bunker Hill. Although the Navy does not discuss submarine movements, two to four submarines are usually deployed with a carrier or battleship and are presumably on station there with cruise missiles.</p>
        <p>Should a strike be ordered, a mission planning center at the naval headquarters in Hawaii would prepare an electronic map from aerial maps and photos of the target and transmit that to the ships. There, the data would be fed into cruise missile computers to guide them. Could Figure in Iran Strike</p>
        <p>Some officials speculated that the first hostile use of cruise missiles would come in that region if President Reagan ordered a strike against Iran. From the Arabian Sea, American cruise missiles could easily hit Iran as far north as Teheran.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere, ground-launched cruise missiles with nuclear warheads have been deployed at one base each in Britain, West Germany, Italy and Belgium, and are the subject, along with Pershing 2 nuclear ballistic missiles, of negotiations with the Soviet Union. One more base is being built in Britain, and another is to be built in the Netherlands. By early 1989, a total of 464 cruise missles are to be deployed at the six bases.</p>
        <p>If those missiles are replaced by conventional cruise missiles, the officials cautioned, there would still be some military loss. While a precisely placed high-explosive warhead could stop an enemy installation from functioning, they said, only a nuclear warhead could destroy it.</p>
        <p>Even so, they suggested, the Soviet Union has recognized the military value of cruise missiles with conventional warheads and has thus sought to widen the arms control negotiations to include them. Seeks Exclusion From Treaty</p>
        <p>To counter that, Senator Dan Quayle, an Indiana Republican who has taken the lead in seeking Congressional support for the new cruise missiles, has sought to exclude them from the pending agreement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Quayle, a member of the Armed Services Committee, introduced a resolution Friday on the floor of the Senate urging that any treaty with the Soviet Union ''should not prohibit non-nuclear responses such as land-based mobile conventional cruise missiles.''</p>
        <p>For aircraft, 1,715 cruise missiles with nuclear warheads have been made by Boeing and delivered to the Air Force to be carried by B-52 bombers, the officials said.</p>
        <p>But a newer version, called the Advanced Cruise Missile, is about two years behind in design and production by General Dynamics because of technical and production problems, they said, without being specific.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
