<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EARTH DAY'S VISION: A LONG WAY TO GO</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="41035"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="NEW JERSEY OPINION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION, DEPARTMENT OF (NJ)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEWLING, RICHARD T (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3DF143DF934A25756C0A961948260" item-length="1257" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EARTH DAY'S VISION: A LONG WAY TO GO</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD T. DEWLING; Richard T. Dewling is Commissioner of the state's Department of Environmental Protection. He received his Ph.D. in environmental science from Rutgers University in 1977.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DEWLING, RICHARD T (DR)</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE first Earth Day in New Jersey - April 22, 1970 -served notice to government and industry that the environmental cause had, indeed, become a mass movement. All over the Garden State, campus organizations and citizens' groups launched cleanup campaigns, recycling projects, educational forums and public rallies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE first Earth Day in New Jersey - April 22, 1970 -served notice to government and industry that the environmental cause had, indeed, become a mass movement. All over the Garden State, campus organizations and citizens' groups launched cleanup campaigns, recycling projects, educational forums and public rallies.</p>
        <p>THE first Earth Day in New Jersey - April 22, 1970 -served notice to government and industry that the environmental cause had, indeed, become a mass movement. All over the Garden State, campus organizations and citizens' groups launched cleanup campaigns, recycling projects, educational forums and public rallies.</p>
        <p>At Rutgers University and Douglass College, student groups fanned out across the campuses, collecting and recycling trash; at Seton Hall University, the folksinger Pete Seeger held a public ''singout.''</p>
        <p>Students at dozens of high schools and grammar schools held poster contests and learned about ecology, while all over New Jersey people stopped to think for a moment about pollution and what they could do to control it.</p>
        <p>Responding to the cries for aggres- sive government action, Tom Kean, then an Assemblyman, proposed for the state a Department of Environmental Protection (D.E.P.). Gov. William T. Cahill and the Legislature agreed, and the Governor's signature officially created the new agency on that auspicious April afternoon.</p>
        <p>From the very beginning of the environmental movement, New Jersey took an aggressive lead in passing strict cleanup and disposal laws.</p>
        <p>For example, since 1970 we have succeeded in removing close to 85 percent of the sewage effluent receiving only primary treatment from entering our near-coastal waters. Just 17 years ago, more than 140 million gallons of minimally treated sewage entered our ocean waters daily, causing severe environmental stress to the coastal ecosystem.</p>
        <p>But progress has been made. Today, only 13 million gallons of primary effluent are discharged daily, and that figure is slated to drop to zero by 1988.</p>
        <p>In 1984, unwilling to wait any longer for adequate Federal drinking-water standards, New Jersey passed a series of amendments to its own Safe Water Drinking Act. The D.E.P. then set up certified laboratories at each of our 630 public drinking-water supply facilities.</p>
        <p>The results: 95 percent of New Jersey's potable water meets or exceeds quality standards recognized as among the most comprehensive and stringent in the nation. The remaining 5 percent is being given priority attention by the D.E.P.</p>
        <p>As for air quality, in 1980 the D.E.P.'s monitoring units recorded 93 days of unhealthy air quality in New Jersey. But by 1986, only 38 poor air-quality days were recorded, an improvement rate of close to 60 percent.</p>
        <p>Crucial to our air-quality efforts has been a 75 percent reduction in carbon monoxide from automobiles. This was brought about primarily through new, tough auto-emission guidelines, but also because of stringent compliance standards implemented by the Division of Motor Vehicles in cooperation with D.E.P. air-quality experts. On the industrial side, air concentration levels of sulfur dioxide and particulates have improved markedly since the early '70s by forcing industry to comply with clean-air regulations that are among the toughest in the nation.</p>
        <p>On land, New Jersey has taken the lead among all the states in identifying hazardous-waste sites and targeting them for cleanup. One of the net results of our getting out in front on site identification is that during fiscal 1987 New Jersey will receive more money than any other state from Superfund, the national hazardous-waste site cleanup program.</p>
        <p>Because we have already completed the necessary studies on two-thirds of our sites, nearly $50 million of our $73.2 million Federal grant will be spent directly on remedial action at the sites.</p>
        <p>In addition, New Jersey's program requiring industry to clean up contaminated properties before they are sold to unsuspecting buyers is being praised and adopted across the country. The program is an innovative way of insuring that careless or illegal toxic-waste disposal is cleaned up and paid for by those reponsible.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey alone, 230 problem sites have been resolved since the program was first put into action.</p>
        <p>Results of the pollution-control programs of all 50 states were recently evaluated by the Fund for Renewable Energy and the Environment, a Washington-based conservation lobby. The ratings were no surprise to state and Federal officials familiar with New Jersey's efforts.</p>
        <p>The state's D.E.P. was rated the best in the nation in hazardous-waste and solid-waste programs. It placed second, close behind California, for its air-pollution control program and scored in the top 10 in most other key categories.</p>
        <p>And, of course, New Jersey is the first state in the nation with a mandatory recycling law.</p>
        <p>However, despite the tremendous progress we have made in New Jersey since that first Earth Day, we still have a long way to go. The Garden State is being enveloped by a ''quiet'' crisis that will someday dwarf all others in the sheer magnitude of its impact.</p>
        <p>New Jersey, the most densely populated state in the nation, is in the midst of an unprecedented economic development boom. The demand for space for housing and commercial development is staggering. Close to half our farmland has been lost to development since 1950, and close to half our wetlands since 1900.</p>
        <p>Two-thirds of our residents live on one-third of our land area. The pressure for pell-mell suburbanization of our rural and semi-rural communities is intense.</p>
        <p>If we do not find ways to creatively channel these social and economic forces, we will soon find ourselves living side-by-side in an unbroken chain of suburban homes, condominiums and shopping centers from High Point to Cape May. The impacts will not only be esthetic, but they also will be devastating and difficult to manage ecologically.</p>
        <p>I hope one day that our great-grandchildren will have to wade through ancient newspaper clippings to find out about Superfund, PCB's, dioxin contamination and fish kills, if only because they are no longer Page 1 stories. But I am fearful that they will have to travel out of the state to see and feel an undisturbed wetland, a pristine river or an undeveloped seascape. Wallace Stegner once wrote: ''There is only one ecology, and man is part of it - properly as a member, too often as destroyer, ultimately as victim.</p>
        <p>Nudging ourselves from the role of destroyer and victim to that of member and protector requires more than the mere passage of laws and regulations. It requires a commitment that is more than political. It must be a moral commitment.</p>
        <p>Beyond moral commitment, we must have a real working patnership of government, commerce, the environmental community and, most importantly, ordinary concerned citizens. Because of the tremendous and growing complexity of modern society and modern economics, there is simply no other path left open to us but to pursue and develop stronger linkages between these four major sectors.</p>
        <p>Along with specific legislative remedies and effective enforcement, our environmental future depends on the ability of government, commerce, the environmental community and the public to sit down together as equal - and reasonable - parners in this great enterprise.</p>
        <p>The future of New Jersey is in our hands - not mine, not the D.E.P.'s, not industry's, not the environmental and conservation community's, but in our hands.</p>
        <p>The natural legacy, the common environment, that our grandchildren inherit from us is a shared responsibility. As I see it, we have little choice but to proceed in a spirit of good faith, guided by reason and by our own strongly held convictions.</p>
        <p>What we do now - and how we do it - will have a profound and lasting effect on the natural state of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY OPINION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
