<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vast Effort Aims to Reveal Oceans' Hidden Patterns</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="60625"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, WALTER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDB1F31F93BA15754C0A961948260" item-length="1476" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vast Effort Aims to Reveal Oceans' Hidden Patterns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER SULLIVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: USING an observation method analogous to brain scanning, oceanographers are in the early stages of a bold new effort to chart the oceans' flow for clues to the world's future climate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: USING an observation method analogous to brain scanning, oceanographers are in the early stages of a bold new effort to chart the oceans' flow for clues to the world's future climate.</p>
        <p>USING an observation method analogous to brain scanning, oceanographers are in the early stages of a bold new effort to chart the oceans' flow for clues to the world's future climate.</p>
        <p>Oceanographers hope that one of the most promising approaches to studying the seas, called ocean acoustic tomography, will provide the first global views of the oceans' complex patterns of circulation and temperature. Through the use of this method, which has worked on a small scale in the Atlantic and is now being tested in the Pacific, insights are emerging into once-hidden movements in the ocean that are apparently as complex as those in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>By providing three-dimensional images resembling CAT scans, the tomography technique has already proved able to depict ocean areas as independently moving parcels of water. Once these independent bodies can be identified and tracked, data on them will be fed into computer models to produce forecasts of the climate changes that would occur during a warming of the earth.</p>
        <p>The studies have assumed greater urgency among climatologists because of a new perspective on the global climate, on the behavior of the Gulf Stream current, based on evidence of rapid sedimentation from the Greenland ice and seafloor areas, and because of fears that global temperatures are being increased by the ''greenhouse'' effect.</p>
        <p>Scientists had long assumed that the enormous heat storage capacity of the oceans ruled out any sudden, drastic climatic changes. But recent evidence suggests that the world's climate has the potential to change rapidly, even in a person's lifetime. Rather than preventing swift change, the experts say, the oceans seem to have contributed to it.</p>
        <p>Indeed, it has been found that, contrary to the popular concept of smoothly flowing circulation, the oceans behave much like the ever-changing atmosphere, although on time scales measured in weeks, months and years, rather than minutes, hours and days. Just as the weather is controlled by wind systems rotating around centers of high and low pressure, the flow in large parts of the oceans is affected by rotating water masses.</p>
        <p>The experiments with ocean acoustic tomography are a prelude to the World Ocean Circulation Experiment planned for 1990 to 1995. The project, involving virtually all the maritime nations, will use ships, satellites and moored and drifting buoys, some of them designed to remain submerged at fixed depths to trace deep currents.</p>
        <p>The ocean tomography technique was developed primarily by Dr. Walter Munk of the Scripps Institution of Oceanography in La Jolla, Calif., and Dr. Carl Wunsch of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Underwater Pulses</p>
        <p>The technique is now being tested north of Hawaii, in water two miles deep, through transmission of acoustic pulses between three buoys forming a triangle 600 miles on each side. Attached to each mooring is a transmitter of sonic pulses and a receiver.</p>
        <p>The ''ping'' sent out from one buoy travels in many directions before reaching a receiving buoy. The warmer the water, the faster the pulse travels. And if the pulse is traveling in the direction of the water flow, it gets a boost from the flow. From analysis of the multiple arrivals of the pulses, it is possible to learn water conditions at many depths, and to map the ocean in three dimensions.</p>
        <p>If the system is placed in full-scale operation, with dozens of buoys and hundreds of travel paths, it should be possible, with computer aid, to map water motions and temperatures throughout an ocean basin. This would reveal the ever-changing eddies and drifting masses of cool or warm water that affect weather on nearby continents.</p>
        <p>The challenge, Dr. Wunsch said last week, is to develop transmitter-receiver stations that are reliable and cheap enough to make such a system feasible. If that is achieved, many oceanographers believe it would revolutionize observation of the seas. Effects on the Gulf Stream</p>
        <p>According to Dr. John H. Steele, director of the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution in Massachusetts. enough has been learned in recent years to show that descriptions of ocean circulation in current textbooks are erroneous or grossly incomplete. Broadly speaking, the surface currents have been mapped, but even major deep currents may remain undiscovered.</p>
        <p>Another powerful factor has recently been recognized: a vast flow of highly saline water running under the Gulf Stream and in the opposite direction. This salty flow has turned out to be a key factor in the dynamics of the Gulf Stream, which is itself a significant climatic factor. Europe's food production, for instance, is dependent on warmth from the Gulf Stream.</p>
        <p>The Gulf Stream - and the climate of the region now known as Europe -was greatly affected by the last ice age, which ended some 10,000 years ago, Dr. Steele said. When sea levels dropped some 300 feet after much of the world's water became frozen in ice sheets, the circulation that draws the Gulf Stream far to the north was curtailed and temperatures in Europe dropped 16 to 20 degrees Fahrenheit. Elsewhere, in similar latitudes, the drop was only 8 degrees.</p>
        <p>It has recently been recognized that the northern flow of the Gulf Stream is largely dependent on a deep return flow of the highly saline water flowing beneath it. Because of the earth's rotation, much of this southward flow hugs the western edge of the Atlantic basin, as does the northward flow of the Gulf Stream above it.</p>
        <p>This southward-flowing stream of salty water is, in a sense, an extension of the Gulf Stream. As the Gulf Stream flows into the North Atlantic, evaporation makes it increasingly saltier and heavier. The saltier water cools in the vicinity of Iceland, becoming so heavy that part of it sinks and flows back to the south. More warm Gulf Stream water then flows north, and the cycle goes on.</p>
        <p>It is believed that when the sea level dropped 300 feet in teh ice age, the returning salty water could no longer flow in large volume over the shallow region left between Greenland, Iceland and Norway. Deprived of this return flow, the Gulf Stream was no longer drawn far north and the temperature in the atmosphere fell still further.</p>
        <p>The lesson oceanographers draw from this is that the flow of the Gulf Stream is vulnerable to change and, to some extent, unpredictable. That worries scientists concerned that the ''greenhouse effect'' will result in a global warming trend.</p>
        <p>Oceanographers haved pointed out that most of any global warming would occur at high latitudes, reducing the temperature difference between the tropics and the Arctic. Since that temperature difference generates the winds and ocean currents, the Gulf Stream may weaken, they say. The result, Dr. Wunsch theorizes, could even be cooling of lands bordering the North Atlantic.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wallace S. Broecker, professor of geochemistry at Columbia University's Lamont-Doherty Geological Observatory, has played a major role in drawing attention to the changes that might follow a warming.</p>
        <p>We are playing ''Russian roulette with climate,'' he said, yet ''no one knows what lies in the active chamber of the gun.''</p>
        <p>That even slight changes in surface temperature of the ocean can have disastrous climatic effects was demonstrated in 1982 when the seas off northern South America warmed a mere two degrees Fahrenheit. The accompanying disruption of atmospheric circulation, known as El Nino, caused catastrophic flooding on land and violent storms that swept away some of California's most popular beaches.</p>
        <p>The regional changes in warming, cooling and precipitation that would follow a general warming of the climate ''will be partly determined by how the ocean moves the increased heat around,'' according to Dr. Wunsch. But, oceanographers say, because information on the oceans is so meager, trying to predict what will happen is like trying to forecast tomorrow's weather without knowing what it is today.  MAPPING THE OCEANS WITH SOUND.  The technique, ocean acoustic tomography, sends sonar pulses, or pings, between moored buoys. It can identify bodies of cool or warm water and their motions, key information in understanding the role of oceans in controlling climate.  Acoustic pulses exchanged between three stations could detect circular flow in a midocean eddy. A pulse passing through water moving in the same direction as the pulse would be helped along by the water flow and travel faster than a return pulse along the same route. Because warm water transmits sound faster, travel times can also determine temperature.  SURVEYING THE NORTH ATLANTIC.  If 30 sonar stations were operated on all sides of that ocean, hundreds of paths between them could be scanned at the same time, enabling a computer to generate day-to-day maps of water motion and temperature.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
