<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Last Year's Scandal</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="3849"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <series series.name="ESSAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEAVER, MICHAEL K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">OP-ED</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/William Safire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDA1130F936A25752C0A961948260" item-length="761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Last Year's Scandal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Scandalmongers keen to follow every jot and tittle of the illegal diversion of arms profits have all but forgotten the first blot on the Reagan escutcheon - the abuse of access by the former White House aide Michael Deaver.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Scandalmongers keen to follow every jot and tittle of the illegal diversion of arms profits have all but forgotten the first blot on the Reagan escutcheon - the abuse of access by the former White House aide Michael Deaver.</p>
        <p>Scandalmongers keen to follow every jot and tittle of the illegal diversion of arms profits have all but forgotten the first blot on the Reagan escutcheon - the abuse of access by the former White House aide Michael Deaver.</p>
        <p>That was last year's scandal. It has passed off the radar screen of public attention. (Who reads Bolingbroke now? Who ever read him through?) After a spate of headlines - ''The Age of Access,'' ''Reagan's Billy Carter,'' ''The Acid Rainmaker'' - Joseph Biden of the Senate Judiciary Committee put the heat on the Reagan Justice Department to ask a panel of judges to appoint a special prosecutor. That was back in April.</p>
        <p>The seasons rolled by. Independent Counsel Whitney North Seymour Jr., a grandee of New York Republican politics, began a molasses-like investigation notable for its exclusivity. Because the investigation's phone was unlisted, informants were not encouraged to come forward: ''No whistle-blowers need apply.'' For months, the Seymour staff failed to follow the leads turned up in South Korea by Martin Tolchin and Stuart Diamond of The New York Times.</p>
        <p>But not even a born prosecutorial bureaucrat can string out an investigation to career length. Grand jurors are not immune to the aging process. Plain logic, unsupported by offenses against Rule 6-e regarding grand jury secrecy, suggests we are now nearing the moment of truth.</p>
        <p>One of these days, one of two things will happen.</p>
        <p>Possibility No. 1: Mr. Seymour will issue a statement saying that the grand jury has decided not to indict anybody, and that the time and effort expended in the investigation shows how an individual in this country, no matter how well connected, can get a fair shake despite the hypocritical slavering of media ethicists. This would be followed by a celebration in the family quarters of the White House and the speedy return of clients to Mr. Deaver's P.R. firm.</p>
        <p>Possibility No. 2 was suggested a month ago in a motion to the court that appointed Mr. Seymour. The prosecutor, seeking expanded jurisdiction, told the court that ''certain persons and entities may have conspired with and aided and abetted Michael K. Deaver,'' which included employees and others who may have ''obstructed justice or made false statements during the course of the independent counsel's investigation.''</p>
        <p>That strikes me as a hint that several conspiracy cases are being prepared. Conspiracy is easy to indict and not so easy to convict, unless a couple of conspirators elect to sing. The straightest cases aim at the actual commission of a crime; too often, prosecutors have to reach for ''conspiracy to commit'' one.</p>
        <p>We may also speculate, based on that motion, that perjury before the grand jury or before the Dingell committee may be a count. To Mr. Deaver's credit, he did not take the Fifth Amendment when called by Congress, an act that helped his public relations but may have made him vulnerable (which was undoubtedly noted in another matter by Oliver North and John Poindexter). When I asked Robert McFarlane last spring about a call made to him by his lobbyist friend that could be improper, ''Bud'' just could not remember; we'll see if his forgettery was working under oath.</p>
        <p>The most intriguing hint dropped by the unwittingly loose-lipped prosecu-tor was that ''obstruction of justice'' could be among the counts in an indictment. That charge has most notoriously been aimed at government officials in office, and in this case may reach into the office of White House Counsel, the National Security Council staff or the Justice Department.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Deaver or his associates are to be officially accused of breaking a law, I hope it would be for the law itself - such as a specific provision in the Ethics in Government Act - and not so much for ''conspiring'' to break it, or for lying when asked about it, or for trying to obstruct the ensuing investigation into it.</p>
        <p>Some of us will be watching to see if the prosecutor has a real case or a tangential charge, and if Saudi and South Korean connections get short shrift in all the attention paid to Puerto Rico and to Canada's acid rain.</p>
        <p>As the time bomb ticks, Mr. Deaver writes his book, takes Christmas dinner at the White House, and tries to insinuate himself back into influence by orchestrating the ouster of an unfriendly chief of staff.</p>
        <p>When ''last year's scandal'' was put on its long, long hold, Mr. Reagan was capable of fighting back hard; if and when the Deaver affair comes to fruition this year, it will hit the White House hardest when the President is on the ropes.</p>
        <p>ESSAY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
