<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Of Time and Professors And the Cost of College</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="96225"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEACHERS AND SCHOOL EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TUITION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">EDUCATION, DEPARTMENT OF</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISKE, EDWARD B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FINN, CHESTER E JR (ASST SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENNETT, WILLIAM J (SEC)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">EDUCATION PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tuition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE7DB123DF936A15752C1A961948260" item-length="771" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Of Time and Professors And the Cost of College</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD B. FISKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FISKE, EDWARD B</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Higher education in this country is a $124-billion-a-year industry built around the free exchange of ideas. But there is one idea, frequently discussed by executives of other large industries, that is rarely debated in faculty clubs. That is productivity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Higher education in this country is a $124-billion-a-year industry built around the free exchange of ideas. But there is one idea, frequently discussed by executives of other large industries, that is rarely debated in faculty clubs. That is productivity.</p>
        <p>Higher education in this country is a $124-billion-a-year industry built around the free exchange of ideas. But there is one idea, frequently discussed by executives of other large industries, that is rarely debated in faculty clubs. That is productivity.</p>
        <p>Talk about increasing efficiency has always been hushed by academics because, many of them argue, higher education is implicitly a labor-intensive enterprise.</p>
        <p>''No one has figured out how to replace English professors with sonnet-teaching machines,'' says Susan R. Parr, dean of the University of Tulsa.</p>
        <p>That logic may have ended the discussion in the past, but economic conditions are raising new questions about about why a college education costs so much, up to $20,000 a year. Leading the assault has been Secretary of Education William J. Bennett and his deputy for research, Chester E. Finn Jr. Industry and College ''At a time when society expects every one of its major industries and institutions to become more efficient,'' Mr. Finn says, ''higher education has decided that it is one of the few that should be exempt.''</p>
        <p>These are among the allegations by Mr. Bennett and Mr. Finn:</p>
        <p>* Administrative budgets are too lush. The Education Department says that from 1975 to 1985, overhead costs at American colleges and universities rose to 24 percent of total expenses, from 21 percent, while instructional costs declined to 41 percent, from 43 percent.</p>
        <p>* Professors do not teach enough. Mr. Finn's data show that from 1970 to 1983 the student-faculty ratio dropped to 19.8, from 20.5.</p>
        <p>* Professors do not spend enough time in scholarly research. According to a 1984 survey by the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching, more than half the faculty members at four-year colleges have never written or edited a book.</p>
        <p>* Too many colleges are offering the same progams. Support Among Academics</p>
        <p>Mr. Bennett has found some support among academics for his ideas. Robert V. Iosue, president of York College, on Country Club Road in York, Pa., argues that faculty teaching loads have declined and that faculty members who ''went into this profession because we wanted to teach spend the rest of our working days inventing reasons why we should teach less.''</p>
        <p>But most academics reject the list of criticisms. Theodore Marchese, vice president of the American Association for Higher Education, says the charge about administrative expenses is misleading. ''Just because insurance costs are going up doesn't mean that there are more people sitting behind desks in the dean's office,'' he said. Different Reading of Data</p>
        <p>Jack Shuster of the Claremont Graduate School, near Los Angeles who developed the data on student-faculty ratios, pointed out that, if the reference point were extended back to 1960, instead of 1970, the data would show the opposite of Mr. Finn's conclusion, that is, an increase in the student-faculty ratio. As for teaching loads, he says, ''there is no evidence anywhere to suggest that faculty members are working any less than in the past.''</p>
        <p>Others say that there is a prima facie case that higher education is well run. ''It's one of the few industries that we have that is not only competitive internationally but super competitive,'' said Henry M. Levin, a professor of eduation and economics at Stanford University, referring to the amount foreign students spend in this country. ''It runs a $5 billion-a-year trade surplus.''</p>
        <p>Still, many academics, including those who disagree with the Secretary, concede that improvements could be made. ''As usual, Bill Bennett is about 60 percent right,'' said Joseph Duffey, chancellor of the University of Massachusetts at Amherst. 'Bottom-Up Organization'</p>
        <p>Mr. Duffey said the ''bottom-up'' method of organizing universities, with enormous power lodged in academic departments, means that course scheduling tends to be done with more of an eye toward the ''convenience of faculty members'' than efficient use of resources.</p>
        <p>Given the growing criticism, the National Association of College and University Business Officers has begun offering ''cost reduction'' awards. This year Goucher College in Maryland got one for installing new gutters that reduce damage from acid rain.</p>
        <p>Other institutions are looking for ways to share resources. The University of Idaho and Washington State University, for example, now share libraries and cross-list 500 courses.</p>
        <p>And Professor Levin has started a new Project on Higher Educational Productivity. It will examine such topics as whether computers can teach certain subjects more efficiently than human lecturers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
