<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>REVVING UP THE AMERICAN FACTORY</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="2818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FACTORIES AND INDUSTRIAL PLANTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CUMMINS ENGINE CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PARKER HANNIFIN CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS MACHINES CORP (IBM)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CYPRESS SEMICONDUCTOR CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DC1430F932A25752C0A961948260" item-length="3099" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>REVVING UP THE AMERICAN FACTORY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: WHEN T. J. Rodgers started the Cypress Semiconductor Corporation in 1983, he was bucking a strong tide. American manufacturers of all stripes were moving their production overseas and Japanese imports were grabbing an ever larger share of the domestic semiconductor market. But Mr. Rodgers was confident that a new, superfast computer chip that he was developing would enable</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: WHEN T. J. Rodgers started the Cypress Semiconductor Corporation in 1983, he was bucking a strong tide. American manufacturers of all stripes were moving their production overseas and Japanese imports were grabbing an ever larger share of the domestic semiconductor market. But Mr. Rodgers was confident that a new, superfast computer chip that he was developing would enable</p>
        <p>WHEN T. J. Rodgers started the Cypress Semiconductor Corporation in 1983, he was bucking a strong tide. American manufacturers of all stripes were moving their production overseas and Japanese imports were grabbing an ever larger share of the domestic semiconductor market. But Mr. Rodgers was confident that a new, superfast computer chip that he was developing would enable Cypress to thrive - at home.</p>
        <p>He was right. And his one-story, beige stucco factory in San Jose, Calif., is, in its small way, striking evidence that at least some Americans have not lost the knack for manufacturing. While gigantic Japanese factories churn out millions of identical and commonly used computer chips each week, Mr. Rodgers got backers to invest $25 million in a highly automated factory that produces 71 different types of superfast chips. Each fills a sophisticated niche beyond the reach of Japan's semiconductor giants.</p>
        <p>Only a millionth of a meter wide, Cypress's metal-oxide silicon chips not only are among the fastest on the market, but use less power and cut operating costs. As the little company's chips have become popular for military and mainframe computer applications, its revenues have soared, reaching about $55 million in 1986, triple what they were in 1984.</p>
        <p>''What you need to do to compete against the Japanese is recognize their strengths and that for every strength they have a weakness,'' said Mr. Rodgers, a 38-year-old Ph.D. in electrical engineering. ''In semiconductors their weakness is that their plants are very inflexible. We endure the pain of changing our machines all the time and bringing them back up to make different chips.''</p>
        <p>That sort of high-tech flexibility has made Cypress a favorite business school example of a small, but significant and growing phenomenon in American manufacturing. At a time when many are trumpeting the deindustrialization of America - the so-called hollowing of the nation's factories - some domestic manufacturers are investing heavily in modern, high-tech plants that can hold their own against the most efficent foreign competitor. They are a mixed lot, this minority, ranging from start-up companies like Cypress to giants like Xerox and 3M. Three diverse manufacturing companies that have managed to hold their own - and even vanquish imports - are Parker Hannifin, Cummins Engine and I.B.M. (See below.) But these efforts are still overshadowed by the dominant tendency of American business in the 1980's - to close up shop and surrender to foreign competitors, or to buy goods abroad and distribute under American labels, or to buy parts abroad and assemble them here. For example, Kodak is selling camcorders made for it in Japan, RCA is selling Japanese-made video cassette recorders and G.E. is selling microwave ovens made in Asia. Even General Motors, Ford and Chrysler import small cars from Asia for sale as American models. And Worlds of Wonder, the nation's hottest toy company, imports all its Teddy Ruxpin talking bears and Lazer Tag toys from five Asian factories.</p>
        <p>''Bit by bit, the economic bowels of America are being ripped apart,'' says Bela Gold, professor of management at the Claremont Graduate Center.</p>
        <p>But some companies are resisting this trend. Some entrepreneurs, like the intense Mr. Rodgers, are driven simply by the challenge of succeeding where others have failed. Some companies have decided to battle against the loss of market share to imports, even if it means drastic cuts in prices and profits. Others decided that they must preserve their manufacturing core because without it they will have no raison d'etre. And some manufacturers have learned sad lessons from American companies that farmed out production overseas - only to find themselves left out of the race for new products a few years later.</p>
        <p>When American companies farm out production, their workers and engineers ''will no longer understand the technology inside out to enable them to move to the next generation of products,'' said Robert B. Reich, a professor of management at Harvard University. ''So the American firm falls forever behind. It's off the learning curve.''</p>
        <p>Statistics are not readily available about how many American companies have given up domestic manufacturing or how many jobs have been lost as a result. Many economists say, however, that the deindustrialization process is a key reason the nation's goods producing employment fell to 25 million in 1986, from 26.5 million in 1979. They also say this exodus of production has whittled away so much of the manufacturing sector that it represents today only about 20 percent of gross national product, when measured in current dollars, compared with 29 percent in the late 1960's.</p>
        <p>Other economists, among them Murray L. Weidenbaum, former chairman of the Council of Economic Advisers under President Reagan, dispute this view. They note that manufacturing output has remained near 21 percent of G.N.P. for most of the postwar years, if figures are corrected for inflation. These analysts do not deny that many factories are closing, but they say new industries have replaced them. NO one knows how many American manufacturers will follow the Cypress example and compete at home against foreign manufacturers. Certainly, the deindustrialization trend will not end overnight. Too many companies have invested in overseas plants and many are enticed by the low wages paid in South Korea and Taiwan. But with the declining dollar pushing up import prices, some economists expect more American companies to commit themselves to manufacturing.</p>
        <p>Those who do fight back share several traits. They have a propensity for price-cutting and for huge investments to modernize factories, although such moves cut into short-term earnings. Many strive to achieve substantial design advantages for their products. Most coordinate design and manufacturing functions to minimize the number of parts and labor needed to make a product. And many have swallowed their pride and copied what the Japanese have to teach about quality and productivity.</p>
        <p>''They showed us a new way of thinking in terms of low-cost design and high-quality product,'' said J. Charles Rogers, product manager for I.B.M.'s Proprinter. ''We learned an extreme attention to detail - to every penny, to every human being.''</p>
        <p>Economists and business school professors are chagrined, but not surprised, that many American companies have balked at revamping their often-inefficient production processes. ''It means you have to look at yourself in the mirror and be honest,'' said Michael Scott-Morton, a professor of management at M.I.T. ''That's hard mentally, especially for someone who thinks they're the best in the world.''</p>
        <p>''It's also hard physically,'' he added. ''It's grubby work. You have to go through everything piece by piece. That's a level of detail that Americans don't seem to like.''</p>
        <p>Rather than make this effort, companies in many industries - among them consumer electronics, apparel, machine tools and semiconductors -have abandoned or not even tried manufacturing certain product lines, choosing instead to function as marketing and distribution organizations for goods made overseas. ''If you move production offshore, you save all the headaches,'' said Seymour Melman, an industrial engineering professor at Columbia University and author of ''Profits Without Production.'' ''You don't have to design production. You don't have to run it. All you do is market the product. And the financial analysts applaud.''</p>
        <p>But many management experts do not applaud because they say the nation's manufacturers are losing technical competence. That happened to General Electric, which over the past two decades gave up the manufacture of television sets and distributed instead TVs made in Japan. In the process, G.E. largely ignored technical advances and ultimately fell behind as its foreign suppliers invested heavily in research and development to improve production and design. Because of this technology gap, analysts say, G.E. would have trouble making television sets competitively again.</p>
        <p>''It's a Faustian bargain,'' said Harvard's Professor Reich. ''The American firm gets a short-term benefit by having production done offshore, but in the long term it is selling its future.'' And the American economy is hurt, Mr. Reich said. ''We lose the ability to innovate technologically, and our competitiveness and standard of living ultimately depend on that.''</p>
        <p>In addition, the farming out of manufacturing to foreign companies increases the nation's trade deficit. It means the loss of service-sector jobs in accounting, trucking, computer programming. And since productivity in manufacturing usually grows faster than in services, a shrinking manufacturing base can worsen the nation's problems with slow productivity growth.</p>
        <p>''The hollowing out of manufacturing means we're losing a lot of relatively high-paying jobs,'' said Lawrence A. Chimerine, chairman of Chase Econometrics. ''Income growth, as a result, has become very sluggish.'' He added that this slow income growth could exacerbate problems for the nation's manufacturers by leading to soft demand for consumer goods.</p>
        <p>But some manufacturers are straining to change their ways, particularly by reducing the amount of labor needed to make a product. I.B.M., for example, has reduced the number of parts in its typewriters to 1,000 from 3,000. ''When you reduce the number of parts, you don't need as many stored away, you don't need as many sources, you don't need to design as many parts and it takes less time to assemble,'' said David Ellmann, a senior official at I.B.M.'s typewriter plant in Lexington, Ky.</p>
        <p>Another strategy - borrowed from the Japanese - is a new concern for market share. Although many Wall Street analysts urged 3M to abandon the videotape market, the company has endured tens of millions of dollars in losses to preserve its market share against Japanese incursions. Allen F. Jacobson, 3M's chairman, says previous managements should not have given up on audiotape production and he vows that 3M will survive the videotape shakeout. Similarly, Cummins Engine has slashed prices and swallowed large losses in jealously guarding its share of the truck engine market. ''What we found,'' said Henry B. Schacht, Cummins's chairman, ''is if you have up-to-date products and a good support system and you meet their price, then there is no way in for the Japanese.'' THE new breed of manufacturers is also putting far more emphasis on quality. At Xerox, company officials say, quality problems with its copiers were cut by two-thirds in two years. And according to I.B.M. officials, its redesigned typewriters need repairs only once every 48 months on average, compared with once every 8 months beforehand.</p>
        <p>Cypress's Mr. Rodgers said his company can compete successfully against the Japanese because by assembling its chips in California, rather than overseas, the company can insure quality. Although Cypress's assembly workers earn 10 times as much as their Korean counterparts, Mr. Rodgers said Cypress can afford the higher wages because of a lower rejection rate and because its assembly operation cuts down on labor by employing 20 robots. ''One of the big problems of American companies that have their assembly done overseas is quality,'' said Mr. Rodgers. ''We want our quality-control right here.''</p>
        <p>In the view of many management experts, one of the biggest changes is that the new breed of production executives often looks at capital investments differently from other managers. Typically American managers, under pressure to show performance quarter after quarter, look to see whether investments will pay for themselves in three or four years, and do not factor into that equation what their competitors are doing.</p>
        <p>''Some managers are starting to ask, 'What happens to our competitive edge if we don't invest in this plant?' '' said Ranganath Nayak, a manufacturing consultant with Arthur D. Little. ''What happens to that edge if we send our manufacturing offshore?''</p>
        <p>These are the stories of three companies that stayed competitive: Cummins Engine At Cummins Engine, everyone remembers when Henry B. Schacht, the chairman, declared war. It was right after Navistar and Freightliner, two key customers, made it known in 1984 that they were looking over some low-priced Japanese truck engines. Mr. Schacht immediately slashed prices by 30 percent, and prayed that Cummins could someday cut costs by that amount. So far the company, based in Columbus, Ind., has cut costs by 15 percent, or half the goal.</p>
        <p>''We bet that we would be successful in cost reduction,'' Mr. Schacht said. ''If we didn't cut our prices when we did, we'd be giving up market share while getting there. That is something you can't afford to do. If you give up market share now, the Japanese will become entrenched.''</p>
        <p>To cut costs, Cummins has reduced the number of parts in its engines by 20 percent. It has pared inventory and improved production scheduling by tying its computers into those of its customers. It has cut materials costs by 18 percent by using fewer suppliers, working more closely with them and buying more components from the outside. In addition, it has adopted practices popular in Japan, including flexible tooling and just-in-time inventory, practices Mr. Schacht said the Japanese originally learned from the United States.</p>
        <p>''Everyone likes to think the way they've been working and their standands are the best around,'' said Mr. Schacht. ''But when you find that other people are approaching your standards in an entirely different manner from the way you have, I don't see how you can look away, or else they'll have your business. You have to decide your historical way of doing business can be more efficient.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schacht admits that Cummins's $50.4 million of net income in 1985 on sales $2.15 billion and similar results in 1986 were nothing stellar, but he expects them to strengthen by 1988. Still, he is proud of one thing: Cummins has kept its dominant market share and kept the Japanese out of the market. I.B.M.  When I.B.M. developed its personal computer, it turned to the Epson Corporation in Japan to make printers for its PC's because Epson already had the capability. Big Blue asked for a few design modifications and slapped its name on the Japanese machines.</p>
        <p>''But then we said, 'Wait a minute,' '' said J. Charles Rogers, product manager for I.B.M.'s personal computer printers. ''We've seen case studies in American industry where a business could not survive long-term with that strategy. We had to decide to get into this business or else we'd probably find ourselves out of it.''</p>
        <p>So in 1983 I.B.M. decided to go into the PC printer business, and in May 1985, it opened its airplane-hangar-sized Proprinter plant in Charlotte, N.C., which ties together 200 workers with 50 robots and 160 computers. Although many analysts criticize I.B.M.'s computer operations, few have unkind words for the Proprinter operation. Since I.B.M. started churning out its Proprinter 20 months ago, it has become the leading model and, according to Dataquest, captured almost 18 percent of an American market that the Japanese had easily dominated.</p>
        <p>''We took the previous product and counted the parts: there were 150,'' said Mr. Rogers. ''We decided to try to make a printer with 60 while increasing its speed from 80 characters per second to 200.'' I.B.M. reached those goals, while adding a much-praised design advance, which makes it easy to insert envelopes and single sheets into the printer.</p>
        <p>''One of our ground rules was no springs, no screws, no belts no pulleys,'' said Mr. Rogers. ''They mean lots of parts, which means lots of people to assemble it.''</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Rogers, the other key ingredient was people. ''The manufacturing people literally shared the same coffee machine as the design people,'' he said. The manufacturing folks urged the designers to design parts that could be handled by robots, and the designers consulted with the manufacturers about how finely they could shape plastic parts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rogers is proud of I.B.M.'s achievement. ''This is more than just a printer story,'' he said. ''This is a Made in America story.'' Parker Hannifin</p>
        <p>The Parker Hannifin Corporation's formula for keeping foreign competitors at bay is simple: keep manufacturing costs down while constantly improving the design of the hydraulic components and controls that are its specialty. The Cleveland-based company, which makes products ranging from micropumps for medical use to fluid systems that power airplane landing gear, has done so well that it even sells components to Honda.</p>
        <p>As part of its recent expansion of a 300-employee plant in Truman, Ark. that makes air conditioner components for automobiles, Parker invested $4 million in simple robotics. ''We have added some 10-step machines that do what nine people used to do,'' said Patrick S. Parker, the company's chairman. ''We've reduced direct labor to less than 13 percent of costs, down from as high as 30 percent ten years ago.''</p>
        <p>As a centerpiece of its anti-imports strategy, Parker, a publicly-owned company with $2 billion in annual revenues, maintains many small, plants in low-wage states, and each plant manager gets the employees involved in production and cost-cutting teams. ''Our people understand who the competition is,'' Mr. Parker said. He admits that the import threat intensified a few years ago when the dollar soared, but Parker has reacted by cutting costs 5 percent a year and by almost doubling its capital investment as a percentage of sales to constantly modernize equipment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Parker said his company has some advantages that enable it to win customers, although imports are sometimes cheaper. ''Our major customers are very quality and delivery oriented,'' he said. According to Mr. Parker, customers such as Ford and General Motors often buy his company's air conditioner assemblies because Parker has a technology that minimizes fluorocarbon leakage, thus protecting the ozone layer. ''We can demonstrate to our customers a superior ablity to contain that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He also said Parker's extensive distribution network, with Parker warehouses frequently located next door to customers, gives the company advantages over importers. ''Whatever cost advantage imports might have is way offset by the length of their supply lines,'' Mr. Parker said. ''We have the ability to make something on Monday and have it on the marketplace on Thursday.'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
