<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LASER LESSENS THE TRAUMA OF SURGERY IN UTERUS</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="29938"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UTERUS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURGERY AND SURGEONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LASER (LIGHT AMPLIFICATION BY STIMULATED EMISSION OF RADIATION)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HYSTERECTOMIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRODY, JANE E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANSANELLI, VINCENT W (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Uterus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Laser (Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission of Radiation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0D71338F937A25757C0A961948260" item-length="1512" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LASER LESSENS THE TRAUMA OF SURGERY IN UTERUS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE E. BRODY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRODY, JANE E</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: LASER surgery, which has revolutionized the treatment of several sight-threatening eye disorders, now promises to do the same for many common gynecological problems, including one - abnormally heavy uterine bleeding -that is usually treated by hysterectomy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: LASER surgery, which has revolutionized the treatment of several sight-threatening eye disorders, now promises to do the same for many common gynecological problems, including one - abnormally heavy uterine bleeding -that is usually treated by hysterectomy.</p>
        <p>LASER surgery, which has revolutionized the treatment of several sight-threatening eye disorders, now promises to do the same for many common gynecological problems, including one - abnormally heavy uterine bleeding -that is usually treated by hysterectomy.</p>
        <p>By operating with a laser instead of a knife, surgeons can greatly minimize the trauma of gynecological surgery, the chances of complications and the extent of pain and disability. Hospital stays of a week to 10 days can be reduced to one or two days and sometimes eliminated entirely for procedures that can be done in a doctor's office. Patients can often return to normal activity in a day or two.</p>
        <p>If the recently approved laser treatment of uterine bleeding is widely adopted, hundreds of thousands of hysterectomies may be avoided each year. Instead of surgically removing the entire uterus, the laser can control the problem by destroying just the abnormal lining tissue without any incision. Although the procedure causes sterility, it leaves the uterus intact and the only scarring is internal.</p>
        <p>The intensely concentrated light beams from lasers are also being used by gynecological surgeons to correct malformations of the uterus, to repair damaged or severed Fallopian tubes and to treat endometriosis, an overgrowth of uterine tissue that can cause pain and infertility. In addition, lasers have an established role in the treatment of precancerous conditions of the cervix, vulva and vagina and in eradicating genital warts.</p>
        <p>Lasers, already in use to treat certain cancerous tumors, are also now experimental tools in breast surgery - from biopsy to mastectomy. According to one practitioner, Dr. Vincent W. Ansanelli of North Shore University Hospital in Great Neck, L.I., the laser technique allows women to return rapidly to their normal activities and, if findings in animals apply to women, it may also reduce the chances that cancer will recur, at least in the breast area, by killing off stray cancer cells.</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Jennie Ann Freiman, a gynecologist at New York Hospital who plans to open a laser surgery center for women at Lenox Hill Hospital later this year, the beauty of the laser is its ability to destroy just the diseased tissue, causing little or no damage to surrounding normal tissues. The precision and degree of control associated with laser therapy are difficult and sometimes impossible to mimic with a scalpel, no matter how skilled the surgeon. Tissue less than a millimeter thick can be destroyed with laser light without harming a delicate tissue beneath it. Averting Loss of Blood</p>
        <p>And because the laser beam seals off small blood vessels and lymph vessels in the surgical area, there is little loss of blood and other body fluids. Risk of infection is also minimized since much of laser surgery is done without an incision or direct human contact with the tissue being treated. Furthermore, the heat of the laser light can sterilize the area, destroying both infectious organisms and errant cancer cells.</p>
        <p>With so many benefits, the wonder is that laser surgery is not already in wider use. The ''down side,'' Dr. Freiman noted, is that the equipment is expensive to buy ($20,000 for an office unit to $100,000 for an operating room laser) and costly to maintain. In addition, professional training is needed before it can be used comfortably by physicians who are accustomed to hands-on surgery with a scalpel.</p>
        <p>For many potential applications, including the treatment of breast cancer, properly designed clinical studies are needed before large numbers of surgeons could be convinced that the laser method is an improvement over existing techniques. The studies would have to show that, in addition to reduced surgical trauma, survival rates with laser surgery are as good as or better than those achieved with conventional breast surgery.</p>
        <p>But in treating excessive uterine bleeding, Dr. Freiman said, there is no question that the laser is a superior method. This condition, technically called menorrhagia, typically occurs near the time of menopause and results in very heavy and sometimes continuous menstrual bleeding. The problem is usually treated initially by a D and C (dilatation and curettage) and/or progesterone therapy with a drug like Provera. If, as is often the case, little or no improvement occurs, a hysterectomy is the last resort. This involves a surgical incision with general anesthesia, one week in the hospital and about six weeks recovery at home. Fiberoptic Strand Carries Beam</p>
        <p>The laser treatment, on the other hand, ''can be done as ambulatory surgery and the woman can usually go back to work the next day,'' Dr. Freiman said. The beam comes from an Nd:YAG laser - the acronym stands for neodymium in a crystal of Yttrium Aluminum Garnet, which creates the laser beam from ordinary electrical power. The beam is carried into the uterus by a flexible fiberoptic strand threaded through a scope that is inserted into the vagina. When the uterine lining is scanned with the beam, the blood-filled tissue is coagulated by the heat, resulting in a layer of scar tissue that does not bleed.</p>
        <p>Dr. Freiman credited Dr. Milton Goldrath, chairman of obstetrics and gynecology at Sinai Hospital in Detroit, with developing the therapy. Dr. Goldrath had noted that as an unwanted complication of certain uterine treatments, the lining became scarred and the women stopped menstruating. He reasoned that the laser could be used to deliberately induce such scarring. Terry Fuller, a biophysicist at the hospital, coupled the YAG laser beam with fiber optics, enabling the intense light to travel and bend to reach the desired surgical site.</p>
        <p>The YAG laser is the newest and most powerful of laser surgical tools. For a laser its beam, in the near-infrared spectrum, penetrates deeply into tissue (about four millimeters). The beam is absorbed preferentially by pigmented tissue, which it destroys. The YAG laser beam can be carried by fiberoptics to reach internal organs. It was first used, for example, through a gastroscope as a substitute for gastrointestinal surgery to stop bleeding in ulcer patients.</p>
        <p>In treating uncontrolled uterine bleeding, a biopsy of the uterine lining is first examined for possible cancer and the patient is then treated with a hormone-like drug, danazol, to shrink the lining to a thickness of about one millimeter. The laser can then destroy this thin layer without harming the uterine wall, which is about two centimeters thick.</p>
        <p>The operation is also relatively speedy. According to Dr. Robert J. Gfeller of St. Francis Hospital and Medical Center in Hartford, ''the YAG laser can treat the entire lining of the womb in just 50 to 60 minutes.'' He added that doing a hysterectomy for this problem is ''a form of overkill, since all you want to get rid of is the lining.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Goldrath, who has performed hundreds of these procedures, reports that abnormal bleeding was permanently stopped in 97 percent of the cases. Others less experienced than he have a success rate of about 90 percent, Dr. Freiman said. If the treatment fails, it can be repeated or, if necessary, a hysterectomy can be done, she said. Laser for Breast Surgery</p>
        <p>A different type of laser - the CO#2 (carbon dioxide) laser - is being used for surgery on the breast and other tissues like the cervix that are readily accessible from outside the body. The CO#2 laser beam cannot yet be carried by fiberoptics, so internal uses are more difficult, though the beam can be bent using a series of mirrors. The CO#2 laser beam does not penetrate tissue beyond one-tenth of a millimeter; rather, it causes a surface burn only at the point of contact. The beam is rapidly absorbed by water, boiling the water inside cells and causing them to explode into a smoky vapor.</p>
        <p>Thus, the CO#2 laser is often used as a surgical knife to cut away pieces of tissue bloodlessly. But it is also used through a laparoscope (a lighted tube inserted into the abdomen through a small incision in the navel) to cut away pelvic adhesions and ovarian cysts and to evaporate endometriosis.</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Ansanelli, who is using the CO#2 laser for breast surgery, in the hands of a well-trained surgeon, a laser knife is more precise and safer than a scalpel. Since it seals blood and lymph vessels in the course of treatment, he predicted it would minimize the chances of cancer spreading during surgery by cutting off the channels by which cancer cells can travel.</p>
        <p>''You can cut out a lump for biopsy like you would cut the eye from a potato,'' he remarked. ''There is no dead tissue and no pain afterward. Patients can go right back to work after a biopsy. If a mastectomy is needed, they can go home the same day or within 48 hours without drains and without pain.''</p>
        <p>Despite such reported success, Dr. Goldrath maintains an attitude of cautious realism. ''I look upon the laser as a tool that should be matched to the job to accomplish what we want,'' he said. ''It is not a magic bullet and it should not be used indiscriminately.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
