<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DUKAKIS SHIFT SEENON ENVIRONMENT</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="46" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="17602"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REAL ESTATE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1988</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MASSACHUSETTS</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">AUDUBON SOCIETY, MASSACHUSETTS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SIERRA CLUB</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONSERVATION LAW FOUNDATION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUKAKIS, MICHAEL S (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4D9113CF932A35750C0A961948260" item-length="851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DUKAKIS SHIFT SEENON ENVIRONMENT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Feb. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As Gov. Michael S. Dukakis of Massachusetts considers a run for the 1988 Democratic Presidential nomination, environmentalists say he may be taking steps to resolve longstanding differences with them over his environmental policies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As Gov. Michael S. Dukakis of Massachusetts considers a run for the 1988 Democratic Presidential nomination, environmentalists say he may be taking steps to resolve longstanding differences with them over his environmental policies.</p>
        <p>As Gov. Michael S. Dukakis of Massachusetts considers a run for the 1988 Democratic Presidential nomination, environmentalists say he may be taking steps to resolve longstanding differences with them over his environmental policies.</p>
        <p>In his previous term, the re-elected Governor was often at odds with organizations like the Sierra Club, the Massachusetts Audubon Society and the Conservation Law Foundation of New England for his policies on waste disposal, water pollution and protection of wetlands. Environmentalists accused Mr. Dukakis of favoring economic development at the expense of environmental concerns.</p>
        <p>But the environmental lobbyists say they are beginning to detect a recent shift. First Mr. Dukakis urged the State Legislature to pass three major bills to insure the safe cleanup and disposal of solid, low-level radioactive and hazardous wastes. Critics said two of the three bills died in the Legislature last year because Mr. Dukakis did little to aid their passage.</p>
        <p>Then this month the Governor's staff briefed the environmentalists on another measure they embraced enthusiastically, a $150 million bond that Mr. Dukakis will recommend to protect ground water and acquire land for conservation purposes. 'Things We've Been Looking For'</p>
        <p>The lobbyists have called the Governor's measures extraordinary steps to improve the quality of life for Massachusetts residents.</p>
        <p>''We've been frustrated in the past and now we're seeing the kinds of things we've been looking for,'' said Marsha Rockefeller, legislative liaison representative for the Massachusetts Audubon Society.</p>
        <p>Judy Shope, legislative director for the Environmental Lobby of Massachusetts, said the Governor now appeared willing to take tough stances on difficult issues.</p>
        <p>Not all of the environmentalists accept that view.</p>
        <p>''I think there are some serious wounds that he needs to repair,'' said Douglas I. Foy, executive director of the Conservation Law Foundation.</p>
        <p>The Governor's chief spokesman, James Dorsey, disputed assertions that Mr. Dukakis had changed his attitude. He took particular issue with the suggestion of some environmentalists that the new tack was an act of political expediency.</p>
        <p>''We do not question their motives for being advocates and we would hope, especially in light of the record, that they would not question the motives of the Governor,'' Mr. Dorsey said. Disagreement Over Record</p>
        <p>Mr. Dorsey cited a list of initiatives taken by the administration, including legislation to supplement Federal money for hazardous waste sites, a cleanup of Boston Harbor, measures to reduce acid rain, a coastal protection act and land acquisitions at a rate unparalleled in state history.</p>
        <p>Priscilla Chapman, executive director of the Sierra Club, countered that the administration has signed its share of environmental legislation, but has not adequately financed many of the efforts.</p>
        <p>''It's great to have these laws on the books, but where the rubber meets the road is whether they actually get out and enforce,'' she said. ''Is the Governor going to back all these good legislative programs with resources?''</p>
        <p>She and others also said it was disingenuous for the administration to take credit for the Boston Harbor cleanup. The state's harbor efforts began in earnest after the Federal Environmental Protection Agency, under the direction of its New England administrator, Michael Deland, and the Conservation Law Foundation went to court to force the cleanup. The state had been violating the Federal Clean Water Act since 1977, when Mr. Dukakis was serving his first term.</p>
        <p>''I think it's fair to say that in Massachusetts the most significant steps to protect the environment are being taken by Mike Deland, who is a member of the Reagan Administration,'' Mr. Foy said. ''I think that should be embarrassing to Mike Dukakis.''</p>
        <p>The critics suggested that the Governor has often made the political choice of economic development over the environment. Dukakis Aide Sees Link</p>
        <p>This assertion, too, was denied by the Governor's spokesman. ''It's flat-out wrong to say it's a choice of one over the other,'' Mr. Dorsey said. ''We see them as being linked.''</p>
        <p>But the environmentalists pointed to at least two projects that seem to say differently. Last year, for example, a developer sought to construct a shopping mall in depressed Attleboro on protected wetlands. The Pyramid Companies proposed to replace the wetlands with artificial wetlands. Environmentalists contended that this would set a dangerous national precedent, but the Dukakis administration declined to block the development. Mr. Deland then stepped in and denied Pyramid an environmental permit.</p>
        <p>A similar battle is shaping up over construction of Fan Pier, a five million square-foot commercial development on the waterfront in South Boston. The state has conditionally approved the environmental impact report for the proposal, the largest in Boston's history. The Conservation Law Foundation has served notice that it intends to sue the state over this project, just as it did over the Attleboro development.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
