<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>POPULATION BOMB': CONCERN FOR FUTURE GENERATIONS</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="46" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="99494"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIRTH CONTROL AND FAMILY PLANNING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LIGHTFOOT, FREDERICK C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDA103CF935A35751C1A961948260" item-length="352" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>POPULATION BOMB': CONCERN FOR FUTURE GENERATIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: It may be impossible to convince Christians who are ''fundamentalists'' that taking everything in the Bible literally can lead to very un-Christian results, but this is certainly the case insofar as following the instruction to ''go forth and multiply'' is concerned today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: It may be impossible to convince Christians who are ''fundamentalists'' that taking everything in the Bible literally can lead to very un-Christian results, but this is certainly the case insofar as following the instruction to ''go forth and multiply'' is concerned today.</p>
        <p>It may be impossible to convince Christians who are ''fundamentalists'' that taking everything in the Bible literally can lead to very un-Christian results, but this is certainly the case insofar as following the instruction to ''go forth and multiply'' is concerned today.</p>
        <p>There already are more people on our tiny planet than the earth's self-healing ability can tolerate, at least if all of us are going to keep using as much electricity, oil, gas or wood heat; and fuel for operating manufacturing, transportation and all other motorized equipment as we now do.</p>
        <p>The carbon dioxide produced by burning fuel for all these purposes ends up in the higher atmosphere and has the property of preventing heat from leaving the earth. So the heat coming to us from the sun and from the fuel we burn is accumulating slowly and causing a rise in the earth's temperature.</p>
        <p>Eventually, according to present experience and scientific calculations, this heat will melt enough ice at the North and South Poles and in glaciers to raise the sea level many feet. Long Island already is losing beachfront to the rising sea and could lose its outer beaches in the next century.</p>
        <p>More serious is the probability of drastic climate changes around the earth that could shift rain clouds toward the poles. Temperate-zone lands could become deserts, causing world famine and the death of hundreds of millions of people.</p>
        <p>Presumably God has, since biblical times, given scientists the knowledge to detect such changes and prepare plans to take action to prevent disaster. However, if we selfishly insist on continuing to have as many children as we want for ourselves, and to live with so much use of fuel - which many corporation leaders are likely to encourage us to - we will disregard the scientists' warnings, and our own children and grandchildren may die as a result. However, people in Arctic and tropical areas may survive.</p>
        <p>God has also allowed scientists to discover that the dinosaurs perished. This warns us that we don't necessarily have a permanent lease on the earth.  FREDERICK S. LIGHTFOOT  Greenport</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
