<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>REVAMPED ROCKET FOR SPACE VEHICLE PASSES A KEY TEST</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="70585"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROCKETS AND ROCKET PROPULSION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TESTS AND TESTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE SHUTTLE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRIGHAM CITY (UTAH)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MORTON THIOKOL INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SANGER, DAVID E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CHALLENGER (SPACE SHUTTLE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rockets and Rocket Propulsion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEEDD173AF932A0575BC0A961948260" item-length="1665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>REVAMPED ROCKET FOR SPACE VEHICLE PASSES A KEY TEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SANGER, DAVID E</byline>
      <dateline>BRIGHAM CITY, Utah, Aug. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A redesigned version of the shuttle booster rocket whose leaking seal led to the Challenger disaster was tested for the firrt time here today, filling a mountain valley with a roar that space agency officials said marked a major milestone for getting the shuttle flying again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A redesigned version of the shuttle booster rocket whose leaking seal led to the Challenger disaster was tested for the firrt time here today, filling a mountain valley with a roar that space agency officials said marked a major milestone for getting the shuttle flying again.</p>
        <p>A redesigned version of the shuttle booster rocket whose leaking seal led to the Challenger disaster was tested for the firrt time here today, filling a mountain valley with a roar that space agency officials said marked a major milestone for getting the shuttle flying again.</p>
        <p>The solid fuel rocket shed a stream of fire and smoke across the desert precisely on schedule at 1 this afternoon, in sharp contrast to the three aborted efforts to conduct the test firing last Thursday.</p>
        <p>While the full results of the tests will not be known for a week or more, when the rocket segments are separated and its new safety seals dissected, officials of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration and the rocket's manufacturer, Morton Thiokol Inc., said they saw no early signs of problems.</p>
        <p>''Looks good, looks good,'' John Thirkill, the head of Thiokol's sprawling plant and test grounds at the foot of the Wasatch Mountains, said today, his left fist clenched tightly as the 1.2 million-pound rocket roared two miles from a reviewing stand. ''Boy, does that look good.'' Worth 'a Couple of Grins'</p>
        <p>As soon as the two-minute test ended, a cheer rose from the more than 9,000 people who lined the highway near the test grounds, many of whom had turned the day into an occasion for tailgate picnics and touch football games.</p>
        <p>''It's a day for a couple of grins,'' said Adm. Richard Truly, NASA's Associate Administrator for space flight, as space agency and Thiokol officials slapped each other on the back and hugged. ''We waited a long time to see this.''</p>
        <p>For NASA and Thiokol, today's test came at a critical juncture. Without virtually flawless test results - and no sign of the safety seal erosion that downed the Challenger 19 months ago - NASA officials concede there is no way they will be able to meet their target of a June 1988 resumption of flights. Even with a successful test, many doubt that a first flight will come for another year, both because additional rocket tests are required, and because improvements are being made in other parts of the shuttle, from its main engines to its braking system. Problems With Test Equipment</p>
        <p>Politically, the test is also important for the agency, which has found its goals and budgets facing increasing questions as NASA has struggled to repair the shuttle. ''To the public and the Congress, and the people who are depending on us, a full scale test is a very significant event,'' said Admiral Truly. But he warned that, even when the redesigned rockets are certified for flight, ''the only way for America to have a risk-free space program is to get out of this business.''</p>
        <p>Even though the test went off as scheduled, Thiokol continued to be plagued by some of the technical problems with its testing equipment that scuttled Thursday's test. The water-deluge system, which failed Thursday and began a series of problems that forced postponement, did not supply enough water at the conclusion of today's test to cool the aft section of the rocket. Firemen had to race up the mountainside and douse the rocket's casing to prevent damage.</p>
        <p>In addition, about 35 of the more than 500 sensors attached to the rocket failed to operate properly, though Thiokol officials said most are providing redundant readings that were available from other sensors.</p>
        <p>''It just proves that you can trust solid rockets but you can't trust liquids or electrons,'' joked Allan McDonald, the head of Thiokol's rocket redesign team. He gained national attention last year after testifying that he had warned Thiokol and NASA not to launch the Challenger, which exploded 72 seconds into its flight on Jan. 28, 1986, killing its crew of seven. Weekend Repairs Pay Off</p>
        <p>Both NASA and Thiokol officials today insisted that their caution on Thursday paid off, and that repairs conducted over the weekend assured that the $15 million test would not be wasted. ''A bad test on time - well, I can't compare that to a good test that's late,'' said J. R. Thompson, the head of the Marshall Space Flight Center, which is responsible for overseeing the rocket's redesign.</p>
        <p>In many respects, today's test took on the air of a launching. The countdown was conducted from an underground bunker with rows of computer consoles manned by technicians, and an observation room that included several astronauts and officials of NASA and the Air Force.</p>
        <p>The countdown itself was boomed over huge loudspeakers, and television monitors around the site provided closeups of the rocket. One camera was focused on the precise area of the rocket where the Challenger's safety seal seared open.</p>
        <p>Seconds after the rocket was ignited, the sound wave hit the reviewing area and rolled out toward the Great Salt Lake, as smoke billowed high in the air. But the first indications of success did not come until Mr. McDonald and other officials were able to get within about 50 feet of the motor as it was being cooled down with carbon dioxide and streams of water. One Issue Especially Critical</p>
        <p>''We couldn't get real close because it was turning into the world's largest refrigerator,'' said Mr. McDonald. But as seen through binoculars, he said, the heaters that now surround the rocket's seals, along with the retention bands and pins that connect the segments, ''all looked real good.''</p>
        <p>As engineers analyze test results over the next few weeks, they will focus on one main issue: whether superheated gases escaped through the joints that connect the booster's main segments. Such leakage paved the way for the disastrous flight of the Challenger.</p>
        <p>Many of the spent booster rockets from previous shuttle flights, retrieved from the sea after they were jettisoned, showed evidence that the rubber O rings sealing the joints had been charred. Some of the O rings were eroded. Engineers thought that they understood the phenomenon, and moved to correct it, but testimony before a Presidential commission last year revealed that few at Thiokol or NASA thought the problem serious enough to stop the shuttle flight.</p>
        <p>The problem was worsened by the cold weather at Cape Canaveral on the morning of Jan. 28, 1986. Under the stress of launching, a heavy steel joint in one of the two boosters opened slightly, allowing the gases to escape. The chilled O rings had lost their resilience, and they did not spring into place to stop the leakage. The flaming gases burned like a blowtorch through the steel booster casings and a connecting strut to the external fuel tank. That is when the craft began to disintegrate. Extra Metal Lip Added</p>
        <p>The new design, a modification of one started before the Challenger accident, seeks to prevent the joints from opening. An extra metal lip, called a ''capture feature,'' is designed to keep the tongue-and-groove joint from opening up. In addition, a third O ring has been added to each joint. Putty that surrounded the old joint - suspected of worsening the leaks by creating narrow passageways for the hot gases to get to the joint - has been removed, and a new ''J seal'' carved from the insulation should prevent gases from getting to the O rings in the first place.</p>
        <p>Most experts who have examined the new joint design, including an independent panel from the National Academy of Sciences, have pronounced themselves satisfied. ''We think there is every reason it should work,'' Mr. Thompson said on Thursday as he waited for the test firings of the rockets that were later aborted. ''But of course, whenever you change something, there is a possibility that some other element is affected.''</p>
        <p>Some expert observers are not so sanguine about the trickier cape-to-nozzle joint at the aft end of the rocket, where two million pounds of thrust race out the rockets in less than two minutes. That seal, long considered troublesome but not involved in the Challenger accident, has also be redesigned. One hundred bolts have been added around the radius of the V-shaped connection to assure that it, too, does not crack open under pressure.</p>
        <p>But the geometry of that part of the booster makes the design of any seal especially difficult, and some engineers questions whether the bolt holes might in fact weaken the overall structure. Some former Thiokol engineers, notably Roger Boisjoly, who warned against the launching of the Challenger, complained that more reliable designs were overlooked. Mr. Boisjoly is now suing the company, charging that it knowingly provided defective rockets, and that it defamed him. Metal Seals to Be Tested</p>
        <p>Thiokol officials, including Mr. McDonald, say that the design which Mr. Boisjoly favored, which uses metal seals, is also being explored by the company. If troubles develop with the design tested today, the metal-seals design ''is our next option,'' said Mr. McDonald. In any event, he said, Thiokol will soon begin to test the metal-seals design.</p>
        <p>The last major change to the booster involves the protective material used within the nozzle to prevent it from burning through. That material is now wrapped differently than in the past, and bonded in a different to the seal.</p>
        <p>Some of the results of the test were available almost immediately today, read from more than 500 sensors wired around the rocket. But most of the data will take days to interpret. And the most critical information - whether gas and flames actually reach the joints - will not be learned until engineers take the booster apart in the next two weeks to inspect the O rings and other elements of the joint.</p>
        <p>Even then, there are questions about the validity of the test. The rocket was tested horizontally, rather than vertically the way a shuttle is launched. Thiokol officials insist that the position of the rocket should have no significant affect on the results. More importantly, this test did not reproduce stresses caused on a flight rocket by the weight of the shuttle orbiter and external fuel tank. A test that will reproduce such stresses will not be completed here for several months.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
