<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CHLORINE LEVELS REPORTED HIGH OVER ANTARCTICA</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="20365"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLORINE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSE SUBCOMMITTEE ON HEALTH AND ENVIRONMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DA1630F933A25750C0A961948260" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CHLORINE LEVELS REPORTED HIGH OVER ANTARCTICA</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A scientist who recently returned from studying the mysterious ''hole'' in the ozone layer over Antarctica reported today that strikingly high levels of chlorine, almost certainly from industrial chemicals, were found in the polar atmosphere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A scientist who recently returned from studying the mysterious ''hole'' in the ozone layer over Antarctica reported today that strikingly high levels of chlorine, almost certainly from industrial chemicals, were found in the polar atmosphere.</p>
        <p>A scientist who recently returned from studying the mysterious ''hole'' in the ozone layer over Antarctica reported today that strikingly high levels of chlorine, almost certainly from industrial chemicals, were found in the polar atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The findings were described by several scientists as very strong, although not conclusive, evidence to support the hotly debated theory that chemicals released by industrial actvity are important causes of the huge gaps in the atmospheric ozone that appears over Antarctica every September and October.</p>
        <p>It is now widely accepted by scientists and industry that chlorofluorocarbons can destroy the atmospheric ozone that shields the earth from dangerous ultraviolet rays. Whether they also contribute to the annual decline in Antarctic ozone has been disputed. But several scientists today said they viewed the trends in Antarctica as an indication of the serious vulnerability of the earth's atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Dr. Susan Soloman, of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, told a House subcommittee today that her team of scientists had found levels of chlorine dioxide over Antarctica 20 to 50 times higher than anticipated. She said that the source of most of the chloride molecules is chlorofluorcarbons or other chemicals manufactured for refrigerants, insulation, foam packaging, aerosols and other uses.</p>
        <p>She and other scientists at today's hearing said that it was premature to conclude on the basis of her findings that chlorofluorcarbons were the cause of the ozone loss in the Antarctic and that the polar climate may play an important role in the chemical reactions taking place in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>But in response to a question she said ''I think we eventually will see a large scale depletion in other latitudes.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Donald Heath, a scientist with the Federal space agency's Goddard Space Flight Center, said that satellite observations and other research findings over the past year confirm losses in the ozone layer over other parts of the globe, including the temperate zones, as well as over Antarctica. Global Agreement Urged</p>
        <p>Dr. F. Sherwood Rowland, a chemist who in the 1970's first predicted the destruction of atmospheric ozone by chlorinated chemicals said in an interview today that the findings in Antartica ''pretty well nail down'' the case against chlorofluorocarbons as the cause of the ozone losses.</p>
        <p>He and other scientists at today's hearing before the Subcommittee on Health and the Environment agreed that the finding made it even more urgent to reach a global agreement to control the use of these chemicals, which are believed to be destroying the atmospheric ozone that shields the earth from dangerous ultraviolet radiation from the sun.</p>
        <p>However, Dr. Elwood P. Blanchard, a vice president of E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company, which makes chlorofluorocarbons, said that ''no unequivocal trends of ozone depletion have yet been verified and also maintained that ''the changes noted in Antarctica cannot be extrapolated to the rest of the world.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Blanchard and other industry representatives appearing at today's hearing insisted that there is no imminent threat to the ozone layer and human health and urged that care be taken not to damage the economy with precipitate action to bar chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rowland, a professor of chemistry at the University of California-Irvine, said there still is a large range of uncertainty built into the mathematical models predicing ozone loss. Ozone Layer Called 'Fragile'</p>
        <p>''However,'' he added, ''we can now look at the Antarctic ozone hole and know that the ozone layer is not endowed with enormous resiliency, but is instead very fragile.''</p>
        <p>While it is not possible to transfer observations of what is happening in Antarctica to other parts of the world, the fact that the ozone levels could decrease by 50 percent under certain conditions in the south polar area ''suggests that extreme care is now appropriate for the entire global atmosphere,'' Dr. Rowland insisted.</p>
        <p>Dr. Richard T. Watson, acting program for the National Aeronautics and Space Administration's upper atmospheric research program said that even though it could not be stated definitively that the Antarctic ozone hole was caused by chlorofluorocarbons, ''in my opinion, protection of the ozone layer is one of the most important environmental issues of our time.''</p>
        <p>Lee M. Thomas, Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, said at the hearing that even without the new evidence about the Antarctic hole, ''the global data is sufficent to warrant a freeze and phaseout'' of chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>A draft report on the chemicals by the agency found that increased ultraviolet radiation reaching the earth's surface through a depleted ozone layer could cause as many as 40 million cases of skin cancer and 800,000 cancer deaths in the United States alone over the next 88 years. The report also noted that increased ultraviolet radiation could cause eye catracts, damage to the immune system and damage crops and aquatic life.</p>
        <p>The United States barred the use of chlorofluorocarbons in aerosols in 1977 and Canada and several Scandanavian nations followed suit. However, other nations continue to produce aerosols and total production of the chemicals, including in the United States, is continuing to rise sharply. Freeze on Production Urged</p>
        <p>The United States has proposed an international protocol that would freeze production of harmful chlorofluorocarbons at current levels of production and gradually phase them out over 10 or 15 years while practicable substitutes are developed.</p>
        <p>Richard E. Benedick, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Health, Environment and Natural Resources said that there had been some progress toward an international agreement at a meeting of the industrial nations in Vienna late last month. But he added that ''the hardest negotiations are still to come.''</p>
        <p>Those familiar with last months negotiatons said that several European countries, particularly Britain and France, had been strongly opposed to any controls on chlorofluorocarbons that might cost jobs or harm their international trade position.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
