<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York Earns High Rank on Environment</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="15730"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">RENEWABLE ENERGY AND THE ENVIRONMENT, FUND FOR</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1DA1731F931A15751C0A961948260" item-length="653" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York Earns High Rank on Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: New York, New Jersey and Connecticut rank among the top five states in establishing and enforcing programs to protect the environment, according to a private report issued today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: New York, New Jersey and Connecticut rank among the top five states in establishing and enforcing programs to protect the environment, according to a private report issued today.</p>
        <p>New York, New Jersey and Connecticut rank among the top five states in establishing and enforcing programs to protect the environment, according to a private report issued today.</p>
        <p>The report, prepared by the Fund for Renewable Energy and the Environment, said that many states were making progress with their environmental programs, but that there was ''an overall stall in progress for a safe environment'' because the Federal Government had retreated from its regulatory role under the Reagan Administration. Tina Hobson, executive director of the fund, a nonprofit educational group, said that, because of Federal retrenchment, ''the states have been left to struggle with both new and existing environmental hazards.''</p>
        <p>The report found that because of economic conditions and competing needs, environmental hazards have been ignored or action to correct them delayed in many states, particularly the poorest ones. #6 Areas Examined The report did not measure the environmental quality in the individual states but rather the effectiveness of their programs to deal with the environment. It looked at state efforts in six areas - air pollution reduction, soil conservation, solid waste disposal and recycling, hazardous waste cleanup, groundwater protection and renewable energy and conservation - and ranked the relative strength of their programs in these areas.</p>
        <p>New York State ranked first in groundwater protection and No. 5 in overall rankings among the 50 states.</p>
        <p>New York's Commissioner of Environmental Conservation, Henry G. Williams, interviewed before today's news conference, said he hoped the recognition of New York's ''significant performance'' would silence criticism that Governor Cuomo and he were not ''sufficiently concerned with environmental protection.''</p>
        <p>During his first term, Mr. Cuomo was often criticized for giving short shrift to environmental issues and environmentalists have long been critical of the State Environmental Conservation Department and Mr. Williams.</p>
        <p>The Governor has nominated him as a member of the Public Service Commission and, in a move that was applauded by many environmentalists, nominated Thomas C. Jorling, head of the Center for Environmental Studies at Williams College, to replace Mr. Williams.</p>
        <p>New Jersey received the highest ranking in both the hazardous waste cleanup and solid waste disposal categories and was No. 3 on the overall list. Connecticut, while not top-ranked in any single category, was No. 4 over all.</p>
        <p>The top overall ranking among the states went to Wisconsin, with California second. The states ranked as having the weakest environmental programs included Mississsippi, West Virginia, Wyoming, Utah, and North Dakota The report noted that many of the states with the highest rankings tended to be states with the severest environmental problems, such as New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Many of the states on the bottom of the list were among those with low per-capita incomes and with insufficient resources to meet all the requirements of filling in the gaps in environmental, health, education and other social programs left by the Federal Government's transfer of responsibility for these programs to the states. The report lists what it regards as defects as well as accomplishments by state environmental programs. In its report on New York, for example, it says the state has three counties that have deficient programs for carrying out the Clean Air Act and that the Environmental Protection Agency has imposed sanctions, such as withholding Federal grants, as a result.</p>
        <p>The report noted that New Jersey had 18 counties with inadequate programs to carry out the provisions of the Clean Air Act, although no Federal sanctions had been imposed. It also said that the state had no acid rain control program in place.</p>
        <p>Connecticut also does not have an acid rain program in effect, although the state does conduct research into acid rain.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
