<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY: FRIDAY, JULY 17, 1987</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="57425"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">SUMMARY</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDB1338F934A25754C0A961948260" item-length="1047" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY: FRIDAY, JULY 17, 1987</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A2-8</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A2-8</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A2-8</p>
        <p>John M. Poindexter testified yesterday he was not asked by White House leaders when he resigned as national security adviser last November about what he knew about the diversion of Iran arms profits to the contras. Page A1</p>
        <p>President Reagan has been harmed and the Republican Party has been weakened despite testimony that Mr. Reagan was unaware of the diversion of Iran arms sales profits to the contras, many politicians and academics said. A7</p>
        <p>The White House adopted a strategy of not criticizing Admiral Poindexter directly while at the same time sharply criticizing what the former national security adviser had done in the Iran-contra affair. A7</p>
        <p>News analysis: European allies widely view the testimony of former officials about the Iran-contra affair as a sign of chaos at the heart of the Reagan Presidency's foreign policy machinery. A8</p>
        <p>Contras claimed the greatest victory in the six-year civil war, saying about 500 Nicaaguan rebels had overrun a military garrison. There was no comment from the Sandinista Government. A3</p>
        <p>Fading prospects for summit talks this fall between President Reagan and Mikhail S. Gorbachev were indicated by Administration officials. They said the mood at negotitions in Geneva has been sour for several weeks. A1</p>
        <p>Moscow will allow Erich Honecker, the East German leader, to make a milestone official visit to West Germany in September, according to Bonn officials and Western diplomats. A1</p>
        <p>Japan agreed to meet all demands by the United States to prevent any recurrence of its illegal sale of advanced submarine technology to the Soviet Union, the Commerce Department disclosed. A1</p>
        <p>Man in News: Ramaswamy Venkataraman  A2</p>
        <p>Mexico challenges U.S. on drugs  A3</p>
        <p>Salvador's rebels push hard in capital  A3</p>
        <p>Russians in Israel play to U.S. audience  A5</p>
        <p>Iran threatening to cut French ties  A8</p>
        <p>nATIONAL A9-10, A36, B8, D15</p>
        <p>Lyn Nofziger was indicted on conflict-of-interest charges related to lobbying by the former senior aide to President Reagan on behalf of the Wedtech Corporation, a Government official and other sources said. A1</p>
        <p>The Deaver trial was postponed for at least three months after lawyers for the former White House aide vowed to appeal to the Supreme Court an order requiring jury selection to be conducted in public. A1</p>
        <p>Congressmen and protesters hailed the 200th anniversary of the creation of Congress outside Independence Hall after a great compromise resolved the issue of state representation in the Senate and House. A36</p>
        <p>Women's groups seem to be ebbing as the 21st meeting of NOW opens in Philadelphia today, but millions of women have adopted the movement's ideals as a matter of course. A10</p>
        <p>NASA has chosen a final design for the space shuttle's new rockets and will heat O ring seals in cold weather rather than use new materials to prevent leaks, officials of the space agency announced. D15</p>
        <p>Six states sued the E.P.A. in an effort to force the Federal environmental agency to curb power-plant emissions that cause acid rain. The Northeastern states contend the agency has not complied with provisions of the Clean Air Act of 1977. D15</p>
        <p>The F.A.A. was told to force airlines to increase security and to fine the carriers for any lax screening of passengers and carry-on baggage at airports. The order came from Transportation Secretary Elizabeth Hanford Dole. D15</p>
        <p>Texans would pay higher state taxes under a $38.3 billion budget endorsed by Gov. Bill Clements. The new taxes are expected to total $5.5 billion and are opposed by many Republican legislators. A10</p>
        <p>A leading low-cost home builder, the Jim Walter Corporation, said it had received an unexpected takeover bid for $50 a share, or $2.03 billion in cash. It said the offer came from a key investor group. D1</p>
        <p>Bakkers plot their next moves  A10</p>
        <p>Grand jury to investigate PTL  A10</p>
        <p>Washington Talk A9</p>
        <p>Politics and the litmus test  Of trees and laws and bad raps  REGIONAL B1-4, B12</p>
        <p>A Syracuse ex-Mayor was indicted on charges of masterminding a scheme that brought him $1.5 million in kickbacks from contractors. The defendant, Lee Alexander, a Democrat, 60, was charged with 40 counts in a 60-page Federal indictment. A1</p>
        <p>Mr. Alexander had led Syracuse as Mayor for 16 years while earning a national reputation as a leading spokesman for the cities. B2</p>
        <p>More children are contracting AIDS in New York and around the country. The children usually die by the age of 3, but many are living longer than anyone thought possible when AIDS was identified in 1981. B4</p>
        <p>The burden of AIDS will fall most heavily on minority group members, Mayor Koch said in urging a group of black church leaders to resist any effort to quarantine or discriminate against victims of the disease. B4</p>
        <p>A U.N. envoy has been accused of ramming his automobile into a Queens woman and injuring her in a dispute over a parking place. The envoy is Shah Mohammad Dost, the chief Afghan delegate. B1</p>
        <p>Outdoor sculpture is increasing and there are currently four large shows, but Manhattan's rising costliness is prompting much more activity in New York City's other boroughs, particularly Queens. C1</p>
        <p>An offbeat festival, Serious Fun!, begins tonight at Alice Tully Hall and runs through Aug. 2. The gala promises dancing, singing, jazz, new faces, new vaudeville and established innovators. C1</p>
        <p>City plans to end concrete pact  B1</p>
        <p>Political apathy in Connecticut  B1</p>
        <p>Maintaining Brooklyn churches  B1</p>
        <p>Jersey couple struggles in right-to-die case  B2</p>
        <p>Executive charged in $5 million postal fraud</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Hearing on Indian museum held  B3</p>
        <p>8 hurt in hotel fire  B3</p>
        <p>Ambulance proposals released  B3</p>
        <p>Black revolutionary arrested  B3</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
