<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY: SATURDAY, FEBRUARY 28, 1987</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="17444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">SUMMARY</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5D8173CF93BA15751C0A961948260" item-length="998" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY: SATURDAY, FEBRUARY 28, 1987</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE WHITE HOUSE CRISIS 6-10  The President ousted Donald Regan from his post as the White House chief of staff and replaced him with former Senator Howard H. Baker Jr., in a dramatic move to revive his troubled Presidency.  Page 1  Man in the News: Howard H. Baker had always said that it's hard to say ''no'' to the President.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE WHITE HOUSE CRISIS 6-10  The President ousted Donald Regan from his post as the White House chief of staff and replaced him with former Senator Howard H. Baker Jr., in a dramatic move to revive his troubled Presidency.  Page 1  Man in the News: Howard H. Baker had always said that it's hard to say ''no'' to the President.</p>
        <p>THE WHITE HOUSE CRISIS 6-10  The President ousted Donald Regan from his post as the White House chief of staff and replaced him with former Senator Howard H. Baker Jr., in a dramatic move to revive his troubled Presidency.  Page 1  Man in the News: Howard H. Baker had always said that it's hard to say ''no'' to the President. So his friends were not surprised when he quickly accepted the post of White House chief of staff. 7  Mr. Baker's presidential ambitions had him on the verge of deciding to run for President when President Reagan offered him his new post. ''I didn't see how I could turn it down,'' Mr. Baker said. 1  The Tower panel was dismayed and surprised by President Reagan's lack of knowledge about the Iran-contra affair during their two long conversations last month, the 3 commission members said in an interview. 1  News analysis: Mr. Reagan's choice of Mr. Baker as his new chief of staff was taken by political Washington today as the first distinct sign in months that the President is rousing himself from political torpor. 1  George Bush accepted the conclusion of the Tower Commission that Washington's negotiations with Iran disintegrated into a trade of arms for hostages and said the policy had ''failed the American people.''  6  Tangled web of legal issues</p>
        <p>9  Guatemalan role cited in reportbe,  10  Nicaragua derides Tower report</p>
        <p>10  INTERNATIONAL 2-10  The Paris trial of a terrorism suspect heard a prosecutor's plea for a ''moderate'' sentence. He said France could be held hostage if it made Georges Ibrahim Abdallah into a ''martyr.''  1  The Vatican expressed astonishment at efforts by the Italian authorities to arrest the American head of the Vatican bank and two of his closest associates. A sharply worded statement fully supported Archbishop Paul C. Marcinkus.  2  Protecting the ozone layer was the subject of criticism leveled against Europe by the United States, which said foot-dragging had prevented action against destructive chemicals at an international conference on the issue.  2  News analysis: Russian opposition to Mikhail S. Gorbachev's new policies is evident among high party officials and farmers alike, and the leader has felt increasingly compelled in recent weeks to address their concerns. 4  George Shultz arrived in Hong Kong. He begins a five-day visit Sunday to 5 Chinese cities, including Dalian, the center of an economic development zone, in an effort to reinforce an improving relationship with China.  3  Prosecutions urged in Manila  3  NATIONAL 11-13, 32  Drug profits in Florida are so great that prominent figures from professional automobile and boat racing appear to have been drawn into competition with agents.  11  News Analysis: The welfare system and how to overhaul it have suddenly become the center of a national consensus among liberals and conservatives, governors and members of Congress and the Reagan Administration.  11  A $14.8 billion trade deficit was reported by the Commerce Department for the month of January, with imports flowing at nearly twice the level of exports. The showing was much worse than in December.  39  Consumer prices were up 0.7 percent in January, the biggest advance in four and a half years, the Government reported. But many analysts said that the rise did not necessarily mean a new inflation surge.  39  The release of 185 Texas prisoners will be the immediate result of Gov. Bill Clements' declaration of a state of emergency in the prison system. The move cleared the way for the release of perhaps hundreds of others 11  Secret U.S. nuclear experiments were conducted, with President Eisenhower's approval, while the United States and the Soviet Union had a moratorium on testing, according to a newly published report.  13  A convicted spy portrayed himself as a loyal American who helped Israel and cited ''extremely detailed'' requests for American intelligence data as evidence of Israel's highly coordinated espionage effort.  12  Politics is big business in Louisiana, and with the biggest business, oil, in the dumps, the upcoming election year can be counted on to stoke the economy through the nonpartisan primary on Oct. 24 and the run-off Nov. 21.  13  A Federal research funding pattern was noted by the auditing arm of Congress, which found that 16 of the 20 universities that received the most Federal research money in 1967 were at the top of the list for 1984.  12  A land swapping proposal in Alaska aims to shift title to subsurface oil rights in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge from the Federal Government to Alaska Natives and perhaps to the state.  12  WASHINGTON TALK 12  Consequences of Fawn Hall  REGIONAL 33-37  New regulations on tow trucks were proposed by the Mayor, who noted that tow trucks speeding to crash sites contributed to 7 deaths, about 800 personal injuries and 1,200 collisions between 1983 and 1986.  1  An offer of free AIDS testing will be required in hundreds of clinics in New York State that specialize in prenatal care, family planning and the treatment of sexually transmitted diseases and drug abuse, a health official said.</p>
        <p>33  Stabilized rent rules will change in New York City under a Board of Estimate decision. But city officials, building owners and tenants are not certain how the process of setting rent guidelines will proceed.  37  Refugees seeking to enter Canada are gathering on the New York-Canada border. The refugees, many from Central America, are hoping to avoid deportation under the new United States immigration law.  33  3 L.I.R.R. unions reach pacts</p>
        <p>33</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
