<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Europe Under Wraps; Scaffolding: A New Esthetic...and a Report by 6 Times Correspondents Athens</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="84079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HISTORIC BUILDINGS AND SITES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCAFFOLDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ATHENS (GREECE)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ACROPOLIS (GREECE)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">COWELL, ALAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Greece</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Greece/Athens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1D9123FF93BA25753C1A961948260" item-length="454" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Europe Under Wraps; Scaffolding: A New Esthetic...and a Report by 6 Times Correspondents Athens</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Cowell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COWELL, ALAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Athens skyline is supposed to bristle a little with antiquity. These days, the bristling comes more from the ravages of modernity on older things, symbolized in the gantries and scaffolding atop the Acropolis, which in recent years have grown to enfold the Parthenon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Athens skyline is supposed to bristle a little with antiquity. These days, the bristling comes more from the ravages of modernity on older things, symbolized in the gantries and scaffolding atop the Acropolis, which in recent years have grown to enfold the Parthenon.</p>
        <p>The Athens skyline is supposed to bristle a little with antiquity. These days, the bristling comes more from the ravages of modernity on older things, symbolized in the gantries and scaffolding atop the Acropolis, which in recent years have grown to enfold the Parthenon.</p>
        <p>The gradual decay of renowned sites is not unique to Athens. Elsewhere in this region of ancient cities, the authorities in Istanbul seem only now to be getting around to a sustained effort to resurrect the decaying city walls that for centuries have girded the metropolis. In Athens, however, the impact seems more direct and obvious, an intrusion of steel grafted onto the 300-foot-high pedestal of rock and girding the Parthenon itself.</p>
        <p>Manolis Korres, the architect in charge of the Acropolis renovation, estimates that the project will consume a full decade before the damage caused by pollution and earlier restoration is repaired.</p>
        <p>The project, however, is not the only potential drawback for visitors. Earlier this year, in what seems a kind of annual rite, government employees who act as custodians of Greece's antiquities went on strike for higher wages, and the Acropolis was closed for three days. When it reopened, a British visitor said, the lines of frustrated visitors were so long, the heat so great and the ticket facilities so slow that some visitors gave up in despair.</p>
        <p>Thus far, Mr. Korres said, only about one-tenth of the restoration work needed for the Acropolis has been completed, and some of its monuments have been removed altogether for safe keeping. For example, the Erechtheum's maidenly sculptures - the Caryatids - have been placed in a museum.</p>
        <p>The problems, the architect said, relate to two separate assaults on the marble of the Acropolis temples. One, familiar in Europe, has been caused by air pollution and acid rain. The other, he said, resulted from incautious restoration work early in this century when iron clamps and fastenings were used to bind columns and walls together.</p>
        <p>The clamps have rusted and swollen, damaging the stonework. The original builders, Mr. Korres said, coated their fastenings with corrosion-resistant lead.</p>
        <p>Part of the current restoration project, Mr Korres added, calls for removal of the rotten iron bindings, using instruments that he compared to those employed by a surgeon, so as to replace the bindings with a titanium alloy when reconstruction begins. The first replacements are scheduled for this fall.</p>
        <p>Of equal concern is pollution caused by the city's industrialization, its snarled traffic and by fumes from heating oil. In some cases, Mr. Korres said, the only protection against that onslaught is the removal of damaged pieces and their replacement with copies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
