<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AMBITIOUS AMAZON EXPEDITION PROBES FOREST'S ROLE IN GLOBAL ATMOSPHERE</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="45704"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GASES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRAZIL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AMAZON RIVER</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMONS, MARLISE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5DA163FF931A35755C0A961948260" item-length="1746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AMBITIOUS AMAZON EXPEDITION PROBES FOREST'S ROLE IN GLOBAL ATMOSPHERE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMONS, MARLISE</byline>
      <dateline>MANAUS, Brazil</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: SHORTLY after dawn, the Electra climbed above the Amazon River, nudged through plumes and layers of steam, then bumped along just 500 feet over the jungle canopy. On board, a phalanx of scientists started probing the breath of the forest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: SHORTLY after dawn, the Electra climbed above the Amazon River, nudged through plumes and layers of steam, then bumped along just 500 feet over the jungle canopy. On board, a phalanx of scientists started probing the breath of the forest.</p>
        <p>SHORTLY after dawn, the Electra climbed above the Amazon River, nudged through plumes and layers of steam, then bumped along just 500 feet over the jungle canopy. On board, a phalanx of scientists started probing the breath of the forest.</p>
        <p>Laser beams shot through openings on the roof and floor of the aircraft, measuring gases at different levels. Thin pipes sucked samples of air into gas detectors. Down below, a network of investigators in weather stations, towers and ships examined the forest soil and water and the gases emerging from the lush ecosystem.</p>
        <p>The scientists, from the United States and Brazil, were participating in the most ambitious expedition ever mounted to study the chemistry of the tropical forest and atmosphere. This research is part of a worldwide project, sponsored by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, that aims to quantify for the first time the contribution of the earth's living systems to key compounds in the atmosphere - compounds that in turn help regulate climate and life.</p>
        <p>Scientists give high priority to improving knowledge of the rain forest's role in these processes. To understand the earth's chemistry, it is essential ''to couple the forest to the atmosphere,'' said Dr. Robert J. McNeal, a NASA scientist who is a manager of the global research project.</p>
        <p>Here in the world's largest tropical forest, the key questions include these: Just how much does the forest produce and consume of a host of gases and particles that play important roles in the atmosphere? What is the global impact of the intense tropical storms that constantly mix and turn over these compounds, pushing some up into the upper atmosphere and pulling others down to the jungle? How does the vast rain forest influence levels of gases that may contribute to global warming or that destroy the stratospheric ozone that shields the earth from dangerous ultraviolet radiation?</p>
        <p>Many of the elemental cycles of the forest, water and air are known in a general way. The giant trees of the rain forest, for example, absorb carbon dioxide as they grow but release it to the atmosphere when they burn or rot. Plants and animals in the forest soils and waters produce nitrous oxide, which can be transformed into ozone destroyers in the upper atmosphere. At the same time, the forest vegetation itself destroys ozone near the ground, where it is a pollutant.</p>
        <p>But the exact quantities of these and many other compounds the forest exchanges with the atmosphere are unknown, and the scientists here are hoping the data they gather will complete some of these crucial equations. ''The existing models are based on guesswork and small-scale experiments,'' said Dr. McNeal.</p>
        <p>The Amazon expedition, conducted with Brazil's National Institute for Space Research, is one of the early phases of NASA's Global Tropospheric Experiment. NASA has conducted two expeditions in the Amazon and another in Barbados; work will begin next on the Arctic tundra and over the equatorial Atlantic and Pacific Oceans. NASA also hopes to extend its program to China to measure the high methane emissions over the country's extensive rice paddies and the impact of the Gobi's dust storms.</p>
        <p>Industrial activities are producing carbon dioxide and other gases that trap heat like a greenhouse, raising the earth's temperature. Scientists believe that man-made chemicals are helping deplete the ozone of the upper atmosphere.</p>
        <p>But nature, too, emits and absorbs many compounds, including various ''greenhouse'' gases, ozone, and ozone-destroying compounds. While specialists have learned a great deal about man-made pollution, they still know little of the atmospheric role of natural ecosystems. Such knowledge is important both for understanding current trends and for predicting the consequences of such changes as the large-scale clearing of the Amazon and other rain forests.</p>
        <p>''Atmospheric science is a new frontier that requires new ways of thinking, new techniques,'' said Dr. Robert Harriss of NASA. ''We are dealing with a whole new set of issues. There is almost nothing in the textbooks about this.''</p>
        <p>The Amazon tests have been made possible now only by the development of new instruments that can measure gases and particles on the smallest scales. For instance, a new laser system devised at NASA is able to picture ozone all the way from the forest to an altitude of 40,000 feet.</p>
        <p>In addition, the six-week expedition, which ended May 15, brought together an unusually diverse group of 60 Americans and 90 Brazilians, including geochemists, physicists, biologists and meteorologists, working at 20 different sites. In a gigantic logistical operation, tons of equipment from the United States was moved up the Amazon by ship. Sometimes things simply bogged down when no bulldozer could be found to move heavy gear up the mud roads.</p>
        <p>Between field trips and flights, the experimenters compared notes here in the heart of the Amazon basin, a place where heat and humidity cling to everything like a sheen of oil. In rooms full of computers and maps, there were daily meetings with meteorologists who received satellite pictures of the rain forest every 30 minutes from NASA offices in Langley, Va.</p>
        <p>''We are trying to see how the whole clockwork functions,'' said Meinrat Andreae of Florida State University. ''There are wheels within wheels in a very complex mechanism and only by scrutinizing all the parts can we understand it.''</p>
        <p>The scientists will be interpreting their data for months, but some felt they had already gained significant insights. Differences between the wet and the dry season, for example, have proved so great that existing studies based largely on the dry months are now seen as misleading. 'Extremely Weird Things'</p>
        <p>At one forest site northwest of Manaus, tests were in progress 24 hours a day. Free-flying balloons carrying instruments and a radio transmitter were launched every three hours to register ozone, temperature, moisture. Tethered balloons hovered at 500 meters and 1,500 meters, sometimes dancing wildly in the wind. Instruments on the ground and up on towers monitored the breath of the jungle day and night as it came off the mud, the debris, the living forest, and then rose up through the canopy.</p>
        <p>''Plants do extremely weird things - they throw off gases and shed particles from their leaves that are one-thousandth of a millimeter in size,'' said Paulo Artaxo, a Brazilian nuclear physicist who examines such particles or ''aerosols'' in a nuclear accelerator. ''These plant aerosols are made of potassium, phosphorus, calcium, sulfur and chloride. We want to know how they are generated, change, get into the rain. Because the Amazon is so big it throws tons of these into the air.''</p>
        <p>Working from a 45-meter tower, where he watched green, red and blue macaws skim along the treetops, Steven Wofsy of Harvard University found that gas emissions could be identified and measured; he was able to quantify nitrogen produced in the tropical soil. Substantial Emissions</p>
        <p>''Nitrous oxide is an important gas influencing the ozone layer in the stratosphere,'' he said. ''We found the emissions in the ocean and the Northern Hemisphere to be very small. They are very substantial here.'' But to infer the forest's total emissions, he said, would be complicated. ''Heavy rains have a great effect on the soil,'' he said. ''We found the emissions shut down and could take two days to come back up again.''</p>
        <p>In the silent understory, a slender metal structure holding up a solar panel and a radio transmitter incongruously competed for light with trees a hundred feet high. ''This is beaming climate data, first up to a satellite, then to Boulder, Colorado,'' said James Hoell, a NASA project manager.</p>
        <p>Experimenters have registered some of the purest air and rainwater on record, testifying to the jungle's cleansing efficiency.</p>
        <p>Dr. Andreae's measurements of the forest sulfur cycle led him to suggest that natural systems, like the forest, do not produce high sulfur emissions. ''Emission of hydrogen sulfide and other sulfurs we found here were not only very low,'' he said, ''they were 10 times lower than the extrapolations people had made in the U.S.'' from incomplete data.</p>
        <p>For such experiments, instruments had to be specially adapted or designed. ''Equipment available was suited for polluted atmospheres,'' said Dr. Andreae. ''Here you can be measuring concentrations a thousand times lower. Much of the rain was clean as distilled water.''</p>
        <p>Equally striking, he said, was the rain's high acidity in earlier tests in the dry season. The acid levels resembled those in acid rain in the United States, but these naturally produced acids, in contrast with those deriving from industrial pollution, quickly break down, he said.</p>
        <p>Many expedition scientists were excited by their more sophisticated sensing of ozone, the understanding of which is a fundamental goal of this NASA program. While ozone provides a shield against radiation in the stratosphere, it is considered a pollutant at the earth's surface.</p>
        <p>Burnings to clear forests and fields produced a lot of ozone in the dry season, said Dr. Harriss. ''But the rain forest is unique in destroying the polluting ozone. When it comes in contact with a surface like a leaf, it oxydizes and is consumed.''</p>
        <p>Ozone concentrations of 4 parts per billion found here over extended periods in the wet season, he said, were among the lowest in the world. ''In any big city it is 10 to l00 times higher,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The most dramatic experiments were conducted on the plump 1961 Electra, an ''electronic fleamarket'' containing a new system of lasers, mirrors and telescopes, uniquely capable of detecting ozone and other particles from the ground up to 40,000 feet. Its creator, Edward V. Browell of NASA, used the data to make color charts of atmospheric levels.</p>
        <p>As the Electra circled low over the forest, turbulence and 90-degree heat caused by computers and compressors made the passengers weary. The discomfort was offset by majestic views of nature's lushest stronghold - the Amazon basin, encompassing seven million square kilometers of jungle, savannas and wetlands and a grid of 1,100 rivers.</p>
        <p>Also in view were the widening scars of land stripped bare for cattle and sugar cane - harbingers of a trend that, if unchecked, will ravage much of the rain forest, altering the world's atmosphere as well as destroying an unparalleled natural treasure.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
