<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DOZENS OF NATIONS REACH AGREEMENT TO PROTECT OZONE</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="75204"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MONTREAL (QUEBEC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN ECONOMIC COMMUNITY (EEC) (COMMON MARKET)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Quebec/Montreal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Quebec</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19870917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFDE133BF934A2575AC0A961948260" item-length="1335" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DOZENS OF NATIONS REACH AGREEMENT TO PROTECT OZONE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>MONTREAL, Sept. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Hailing a milestone in international cooperation to safeguard the environment, delegates from rich and poor nations approved an agreement today intended to protect the earth's fragile ozone shield.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Hailing a milestone in international cooperation to safeguard the environment, delegates from rich and poor nations approved an agreement today intended to protect the earth's fragile ozone shield.</p>
        <p>Hailing a milestone in international cooperation to safeguard the environment, delegates from rich and poor nations approved an agreement today intended to protect the earth's fragile ozone shield.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement, participating nations will first freeze and later reduce consumption of widely used chemicals that, according to emerging scientific consensus, destroy ozone molecules in the upper atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The ozone shields the earth by blocking some ultraviolet radiation from the sun. Any increase in that radiation resulting from a thinning of the ozone layer will cause skin cancer and other harm to humans and damage crops, forests and other natural systems, scientists say. 'Historically Significant'</p>
        <p>''This is perhaps the most historically significant international environmental agreement,'' said Deputy Assistant Secretary of State Richard E. Benedick, the chief United States negotiator here.</p>
        <p>''For the first time the international community has initiated controls on production of an economically valuable commodity before there was tangible evidence of damage.''</p>
        <p>Environmentalists here, while praising the agreement, expressed concern that it did not go far enough to restrict emissions of the damaging chemicals. #24 Nations Sign Protocol Twenty-four nations plus the European Community signed the protocol today. Forty-nine countries signed a document approving the meeting's actions, but some - including the Soviet Union - did not sign the protocol itself, in many cases because delegates did not have the authority.</p>
        <p>Before coming into force, the agreement must be ratified by at least 11 nations, representing at least two-thirds of global use of the chemicals. United Nations officials here said they expected all major producing nations to ratify it.</p>
        <p>The chemicals, called chlorofluorocarbons or CFC's, are used in a wide variety of applications including air-conditioning and refrigeration, aerosol sprays, foam insulation, packaging and solvents. Industry representatives here estimated that annual world production is about $2.2 billion but that industries that use them now have annual sales of many billions of dollars.</p>
        <p>Lee M. Thomas, Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, who signed the protocol for the United States, said the agreement on the use of the chemicals ''has the potential to serve as a model for other international actions as we increasingly learn there are global environmental problems that have to be dealt with on a global scale.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Benedick, the chief negotiator, noted that while the agreement was reached only after ''very complex and difficult'' scientific, economic and geographic issues were resolved, ''it shows that the world community can sit down and engage in international risk assessment and risk management.''</p>
        <p>These are the major provisions of the protocol:</p>
        <p>* In 1989, when it takes effect, participating nations are to freeze use of chlorofluorocarbons at levels of 1986.</p>
        <p>* By 1994, the consumption must be reduced by 20 percent.</p>
        <p>* By 1999, consumption is to be cut 30 percent more, for a total of 50 percent of 1986 levels.</p>
        <p>* Use of halons, chemicals used as fire suppressants, is to be frozen at 1986 levels by 1994, but reductions would not be required. Allowance for Developing Nations</p>
        <p>While all of the developed countries must limit and then roll back chlorofluorocarbon consumption, the protocol allows developing countries to increase their use if it will help their economic development. To meet possible needs of poorer countries, producing countries would be able to increase their annual production of CFC's by as much as 10 percent a year over the next 10 years.</p>
        <p>Thus, while all of the major producing countries are expected to adhere to the protocol, the decline in total emissions of the chemicals will depend on how much is used by poor countries.</p>
        <p>United States officials here, however, said that because the tough restrictions on CFC use would force industry to develop safe alternatives quickly, it was just as likely that the chemicals could be forced off the market by substitutes even more rapidly than envisioned by the protocol. U.S. Bars CFC's in Aerosols</p>
        <p>The United States, along with Canada and Scandanavian countries, voluntarily ended the use of CFC's in aerosol sprays in the 1970's. But other industrial countries, including Japan and those in the European Community, continued to use them. Industry representatives here said those countries would be able to meet their obligations under the protocol almost entirely through abandoning the aerosols.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mustafa K. Tolba, the executive director of the United Nations Environment Program, who convened the negotiations, has said he would call an emergency meeting to reopen the protocol if new scientific evidence indicated stronger action was needed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thomas of the E.P.A. said further action against the global warming problem, caused by emissions of carbon dioxide, chlorofluorocarbons and other gases, was a likely candidate for future international cooperation.</p>
        <p>A scientific expedition is now examining the ozone hole that appears over the Antarctic each September and is expected to report its findings before the end of the year. Scientists are not yet sure whether that hole is caused by man-made chemicals, but in any case, worry about a gradual worldwide thinning of the ozone layer lay behind today's agreement.</p>
        <p>Some of the impetus for the agreement came from the chlorofluorocarbon industry in the United States, which was facing the prospect of regulatory action by Congress and thus a competitive disadvantage in world markets. Comment From Industry</p>
        <p>Kevin Fay, executive director of the Alliance for Responsible CFC Policy, a United States industry group, called the agreement a ''significant step.'' But he also said that the schedule for compliance seemed to be ''too tight'' and that the industry would have to examine the agreement closely to see if it gave the United States ''a level playing field'' in world markets.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists here praised the agreement as a major step in dealing with the threat to ozone and a precedent for future action.</p>
        <p>David Wirth, a lawyer for the Natural Resources Defense Council, an American environmental group, said, ''Lee Thomas and the United States deserve a lot of credit for proposing this agreement and for following up with measures that got the agreement here.'' Such praise for a Reagan Administration environmental official from an environmentalist is rare.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Wirth and other environmentalists said the agreement was not strong enough to give adequate protection to the ozone layer and included too many loopholes, including the special provisions for the developing countries and permission to the Soviet Union to complete CFC-producing plants now under construction or under contract.</p>
        <p>The environmentalists contend that an 85 percent reduction in CFC's over the next five years is necessary to stabilize the ozone layer. E.P.A. Forecasts Gains</p>
        <p>But officials of the Environmental Protection Agency said the protocol would dramatically reduce radiation damage.</p>
        <p>They said the agency's computer models indicated that if the actions required by the protocol were observed, they would avert 132 million cases of skin cancer and 27 million deaths from skin cancer that would otherwise have occurred among people born before 2075.</p>
        <p>Even with the new controls, there is expected to be a 2 percent depletion of the ozone layer by the middle of the next century. This will cause some 7 million extra skin cancer cases among people born between now and 2075, according an an estimate by Canada's Environment Ministry.</p>
        <p>The destruction of the ozone layer by chlorofluorocarbons was first hypothesized 23 years ago by two American scientists, F. Sherwood Rowland and Mario J. Molina. As recently as a year ago, many of the major CFC-producing nations opposed any stringent control on production and use of the chemicals.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
