<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deaver Prosecutor Terms Allegations False</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1987" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="83553"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1987"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOBBYING AND LOBBYISTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">JUSTICE, DEPARTMENT OF</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEYMOUR, WHITNEY NORTH JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEAVER, MICHAEL K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOTLIEB, ALLAN E (AMB)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19871017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3DE163BF934A25753C1A961948260" item-length="734" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deaver Prosecutor Terms Allegations False</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Whitney North Seymour Jr., the special prosecutor, today accused the Justice Department and Canada of orchestrating ''false accusations'' about his attempt to persuade the Canadian Ambassador to testify at the perjury trial of Michael K. Deaver, the former White House aide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Whitney North Seymour Jr., the special prosecutor, today accused the Justice Department and Canada of orchestrating ''false accusations'' about his attempt to persuade the Canadian Ambassador to testify at the perjury trial of Michael K. Deaver, the former White House aide.</p>
        <p>Whitney North Seymour Jr., the special prosecutor, today accused the Justice Department and Canada of orchestrating ''false accusations'' about his attempt to persuade the Canadian Ambassador to testify at the perjury trial of Michael K. Deaver, the former White House aide.</p>
        <p>In a court filing on the eve of Mr. Deaver's trial, Mr. Seymour charged that Canada and the Justice Department were waging ''a P.R. campaign'' in response to his Oct. 2 letter urging Ambassador Allan E. Gotlieb to waive diplomatic immunity and testify.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour's letter stated that without Mr. Gotlieb's testimony he would be forced to emphasize ''the unlawful acts engaged in by Deaver'' when he worked as a $105,000-a-year lobbyist for Canada. Responding to what he called a ''partisan document'' filed by the Justice Department, Mr. Seymour denied that he was threatening to embarrass Canada when Mr. Deaver goes on trial next week.</p>
        <p>''The letter did not contain a threat but a statement of fact, and an invitation to work things out to mutual advantage,'' Mr. Seymour said in papers filed with Federal District Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson, who will preside at Mr. Deaver's trial. 'Unpleasant Truth' at Trial</p>
        <p>''Canada decided instead to attempt to make the letter a cause celebre, conceivably to divert attention from the unpleasant truth which they now realize will emerge at trial,'' Mr. Seymour said.</p>
        <p>''The result has been much colorful publicity, false accusations against this office and unwarranted application to this court,'' Mr. Seymour said of the Justice Department's motion on Thursday that he be admonished against trying to ''threaten, embarrass or punish the Canadian Government for asserting the immunity of its diplomats.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Deaver, the former deputy White House chief of staff, is charged with lying to a grand jury and a House subcommittee that investigated allegations that his lobbying violated conflict-of-interest laws.</p>
        <p>Among other things, Mr. Deaver is charged with lying when he said he could not recall a Jan. 5, 1985 luncheon he had with Mr. Gotlieb and his wife, Sondra. Mr. Deaver is also accused of lying when he said he was not involved with the decision to select Drew Lewis as the United States envoy to Canada on the issue of acid rain.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour had said he intended to introduce evidence that Mr. Deaver violated conflict-of-interest laws when he met with Mr. Lewis and Mr. Gotlieb while working for Canada. Protest Over Subpoenas</p>
        <p>The special prosecutor provoked a furious diplomatic protest last May when had subpoenas served on the Gotliebs at the Canadian Embassy. The State Department quickly joined Canada's successful fight to quash the subpoenas on the ground that the Gotliebs were protected by diplomatic immunity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour said his private letter to Stuart Pierson, an attorney representing the Canadian Embassy, ''was entirely proper, notwithstanding the reckless charges of the representatives of the Department of Justice in the papers and in related public statements.''</p>
        <p>The prosecutor called the Justice Department's motion ''an inexcusable attempt to embroil the court in a political controversy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Seymour accused the department of concocting a ''complete fabrication'' when it asserted that he had violated an understanding made last spring with the State Department to use diplomatic channels to contact Canada.</p>
        <p>The prosecutor said he had extensive discussions with Mr. Pierson last spring, when the embassy's attorney indicated Mr. Gotlieb was considering testifying voluntarily.</p>
        <p>He said it was from Mr. Pierson, not the State Department, ''that our office later learned that the Government of Canada had decided not to permit Ambassador Gotlieb to testify at the Deaver trial.''</p>
        <p>He said, ''We have never been requested by Mr. Pierson, by the State Department, or by the Department of Justice to cease dealing with Mr. Pierson in connection with preparations for trial of the Deaver case or to send our communications on that subject by any other route than to Mr. Pierson.''</p>
        <p>A Justice Department spokesman, Patrick Korten, apologized for suggesting that Mr. Seymour had violated an understanding with the State Department about contacting Canada.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Korten rejected Mr. Seymour's demand that he apologize for saying the special prosecutor had violated Justice Department regulations by directly contacting Canada.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
