<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ANSWERS TO QUIZ</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="50" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="170400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">QUESTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4D71F3FF930A2575BC0A96E948260" item-length="375" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ANSWERS TO QUIZ</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  Questions appear on page 14.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  Questions appear on page 14.</p>
        <p>Questions appear on page 14.</p>
        <p>1. There are two kinds of cruciverbalists, as crossword puzzle makers refer to themselves: the ''new wave,'' which says puzzles should reflect the ''living language'' of most Americans, including brand names, and slang, and the old school, which insists on traditional language.</p>
        <p>2. The United States' failure to pay the United Nations $467 million in back dues endangers the peace efforts.</p>
        <p>3. There is concern about bringing the case before the Supreme Court because of Justice Anthony M. Kennedy, who has never ruled on an abortion case, and might cast the rucial fifth vote to restrict abortion rights for minors or even adult women.</p>
        <p>4. The Governor said he believed opposition to the desegrated housing plan was based on class, not racism.</p>
        <p>5. Showing the Arab world that reaching a comprehensive peace without Jordan is impossible.</p>
        <p>6. The artist's unwitting use of Lithol Red, an unstable pigment, as the dominant color in the murals resulted in canvases that would fade in light.</p>
        <p>7. The church depicted on the stamp, the second Trinity Church, had not been built by July 26, 1788, the date on the painting.</p>
        <p>8. A radar-based system that detects abrupt wind shifts and alerts air controllers, who relay warnings to pilots of danger to planes taking off or landing.</p>
        <p>9. According to scientists, the fires account for at least one-tenth of the global output of man-made carbon dioxide, which is believed to be causing a warming of the earth, as a greenhouse might do.</p>
        <p>10. Natalia Makarova danced with the Kirov Ballet, becoming the first Russian dancer allowed to perform with a Soviet company after emigrating to the West.</p>
        <p>11. The Commissioner asked the police Review Board to create a special panel of its members rather than use staff personnel for the inquiry.</p>
        <p>12. More and more heart surgeons are using mammary arteries rather than sections of leg vein to bypass blocked coronary arteries because the mammary arteries rarely develop fatty deposits.</p>
        <p>13. Under the law to redress wrongs committed by the United States against Japanese-Americans in World War II, the Government will issue individual apologies and award $20,000 in tax-free payments to each eligible person.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
