<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Break in the Acid Rain Impasse</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="152051"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">OHIO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUOMO, MARIO M (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CELESTE, RICHARD F (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DE113FF934A35755C0A96E948260" item-length="452" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Break in the Acid Rain Impasse</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Acid rain is slowly poisoning the lakes, estuaries and forests of the Eastern Seaboard, yet Congress has been deadlocked for years over how to avert the threat. Governor Cuomo of New York and Governor Celeste of Ohio now propose an ingenious solution. By sidestepping conflicting regional interests, the two Governors may have pointed</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Acid rain is slowly poisoning the lakes, estuaries and forests of the Eastern Seaboard, yet Congress has been deadlocked for years over how to avert the threat. Governor Cuomo of New York and Governor Celeste of Ohio now propose an ingenious solution. By sidestepping conflicting regional interests, the two Governors may have pointed</p>
        <p>Acid rain is slowly poisoning the lakes, estuaries and forests of the Eastern Seaboard, yet Congress has been deadlocked for years over how to avert the threat. Governor Cuomo of New York and Governor Celeste of Ohio now propose an ingenious solution. By sidestepping conflicting regional interests, the two Governors may have pointed Congress toward resolving a long-festering issue.</p>
        <p>The principal source of acid rain is the coal-burning power plants of the Ohio Valley, which spew out acrid gases, the oxides of sulfur and nitrogen, through their tall smokestacks. Borne by westerly winds, these pollutants acidify the rain falling hundreds of miles to the east. Purifying the rain would require the Middle Western plants to burn cleaner, low-sulfur coal - thus putting miners in Ohio and West Virginia out of work - or to install expensive scrubbers. Western states resent being asked to help pay for a federally imposed cleanup, since they neither produce nor are affected by acid rain.</p>
        <p>Bills on acid rain have been blocked in the Senate by Robert Byrd of West Virginia, and in the House by John Dingell of Michigan. The deadlock in Congress has been matched by obstruction from the Administration, which disputes the seriousness of the ecological damage and opposes doing anything about acid rain except study it.</p>
        <p>The new proposal originated at a Democratic governors' conference last year, where Mr. Cuomo proposed a joint approach. In outline, the plan imposes a tax on oil imports to pay for an acid rain cleanup, amounting to half the cost of technology to reduce pollutants. The other half, and all operating costs, would be borne by ratepayers. Mr. Celeste becomes the first Middle Western Governor to endorse a major cutback in acid rain pollutants, a courageous step that changes the political complexion of the acid rain debate.</p>
        <p>The Cuomo-Celeste proposal would require oil importers to place 2 percent of their imports in the Federal strategic petroleum reserve, and to contribute a ''storage fee'' that would go into the acid rain fund. Proponents of the plan say it would increase the cost of gasoline by one cent a gallon. Besides addressing acid rain, filling the reserve more quickly would enhance energy security.</p>
        <p>The plan raises obvious questions: Why should an oil import fee pay for an acid rain cleanup? Why should all states bear the burden in higher oil prices?</p>
        <p>Still, the Cuomo-Celeste plan stands on its political merits. After years of fights between regions, two important Governors - the chief victim of acid rain and the chief perpetrator of it- have found common ground. Washington's challenge is to either adopt the Cuomo-Celeste proposal or come up with a better one.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
