<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Overpopulation Strains Earth's Resources</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="209580"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POPULATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WHELAN, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDF163BF935A15751C1A96E948260" item-length="318" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Overpopulation Strains Earth's Resources</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>It is difficult to believe that the rosy predictions Robert Whelan of Britain offers on the benefits of continued population growth (''Population and Prosperity Often Grow Together,'' letter, Dec. 13) take into consideration facts with which he is familiar.</p>
        <p>In particular, he must be aware that the prosperity England and the European Continent developed during the 19th century is believed by a number of historians to have been made possible in part by the departure of many millions of people to North and South America and Australia. Today, Ireland's economy is deteriorating because there is no longer enough emigration to relieve serious unemployment.</p>
        <p>Britain cannot supply jobs for all its people, especially in Scotland, despite the prosperity of its steel industry. A recent report says that its health care system has a backlog of more than 600,000 discretionary surgical procedures. And it is only a matter of relatively few years before Britain's drain on its nonrenewable resources of oil and gas will finish the country off, placing it at the mercy of the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries.</p>
        <p>Population experts in 1945-47 forecast that we would be able to feed five billion people, but they warned that the cost in overworking farmlands, using up nonrenewable resources and otherwise impinging harmfully on the earth's support system would be excessive. They did not take into account the ''greenhouse effect,'' which can be expected, according to a very recent computer analysis, to increase the chances of drought four or five times, and raise maximum hurricane winds to 225 miles an hour over the next 40 years.</p>
        <p>Changes in energy technology can moderate the greenhouse effect, but the benefits will be swamped if population growth isn't slowed down and then reversed to reduce the use of fuel.  FREDERICK S. LIGHTFOOT  Greenport, L.I., Dec. 13, 1988</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
