<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bronx Botanical Garden Plans an Expansion</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="121824"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATE AND LOCAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HISTORIC BUILDINGS AND SITES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRONX (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BOTANICAL GARDEN, NY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANDERSON, SUSAN HELLER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFD8113FF937A15751C0A96E948260" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bronx Botanical Garden Plans an Expansion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN HELLER ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ANDERSON, SUSAN HELLER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The New York Botanical Garden is planning an ambitious expansion that will include a new plant science center and the renovation of its landmark museum building in the Bronx to house exhibitions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The New York Botanical Garden is planning an ambitious expansion that will include a new plant science center and the renovation of its landmark museum building in the Bronx to house exhibitions.</p>
        <p>The New York Botanical Garden is planning an ambitious expansion that will include a new plant science center and the renovation of its landmark museum building in the Bronx to house exhibitions.</p>
        <p>The $21.4 million project, the largest expansion since the botanical garden was established in 1891, reflects its growing stature as one of the world's premier plant research institutions.</p>
        <p>The project will include a new 75,000-square-foot wing to house the Herbarium, a collection of more than five million plant specimens, and the garden's library.</p>
        <p>The four-story brick addition will adjoin the existing complex at 200th Street and Kazimiroff Boulevard. Its design, by Philip Johnson and John Burgee, echoes the 88-year-old museum building's graceful arches and elegant facade.</p>
        <p>The museum building originally housed two exhibition halls and the Herbarium. As the Herbarium's collection grew, however, it took over all the exhibition space. Relocating the Herbarium will allow the museum building to accommodate exhibitions again.</p>
        <p>The garden was founded by J. Pierpont Morgan, Cornelius Vanderbilt 2d and Andrew Carnegie, among others, primarily for study and public enjoyment. Since then, the garden's research and scientific function has grown, along with its education programs and scientific institutes.</p>
        <p>For the new wing, the city will contribute $11.4 million and the botanical garden must come up with the rest. It is seeking to raise much more - $62 million to finance the new construction and endow its various science, horticulture and education programs and its research institutes. Ground will be broken next January, and the building is expected to be finished in the summer of 1991.</p>
        <p>To minimize exposure of the Herbarium's collections, the new wing will have windows on one side only.</p>
        <p>''Horticulture is having a great renaissance,'' Dr. James M. Hester, the garden's president, said in an interview. ''The new building will allow for expansion of the library, storage of our precious collections and room for graduate students and visiting scientists.''</p>
        <p>Renovation of the museum building, a Beaux-Arts confection designed by Robert W. Gibson with Corinthian columns and a copper dome, will include refurbishing a 700-seat auditorium, the creation of new classrooms and expansion of the garden's retail operation.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hester is to announce the plans tonight in the Enid B. Haupt Conservatory, a glass structure modeled after the Crystal Palace in London, which houses 1,000 rare and fragile plants. #25,000 Species The most visible aspect of the botanical garden is its explosion of flowers and plants on 250 acres in the north-central Bronx, where 25,000 species bloom. On a second site in Millbrook, N.Y., the Mary Flagler Cary Arboretum occupies 2,000 acres of forest and wetlands open to the public.</p>
        <p>The garden's primary research activity is the discovery, classification and study of the earth's one million-plus plant species through expeditions. The plants serve in research that may offer new sources of food and energy and cures for diseases, as well as ways to use plants to curb pollution.</p>
        <p>In the early 1980's, Dr. Hester, the former president of New York University, established two institutes to tie plant research to human problems.</p>
        <p>The Institute of Economic Botany studies plants used by people. It has contracts with pharmaceutical companies to collect plants for medical experiments.</p>
        <p>The Institute of Ecosystem Systems examines ''how man's activities are affecting the plant world,'' Dr. Hester said. ''When we're increasing awareness of how damaging man is to the environment, it's our job to be as active as possible in the public debate on things like acid rain.'' Famed Explorers Represented</p>
        <p>The garden's education program reaches more than 54,000 children a year. In the Children's Garden, they plant and harvest their own vegetables.</p>
        <p>In cooperation with the City University of New York, the garden enables students to earn master's degrees and doctorates in biology. It also runs undergraduate programs with Lehman College and Bronx Community College.</p>
        <p>A key resource for its programs is the Herbarium, one of the world's most comprehensive. Specimens are gathered on expeditions, dried, preserved, pasted onto papers and stored in cabinets, away from light, dust and insects.</p>
        <p>Specimens from Captain Cook's first voyage in 1768 are preserved in the Herbarium's lockers. There are specimens from the Lewis and Clark expedition, and an 1835 collection by David Douglas, who gave his name to a fir tree.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
