<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dole Makes Environment An Issue in New Hampshire</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="115489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1988</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRIMARIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW HAMPSHIRE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOLE, ROBERT J (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KEMP, JACK F (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOYD, GERALD M</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">POLITICS PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1D7123AF930A35751C0A96E948260" item-length="633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dole Makes Environment An Issue in New Hampshire</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD M. BOYD, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BOYD, GERALD M</byline>
      <dateline>CONCORD, N.H., Feb. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Senator Bob Dole unveiled broad elements of an environmental policy today while vigorously attacking the Reagan Administration's enforcement efforts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Senator Bob Dole unveiled broad elements of an environmental policy today while vigorously attacking the Reagan Administration's enforcement efforts.</p>
        <p>Senator Bob Dole unveiled broad elements of an environmental policy today while vigorously attacking the Reagan Administration's enforcement efforts.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the Kansas Senator targeted his two leading rivals for the Republican Presidential nomination, Vice President Bush and Representative Jack F. Kemp, for increasingly testy verbal sparring over leadership ability and negative campaign advertising.</p>
        <p>Standing on the porch of St. Paul's School here, Mr. Dole challenged Mr. Bush to debate to ''one hour, two hours or two days'' the question of who could better lead the nation. Offers to 'Explain Leadership'</p>
        <p>''I would be happy to talk to him and explain leadership if he has the time,'' said Mr. Dole, who trails the Vice President in this state.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole also went after Mr. Kemp, the Congressman from upstate New York who is in third place in New Hampshire, but who has been gaining ground in recent polls. The Senator assailed Mr. Kemp's television commercials that imply Mr. Dole supported cutting Social Security benefits and would support an oil import fee.</p>
        <p>Accusing Mr. Kemp at one point of trying to peddle ''a bunch of trash,'' Mr. Dole said that ''it's on the borderline of unfair campaigning.'' ''It's deceptive,'' he said, explaining the 1985 Social Security vote as part of bipartisan deficit reduction plan later abandoned by Mr. Reagan. He said that he had opposed oil import fees previously and would consider a limited one now only to stabilize energy prices. Distancing From Reagan</p>
        <p>By highlighting an environmental policy during a morning speech at St. Paul's, a preparatory school here, Mr. Dole appeared to be seeking ammunition that would allow him to maintain that he was addressing issues, while Mr. Bush and other opponents are not. The candidate displayed a continued willingness to distance himself from President Reagan in some areas.</p>
        <p>Presenting what he said was a ''full panoply of environmental concerns'' his administration would address, Mr. Dole offered clear criticism of the President.</p>
        <p>''Above all, we need determined leadership that begins in the White House - and runs strongly through the Environmental Protection Agency, the Interior Department and the dozens of other Federal agencies that monitor compliance with environmental laws,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole singled out the Environmental Protection Agency saying that it had failed to follow adequately a Congressional mandate to clean up toxic waste sites, under the Superfund legislation enacted two years ago. Only 16 of 900 sites have been cleaned up fully, a record he called ''appalling.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole said also that it was ''time to admit'' that pollution caused by acid rain was a problem and ''to get to work on it.'' The issue has been a top concern of environmentalists in this state.</p>
        <p>''We don't have the luxury of waiting until we get details on the extent of the potential problem,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Acid rain is rain with a concentration of air pollutants, largely sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide from the combustion of fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole said that nitrogen oxide could be reduced by tightening emission standards on cars and that sulfur dioxides can be reduce through new technologies developed by industry and Government, which must provide some financial incentives, he said.</p>
        <p>Yet, the general thrust of the environmental policy was one Mr. Bush has championed that is designed to express Republican concern for the environment and to argue that the Democratic Party does not have a monopoly on concern for the environment.</p>
        <p>The leadership skirmish between Mr. Bush and Mr. Dole has been somewhat odd since both are steep in experience and part of the party's establishment. But it has raged with intensity especially as Monday's Iowa caucus approaches.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
