<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SAFETY BARRIERS</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="80" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="207753"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="BEAUTY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COSMETICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SKIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WELLS, LINDA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skin</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DA1F30F93BA25751C1A96E948260" item-length="771" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SAFETY BARRIERS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Linda Wells</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WELLS, LINDA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Once, the fear of wrinkles was enough to send women racing for a jar of cream. Now, the threats to skin are, well, more threatening. The diminishing ozone layer, the multitude of pollutants, the swarm of free radicals - all are being flagged by cosmetics companies as hazards to skin. It figures that a new category of products would emerge to protect skin from the environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Once, the fear of wrinkles was enough to send women racing for a jar of cream. Now, the threats to skin are, well, more threatening. The diminishing ozone layer, the multitude of pollutants, the swarm of free radicals - all are being flagged by cosmetics companies as hazards to skin. It figures that a new category of products would emerge to protect skin from the environment.</p>
        <p>Once, the fear of wrinkles was enough to send women racing for a jar of cream. Now, the threats to skin are, well, more threatening. The diminishing ozone layer, the multitude of pollutants, the swarm of free radicals - all are being flagged by cosmetics companies as hazards to skin. It figures that a new category of products would emerge to protect skin from the environment.</p>
        <p>Consider the names of these products: Skin Defender, Detoxifying Lotion, Immunage UV Defense Cream. At the Biotherm counter are stacks of cards telling the customer how to ''city proof'' skin.</p>
        <p>The message here is that the environment is hostile, especially to skin. When Estee Lauder recently introduced its Skin Defender lotion, ''We wanted to focus on an imperfect world, and on being assaulted,'' says Walter Smith, vice president of research and development. The cosmetics industry seems to be borrowing tactics used in antismoking, antidrinking and antidrug campaigns. For instance, printed on the box holding Elizabeth Arden's UV Defense Cream is a note that, in look and language, resembles the Surgeon General's warning on a pack of cigarettes. This one tells of the link between sun exposure and premature aging and skin cancer, and says that the product may help reduce this risk.</p>
        <p>''I think consumers fear the environment,'' says Robert Lukey, manager of marketing development, treatment, at Elizabeth Arden. ''There's an increase in that fear. The press is filled with it.''</p>
        <p>The greatest environmental hazard to skin is still the sun. Along with the usual sunblocks, many of the moisturizers meant for everyday use are being bolstered with sunscreens. ''Years ago, putting a sunscreen in a moisturizer was an added plus,'' says Margaret Sharkey, vice president and general manager of Biotherm. ''Now it's almost mandatory.'' Most of these moisturizers contain only mild doses of sunscreens with SPFs of 2 or 4. This is probably sufficient to protect against the kind of sun exposure ordinarily experienced on a workday in the city. But many dermatologists believe that additional protection is prudent, and suggest using a highly protective sunscreen every day. To that end, Elizabeth Arden's UV Defense Cream has an SPF of 15, as does Chanel's Total Protection Moisture Cream. ''We once thought that the danger was sunbathing,'' says Margaret McAuliffe-Edelman, vice president of marketing at Intelligent Skincare. Not necessarily: ''It's walking down the street, it's being outside. Frightening or not, you have to face that.''</p>
        <p>A few companies are tackling man-made environmental frights, such as pollution.</p>
        <p>''Most people's skin is irritated by things they don't recognize,'' says Dr. Smith. ''Fibers, chemicals in the air, pollution. We know that exposure to the sun causes damage even when it doesn't cause redness. The same is true of other kinds of irritants. Gradually, the skin deteriorates.'' Estee Lauder's proposed solution to these irritants is Skin Defender, a lotion that relieves stinging and burning and forms a barrier against other assaults.</p>
        <p>This elixir also pushes the hot buttons in skin care. Skin Defender contains vitamin E and BHT - antioxidants that seek out and neutralize free radicals, which form as a result of such ''insults'' as sunlight, tobacco smoke, chemical carcinogens and ozone in the air. Because free radicals destroy certain cells, including those in the skin, some scientists believe that eliminating free radicals may help to prevent skin sagging and wrinkling. But no study has proven that a cream fortified with antioxidants can prevent the destruction of the skin's connective tissue, according to Dr. Douglas Darr, assistant medical research professor in the division of dermatology at Duke University Medical Center.</p>
        <p>That hasn't stopped cosmetics companies from listing antioxidants among their products' beneficial ingredients. On the contrary. Prescriptives recently poured additional antioxidants in the form of vitamin E into its Line Preventor. Almay is about to bring out the Stress Moisture Supplement with vitamin E. And Intelligent Skincare added the Detoxifying Lotion - a clear solution that contains the antioxidant vitamins A and E - to its recently revised line of products.</p>
        <p>Many of these products alert consumers to the dangers lurking in the air. ''I think we're going to be in worse shape as time goes on,'' says Dr. Smith. ''If the environment keeps changing, today's products might not be able to help us tomorrow.'' By playing on the fear of the environment, cosmetics companies may well propel women to buy new and ever more expensive creams and lotions.</p>
        <p>BEAUTY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
