<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S.-Soviet Panel Formed to Study Ecology</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="206481"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SCIENCES, NATIONAL ACADEMY OF (LENINGRAD)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SCIENCES, NATIONAL ACADEMY OF, AND NATIONAL RESEARCH COUNCIL</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4D9143FF937A25751C1A96E948260" item-length="669" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S.-Soviet Panel Formed to Study Ecology</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The national science academies of the United States and the Soviet Union, warning that the earth's ''ecological security'' is now endangered, announced today the formation of a joint Committee on Global Ecology Concerns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The national science academies of the United States and the Soviet Union, warning that the earth's ''ecological security'' is now endangered, announced today the formation of a joint Committee on Global Ecology Concerns.</p>
        <p>The national science academies of the United States and the Soviet Union, warning that the earth's ''ecological security'' is now endangered, announced today the formation of a joint Committee on Global Ecology Concerns.</p>
        <p>The new committee will identify and investigate threats to the global environment and report its conclusions, along with policy recommendations, to their Governments and to international organizations.</p>
        <p>At a news conference held in Irvine, Calif., and carried by telephone to Washington, members of both academies said that the formation of the committee indicated the growing seriousness with which degradation of the global environment is viewed by scientists. They said that they regarded the new group as equal in importance to an existing joint Committee on International Security and Arms Control.</p>
        <p>A member of the Soviet academy, Igor M. Makarov, said through an interpreter that the need to control nuclear arms and to save the global environment ''are the most important problems that will influence the survival of mankind.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Frank Press, president of the National Academy of Sciences in Washington, also announced today that the Soviet academy had accepted an offer by the American academy to send a team of earthquake experts to Armenia to cooperate on a scientific and technological fact-finding project.</p>
        <p>The American team will consist of 16 experts in seismology, architecture, structural engineering, geotechnical engineering, industrial installations, lifelines, emergency planning and rescue operations.</p>
        <p>The team will leave for the Soviet Union in several days, Dr. Press said.</p>
        <p>Among the issues the panel will consider are global warming and global energy and biological chemistry cycles, depletion of the stratospheric ozone that shields the earth from harmful radiation from the sun, loss of biological diversity and the impact of population growth on the global ecology. 'Early-Warning Mechanism'</p>
        <p>A statement issued by the two academies today said, ''The consequences of the rapid growth of our population coupled with global economic development now pose a significant threat to our continued existence.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Press said, ''The special mission of the committee will be to provide an early warning mechanism for identifying long-range environmental and ecological problems and bringing them to the attention of the United States and Soviet Governments.'' Dr. Press said the panel would be able to offer its policy recommendations ''with some authority'' to their Governments and to international governments, who could then ''deal effectively with these problems before it is too late and we have irreversibly damaged the earth's ecosystems.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Peter Raven, director of the Missouri Botanical Garden and a member of the American delegation, noted that Soviet leader Mikhail S. Gorbachev and President-elect Bush have already remarked on the seriousness of the threats facing the global environment.</p>
        <p>Dr. Raven pointed out that the United States and the Soviet Union account for about 40 percent of total global consumption of energy and thus contribute about 40 percent of the gases, mainly carbon dioxide and other gases released by burning of fossil fuels, that are causing the greenhouse effect by trapping heat from the sun and causing the earth's surface to warm.</p>
        <p>Another very urgent problem, Dr. Raven said, is the loss of the earth's biological diversity because of the rapid rate of extinction of plant and animal species as their habitat is destroyed for economic development. He said the current extinction rate is ''a thousand times the normal rate.''</p>
        <p>At the news conference, Dr. Makarov thanked the American academy and American citizens for their quick offer of material and scientific aid after the devastating earthquake.</p>
        <p>Dr. Makarov also said Soviet scientists had predicted the earthquake ''long before it happened.''</p>
        <p>The first joint meeting of the panel is scheduled to be held in the first half of 1989 in the Soviet Union.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
