<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Theory Is Unveiled on Breaking Barrier of Electricity Resistance</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="182780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRICITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUPERCONDUCTORS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CHEMICAL SOCIETY, AMERICAN</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GODDARD, WILLIAM 3D (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHEN, GUANHUA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUO, YUEJIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LANGLOIS, JEAN-MARC</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electricity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1D8143AF935A1575AC0A96E948260" item-length="1401" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Theory Is Unveiled on Breaking Barrier of Electricity Resistance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Sept. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A team of scientists from the California Institute of Technology announced today that they had developed a long-sought comprehensive theory explaining key aspects of superconductivity, the phenomenon in which certain materials are able to conduct electricity without resistance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A team of scientists from the California Institute of Technology announced today that they had developed a long-sought comprehensive theory explaining key aspects of superconductivity, the phenomenon in which certain materials are able to conduct electricity without resistance.</p>
        <p>A team of scientists from the California Institute of Technology announced today that they had developed a long-sought comprehensive theory explaining key aspects of superconductivity, the phenomenon in which certain materials are able to conduct electricity without resistance.</p>
        <p>The theory appears to rule out the possibility that currently known superconductors could ever be made to work at room temperature, a requirement for many of the technological marvels envisioned when researchers recently discovered the new class of materials that are superconductors at higher temperatures than previously seen. Search for Better Materials</p>
        <p>But the Caltech scientists predicted that their theory, based on complex calculations involving the quantum mechanics of bonds between atoms, would eventually guide experimenters to the development of materials that would become superconductive at about 55 degrees below zero Fahrenheit, warmer than dry ice and far warmer than the temperature of 243 degrees below zero required by the best existing materials. Visions of Levitated Trains</p>
        <p>An outline of the theory was presented at the annual meeting in Los Angeles of the American Chemical Society by Dr. William A. Goddard 3d, a professor of chemistry and applied physics at Caltech, and three of his graduate students, Guanhua Chen, Yuejin Guo and Jean-Marc Langlois.</p>
        <p>Superconductivity has already been exploited in many scientific instruments, astronomical sensors and such clinical diagnostic techniques as nuclear magnetic resonance, which is used to view the brain and other previously inaccessible parts of the body.</p>
        <p>But the theory presented today may disappoint engineers and others who hoped recent advances would lead to trains levitated and propelled by superconducting magnets or to power lines in which current flows without loss.</p>
        <p>The theory described by Dr. Goddard faces challenges from rival theories, however. In the weeklong gathering that began today, 23 scientists, including 11 theorists, are to present their findings and views on the nature of high-temperature superconductivity.</p>
        <p>Among them is Dr. Richard Martin of the Los Alamos National Laboratory, who outlined a theory today that depends on the electrical charge structure of superconducting materials, rather than on the magnetic orientation effects essential to the Caltech theory.</p>
        <p>Dr. Martin and Dr. Goddard said in interviews that experiments in the next few years will almost certainly settle which kind of theory explains the most. But Dr. Martin added that it might turn out that different forms of superconductivity could be explained only in terms of different theories.</p>
        <p>''This is a hot issue and there will be no lack of experiments,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Superconductivity was discovered in 1911 when it was found that certain metals completely lost resistance to electricity when chilled by liquid helium to a temperature only a few degrees above absolute zero, the point at which all molecular motion stops. That is about 459 degrees below zero Fahrenheit.</p>
        <p>In the past few years, experimenters have hit upon a dozen or so compounds that become superconductive at higher temperatures. But despite these laboratory successes, theorists have been unable to explain the phenomenon or to offer guidance for future experiments. Caltech's theory may for the first time fill this gap, its authors say.</p>
        <p>Dr. Goddard said in an interview that the new Caltech ''magnon-pairing mechanism'' theory calculates superconducting temperatures for compounds containing copper oxide, a component of all the new superconductors. These theoretical calculations closely match the results of actual experiments, he said. Need for General Theory</p>
        <p>Dr. Paul C. W. Chu of the University of Houston, a leader in the field, said in a telephone interview that although he had not yet had an opportunity to study the new theory, ''if it can really predict the conditions of superconductivity, it is very important.'' A satisfactory theory of superconductivity must be as general, simple and predictive as possible, he said, ''and since the Caltech theory is described in one single equation, it sounds simple enough to meet my criteria.''</p>
        <p>The Caltech group expects experimenters to test its theory in various ways. Dr. Goddard suggested that one approach would be to squeeze certain superconductors from different directions. The theory predicts that compression in one direction would raise the temperature at which the substance becomes superconducting, while compression from another direction would lower it.</p>
        <p>He said calculations based on the new theory show that laboratory experimenters have a long way to go before reaching the theoretical limiting temperature his group has calculated for copper oxide superconductors. The theory predicts that some variant of a copper oxide compound could one day be discovered that would become superconductive at a temperature as high as 54.7 degrees below zero Fahrenheit, he said. Uses in Motors and Computers</p>
        <p>This temperature is well above that of the dry ice (frozen carbon dioxide) often used to refrigerate ice cream and certain drugs, 108 degrees below zero Fahrenheit. A superconductor that could be chilled by something as readily available as dry ice would find many applications in devices used to operate motors and computers and to measure very weak magnetic fields and faint infrared radiation.</p>
        <p>But, while cheaper to operate than a superconductor requiring liquid helium or liquid nitrogen, it would still be much more expensive than a room-temperature superconductor requiring no refrigeration at all. For very large-scale applications of superconductivity, such as power lines and magnetically levitated trains, any need for refrigeration might be prohibitively expensive.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Goddard offered hope that new systems of superconductors, some possibly based on copper sulfide rather than copper oxide, may be permitted by his theory. Their transition temperatures or temperatures below which they become superconductors could be much higher than those of any compounds now known. Basis of Theory</p>
        <p>The Caltech theory is based on the fact that copper and oxygen atoms in the new superconductors are arrayed in a checkerboard pattern, linked into a grid by electrons. Very complex quantum mechanical calculations using supercomputers permitted the group to analyze the electronic bonds that link the atoms.</p>
        <p>Current high-temperature superconductors are all based on stacked grids of copper and oxygen atoms, which are interspersed like the red and black squares of a checkerboard. A few of the atoms in such a grid must be replaced by atoms of other elements that disturb the regularity of the pattern.</p>
        <p>As Dr. Goddard explained it, the copper atoms in the grid behave like little magnets with north and south poles. Ordinarily, the oxygen atoms in the grid are not magnetic. Two magnetic copper atoms separated by one non-magnetic oxygen atom tend to orient themselves in opposite directions.</p>
        <p>But when a checkerboard grid of copper and oxygen atoms becomes superconducting, he said, a few of the oxygen atoms temporarily lose one of their two bonding electrons, and when this happens, the oxygen atoms themselves become magnetic. A magnetic oxygen atom situated in a grid between two magnetic copper atoms causes the adjacent copper atoms to line up with each other as well as with the oxygen. Microscopic Pocket Is Created</p>
        <p>This creates a microscopic pocket called a ''hole,'' in which any nearby electron will almost instantly jump. When the electron fills the ''hole,'' however, it creates another hole in the space it vacated, and this in turn must be filled by another electron. In a superconductive state, this process continues indefinitely, with the oxygen atoms acting as carriers of the hole.</p>
        <p>''Before superconductivity is established, Dr. Goddard said, ''the copper-oxygen grid is like a checkerboard that is fully occupied by the players' pieces. It is gridlocked, and no piece can move. But once a hole is created, another piece may be moved into the hole, and the process repeats itself indefinitely.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Goddard and his colleagues published two papers in the journal Science last February describing their preliminary calculations, but today's report greatly extended the applicability of the theory and presents a unifying equation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
