<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSH PICKS DOCTOR WHO WAS CHIDED ON ABORTION VIEWS</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="208743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CABINETS AND SUB-CABINETS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HEALTH AND HUMAN SERVICES, DEPARTMENT OF</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERIOR, DEPARTMENT OF THE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">TRANSPORTATION, DEPARTMENT OF (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">VETERANS AFFAIRS, DEPARTMENT OF</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, LOUIS W (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LUJAN, MANUEL JR (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REILLY, WILLIAM K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DERWINSKI, EDWARD J (UNDER SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SKINNER, SAMUEL K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOYD, GERALD M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DE1539F930A15751C1A96E948260" item-length="1357" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSH PICKS DOCTOR WHO WAS CHIDED ON ABORTION VIEWS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD M. BOYD, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BOYD, GERALD M</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President-elect Bush, acting after days of fierce controversy over the abortion issue, today announced his selection of Dr. Louis W. Sullivan, the president of the Morehouse School of Medicine in Atlanta, to be Secretary of Health and Human Services.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President-elect Bush, acting after days of fierce controversy over the abortion issue, today announced his selection of Dr. Louis W. Sullivan, the president of the Morehouse School of Medicine in Atlanta, to be Secretary of Health and Human Services.</p>
        <p>President-elect Bush, acting after days of fierce controversy over the abortion issue, today announced his selection of Dr. Louis W. Sullivan, the president of the Morehouse School of Medicine in Atlanta, to be Secretary of Health and Human Services.</p>
        <p>In choosing Dr. Sullivan and four others for top posts, the President-elect sought to fulfill his promise to place ''new faces'' in the top echelons of government. Also named today were William K. Reilly to be Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, Samuel K. Skinner to be Secretary of Transportation, Representative Manuel Lujan Jr. of New Mexico to be Interior Secretary, and former Representive Edward J. Derwinski of Illinois to be Secretary of the newly created Department of Veterans Affairs.</p>
        <p>Under other circumstances the selection of Mr. Reilly, a mainstream conservationist, to head an agency that has often been at odds with environmentalists, would have been seen as the most significant appointment today. But the controversy over Dr. Sullivan had overshadowed other deliberations on filling the Cabinet. Says Views Are Alike</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's choice of Dr. Sullivan, a friend of the President-elect and his wife, Barbara, capped a troublesome selection process fueled by concerns from anti-abortion groups. Mr. Bush once again sought to assure critics that the two men's positions on abortion were similar, saying that he and Dr. Sullivan ''see eye to eye on the criticial issues facing the next Secretary of H.H.S.''  [ Excerpts from a transcript of remarks by Mr. Bush and his designees appear on page A24; profiles of the men are on page A25. ]  Dr. Sullivan's appointment had generated a firestorm of opposition after he was quoted in The Atlanta Journal and Constitution last weekend as saying women should be free to have abortions. Today, both he and Mr. Bush sought to assure anti-abortion groups that this was not Dr. Sullivan's position, and that he and Mr. Bush agreed that access to abortions should be severely limited.</p>
        <p>Reading from a prepared statement today, Dr. Sullivan said: ''I wish to emphasize that in the areas of abortion, my personal position is that I am opposed to abortion except in the case of rape, incest or threat to the life of the mother. I'm also opposed to Federal funding for abortion except in the case of a threat to the life of the mother.</p>
        <p>''This position is the same as that of President-elect Bush, with whom I agree completely.'' he said. Critics Were Mollified</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said he believed that Dr. Sullivan's comments, as well as the support of some leading Congressional opponents to abortion, should allay the concerns of the critics. Those Congressmen voiced support for Dr. Sullivan after meeting him Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The nominations sent several signals. Dr. Sullivan is the first black to named to served in the Bush Cabinet. Mr. Skinner is chairman of the Northeastern Illinois Regional Transportation Authority and has strong political ties to Mr. Bush. Mr. Derwinski, of Polish ancestry, is popular among ethnic voters, a onetime Democratic voting block that has been a target of Republicans in recent years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lujan, who did not seek re-election this year after 10 terms in Congress, is a Westerner and the second Hispanic American named to the Bush Cabinet.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly is the president of the Conservation Foundation and the World Wildlife Fund, two leading mainstream conservation organizations. Under a succession of Administrators in President Reagan's first term, the E.P.A. frequently clashed with environmentalists, who portrayed the agency as a symbol of an Administration that sided too often with business.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said that although the E.P.A. is not part of the Cabinet, ''it is an agency whose mission, in my view, is of tremendous importance to America's future.''</p>
        <p>''I'm proud to reach directly into the conservation community to find someone to lead this agency,'' the President-elect said, ''and I expect to be a very active President in protecting the environment.'' 'The Best People'</p>
        <p>In implied criticism of the Reagan Administration's approach toward environmental issues, Mr. Bush had courted voters by asserting that he would enforce environmental laws aggressively, move immediately to combat acid rain and work to clean up toxic waste sites. He also pledged to put ''the best people we can find to work on the environmental agenda,'' language critical of some Reagan Administration officials assigned to such duties, Bush aides said at the time.</p>
        <p>Asked today to assess the E.P.A. under Mr. Reagan, Mr. Reilly called it an ''effective institution'' under its current Administrator, Lee Thomas. He offered no assessment of the agency under previous Administrators in the Reagan Administration, who were frequently criticized by environmentalists.</p>
        <p>''I have given most of my career to the effort to try to promote consensus between the interests concerned with development and those concerned for protection of the environment,'' he said. ''The environmental problem of the United States is very much one of trying to insure that we have as much collaboration as possible in achieving these objectives.''</p>
        <p>But while demonstrating that he is ready to strengthen the Government's protection of the environment, Mr. Bush also made it clear that he is not prepared to prohibit the development of Federal lands altogether. He had offered such contrasting positions in the campaign when he supported a halt on drilling leases off the coast of Northern California while opposing such a ban in other coastal waters. A Shared Commitment</p>
        <p>Mr. Lujan, who served on the House Interior and Insular Affairs Committee, has had close ties to oil, coal, and timber development interests in his two decades in Congress.</p>
        <p>In announcing the selection, Mr. Bush said Mr. Lujan ''shares my commitment to finding a careful balance between the need to protect our environment and the desire to proceed with the sound development of this nation's many valuable resources.''</p>
        <p>As for the selection of Dr. Sullivan, Mr. Bush acknowledged that the abortion issue was difficult. He said at one point that the ''emotional aspects of rape and incest'' could be ''very demoralizing to the health of the mother.''</p>
        <p>''But each person reaches a very personal decision on this, and I have,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He added: ''And I'm the one that's going to set the policy as it relates to this very important issue and quite personal issue for many. And I'm the one that's going to err on the side of human life. I'm the one that's going to, if you want to make it so simplistic, be pro-life instead of pro-choice.'' Declines to Answer</p>
        <p>Dr. Sullivan, who is expected to faced intense questioning on the subject in Senate confirmation hearings, refused to answer numerous questions concerning his position, saying that it was inappropriate at this point. He insisted that Bush transition officials had not told him to remain silent.</p>
        <p>Among the issues he left unanswered were whether he believed that a woman had a right to determine if she should have an abortion, how he justified allowing some exceptions and whether women having abortions should be prosecuted. He also declined to discuss his position on fetal research.</p>
        <p>He refused to comment directly on the Atlanta newspaper article.</p>
        <p>Indicating that they would not seek to block his confirmation, anti-abortion groups nevertheless expressed disappointment with the choice.</p>
        <p>''Millions of pro-life citizens will be watching Dr. Sullivan and the Administration closely to see if the pro-life commitments of the Republican Platform and President-Bush are carried out,'' said Dr. John C. Willke, the president of the National Right to Life Committee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush still must fill two other Cabinet positions, Secretaries of Energy and Labor. He is expected to make his choices over the next day or so, although the formal announcement may not come until next week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Derwinski, who is currently the State Department's Under Secretary for Security Assistance, Science and Technology, served in Congress when Mr. Bush was first elected to the House in 1966.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
