<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Matters; Little Is Said And Less Is Done About Yonkers</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="174127"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTEMPT ACTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CITY COUNCILS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YONKERS (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PURNICK, JOYCE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WASICSKO, NICHOLAS C (MAYOR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAND, LEONARD B (JUDGE)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DA1431F936A1575BC0A96E948260" item-length="764" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Matters; Little Is Said And Less Is Done About Yonkers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE PURNICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PURNICK, JOYCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A new slogan seems to have captured the imagination of New York's leading citizens: ''Just say nothing.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A new slogan seems to have captured the imagination of New York's leading citizens: ''Just say nothing.''</p>
        <p>A new slogan seems to have captured the imagination of New York's leading citizens: ''Just say nothing.''</p>
        <p>Maybe it began when some kind of static distorted Nancy Reagan's dictum to ''Just say no.'' Maybe it is the tone set by presidential candidates so masterly at avoiding fundamental issues like the deficit and taxes. Or maybe it is the greenhouse effect. Everything seems to have something to do with the greenhouse effect these days.</p>
        <p>But whatever it is, this fondness for silence or its equivalent, though far from new in public life, is showing signs of turning into a genuine trend. The only persistent, if selective, exception seems to be Mayor Koch, whose outspoken ways have caused him so much trouble that he is no argument for the benefits of candor.</p>
        <p>In any case, the examples of the silent treatment are many, ranging from the Democratic primary for President last April, featuring the neutrality of Governor Cuomo and most other prominent Democrats in the state (with the Koch exception) to the Tawana Brawley case. That went on for quite a while before Mr. Cuomo and some others ventured into the fray.</p>
        <p>There are other examples, many of them, and now comes the latest - Yonkers.</p>
        <p>That city in Westchester has been in contempt of court since Aug. 2, after its City Council voted to defy part of a judge's housing desegregation plan.</p>
        <p>And since Aug. 2, the state's most prominent leaders have been less than outspoken. ''I feel all alone,'' said Mayor Nicholas C. Wasicsko of Yonkers, who supports the plan but says he does not have enough clout to influence its opponents. ''I need someone who has stature or patronage or whatever else it is that would get recalcitrant members to reconsider.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wasicsko says that since the contempt ruling imposed by Judge Leonard B. Sand of Federal District Court in Manhattan, he has heard little from officials, including Andrew P. O'Rourke, the Westchester County Executive; Attorney General Robert Abrams, and Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato. Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan has said that the court must be obeyed and has offered to help Yonkers, but has not played a prominent role.</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Koch, who has made headlines with his remarks about foreign countries, has had little to say on the Yonkers case.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo has sent what has been judged -unfairly, he suggests - to have been a mixed message, and so has John Cardinal O'Connor of the Roman Catholic Archdiocese of New York. The Cardinal has both criticized the plan and assailed the situation.</p>
        <p>The Governor said yesterday that ''the law is the law.'' He said three weeks ago that he had not assumed a more active role in the case because ''nobody asked me to.'' Mr. Cuomo has also raised the possibility of modifying the desegregation plan, but suggested yesterday that any further discussion of that was premature, pending resolution of an appeal of Judge Sand's contempt finding.</p>
        <p>''I am not willing to help; I am eager to help,'' Mr. Cuomo said. ''But this is before the Court of Appeals.''</p>
        <p>Then again, Mr. Cuomo did not wait for the resolution of many court actions before taking a position on Shoreham, the nuclear power plant on Long Island that he wants to close. On that issue he has been most outspoken, as he noted yesterday. What's going on? ''Politicians are not always the most courageous peole in the world,'' advises a former Mayor, Robert F. Wagner of New York, known for his measured ways.</p>
        <p>Other reasons range from the pending court case to the theory that speaking out would only exacerbate tensions.</p>
        <p>Maybe. Maybe it is just basic political self-preservation. But what could have happened -a concerted effort by leaders to pressure either the Council to accept the desegregation plan, or the N.A.A.C.P. to request a renegotiation of that plan - has not happened.</p>
        <p>And by now, the impact of all this equivocation extends well beyond Yonkers.</p>
        <p>''Communities today are making decisions throughout the state which will either recreate segregation or open up opportunities,'' said Michael Sussman, the N.A.A.C.P. lawyer on the Yonkers case. ''This is sending a message.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sussman also wonders what this means to the poor, many of whom are already cynical about the law. ''We're never going to instill value in the law when we say we're not going to follow laws we don't like,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Not that he, or anyone else familiar with the public life, is surprised. ''It's natural not to want to say something that might make things worse.'' Mr. Wagner explains.</p>
        <p>Which is yet another reason why it is sometimes natural, too, to just say nothing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
