<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Don't Make a Villain of the Greenhouse Effect; Oceans Are Rising</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="158543"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">VEZIROGLU, T NEJAT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DC133DF930A35754C0A96E948260" item-length="424" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Don't Make a Villain of the Greenhouse Effect; Oceans Are Rising</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Thank you for your very timely article ''The Heat Is On'' and the accompanying, informative illustrations (Week in Review, June 26). As you state, most of the experts agree that atmospheric carbon dioxide is increasing due to the growing consumption of fossil fuels, i.e., coal, petroleum and natural gas. Carbon dioxide is their main combustion product. Additionally, they produce pollutants and acid rain.</p>
        <p>Environmental Protection Agency officials, you say, noted ''that in planning for a new storm sewer system, officials of Charleston, S.C., are taking into account the possibility that melting polar ice and thermal expansion will cause the ocean to rise.'' Actually, the melting process of glaciers and the polar ice caps has started. Between 1951 and 1981, the oceans have risen six inches. They are rising at the rate of half an inch a year, and the rate is growing. When the melting is completed, many coastal cities and plains will be flooded. For example, three-quarters of Florida will be under water.</p>
        <p>Do we have to suffer the greenhouse effect, drought, pollution, acid rain and the resulting damage to farm produce, water supplies and the environment? The answer lies in finding a fuel that will not produce carbon dioxide and pollutants. Our studies at the University of Miami indicate that the best fuel meeting this criterion is hydrogen, produced using clean primary energy sources, such as solar, wind, ocean-thermal and hydro. The United States has a vast potential of these clean primary energy sources for all of our energy needs. The hydrogen produced will cost two to three times the price of petroleum. But when you take the damage caused by carbon dioxide, pollutants and acid rain into consideration, hydrogen becomes much cheaper.</p>
        <p>Changing our fuel from fossils to hydrogen will solve the greenhouse problem and the pollution and acid rain problems; result in a clean and permanent energy system; provide jobs; create export potential of new energy technology; reduce the import of petroleum and the trade deficit, and boost the economy, while protecting the environment.</p>
        <p>According to our institute's estimates, conversion to hydrogen would take 40 to 60 years to complete; environmental benefits will become noticeable in 20 to 30 years. There is no time to lose. T. NEJAT VEZIROGLU  Coral Gables, Fla., June 27, 1988  The writer is director of the Clean Energy Research Institute at the University of Miami and president of the International Association for Hydrogen Energy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
