<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S.-Soviet Dialogue On Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="139534"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROBERTS, WALTER ORR (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MINTZER, IRVING (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DA173AF935A15757C0A96E948260" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S.-Soviet Dialogue On Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Scientists in the United States and the Soviet Union, linked through desk top computers, have begun a conference on what the two nations can do to cope with an expected global warming caused by the ''greenhouse effect.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Scientists in the United States and the Soviet Union, linked through desk top computers, have begun a conference on what the two nations can do to cope with an expected global warming caused by the ''greenhouse effect.''</p>
        <p>Scientists in the United States and the Soviet Union, linked through desk top computers, have begun a conference on what the two nations can do to cope with an expected global warming caused by the ''greenhouse effect.''</p>
        <p>Participants on both sides are calling the effort ''greenhouse glasnost.'' It began this month and is scheduled to last a full year.</p>
        <p>Plans call for scientists in the two countries to conduct a dialogue through the computer network. One participant, Dr. Irving Mintzer of the World Resources Institute here, said the scientists would try to construct a ''plausible scenario'' for the impact over the next 50 years of new weather patterns that will be caused by the expected warming trend. The global warming will be caused by the buildup in the atmosphere of carbon dioxide and other gases that trap heat, somewhat like the glass of a greenhouse.</p>
        <p>The two teams will try to assess how expected climate changes will affect their countries and how they will influence activities like trade in grain. At the end of a year, said Dr. Walter Orr Roberts, president emeritus of the University Corporation for Atmospheric Research and co-chairman, with former astronaut Russell (Rusty) Schweikert, of the United States team, the two sides hope to report their findings and make recommendations to the two governments.</p>
        <p>Consensus is emerging among scientists that the accumulation of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere from the burning of fossil fuel and the buildup of other industrial gases is trapping infrared radiation from the sun that would otherwise escape back into space.</p>
        <p>Many scientists believe this phenomenon is causing the global temperature to rise. As more gases accumulate, the climb in temperature is expected to accelerate, changing global climate patterns and causing the oceans to rise from thermal expansion and the melting of glaciers.</p>
        <p>Dr. Roberts described the electronic conference as the first of its kind between scientists of the two countries and a breakthrough in communications between scientists in the United States and the Soviet Union. He said the fact that such a conference was arranged shows ''that the Soviets are as deeply interested in this subject as we are.''</p>
        <p>The chairman of the Soviet panel of scientists is Roald Sagdeyev, director of the Institute for Space Research of the Soviet Academy of Sciences.</p>
        <p>Because of their industrial activity and heavy use of coal and oil, the two countries emit a large proportion of the gases that contribute to the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Roberts, the project was held up for some months because the Defense Department withheld permission to ship Apple Macintosh personal computers to the participating Soviet scientists on the ground that they contained sensitive advanced technology. The problem was resolved by a decision to use I.B.M. or similar desktop computers that are readily available here and in Europe.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the Defense Department said that the plan to export the personal computers had not fully complied with rules governing the transfer of such technology to the Soviet Union. She added, however, that the rules controlling the export of desk top computers had recently been dropped.</p>
        <p>Dr. Roberts said the linkage is already operating to Moscow but that links to scientists in Leningrad and other Soviet cities were delayed for reasons he did not know.</p>
        <p>He explained that the scientists from the two countires had decided to try a conference by computer because it would be less disruptive to schedules than a face-to-face meetings, would be less expensive and could continue over an extended period.</p>
        <p>One of the issues likely to be discussed will be changes in food production that result from climate change, Dr. Roberts said. One possible scenario, he said, would be a drying trend in the grain belt of the United States, reducing crop yields, and a warming trend in areas of the Soviet Union allowing it to grow more winter wheat.</p>
        <p>Another change that could affect bilateral relations would be the melting of the ice over the Arctic Ocean, leaving seaports in the north of the Soviet Union, Canada and the United States open all year, he said. These kinds of changes needed to be planned for in advance, he contended.</p>
        <p>Dr. Roberts said the scientists would also consider strategies for slowing or reducing the global warming, such as limiting the burning of fossil fuel. But he added that he did not believe that much could be done to head off the greenhouse effect at this point.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
