<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Huge Chunk of Antarctica Is Heading Out to Sea, at a Glacial Pace</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="117471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICEBERGS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHIPS AND SHIPPING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GLEICK, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Glaciers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DD1030F93AA35751C0A96E948260" item-length="777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Huge Chunk of Antarctica Is Heading Out to Sea, at a Glacial Pace</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES GLEICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GLEICK, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A 90-MILE-LONG Antarctic iceberg, the latest product of an extraordinary two years of glacial breakup, seems to be plowing toward the shipping lanes at the less-than-hazardous rate of about a tenth of a mile per hour.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A 90-MILE-LONG Antarctic iceberg, the latest product of an extraordinary two years of glacial breakup, seems to be plowing toward the shipping lanes at the less-than-hazardous rate of about a tenth of a mile per hour.</p>
        <p>A 90-MILE-LONG Antarctic iceberg, the latest product of an extraordinary two years of glacial breakup, seems to be plowing toward the shipping lanes at the less-than-hazardous rate of about a tenth of a mile per hour.</p>
        <p>The departure of this oceangoing monstrosity, known as B-9, has been monitored with intense interest by oceanographers and meteorologists concerned about the links between global climate, polar ice and sea level. Most scientists doubt that the earth's warming could already be speeding the flow of Antarctic ice; still, the surprising surge of icebergs from the glacial breakup has given them pause.</p>
        <p>''If you look just at 1986 and 1987, there have been some extreme events,'' said Stanley Jacobs, an oceanographer at Columbia University's Lamont-Doherty Geophysical Observatory. ''You couldn't have the ice breaking away at this rate every year or the ice sheet would soon be seriously out of balance.''</p>
        <p>B-9 - the name is glaciologist shorthand for Berg 9 - broke off from the Ross Ice Shelf last October. The act of ''calving'' entirely eliminated the Bay of Whales, where Adm. Richard E. Byrd established his first scientific bases beginning in 1928.</p>
        <p>In making its exit, B-9 single-handedly removed about a half-year's snowfall from the Antarctic continent. So great is its bulk that the earth's oceans are thought to have risen by about the thickness of 10 playing cards.</p>
        <p>Nor is B-9 the biggest. Two or three larger icebergs split off the Filchner Ice Shelf in 1986. Around the same time, the Larsen Ice Shelf divested itself of a huge projection.</p>
        <p>But B-9 has become something of a phenomenon - a celebrity among icebergs, perhaps because it is so close to Antarctica's main scientific stations. ''It's impressive,'' said Robert H. Whritner, manager of the Antarctic Research Center of the Scripps Institute of Oceanography in La Jolla, Calif. ''I mean, it's hard to fathom something this large.''</p>
        <p>Scripps is just one of the institutions tracking B-9's course by satellite. Government meteorologists follow it daily, putting its present drift at two to three miles a day, heading roughly west-northwest.</p>
        <p>''It seems to have accelerated a bit in the last week,'' said Don Barnett of the Naval Polar Oceanography Center near Washington.''It's also rotated quite a bit counterclockwise.'' Yearly Ice Budget</p>
        <p>For climate researchers, Antarctica is a focus of concern about the greenhouse effect, the warming of the atmosphere by carbon dioxide and other gases through the trapping of infrared radiation. They wonder how higher air and water temperatures will change the yearly budget of incoming and outgoing ice.</p>
        <p>Understanding that budget has been a surprising difficult problem. Accumulation from snow seems to amount to about 2,500 cubic kilometers a year. Researchers need to know how much ice melts around the continent's edges and how much breaks off as icebergs of every size.</p>
        <p>For lack of a better alternative, scientists have supposed that a long-term balance exists between incoming and outgoing ice. But no one knows for certain. By its nature, iceberg formation is an erratic, fluctuating process - years of buildup followed by a catastrophic break.</p>
        <p>''It is a problem,'' Dr. Jacobs said. ''It's generally assumed that it's in balance, and this is probably largely because there is not sufficient data to show otherwise.''</p>
        <p>Data collection poses special problems. Ice fragments range from gargantuan to minuscule. Passing ships are asked to report on every iceberg they spot, and satellites can see large ones, but over all, reliable information is hard to come by.</p>
        <p>Satellites will soon be able to monitor the changing coastline directly, giving a better measurement than scientists can get by counting icebergs. At the same time, researchers on the continent are trying to understand the dynamics of flowing glaciers. As ice warms, its mechanical properties may change; as the ocean warms, the interaction of water with glaciers may change.</p>
        <p>So scientists are watching to see whether the excesses of the last two years will lead to a period of calm, or whether giant icebergs will continue to pop from the Antarctic shelves. And they are keeping their eyes on B-9. By next year, it should be in the shipping lanes of Antarctica, Dr. Barnett said, and then it could find its way to the Drake Passage, toward New Zealand.</p>
        <p>It already seems to have set off ripples of iceberg awareness. In California, Dr. Whritner reports a worried call from a woman who thought she had sighted an iceberg basking in the waters off Del Mar.</p>
        <p>''People have gotten hyped on this thing,'' he said, ''and it triggers the imagination.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
