<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>States March Into The Breach</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="207426"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANTITRUST ACTIONS AND LAWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PROTECTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LABATON, STEPHEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DF163FF93BA25751C1A96E948260" item-length="2313" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>States March Into The Breach</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN LABATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LABATON, STEPHEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Reagan Administration has done its best to fulfill its promise to get the Federal Government out of corporate America's life, but as it has done so, the states have rushed to fill the void. Especially in the past two years, the states have become activists in a broad variety of areas, like antitrust, consumer protection and the environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Reagan Administration has done its best to fulfill its promise to get the Federal Government out of corporate America's life, but as it has done so, the states have rushed to fill the void. Especially in the past two years, the states have become activists in a broad variety of areas, like antitrust, consumer protection and the environment.</p>
        <p>The Reagan Administration has done its best to fulfill its promise to get the Federal Government out of corporate America's life, but as it has done so, the states have rushed to fill the void. Especially in the past two years, the states have become activists in a broad variety of areas, like antitrust, consumer protection and the environment.</p>
        <p>It is too early to tell whether the Bush administration will take a tougher regulatory and enforcement stand than the Reagan Administration. But even if the new administration does, one thing is clear: The states are not likely to surrender their new power easily.</p>
        <p>''It's become the widely held view that in the antitrust area, we are at least the co-equals to Washington,'' said Robert Abrams, New York's Attorney General and one of the most aggressive in the nation.</p>
        <p>Hal Stratton, New Mexico's Attorney General, also expects no retreat but for a different reason. ''Some of the guys really like the national attention; it's addictive,'' said the Republican and only attorney general to criticize openly the state initiatives.</p>
        <p>The states have succeeded in going beyond Federal regulations to create tougher national standards for pesticides and other environmental hazards. They have also blocked some large takeovers and forced others to be be scaled back.</p>
        <p>In late September, John K. Van de Kamp, the California Attorney General, stunned the American Stores Company and Lucky Stores Inc. when it persuaded a Federal judge to block the $2.5 billion merger of the two supermarket chains on Federal antitrust grounds. The move came just days after regulators in Washington assured American Stores' lawyers that they would not object on antitrust grounds. An appeal was heard earlier this month on the state's objections, and a ruling is expected early next year.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, the Campeau Corporation was forced to agree to sell some units to complete its $6.6 billion acquisition of Federated Department Stores Inc. because of the intervention of state prosecutors.</p>
        <p>In deals like US Air's merger with Piedmont and Texas Air's purchase of Eastern Airlines, state officials, sometimes acting with Federal authorities, have extracted commitments on fares and services designed to encourage competition and lower prices.</p>
        <p>One significant test of how far the state officials can push antitrust enforcement will come soon from the Supreme Court. The justices are weighing whether Federal antitrust law pre-empts state law from going further in certain price-fixing cases.</p>
        <p>But on the broader front, the aggressive actions by the states have frustrated and angered a number of large businesses, which had assumed that the Reagan years would make their regulatory lives easier.</p>
        <p>''If it becomes a trend that you must seek permission from every state or run the risk of jeopardizing a deal, then there will be an enormous burden on national transactions,'' said Stephen M. Axinn, head of the antitrust department at Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher &amp; Flom, the law firm representing American Stores in its battle with California.</p>
        <p>While business is still in the process of legally challenging many of the actions, it is clear that some intiatives have already changed the way companies conduct their affairs.</p>
        <p>For instance, new state advertising guidelines that require airlines to describe explicitly the terms of discounts have caused airlines to cut back advertising of low fares to avoid the new rules, said Wally Snyder, senior vice president of the American Advertising Federation, a lobbying group. ''It would be far better for everybody to follow the standards set by the Federal Government'' because they are less restrictive on the airlines but still forbid fraudulent advertising, he said.</p>
        <p>Consumer groups like Public Citizen, however, see the state attorneys general as a powerful ally against the Administration. The groups have endorsed many of the actions by states, which include the following:</p>
        <p>* Insurance. Joining forces last March, 18 states charged that leading insurers conspired to eliminate certain types of commercial general liability insurance for environmental damages. The case, filed against Hartford Fire Insurance, Allstate, Aetna and Cigna, is still in the pre-trial stages before a Federal judge in San Francisco, but experts say it could have a dramatic impact not only on insurance rates but also on policies issued by leading carriers. The Attorney General of Texas has filed a separate but related action.</p>
        <p>* Antitrust. Over the last three years, the National Association of Attorneys General, an 80-year-old organization, has issued a series of guidelines in antitrust enforcement that are substantially tougher than their Federal counterparts. In 1987, a group of state prosecutors led by New York and Maryland officials reached a $4 million agreement with the Minolta Corporation, which they had charged with illegally trying to control the retail price of cameras.</p>
        <p>* Securities. State legislatures have all but replaced the Congress in initiating reforms. Thirty-two states within the last 18 months have dramatically rewritten the takeover rules, which have limited the ability of unwanted suitors to gain control. Those actions, often encouraged by local companies in the middle of takeover fights, followed a Supreme Court decision last year upholding an Indiana merger restriction.</p>
        <p>* Consumer Protection. Earlier this month, the National Association of Attorneys General preliminarily adopted a broad set of tough standards for advertising by car rental agencies. If finally approved by the group in March, such hidden costs as fuel and mileage caps would have to be prominently displayed in rental ads. In a separate case, the Chrysler Corporation pleaded no contest last December to charges brought by Federal authorities and 41 attorneys generals that it had illegally tampered with the odometers of thousands of cars; it agreed to pay more than $16 million to car buyers. At about the same time, 48 states adopted guidelines that require advertising by airlines to describe the terms of discounts and avoid using what Attorney General Abrams calls ''mice-sized type'' to describe restrictions.</p>
        <p>* Environment. California has repeatedly sued the Department of Energy to force it to enforce restrictions on coastal drilling more strictly, and last month nine states sued the Environmental Protection Agency to force it to take action to reduce acid rain. Most of these cases are still pending. Other states have sued the Federal Government over contamination at nuclear weapons plants.</p>
        <p>Opponents of the state moves argue that they have no business meddling in the affairs of Federal authorities and setting policies with broad national ramifications.</p>
        <p>''The attorneys general, by joining together in these national efforts, are getting into areas where they weren't intended to be,'' said Mr. Stratton, New Mexico's Attorney General. ''It frustrates the will of the people who have made their national selections at the ballot box.''</p>
        <p>Daniel Oliver, the outgoing chairman of the Federal Trade Commission, warned that the state trend could lead to the ''Balkanization'' of consumer and antitrust laws, paving the way for ''a single state that can effectively block the commerce that affects the 49 other states.''</p>
        <p>Charles F. Rule, the Justice Department's antitrust chief, added: ''There has been a recognition that the states have a legitimate role in enforcement, but there has also been a recognition by some that antitrust enforcement can be an effective political tool for career enhancement.''</p>
        <p>Attorneys general leading the movement insist, however, that they have been acting out of concern for their constituents. They say the movement is not a case of politically motivated Democratic attorneys general taking on a Republican Administration. Indeed, although the leaders - including Mr. Abrams of New York and Mr. Van de Kamp of California - are Democrats, the movement also includes a large number of Republicans from such states as Kansas, Oregon and Washington.</p>
        <p>''It's a truly bipartisan effort, and it's being done simply because the Federal Government isn't doing its job,'' said Charles Brown, West Virginia's Attorney General, referring to state activism in antitrust. ''We are empowered by the Federal antitrust laws to be involved in this area,'' said the Democrat, who heads the antitrust committee of the National Association of Attorneys General.</p>
        <p>Mr. Van de Kamp of California added: ''We are no more political than Washington. The Justice Department and the Federal Trade Commission have just not been taking into account any local concerns.''</p>
        <p>During the Reagan Administration, the F.T.C. has filed an average of less than half the number of cases filed annually in the prior 17 years by other administrations - Republican and Democratic. None of the 10 largest mergers - all of which occurred during the Reagan years - have been challenged on antitrust grounds.</p>
        <p>There are plenty of historical precedents for the state activism. Prior to the adoption of Federal legislation, the states acted as the primary enforcers against price fixing and monopolies through the use of common law. The first state antitrust law was adopted by Kansas in 1889.</p>
        <p>But the public outcry was so great against the price-fixing practices of railroad, oil and heavy industry that both the Republican and Democratic Parties in 1888 had planks supporting Federal reform. Reform came in 1890 with the passage of seminal legislation in the area, the Sherman Act. It was strengthened in 1914 with the adoption of the Clayton Act. At about the same time, the major state laws were adopted in such places as New York, Ohio and California. Those laws still largely govern state antitrust.</p>
        <p>Still, periods followed when Federal enforcement was lax. Scholars have chronicled the New Deal years as a classic period when bigness was fostered in the interests of economic recovery. That changed in the late 1930's with the appointment of Thurman Arnold to head the antitrust section of the Justice Department. Mr. Arnold led the ''trust busting'' of his era, a period of vigorous enforcement that went unparalleled until more than three decades later.</p>
        <p>While no one is expecting a similar period under the Bush administration, state officials and private lawyers wonder whether the new administration will be as laissez-faire as the current one. ''We may see a little more enforcement of the Justice and F.T.C. guidelines, but the guidelines will probably not be significantly altered,'' Abe Krash, senior partner for antitrust at Arnold &amp; Porter, said, reflecting a common view among Washington lawyers. ''The area that will be worth watching is international. The spirit of protectionism may lead to more challenges of foreign acquisitions of domestic companies.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Bush made vague promises during the election campaign to protect the environment, he was silent on specific policies in antitrust, consumer protection and securities regulation. But early on as Vice President, he headed a regulatory relief task force, which recommended the dismantling of several consumer-protection programs and a reduction of regulations in the areas of worker safety and the environment.</p>
        <p>The people that Mr. Bush selects to fill key posts at the Federal Trade Commission, the Environmental Protection Agency, the Securities and Exchange Commission and the Justice Department will offer the first indication of just how laissez-faire he intends to be.</p>
        <p>Of those positions, Mr. Bush has so far only chosen an Attorney General. Dick Thornburgh will continue in that job, and Loye Miller, a spokesman for Mr. Thornburgh, said, ''There's no evidence that there will be a major change in antitrust policy.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, state prosecutors have seen some setbacks, and they may see others soon.</p>
        <p>In October, the California Supreme Court, sharply limiting an earlier decision, said the state's major antitrust law, the Cartwright Act, could not be used to contest mergers. The court, in a 4-to-3 ruling, dismissed a challenge by the Attorney General to Texaco Inc.'s $10.1 billion acquisition of the Getty Oil Company.</p>
        <p>And the Supreme Court has agreed to decide whether states can offer greater protection than Federal antitrust laws provide to purchasers who may have been indirectly injured from a price-fixing conspiracy among manufacturers. The justices, in effect, will rule on the issue of more than a dozen state antitrust laws passed after a 1977 Supreme Court decision that sharply restricted the rights of ''indirect purchasers'' to sue for antitrust damages.</p>
        <p>After that 1977 decision, known as the Illinois Brick case, many states amended their laws to permit purchasers to sue under state laws if they were injured by overcharges by wholesalers or middlemen. But last year, in California v. Arc America, the United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit, in California, struck down the state law, ruling it had been pre-empted by Federal law. California has been joined by 20 state attorneys general and the Justice Department in seeking to reverse the appeals court.</p>
        <p>Despite these challenges, the attorneys general remain undaunted. At a December meeting of the National Association of Attorneys General, they adopted new tougher guidelines on car-rental advertising. They have also vowed during the next Congress to lobby hard to repeal the McCarran-Ferguson Act of 1945. The law protects insurance carriers from Federal antitrust charges of price-fixing, but does not cover boycotts, threats or intimidation, charges at the heart of the California insurance case.</p>
        <p>Whatever happens in these cases, state prosecutors vow to press on. ''It's imperative to have both levels of government use their maximum power in all of these areas,'' Mr. Abrams of New York said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
