<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ACID RAIN IS CALLED PERIL FOR SEA LIFE ON ATLANTIC COAST</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="139409"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NITROGEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NITRATES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALGAE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FACTORIES AND INDUSTRIAL PLANTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ATLANTIC OCEAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EASTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHESAPEAKE BAY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL DEFENSE FUND (ORGN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service"></person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDA1538F936A15757C0A96E948260" item-length="1281" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ACID RAIN IS CALLED PERIL FOR SEA LIFE ON ATLANTIC COAST</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP;</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Acid rain, already recognized as a serious threat to fresh-water organisms, is also contributing far more to the degradation of marine life in Atlantic coastal waters than previously recognized, according to a new report.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Acid rain, already recognized as a serious threat to fresh-water organisms, is also contributing far more to the degradation of marine life in Atlantic coastal waters than previously recognized, according to a new report.</p>
        <p>Acid rain, already recognized as a serious threat to fresh-water organisms, is also contributing far more to the degradation of marine life in Atlantic coastal waters than previously recognized, according to a new report.</p>
        <p>Up to now, most experts have assumed that agricultural runoff and sewage were the main pollutants responsible for the increasing frequency of mass killings of marine life along the Northeastern coast. But the new report shows for the first time that acid rain is also a major culprit. It suggests that a reversal of the declining quality of Atlantic coastal waters will depend on measures to control air pollution as well as pollution on the land.</p>
        <p>The study is also likely to add fuel to the scientific debate over the effects of acid rain and to the battle in Congress over whether stringent new controls are needed for the sources of the pollution that cause acid rain. Eutrophication Is Culprit</p>
        <p>The air pollutant causing problems in this case is not sulfur dioxide, the primary component of acid rain, but oxides of nitrogen, a secondary component that is mainly produced by automobiles and electric utilities. In the atmosphere, nitrogen oxides are converted into nitric acids and nitrates. The damage to coastal aquatic life highlighted in the new report results not from acidity but from eutrophication, in which excessive growth of algae, stimulated by nitrate salts and other nutrients, chokes off the oxygen supply and blocks the sunlight required by other plants and animals.</p>
        <p>Prepared by scientists of the Environmental Defense Fund, a nonprofit environmental group, the study found that airborne nitrates, mostly from motor vehicles, power plants and other industries are a major source of the nitrogen that is polluting Eastern coastal waters by feeding algae blooms.</p>
        <p>The conclusion was endorsed by other scientists who have read drafts of the report. Joel S. O'Connor, an ecologist with the Waste Management Institute of the State University of New York at Stony Brook, said that the report was a ''technically good job that points out a problem that is not widely recognized enough.'' Focus on Chesapeake</p>
        <p>George Hidy, director of the environment division of the Electric Power Research Insitute, a research association of utility companies that emit large amounts of sulfur and nitrogen pollutants from their plants, called the report's findings ''an interesting and surprising hypothesis that needs to be verified.'' He said he would welcome the chance to look at the report in detail.</p>
        <p>The study focuses on Chesapeake Bay and its tributaries, and found that atmospheric sources account for about a fourth of the nitrates entering the bay, second only to fertilizers, which accounted for about a third. The report said that nitrogen in acid rain also contributed significantly to degradation of the waters of Long Island Sound, the New York Bight, and North Carolina's Albemarle-Pamlico Sound.</p>
        <p>Dr. Michael Oppenheimer, an atmospheric physicist for the environmental group and a co-author of the report, said the findings were important because acid rain had previously been thought of largely as a problem that affected ''a few hundred or a few thousand acidified lakes in remote areas.'' Now, he said, it can be demonstrated that nitrogen in acid rain is having a direct impact on coastal resources used by millions of people.</p>
        <p>''It is choking off the ocean's nurseries,'' he said. ''It is shutting down the playground for millions of Americans. It is a regionwide problem, and it is only going to get worse because of the projected growth of nitrogen emissions.'' Besides Dr. Oppenheimer, the other authors of the report were Diane Fisher, Jane Ceraso and Thomas Mathew.</p>
        <p>Nitrogen is a nutrient that stimulates the proliferation of algae in water. These algae use up the dissolved oxygen required by other marine life and cloud the water - a process called eutrophication - thus reducing the amount of sunlight that penetrates the surface. Along with other pollutants like toxic chemicals, increased nitrates are believed to be contributing to a longterm decline in fish and other aquatic animals and plants in many areas. They play a central role in the increased susceptibility of coastal waters to dramatic short-term algae blooms that kill fish and plants.</p>
        <p>Last summer, in an example of the severe problems that can develop when an excess of nutrients combines with prolonged warm weather and calm waters, fishermen in Long Island Sound hauled in catches of dead lobsters, crabs and other bottom-dwelling animals killed by eutrophication.</p>
        <p>Tudor Davies, of the Environmental Protection Agency, said there had been a growing number of cases of severe oxygen depletion and fish kills in Eastern coastal waters in recent years, particulary in estuaries. He said there had been serious incidents of eutrophication in the Chesapeake and Delaware Bays, the New York Bight, Long Island Sound and Narragansett Bay in Rhode Island.</p>
        <p>However, in some rivers, notably the Potomac, the eutrophication problem has been reduced because of the construction of sewer treatment facilities in recent years, Dr. Davies said.</p>
        <p>Airborne nitrates account for about 25 percent of the nitrogen pouring into the Chesapeake each year and this proportion will increase with the growing amount being spewed into the air, the study warned. Fertilizers currently account for 34 percent, sewage and other industrial discharges 23 percent, and animal wastes, including runoff from land and evaporated ammonium from manure that travels through the atmosphere, 18 percent.</p>
        <p>If trends continue, atmospheric nitrates would constitute 42 percent of annual nitrogen deposits into the bay by the year 2030, according to the report, which is based on data accumulated by Federal and state agencies.</p>
        <p>Acid rain results from pollution, chiefly oxides of sulfur and nitrogen from power plants and other sources that burn fossil fuels like coal and oil, that is transformed chemically as it travels through the atmosphere and falls to earth as acidified rain, snow, fog or dry particles.</p>
        <p>Congress is considering amendments to the Clean Air Act that would, among other things, require sharp reductions in these sulfur and nitrogen emissions. These amendments are supported by environmentalists and states downwind from the pollution sources, chiefly in the Middle West. But they are opposed by the Reagan Administration, by industry and by others who contend that the damage to human health and the environment caused by acid rain is not significant enough to warrant the high cost of curtailing emissions.</p>
        <p>Dr. Oppenheimer contended that the new information about the effect of nitrogen from acid rain shifts the equation even more in support of controls on the sources of pollution. ''In ignoring the acid rain problem,'' he said, ''Congress and the Administration decided to sacrfice thousands of lakes. As it turns out, they were also pulling the plug on our estuaries and coastal waters.''  ACID RAIN'S CONTRIBUTION TO COASTAL DECLINE</p>
        <p>Nitrogen in emissions from automobiles, electric power plants, other industries and residences returns to earth in acid rain. Nitrogen raining on coastal waters originates mainly in seaboard and Midwestern states.</p>
        <p>A new study jfound that acid rain contributes far more nitrogen to the waters of the Chesapeake Bay and other Atlantic coastal waters than previously thought. The buildup of nitrogen and other nutrients encourages growth of algae, which in turn use up oxygen needed by other plants and animals. It may explain the rising frequency of severe, temporary blooms of algae that kill large numbers of fish.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
