<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Study Shows Significant Decline in Ozone Layer</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="128014"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880316T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D7103BF935A25750C0A96E948260" item-length="1246" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Study Shows Significant Decline in Ozone Layer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Federal scientists reported today that atmospheric ozone over the Northern Hemisphere had declined significantly over the last two decades. The study, the most authoritative so far, reaches a conclusion similar to another reported earlier this year but adds important new details on the extent of worldwide depletion of the protective ozone shield.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Federal scientists reported today that atmospheric ozone over the Northern Hemisphere had declined significantly over the last two decades. The study, the most authoritative so far, reaches a conclusion similar to another reported earlier this year but adds important new details on the extent of worldwide depletion of the protective ozone shield.</p>
        <p>Federal scientists reported today that atmospheric ozone over the Northern Hemisphere had declined significantly over the last two decades. The study, the most authoritative so far, reaches a conclusion similar to another reported earlier this year but adds important new details on the extent of worldwide depletion of the protective ozone shield.</p>
        <p>Today's study, released by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, also found that loss of ozone in the Southern Hemisphere, which is most acute in springtime over Antarctica, was spreading into wider areas and that ozone levels were reduced throughout the year.</p>
        <p>The gas ozone that is in the upper atmosphere absorbs ultraviolet rays from the sun that can cause skin cancer and eye problems and damage other human health and natural systems, including aquatic life, forests and crops. Scientists estimate that for every 1 percent decline in atmospheric ozone, 2 percent more ultraviolet radiation reaches the earth's surface. Consensus on Blame</p>
        <p>Government and academic scientists who helped prepare the new study said that there is now, for the first time, a broad scientific consensus that man-made chemicals are responsible for much of the ozone loss.</p>
        <p>They also said that the new findings showed that the health threat from ultraviolet radiation piercing the thinning ozone shield is serious one. They said it required quick international ratification of a treaty reached by 31 nations last September to restrain the use of chlorofluorocarbons and other chemicals that are destroying ozone in the upper atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robert T. Watson, a NASA scientist who was chairman of the panel of scientists that prepared the new report, said at a news conference today its findings suggested that more ''draconian'' measures than the treaty may be needed to stabilize the protective ozone shield. Measurements From Space</p>
        <p>The study was prepared by more than 100 scientists who analyzed atmospheric measurements from both satellites and ground stations. They found that, after discounting for natural causes of depletion, such as decreased solar activity, ozone in the range of 30 degrees to 60 degrees north latitude decreased 1.7 to 3 percent from 1969 to 1986.</p>
        <p>This area includes most of the heavily populated regions of the United States and Canada, Western Europe, the Soviet Union, China and Japan.</p>
        <p>The ozone loss was found to be as much as 6.2 percent in wintertime at some latitudes, more severe than had been predicted by scientific models.</p>
        <p>An analysis published earlier this year by scientists at the University of Illinois found that global ozone levels dropped by 5 percent from 1979 to 1986. But scientists at today's news conference said that they had made new, more accurate corrections of raw data from satellite instruments, accounting for much of the difference.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kenneth Bowman, an author of the Illinois study, said that the results reported in the NASA study are based on a recalibration of data from the satellite measurements and that there was ''no real disagreement'' in the two studies, except that his estimates of ozone depletion were a little higher. He said that, based on the refinement of the measurements, he would agree that the decline in ozone was not quite as large as his report had suggested.</p>
        <p>Today's study also found that the dramatic loss of ozone that has been occurring over Antarctica in springtime is now having an effect on much of the Southern Hemisphere. The ozone layer over the Antarctic declined by as much as 50 percent last September. But today's study notes that ozone appears to have decreased since 1979 by 5 percent or more throughout the year at all latitudes south of 60 degrees south. Theory on Chemicals</p>
        <p>The report said a cyclical increase in solar radiation, which stimulates the production of ozone in the atmosphere, from 1986 to 1991 is expected to offset ozone losses to man-made chemicals. But the loss of ozone is expected to resume after 1991 as solar radiation declines.</p>
        <p>In the early 1970's, F. Sherwood Rowland and Mario Molina, scientists at the University of California, Irvine, speculated that chlorofluorocarbons, industrial chemicals widely used in refrigeration, insulating foam, solvents and aerosol propellents were remaining in the atmosphere for long periods and combining with and destroying ozone molecules. Later, halons, chemicals used in fire extinguishers, were added to the list of suspects.</p>
        <p>That theory has now gained wide acceptance as correct.</p>
        <p>Dr. John Gille, a scientist with the National Center for Atmospheric Research and one of the leaders of the panel of scientists that prepared today's study, said that for a long time it was strongly suspected that the man-made chemicals were destroying the ozone layer. But he said this study had produced ''the corpse.''</p>
        <p>''For the first time,'' he said in an interview, ''we have a really definitive answer that ozone has decreased. We understand what is going on and we can predict it will be much more severe in the future.'' Elements of Treaty</p>
        <p>The protocol adopted last September in Montreal would freeze the production and use of chlorofluorocarbons at 1986 levels starting in 1989 and roll back production by as much as 50 percent by 1999.</p>
        <p>The United States Senate voted on Monday, 83 to 0, to approve ratification of the international agreement and President Reagan issued a statement today praising the vote. But the only other nation to ratify the protocol so far is Mexico.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rowland noted, however, that because chlorofluorocarbons remain in the atmosphere for many decades, the destruction of ozone will continue after the freeze as more of the chemicals are used and released into the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>''My own view is that we are seeing severe damage now and we know it is going to get worse because more chlorine is on its way'' into the atmosphere, Dr. Rowland said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Watson of NASA said that study shows that ''ratification of the Montreal protocol is an essential first step.''</p>
        <p>But he added that the study's findings suggest that Lee M. Thomas, Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, and Mustafa K. Tolba, the director of the United Nations Environmental Program, ''should look long and hard'' at whether to invoke a provision of the protocol that calls for member nations to reconvene if scientific evidence shows that the the agreement is insufficient to protect the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>After today's news conference, Mr. Thomas said the findings of the new study would be considered during a reassessment of the global ozone situation scheduled under the protocol for 1990.</p>
        <p>Dr. Michael Oppenheimer, an atmospheric physicist with the Environmental Defense Fund, said that ''the real meaning of what they told us today is that we made a mistake 10 years ago when we failed to ban these chemicals.''  DECLINE IN THE OZONE SHIELD</p>
        <p>Ozone over the Northern Hemisphere fell significantly in between 1969 and 1986, a Federal study says.</p>
        <p>Average</p>
        <p>Change</p>
        <p>Winter</p>
        <p>S ummer</p>
        <p>Latitude</p>
        <p>1969-86</p>
        <p>Change</p>
        <p>Change</p>
        <p>53 degrees-64 degrees</p>
        <p>-2.3%</p>
        <p>-6.2%</p>
        <p>+0.4%</p>
        <p>40 degrees-52 degrees</p>
        <p>-3.0</p>
        <p>-4.7</p>
        <p>-2.1</p>
        <p>30 degrees-39 degrees</p>
        <p>-1.7</p>
        <p>2.3</p>
        <p>-1.9</p>
        <p>Scientists blame the reduction in ozone, which blocks harmful ultraviolet radiation, on industrial chemicals. Winter losses are greater because cold and lack of light speed up ozone-destroying chemical reactions.  (Source: NASA)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
