<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jersey Fish Kill Stirs New Fears of Decline In Region's Waters</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="158698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALGAE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BROWN TIDE (ALGAE)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ATLANTIC OCEAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY METROPOLITAN AREA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LEONARDO (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SANDY HOOK (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUTIS, PHILIP S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DF153EF930A35754C0A96E948260" item-length="1287" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jersey Fish Kill Stirs New Fears of Decline In Region's Waters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP S. GUTIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GUTIS, PHILIP S</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A fish kill that left a New Jersey beach strewn with tens of thousands of eels, flounder, bass, shrimp and crabs has confounded scientists and heightened fears that the waters of the New York region are growing increasingly inhospitable to marine life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A fish kill that left a New Jersey beach strewn with tens of thousands of eels, flounder, bass, shrimp and crabs has confounded scientists and heightened fears that the waters of the New York region are growing increasingly inhospitable to marine life.</p>
        <p>A fish kill that left a New Jersey beach strewn with tens of thousands of eels, flounder, bass, shrimp and crabs has confounded scientists and heightened fears that the waters of the New York region are growing increasingly inhospitable to marine life.</p>
        <p>Already this season, a region battered last year by shoreline pollution and environmental problems has had warnings of another troubling summer - a recurrence of the ''brown tide'' off Long Island and the low-oxygen conditions in Long Island Sound that killed lobsters by the hundreds last year.</p>
        <p>Then, on June 23, the fish died mysteriously and washed up on the small municipal beach in Leonardo, N.J., about four miles across Sandy Hook Bay from Sandy Hook. Message From Nature</p>
        <p>''The environment is trying to say something,'' said Stuart J. Wilk, the chief of environmental analysis investigation with the National Marine Fisheries Service's center in Sandy Hook.</p>
        <p>''I strongly believe that the environment will give us warnings periodically on whether or not it is being stressed,'' Dr. Wilk continued. ''These warnings come when we see things we have not seen before - and for me, we've seen one here.''</p>
        <p>Coming so soon after last summer's troubles - widespread algal blooms, the hundreds of dolphins that washed ashore from New Jersey to Florida, low-oxygen conditions in Long Island Sound and garbage and sewage washing ashore in New Jersey - the fish kill has alarmed scientists and shoreline residents.</p>
        <p>''People are scared that the waters are deteriorating at a rapid pace,'' said Christopher F. Smith, the chairman of the Brown Tide Task Force in Suffolk County, a group established by the county. ''There is major concern about the future of the ecology of the region's bays.'' Death by Suffocation</p>
        <p>New Jersey environmental officials describe the fish kill as a natural, if unfortunate, incident that can be explained by the week's intense heat and calm conditions that created low levels of oxygen in Sandy Hook Bay and the nearby Raritan Bay, suffocating a wide variety of the bays' marine life.</p>
        <p>But Federal officials who analyzed the fish kill are less certain. ''The fish kill was unusual, if not unique, in the variety of species that died,'' Dr. Wilk said. ''It got all species of all sizes from an inch to 30 inches, from weights of a fraction of an ounce to tens of pounds.''</p>
        <p>One theory being explored is that the fish were killed by a toxin, either natural or man-made. But Dr. Wilk said his agency has been unable to find any such toxin. ''The fish are dead and its hard to tell what did it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Whatever the cause, the fish kill again raised concerns about the quality of the region's waters. ''We are seeing a conglomeration of poured, pumped, piped and barged pollutants that are making the whole apex of the New York bight a biological monster,'' said Dennis G. Sternberg, an Allenhurst, N.J., dentist who is executive director of Save Our Shores, an influential citizens group in New Jersey. Bills to End Dumping</p>
        <p>Dr. Sternberg praised Governor Kean and the New Jersey Legislature for bills approved in late May that would eliminate the dumping of sewage sludge in the ocean by March 17, 1991, increase surveillance of illegal ocean dumping and subject violators to prison sentences of up to five years.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, he said, ''The Legislature has not been zealous enough in attacking the problem.''</p>
        <p>Concern in the New York region coincides with fears about the nation's estuaries - the coastal bays, inlets and rivers where nourishing freshwater mixes with shallow saltwater to provide a rich environment for marine life. Such fears intensified last summer, which was described by many experts as one of the worst in memory for marine life along the East Coast. Pollution Problem</p>
        <p>Although many scientists argued that the problems last summer resulted largely from unusually hot weather, most experts interviewed said the situation was aggravated by industrial discharges, sewage, fertilizer runoff, acid rain and other pollutants.</p>
        <p>Of increasing concern, scientists say, is the gradual warming of the Earth's atmosphere, described as the greenhouse effect, and acid rain, which the Environmental Defense Fund, a nationwide nonprofit group, this spring described as a major source of the nutrients feeding blooms of algae in Eastern coastal waters.</p>
        <p>One of the symptoms of what some call a faltering marine ecosystem is Suffolk County's continuing problem with the ''brown tide,'' an algal bloom of Aureococcus anorexefferens, a phytoplankton that has plagued the waters of eastern Long Island for three years. Ominous Finding</p>
        <p>Last winter, scientists discovered that the Aureococcus organism, which turns water brown when in bloom, survived extremely cold water in pre-bloom conditions. Scientists, startled by the find, said it did not augur well for this summer.</p>
        <p>The brown tide is indeed back, but not where it had previously been found in heavy concentrations. This year, instead of invading the Peconic Bay system, which separates the North and South Forks of eastern Long Island and where a $1.8 million scallop industry has been wiped out, the Aureococcus has moved west. It is now being found in significant numbers in the Great South Bay, on Suffolk County's south shore.</p>
        <p>Water samples taken last week by the Suffolk County Department of Health, for example, found 350 cells per milliliter near Flanders Bay in the Peconic system. But in the Great South Bay, off Sayville, samples had 400,000 cells per milliliter.</p>
        <p>''Making a definitive statement is difficult,'' said Robert J. Ochsenreiter, an official with the Bureau of Marine Resources in the Suffolk County Health Department. ''But what we have is definitely a bloom and should be watched.'' Effect on Hard Clams</p>
        <p>The main marine crop in the Great South Bay is hard clams, which are not harmed by the brown tide as much as other sea life is. Scallops, for example, cannot feed on the Aureococcus and therefore starve.</p>
        <p>Even though the clams do not appear to die in the midst of an Aureococcus bloom, they are believed affected. ''With hard clams,'' said Mr. Smith, ''the shelf life is shortened and the meat weights are dropped.''</p>
        <p>The situation in Long Island Sound, the other major water resource off Long Island, is also uncertain. Although the shortage of oxygen that caused widespread fish kills last summer in the western end of the Sound has not reoccurred, some scientists are concerned it will reoccur if the region has a long spell of hot, sultry weather.</p>
        <p>Last summer, an algal bloom made up of a different organism, the Prorocentrum redfieldii, compounded by a hot atmosphere with little wind, led to the suffocation of masses of fish, crabs and lobsters. ''Now we are finding dissolved oxygen conditions of 4 or 5 parts per million,'' said Barbara J. Welsh, a scientist at the University of Connecticut who is leading sections of a major Federal study of the Sound.</p>
        <p>''It does not get serious biologically until we reach 3 parts per million,'' Dr. Welsh said. ''But we are definitely beginning to see some of the same conditions that we saw last July.''</p>
        <p>In relatively calm bodies of water like Long Island Sound, water typically becomes stratified during the summer, with high oxygen conditions and warmer temperatures near the surface and colder water, with less oxygen, remaining on the bottom.</p>
        <p>This condition is normal, but when a huge algal bloom also occurs, the situation can become deadly. ''That's when we saw heavy fish kills in the Hempstead Harbor region,'' Dr. Welsh said. ''You get down below 0.1 percent of oxygen and you overwhelm the system with hydrogen sulfide, which is toxic for animals.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
