<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bill Bradley's Theme Song For '88: On the Road Again</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="201540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1988</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SENATE (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONGRESS (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRADLEY, BILL (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUKAKIS, MICHAEL S (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENTSEN, LLOYD (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAUTENBERG, FRANK R (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAY, CLIFFORD D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DE1339F935A15752C1A96E948260" item-length="1002" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bill Bradley's Theme Song For '88: On the Road Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD D. MAY, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MAY, CLIFFORD D</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ''A great experience,'' Bill Bradley called it, an opportunity to see the country while performing a useful service for his party, for his state and - though he neglected to mention it - perhaps for himself as well.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ''A great experience,'' Bill Bradley called it, an opportunity to see the country while performing a useful service for his party, for his state and - though he neglected to mention it - perhaps for himself as well.</p>
        <p>''A great experience,'' Bill Bradley called it, an opportunity to see the country while performing a useful service for his party, for his state and - though he neglected to mention it - perhaps for himself as well.</p>
        <p>Between Labor Day and Election Day, New Jersey's senior Senator campaigned in 24 states in behalf of the Dukakis-Bentsen ticket, more than 40 Democratic Senate, House and gubernatorial candidates, and as many state and county Democratic contenders as he could squeeze in.</p>
        <p>''He was one of the most-requested and active surrogate campaigners we had,'' said Anita Dunn, communications coordinator for the Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee. ''He was also one of the few Democrats who was not only welcome but eagerly sought-after in every state. Frankly, we don't have a whole lot of people who can travel to all corners of the country and get the kind of respect and popularity that Bradley commands.''</p>
        <p>Two other especially active and well-received Democratic politicians, she said, were Senator Sam Nunn from Georgia and Senator John Glenn from Ohio. Governor Cuomo was peripatetic, too, campaigning in nine states this fall, a spokesman in his Washington office said. Moving Beyond Basketball</p>
        <p>In an interview here, Mr. Bradley emphasized that his highest priority had been to support New Jersey's junior Senator, Frank R. Lautenberg, who waged and eventually won, by a comfortable margin of 8 percentage points, a grueling re-election battle against the retired Army General Pete Dawkins.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley noted, too, that he had campaigned for Democratic incumbents and challengers before. But this time around, he said, he received more requests and was better known as a Senator and perhaps a little less known as a former professional athlete.</p>
        <p>''In 1980, people were curious: How does a basketball player conduct himself as a Senator?'' he said. ''Now, I think, it's moved beyond that and they also know something about my work.''</p>
        <p>Spending time on the campaign trail in pursuit of votes for others ''serves a couple of purposes,'' Mr. Bradley said. ''It gives me an opportunity to be with a Senator or a Congressman in their home state or district. It helps me understand them better. That helps them. But the relationships are also important for the process, for the things I do in the Senate. I pick up chits helping with other campaigns, and I can use those chits for New Jersey's benefit later.'' Situation Where 'Everybody Wins'</p>
        <p>Does he not also pick up chits that he can use for his own benefit should he decide to seek his party's Presidential nomination in 1992? ''I sure don't think about that,'' Mr. Bradley said.</p>
        <p>Eddie Mahe, a Republican political consultant, was troubled by Mr. Bradley's response. ''It disappoints me that Bradley can't be more honest than that,'' he said. ''Why won't he just say that among the reasons for campaigning all over the place was that it gave him an opportunity to get acquainted with people and for people to get acquainted with him and that that may be very helpful should he decide to exercise the option he has of running for higher office?</p>
        <p>''It's particularly hypocritical for him to talk like that this year when one of the lessons of the election clear to every politician was that Dukakis was weaker as a candidate precisely because he had no national network out there.''</p>
        <p>Cliff Zukin, a professor of political science at Rutgers University in New Brunswick, was more charitable in his evaluation. ''Bradley is a sincere guy,'' he said. ''If he says he's out there working hard for the party and the state, that's true. But Bradley also isn't a stupid guy. He knows this has some nice fringe benefits, that he's increasing his name recognition nationwide and collecting i.o.u.'s that he can call in later. It's a terrific situation for him. Everybody wins.'' #17 States in 10 Days All the more so because none of the expenses were paid by Mr. Bradley or New Jersey. The bills went instead to the individual campaigns in whose behalf the Senator appeared. In the most intensive stretch of the campaign, the Senator traveled by chartered jet to 17 states in 10 days, stopping in several cities in each state. ''Each campaign paid a prorated share,'' said Nick Donatiello, Mr. Bradley's press secretary.</p>
        <p>Environment and education were the topics Mr. Bradley said received the most attention from the candidates and constituents with whom he came into contact. As it happens, those are among the issues he said would be highlighted on his agenda when Congress reconvenes next year.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to continue to work on children's issues, infant mortality, education and child support,'' he said, ''and on the environment, in particular open space, parks and holding the Bush Administration to their promises on environmental issues, from acid rain to oceans policy to the cleanup of toxic wastes.''</p>
        <p>He said he would also work on issues of concern to the elderly, like long-term health care. ''Those are things that I think are important for the state, for the region and for the country,'' he said. Children Ask Tough Questions</p>
        <p>During his frenetic campaign travels, Mr. Bradley said, he was struck by two things: the geographic and climatic diversity of the country and the profound political changes that have occurred.</p>
        <p>For example, in Mississippi, he went to a fund-raiser on behalf of Mike Espy, the first black Congressman from that state since Reconstruction. The affair was held at the plantation of Hiram Eastland, ''the nephew of James Eastland, the arch-segregationist,'' Mr. Bradley said. ''That was a striking and encouraging experience.''</p>
        <p>The Senator said he was also impressed in Miami, where children in an experimental program may take supplemental elementary school classes on Saturdays and student reporters operated video cameras to interview him.</p>
        <p>''Kids always ask the most obvious and the most difficult questions,'' he said. ''Like 'Why are you a Senator?' Not so easy to answer.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
