<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Striped Bass, In Comeback, Spur Debate Over Fishing</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="148186"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASS (FISH)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISHING, COMMERCIAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REPRODUCTION (BIOLOGICAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STRIPED BASS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HUDSON RIVER</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHESAPEAKE BAY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EAST COAST</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DB143EF937A15756C0A96E948260" item-length="1412" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Striped Bass, In Comeback, Spur Debate Over Fishing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>CHESAPEAKE CITY, Md.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The low-slung aluminum boat, a big electric generator squarely amidships, moved in a lazy S pattern through the tidal waters of the Elk River, two poles in front sending 1,000 volts into the brackish water. Dozens of small white perch, temporarily stunned, traced a kind of wake behind the boat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The low-slung aluminum boat, a big electric generator squarely amidships, moved in a lazy S pattern through the tidal waters of the Elk River, two poles in front sending 1,000 volts into the brackish water. Dozens of small white perch, temporarily stunned, traced a kind of wake behind the boat.</p>
        <p>The low-slung aluminum boat, a big electric generator squarely amidships, moved in a lazy S pattern through the tidal waters of the Elk River, two poles in front sending 1,000 volts into the brackish water. Dozens of small white perch, temporarily stunned, traced a kind of wake behind the boat.</p>
        <p>But the scientists in the boat were after bigger fish. Jorgen Skjeveland, a United States Fish and Wildlife Service biologist, suddenly thrust his net into the water and hauled out a weakly thrashing monster. ''It's a female,'' he called out.</p>
        <p>A second boat, manned by two biologists from the Maryland Department of Natural Resources, pulled alongside, and the two men gently removed the fish, a 50-pound striped bass, or rockfish, as it is called in Maryland, to their boat. James Van Tassel carefully inserted a thin plastic tube into the fish's ovarian duct and removed a sample of clear roe. ''She'll be ready to hatch in eight hours,'' he announced.</p>
        <p>In part because of a joint state and Federal restocking program and in part because of strict limits on fishing, the striped bass, in danger of vanishing five years ago, is returning in large numbers to the waters of the Chesapeake, the Hudson and other estuaries of the Eastern Seaboard. As the populations rise, commercial fishermen are demanding that they be allowed to resume catching the prized species.</p>
        <p>But Government biologists and conservationists warn that the return of the striped bass is fragile. The future of the fish will not be secure, they insist, unless the water pollution and the acid rain that threaten its habitat and reproductive processes are controlled. They insist that a resumption of commercial fishing would be premature.</p>
        <p>A migratory fish appreciated since colonial times for its size, its fighting abilities and its taste, the striped bass was one of the most important commercial and game fishes of the East Coast until the early 1970's. But by the late 70's and early 80's the striped bass population had plunged to dangerously low levels.</p>
        <p>The commercial catch of stripers from Maine to North Carolina dropped from about 14.7 million pounds in 1973 to 1.7 million pounds by 1983. Biologists feared that these fish would disappear forever.</p>
        <p>Charles M. Wooley, a marine biologist and Chesapeake Bay fisheries coordinator for the Fish and Wildlife Service, said the reasons for the steep decline of the striped bass were still not fully understood. But he said most scientists who had studied the problem believed that the explanation was probably a combination of overfishing, particularly of breeding-age females; pollution that degraded the aquatic habitat of the Chesapeake Bay and other estuaries, and acid rain that limited the reproductive capacity of the big fish by destroying eggs and larvae.</p>
        <p>In 1985, Maryland imposed a moratorium on all commercial and sport fishing for striped bass and, acting under a mandate of Congress, other coastal states put strict limitations on the number of fish that could be taken. Mr. Wooley said these curbs were especially needed to protect female stripers of breeding age.</p>
        <p>The biologists were hauling in a striper here from the Elk River as part of the restocking effort. They wrestled the big gray and silver fish, which was already recovering from the electric shock used to bring it to the surface, into a tank filled with salt water and spiked with oxygen and an anesthetic, to keep it, and about a dozen other stripers already netted, alive but quiet until they could be taken to a state hatchery.</p>
        <p>There the eggs are removed and fertilized. Fingerlings are kept in ponds until they reach six to eight inches long, to improve their chances for survival in open water. Then, after being tagged with a tiny microchip, so their movements can be traced by scientists with metal detectors, they are returned to the tributaries of the Chesapeake from which their parents were taken. The parents are taken back to the same waters within a day or so of being captured.</p>
        <p>Because of the restrictions on fishing and the restocking program, there are now substantial numbers of striped bass in the Chesapeake again, as well as in other areas along the coast. In the Hudson there is now ''the highest number since we started counting in 1976,'' said Byron Young, a marine resource specialist for the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation. One reason for the high population in the Hudson is that no commercial fishing of the stripers has been allowed since 1976 because PCB's in the river are absorbed by the fish. But Mr. Young said that probably an even more important reason for the comeback of the striped bass in the Hudson is that ''we are getting better at cleaning up environmental pollution.''</p>
        <p>''We are not home free yet,'' he said. ''Some areas like New York Harbor still need a lot of work. And now Long Island Sound is starting to be impacted.'' The moratorium on fishing in Maryland and other states is also helping to increase the Hudson bass population. Overfishing or Pollution?  Because of the growing number of striped bass in breeding areas, commercial fishermen contend that limited harvests can resume.</p>
        <p>Larry Simns, president of the the Maryland Waterman's Association, said, ''There are large numbers of fish out there, not enough to go out and fish the same number as we used to, but enough for limited sports and commercial fishing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Simns insisted that the reason for the decline of rockfish was not overfishing but the pollution of the Chesapeake's ecological system because of the growth of population and industry around it.</p>
        <p>''I am 50 years old now, and have spent 40 years on the water,'' he said. ''When I was a kid you couldn't get in and out of the harbor for the grass. We had an abundance of everything. Now there is no grass out there and not many fish.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Simns thinks that the main culprit is the discharge from the numerous sewage plants that have sprung up in recent years around the bay, along with the runoff from storm sewers that he said was killing the bay by pouring nutrients into the water that cause algae to proliferate and use up the oxygen needed by sea grasses and other organisms.</p>
        <p>Scientists and conservationists agree that pollution is making the bay and other coastal areas a poor environment for the striped bass. And the bass, noted Mr. Wooley of the Fish and Wildlife Service, is a good ''indicator species,'' in that it reflects early the pressures that will affect other marine life.</p>
        <p>The Federal Government has joined with the states of Maryland, Virginia and Pennsylvania and the District of Columbia in a long-range program to restore the health of the Chesapeake by reducing the pollution that enters the bay from such sources as sewage plants and factories, runoff of pesticides and fertilizers from farms, and residues of metals and chemicals that are washed from city streets. This pollution, along with acid rain, which is believed to be chiefly caused by the burning of coal and other fossil fuels, and the damming of spawning rivers such as the Susquehanna, have been major factors in the decline, not only of striped bass, but also of other important commercial fish such as the shad and herring, biologists have found. Reasons to Delay Catch</p>
        <p>Despite gains against pollution, scientists and conservationists give at least two reasons for their contention that it is still too early to allow fishing for striped bass to resume. First, they say, the young fish now in coastal waters must be allowed to reach breeding age and begin a self-sustaining population. Mr. Wooley said there were still relatively few fish of breeding age around.</p>
        <p>Second, ''until the habitat is cleaned up, we need to have restrictions on fishing,'' said Dick Russell, president of Striped Bass Emergency, a nonprofit clearinghouse for private efforts to save the striped bass.</p>
        <p>The struggle to save the fish is a ''real milestone'' in wildlife management, Mr. Wooley said. Perhaps for the first time, he said, Federal and state scientists and managers are working together to save a migratory fish throughout its entire range.</p>
        <p>''Half the battle is biological, but the other half is political,'' Mr. Wooley said, explaining that without the political will to curb acid rain and clean up the sewage flowing into the bay, the fight to save the striped bass could be lost no matter how much restocking is done or how long the fishing restrictions are imposed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
