<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Secrets of the Rain Forest</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="110329"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">COSTA RICA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ECKHOLM, ERIK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PERRY, DONALD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Costa Rica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Costa Rica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DE163FF934A25752C0A96E948260" item-length="3785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Secrets of the Rain Forest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Erik Eckholm; Erik Eckholm is deputy science and health editor of The Times.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ECKHOLM, ERIK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ''BUTTERFLY heaven,'' exults Donald Perry from his mobile perch above the jungle roof. The first sunny morning all week and the butterflies are out; a dozen varieties, a dozen different color swatches, flit by within half an hour.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ''BUTTERFLY heaven,'' exults Donald Perry from his mobile perch above the jungle roof. The first sunny morning all week and the butterflies are out; a dozen varieties, a dozen different color swatches, flit by within half an hour.</p>
        <p>''BUTTERFLY heaven,'' exults Donald Perry from his mobile perch above the jungle roof. The first sunny morning all week and the butterflies are out; a dozen varieties, a dozen different color swatches, flit by within half an hour.</p>
        <p>Perry, naturalist, dreamer and impresario of the treetops, is becoming acquainted with his new habitat, a patch of rain forest in the hills of Costa Rica. We cruise with ease through the upper stories, a zone biologists call their last frontier. Our vehicle is a moving steel platform dangling from cables stretched between giant trees 700 feet apart. By remote control, with a small joy stick, Perry directs distant winches that move us forward and backward, up and down. Bouncing gently, we might be in the basket of a hot-air balloon.</p>
        <p>It is early December, only five days since the tramway was up and running above a curving gorge. Inching through the vines, aerial ferns and orchids that give the forest its tropical air, the thick brown mud below seems a world away.</p>
        <p>Today, the incessant rains have stopped. Years of scraping and scheming, more than two weeks of grueling construction on steep, slippery hillsides are finished and Perry's audacious contraption is actually working.</p>
        <p>''I'm exhilarated,'' says Perry, a lean, 6-foot-4-inch man of 40 who, lacking formal academic backing, calls himself a ''freelance biologist.'' ''Now the fun begins.'' If nothing else, the machine gives a ride that Disney would have envied. The view of two roaring waterfalls and lush jungle is sensational; the 150-foot drop below us hints at danger. More than a toy, though, this is an important step toward many a biologist's dream: to move through the forest canopy with the freedom of a bird. In coming years, Perry hopes, even bigger ''automated webs'' will open new realms for jungle researchers the way scuba gear did for explorers of the seas.</p>
        <p>As though seeing nature for the first time, Perry jumps and points to each new bird or bug that flutters into view, racing the platform to examine every flower. To his companion, a New Yorker without training in tropical biology, the unremitting greenery slowly seems less strange as the eyes pick out oversized but obvious relatives of common houseplants: stupendous climbing philodendrons; the droopy leaf clusters of the Shefflera; the shiny, ribbed leaves of a 100-foot fig tree.</p>
        <p>It takes reminding that we are making a rare foray into territory that scientists consider equivalent to an unexplored continent. The discovery of life in the rain forests has hardly begun, but the findings already made about the multitudes of plants and animals and their extraordinary interrelations leave many biologists almost breathless.</p>
        <p>''If I were 30 years younger, I'd be hanging up there in the ropes myself,'' says Edward O. Wilson, the 58-year-old Harvard biologist.</p>
        <p>THANKS MAINLY to the warnings of conservationists, by now nearly everyone has heard superlatives about the dwindling rain forests of tropical Africa, Asia and Latin America. Why they abound with so many species is debated. Many, scientists, though not all, Wilson says, attribute it to a combination of factors: the equable climate that allows year-round growth, and the relatively long history that some areas in the tropics, known as ''refugia,'' have enjoyed without major climate change, allowing more time for species to evolve. Whatever the reasons, jungles comprise the richest ecosystems on earth, and the least examined. They are home to millions of unnamed plants and animals and have untold lessons to teach about the history and workings of life.</p>
        <p>This holds doubly true for the upper stories, from some 30 feet above ground to the 150-foot-plus crowns of forest behemoths. There, all-important sunlight drives a riotous dance of life.</p>
        <p>''Biologically, that's the hot spot of the forest,'' said Alan P. Smith, an ecologist at the Smithsonian's Tropical Research Institute in Panama. ''That's where most of the photosynthesis is, and most of the plant-animal interactions. That's where the growing tips of the plants are.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps two-thirds of the rain-forest species live aloft; many plants and animals are born, reproduce and live their entire lives without ever touching the ground. It is estimated that as many as half of all life forms may live in the jungle canopy (most, without doubt, insects).</p>
        <p>This arboreal realm remains largely out of scientists' reach. Simply climbing the trees is usually out of the question. They brim with stinging ants, scorpions, spiders and wasps, not to mention the occasional deadly viper. Many have weak branches, already sagging with heavy vines and piggybacking plants.</p>
        <p>In the past, Perry and others have adapted mountain-climbing techniques to haul themselves up tall trees on ropes, sometimes to camp in lofty observation platforms. A handful of researchers have built ladders and walkways through the branches. For scientists to see what they need to see, platforms and catwalks would carve up the forest so thoroughly that natural patterns would be destroyed.</p>
        <p>Then there is the question of safety; in 1984, a British researcher in Venezuela fell to his death from the trees.</p>
        <p>AT FIRST, THE JUNGLE seems to offer little more than a hundred shades of green. Only sporadically is the verdure broken by the jolting flash of a flower's red or yellow or white. A preposterous procession of overburdened leaf-cutter ants, a hovering dragonfly and, at a lucky moment, a passing troop of parrots may offer the only hints of wildlife.</p>
        <p>But the forest rewards patience. Watch, and one among the brown leaves fluttering to earth jumps sideways, revealing itself to be a hefty Morpho butterfly, camouflage-brown on the underside but, you are startled to see, brilliant azure on the top.</p>
        <p>More than patience, the forest rewards knowledge. Each high-wire trip through the canopy reveals more variety. ''You get a glimpse of canopy life now and then from a fallen branch or tree,'' says Michael Grayum, a botanist who has spent the last three-and-a-half years collecting the flora of Costa Rica for the Missouri Botanical Garden. ''But I've never seen it like this.''</p>
        <p>A cruise with him is instructive not only for what plants he identifies but also for those he, unapologetically, cannot. There might be 150 different plant species within view along the tramway's span, he guesses, some of them never described in the literature. ''Here it's so diverse that nobody can know everything,'' he says with a shrug.</p>
        <p>We stop alongside trees laden with epiphytes, plants that grab nutrients and water from the air and transform many branches into exotic gardens. Epiphytes - the word comes from Greek for ''upon plants'' - use trees for physical support but do not, like parasites, sap nutrients from their hosts. They include not only the ferns, mosses, lichens and liverworts seen in northern forests, but also arboreal cactuses and bromeliads. The latter, relatives of the pineapple, often store rainwater at the base of their erect leaves, supporting microcommunities of insects and even frogs.</p>
        <p>And, more than anything else, the epiphytes include orchids. Most of the world's 20,000 species of orchids live on the trunks or branches of tropical trees. In Costa Rica alone, more than 1,100 species of orchids have been identified. When we take time to look, several orchids are in flower. A white flower the size of a hand is easily spotted. Others, strings of yellow or purple blossoms hardly bigger than dewdrops, are easy to miss.</p>
        <p>We direct the platform ahead and down to the branches of an enormous fig tree, its fruits clustered about the shiny leaves. From on high, the leaves in the middle of the crown had seemed a different color and up close we see why: these are actually two stranglers entwined.</p>
        <p>Grayum explains the fierce, silent struggle under way. The fig is one of the strangler figs known as ''tree-killers'' in Central American vernacular. These begin life as epiphytes, germinating in a humus-rich crotch of a big tree. They send roots down to dig into the ground and suck up the nutrients and water that power a relentless sunward push. As the leaves above spread, stealing ever more sunshine, the roots fuse around the host tree's trunk. Squeezed and increasingly bereft of light, the host dies and there, innocent-looking, stands the triumphant usurper.</p>
        <p>But here the second tree is another variety of strangler tree, and the two may fight until one triumphs. More likely, Grayum observes, they will coexist for years in an uneasy detente.</p>
        <p>ON A SUNNY morning, prime time for butterflies, I traverse the treetops with Isidro Chacon, a butterfly expert with the National Museum of Costa Rica. He has heard that this site is rich in butterflies and is eager to see for himself.</p>
        <p>As soon as we embark, he nets a blue, black and yellow Heliconius. He holds the insect by the wings and examines the clusters of plant pollen attached to its front legs. This species mixes pollen and nectar ''like a milkshake,'' Chacon says. After being poked and probed for several minutes, the released insect flies off, none the worse. Above us, a green hummingbird stops for a quick rest on the steel cable, perhaps mistaking it for one of the lianas, woody vines that creep and dangle everywhere.</p>
        <p>Next, Chacon nets a brilliant yellow-and-black funeral moth, a species whose body is poisonous enough to make a bird vomit and remember not to make the same mistake again. Severalbutterfly species that lack such poison have evolved nearly identical coloration, he says, offering them a sort of borrowed security. The moth species is usually quite hard to collect; this specimen disappears into a paper packet and Chacon's pocket. Other butterflies are fluttering above a nearby tree and we move on to watch, enjoying a box-seat view of behavior that researchers have usually had to study through telescopes.</p>
        <p>In the late afternoon, just after we glide past a primeval tree fern, Perry halts next to a colorful vine. On stiff stalks are tiny closed flowers and rows of red, ladle-shaped nectaries that attract a variety of hungry birds. A few years ago, watching at another site, Perry made a circumstantial case that this vine uses birds' feet to transport its pollen from one plant to another; the gummy pollen, he believes, sticks to the feet of nectar-sippers and is rubbed off later. If true, Perry says, this is a reproductive strategy scientists have rarely seen.</p>
        <p>It is good luck that the same plant grows here, he says, so that observations can continue. Perry's critics in the scientific world charge that many of the observations he has made during more than a decade of research in Costa Rica have been reported as anecdotes in his 1986 book, ''Life Above the Jungle Floor,'' and in popular magazines rather than as carefully documented cases in journals. He has no intention, he adds, of carrying out the tedious studies necessary to convince skeptical scientists of his birds'-feet theory. ''I'm not going to spend five years proving something I think is obvious,'' he says.</p>
        <p>DON PERRY,'' A friend of his said, ''is the sort of person people talk about - whether they love him or hate him.''</p>
        <p>For about a dozen years now, Perry has been a promoter of canopy exploration, garnering no little publicity himself in the process. Other scientists say that he has not buckled down to painstaking research. Also factor in his penchant for the telegenic gesture - it is no coincidence that the new cable system, which has already been visited by a film crew, has a stunning backdrop - and it is no surprise that some colleagues see him more as showman than scientist.</p>
        <p>Perry freely admits his lack of interest in producing meticulous articles for scientific journals. ''I'm a naturalist,'' he says. Nor does he apologize for the publicity he wangles, asking: ''Why shouldn't I pick a beautiful site that will make the jungle seem more accessible to laymen?'' He figures he has done more than many academic specialists to stir public interest in rain-forest ecology and conservation.</p>
        <p>A self-described Californian who says he ''feels out of place'' in upstate New York, where he now lives with his wife, Perry received a doctorate in biology in 1983 from the University of California at Los Angeles. His time has increasingly been divided, he says, between his popular writing and his quest for better tools that researchers can use to reach the jungle roof.</p>
        <p>Perry remembers exactly when he became interested in treetops. In 1973, while a graduate student at California State University at Northridge, he went hang gliding with a friend, John Williams. In high winds, Williams had a mishap, and the glider ended up stuck atop some 30-foot trees. Climbing up to help disassemble it, Perry recalled, ''I actually began enjoying myself. My perspective shifted and I had a very distinct impression of being a monkey or an ape.'' (At times, Perry's rapture for the treetops borders on the mystical. He says, for instance, that when he first climbed tall tropical trees in the mid-1970's, he felt ''an amazing sense of deja vu.'') Bored with lab work, Perry was then shopping for a thesis topic. A professor told him of the dearth of knowledge about the canopy of tropical forests. With his own money, augmented by some modest grants, he set out for Costa Rica, a country where many scientists pursue tropical studies because large forest areas are protected and the Government is hospitable to research.</p>
        <p>To reach the heights, Perry modified a mountain-climbing method that other researchers had already been experimenting with. Devices called Jumars, or ascenders, which slide freely up and down a rope when loose but lock firmly when weight is applied, were the key. Hanging in a body harness attached to one ascender, feet in stirrups attached to a second one, a person can creep up a rope like an inchworm by moving the devices up one at a time while putting weight on the other.</p>
        <p>The challenge was to get a strong rope over the right branch. First, you need to know the trees well enough to pick a strong one (perhaps half of jungle species are too weak). Then you need a way to get a line over and down from the target branch, which may be more than 100 feet above and covered with entangling vegetation. Perry's innovation was to use a crossbow to shoot an arrow carrying a nylon fishing line over the branch. That first line was used to pull up a bigger rope, and that one, provided it did not become caught in bark or branches, to pull up an even sturdier rope. Several researchers now use similar techniques to study arboreal ecology.</p>
        <p>In search of greater mobility, Perry enlisted his friend Williams, an engineer, to help design a web of rope hung from three giant trees. An ingenious system of pulleys allowed Perry to swoop in every direction. While Perry himself used the system in 1979, it proved too difficult and dangerous for most researchers' tastes.</p>
        <p>NEXT, PERRY EM-barked on what he calls the automated web for canopy exploration. The current system, also engineered by Williams, uses three steel cables, strung between two strong trees along the side of a twisting ravine. On signals radioed with the joy stick, hydraulic winches run by a 10-horsepower gasoline engine move the platform along the cables or up and down. Two people can ride with ease.</p>
        <p>The tramway is located in a private forest reserve, Rara Avis, 40 miles north of San Jose, established by Amos Bien, an American biologist who is creating a center for nature-loving tourists and for research. The land borders a national park and its stream waters are safe to drink, good evidence that the clearing of forests to make cattle pastures, which have replaced so much of Costa Rica's unprotected jungles, has been held at bay here. Before flying their equipment to Costa Rica last November, Perry and Williams had assembled the system in Topanga Canyon, Calif., to make sure it worked. But then, getting the equipment to the jungle site and getting the cables strung was an adventure in itself.</p>
        <p>The rains were heavy and even four-wheel-drive vehicles often stalled in the soupy channel that was the last eight miles to the building site. Once the equipment was there, five people took a week in the rugged, overgrown terrain, knee-deep in mud, to hang the cables.</p>
        <p>To raise the heavy cables, smaller lines were first pulled through the branches. Positioning the pulleys to achieve the right ''hang'' and smooth movement took days more. Finally, after two-and-a-half soggy weeks of construction, Perry took his first invigorating ride.</p>
        <p>MUCH OF THE ACTION in the canopy revolves around the sex lives of plants, the foundation of the ecosystem. For many species, this means the transfer of pollen, male sex cells, from flowers on one plant to flowers on another.</p>
        <p>Just the mention of pollen nearly provokes a runny nose in this hay-fever victim. Strangely, though, as I ride on Perry's platform amid opulent greenery, my sinuses are perfectly clear. This is an unintended benefit of the great diversity of plants in the rain forest. In the more repetitious ecosystems of the Temperate Zone, many plants can rely on the random action of the wind to carry their pollen. Releasing the powder to the breezes wastes prodigious amounts, including the particles that torment passing humans; but when many of the plant's relatives are about, some of the pollen will reliably reach its destination.</p>
        <p>Not so in the rain forest, where a plant is apt to be surrounded by a multitude of other species. Instead, the delivery of pollen by specialized bees, beetles, bats, butterflies, moths or birds is common. The plant must entice a creature not only to pick up some pollen but also to deliver it to a member of its own species. For this, a bird that flies randomly from flower to flower won't do. Instead, astonishingly specific physical features and interdependencies between plants and animals have developed, in a process known as coevolution.</p>
        <p>The sexual strategies of orchids alone include some improbably exquisite arrangements. Some orchids offer sweet nectar as a bribe for go-between services. Others offer, instead of food, packets of perfume to ''orchid bees.'' The cruising male bees store the perfumes in pockets on their hind legs and use them indirectly to find mates. A male cannot entice a female by himself, but with the fragrance he can attract other males; the buzzing mass of males draws in receptive females.</p>
        <p>Still other orchids lure insects with pure deceit, mimicking nectar-bearing flowers without bothering to produce any of the fluid. Perhaps most outlandish are the orchids that mimic female insects, achieving pollination when the duped males attempt to copulate with them.</p>
        <p>Researchers have also discovered that several different varieties of orchid can harness the same insect, avoiding wastage by attaching their pollen to different locations on its body. Because the flowers have unique, precise anatomical structures, each bit of genetic material picked up by a feeding bee has a good chance of being rubbed off in another flower of the same species. One scientist found 13 specific locations for pollen on the body of a single bee.</p>
        <p>KNOWLEDGE OF such rain-forest marvels leaves scientists feeling merely tantalized, which is why so many are keeping a close eye on Perry's efforts to gain access to the jungle roof. Recent work by a ground-based student of canopy ecology, Terry L. Erwin of the Smithsonian Institution in Washington, suggests how much more awaits discovery.</p>
        <p>Erwin fogged tropical trees with biodegradable insecticides, catching everything that fell in a tray. His findings astounded biologists. From 19 specimens of a single type of tree in Panama, for example, he collected more than 1,200 different species of beetles. They included some that fed on the tree, some that fed on fungi, some that fed on fellow beetles and some that were scavengers. One in seven, he estimated, lived on that tree species and no other.</p>
        <p>Extrapolating from this and from similar studies he made in Peru and Brazil, Erwin estimated that the world's rain-forest canopies house anywhere from 10 million to 30 million species of insects.</p>
        <p>While Erwin's extrapolation remains controversial, many scientists say it is plausible. Even if he is only half right, the findings transform the understanding of the scope of the earth's life. Only about a million and a half species have ever been described, half of them insects. Scientists have described only about 222,000 species of flowering plants, and only expect to find tens of thousands more. Only about 43,000 vertebrate animals are known.</p>
        <p>The insect discoveries have thrilled Edward Wilson, the Harvard biologist. Erwin sent him the ants collected from a single tree in Peru. Wilson found 43 species, including several new ones. ''That's equal to the entire number of ant species in Canada or the British Isles,'' Wilson marveled. ''How on earth can 43 species of ants coexist on the same tree?'' he wonders. ''Ants are so fierce and territorial.''</p>
        <p>AS PERRY KNOWS, the true success of his canopy vehicles will be determined by how much scientists are actually able to use them for research. In part because of concerns over liability in case of an accident, and perhaps in part because of uneasy relations, none of the established centers for tropical research asked Perry to build the prototype in their territories.</p>
        <p>That, he predicts, will change as soon as more researchers see what new worlds the system can reveal. ''This is a very, very powerful tool for field biology,'' he says with confidence. ''As well as a fun toy.''</p>
        <p>Perry's cheeky statements have cost him. Without the support of Federal science agencies or major foundations, he had to piece together $30,000 to build the current cable system from unconventional sources: a Rolex Award for Enterprise, a fellowship from the Institute of Current World Affairs in New Hampshire, a small grant from the H. John Heinz 3d Fund and money from private individuals.</p>
        <p>For their next project, Perry and Williams envisage an expanded version, incorporating cables from a third tree in a way that would permit sideways sweeps as well, giving researchers ready access to all the life over four acres. Perry is already imagining still another step: a fully automated system of video cameras and sensors, broadcasting information via satellite to distant researchers.</p>
        <p>All that will have to wait a bit, though, until Perry finishes his book on human evolution. The thesis? That, far more recently than anthropologists have assumed, our ancestors remained arboreal creatures, at home in the treetops.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
