<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parley Urges Quick Action to Protect Atmosphere</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="158090"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DF153BF932A35754C0A96E948260" item-length="734" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parley Urges Quick Action to Protect Atmosphere</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, June 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Government officials, scientists and environmentalists from 48 countries called today for immediate action to halt degradation of the earth's atmosphere and set targets for global reductions in the burning of fossil fuels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Government officials, scientists and environmentalists from 48 countries called today for immediate action to halt degradation of the earth's atmosphere and set targets for global reductions in the burning of fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>Government officials, scientists and environmentalists from 48 countries called today for immediate action to halt degradation of the earth's atmosphere and set targets for global reductions in the burning of fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>Delegates to a conference on ''the changing atmosphere'' urged strong global measures to slow and then roll back pollution that, they agreed, is rapidly warming the earth's surface in a process that will produce profound climate change.</p>
        <p>The conference specifically called for a 20 percent worldwide reduction in the use of oil, coal and other fossil fuels by the year 2005 and an eventual reduction of 50 percent in the use of such fuels. The combustion of fossil fuels produces carbon dioxide, a chief cause of the global warming trend attributed to the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>Called by the Government of Canada, the conference included officials of many countries, as well as private scientists and others. The recommendations have no official or legal status. But participants said the newly emerging consensus on the need to act against atmospheric pollution, and the specific targets set here, would give an important impetus to national and international actions in the near future. First Such Agreement Cited</p>
        <p>At a news conference, Richard Ayres, a lawyer and expert for the Natural Resources Defense Council, an American group, said this was ''the first time that many countries have agreed to major changes in policy to protect the atmosphere, including setting the target of a 50 percent reduction in carbon dioxide levels.''</p>
        <p>In addition to the greenhouse effect, caused when carbon dioxide and other pollutants trap solar heat in the earth's atmosphere, the related problems of acid rain and destruction of the earth's ozone shield by industrial chemicals called chlorofluorocarbons must also be addressed, the conference said in a statement. Economic Needs Recognized</p>
        <p>The statement emphasized, however, that steps to halt the deterioration of the atmosphere must be compatible with sustainable economic growth, particularly in developing countries.</p>
        <p>The statement urged development of a ''comprehensive global convention'' for the protection of the atmosphere by the year 1992. Last year more than 40 nations agreed on a treaty to protect the ozone layer, which filters harmful ultraviolet rays, by curbing use of ozone-destroying chemicals. But experts said measures to slow the greenhouse effect would be more difficult and expensive because they require far-reaching changes in energy use.</p>
        <p>''Humanity is conducting an enormous, unintended, globally pervasive experiment whose ultimate consequences could be second only to global nuclear war,'' the conference statement said. ''The earth's atmosphere is being changed at an unprecedented rate by pollutants resulting from human activities, inefficient and wasteful fossil fuel use and the effects of rapid population growth in many regions. These changes represent a major threat to international security and are already having consequences over many parts of the globe.''</p>
        <p>Concerns about the atmosphere have become more urgent in recent weeks as some scientists argued that the global warming caused by the greenhouse effect had already begun. Other Recommendations</p>
        <p>Among other recommendations and findings of the conference were these:</p>
        <p>* Goverments should establish a ''world atmosphere fund'' financed by a tax on fossil-fuel consumption in the industrialized countries.</p>
        <p>* Half the 20 percent reduction in fossil fuel use should come from more efficient use of energy and the other half from switching to fuels that emit less carbon dioxide. Nuclear energy should be reviewed as an option but only if considerations of safety, waste disposal, proliferation and environmental damage are paramount.</p>
        <p>* The industrialized countries bear chief responsibility for the degradation of the earth's atmosphere and should be responsible for remedial actions. They also should help the developing countries industrialize in ways that do not add to the problem.</p>
        <p>* The treaty to protect the ozone layer should be revised to call for an almost complete elimination of chlorofluorocarbon production by 2000. The current agreement calls for a 50 percent rollback by the end of the century.</p>
        <p>The statement also said technology should be used vigorously to reduce the pollution that causes acid rain.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
