<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Quiet Vermonter Who Makes His Words Count</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="210009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="WASHINGTON TALK: THE SENATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">VERMONT</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONGRESS (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SENATE (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STAFFORD, ROBERT T (BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON TALK PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Vermont</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DB1730F93BA15751C1A96E948260" item-length="1265" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Quiet Vermonter Who Makes His Words Count</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Vermont's Republican Senator, Robert T. Stafford, may give the worst interview of any public official in the capital.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Vermont's Republican Senator, Robert T. Stafford, may give the worst interview of any public official in the capital.</p>
        <p>Vermont's Republican Senator, Robert T. Stafford, may give the worst interview of any public official in the capital.</p>
        <p>Retiring now after 28 years in Congress, Senator Stafford not only upheld the reputation of New Englanders for being laconic; he even enhanced it, in the view of many who know him well.</p>
        <p>When asked probing questions about such complex issues as the renewal of the clean air and hazardous waste laws, he would typically respond with a carefully considered ''Yes,'' ''No,'' or ''I don't know.''</p>
        <p>''I talked more when I was younger,'' he explained in an interview shortly before departing from Washington. Stood Up to Reagan</p>
        <p>Despite his terseness, Mr. Stafford is leaving office as one of the most popular members of Congress, with a record of success that includes backing landmark environmental laws and then defending them from attack. Among the attacks, several of his admirers noted, were some by President Reagan. In one notable case, Mr. Stafford helped lead the successful effort to override the President's veto of a strengthened Clean Water Act.</p>
        <p>''I didn't particularly enjoy finding myself at odds with the President,'' Mr. Stafford said, ''but it had to be done. I was not very popular at the White House.''</p>
        <p>His said his toughest job on the Senate Environment and Public Works Committee, of which he was chairman when the Republicans controlled the Senate from 1981 through 1986, was persuading Congress to expand and strengthen the toxic waste cleanup law in 1986. He also considers as highlights of his Senate career his efforts in passing or strengthening legislation such as the Clean Air Act, the Clean Water Act, the Safe Drinking Water Act and the law to clean asbestos in schools.</p>
        <p>He said he was pleased to be able to continue a tradition of bipartisanship that has marked the committee's activities. He said the committee's success was in large measure due to the efforts of two Democratic Senators, George J. Mitchell of Maine and Max Baucus of Montana, and two Republicans, John H. Chafee of Rhode Island and Dave Durenberger of Minnesota. Easy to Underestimate</p>
        <p>''He is so quiet and unassuming that people always underestimate him,'' said one of his staff aides. ''Everybody thinks he is a pushover. By the time they find out he is not, he has won. He is absolutely unyielding on something important. He is willing to compromise, but he will not capitulate.''</p>
        <p>Senator Mitchell, the new Senate majority leader, who was long a colleague on the Environment Committee, said the Vermonter's record on the committee was outstanding, particularly in his tenure as chairman.</p>
        <p>He called Mr. Stafford's environmental record noteworthy because ''of the environmentally hostile Administration with which we had to deal.'' Mr. Mitchell added: ''Against that tide he was able to lead the Congress in adopting landmark legislation.'' He mentioned amendments to toxic waste cleanup regulations, the Clean Water Act and the Endangered Species Act.</p>
        <p>''He was a great Senator and one of the nicest people I have met in or out of politics,'' Mr. Mitchell said. Still Making Suggestions</p>
        <p>Although one of Mr. Stafford's notable successes was helping to gain passage of the Clean Air Act, one of his disappointments was his inability to persuade Congress to strengthen the act, including new provisions to deal with acid rain, before he left Congress. But colleagues in Congress and environmentalists agree that the protections of the Clean Air Act would have been weakened in the Reagan Administration but for his staunch defense of the law as chairman of the Environment Committee.</p>
        <p>Although he is about to leave office, Mr. Stafford is still pressing for Government action to defend the country and the world from an array of what he perceives as increasingly grave environmental threats. Last summer, he introduced legislation that would address, in a comprehensive way, national and global environmental threats such as acid rain and the global warming caused by carbon dioxide and other industrial gases trapping heat from the sun. The Senate did not act on his bill, but it is widely expected that the 101st Congress will consider similar proposals.</p>
        <p>At a recent dinner in his honor given by the Environmental Law Institute, he said the ''next Administration should propose and the next Congress adopt legislation to deal with the hazards of acid rain and urban smog.'' But the ''real challenge'' facing the Bush administration, he contended, is ''to go beyond that narrow agenda.''</p>
        <p>''The true challenge, and the great opportunity,'' he continued, ''is to develop solutions that attack acid rain and other ground-level pollution and, at the same time, set us on a course to restore the atmospheric ozone level and to reclaim a normal global climate.'' Tribute From Muskie</p>
        <p>At that same dinner, former Senator Edmund S. Muskie of Maine, who for many years was chairman of the Senate Environmental Pollution Subcommittee and worked with Mr. Stafford on developing clean air and water legislation, said the Vermonter ''leaves Washington at the height of his reputation - appreciated and respected for his plain manners, his honesty, and his decency and valued as the conscience of the Senate in education, environment and public health.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Stafford's work on environmental legislation has attracted the most public attention, he said he was just as proud of legislation he sponsored requiring public schools to teach handicapped children in their regular programs. Before that legislation was passed, handicapped children were placed in separate programs. Because of the law, they are now included in the ''mainstream of education,'' he said. He also said he was happy about legislation he sponsored to help the children of poor Americans go to college.</p>
        <p>Born 75 years ago in Rutland, Vt., Mr. Stafford has served as a Rutland City prosecutor, an officer in the Navy, state's attorney, deputy Attorney General and Attorney General of Vermont, Lieutenant Governor and Governor, Vermont's Congressman in the United States House of Representatives and a member of the Senate since 1971. As Mr. Muskie noted, Mr. Stafford has received a government paycheck of one kind or another for the last 50 years. A Joke on Himself</p>
        <p>While no stand-up comic, Mr. Stafford has a somewhat sly, often self-deprecating sense of humor. He likes to tell of the time when he was Attorney General in Vermont and unsuccessfully arguing a case before the state's Chief Justice, Olin Jeffords, the father of Representative James M. Jeffords, who will take Mr. Stafford's Senate seat in the next Congress. As Mr. Stafford tells it, he complained to Justice Jeffords that arguing his case was ''like butting my head against a stone wall.''</p>
        <p>To which the Chief Justice replied: ''Mr. Attorney General, no one could do that with less fear of personal injury than you.''</p>
        <p>Jonathan Lash, who is head of Vermont's environmental protection agency, said, ''Bob Stafford symbolizes the qualities we like to think Vermont politicians should have - dignity, integrity, commitment to the environment.''</p>
        <p>Another Yankee virtue for which Mr. Stafford is noted, at least among his loyal and affectionate but not overawed staff, is thrift.</p>
        <p>''I am not going to call him parsimonious because he reprimanded me once for using that word,'' said one staff aide. ''But he is still wearing suits I know he had to have bought 15 or 20 years ago. He is definitely frugal.''</p>
        <p>''I don't think,'' the Senator conceded, ''that I have spent a lot of unnecessary money.''  WASHINGTON TALK: THE SENATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
