<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>35-Nation Conference Addresses Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="197638"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2D6153FF930A25752C1A96E948260" item-length="549" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>35-Nation Conference Addresses Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>GENEVA, Nov. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Representatives of 35 countries, including the United States, have begun an international effort to evaluate global climate trends and map policies to cope with the drastic consequences that a global warming would have on human life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Representatives of 35 countries, including the United States, have begun an international effort to evaluate global climate trends and map policies to cope with the drastic consequences that a global warming would have on human life.</p>
        <p>Representatives of 35 countries, including the United States, have begun an international effort to evaluate global climate trends and map policies to cope with the drastic consequences that a global warming would have on human life.</p>
        <p>In a three-day meeting that ended Friday, they established working groups with these assignments:</p>
        <p>* Assessing scientific evidence and longtime temperature records to determine if a global warming trend has really begun and, if so, to look at its causes.</p>
        <p>* Analyzing the environmental, economic and social impact of climate change.</p>
        <p>* Formulating responses. This group will be headed by the United States.</p>
        <p>The effort could lead to an international treaty to reduce the emission of carbon dioxide and other gases in the atmosphere, trapping heat from the earth in a ''greenhouse effect.''</p>
        <p>The Geneva meeting was organized by two agencies: the United Nations Environmental Program and the World Meteorological Organization, a United Nations specialized agency.</p>
        <p>The findings of the three groups are to be ready by mid-1990. It is hoped that their conclusions will ''justify actions by governments to limit and cope with climate change and to start negotiations'' for a treaty, said the executive director of the Environmental Program, Mustafa K. Tolba of Egypt. Global Villains Identified</p>
        <p>Officials expect the responses to center on changing global energy policies so as to use fossil fuels more efficiently and, in time, to reduce such use. Fossil fuels are the main source of atmospheric carbon dioxide, thought to be responsible for about half of global warming.</p>
        <p>Other major culprits - methane, nitrous oxide and chlorofluorocarbons, which are used as aerosol propellants, refrigerants and in injected foam -are also believed to contribute to the destruction of the protective ozone layer in the upper atmosphere.</p>
        <p>An agreement signed in Montreal last year commits industrial nations to a 50 percent reduction in the use of chlorofluorocarbons by 1999. Officials say another likely measure to combat global warming would be to further reduce the use of chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>''The fact that the U.S. could come here with a coherent position and a high level of representation was positive,'' said Rafe Pomerance, senior associate of the Washington-based World Resources Institute, which has previously criticized the Reagan Administration for inaction on this issue.</p>
        <p>Although international environmental officials tend to believe that evidence of a global warming trend is convincing, the United States is one of the countries that insisted on the definitive assessment that is to be made here.</p>
        <p>But American officials already believe that the evidence strongly suggests that the problem is real. ''We know that greenhouse gases are accumulating and in principle, they should lead to a global warming,'' said Frederick M. Bernthal, Assistant Secretary of State for International Environmental and Scientific Affairs.</p>
        <p>The United Natiions Environmental Program is a prime promoter of an international treaty on global warming. The organization is also involved in negotiations on a treaty to sharply limit the export of hazardous waste. That accord is expected to be ready for signing at a meeting scheduled in March in Basel, Switzerland.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
