<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For California Chardonnays, A Graceful 12-YeaR Evolution</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="119745"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDBERG, HOWARD G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAWLEY, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAMEY, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEIS, KEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DB103FF934A25751C0A96E948260" item-length="1186" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For California Chardonnays, A Graceful 12-YeaR Evolution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD G. GOLDBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDBERG, HOWARD G</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: CALIFORNIA chardonnay is the Cinderella of American wines. Largely klutzy, over-oaked and superalcoholic 12 years ago, it is today often seductively complex and smoother.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: CALIFORNIA chardonnay is the Cinderella of American wines. Largely klutzy, over-oaked and superalcoholic 12 years ago, it is today often seductively complex and smoother.</p>
        <p>CALIFORNIA chardonnay is the Cinderella of American wines. Largely klutzy, over-oaked and superalcoholic 12 years ago, it is today often seductively complex and smoother.</p>
        <p>Among the vintners who transformed this white wine are John Hawley of Clos du Bois and David Ramey of Matanzas Creek Winery, both in Sonoma County, and Ken Deis of Flora Springs Wine Company, in the Napa Valley. These are experts characterized as ''on the cutting edge'' by Rory P. Callahan, president of Wine and Food Associates, a Manhattan market-development company that represents the Wine Institute, a California trade association.</p>
        <p>Precisely what these men did, and how they did it, was the subject of a recent seminar held in New York and sponsored by their wineries. Mr. Callahan acted as moderator.</p>
        <p>Their theme was ''the evolution of California chardonnay.'' Their goal, the panelists agreed, was to overcome outdated notions about today's new-wave style.</p>
        <p>''What we feel, as representatives of sort of a younger, newer crowd of wine makers, is we are past the stage of just trying to make clean, sound wine,'' said Mr. Ramey, summarizing their professional intent. ''We're trying to make world-class wine now.''</p>
        <p>''Twelve years ago,'' he added, ''the wine-making ethos was that the wine maker was a baby sitter; that the highest calling was to take the optimum ripe fruit character and get it through into the bottle undisturbed.'' Today's leaner chardonnays are ''a made wine,'' he said, adding, ''We want to bring up the other notes of complexity.''</p>
        <p>Chardonnay, a so-called noble grape of the Vitis vinifera species, has become ''the runaway favorite of America's varietal wine drinkers,'' the hosts said in literature that accompanied their presentation.</p>
        <p>This popularity is mirrored in the quantity of chardonnay vines planted throughout their state. In 1976, the acreage totaled 11,410; by 1986, it had skyrocketed to 29,319. When 1987 figures of the California Agricultural Statistics Service are tabulated, the volume is likely to be still greater.</p>
        <p>Nationwide, 613 wineries produced chardonnay in 1986, the last year for which data are available, according to Wines and Vines, a trade publication. Of these, 420 were in California, and many of the 420 make more than one style of chardonnay yearly: a regular bottling, a vineyard-designated reserve and perhaps a version under a second label.</p>
        <p>The panelists, addressing 47 members of the wine trade and press at Keens Chop House, agreed that fast-changing technology and ceaseless research and experimentation have abetted significant advances in all stages of production.</p>
        <p>One can now find innovative viticultural techniques, gentler methods of handling and processing the fruit after harvest and improved methods of moving the juice from presses to tanks and vats and of fermentation, aging and blending.</p>
        <p>First, Mr. Hawley said, ''Wine makers are probably spending more time in the vineyards'' than before. Further, he said, ''there has been a re-evaluation of what makes or constitutes a ripe grape.'' The quantity of acid in grapes, which contributes to freshness and possibly longevity in wine, declines as the sugar content steadily increases during ripening. Today, chardonnay is being harvested earlier than before, the vintners said, and one result is a livelier fruit character in the wine.</p>
        <p>A dozen years ago, Mr. Deis said, most of the better grapes came from one vineyard because there were not many chardonnay vineyards, and, besides, ''few were very, very good.'' Today, to achieve nuances, vintners blend wines made from a spectrum of chardonnay areas, especially in cool climates, and from various growers.</p>
        <p>From the consumer's standpoint, the radical changes in enology - the science of wine making - in California cellars mean that the chardonnays are being made to taste better balanced and more complicated, and that they will generally age longer and more gracefully than most predecessors did.</p>
        <p>However, in the United States, ''ageability,'' as wine makers call one of their ideals, is pretty much theoretical. As Mr. Hawley said, polls ''have showed that 95 percent of all wines purchased, I think, are consumed within the next week.''</p>
        <p>The wine makers - who agreed that two other key sensory ideals, complexity and gracefulness, remain elusive - acknowledged a debt to the classical chardonnays that have made Burgundy famous. At Clos du Bois, Mr. Hawley said, the ''adoption of traditional Burgundian wine-making practices and learning how to apply these techniques'' have been the most important developments.</p>
        <p>One sea change in California, the wine makers said, is the shift away from the post-harvest fermentation in stainless-steel vats at 45 to 50 degrees Fahrenheit, which yields clean wines that, while highly fruity, tend to be one-dimensional.</p>
        <p>Today's emphasis is on French-style fermentation and many months of aging on yeast lees in relatively small oak barrels at 60 to 70 degrees.</p>
        <p>This enriches the aroma and, Mr. Hawley said, ''really marries the oak flavor into the wine.'' When the lees - virtually spent yeast cells and other solids precipitated from the wine - are periodically stirred, they may create a flavor that Mr. Deis called ''toastiness, as in Champagne.''</p>
        <p>During the first fermentation, within hours after grapes are picked, natural and commercial yeasts convert the fruit sugar to alcohol and carbon dioxide. Like many wineries in Burgundy, Clos du Bois and Matanzas Creek are increasingly putting fractions of their wines through a crucial flavor-enhancing second fermentation.</p>
        <p>This process, still the subject of debate, is called malolactic fermentation. It lends a butterlike fragrance to the aroma, imparts subtle flavors, softens the wine and adds body. It involves bacterial action that converts sharp malic acid (the kind found in apples) to softer lactic acid (the kind found in milk).</p>
        <p>Mr. Deis said Flora Springs avoided malolactic fermentation, believing that it would ''ruin the natural complexity and balance that we get with the grapes'' from the relatively warm central sector of the Napa Valley.</p>
        <p>Why did the muscular chardonnays of 12 years ago age poorly: taste overripe, become oxidized and turn orange and brown? To age properly, white wines require low infusions of tannin. (By contrast, red wines such as cabernet sauvignon need heavy doses of tannin.) Mr. Ramey blamed ''a fad of skin contact, which is not practiced at all in France'' during the first fermentation. After the grapes were crushed, they used to sit ''on the skins,'' sometimes overnight, a procedure that extracted the tannins from the skins. Today, minimal or no skin contact yields wine that, the vintners say, has a ''delicate mouth feel.''</p>
        <p>After nearly 90 minutes of dialogue involving the panel and the audience about breakthroughs, Peter Morrell of Morrell &amp; Company, an East Side wine merchant, asked, ''Have we skipped over one area totally - and that is soil?''</p>
        <p>Not to worry, Mr. Ramey assured him: ''Nothing has changed. We still have the same soil.'' For die-hard traditionalists, the news provided relief.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
