<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY: SATURDAY, JANUARY 9, 1988</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="108027"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">SUMMARY</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DD1338F93AA35752C0A96E948260" item-length="1082" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY: SATURDAY, JANUARY 9, 1988</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL/2-5</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL/2-5</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL/2-5</p>
        <p>Dozens of Palestinians were jailed under a procedure in which they can be held without trial for up to six months, Israeli officials said. An army spokesman said that the procedure was continuing in the Gaza Strip and the West Bank. Page 1</p>
        <p>A sense of powerlessness about Haiti seems to have overcome the Reagan Administration. American officials speak gloomily of a lack of leverage, of having exhausted the options, of casting about for the help of some trusted outsider. 2</p>
        <p>The costs of U.S. troops in Japan are the focus of legal changes that the Government and ruling party leaders have agreed to seek. The changes would enable Japan to absorb a larger share of the costs. 3</p>
        <p>Punitive measures against Panama are being considered by the Administration if Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega moves to consolidate his position of power, Administration officials said.  5</p>
        <p>In El Salvador, amnesty was refused by a judge to the five national guardsmen convicted of murdering four American churchwomen in 1980. Three of the men had applied for release under a general amnesty offered Nov. 5. 5</p>
        <p>In the Iran-contra investigation, Vice President Bush is expected to be placed under oath Monday during an interview with representatives of the special prosecutor in the affair, Reagan Administration officials said.  3</p>
        <p>Erich Honecker visited Paris. On his first visit to a Western country responsible for the security of Berlin, the East German leader, met polite but firm disagreement on human rights and arms control. 5</p>
        <p>A political murder in Philippines  3</p>
        <p>Dharmsala journal: Dalai Lama is Tibetans' refuge  A4</p>
        <p>Ice hockey follies, starring Qaddafi  5</p>
        <p>The nine Palestinians who face deportation by Israel  5</p>
        <p>NATIONAL/6-9, 28</p>
        <p>The unemployment rate eased one-tenth of a percentage point to 5.7 percent, the lowest since mid-1979, the Government reported. The growing economy created 326,000 more jobs in December. 1</p>
        <p>Unemployment drops in region  32</p>
        <p>Stock prices plunged violently, rekindling memories of the Friday that preceded the Wall Street collapse on Monday, Oct. 19. The Dow Jones industrial average dropped 140.58 points, or 6.85 percent, to 1,911.31.  1</p>
        <p>The cause of October's stock plunge was related to the use of two types of computerized stock trading employed by a handful of Wall Street's largest brokerage firms, according to a Presidential task force.  1</p>
        <p>News analysis: The report's finding that the market's plunge in October was set off and sustained by less than 10 institutions is a terrifying prospect that says much about modern financial markets 39</p>
        <p>Construction of a small space station by a private group would be backed by the Government under an agreement in principle reported to have been reached by a White House policy group. The station would fly into orbit years ahead of NASA's space outpost.  1</p>
        <p>Winter invaded the East Coast with heavy snow and freezing winds that disrupted transportation, government and business and recast the landscape into snowbound shapes from the Carolinas to New York. 1</p>
        <p>Arizona's Governor was indicted on six felony counts, including perjury and filing a false contribution report, that state's Attorney General's office announced. The Governor's brother, Willard, was also indicted on three counts.  1</p>
        <p>The President's emerging budget for 1989 proposes increases for the Education Department, the air traffic control system, the Federal crackdown on drug trafficking and white-collar crime, and other programs, confidential documents show.  28</p>
        <p>History convention reflects change to ''gender'' studies  6</p>
        <p>Los Angeles get $2 billion plan to provide housing for homeless  6</p>
        <p>Federal official says age bias cases were ignored  6</p>
        <p>AIDS testing without consent reported  7</p>
        <p>New method for detecting AIDS virus is reported  7</p>
        <p>Reaction to needles-for-addicts plan  7</p>
        <p>Canada denounces American report on acid rain  7</p>
        <p>Gary Hart says events last May made him stronger be,re1 8</p>
        <p>Petitions of Dole and Haig in Texas reported faulty  8</p>
        <p>Bush is target of foes at debate  9</p>
        <p>REGIONAL/29-32</p>
        <p>A hunt for the mentally disabled in New York City is being pressed by health and social workers. The people being sought may be due Social Security benefits that the courts have said were illegally cut off several years ago. 1</p>
        <p>The homeless in the bus terminal of the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey have become increasingly permanent residents. The terminal has become a refuge for hundreds of homeless people, who often have public services delivered to their blanket. 1</p>
        <p>Major changes in housing rules, including making leases in rent-stabilized apartments permanent and stiffening some penalties against landlords who do not properly maintain apartments are planned by the Cuomo administration. 29</p>
        <p>Princeton's 18th president, Harold T. Shapiro, took office. In his inaugural address, he appealed to American higher education to be more mindful of the moral and spiritual needs of college students.  29</p>
        <p>The Yonkers desegregation suit may be nearer to a settlement. The city's officials were reported to have offered to settle at least part of the suit by proposing to build 10 units of public housing on each of 20 sites in white neighborhoods.  30</p>
        <p>A man wanted in a shotgun killing of his former companion Thursday on a crowded platform in the Grand Central subway station was arrested outside his brother's home in East Orange, N.J., the police said.  be,re1 31</p>
        <p>Connecticut town finally ratifies the Constitution be,re1 29</p>
        <p>Life in Hell's Kitchen becomes a play  be,re1 29</p>
        <p>O'Neill does not have cancer be,re1 30</p>
        <p>Supreme Court is asked to block boy's return to Zimbabwe  30</p>
        <p>Officer cites wounds on Levin's neck  31</p>
        <p>Koch shunned by King memorial committee be,re1 31</p>
        <p>A feud at the City Bar Association moves to the court  31</p>
        <p>Taxi Commission member resigns</p>
        <p>31</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases 34</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
