<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush, Fighting Back Glee, Vows Tough Battle to End</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="188143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1988</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEBATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOYD, GERALD M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DE103EF936A25753C1A96E948260" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush, Fighting Back Glee, Vows Tough Battle to End</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD M. BOYD, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BOYD, GERALD M</byline>
      <dateline>LA JOLLA, Calif., Oct 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Vice President Bush's campaign began a battle against over-confidence today, with the Presidential nominee pledging to run hard over the remaining three weeks and aides publicly predicting a close race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Vice President Bush's campaign began a battle against over-confidence today, with the Presidential nominee pledging to run hard over the remaining three weeks and aides publicly predicting a close race.</p>
        <p>Vice President Bush's campaign began a battle against over-confidence today, with the Presidential nominee pledging to run hard over the remaining three weeks and aides publicly predicting a close race.</p>
        <p>But like a surfer riding the crest of a wave, Mr. Bush and his aides found it hard to hide clear feelings of exhilaration. As the Vice President began two days of campaigning in California, the aides used words like ''terrific'' and ''superb'' to describe his performance in Thursday night's debate against Gov. Michael S. Dukakis.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush described the last meeting between the two candidates as a sort of gunfight at the O.K. Corral. In his view, he was Marshal Wyatt Earp. 'Specific on the Issues'</p>
        <p>''The American people had a chance to watch two candidates in action,'' Mr. Bush said at an outdoor rally in Cerritos, a Los Angeles suburb bordering the Republican stronghold of Orange County.</p>
        <p>''We were specific on the issues, we came at each other pretty hard, and when the smoke cleared it was pretty clear where we stood. I believe that I moved my campaign forward by what happened last night.''</p>
        <p>But at the same time, the Republican nominee added a note of caution that other senior strategist made their message of the day.</p>
        <p>''I'm glad that that last debate is over, and now we have three weeks to take our case to the American people in rallies like this and at events all over this country,'' Mr. Bush said. ''I mean to run hard to campaign hard to stand on the issues, and I mean to win this election on Nov. 8.'' Dukakis Failures Seen</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's press secretary, Sheila Tate, said the candidate believed that the election remained close. ''We are going to fight it that way, flat out until election day,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But several senior Bush conceded that the campaign had clearly received a boost from the debate because in their view Mr. Dukakis had failed to accomplish several of the objectives that they said were important for the Democratic nominee, such as moving more to the political center and addressing an impression that he was distant as a candidate.</p>
        <p>James A. Baker, 3d, Mr. Bush's campaign chairman, said Mr. Dukakis had had too much to handle in the debate if he wanted both to appear more likable and to damage Mr. Bush. ''It's pretty hard to attack in a debate and at the same time appear more likable,'' Mr. Baker said on ''CBS This Morning.'' Comparison to Ford</p>
        <p>And Mr. Bush's campaign manager, Lee Atwater, said that the candidate had a firm 205 to 236 Electoral College votes, moving him close to the the 270 electoral votes needed to become President. By contrast, Mr. Atwater said, Mr. Dukakis will have to win all of the large Midwestern and Northeastern states as well as California. ''If he loses one or two of them, he's out,'' Mr. Atwater said. ''It's the same place Gerald Ford found himself in in 1976.''</p>
        <p>The air of caution was evident, however, in public statements by Mr. Bush's aides throughout the day. Mr. Baker had warned senior aides at the morning staff meeting against over-confidence. ''I think that the single biggest mistake we could make is to get over-confident,'' Mr. Atwater said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush received an enthusiastic reception from a crowd of several thousand people as he campaigned in Cerritos. a Republican stronghold. He spoke beneath a banner proclaiming, ''Good night, Mike.'' Focus on Strengths</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Bush appeared to take the high road today, his aides said he would continue his aggressive campaigning. They said he was prepared to meet what they predicted would be a negative barrage of campaigning from the Democratic nominee in an attempt to close the gap that polls show between the two candidates.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Bush's aims, they said, is to focus on issues where he is perceived as strong, like foreign policy. He plans to speak next week at Westminster College in Fulton, Mo., where Winston Churchill delivered his Iron Curtain address. Pledge on Environment</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Bush hopes to spend part of the next three weeks shoring up support among voters like Reagan Democrats in the Middle West and Northeast, environmentalists in California and Jewish voters in Illinois. Beginning on Oct. 24, he will remain on the road until the election.</p>
        <p>Today, he told the crowd in Cerritos: ''There are two men now asking for your vote, but only one of them shares your hopes, the values of the people here today. The values of plain, ordinary people.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also plans to attempt to counter issues that Mr. Dukakis has used to his advantage, such as the Vice President's record on the environment. Later today, with the Pacific Ocean as a backdrop, he spoke at the Scripps Institution of Oceanography at the University of California at San Diego.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush vowed to convene a global conference on the environment in his first year in office if he is elected, saying that such a gathering would address concerns such as acid rain and the possible warming of the earth's atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, seeking to counter Mr. Dukakis's attempt to attack the Republican nominee's position on offshore oil drilling, by offering what aides described as a balanced position.</p>
        <p>''I do believe that development of our most promising oil and gas reserves is called for, because continued domestic production of oil and gas is vital to the national security of the United States,'' he said. ''At the same time, I oppose drilling in those environmental sensitive areas where the risk of damage is too great,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
