<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Supporters Seeking Platform Offering a Wide-Ranging Appeal</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="155629"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1988</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUKAKIS, MICHAEL S (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DA123DF932A15755C0A96E948260" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Supporters Seeking Platform Offering a Wide-Ranging Appeal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD M. BOYD, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Supporters of Vice President Bush are hoping to use the 1988 Republican platform to make two key statements: that Mr. Bush is a leader who is ready to move in directions that President Reagan has not tried and that the politics of Michael S. Dukakis are out of touch with the majority of American voters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Supporters of Vice President Bush are hoping to use the 1988 Republican platform to make two key statements: that Mr. Bush is a leader who is ready to move in directions that President Reagan has not tried and that the politics of Michael S. Dukakis are out of touch with the majority of American voters.</p>
        <p>Supporters of Vice President Bush are hoping to use the 1988 Republican platform to make two key statements: that Mr. Bush is a leader who is ready to move in directions that President Reagan has not tried and that the politics of Michael S. Dukakis are out of touch with the majority of American voters.</p>
        <p>Those objectives are dominating the early drafting of the platform document, which is being completed with little public attention and with general agreement over much of what it will say. While supporters of Mr. Bush would like it to reflect language that any Republican candidate can run on, they also want it to highlight that the Vice President wants a Republican Party that will spend more on education and will take tougher measures to protect the environment than Mr. Reagan has done. Larger U.S. Role Is Sought</p>
        <p>''It will be clear that a President Bush will anticipate a much larger Federal role on those issues,'' said a key Bush aide, who has been involved in the platform deliberations.</p>
        <p>The attempt to use the platform as a weapon against Mr. Dukakis, the probable Democratic nominee, is expected to come through in language criticizing some Democratic positions on taxes and military spending.</p>
        <p>But Bush campaign aides say the platform could offer more personal attacks. For example, officials familiar with the early work on it say they would not be surprise to see it include language that supports the Pledge of Allegiance being recited at the start of each school day. That would represent a swipe at Mr. Dukakis, the Governor of Massachusetts, who vetoed a bill in 1977 requiring teachers to lead students in the pledge at the beginning of each school day.</p>
        <p>As envisioned by Mr. Bush's aides, the platform will attempt to spell out what Mr. Bush's leadership would mean. For example, they say it will stress that the Vice President will make such issues as education a priority and that it will receive more Federal money than it has under President Reagan. Mr. Bush has already called for spending about $600 million more than the $20.3 billion that President Reagan sought in the budget for fiscal 1989.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's supporters also expect the platform to reflect the Vice President's contention that the Republican Party must become committed to the environment. That point could be reflected in language that calls for a curb on off-shore drilling leases, which the Vice President recently proposed, and that endorses immediate Federal action to combat acid rain, which received only brief mention in the 1984 Republican Party document, aides to the Vice President said. A Line Item Veto</p>
        <p>In addition, to reflect a key campaign issue of Mr. Bush, the platform would place more emphasis on such issues as providing the President with the authority to veto individual items in appropriations bills than the 1984 document did, a top aide said.</p>
        <p>The small group drafting the platform has already held two public meetings, one in Kansas City and another in Washington. A third and final session is planned for Los Angeles at the end of the month. But little formal drafting has actually happened. The committee will submit the document to delegates to vote on at the Republican National Convention, which will be held Aug. 15-18 in New Orleans.</p>
        <p>Despite the public hearings, however, the Republican platform has attracted little notice. Moreover, aides and supporters of Mr. Bush are not anticipating major squabbles such as those that could erupt at the Democratic National Convention next month.</p>
        <p>''I expect the 1988 Republican Party platform to be similar to 1984, although certain issues will receive more emphasis and others less,'' said Governor Kay Orr of Nebraska, the chairman of the Republican Platform Committee. He Placates the Right</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush sought to prevent an eruption over the platform several weeks ago by seeking to placate the party's far right. The Vice President indicated that he would essentially adhere to the language in President Reagan's 1984 platform, which most of the conservatives endorsed.</p>
        <p>''We certainly look forward to using the platform as an opportunity to go on the offensive against the Democrats,'' said James P. Pinkerton, the director of research for the Bush campaign and who has been working on issues related to the platform. ''We think it will make clear the choice between George Bush, the conservative, and Mike Dukakis, the liberal.''</p>
        <p>Aides to Mr. Bush say the platform could also voice strong opposition to prison furlough plans, which Mr. Dukakis supported at one time as Governor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dukakis reversed his position on a furlough program in March, after his declining to support a ban on such a furlough had threatend to make him the target of a law-and-order campaign.</p>
        <p>Supporters of the Vice President say he will not attempt to change some more conservative planks that have appeared in the platform since Mr. Reagan took office in 1980. Mr. Bush is in general agreement with such planks, which include opposition to the Equal Rights Amendment, prayer in school and a constitutional amendment to outlaw abortion.</p>
        <p>The approach would accomplish two objectives, supporters of Mr. Bush say: steering the Republican Party clear of more divisive issues that have often been found in some previous platform and making the document one that Mr. Bush and other Republican candidates can embrace.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
