<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To the Tories, Thatcher Stays to Rule</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="188169"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WHITNEY, CRAIG R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">THATCHER, MARGARET H (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DD1F3EF936A25753C1A96E948260" item-length="893" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To the Tories, Thatcher Stays to Rule</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG R. WHITNEY, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WHITNEY, CRAIG R</byline>
      <dateline>BRIGHTON, England, Oct. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Will the Conservative Party rule Britain into the 21st century? If you asked that question here this week during the annual conference of Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher's Conservative Party, the answer was yes, and why not?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Will the Conservative Party rule Britain into the 21st century? If you asked that question here this week during the annual conference of Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher's Conservative Party, the answer was yes, and why not?</p>
        <p>Will the Conservative Party rule Britain into the 21st century? If you asked that question here this week during the annual conference of Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher's Conservative Party, the answer was yes, and why not?</p>
        <p>Lord Young, the Minister for Trade and Industry, promised the delegates that Britain's coal industry, nationalized in 1946, would be turned back to private industry ''in the next Parliament'' - after elections in 1991, which no one in the room appeared to have any doubt the Conservatives would win.</p>
        <p>Nor did any of the speakers, including the main figures in Mrs. Thatcher's Cabinet, voice any doubt in four days of gentle debate that she would, in her own words, go ''on and on'' for most of the rest of this century if her robust health held up.</p>
        <p>Royal Navy destroyers and armed commandos patrolled the waters in front of the sealed-off conference center and the beachfront Grand Hotel, heavily damaged by an Irish Republican Army terrorist bomb in 1984, the last time the Conservatives met here. Mrs. Thatcher passed her 63d birthday inside the hotel on Thursday. To Keep Interest Rates High</p>
        <p>''Have you ever known a time when our country was more prosperous?'' the Chancellor of the Exchequer, Nigel Lawson, asked Thursday, acknowledging that he would have to keep interest rates high well into next year to fight inflation because of ''just a bit too much of a good thing.''</p>
        <p>All this might be written off as partisan self-congratulation if the opposition Labor Party were not in disarray, as evidenced at its own conference in Blackpool last week. As it is, only an unofficial Conservative group calling itself the Charter Movement invited the 4,000 delegates to think about what the party's future would be without Mrs. Thatcher, and pick her successor.</p>
        <p>A total of 572 took part, and the front-runner with 148 votes was Michael Heseltine, 55 years old, who was Defense Secretary in Mrs. Thatcher's Cabinet until a scandal involving a British helicopter company forced him to leave in 1986. Out of office, he has hardly concealed his ambition to succeed Mrs. Thatcher as leader, but the vote does not mean he will ever get it, explained Eric Chalker, a Charter Movement delegate from London.</p>
        <p>''We think that the party should be run democratically, but we have 100 years of tradition to shift,'' he said with resignation, explaining that Jeffrey Archer, the novelist and entrepreneur, had come in second with 129 votes. Mr. Archer was forced to resign as deputy chairman of the party's central office when his name and that of a prostitute were published in proximity in two British tabloids. Mr. Archer later won damages from the papers. Heath Talks About Europe</p>
        <p>A bookmaker, William Hill, was taking 3-to-1 odds at the conference for Education Secretary Kenneth Baker, with Mr. Heseltine at 12 to 1. But there will not be a new party leader unless the party's members of Parliament choose somebody else, a thought that has not even arisen here this week.</p>
        <p>A man who used to be leader, former Prime Minister Edward Heath, took the floor Thursday to disagree with Mrs. Thatcher's vision of Europe. It was Mr. Heath who took Britain into the European Community in 1973.</p>
        <p>''It is not just a single market,'' Mr. Heath said; ''it is a single market which is also concerned with a single currency and a single central bank.'' Mrs. Thatcher has opposed both of these as unrealistic now, and her supporters in the hall booed Mr. Heath as he went on to say, ''The rest of the community is going ahead, with or without us.''</p>
        <p>Winding up the conference this afternoon, Mrs. Thatcher acknowledged that some of her recent utterances on Europe had made people think she had reopened the Hundred Years' War. She said the debate had brought into the open ''the choice between two kinds of Europe: a Europe based on the widest possible freedom for enterprise, or a Europe governed by socialist methods of centralized control and regulation.''</p>
        <p>''We haven't worked all these years to free Britain from the paralysis of socialism only to see it creep in through the backdoor of central control and bureaucracy from Brussels,'' she said. But she added that Britain made the second-largest financial contribution to the European Community budget, and stationed nearly 70,000 troops, mainly on the Continent.</p>
        <p>''With those sort of credentials,'' she said, ''no one should doubt Britain's wholehearted commitment to Europe.'' About the future, she said that after nearly 10 years in power, next year would mark the start of the next 10.</p>
        <p>Increased prosperity, she said, had prompted individual and corporate generosity, to the tune of $2.5 billion a year ''to boost charities, rebuild churches, help medical research and feed the hungry.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Thatcher pledged to support policies to protect the environment, cutting down the use of fossil fuels, but continuing to use nuclear power in its place, but she got her biggest round of applause when, discussing Northern Ireland, she said, ''This Government will never surrender to the I.R.A. -never!''</p>
        <p>''President Reagan has rebuilt the strength and confidence of the West, not without a little help,'' she said. ''It is vital that Britain and America should always stand together. So the next President of the United States too will have the United Kingdom as a staunch ally.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
