<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="204673"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7D91631F934A35751C1A96E948260" item-length="845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International A3-19</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International A3-19</p>
        <p>International A3-19</p>
        <p>Mikhail Gorbachev is in New York on a visit intended to showcase a more benign Soviet foreign policy and set an agenda for dealings with the Bush administration. Page A1</p>
        <p>The Gorbachevs swept to Manhattan waving from their Zil limousine, which probably missed the Gorbachev look-alike at Trump Tower. The city that never sleeps but is always ready to yawn was excited, in a sort of blase way. A1</p>
        <p>Three people were killed in Baku, the Azerbaijani capital, and 44 were wounded in rioting that followed the forcible early-morning disperal of a rally on a central square, the military commander of the city said. A3</p>
        <p>Mikhail Gorbachev's U.N. address today shows the change in Moscow's view of the United Nations: a major player in world affairs rather than a platform to attack the West and court the third world. A18</p>
        <p>Yasir Arafat met five U.S. Jews in Sweden to discuss the prospects for peace in the Middle East. Mr. Arafat used the day's symbolism to portray himself as a moderate Middle East peace broker. A6  Labor will reconsider a coalition with the Likud party when it holds a Central Committee vote. Shimon Peres called for the vote to reopen negotiations one day after saying such talks were unworkable. A6</p>
        <p>Israel is holding Palestinians in ''crowded and inhumane'' conditions at its army's Ketziot detention center, violating the Fourth Geneva Convention, an international human rights group said in a report. A6</p>
        <p>At Kabul University, Marxist symbols are put away A13</p>
        <p>China replaces Tibet Communist leader amid signs of unrest A14</p>
        <p>National A20-28, B12-15, D22</p>
        <p>Nuclear weapon plant pollution in Ohio, Texas, and a national laboratory in California posed much greater threats to public health than had been acknowledged, the Energy Department said. A1</p>
        <p>William Webster will be C.I.A. chief in the next administration, the President-elect said, naming choices for Commerce Secretary, representative to the United Nations and U.S. Special Trade Representative. A1</p>
        <p>A top lawmaker said a tax increase is undoubtedly needed to reduce the budget deficit. Dan Rostenkowski, who heads the House tax-writing committee, said his first choice was to increase the tax on gasoline. A1</p>
        <p>Attorneys prosecuting Oliver North pared back their case against him, saying they no longer contend that he used the profits from U.S. arms sales for any illegal purpose except covert war in Central America. A1</p>
        <p>The Justice Department told doctors that they are under surveillance for evidence of price fixing and other violations of the antitrust laws. Grand jury investigations are under way in three cities. A1</p>
        <p>The shuttle Atlantis landed safely at Edwards Air Force Base in California in the afternoon, testing its newly designed brakes and nose wheel steering system. D22</p>
        <p>Son of an old Massachusetts family, Joseph Eaton was homeless when he died outside a San Francisco restaurant. Mr. Eaton had struggled against addictions to alcohol and drugs for many years, reports said. A22</p>
        <p>Global warming caused by pollution will make droughts much more frequent and storms much fiercer, new data presented at a conference on climate change show. A25</p>
        <p>Coal miners were denied benefits improperly by the Federal Government, the Supreme Court ruled. The miners developed symptoms of black lung disease in the 1970's. A26</p>
        <p>Washington Talk B15</p>
        <p>Regional B1-10, B18</p>
        <p>An unabated rise in AIDS cases and deaths that will require billions of dollars in expanded services over the next five years is indicated in stark new AIDS projections by New York State health officials. B1</p>
        <p>Governor Cuomo said tax increases would probably be included with spending cuts in his plan to meet the state's budget gap. He said he remained opposed to increases in income tax. B1</p>
        <p>Evidence of sexual abuse on Lisa Steinberg was seen by Hedda Nussbaum when Lisa was 2 years old and had just returned from three weeks at the house of a couple with whom Ms. Nassbaum used to smoke cocaine, she said. B1</p>
        <p>The Republican candidacy for mayor of New York City may interest United States Attorney Rudolph Giuliani, he has told party leaders through intermediaries. Leaders say he has hinted that he may leave his post in January. B1</p>
        <p>A jury verdict may cripple Lilco, Wall Street analysts said, but the situation created by a Federal jury finding that Lilco lied to obtain a rate increase will remain unsettled until several questions are resolved. B2</p>
        <p>Old Scibner Bookstore on Fifth Avenue to close B3</p>
        <p>Columbia County's 'trial of century' has a sequel B5</p>
        <p>Drive against underground economy nets city $151 million B7</p>
        <p>Trump is prepared to advertise against Koch B8</p>
        <p>Koch proposes charging shelter residents rent B9</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases B6</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
