<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Celebration of Hospitality</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="142057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">APPALACHIAN MOUNTAIN CLUB</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRYANT, NELSON</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">OUTDOORS (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED71E3BF936A35756C0A96E948260" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Celebration of Hospitality</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nelson Bryant</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRYANT, NELSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: WHAT it describes as a ''celebration of 100 years of hospitality in high places'' is planned by the venerable Appalachian Mountain Club this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: WHAT it describes as a ''celebration of 100 years of hospitality in high places'' is planned by the venerable Appalachian Mountain Club this year.</p>
        <p>WHAT it describes as a ''celebration of 100 years of hospitality in high places'' is planned by the venerable Appalachian Mountain Club this year.</p>
        <p>The club's hut system, a chain of eight mountain lodges within a 50-mile radius, began 100 years ago. The only setup of its kind in the United States, it permits hikers carrying a minimum of gear and food to spend up to a week in the White Mountains.</p>
        <p>On May 18-21, the club is sponsoring a research conference at the Eagle Mountain House in Jackson, N.H., that will explore ways to watch over the ecosystems of mountains in the Northeast. It will include discussions of the threats posed to water quality by housing and ski area developments and acid rain.</p>
        <p>On June 4 in the Pinkham Notch area there will be an afternoon program aimed at recognizing both volunteers and staff who have contributed to the success of the hut system. A buffet lunch is included. This affair is open to the public and tickets may be obtained from the club. Another event, by invitation only, will be held June 5 at the Madison hut, the first to be built, and will include yarn-spinning by veteran hut crew and club members.</p>
        <p>This year, the club will have a computerized reservation system for its huts, which, in addition to accepting credit cards for the first time, will include special rates for those who agree to visit less-used huts or who are willing to schedule their hikes during off-peak periods. Last year, approximately 400,000 hikers visited the huts, each of which is staffed by a crew of four to eight. All huts are open for full service from early June through early September and two of them are maintained on a self-service basis by caretakers during the winter. For more information - including a brochure explaining the new rates - on the centennial celebration, write Reservations, A.M.C. Pinkham Notch Camp, Box 298-A, Gorham, N.H. 03581, or call (603) 466-2727. Those who may wish to join the club may call its Boston headquarters (617) 523-0636.</p>
        <p>Each year the 112-year-old club, which calls itself the ''nation's oldest mountaineering/conservation organization,'' sponsors a wide variety of classes ranging from alpine biology to backpacking in the wild. This spring and summer there will also be an evening lecture series at the Pinkham Notch facility whose subjects include mycology, wolves, Arctic and alpine plants and difficulties encountered by high-altitude hikers.</p>
        <p>For those who haven't the time for a full-fledged fly-fishing school, the Orvis Company of Manchester, Vt., is offering a series of Friday-Saturday fly-casting sessions at the Eldred Preserve in the Catskills.</p>
        <p>The sessions - May 6-7, 13-14, 20-21 and June 17-18 - will include casting, knot tying, the selection of rod, reel and flies and identification of the insects, aquatic and terrestrial, upon which trout dine. Particpants - who will actually catch and release trout - will be served what is described as a gourmet dinner Friday night, after which there will be a presentation intended to prepare them for the next day's activities. The cost, including one night's lodging, Friday's meal and two on Saturday, some complimentary trout flies and a copy of the ''Orvis Fly-Fishing Guide,'' is $175, and the sessions are limited to 15 persons each. The preserve is about a 90-minute drive from New York City. For more information and reservations, call Randy Carlson or Wayne Nester at (212) 697-3133.</p>
        <p>Concentrations of PCB's, polychlorinated biphenyls, in Hudson River striped bass sampled last year remain above the limit deemed fit for human consumption by the Food and Drug Administration. For that reason, the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation has said that it would continue the ban begun in 1976 against commercial fishing for the species in the Hudson for another year. Recreational anglers who take stripers from the lower Hudson have been cautioned to restrict their consumption of the fish severely, and women of child-bearing age have been urged to avoid stripers altogether. Fishing is not permitted at all in the Upper Hudson between Fort Edward and the Troy dam, where the PCB's are at their highest concentrations.</p>
        <p>Every once in a while a product lives up to the claims made for it. This is true of the ''Sports Guard'' gloves recently put on the market by DuPont. Made of Kevlar fibers, the same material that is used in bullet-proof vests and in manufacturing the lightest, toughest canoes available, the gloves have hundreds of rubber ''dots'' on fingers, thumb and palm. They are excellent for guarding one's hand's from knife or fins while cleaning fish, and they provide superb protection for the amateur opener of oysters. The rubber dots also enhance the gripping tool handles when one's hands are cold. The literature that comes with them suggests that they would also be good for handling the leader when a big-game fish is coming aboard. To partially test that theory, I put them on, wrapped a couple of turns of 50-pound monofilament line around each hand and snapped it easily. Had I tried that barehanded, I would have been cut to the bone.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
