<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Space Age, the Old Wind Tunnel Is Being Left Behind</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Education; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="107080"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DESIGN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED7113FF936A35752C0A96E948260" item-length="1652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Space Age, the Old Wind Tunnel Is Being Left Behind</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: AEROSPACE engineers have hit a dead end in conventional efforts to test designs for the next generation of spaceships, planetary probes and other futuristic flying machines, prompting a rush of new proposals and projects for exotic techniques to help develop 21st-century spacecraft.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: AEROSPACE engineers have hit a dead end in conventional efforts to test designs for the next generation of spaceships, planetary probes and other futuristic flying machines, prompting a rush of new proposals and projects for exotic techniques to help develop 21st-century spacecraft.</p>
        <p>AEROSPACE engineers have hit a dead end in conventional efforts to test designs for the next generation of spaceships, planetary probes and other futuristic flying machines, prompting a rush of new proposals and projects for exotic techniques to help develop 21st-century spacecraft.</p>
        <p>The technology to build new types of space-age vehicles is rapidly taking shape; in theory, they will be partly powered by atmospheric gasses rather than exclusively by on-board fuels. They will be able to reach incredibly fast speeds, and to perform complex maneuvers such as zipping in and out of planetary atmospheres rather than just plunging through them in uncontrolled descents.</p>
        <p>The problem is getting realistic flight data. Today, testing these tricky designs is based on little more than the wind tunnel, a 19th-century invention used by the Wright brothers to pave the way for powered flight.</p>
        <p>''We've pushed beyond the capacity of most of our ground facilities,'' said William I. Scallion, an official at NASA's Langley Research Center in Hampton, Va.</p>
        <p>As a result, the Air Force, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration and various universities around the nation are exploring a wide range of new ways to mimic the daunting speeds, heats, stresses, forces and vibrations that challenge the future of flight.</p>
        <p>Among them are improved wind tunnels, entirely new classes of ground-test facilities to achieve higher simulated speeds. Other techniques include rockets firing small-scale models into the earth's atmosphere and tiny test vehicles that would be dropped from space shuttles in space. The cost of such projects could add up to billions of dollars, experts say.</p>
        <p>''No one facility will do everything,'' said Seymour M. Bogdonoff, a professor of aerospace engineering at Princeton University who advises the space agency. ''It's a whole broad frontier that has to be investigated.''</p>
        <p>The need for more advanced testing facilities arises from the growing complexity of spacecraft and their missions. Spaceships are no longer simple objects that plunge though planetary atmospheres, as the Mercury and Apollo space capsules did. Instead, like the space shuttles, they are to incorporate increasingly complex aerodynamic features to achieve greater flexibility and economy.</p>
        <p>The most pressing challenge is presented by the multibillion-dollar Federal effort to build the X-30 aerospace plane. Unlike today's conventional rockets and space shuttles, its engines would use atmospheric oxygen to burn their fuel. In the late 1990's, the plane would lift off runways and fly directly into space at speeds of more than 17,000 miles an hour, or 25 times the speed of sound. Current wind tunnels can realistically mimic conditions at only half that speed.</p>
        <p>Another design hurdle is presented by NASA's Aeromaneuvering Orbit Transfer Vehicle, a low-cost space tug meant to slow itself by grazing the earth's outer atmosphere rather than firing retrorockets, which are heavy and expensive to lift into space. No current facility can get close to mimicking such conditions.</p>
        <p>Still other goals are to design complex probes to fly through the atmospheres of Mars, Jupiter and Titan, a moon of Saturn, whose atmospheres are quite different from Earth's. Role of Super Computers</p>
        <p>Some of the expected conditions can be simulated by super computers, incredibly fast machines that perform billions of calculations a second to mathematically mimic events in the real world. But experts agree that super computers are not enough.</p>
        <p>''Computers can't do anything unless you know what data to put in them,'' said Dr. Bogdonoff of Princeton. The current task, he said, is to discover and document the key physical phenomena that will govern the era of future flight. These can then be fed into computers to perfect new types of designs.</p>
        <p>Experts say one strategy in gathering new data is to tease more information out of the current generation of wind tunnels, since at even relatively low speeds the new aerodynamic shapes will present daunting challenges.</p>
        <p>''The airflow over the aerospace plane is going to be horribly complicated,'' said Gary S. Settles, a professor of mechanical engineer at Pennsylvania State University. ''Until we really understand these very difficult flows of gasses, we cannot design advanced vehicles.''</p>
        <p>At Penn State, Dr. Settles and his colleagues have pioneered new probes that shine thin slices of laser light through air currents in conventional wind tunnels, revealing complexities otherwise hidden amid whorls of wind. Such methods are being pushed even further with holography, which uses laser light to create three-dimensional pictures of turbulence.</p>
        <p>''You can capture the flow field and study it at leisure from all angles,'' Dr. Settles noted. Mimicking Hypersonic Speeds</p>
        <p>Another tactic is to build new wind tunnels that unleash more powerful blasts, such as the Hypersonic Facility Complex being planned at the Air Force's Arnold Engineering Development Center, in Tullahoma, Tenn. One option under consideration is to use flashes of electricity to explosively heat air, which would rush over test objects. The goal is realistic mimicry of hypersonic speeds, more than five times the speed of sound. The speed of sound at sea level is 760 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>A radical new approach is being studied by NASA and researchers at the University of Texas. Rather than blowing gasses over a stationary model, as current wind tunnels do, it would use rail guns, propulsive devices that use magnetic rather than chemical energy, to fire small-scale models of advanced flying machines through different kinds of atmospheric gasses.</p>
        <p>Researchers at the University of Texas have proposed a facility that would be the world's largest rail gun. It would be a third of a mile long, and its center pipe would be 18 inches in diameter. After being accelerated by powerful magnets to a speed of 13,500 miles an hour (and possibly twice that in advanced versions), the test vehicle would speed into a 1,000-foot-long test chamber, where it would undergo the shaking and pounding of simulated flight. The chamber would be filled with air, nitrogen or carbon dioxide, simulating the planetary atmosphere under study.</p>
        <p>''A driving force is that there's no data on how different bodies behave in the atmospheres of other planets,'' said William F. Weldon, a Texas researcher at the University's Center for Electromechanics who is working on the rail-gun proposal.</p>
        <p>Test vehicles could weigh up to 22 pounds, and would emit radio signals reporting on-board temperatures, pressures, stresses and other phenomena.</p>
        <p>In addition to high speeds, the setup has another advantage over wind tunnels: the test chamber could simulate the different densities of gasses found at various altitudes in real planetary atmospheres. Unlike gun-powered ballistic test ranges, which can also fire small-scale models, the facility's acceleration would be exceedingly smooth, protecting fragile models from breakup so they could be examined after the flight. Estimates Up to $200 Million</p>
        <p>Texas researchers estimate such a facility would cost from $47 million to $57 million, depending on the choice of electromagnetic accelerator. Other estimates range up to $200 million or more.</p>
        <p>''This facility would not be cheap,'' said Mr. Scallion at NASA Langley, who is studying the concept for the space agency. ''But it's less expensive than doing lots of sub-scale flight tests.''</p>
        <p>One mystery such a facility could address is the strange vortexes shed by the nose of high-speed flight bodies. When these vortexes encounter shock waves further back on a craft, the vortexes can burst apart, causing violent pressures and serious damage. Some engineers believe that such forces were to blame for the loss of protective tiles from the tail region of space shuttles when they re-entered the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Going beyond new ground facilities, NASA is planning to fire advanced vehicle models atop rockets into the atmosphere at speeds of up to Mach 12, radioing data back to ground controllers. The first such flight, in what is known as the Hyfire program, might take place as early as January 1989.</p>
        <p>''We think we could eventually fly six to eight flights a year to pin down key technical questions'' about the aerospace plane, said Randolph A. Graves Jr., director of NASA's aerodynamics division. ''It looks quite attractive.''</p>
        <p>In 1993, in one of the most ambitious projects of all, NASA is planning to toss a model of a new vehicle out of the space shuttle. Called the Aeroassist Flight Experiment, it is to gather data to perfect a technique known as ''aerobraking,'' in which a light-weight shield slows down a vehicle as it zooms through a planetary atmosphere. Aerobrakes are key to the Aeromaneuvering Orbit Transfer Vehicle, a low-cost space tug planned for the late 1990's to move payloads routinely back and forth between high-earth orbits and low ones. Aerobrakes for Spacecraft</p>
        <p>Further off, a second NASA space experiment focuses on aerobrakes for Mars missions, which would slow fast-moving unmanned spacecraft so they could land safely on the planet.</p>
        <p>''Aerobraking is an interesting, low-cost technique,'' said Dr. Graves at NASA headquarters, ''but it's going to take work to perfect it.''</p>
        <p>Experts say that the United States is not the only country pursuing the goal of advanced, 21st century flying machines. Japan, Britain, France, Germany and the European Space Agency all have hypersonic research programs, with ambitious space projects on the drawing boards. For the moment, the United States leads the world in the pursuit of such goals - and aerospace engineers say they want to keep it that way.</p>
        <p>''We have to push ahead,'' said Mr. Scallion of NASA Langley, warning that ''otherwise we're going to lose out'' in the race to exploit the heavens with new classes of spacecraft.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
