<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Season Grows Longer In Saratoga</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="153291"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPAS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SARATOGA (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KUNSTLER, JAMES HOWARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1D91326E432BC4E53DFBE6E958A" item-length="2371" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Season Grows Longer In Saratoga</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES HOWARD KUNSTLER; JAMES HOWARD KUNSTLER's new novel, ''Thunder Island,'' was published this month by Bantam; he lives in Saratoga County.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KUNSTLER, JAMES HOWARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: HERE'S what it's like to take a mineral bath at the Saratoga Spa. An attendant ushers you into a spacious chamber done in austere Depression-vintage decor. The floor is covered with tiny black and white tiles. There is a plain single bed and a rattan chair. Sydney Greenstreet would not look out of place sitting there in a wrinkled white suit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: HERE'S what it's like to take a mineral bath at the Saratoga Spa. An attendant ushers you into a spacious chamber done in austere Depression-vintage decor. The floor is covered with tiny black and white tiles. There is a plain single bed and a rattan chair. Sydney Greenstreet would not look out of place sitting there in a wrinkled white suit.</p>
        <p>HERE'S what it's like to take a mineral bath at the Saratoga Spa. An attendant ushers you into a spacious chamber done in austere Depression-vintage decor. The floor is covered with tiny black and white tiles. There is a plain single bed and a rattan chair. Sydney Greenstreet would not look out of place sitting there in a wrinkled white suit. A 60-gallon tub, roughly twice the size of the average home model, is filled with greenish spring water heated to 98 degrees. The attendant discreetly withdraws.</p>
        <p>You submerge. The smell of the waters is piquant, shall we say. Almost at once tiny bubbles begin to collect on the hairs of your chest (if you are so lucky to have any) as the carbon dioxide comes out of solution. You sink deeper, submersing your ears - the room is exceedingly quiet anyway, the bathhouse being a good mile from the highway.</p>
        <p>Soon you begin to notice an interesting phenomenon. Breathe in and your torso rises to the surface. Breathe out and you slowly sink back down into bubbly depths. Extend your arms and they float weightlessly. This is due to the high content of dissolved minerals, same as if you were swimming in the Great Salt Lake.</p>
        <p>By and by the attendant returns and wraps you in a warm sheet. You are invited to snooze on the bed for a while. You do not even hear him leave. Next, the masseur wakes you. You slide on top of his portable padded table and all the cares and woes of life in an election year are expelled from your muscle fibers. You depart feeling as though your backbone had been surgically removed.</p>
        <p>Long before the famous race track was carved out of the pines and bracken, Saratoga was renowned for its carbonated mineral springs. Sir William Johnson, the beloved diplomat to the Iroquois nation, was carried here on a litter by the Mohawks in 1767 to cure a siege of gout. Alas, the treatments did not avail, but word got out about the curious fizzy waters, slightly redolent of eggs gone bad. George Washington was lured over in 1783, after an inspection of Fort Ticonderoga, and briefly thought about building a summer place here - but then the Constitution came along and somebody had to be president.</p>
        <p>During the 1800's, a village grew up around Gideon Putnam's hotel, Congress Hall. New springs were easily tapped by drilling a few hundred feet down into the dolomitic limestone, and the elaborate pavilions built to house them became popular gathering spots. Soon the best families of the East came to sojourn in the ''season,'' as July and August were called.</p>
        <p>The Saratoga that lives in the popular imagination today is a Victorian fantasia of mammoth hotels, outlandish characters like Diamond Jim Brady, languid summer romance, and the kind of wretched excess that only vast amounts of money can buy. As a way of life it died out as completely as the civilization of the Incas. In the 1920's 30's and 40's, the town entered a shady phase when its allure was based on illicit gambling that flourished in fancy nightclubs operated by the mob, where society swells rubbed elbows with gangsters like Arnold Rothstein, Owney Madden and Charles (Lucky) Luciano. The Kefauver Commission would put an end to that scene after World War II.</p>
        <p>There was also a push in those days to make Saratoga into a health spa on the order of Baden-Baden and similar European resorts. This became a reality when Gov. Franklin Roosevelt was elected President in 1932. Because of his own health problems, Roosevelt was an aficionado of hydrotherapy. So the new President channeled millions of public works dollars into what eventually became the Saratoga Spa Reservation.</p>
        <p>The claims made for the spa waters over the years range from the plausible to the absolutely preposterous. In the old days, when medical knowledge was on a par with astrology, these claims were couched in the sort polysyllabic rhetoric that only W. C. Fields might utter with a straight face. The waters were said to ''promote the retrogressive change of tissue'' and to act as ''a prophylactic against dangerous congestions of the internal organs.'' Overindulgence was cautioned against for ''those who are by nature feeble.'' A sample list of diseases ''cured'' by imbibing the waters included scrofula, dropsy, smallpox, piles and ''hypochondrical complaints.''</p>
        <p>Baneology, or the science of bathing, was imported from Europe chiefly by Dr. Simon Baruch, father of the financier Bernard. Elaborate experiments were conducted at Saratoga to prove that the purported beneficial effects of the baths had some basis in scientific fact: that blood pressures could be lowered or that carbon dioxide bubbles on the skin dilated the capillaries. One Dr. Oskar Baudisch, the spa's director of research, maintained that the waters worked because the minerals they contained came from the dissolved fossils of prehistoric plants, and were thus chemically compatible with the stuff in living cells. In its heyday of the 1930's and 40's, the baths had a medical staff that ''prescribed'' such bathing therapies as the Nauheim Treatment (named after the German spa) for cardiac cases.</p>
        <p>''I think all therapy has some psychology to it - when you know you're being treated and told you're getting well, but it's only partially that,'' said Dr. Grace Swanner, a Saratoga Springs physician, now in her 80's, who was associated with the spa in its glory days. ''The American people are very impatient. They want a quick fix, they want to be cured yesterday.'' The baths went into a long, sad decline when the spa was turned over to the agency that runs New York's state parks. By 1970 the medical staff was gone and all pretensions about curing disease were abandoned. To make matters worse, state hydrologists had discovered traces of radium dissolved among the other minerals in the water, and the Health Department posted scary bulletins to inform the public. The fact that you had to drink 500 quarts a day for 30 years to gain the equivalent radiation of a dental X-ray seemed beside the point. It was terrible public relations.</p>
        <p>At their low ebb, the baths were operated by a demoralized staff of state workers who dealt with the public in the surly manner of Soviet shop clerks. The handsome Georgian Revival buildings, 50 years old, were starting to crumble. More than once the state threatened to close up the baths altogether.</p>
        <p>Saratoga itself went on a binge of self-destruction, as though it were bent on erasing its past and becoming just another upstate burg of raised ranch houses, auto parts shops and Kiwanian modernity. The United States Hotel (setting of Edna Ferber's ''Saratoga Trunk'') was razed and replaced by a Red Barn restaurant (plus several acres of parking lot). More cruelly ironic, the colossal Grand Union Hotel was torn down to make way for a Grand Union supermarket (no relation). The town got so seedy that the state even considered ending its August monopoly on horse racing.</p>
        <p>This downward slide might have been terminal, but in 1966 a consortium of businessmen and wealthy society folk like Mr. and Mrs. C. V. (Sonny) Whitney got the Performing Arts Center built, bringing in a new, more cultured breed of visitors. Meanwhile, a major new highway, Interstate 87, made Saratoga a half-hour commute from Albany, luring a professional class that recognized the value of decaying Victorian houses that could be bought cheaply well into the 1970's. Today, the process of yuppification is complete, and the town has more year-round vitality than it knew even in its glory days.</p>
        <p>For the baths, a major rehabilitation project is now under way. T. W. Services, a private enterprise that operates lodges in Yellowstone, Zion, Grand Canyon and Everglades National Parks, has leased the Roosevelt Baths and Gideon Putnam Hotel from the state of New York. They are spending a total of $5.2 million to fix up the spa complex. The Roosevelt Bathhouse No. 1 will be refurbished in time for this season. The Roosevelt Bathhouse No. 2, which had been used as park police headquarters for some time, is going to be converted into a year-round fitness center. The Gideon Putnam is getting redecorated.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile the state itself it doing a $9 million overhaul on the huge Lincoln Baths at the Spa Park's South Broadway front, but they don't expect to finish the job until July of 1989. Finally, the first new privately owned bathhouse built in almost a century, the Crystal Spa, has opened for business at 92 South Broadway.</p>
        <p>After wobbling out of the baths, a stroll around the older parts of Saratoga will put the starch back in your spine. The Urban Cultural Center, in Drink Hall at 297 Broadway, offers a variety of guided walking tours every day from July 1 to Aug. 31.</p>
        <p>Not all the architectural wonders of the past were savaged during the town's Dark Age, and many of the remaining specimens were nicely fixed up during the 80's renaissance. Franklin Square, for example, is an outstanding cluster of Greek Revival mansions, and the North Broadway section of town contains an impressive group of immense Victorian heaps in styles ranging from Gothic Revival to Railroad Romanesque.</p>
        <p>Of the grand hotels that once lined the heart of Broadway, only one remains in anything like original condition. This is the Adelphi, erected in 1877. When Gregg Siefker and Sheila Parkert - a couple of Nebraskans -first took possession of the place in 1979, it had been locked for years, its beds all left eerily made up with fresh linens, towels laid out, and cobwebs festooning the high ceilings. Much of the hotel has now been returned to a historically correct state of decoration, and the elegant bar with its courtyard garden is the main watering hole for the New York City Ballet during its July season.</p>
        <p>Speaking of which, in a departure from its usual summer offerings, the New York City Ballet will celebrate its 40th anniversary this year with a three-week American Music Festival, featuring dances based on works by Gershwin, Ives, Samuel Barber, Duke Ellington, Leonard Bernstein and John Philip Sousa. In the spa's smaller Little Theater, Merce Cunningham, Paul Taylor and other moderns will perform.</p>
        <p>The new National Museum of Dance (in what used to be the Washington Baths in the Spa Park) opens for its second year with expanded exhibits.</p>
        <p>In August, of course, the town's attention turns to horse racing, which more and more attracts day trippers who pour into town off Interstate 87 from points north and south. A couple of changes are worth noting. The beloved Spuyten Duyvil bar adjoining the Fasig-Tipton horse auction pavilion is a thing of the past. Fasig-Tipton, which bought the decrepit old place for $128,000 in 1987, wants to tear it down and replace it with a smaller structure.</p>
        <p>The National Museum of Racing was gutted this winter and will reopen July 14 with entirely new exhibits. Along with a first-time exhibition of the Paul Mellon collection of equine paintings, visitors can view holy relics of the sport such as Eddie Arcaro's boots and Sunny Jim Fitzsimmons's binoculars and stopwatch.  VISITOR'S GUIDE  Mineral Baths</p>
        <p>It is advisable to make appointments. The Roosevelt Bath at Saratoga State Park (518-584-2011) charges $4 for a bath and $6 for a general massage, though prices will go up as renovations proceed. It is considered proper to tip the masseur. The rate at the Crystal Spa (518-584-2556) is $11, and $22 for bath and massage, but the rooms are more luxurious and a sauna is available.  Mineral Springs</p>
        <p>Downtown in Congress Park (designed by Frederick Law Olmsted), a Greek Revival pavilion was recently built around the original Congress Spring. Barely 100 feet away is the domed Columbian Spring Pavilion. On nearby Spring Street is the Hathorn Spring No. 1. On the north side of town, where Excelsior and High Rock Avenues meet, is the Old Red Spring, called ''The Beauty Spring'' because its waters were said to clear complexions. The original High Rock Spring, visited first by Sir William Johnson in 1771, is just down the block from Old Red. There are many more springs in and around town. Each has a distinctive taste. Most are carbonated. All are free. The ones mentioned above are piped into faucets. Drinking vessels are not provided.  Walking Tours</p>
        <p>Guided tours ($2) originate at the Beaux Arts-style Drink Hall, 279 Broadway. There is an east side walk daily at 10 A.M. and a west side walk daily at 2 P.M. On the west side of Broadway, buildings of interest include an impressive array of Greek Revival homes dating from the 1830's and 40's; the east side tour features architecture in a high Victorian mode.  Museums</p>
        <p>The Saratoga Springs Historical Society Museum (including the Walworth Museum), is in the Canfield Casino in Congress Park. It is open 9:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M. daily July and August. (Admission: $2.) The National Museum of Dance is open Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., and Sundays from noon to 4 P.M. ($2).</p>
        <p>The National Museum of Racing, on Union Avenue, plans a gala reopening July 14. Hours are Monday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M., and Sunday noon to 4:30 P.M. During the racing season (Aug. 3 through 29) it is open 9:30 A.M. to 6 P.M. daily. ($2.)  Performances</p>
        <p>The New York City Ballet's summer season, featuring its American Music Festival, opens July 5, and runs until July 23. There are matinees Thursdays and Saturdays. (Tickets: $7 to $22.) A season of modern dance follows in the Saratoga Performing Arts Center Little Theater, with the Paul Taylor Company appearing July 25 to 30, the Lewitzky Dance Company Aug. 8 to 13, the Mark Morris Dance Group Aug. 15 to 20, and the Merce Cunningham Company Aug. 22 to 27. (All tickets are $15.) The Philadelphia Orchestra moves on to the Saratoga Performing Arts Center main stage Aug. 10 through Aug. 27. Among the featured performers are the flutist Jean-Pierre Rampal, Aug. 12; the cellist Yo-Yo Ma, Aug. 18; the singer Ray Charles in a program honoring Leonard Bernstein's 70th birthday, Aug. 20, and an evening with John Williams of the Boston Pops, Aug. 26. Ticket prices are the same as for the ballet. The Saratoga Performing Arts Center box office information number is 518-587-3330. J. H. K.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
