<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business Technology; When Nuclear Plants Are Converted</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="155736"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ZIMMER, WILLIAM H, NUCLEAR POWER STATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5D6113CF931A15755C0A96E948260" item-length="1030" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business Technology; When Nuclear Plants Are Converted</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Ohio</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: When it is finished in 1991, the William H. Zimmer power plant here will probably be the world's only coal-fired plant with a control room designed to survive a nuclear meltdown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: When it is finished in 1991, the William H. Zimmer power plant here will probably be the world's only coal-fired plant with a control room designed to survive a nuclear meltdown.</p>
        <p>When it is finished in 1991, the William H. Zimmer power plant here will probably be the world's only coal-fired plant with a control room designed to survive a nuclear meltdown.</p>
        <p>Zimmer began as a plant at the forefront of nuclear technology. But when construction costs kept mounting, its owners decided to abandon those frontiers and go back to what they knew - coal.</p>
        <p>''We know coal inside and out,'' said Allen M. Hill, a vice president of DPL Inc., whose subsidiary, Dayton Power and Light, owns the plant along with Cincinnati Gas and Electric and American Electric Power.</p>
        <p>The companies had already pumped $1.7 billion into Zimmer as a nuclear plant when they discovered that another $1.7 billion would be needed before it generated its first kilowatt of electricity. So for about the same money it would have taken to finish the reactor, they are grafting on a coal boiler of much larger capacity. Company officials said the project was under budget and ahead of schedule.</p>
        <p>''It's nice after years of nuclear announcements, which are always higher and longer,'' said Peter H. Forster, president and chief executive officer of DPL, referring to the construction delays and cost overruns that have become typical of nuclear plant projects.</p>
        <p>Zimmer is not alone in nuclear plant conversion. Another failed nuclear project, Midland in Michigan, is being converted to gas. Both plants could point the way to conversion of a Zimmer twin, another 800-megawatt General Electric nuclear reactor. That plant is Shoreham on Long Island. After $5.3 billion and 21 years, its owner, the Long Island Lighting Company, has agreed to sell it to the State of New York for $1, for scrap.</p>
        <p>But utility executives on Long Island and here at Zimmer, on the Ohio River 30 miles east of Cincinnati, point to some differences that indicate that coal or gas may not be appropriate on Long Island. The experience in Michigan and Ohio suggests that engineering plays a role in choosing between gas or coal conversion and abandonment. So do politics and regulatory policy.</p>
        <p>Engineering is not an obstacle here, where the post-nuclear era is taking shape rapidly with few if any problems. Sometimes, though, the plant can be a bit jarring to the eye.</p>
        <p>Behind the latticework of girders that will support a 1,300-megawatt coal boiler is the steel-reinforced containment building that houses the reactor that will never be used. And turning the corner inside a re-used turbine hall, the visitor comes to doors marked ''radwaste,'' for radioactive waste. The reactor is sealed, but the radwaste system will be useful for non-radioactive water.</p>
        <p>After completion, the plant will function far more reliably than the typical reactor, because its major components, including an advanced antipollution system, are modeled on five operating coal plants of similar capacity, according to John R. Jones, the project manager for American Electric Power, which is managing the conversion. ''Nothing here is unproven,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Efficient coal boilers make steam hotter and under more pressure than reactors do. But the builders here concluded that if they ran that steam through a standard coal turbine, the second-hand steam emerging at the other end would be very similar to what comes out of a reactor. That allowed them to re-use two of the reactor's three turbines, plus its cooling tower, steam condensing system, electric substation and transmission links.</p>
        <p>More important, perhaps, it also saved the trouble of finding a new site and getting the numerous permits from regulatory bodies.</p>
        <p>That does not mean the decision to abandon Zimmer as a nuclear plant was easy.</p>
        <p>''We took a huge hit,'' Mr. Forster said, referring to the financial drain. ''It had to be the most difficult decision our company ever faced. These things drain the energy of a company, too. The fact that you're really turning your back on all that work and all that energy is an emotional thing. You really don't want to do it.'' The decision also included suing the reactor's manufacturer, General Electric, over design problems.</p>
        <p>There were some technical challenges in the conversion, too. The site here is a scant 300 acres, about the amount that forms the ''lay down'' area for storing parts at a standard coal plant construction site. So American Electric had major components built elsewhere and shipped in by barge in modules, at a cost saving. The procedure also saved time, which is money, because interest costs are accumulating on the earlier investment at about $1 million a day.</p>
        <p>The Zimmer conversion has also benefited from political support. The new coal plant will create a demand for 3.5 million tons of coal a year, which is welcome in Ohio. The state's depressed coal industry produced only 31 million tons last year.</p>
        <p>The conversion was also helped economically by another non-engineering factor: Ohio law prohibited the companies from recovering any of their investment from rate payers unless the plant was ''used and useful.'' Adding a coal boiler allowed the companies to say that about half the expenditures on the reactor were useful for the coal plant.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Midland's conversion to gas is under way. The original builder, the Consumers Power Company, contributed the site and equipment in exchange for a 49 percent stake in a new consortium. Consumers Power spent $4.1 billion to bring two reactors at Midland to what it said was 85 percent of completion, but was forced to walk away in the summer of 1984 because of skyrocketing costs and construction difficulties.</p>
        <p>About $600 million in new money will turn one of the reactors into a 1,380-megawatt gas-fired generator, which will also supply steam to a nearby Dow Chemical plant.</p>
        <p>Paul Knopick, a spokesman for Consumers Power, said conversion should be ''dynamite for the people at Shoreham.'' It is far faster than starting from scratch, he said. If gas is chosen instead of coal, ''we don't have any environmentalists jumping up and down, worrying about acid rain.''</p>
        <p>At Lilco, Russell C. Youngdahl, the president, said there were no technical barriers to conversion of the reactor, but added, ''The economics of it are clearly poor.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
