<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Kentucky Power Plant Offers Cleaner Coal Option</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="200257"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TESTS AND TESTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PADUCAH (KY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">TENNESSEE VALLEY AUTHORITY AND PROJECT (TVA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMOTHERS, RONALD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3D7143EF932A15752C1A96E948260" item-length="750" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Kentucky Power Plant Offers Cleaner Coal Option</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SMOTHERS, RONALD</byline>
      <dateline>PADUCAH, Ky., Nov. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: At a time when electric utilities are cautiously increasing their generating capacity and pondering the uncertainties of technologies like nuclear power, an experiment here in the cleaner burning of coal might provide a new option.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: At a time when electric utilities are cautiously increasing their generating capacity and pondering the uncertainties of technologies like nuclear power, an experiment here in the cleaner burning of coal might provide a new option.</p>
        <p>At a time when electric utilities are cautiously increasing their generating capacity and pondering the uncertainties of technologies like nuclear power, an experiment here in the cleaner burning of coal might provide a new option.</p>
        <p>A boiler that rises 13 stories at the Tennessee Valley Authority's Shawnee Power Plant was dedicated today. It is the nation's largest commercial-scale boiler that uses a technology called atmospheric fluidized bed combustion. Lower Oxide Levels</p>
        <p>The unit mixes crushed coal with limestone and burns it on a bed of circulating air. The process, researchers said, reduces emissions of sulfur dioxide and nitrous oxide below Federal limits without using costly flue-scrubbing technology. The unit has a capacity of 160 megawatts, an amount that would serve about 80,000 homes.</p>
        <p>While the environmental benefits of the technology make it attractive, other factors facing the utility industry, like the uncertainty of future regulation of nuclear plants, make it even more so, said Chris Bergeson of the Utility Data Institute, a nonprofit company based in Washington.</p>
        <p>But he added that, with the exception of some nuclear and traditional coal-burning plants now under construction, there are ''virtually no new utility-owned power plants planned beyond 1992.'' $41 Billion Planned About $41 billion is now being budgeted for building new plants and completing those under construction during the next four years.</p>
        <p>As yet, Mr. Bergeson said, no utilities have committed themselves to the technology of the Shawnee plant or to any other. But if any technology has an edge, it is the atmospheric fluidized bed process, he added.</p>
        <p>Richard E. Balzhiser, the president of the Electric Power Research Institute, an industry organization that is a partner in the $238 million effort to build and operate the plant, said its capacity was gradually increased to 160 megawatts, from 2 megawatts, so that utilities could have confidence in the system's reliability. A Sizable Stake</p>
        <p>At the plant's dedication today, Marvin T. Runyon, the T.V.A.'s chairman, said the authority, which provides electric power to eight states, had a particular stake in the new technology. About 70 percent of its electricity comes from aging coal-burning plants, he said.</p>
        <p>In the last two months, the Government-created authority has reduced its ambitious program of building nuclear plants amid questions about future demand, the need for budget cuts and considerable criticism of its safety record.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Runyon noted that utilities that are privately owned - Duke Power, Carolina Power and Light, Commonwealth Edison, the Southern Company, Virgina Power and Consolidated Edison - had also contributed financially to develop the technology used at the plant here.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department says that at least 25 percent of the nation's electric power is produced by conventional coal-burning units that are near their life expectancy of 30 years. How the Process Works</p>
        <p>Arnold Manaker, the project manager here, said small chunks of coal and limestone are fed into a 2,160-square-foot boiler. At its bottom, they are swirled by 9,000 air-blowing nozzles. The chunks are burned and the heat is used to turn water into steam. The steam then drives turbines that produce electricity.</p>
        <p>When the coal chunks are burned, Mr. Manaker said, the sulfur dioxide emissions are absorbed by the limestone. That eliminates the need for equipment to remove sulfur dioxide gas from the smoke emitted from the plant's stacks.</p>
        <p>Robert Porter, a spokesman for the Energy Department, which also contributed to the project, said the process removed about 90 percent of the sulfur dioxide produced in the conventional coal-burning process and almost all the nitrous oxide, another environmentally hazardous by-product. Consequently, the plants do not contribute to the acid rain problem, he said. More Efficiency Seen</p>
        <p>Mr. Porter added that research had so far shown that such plants could be built at 5 to 10 percent below the cost of conventional coal-burning plants and could operate up to 15 percent more efficiently.</p>
        <p>The plant is particularly important to Kentucky, which has about 96 billion tons of coal reserves, said George E. Evans Jr., the state's Energy Secretary.</p>
        <p>''The T.V.A. and the utilities and their researchers have built the plant of tomorrow here today,'' Mr. Evans said. ''Coal can insure our energy independence, and this plant will demonstrate that to the industry.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
