<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TALKING: Cooling; Central Systems Gaining</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="174678"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR CONDITIONING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY METROPOLITAN AREA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKS, ANDREE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DA1038F93BA1575BC0A96E948260" item-length="1068" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TALKING: Cooling; Central Systems Gaining</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREE BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKS, ANDREE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: UNTIL this summer's seemingly endless series of torrid days, installing central air-conditioning in a single-family house was not considered a necessity. Only 56 percent of newly built houses outside the South are constructed with central air-conditioning, according to the National Association of Home</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: UNTIL this summer's seemingly endless series of torrid days, installing central air-conditioning in a single-family house was not considered a necessity. Only 56 percent of newly built houses outside the South are constructed with central air-conditioning, according to the National Association of Home</p>
        <p>UNTIL this summer's seemingly endless series of torrid days, installing central air-conditioning in a single-family house was not considered a necessity. Only 56 percent of newly built houses outside the South are constructed with central air-conditioning, according to the National Association of Home Builders.</p>
        <p>In the Northeast, despite its history of excessive summer humidity, the figure is 48 percent - making it the area with the fewest such systems in the nation. Most householders get by without cooling or by installing through-the-window or through-the-wall units in only one or two rooms.</p>
        <p>But that may change fast. Forecasts of the ''greenhouse effect'' - which may make reruns of the summer of 1988 commonplace one day - have led to a surge of interest in central systems. Installers say they cannot keep up with the demand for retrofitting existing homes.</p>
        <p>Houses fall into two distinct categories - those that already have the necessary duct network because they are heated by a forced-air system and those that do not because they either have a ''wet'' system that uses circulating hot-water or rely on electric baseboard panels.</p>
        <p>A spot-check of about a dozen contractors and homeowners in the New York area shows that the cost, fully installed, can vary widely. But the range is $3,000 to $5,500 for a 2,500-square-foot house if it already has a duct system and $2,000 to $4,000 more if not. The main variable is the complexity of installation due to the design or size of house.</p>
        <p>Houses with more than 2,000 square feet of living space can most efficiently be divided into upstairs and downstairs zones by installing two separate units. This adds 30 percent to installation costs but should reduce energy needs.</p>
        <p>Expect installers to spend about two days in a house that already has a duct system and two to 10 days in a house that needs duct work. The amount of decorating disruption in a house needing duct work should be minimal since the registers are normally dropped from the attic into the ceilings of upstairs rooms. Ducts brought down to the first floor are channeled through closets. Remember, however, that old plaster ceilings may be messier to cut through.</p>
        <p>Homes built before 1965 tend to require additional amperage, increasing the capacity from 100 amps, standard in the older days, to 200 amps - normal for a house built in the last 20 years, noted Jim Norman, manager of technical services for the American Society of Heating, Refrigeration and Air-conditioning Engineers, based in Atlanta. That can add $600 to $1,200 to the overall cost.</p>
        <p>Another cost variable, said Mr. Norman, is the quality of the unit. Those with a higher efficiency rating will be priced higher, but this could be offset in a few years by the lower amount of energy required.</p>
        <p>Federal law now requires the manufacturer to provide those ratings, said Mr. Norman. Contractors have found that a unit large enough to cool a 2,500-square-foot house should add $50 to $150 to an electric bill during July and August, depending where the house is situated and the system's rating.</p>
        <p>Since the quality of the installation is crucial to operating efficiency, careful selection of the contractor is vital, said Mr. Norman. Key pitfalls can be an incorrect estimate of the amount of tonnage needed (the method by which central units are measured) and poor duct work.</p>
        <p>Andy Morin, president of Cannondale Heating and Air-Conditioning of Wilton, Conn., and a member of the Connecticut Heating and Cooling Contractors, said an oversized unit often cools too rapidly, producing ''a cold, clammy meat locker'' atmosphere. The compressor will also turn itself on and off incessantly, which wastes power.</p>
        <p>BEFORE providing an estimate, he said, a conscientious contractor should take exact floor-area measurements and factor in such variables as protection provided by existing insulation or the negative impact of large glass window panes and skylights. Shoddy or poorly designed duct work can also reduce efficiency by leading to an inbalance in comfort levels between rooms.</p>
        <p>The more reputable air-conditioning contractors are usually already known in their communities as excellent plumbing and heating contractors. Fuel-oil dealers, who now increasingly service the systems they supply, are also adding this service.</p>
        <p>References from customers who have lived with an installation for several seasons are the best source of sound advice. Vincent Tomasso, a general partner in Tomasso Brothers of Elizabeth, N.J., suggested asking a former customer the following questions: Did the contractor show up on time and do the job at the price indicated? Did he do the job in the time estimated? Was the work efficiently performed? How did the system work out? Have there been problems?</p>
        <p>Consider, for instance, the experience of Nancy and Garrett Reilly of Wilton, Conn. They installed central air-conditioning last spring in their 2,500-square-foot raised ranch - in part because of an asthmatic son but also because ''we were tired of carrying fans from room to room,'' said Mrs. Reilly. They received estimates ranging from $8,000 to $16,000 and a variety of suggested unit sizes.</p>
        <p>THEY chose the contractor with the strongest references who also seemed best able to defend his choice of size. He also happened to be the least expensive. The $8,000 cost included duct work throughout most of the house, a 2.5-ton unit, an air-cleaner attachment, some electrical work and an attic fan to lessen the cooling load. The duct work was sufficiently neat that ''no painting was necessary,'' said Mrs. Reilly. Their electric bill only went up by $40 in July - the first full month of use.</p>
        <p>Brokers and appraisers are unanimous in insisting that central air-conditioning will become even more important to a home as time goes on. For instance, Jo Papa, vice president of American Realty of Charlotte, N.C. - where central air-conditioning has been prevalent for a decade - said that a house without such an amenity is now ''harder to sell.'' And, as values rise, window units are no substitute since they are frowned upon as ''cheapening the property.''</p>
        <p>The Northeast is catching up. Ruth Brewster, a broker and developer in northern New Jersey, noted: ''If two houses are comparable the one with air-conditioning will go faster.'' It also adds ''an upscale touch,'' she said, and at least $5,000 to the sale price.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
