<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sweet Success</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business World Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="47" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Business; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="153287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAPLE SYRUP AND SUGAR</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RICE, BERKELEY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DF123DF931A25755C0A96E948260" item-length="2417" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sweet Success</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Berkeley Rice; Berkeley Rice is a writer based in North Tarrytown, N.Y.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RICE, BERKELEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ON THE WALLS OF HIS home in Bristol, Vt., David Folino displays a collection of 19th-century prints and photographs: bushy-bearded New Englanders, horses yoked to a sledge, sugar maples flanked with wooden buckets, deep snow on the ground.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ON THE WALLS OF HIS home in Bristol, Vt., David Folino displays a collection of 19th-century prints and photographs: bushy-bearded New Englanders, horses yoked to a sledge, sugar maples flanked with wooden buckets, deep snow on the ground.</p>
        <p>ON THE WALLS OF HIS home in Bristol, Vt., David Folino displays a collection of 19th-century prints and photographs: bushy-bearded New Englanders, horses yoked to a sledge, sugar maples flanked with wooden buckets, deep snow on the ground.</p>
        <p>That's the way it used to be. Today, the sugarbush looks, in the Vermont writer Noel Perrin's phrase, like an outdoor intensive care ward, with miles of plastic tubing running from the trees down to the sugarhouse, where a vacuum pump sucks sap into a reverse-osmosis machine. Increasingly, the $100-million-a-year maple syrup industry, centered in eastern Canada and the northeastern United States, is in the hands of entrepreneurs such as 33-year-old David Folino. ''I do enjoy making syrup,'' he says, ''but I'm in it for the money, not the pleasure.''</p>
        <p>According to Steve Selby, president of Small Brothers, a maple syrup equipment manufacturing company based in Dunham, Quebec, ''Until recently it was mostly farmers who made syrup on the side, as an extra cash crop. But as the demand and prices have increased, as the new equipment has made it more efficient and more profitable, syrup-making is attracting more and more people as a full-time occupation.''</p>
        <p>Dan Bump, a small-business consultant in Brattleboro, Vt., says that, in the maple syrup industry, ''Labor is being replaced by capital.'' After an investment of $30,000 in state-of-the-art equipment, Folino is able to produce 1,000 gallons of maple syrup from 2,600 taps, nearly .4 gallons a tap. The average producer, lacking Folino's equipment and expertise, gets only .25 gallons.</p>
        <p>Folino's sugarworks is in Starksboro, 12 miles from his home. By late March there are signs that sugaring season has begun: The snow is melting on the hills, the streams are filled with spring runoff and clouds of steam are rising from the sugarhouse.</p>
        <p>Inside, the husky, bearded syrup-maker is nearly hidden in the thick steam, which will permeate his hair, face, hands and clothes with maple essence for weeks to come. He asks a visitor to bring along provisions: cranberry juice and smoked oysters, anything, in fact, to cut the taste and smell of maple syrup.</p>
        <p>Folino is tending his big, open-pan evaporator, boiling off the water to make the finished syrup. ''I always wanted to do something in agriculture,'' he says, ''but I knew I didn't want to milk cows.''</p>
        <p>He earned a degree in elementary education at the University of Vermont. During his one semester teaching third grade in a nearby town, he found the sugarhouse that would be his home for five years: a wooden building with no bathroom and no kitchen. Back in what Folino calls ''my hippie days,'' the spring of 1979, life seemed pretty simple: He taught 8-year-olds until 3 P.M. and then came home and eyed the trees out his back door.</p>
        <p>''At that point I could hardly tell a maple tree from an elm,'' Folino says. ''When I started out sugaring, I did things the old-fashioned way, partly because of tradition, but mostly because I couldn't afford any other way.'' He rented some trees, found some pails, bought some taps and borrowed a team of Belgian horses to haul sap down to his sugarhouse. There, using a small, wood-fired evaporator, he started sugaring off. ''It took me eight hours of boiling, and 40 gallons of sap, to make each gallon of syrup. I made 16 gallons that first year and I ended up giving most of it away to friends. It was very much a learning year,'' he says, ''and one of the things I learned was that I wanted to be a syrup-maker and not a teacher.''</p>
        <p>That fall, he built his own small sugarhouse on the site. He supported himself by doing odd jobs, and the following spring he produced nearly 100 gallons, which he sold for $16 a gallon to friends, stores and restaurants. ''My financial statement for those years showed only losses,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Folino knew that to have a productive one-man operation, he would have to go the plastic-tubing route. The problem? ''I didn't have any money. When I finally bought some tubing, I came up 10 feet short on my main line and couldn't afford to buy the rest. I ended up carrying the sap the last 10 feet by hand.'' Still, his production increased to 330 gallons.</p>
        <p>In 1981, Folino became a sales and installation representative for Industrie Provinciale Limited (IPL), a big Canadian manufacturer of plastic tubing.</p>
        <p>Soon he converted entirely to tubing and to a vacuum-pumping system that would increase production from the trees and pull the sap down through the tubing to the sugarhouse.</p>
        <p>The principle behind a vacuum-tubing system is simple; putting it together is not. IPL publishes a 44-page booklet entitled ''Vacuum Tubing System Setting Technique.'' It warns, for example, that drooping lines ''cause airlocks to form, which will make the sap flow in spurts.'' It also offers shots of ''the perfect connection of a 5/16-inch tubing to the 3/4-inch, 1-inch or 1 1/4-inch double fork.'' A syrup-maker going plastic - at a cost of $2.50 to $3.50 a tap - is told that without a series of such perfect connections, his system will leak.</p>
        <p>According to Steve Selby, sales of syrup-making equipment have been growing at a steady 10 percent a year. In 1988, he says, revenues will reach $50 million. Selling and demonstrating maple syrup equipment has become, for Folino, an increasingly lucrative sideline.</p>
        <p>With a loan from the Federal Land Bank, Folino paid $50,000 for the 86-acre sugarbush he had been tapping; with the money he earned as a sales representative for IPL, he began buying more tubing and rigging it, a few thousand feet at a time, as his budget allowed. As a result, his sugarbush is a matrix of green, orange, gray, white and black plastic. The tubing stays in place year round, strung several feet off the ground. There are no drooping lines in his sugarbush.</p>
        <p>Sumner H. Williams, a maple syrup expert with the University of Vermont's Proctor Maple Research Center, says that David Folino is ''one of the best in Vermont. You can go right down the road from David and find people with the same technology who don't do anywhere as well as he does.'' Folino shares his knowledge with his customers. He has become a teacher after all, but of maple sugaring, not third grade.</p>
        <p>ON THIS AFTER-noon in March, Folino scrambles up the steep slope of his sugarbush, steps over snow-covered rocks, dead branches, stumps and holes and checks the flow in the tube lines that crisscross his hills.</p>
        <p>''Maple trees don't need any prodding to produce sap,'' he says. In the fall and winter, trees store sugar as starch in their roots. In the spring, under ideal conditions of warm days and freezing nights, trees send the sugar back up in the form of sap to feed the buds.</p>
        <p>''What we do,'' says Folino, ''is intercept some of that sap. Since the trees make more sap than they need, it doesn't hurt them as long as you don't overtap.'' A maple tree must be 35 to 50 years old before it can support even one tap; many can support four or more.</p>
        <p>''Every time you tap a tree,'' says Folino, ''you leave a small wound that takes several years to heal. Meanwhile fungus, bugs and other disease can enter the tree and damage it. Too many taps can stress a tree. I also try not to disturb the ground when I'm working in the woods. I use horses, not a tractor.''</p>
        <p>There is a school of thought that holds that the moths, dry leaves and mouse droppings found in open buckets add flavor to maple syrup. Plastic tubing prevents such contamination as well as the deterioration that occurs when sap sits too long in collection buckets.</p>
        <p>The tubing system is not entirely impervious to critters. Squirrels, chipmunks, porcupines and even bears leave toothmarks on the tubing, evidence of their taste for the slightly sweet sap - or perhaps for the plastic.</p>
        <p>Folino plans to expand eventually from 2,600 taps to 8,000 taps, which should triple his annual syrup production. Why stop at that point? ''There's a limit to how much I can manage effectively without hiring a lot of extra help,'' he says. ''Sugaring used to be a big family thing, typically with 5 to 10 people involved. I don't have the family and all those relatives to help out.''</p>
        <p>Folino and his wife, Cindy, have a 3-year-old daughter. Cindy, it should be noted, does some boiling down herself, but not of tree sap: Her Bristol-based company, Executive Book Summaries, reduces 400-page books to eight-page summaries for busy executives.</p>
        <p>IN THE LAST THREE years, production of maple syrup has dropped roughly 50 percent in New England and even more in parts of Quebec. From 1981 to 1985, Vermont produced about 500,000 gallons of maple syrup a year. By 1987 Vermont's production had slipped to 275,000 gallons. The decline has been blamed primarily on the weather -early thaws and unusually warm springs, or late thaws and unusually cold springs. Some people also blame acid rain. Production this year, however, has recovered somewhat to 350,000 gallons.</p>
        <p>When maple syrup shortages nearly doubled the price of syrup between 1978 and 1986, there was some concern that consumers would refuse to buy. But while many customers grumbled, most went ahead and bought anyway.</p>
        <p>Retail customers seemed willing to pay up to $9 a pint for whatever pure maple syrup they could find; some wholesale customers, however, discovered that they could survive without it. Quaker Oats, for example, eliminated the last vestige of anything that had ever been connected with a maple tree in its Aunt Jemima Syrup in 1984. Best Foods decided to do the same with its Golden Griddle Syrup. General Foods, over several decades, reduced the maple syrup in its Log Cabin brand from 15 percent to 2 percent.</p>
        <p>''The choice was to leave the maple syrup in and charge consumers more, or to gradually reduce it,'' says Scott Wilson, senior product manager of Log Cabin Syrup. ''From doing research, we realized that consumers weren't willing to pay the 'up' charge.'' Log Cabin's retail sales have been flat at about $90 million a year; it has a 21 percent share of the table syrup market.</p>
        <p>DAVID FOLINO works 12- and 16-hour days processing the sap in the sugarhouse he put up in 1984. The sap first passes through a sterilizing ultraviolet light that kills bacteria that would otherwise cause the syrup's flavor to turn harsh or strong and its color to darken. (Vermont syrup is graded ''Fancy'' light amber, medium amber and dark amber. The darker the syrup, the stronger the taste and the lower the price; many connoisseurs, however, prefer the darker grades.) Next, water must be removed from the sap, traditionally by building a wood fire underneath an evaporator pan. Folino uses a reverse-osmosis machine, that pumps sap through a membrane. Two-thirds of the water is removed; the sugar and minerals remain. The concentrated sap is then pumped into the evaporator pan for finishing. By cutting back the amount of sap that must be evaporated, Folino saves large quantities of fuel. Still, he burns more than 20 cords of wood in the form of wood chips each season.</p>
        <p>To determine when he has at last reduced the sap in the evaporator to syrup, Folino turns to a hydrometer (to test the amount of water remaining) and a refractometer (to measure sugar content). Just before the syrup comes to a boil, at 219 degrees, he drains it, filters it, then stores it in 30-gallon steel drums.</p>
        <p>During the sugaring season, Folino is in constant motion. When things break down, as they often do during sugaring season, Folino has time only for makeshift repairs. One afternoon in March, just as a group of Cub Scouts showed up for a tour, a hose came loose, gushing sap all over the floor. Folino managed to make repairs with a piece of wire, but he ended up drenched in maple sap from the knees down.</p>
        <p>''I should probably have full-time help here,'' Folino admits, ''but I'm real tight about money.'' The only time he uses help is in the summer, when he thins out ash, beech and birch and the smaller maples to give the remaining maples room to grow. He enlists the aid of a neighboring farmer and, in return, helps the farmer with his fruit trees. No money changes hands.</p>
        <p>In the summer, Folino participates in what for him constitutes marketing and promotion. He shows up at local parades, towing a miniature version of his sugarhouse on a trailer. During the long winters, Folino needs snowshoes to make his way through the woods to check his 18 miles of tubing and replace any that has been gnawed or otherwise damaged. He is constantly putting in new taps and lines, lugging heavy coils of tubing and support wire and his gas-powered taphole drill.</p>
        <p>''It's up in the woods where you really make the syrup,'' says Folino. ''The work down in the sugarhouse is just processing.''</p>
        <p>Folino sells 60 percent of his syrup to stores in nearby Middlebury, 20 percent to local hotels and restaurants, and 20 percent directly to retail customers who drop by the house or order his syrup by mail. He charges $34 a gallon, $5.50 a pint, extra for packing and shipping. The Folinos keep five gallons a year for their own consumption. They pour their maple syrup on waffles and pancakes, of course, but also use it in coffee, on cereal, on fruit salad and in baking.</p>
        <p>David Folino's syrup brings in a gross of about $30,000 a year. After figuring in his loan payments, the maintenance on his equipment and the cost of supplies (steel drums, filters, syrup containers), his net profit comes to about $15,000. The majority of Folino's income derives from his commissions on sales of tubing and equipment.</p>
        <p>Folino has sold equipment to affluent, out-of-state ''flatlanders.'' Unlike most natives, who tend to buy one piece of equipment at a time, the new arrivals may spend $20,000 or more for an entire system. ''A lot of these people dump quite a bit of money into their operations knowing they'll never make any money out of it,'' Folino says. They apparently do it because it keeps their tax rates low. The land is then taxed as agricultural land, not as buildable land.</p>
        <p>Once the sugaring season is over, and the muddy road up to the sugarhouse has dried out, Folino hauls the drums of syrup 20 minutes away to his barn in Bristol. There he pasteurizes the syrup, then packs it in the pint, quart, half-gallon and gallon plastic containers.</p>
        <p>David Folino calls his operation the Hillsboro Sugarworks. He designed its label himself. Ayeh, it depicts a moment in time that is fast passing: an old sugar shack, wooden buckets and a horse-drawn sledge in the snow.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
