<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Maneuvering Picks Up in Debate on Clean Air</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="141389"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BYRD, ROBERT C (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITCHELL, GEORGE J (SEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDD103CF930A35756C0A96E948260" item-length="663" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Maneuvering Picks Up in Debate on Clean Air</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Legislation to control urban air pollution and acid rain has been stalled in Congress, but there is finally movement in both houses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Legislation to control urban air pollution and acid rain has been stalled in Congress, but there is finally movement in both houses.</p>
        <p>Legislation to control urban air pollution and acid rain has been stalled in Congress, but there is finally movement in both houses.</p>
        <p>Factions in the House Energy and Commerce Committee are finally exchanging proposals in negotiations that started only after nine renegade Democrats, led by Representative Al Swift of Washington State, politely grabbed the reins from warring chairmen.</p>
        <p>In the Senate, George Mitchell, a Maine Democrat, is threatening a parliamentary end run around the majority leader, Robert Byrd. Senator Byrd is an opponent of the Mitchell clean-air bill that has been ready for debate since last September.</p>
        <p>On both sides of the Capitol, a new phrase has entered the vocabulary of lawmakers and environmental lobbyists: Michael Dukakis. Their message is clear: the Clean Air Act will be strengthened, possibly with the White House occupied by a man perceived to have a stronger environmental commitment than President Reagan or Vice President Bush. Time Is Running Short</p>
        <p>Senator Mitchell is a candidate to succeed Senator Byrd next year when the West Virginian steps down from the Senate's most powerful post.</p>
        <p>''Hopefully, those who've tried to stop any legislation will look at a new majority leader in the Senate and the possibility of a Democratic administration in the White House and see that this is the year to work out acid rain,'' says Representative Henry Waxman, Democrat of California.</p>
        <p>Time is running short. Congress, which will take time off for the political conventions and its own re-election campaigns, has set an Aug. 31 deadline for action.</p>
        <p>That is the date set last December as the Clean Air Act's deadline for metropolitan areas to meet standards for levels of ozone and carbon monoxide or risk sanctions like a ban on construction. Many Will Fall Short</p>
        <p>More than 60 areas are not expected to attain the standards. The debate in Congress is over how much more time they should be given to reduce air pollution and what steps they must take.</p>
        <p>The biggest stumbling block on the House side apparently is whether to force automakers to produce vehicles with cleaner emissions and install equipment to capture polluting gasoline fumes during refueling.</p>
        <p>These are not pleasant questions for the powerful Energy and Commerce chairman, Representative John Dingell, a Michigan Democrat who comes from an automaking district. Acid Rain More Complex</p>
        <p>The acid rain component of the clean air struggle is far more complicated.</p>
        <p>Senator Byrd illustrates part of the complications. West Virginia not only has power plants that would need improvements under the Mitchell bill but also a high-sulfur coal industry. It could be hurt if power plants switch to cleaner fuel like natural gas to meet the bill's requirements.</p>
        <p>Most of the utilities that would be affected by an acid rain bill are in the Middle West. Lawmakers from that area don't want to see their constituents' electricity bills run up by expensive smokestack scrubbers to clean up emissions. Surtax Idea Unpopular</p>
        <p>Western lawmakers like the idea of being able to sell low-sulfur coal from their region to the Midwest. But many don't like Mr. Waxman's idea of a surtax on electric bills nationwide to soften the blow on Midwestern ratepayers.</p>
        <p>The power companies, like the Reagan Administration, don't want any acid rain legislation. They argue that scientists are divided over the effects of acid deposition, and that the nation should await clean-coal technology being sought under a $2.5 billion research program.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitchell says he has been negotiating with colleagues, including Mr. Byrd, to get his bill to the floor. He said last week that supporters will take direct action if the leadership doesn't call the bill up for debate.</p>
        <p>''Clearly, there will be an effort to tack it on to something else as an amendment,'' said Mr. Mitchell.</p>
        <p>Tina Evans, a Byrd spokeswoman, says the majority leader ''has no plans to call up an acid rain bill.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
