<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Troubled Seas: Global Red Tides of Algae Bring New Fears</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="141310"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALGAE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RED TIDE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUTIS, PHILIP S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5D9153DF930A35756C0A96E948260" item-length="1839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Troubled Seas: Global Red Tides of Algae Bring New Fears</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP S. GUTIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GUTIS, PHILIP S</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: LATE last August, off the coast of Naples, Fla., microscopic algae began to reproduce quickly, thriving and exploding in a matter of days into a huge toxic bloom that dominated the coastal environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: LATE last August, off the coast of Naples, Fla., microscopic algae began to reproduce quickly, thriving and exploding in a matter of days into a huge toxic bloom that dominated the coastal environment.</p>
        <p>LATE last August, off the coast of Naples, Fla., microscopic algae began to reproduce quickly, thriving and exploding in a matter of days into a huge toxic bloom that dominated the coastal environment.</p>
        <p>Two months later, the same organism, Ptychodiscus brevis, invaded estuaries along much of the North Carolina coast.</p>
        <p>It turned the waters yellow, devastated the fishing and tourism economy and caused 41 reported cases of respiratory, gastrointestinal or neurological illness in people who worked the normally productive waters or spent time on the area's beaches. North Carolina's bloom is believed to have traveled north in the Gulf Stream, bypassing other Southern states.</p>
        <p>Some scientists describe it as the latest outbreak in what they say is a spreading global epidemic of toxic and nontoxic algae blooms, called red tides. More toxic tides are being reported worldwide, damaging coastal economies as they choke marine life and foul beaches. While they acknowledge that some of the increase may be due to better reporting, scientists are accelerating research to find out the causes, which may include climatic changes, natural growth cycles and pollution, particularly accumulated nutrients that may have finally glutted coastal areas.</p>
        <p>''We are seeing a global first-order change,'' warned Theodore J. Smayda, a professor of oceanography at the University of Rhode Island.</p>
        <p>Stressing that there appears to be a long-term degradation of coastal waters, Virginia K. Tippie, director of estuarine programs for the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration. said, ''If the natural environmental conditions are in the right sequence this year, we will continue to see some problems as we did last year.''</p>
        <p>Until last year, North Carolina had never had a toxic algae bloom. Indeed, the Ptychodiscus organism had never even been seen north of Jacksonville, Fla., about 800 miles to the south. Other toxic tides have been reported off Suffolk County, N.Y., Rhode Island, Tasmania, Taiwan, Guatemala, Korea, Hong Kong and Venezuela.</p>
        <p>In a scientific paper delivered at a symposium last year in Japan, Donald M. Anderson, an associate scientist at the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution in Massachusetts, said that over the last two decades, scientists have seen ''a global increase in the frequency, magnitude and geographic extent'' of red tides.</p>
        <p>''There's no question that the toxic species have been more noticeable recently,'' Dr. Anderson said in a recent telephone interview. ''But there is no way to really quantify what is going on. We have a general view over time that accumulates, but there is no doubt that in certain parts of the world we are seeing more of these toxic events.''</p>
        <p>Scientists who study phytoplankton, the microscopic plants that when multiplied billions of times create algal blooms, are now trying to learn the cause of the blooms' increasing frequency and force.</p>
        <p>Their ideas range from long-term climate shifts to human-caused changes like the flow of sewage and other nutrients into estuaries. Last week, the Environmental Defense Fund, a nonprofit environmental group, reported that the airborne nitrates in acid rain, which come mostly from motor vehicles, power plants and other industries, are also a major source of the nitrogen feeding algae blooms in Eastern coastal waters.</p>
        <p>Another possibility, some wary scientists argue, is that the increase in blooms results from their being noticed more. The world's oceans are receiving closer scrutiny as they are used more and more for recreation, transportation and aquaculture. Pollution as Stimulant</p>
        <p>Toxic algal blooms have occurred throughout history and can have natural origins. The idea that they could be encouraged by pollution is only now gaining favor with some scientists. ''It clearly was not a necessary factor in some of these algal events,'' Dr. Anderson said. ''What is changing is the recognition that although not necessary, pollution can stimulate certain species.''</p>
        <p>The term ''red tide'' is used generically by scientists and others to describe any bloom, toxic or not, even though the algae that cause the tides can turn waters brown, yellow, green or other shades as well, depending on the makeup of the organism. Most algal blooms are not toxic to fish or people, even though the discolored and turbid waters can make swimming or fishing unpleasant. Problems Beyond Toxicity</p>
        <p>But algal blooms that are not toxic to fish can cause enormous damage. As algae proliferate, they can block sunlight and force out other small organisms that are the start of the marine food chain. And as the algae die, sinking to the bottom, their decay begins to consume much of the water's dissolved oxygen that other marine life need. The other life suffocates.</p>
        <p>''It hasn't clicked with people that we are overfertilizing the oceans to the point where they are choked,'' said Gary T. Burris, the chairman of Survival of the Sea Society, a nonprofit organization that is studying and documenting the decay of the oceans. ''I've seen lobsters caught by fishermen that have algae in their gills. They were choked and rotted.''</p>
        <p>Throughout most of history, algal blooms have been treated as curiosities by most scientists and called ''nuisance blooms.'' But, Dr. Smayda wrote after the Japan symposium, ''their anecdotal treatment and relegation as scientifically curious, enigmatic and episodic blooms of rogue species discoloring seawater, sometimes accompanied by commercial and human loss, are approaches of the past.''</p>
        <p>Now, Dr. Smayda and colleagues said, scientists are looking into every aspect of algal blooms from their nutritional requirements to their global dynamics. The growing interest coincides with increasing concern about the world's estuaries - the highly productive coastal bays, inlets and rivers where nourishing freshwater mixes with shallow saltwater to provide a rich environment for marine life. Bad Year for Estuaries</p>
        <p>The summer of 1987, in fact, has been described by many experts as one of the worst in memory for the world's estuaries. Signs of a faltering marine ecosystem abounded: the unexplained deaths of 200 dolphins that washed ashore from New Jersey to Virginia; enormous algal tides worldwide; widespread low-oxygen conditions linked to algae, and mysterious fish diseases.</p>
        <p>Although many scientists argued that the devastation last summer was in large part due to unusually hot weather, most experts interviewed said they believed the problems were exacerbated by such factors as industrial discharges, sewage, fertilizer runoff, nutrients in air pollution and acid rain and other pollutants. Such conditions have long existed but have worsened with the ever-increasing coastal populations.</p>
        <p>''We are exceeding the assimilative capacity of some of our coastal embayments,'' said Ms. Tippie of NOAA. ''So when we get the right climatological conditions, we are going to have excessive signs of damage.''</p>
        <p>''There is no single bullet that is killing the environment,'' Ms. Tippie said in a recent telephone interview. ''It is a cumulative effect.'' The strongest evidence yet linking red tides to pollution has come in a study published this year. Studying Tolo Harbour in Hong Kong, Katherine Lam, a researcher with the Hong Kong Environmental Protection Agency, established a direct correlation between the number of red tides and the extent of coastal pollution. Dr. Lam found that long-term increases in nitrogen and phosphorus levels were accompanied by increased algal cells counts and red-tide outbreaks. Pollution Link Questioned</p>
        <p>Some scientists remain unconvinced. ''I wouldn't want to come down and say pollution is causing red tide expansions,'' said Daniel Kamykowski, a professor of oceanography at North Carolina. ''I don't think pollution is that well defined in terms of the cause of red tides.''</p>
        <p>Very few scientists argue that estuaries are not showing signs of distress. And most say it is very hard to generalize about causes. In New York, for example, the relatively pristine waters around eastern Long Island have been discolored for three years by huge algal blooms of Aureococcus anorexefferens, a very small organism that makes up the ''brown tide.''</p>
        <p>Although the blooms have not affected people's health, they have proved deadly to the previously lush ecosystem in the Peconic Bay system in Suffolk County.</p>
        <p>The region's famed bay scallops have starved, wiping out a $1.8 billion industry, because the algae have pushed out the scallops' normal foods and the scallops cannot digest the algae. The bloom also seems to have killed entire beds of marine grasses by blocking their light. And last summer, fishermen began reporting the widespread loss of conch and small fish that normally serve as food for the bluefish, mackerel, fluke and flounder that normally migrate into the bays each spring and fall.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, scientists have learned that the Aureococcus organism has survived the winter, in concentrations that may signal another bloom.</p>
        <p>Robert Nuzzi, supervisor of the Suffolk County Health Department's Bureau of Marine Resources, said: ''If the rainfall is normal, I don't think we will have a bloom. If it is less than usual, we will most likely have a bloom.'' Brown Tide Cultured</p>
        <p>Last year scientists at the Marine Sciences Research Center at the State University Center at Stony Brook succeeded for the first time in growing the brown tide organism in the laboratory and with that development began to form a hypothesis on the brown tide's origins.</p>
        <p>They theorize that the brown tide algae's growth over the last three years was due to the unusually dry conditions in that time, rather than pollution. The dry conditions increased the salinity of the bays and decreased water circulation throughout the system, leading somehow to an increase in the nutrients needed by the organism. No one is sure what those nutrients are.</p>
        <p>The scientists also theorize that the brown tide organism is an oceanic rather than coastal species. ''It bloomed in areas that were not particularly affected by pollutants, more of your pristine-type areas,'' said Dr. Elizabeth M. Cosper, an assistant research professor at the center. ''If it were an oceanic species, it wouldn't be able to tolerate high levels of pollutants.''</p>
        <p>In his paper, Dr. Anderson described a 1987 outbreak of paralytic shellfish poisoning in Champerico, Guatemala, that killed 26 people. The organism that caused the shellfish to become poisonous is believed to be a toxic alga called Pyrodinium bahamense. ''There is concern that the toxic variety that has caused fatalities and economic hardship in Southeast Asia has now crossed the Pacific,'' Dr. Anderson wrote.</p>
        <p>''Just as we saw an apparent dispersal of this organism between Papua New Guinea and Sabah, Brunei, and the Philippines in the last 10 years, will there now be a spreading of paralytic shellfish poisoning in Central America and the Caribbean?'' Dr. Anderson asked. ''It is a disturbing prospect.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
