<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Behind Du Pont's Shift On Loss of Ozone Layer</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="130720"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DU PONT DE NEMOURS, E I, &amp; CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GLABERSON, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HECKERT, RICHARD E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DB133FF935A15750C0A96E948260" item-length="1315" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Behind Du Pont's Shift On Loss of Ozone Layer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GLABERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GLABERSON, WILLIAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: On March 4, Richard E. Heckert, chairman of E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company, wrote the kind of combative letter Du Pont executives have been writing for years. Answering three Senators who had sharply criticized the company, he said there was no reason for Du Pont to stop making chlorofluorocarbons, the useful compound that critics say destroys the earth's protective layer of ozone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: On March 4, Richard E. Heckert, chairman of E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company, wrote the kind of combative letter Du Pont executives have been writing for years. Answering three Senators who had sharply criticized the company, he said there was no reason for Du Pont to stop making chlorofluorocarbons, the useful compound that critics say destroys the earth's protective layer of ozone.</p>
        <p>On March 4, Richard E. Heckert, chairman of E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company, wrote the kind of combative letter Du Pont executives have been writing for years. Answering three Senators who had sharply criticized the company, he said there was no reason for Du Pont to stop making chlorofluorocarbons, the useful compound that critics say destroys the earth's protective layer of ozone.</p>
        <p>Two days ago, just 20 days after he had dismissed the concerns of the latest critics, Mr. Heckert announced a dramatic turnaround. Du Pont, he said, would get out of the chlorofluorocarbon business entirely. After years of criticizing the company for dragging its heels, many politicians and environmentalists hailed the decision. Du Pont executives promptly began to call for new worldwide controls on the substance, of which they are the world's leading producer, with about 25 percent of the market.  Taking Science into Account</p>
        <p>In interviews yesterday, Du Pont executives said the change of heart was not an outgrowth of all the years the company had battled environmentalists about the ozone layer. It was a result of pure, hard, cold science making its points in a company where, they said, science has always mattered as much as business.</p>
        <p>Once they decided to turn the huge company around on the controversy, the executives said, the ozone issue took on a life of its own at the company's headquarters in Wilmington, Del. For 10 days this month, scientists, senior managers and communications specialists worked virtually around the clock to communicate the company's policy change clearly and quickly - to ''do it right,'' as Mr. Heckert had ordered.</p>
        <p>The rethinking at Du Pont began on Tuesday, March 15. A panel of scientists assembled by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration issued new findings that day on the chlorofluorocarbons, known as CFC's. The panel said that it had detected a significant reduction in the thickness of the ozone layer that might be linked to CFC's. It also said that whatever caused a previously detected ''hole'' in the ozone layer over the Antarctic seemed to be thinning the layer in other parts of the atmosphere.  Abrupt Change in Course</p>
        <p>Within hours of the panel's news conference in Washington, the huge company began to change course.</p>
        <p>For years, Du Pont had said that it was as concerned about the ozone layer as anyone, but that it did not see any proven connection between CFC's and the thinning of the ozone layer. In the 1970's, the company took out full-page newspaper ads to assure the public that it would end CFC production if the chemical posed a threat to public health.</p>
        <p>Some scientists were convinced years ago that CFC's were the main cause of what they said was an alarming deterioration of the ozone layer, which shields the earth from harmful ultraviolet rays of the sun. A thinning of the layer is believed to increase vastly the risk of skin cancer and might permanently alter the earth's ecological system.</p>
        <p>In 1978, the Government banned aerosols containing CFC's, but American production of CFC's was still permitted for refrigeration and other uses.</p>
        <p>Du Pont, and much of the rest of the chemical industry, contended that the criticism was not based on authoritative evidence, and it was sticking to that position early this month. ''At the moment, scientific evidence does not point to the need for dramatic CFC emission reductions,'' Mr. Heckert wrote in his March 4 letter to Senators Robert Stafford, Republican of Vermont, Max Baucus, Democrat of Montana, and David F. Durenberger, Republican of Minnesota.  Top Experts on Panel</p>
        <p>But the NASA panel, Du Pont's people felt, was different. The space agency had put together the top experts in the field and they had gone through all the data, recomputing much of it with new methods.</p>
        <p>Perhaps most important was Mack McFarland. The 40-year-old atmospheric scientist, who was a member of the NASA panel, had spent nearly a decade studying the ozone layer at the Commerce Department's National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration. Since 1983, he had been Du Pont's chief scientist in charge of keeping track of the latest research and monitoring the company's own ozone findings.</p>
        <p>Though Dr. McFarland had known for some time that the panel's report might mean a change of policy for his company, he had been sworn to secrecy, like the rest of the panel members, and could not discuss the report until it was released.</p>
        <p>Dr. McFarland was asked by company executives whether they should believe the report, The answer he gave, on the day the report was released, was that ''Du Pont's policy has always been to be responsive to the best scientific information available, and this is the best scientific information as of March 15.''</p>
        <p>Until the NASA report, he said, there did not seem to be any deterioration of the ozone layer and existing scientific models were not predicting any. All that was different now, Dr. McFarland told his bosses in Wilmington. The report even indicated CFC's might be responsible.  Top Management Consulted</p>
        <p>One of the first people Dr. McFarland spoke to was Joseph P. Glas, the director of Du Pont's Freon products division since 1985. After studying the report, it did not take Mr. Glas long to decide what to do. ''This is something that has got to have the attention of senior management,'' he said. It was Wednesday, March 16.</p>
        <p>Through Thursday, Dr. McFarland and Mr. Glas briefed their superiors. On Friday, Du Pont's executive committee convened to hear the evidence on the ninth floor of the DuPont building. On the committee sit Mr. Heckert, Edgar S. Woolard Jr., the company's president, and four executive vice presidents.</p>
        <p>They listened to a lengthy presentation, pressing, Dr. McFarland said, to understand why the scientific conclusions were different now than they had been for years. At least until he left, Dr. McFarland said, the discussion was limited to scientific, not business, concerns. (Although CFC production has been symbolically important to Du Pont as a leader in chemicals, it accounts for only about 2 percent of earnings, or about $35 million last year. Plus, the company has spent tens of millions of dollars in recent years on alternative compounds that will probably serve the same purposes in five or 10 years.)  A Complex Task</p>
        <p>Mr. Glas had been visiting a client that Friday in Georgia. Shortly after he returned home at 9:15, Elwood P. Blanchard, Du Pont's group vice president in charge of chemicals, was on the phone. The executive committee, he said, had decided to change the company's CFC policy. By the turn of the century, CFC production would no longer be a Du Pont business, and the company wanted to announce that to the world now.</p>
        <p>The task was a complex one. The company wanted to notify customers, competitors and regulators before it went public. It did not want its 2,000 CFC workers all over the world - or its 145,000 other workers - to hear the news from press reports. And the specific terms of the policy were still to be worked out.</p>
        <p>All day Saturday, Mr. Glas communicated by a personal-computer network with other Du Pont managers who also have PC's in their homes. These executives met at 2 P.M. Sunday in Wilmington. On Monday and Tuesday, the growing cadre of people involved in the CFC project worked 15-hour days. On Wednesday, Du Pont told its major competitors. On Thursday morning, employees were notified and then the press.</p>
        <p>Some of the company's longtime critics said the decision would be carried out too slowly. But some of those who had helped to change the policy said it was a significant step. Mr. Glas said he went home and told his wife and six children what the company had decided to do. ''They said, 'Dad, that's fantastic,' '' he recalled. ''I know I'm doing something that's important, and it felt good.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
