<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>COMMERCIAL PROPERTY: Sick-Building Syndrome; The Growing Problem of Air Pollution in Offices</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="143342"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OFFICE BUILDINGS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCCAIN, MARK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MUNSER, ALFRED (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DE133EF93BA35756C0A96E948260" item-length="1144" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>COMMERCIAL PROPERTY: Sick-Building Syndrome; The Growing Problem of Air Pollution in Offices</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK McCAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCCAIN, MARK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THRIFTY energy habits, shrinking office quarters and sloppy maintenance are helping to pollute the air that workers breathe in many office buildings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THRIFTY energy habits, shrinking office quarters and sloppy maintenance are helping to pollute the air that workers breathe in many office buildings.</p>
        <p>THRIFTY energy habits, shrinking office quarters and sloppy maintenance are helping to pollute the air that workers breathe in many office buildings.</p>
        <p>Although some landlords abide by prudent guidelines, and others are making costly improvements to freshen their air, ignorance and indifference remain all too common, according to health experts.</p>
        <p>They say that molds, bacteria, chemical fumes and other contaminants are making life miserable for many office workers - and costing employers two or three billion dollars a year in extra sick days and medical expenses.</p>
        <p>''The quality of indoor air, especially in office buildings, is becoming an increasing problem,'' said Dr. Alfred Munser, director of critical care at Washington Adventist Hospital in Takoma Park, Md. ''In the last few years we've focused a tremendous amount of attention on outdoor pollution - and that's great - but most people spend their days indoors. And it's high time we paid attention to indoor air.''</p>
        <p>Since the energy crisis a decade ago, landlords have been fighting to reduce their heating and air-conditioning bills. Besides heavier insulation, a common tactic has been to let in less fresh air, which needs to be heated or chilled to the right temperature. Pumping recycled air through the ventilation ducts of a building requires far less fuel.</p>
        <p>''In my practice,'' said Dr. Munzer, a director of the American Lung Association, ''I see an increasing number of people with vague respiratory problems that are quite bothersome. You can't really pin the problems on anything specific, but looking closely at the history of these people, you get the feeling that the symptoms are associated with something at work.</p>
        <p>''Very often,'' he went on, ''ventilation systems are not properly cleaned out. And all sorts of things can grow in those systems.''</p>
        <p>The people on the breathing end of those ventilation systems tend to suffer from more than their share of headaches, sore throats, eye irritations, colds, allergies and influenza, according to Dr. Munzer. In New York City, a law that took effect last month helped vanquish one common contaminant - tobacco smoke - by placing severe restrictions on smoking in enclosed public spaces.</p>
        <p>But health experts say that plenty of other contaminants linger, such as vapors from copying machines and carpets, asbestos fibers, bacteria, hazardous dust, carbon dioxide and carbon monoxide from basement parking garages. Moreover, as compact work stations allow companies to squeeze more employees into less space, the contaminants are becoming more concentrated.</p>
        <p>DURING a recent 18-month period, the building-controls division of Honeywell investigated 30 office buildings that landlords suspected were suffering from poor air quality. Its report noted that:</p>
        <p>* Heat from lights and computer terminals, contaminants like cleaning fluids, and the density of workers had ''increased dramatically'' in 60 percent of the buildings. Consequently, the ventilation systems had been pushed beyond their capacity.</p>
        <p>* Some of the buildings had no fresh-air intakes; others had intakes too close to plumbing waste vents, chimneys or exhaust fans.</p>
        <p>* Changes in control strategies, such as energy-conservation efforts that reduced the amount of outside air, contributed to pollution in 90 percent of the buildings.</p>
        <p>* In three-quarters of the buildings, ''proper maintenance procedures were not followed regularly or were ignored entirely. Dirty air intakes, clogged filters, fouled heating and cooling coils, and contaminated air ducts were common problems.''</p>
        <p>Collectively, the design and maintenance problems that produce poor air quality have come to be known as the ''sick-building syndrome.''</p>
        <p>''We've gone into buildings where you almost can't believe the bad maintenance that results from sloppiness or ignorance,'' said Gray Robertson, president of ACVA Atlantic, a company in Fairfax, Va., that investigates and remedies indoor pollution problems.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robertson often sees central cooling units that have become breeding grounds for fungi. Or banks of filters that have been rendered worthless by neglect. Or ventilation ducts that are clogged with dust and debris.</p>
        <p>''Construction crews leave behind plaster dust, beer cans and lunch bags in the ducts, then a lot more debris accumulates over the years,'' Mr. Robertson said. ''Ductwork is out of sight, and usually built without simple ways to gain access, so people just ignore it.''</p>
        <p>ACVA Atlantic uses fiber-optic scanners to inspect hidden areas, and often cuts access holes into ducts and ventilation shafts to vacuum them clean. Then the company fits miniature contamination sensors into the ductwork to continually monitor the air that passes through.</p>
        <p>''One of the biggest problems today is the lack of fresh air to dilute indoor pollutants,'' Mr. Robertson said. ''In 35 percent of about 240 buildings we've inspected over the past five years, the fresh-air intakes were completely sealed off. That's just ignorance. The building engineers never saw the absenteeism records in the personnel department, and no one made the connection between polluted air and all the headaches, coughs and sickness.''</p>
        <p>Now that most office buildings lack windows that open to let in a breeze, providing acceptable air to employees has become far more complex, and susceptible to trouble. Yet indoor air pollution is virtually unregulated, and the Federal Environmental Protection Agency has little money or authority to deal with the problem.</p>
        <p>''What we need is sound standards for indoor air quality and inspection procedures for ventilation systems,'' said Dr. Munzer, who testified last year before a Senate subcommittee that was considering an indoor clean-air bill.</p>
        <p>Building owners acknowledge that quality control in office ventilation systems runs the gamut from excellent to dismal. But they say that most ventilation systems provide office workers with air of at least adequate quantity and quality.</p>
        <p>''THIS is the time of year when you get the best quality air into a building,'' said James West on a recent balmy day as he inspected a 10-foot-square air intake that serves two floors of a 41-story office tower at 1155 Avenue of the Americas, on the corner of 45th Street. The louvers of the intake were wide open, with fans pulling in the maximum amount of outdoor air because its temperature was almost ideal for circulating through the building.</p>
        <p>''Every building has its own idiosyncrasies,'' said Mr. West, who works for the Durst Organization, a family owned realty company that has established a reputation for maintaining its buildings well. ''Guys in my business have to work with what they have, and make modifications along the way to improve the heating and air-conditioning systems. Things that look great on paper don't always work well in real life.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
