<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="140385"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5D8163FF93AA15757C0A96E948260" item-length="972" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International A3-11</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International A3-11</p>
        <p>International A3-11</p>
        <p>The U.S. and Panama have outlined a tentative accord by which Gen. Manuel Antonio Noreiga would relinquish power in Panama, senior Administration officials said. They said many details still have to be resolved. Page A1</p>
        <p>Two million Ethiopians are starving because the Government has so severly barred emergency relief efforts in the country's north, which is ravaged by both drought and war. Much donated food is piling up at ports. A1</p>
        <p>Soviet military advisers will remain in Afghanistan to help the armed forces after a Soviet troop withdrawal and Kabul has the right to acquire weapons from any country, President Najibullah said. A1</p>
        <p>Labor unrest increased in Poland on the third day of the largest strike in six years. Strikers are demanding pay increases and reinstatement of at least four workers dismissed because of membership in Solidarity. A3</p>
        <p>Big cuts in intelligence budgets have been voted by a Senate committee, reportedly because of anger over the  Reagan Administration's failure to upgrade surveillance systems needed to verify a new arms treaty. A7</p>
        <p>Canada's plan to reduce acid rain from the United States will be the subject of high-level talks, according to Prime Minister Brian Mulroney. He said President Reagan had agreed to the discussion. A6</p>
        <p>Kim Dae Jung on the rebound: taking off the gloves A3</p>
        <p>Hapchon journal: Hiroshima and the bitter Koreans A4</p>
        <p>China issues draft of Hong Kong constitution A5</p>
        <p>China to offer food subsidies to urban residents A6</p>
        <p>National A12-18, B4-5</p>
        <p>Fair trade rather than free trade will be Washington's new policy, according to economists and political analysts, who say the U.S. will make it tougher for foreign competition to take away business from American companies. A1</p>
        <p>Seeking to bar the spread of a virus that has begun to appear in a slight fraction of blood donations, the American Red Cross said it planned to begin testing donated blood for the cancer-causing virus. A1</p>
        <p>At least 59 people were injured, three of them critically, in a midair explosion aboard an inter-island airline flight carrying 84 people from Hilo to Honolulu, a Hawaii Government spokesman said. A1</p>
        <p>David Packard is giving $2 billion to charities, reflecting a commitment shared with this late wife and their four children. The gift will make the Packard Foundation one of the richest in the country. A1</p>
        <p>Ford earned the largest profit ever for an American auto maker in a quarter. The company said earnings in the first quarter totaled $1.62 billion, or $3.31 a share. D1</p>
        <p>Aliens are unlikely to win an extension from next Wednesday to Nov. 30 to apply for amnesty. A procedural vote in the Senate indicated an extension has limited support. B4</p>
        <p>A $1 billion anti-AIDS program to provide research, education and treatment was approved in the Senate by a vote of 87 to 4. The omnibus bill now goes to the House, where approval is also expected. B4</p>
        <p>The Orioles lost their 21st game in a row, setting an American League record. Baltimore was beaten by the Minnesota Twins, 4-2, with just six hits against Allan Anderson and two relief pitchers. B17</p>
        <p>F.A.A. ordered to restructure management A12</p>
        <p>Main Line journal: Diversity now common along Main Line A12</p>
        <p>Hope raised for shorter hospital stays for coronaries A12</p>
        <p>Chance of amnesty extension appears dead B4</p>
        <p>Politics A16</p>
        <p>In many ways, we've already won, according to the Rev. Jesse Jackson. Politicians say 1988 is the Year of Jackson - the year a black man made a serious bid for President and was taken seriously by voters. A16</p>
        <p>Reverend Jackson was asked why Michael S. Dukakis was not campaigning much in Ohio. Mr. Jackson replied, ''He has already been coronated as nominee. So maybe he's focusing on the coronation.'' A16</p>
        <p>Washington Talk A14</p>
        <p>At White House luncheon, issues are on the menu  Regional B1-4</p>
        <p>The bullet that killed a sergeant during a drug raid in upper Manhattan Wednesday came from another police officer's gun, not the gun fired by a pregnant woman in the apartment, the police said. A1</p>
        <p>In seizing the apartment leases of two suspected drug dealers in New York City, Federal officials used a powerful new weapon against illegal drug trafficking by tenants of public housing projects. B1</p>
        <p>Widespread municipal corruption deters economic development in New York City, according to Investigation Commissioner Kevin B. Frawley. He cited ''a pervasive cynicism about doing business'' in the city. B3</p>
        <p>No violation of Tawana Brawley's civil rights has been corroborated, according to the F.B.I., which said it had reassigned three of the four agents on the case to other investigations. B3</p>
        <p>A big Queensboro Bridge market being built under the span has prompted a suit by residents to block the project, charging that necessary approvals for the construction were never granted. B3</p>
        <p>New spending for bridge repairs and a garbage recycling program will be included in the updated budget proposal the Koch administration will release next month. It is seeking service cuts totaling $300 million. B1</p>
        <p>Kindergarten classes are soaring as the children of the postwar baby boom generation are enrolling in growing numbers while high-school enrollments continue to drop. B1</p>
        <p>Neighbors recall slain sergeant B2</p>
        <p>Former executive says Wedtech sought connection to Bush B3</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
