<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Satellite to Improve Monitoring of Ozone Loss</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="191133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER SATELLITES AND ROCKETS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL OCEANIC AND ATMOSPHERIC ADMINISTRATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DF153BF936A15753C1A96E948260" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Satellite to Improve Monitoring of Ozone Loss</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A NEW satellite will considerably improve the ability of scientists to track changes in ozone concentrations high in the earth's atmosphere. The ozone, a gas that acts as a natural shield against the sun's potentially lethal ultraviolet rays, is slowly being eroded by pollution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A NEW satellite will considerably improve the ability of scientists to track changes in ozone concentrations high in the earth's atmosphere. The ozone, a gas that acts as a natural shield against the sun's potentially lethal ultraviolet rays, is slowly being eroded by pollution.</p>
        <p>A NEW satellite will considerably improve the ability of scientists to track changes in ozone concentrations high in the earth's atmosphere. The ozone, a gas that acts as a natural shield against the sun's potentially lethal ultraviolet rays, is slowly being eroded by pollution.</p>
        <p>Launched Sept. 24, the $54.5 million spacecraft, NOAA-11, is operated by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration. It is primarily a weather satellite that carries a variety of additional sensors, one of which measures ozone levels around the world.</p>
        <p>Scientists hope to get the best picture yet of the extent and location of ozone loss in the upper atmosphere. The new sensor is more sensitive than a similar device already in orbit, and it greatly increases the measurement of ozone from space.</p>
        <p>''We want to look over a very long period of time and detect very small changes,'' said Walter G. Planet, the agency's chief ozone scientist. ''It's very important to determine as soon as possible and accurately as possible just what the changes are.'' Potential Health Hazards</p>
        <p>Fears have recently mounted that industrial pollution is causing so much damage to the ozone layer that an increase in ultraviolet radiation will endanger human health, causing a rise in skin cancer and eye damage, and may damage natural systems.</p>
        <p>The ozone sensor on NOAA-11 works by measuring the amount of ultraviolet radiation reflected into space by the earth's atmosphere. Ozone absorbs ultraviolet rays. When stratospheric ozone is present in large amounts, ultraviolet radiation is therefore reflected back into space less strongly. Conversely, low levels of ozone allow other gases in the earth's atmosphere to reflect ultraviolet radiation more strongly.</p>
        <p>Last week the ozone sensor aboard NOAA-11 was turned on for the first time. After a period of checkout and calibration, it is expected to make its first readings in January.</p>
        <p>The sensor is a more advanced version of an instrument operating on NOAA-9, a weather satellite launched in December 1984. The new sensor, which cost about $5 million, is more sensitive and stable than the old one.</p>
        <p>''Generally, the data will reproduce what's happening in the atmosphere with greater accuracy and fidelity,'' Dr. Planet said. Thomas N. Pyke Jr., an assistant administrator for the Federal agency who heads its satellite operations, said NOAA-11's launching was delayed four months so the improved sensor could be put on board.</p>
        <p>''It's very important,'' he said. ''It's helping us advance our mission of monitoring and predicting changes in the earth's environment.''</p>
        <p>NOAA-11 was launched from the Vandenberg Air Force Base in California into a polar orbit some 540 miles above the Earth's surface. The satellite's lifetime is two to five years.</p>
        <p>Since the ozone sensor measures reflected sunlight, it works only half the time, when the satellite is above the sunlit half of the earth. Every 24 hours, however, the sensor maps the entire globe since the Earth rotates on its axis beneath both the sun and the satellite.</p>
        <p>Jim Miller, a meteorologist with the Climate Analysis Center of the National Weather Service, said the satellite is able to measure the worldwide extremes in ozone concentration, which can run from a low of about 240 Dobson units at the Equator up to 450 Dobson units at the Earth's poles, where drastic declines have occurred on a seasonal basis. The Dobson unit is a measure of how ozone absorbs several different wavelengths of sunlight. Recent Ozone Measurements</p>
        <p>This month the amount of ozone in the air above Antarctica was found to average 200 Dobson units, up slightly from 135 last October and 165 the October before. These intensive measurements of the Antarctic ozone were made mainly by high-altitude aircraft and balloons, but cost limits their frequency.</p>
        <p>Dr. Miller said the sensor on NOAA-11 should be sensitive enough to measure ozone changes of one to two Dobson units.</p>
        <p>Krishna Rao, research director of the agency's satellite service, said the ozone instruments on NOAA-9 and NOAA-11 are the only ones that can provide routine daily coverage of the earth.</p>
        <p>He added that the sensors report not only the total ozone, but also its varying concentrations at different heights in the atmosphere. This kind of vertical reading, he said, was possible because ozone at different levels in the atmosphere absorbs ultraviolet light at distinct wavelengths. As many as five ozone bands can be distinguished within the stratosphere, the scientists said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
