<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Strange Glow Is Found at Bottom of Pacific</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="169168"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHRIMP</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIGHT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JUAN DE FUCA RIDGE (PACIFIC OCEAN)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PACIFIC OCEAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">VAN DOVER, CINDY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ALVIN (SUBMERSIBLE CRAFT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shrimp</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DD123AF93AA3575BC0A96E948260" item-length="2010" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Strange Glow Is Found at Bottom of Pacific</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: INFERENCES drawn by a sharp-eyed biology student from her study of a peculiar eyeless shrimp have led to the discovery of a mysterious glow emitted by a scalding jet of water more than one mile beneath the surface of the Pacific Ocean.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: INFERENCES drawn by a sharp-eyed biology student from her study of a peculiar eyeless shrimp have led to the discovery of a mysterious glow emitted by a scalding jet of water more than one mile beneath the surface of the Pacific Ocean.</p>
        <p>INFERENCES drawn by a sharp-eyed biology student from her study of a peculiar eyeless shrimp have led to the discovery of a mysterious glow emitted by a scalding jet of water more than one mile beneath the surface of the Pacific Ocean.</p>
        <p>The faint light at the ocean floor was detected July 26 by a three-member crew of the research submarine Alvin, using the same camera that photographed the wreck of the Titanic two years ago. The discovery that even the Stygian depths of the ocean might have enough light to drive the life-giving photosynthesis reaction could shape future theories as to how life developed.</p>
        <p>Biologists have generally assumed that life forms dependent on light for manufacturing their essential carbon-based building blocks must have developed on land or in water shallow enough for sunlight to penetrate. The notion that photosynthesis could have occurred in the depths of the ocean where no sunlight ever reaches would open new possibilities.</p>
        <p>Dr. John R. Delaney, a marine geologist from the University of Washington at Seattle, served as chief scientist on the Alvin expedition to the Juan de Fuca Ridge, which lies 7,200 feet beneath the ocean's surface 180 miles west of Vancouver, British Columbia.</p>
        <p>''We found the glow during the last two hours of the last dive we made during the three-week program,'' Dr. Delaney said in an interview. ''We had already completed a very successful cruise studying the geological evolution of oceanic ridge crests when we found the glow.</p>
        <p>''At this point, I hate even to speculate on the source of this faint, flame-like light that seems to emanate from the water itself. But if Cindy Van Dover had not advised us what to look for, we would not have found it.''</p>
        <p>Miss Van Dover, a 34-year-old graduate student completing her doctoral studies at the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution, Woods Hole, Mass., specializes in the biology of deep-water organisms.</p>
        <p>''Two years ago,'' she said, ''a very peculiar bottom-dwelling shrimp was brought up from the Mid-Atlantic Ridge, which lies between Bermuda and the Azores. This shrimp, about three inches long, has no eyes, so it was named Rimicaris exoculata. I became interested in its physiology.''</p>
        <p>Miss Van Dover discovered that although exoculata shrimp have no eyes, they do have organs along their backs under their translucent shells that look like primitive light receptors. These organs have reflective backings that might serve to amplify very faint light, she said. In the course of her study she also discovered nerves in the shrimp that seemed to correspond to optic nerves, connecting the suspected light receptors along the animals' backs to their brains.</p>
        <p>''The clincher came two months ago when a colleague and I found that the organs contained rhodopsin,'' she said. ''At that point we were pretty sure the shrimp could perceive light.''</p>
        <p>Rhodopsin is a class of chemicals found in the retinas of ordinary eyes. Light absorbed by rhodopsin triggers a cascade of chemical reactions that underlie the process of vision. The presumed sensory organs of the exoculata shrimp have no lenses and therefore cannot form images. Their ''vision,'' if any, would therefore be limited to awareness of varying intensities of light.</p>
        <p>''These shrimp live at depths far too great for any sunlight to penetrate,'' Miss Van Dover said, ''but I reasoned that if they are capable of perceiving light, there should be some kind of light down there for them to perceive. So I suggested to John Delaney that he look for the light when he visited a similar kind of habitat in the Pacific.''</p>
        <p>The undersea Pacific formation chosen by Dr. Delaney for study consisted of what he described as ''a village of castle-like structures up to 50 feet high,'' each made of dense, sulfur-based minerals. The formation lies over a submarine fault line caused by the separation of tectonic plates. The fault allows sea water to seep down to a cauldron of molten rock, where it is rapidly heated to more than 1,000 degrees Fahrenheit. (The water cannot boil, since it is under immense pressure at those depths.) Laden with minerals dissolved from the hot rock, the water then spurts upward, emerging from orifices on the ocean floor at a temperature of about 670 degrees Fahrenheit. As the super-hot water comes into contact with cool water, the dissolved minerals precipitate as solids, gradually building up the rock chimneys that tower above the surrounding sea floor.</p>
        <p>In the last decade scientists have discovered a rich variety of organisms - clams, crabs and worms, among others -that flourish near these hot-water chimneys, which are sometimes known as smokers.</p>
        <p>At the bottom of the food chain nourishing these strange creatures are microorganisms capable of synthesizing the carbon-based chemicals essential to life without the usual assistance of sunlight. Instead of using the carbon dioxide and water as the raw materials, as conventional plant photosynthesis does, these microorganisms work in total darkness to create the needed chemical building blocks, by combining the carbon dioxide, hydrogen sulfide, water and oxygen that well up from the chimneys.</p>
        <p>The detection of the light Miss Van Dover had predicted required a camera far more sensitive than the human eye. Even using an ultra-sensitive charge-couple device (C.C.D.) video camera, an exposure of 20 seconds was required to photograph the dim glow. 'A Kind of Flame'</p>
        <p>''It appeared on our screen aboard the Alvin as a kind of flame, with a bright, sharp edge at the bottom and a fading luminous zone above it,'' Dr. Delaney said. ''During our time exposure, we had to shut off all the submarine lights to avoid washing out the faint glow. Then, to determine exactly where the glow was coming from, we illuminated the whole chimney with a quick flash from the submarine's lighting system. The time-exposed image of the glow fitted with the flash-illuminated image, and we could see that the lip of the chimney corresponded to the bottom edge of the glow. We could also see that the glow faded out a few inches above the top of the chimney.''</p>
        <p>Recording the glow proved to be both difficult and dangerous.</p>
        <p>To program the Alvin's computer-controlled camera for making time exposures, Dr. Milton Smith, a remote-sensing expert from the University of Washington who made the dive with Dr. Delaney, had to request satellite transmission to the Alvin's mother ship of a complex new computer program from the camera's manufacturer. Hot Enough to Soften Windows</p>
        <p>The intense heat of the water spouting from the chimneys also posed a problem. ''That water was hot enough to soften the Plexiglas windows of the Alvin,'' Dr. Delaney said. ''It's like working within inches of a blast furnace.''</p>
        <p>The submarine pilot, Dudley Foster, had to poise his 17-ton craft so that the viewing window was within six feet of the chimney without coming close enough to melt the window. The slightest error in maneuvering could have meant death for the three men; sea water under a pressure about 200 times as great as that of the atmosphere would have burst through a weakened window, instantly crushing the submarine's occupants.</p>
        <p>To steady the ship for a long-exposure photograph, Mr. Foster nudged the nose of the Alvin against the side of the chimney and then applied forward power to anchor the submarine to the rock.</p>
        <p>Mr. Foster served the expedition in another and more light-hearted capacity. ''We needed some kind of yardstick to include in the pictures we made of the chimney, to provide a record of its scale,'' Dr. Delaney said. ''So we made a life size photograph of Dudley Foster, which we glued to a piece of plywood and fitted with lead weights. Using Alvin's manipulator arm, we put this dummy of Dudley next to a chimney. Some of our pictures show him in a rather startling setting at the bottom of the ocean.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Delaney, Miss Van Dover and their associates say that their discovery leaves so many questions unanswered that much further investigation is needed. They plan to return to the Juan de Fuca Ridge with the Alvin on Aug. 27, this time with a set of improvised light filters for their camera.</p>
        <p>''All we were able to do on the first trip was to detect the glow Cindy said might be there,'' Dr. Delaney said. ''We have no idea what its wavelengths may be, and an estimate of wavelength is essential to determining the nature of the light. We'll need to make several exposures of the glow, using the Alvin's manipulator arm to hold up colored filters like big lollipops in front of the camera lens. Later, by comparing these digitally recorded images, we should able to gauge the color of the glow.'' Chain of Inferences</p>
        <p>Miss Van Diver acknowledges that the shrimp she has studied may not even be capable of perceiving light of the wavelengths found at the chimney. If that should prove to be the case, her chain of logical inferences would crumble, even though it has already led to an important discovery.</p>
        <p>''We have studied these shrimp only in the form of frozen specimens with damaged light receptors,'' she said. ''Eventually, we would like to observe the shrimps' behavior in their normal environment under artificial lighting.''</p>
        <p>She added that the light around submarine chimneys is probably far too faint to provide the energy for large-scale biological photosynthesis. ''But if photosynthesis occurs at all at that depth,'' she said, ''it would have important evolutionary implications. It would mean that a hitherto unsuspected mechanism for sustaining life could have existed in the deep oceans early in the history of life.''</p>
        <p>The biggest puzzle remains the source of the glow.</p>
        <p>The scientists virtually rule out bioluminescence, the chemical process that causes fireflies and many ocean organisms at shallower depths to glow with a cool, greenish light.</p>
        <p>''The glow seems to be confined to the water emerging from the chimneys,'' Dr. Delaney said. ''The light fades out three or four inches above the chimney orifice. Where we see the glow, the water is probably far too hot even for those microorganisms that can stand high temperatures.''</p>
        <p>Although the volcanic magma beneath the fault is incandescent, Dr. Delaney said, the magma lies at a depth at least one half mile below the ocean floor. Light emitted by the molten rock would hardly be intense enough to reach the mouths of the chimneys where the glow is seen. Alternative Explanations</p>
        <p>An alternative explanation might be that a chemical reaction takes place in the water, yielding part of its energy in the form of light. Various ''oxidation-reduction'' reactions are known that produce light.</p>
        <p>Another possibility, Dr. Delaney suggests, is that something in the water is hot enough to emit light, possibly in the infrared region of the spectrum. ''Of course, infrared is strongly absorbed by water,'' he said, ''but it might travel over the short distances from which we observe the glow. Our camera lens was only about 18 inches from the glowing water when we detected the light.''</p>
        <p>During the 15 dives the Alvin will make to the Juan de Fuca Ridge beginning later this month, only part of the time will be devoted to studying the mystery glow. The three-week diving schedule is sponsored by a project called Ridge, which stands for Ridge Interdisciplinary Global Experiments. Experiments in oceanographic physics, chemistry, biology, volcanology, seismology and other fields will be conducted.</p>
        <p>Even with money from the National Science Foundation, the Office of Naval Research, the United States Geological Survey and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, experiments involving the Alvin are constrained by tight budgets.</p>
        <p>''It costs $25,000 a day to run Alvin,'' Dr. Delaney said, ''and that has to cover a lot of experiments. But the work Cindy initiated will be an important part of the forthcoming dives. It has been a delight to watch this young biologist's careful observations, intelligence and self-confidence bring our investigation to its present exciting stage.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
