<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Industry Overcome by the Heat</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="172493"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR CONDITIONING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDUSTRY PROFILES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEVIN, DORON P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7D71F3BF93AA2575BC0A96E948260" item-length="1344" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Industry Overcome by the Heat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DORON P. LEVIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEVIN, DORON P</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: After two consecutive torrid summers, the air-conditioner industry finds itself confronted by an overwhelming clamor for its products that it cannot satisfy immediately.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: After two consecutive torrid summers, the air-conditioner industry finds itself confronted by an overwhelming clamor for its products that it cannot satisfy immediately.</p>
        <p>After two consecutive torrid summers, the air-conditioner industry finds itself confronted by an overwhelming clamor for its products that it cannot satisfy immediately.</p>
        <p>Consumer demand has been so strong that manufacturers expect this year's total sales to top four million units, a level not seen for years. At the same time, untold numbers of consumers, many of them hot, tired and furious, have been astonished to discover that the machines are sold out all the way back to the factory floor.</p>
        <p>The reasons are several, ranging from a difficulty in predicting demand to a reliance on manufacturers abroad for critical components, now in short supply. Getting parts to the factory can take months. Mainly, though, manufacturers were simply not ready for the unusually heavy demand that resulted from repeated long strings of hot days.</p>
        <p>While other durable-goods industries, like cars and refrigerators, closely track the economy to forecast demand, predicting the sales of room air-conditioners remains catch-as-catch-can. The industry is still as dependent on the weather as any Kansas farmer. Cold or Hot, It's 'a Mess'</p>
        <p>''The air-conditioning business is a crapshoot,'' said Ken Arend, director of the home comfort division for White Consolidated Industries, a major builder of home units. ''If you build a lot of merchandise and end up with a cold year, you're in a mess. If you play it safe and it's hot, you have a mess in the other direction.''</p>
        <p>By Aug. 1 American manufacturers had shipped more than 3.8 million room air-conditioners, up 20.6 percent from 1987. Yet demand still outstrips supply, particularly in heat-stricken sections of the Midwest and Northeast, where many homes lack central cooling units. Such units are common in the Sun Belt.</p>
        <p>Total shipments for 1988 almost surely will top four million units, most manufacturers say.</p>
        <p>The dozen or so companies that dominate the American market would be very happy to sell more air-conditioners in a heat wave, but the lead time to gather critical parts is too long, they say.</p>
        <p>''We have to plan well in advance, four to six months, to get all the critical parts, compressors, motors and switches, and we plan for it to be a normal summer,'' said Joseph Zaccaria, a manager of Emerson Quiet Kool of Woodbridge, N.J. ''If the good Lord would enlighten us we'd be happy to take one step beyond and make 50,000 or 100,000 extra units.''</p>
        <p>According to the manufacturers, above-average summer temperatures do not necessarily translate into stronger sales. Only an unbroken string of hot days causes a rush to buy. And if temperatures stay hot at night, resulting in a loss of sleep, the rush becomes greater. 32 Days Above 90 ''The rule of thumb is that three days of temperatures above 90 degrees causes people to go out and buy,'' said Jerome Michaelson, marketing manager for air-conditioning products at the General Electric Company. New York City has already had temperatures above 90 degrees on 32 days this year; the record is 37 days, set in 1944.</p>
        <p>Mr. Michaelson has received several telephone calls from irate consumers who wanted to know why stores did not have any G.E. window units. ''The consumer can't believe that the industry doesn't have a product to cool him off,'' he said.</p>
        <p>General Electric recently signed a tentative agreement to sell its only American plant, in Columbia, Tenn., to the Fedders Corporation. In G.E.'s view, the room-air-conditioner business is mature and will remain relatively flat except in abnormally hot and cold periods. According to industry estimates, 27 percent of all households have at least one room unit.</p>
        <p>The American air-conditioner industry has been partly constrained by a worldwide shortage of rotary compressors, the main component of an air-conditioner. The compressor mechanically puts freon under high pressure; the release of the pressure causes cooling.</p>
        <p>Many compressors used in this country are made in Japan, South Korea, Taiwan, Brazil, Canada and Italy. In addition to the American market, overseas factories in the last few years have received increasing orders from Africa and Asia. Price Increase a Factor</p>
        <p>The weakness of the dollar, moreover, has led to higher prices of imported compressors and resistance by American manufacturers.</p>
        <p>''American assemblers don't want to pay the high price,'' said Ted Kadoya of a Toshiba Corporation subsidiary in this country. Toshiba has been considering building a $100 million compressor plant in the United States, Mr. Kadoya said, but is concerned about the ultimate cost. Toshiba is also contemplating sending air-conditioners to the United States from Japan, but the weak dollar has dimmed that prospect.</p>
        <p>The Carrier Corporation, which has a relatively small share of the domestic market, according to analysts, does not agree with General Electric that the market is mature. Jerry Rudinsky, vice president of light residential products at Carrier, looks for major growth. Unlike most planners, Mr. Rudinsky says he sees the current heat wave as a harbinger of future demand. He also looks at such economic factors as gross national product, disposable income and new household formations.</p>
        <p>''The greenhouse effect may be having an impact,'' he speculated. To satisfy the expected growth in demand, Carrier is expanding its sources of compressors. Until 1986, Carrier bought virtually all of them from the Far East. Now it is buying them from a new Tecumseh Products Company plant in Tupelo, Miss., and has entered into a manufacturing joint venture in South Korea. Pressure Began Last Year</p>
        <p>The current shortage of air-conditioners, the manufacturers say, has its roots in the hotter-than-normal summer of 1987. Because of strong sales all that summer, the industry's distribution pipeline had been depleted by fall. Companies like Fedders added second shifts to build supplies for this summer, but few anticipated a second season of sweltering temperatures, which depleted many store shelves by late July.</p>
        <p>Thus, once the shortages occurred, few manufacturers had inventory to resupply the stores.</p>
        <p>Sales at Fedders for the first half of 1988 rose 57 percent, and apparently could have been higher. ''Our inventory of 5,000 B.T.U. and 10,000 B.T.U. conditioners, which the retailers have been looking for primarily, is completely gone,'' said Barbara Van Blarcum, director of investor relations at Fedders. ''There was some unfinished product that we're working on for shipment now. We're doing the best we can.''</p>
        <p>Although an air-conditioner can be built in a few hours, Ms. Van Blarcum said Fedders needed about 16 weeks to gather parts and materials - far too long to respond to a heat wave. A Seasonal Schedule</p>
        <p>American factories normally begin production in the fall, ship most units during the first and second quarter of the following year and shut down during the summer for maintenance and vacations. The seasonal schedule is meant to accommodate a retail selling season that lasts from May to August for most of the country, and just a few weeks longer in the hottest parts of the Sun Belt.</p>
        <p>The Friedrich Corporation of San Antonio, which shipped its last air-conditioners in the past few days, continued to supply retailers longer than any of its competitors, said Charles Marino, vice president of marketing at Friedrich.</p>
        <p>Friedrich increased production sharply this year for two reasons: first, its distribution pipeline had been depleted last year, as were the pipelines of most competitors. But Friedrich also assumed that last year's hot summer would make potential buyers more susceptible to advertising and promotion this spring. ''We make air-conditioners and nothing else, so we were prepared to invest in inventory,'' Mr. Marino said.</p>
        <p>Friedrich's advertising and promotions were heavy early this year, according to plan, but April and May were unusually cold and wet in the Northeast and retail sales were disappointing.</p>
        <p>''After Memorial Day, things started getting good,'' Mr. Marino said. ''And August has been a frenzy.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
