<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clean Hydrogen Beckons Aviation Engineers</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="148096"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HYDROGEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JET ENGINES AND JET PROPULSION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DESIGN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TU-155 AIRPLANE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrogen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jet Engines and Jet Propulsion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jet Engines and Jet Propulsion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Engines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DA123FF937A15756C0A96E948260" item-length="1896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clean Hydrogen Beckons Aviation Engineers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: VIRTUALLY unnoticed abroad except by aviation experts, a recent broadcast by Soviet television showed an ordinary-looking airliner roaring aloft from a Moscow-area airport, trailing a stream of condensing steam instead of the usual kerosene smoke.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: VIRTUALLY unnoticed abroad except by aviation experts, a recent broadcast by Soviet television showed an ordinary-looking airliner roaring aloft from a Moscow-area airport, trailing a stream of condensing steam instead of the usual kerosene smoke.</p>
        <p>VIRTUALLY unnoticed abroad except by aviation experts, a recent broadcast by Soviet television showed an ordinary-looking airliner roaring aloft from a Moscow-area airport, trailing a stream of condensing steam instead of the usual kerosene smoke.</p>
        <p>Despite the flight's lack of public attention in the West, aerospace engineers in this country recognized it as a milestone in aviation, marking the first time a commercial airliner had flown powered by hydrogen rather than by petroleum-based jet fuel. The event has prompted renewed calls for a hydrogen fuel program in the United States.</p>
        <p>Senator Spark M. Matsunaga, Democrat of Hawaii, has long advocated the exploitation of hydrogen, a gas that can be generated from water using solar energy, ocean thermal power and other renewable energy sources. In an interview, he compared the flight of the hydrogen-powered Soviet airliner last month to the launching of Sputnik in 1957.</p>
        <p>''Once again we've missed the boat,'' he said, ''and we can only hope that the next administration will be more interested in hydrogen than this one has been.''</p>
        <p>In fact, hydrogen will power the National Aerospace Plane, a hybrid airplane and spacecraft that is scheduled to make its first flight in 1994. The plane, described by President Reagan in his 1986 State of the Union address, would be capable of flying within the atmosphere using hydrogen-fueled air-breathing jet engines, and in space using pure rocket engines. The President dubbed it the ''Orient Express,'' since in theory, it could fly from Washington to Tokyo in two hours.</p>
        <p>But Senator Matsunaga and others argue that hydrogen power should be developed for ordinary airplanes as well. The inevitable depletion of oil and the urgent need to curb pollution of the atmosphere will make the widespread use of hydrogen fuel imperative, they contend. For the past decade Mr. Matsunaga has sought increased financial and political support for programs to develop alternative energy sources. Since his state has no fuel resources, energy costs in Hawaii are higher than on the mainland.</p>
        <p>The first test flight of the hydrogen-powered Soviet aircraft took place April 15, and although Soviet aerospace officials have disclosed few details of its propulsion system, Moscow television broadcast film of the flight.</p>
        <p>The aircraft, created at the renowned design bureau of Aleksei Tupolev and designated as the Tu 155, is a modified version of the three-engine Tu 154 transport, which entered service with Aeroflot two decades ago. It is comparable in size and appearance to the Boeing 727.</p>
        <p>Moscow disclosed that a special fuel tank installed in the aft part of the plane's cabin had been engineered to hold liquid hydrogen at a temperature below minus 423 degrees Fahrenheit. As the liquid is warmed, it boils into hydrogen gas, which is ducted to the combustion chambers of a turbojet engine. Combining with oxygen from the air, the hydrogen burns with intense heat, producing a powerful thrust.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tupolev was quoted by Soviet information officials as calling the Tu 155's hydrogen powerplant ''an absolutely ecologically pure engine.''</p>
        <p>When hydrogen burns in air, the combustion product consists entirely of steam. By contrast, the exhaust of a conventional jet engine contains various toxic pollutants as well as carbon dioxide, a gas contributing to the global ''greenhouse effect.'' By trapping solar energy in the atmosphere, increasing levels of carbon dioxide are believed to be causing a steady warming that could have major effects on climate, agriculture and society in the next century.</p>
        <p>Soviet reports did not specify whether all three of the Tu 155's engines were fueled with hydrogen. American experts speculated, however, that for its initial flights, the airliner might have burned conventional fuel in at least one engine in case the hydrogen system failed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tupolev said special gas analyzers had been installed throughout the plane to detect hydrogen leaks, and that a new system of gas-tight welding had been adapted from space applications in the construction of the airliner's fuel distribution plumbing. These and other refinements were intended to minimize the dangers of carrying the violently combustible fuel.</p>
        <p>The destructive potential of hydrogen was spectacularly demonstrated in the explosion of the space shuttle Challenger two years ago and in the 1937 crash of the airship Hindenburg.</p>
        <p>The Soviet announcement said the main purpose in building the Tu 155 had been to show that hydrogen would be a practical aviation fuel as world supplies of petroleum dwindle. Mr. Tupolev added that the same propulsion system could use liquefied natural gas instead of hydrogen and that liquid natural gas, which can be stored at room temperature, would be much easier to handle. The new Tu 154M and Tu 204 airliners, both scheduled to begin service soon, would be especially suitable for conversion to hydrogen or natural gas fuels, he said.</p>
        <p>Willis M. Hawkins, a former president of the Lockheed-California Company, who continues to serve as a consultant to the company, gave the Tupolev organization highest marks for building a hydrogen-powered airliner.</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Hawkins's direction, Lockheed proposed a decade ago to build an experimental fleet of L-1011 cargo planes fueled by hydrogen. The project would have required major financial support from the Federal Government. Despite the interest of Canada, Britain, West Germany and Saudi Arabia in participating in the $1.2-billion venture, nothing came of it.</p>
        <p>''The idea was to operate these planes from airports where hydrogen could be readily obtained in the necessary quantity,'' Mr. Hawkins said. ''We designed lightweight liquid hydrogen tanks for installation in the L-1011's center section and tail, and we developed the necessary fuel distribution system. But when the oil shortage ended and petroleum prices fell, so did the hydrogen project.''</p>
        <p>''Democracy is the greatest political system in the world,'' he continued, ''but it can certainly make long-range planning difficult.''</p>
        <p>An ordinary jet engine requires virtually no modification to run on hydrogen, Mr. Hawkins said.</p>
        <p>''Jet engines love hydrogen because it ignites much more readily than jet fuel,'' he said, ''and it burns evenly in a combustion chamber without creating hot spots. On a pound-for-pound basis, moreover, liquid hydrogen contains nearly three times as much energy as kerosene.''</p>
        <p>Since a given weight of liquid hydrogen can keep an airplane flying nearly three times as long as the same weight of jet fuel, he said, hydrogen fuel would be ideal for long-distance military missions, including intelligence-gathering flights, Mr. Hawkins said. His company once proposed converting several of the Navy's antisubmarine P-3 aircraft to hydrogen power, but that idea also failed to materialize.</p>
        <p>Hydrogen power for airplanes was pioneered in the United States. From 1956 to 1959, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration experimented with a two-engine B-57 jet bomber with one engine modified to fly on liquid hydrogen supplied from a wing-tip tank. On a series of flight tests, a Curtiss-Wright J-65 engine successfully powered the plane using both hydrogen and conventional jet fuel, smoothly switching from one fuel to the other without shutting down or faltering.</p>
        <p>The main objection to liquid hydrogen fuel is its cost. Usually derived from natural gas, liquid hydrogen costs nearly three times as much as jet fuel.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, aviation authorities believe that only when the price of jet fuel rises to about four times its current level or when hydrogen is proportionately cheaper, will hydrogen become attractive as a fuel for commercial airliners.</p>
        <p>But the National Aerospace Plane is another matter.</p>
        <p>William Escher, a project manager for hypersonic propulsion at the Rocketdyne division of Rockwell International, said liquid hydrogen was the only fuel suitable for the plane, which has already been designated the X-30. (Rocketdyne is one of the major contractors developing the space plane for the Air Force and NASA.) The main reason, Mr. Escher said, is that only hydrogen ignites quickly enough to operate a ramjet engine through which air is passing faster than four times the speed of sound.</p>
        <p>The X-30 will have to reach a speed of about 25 times the speed of sound to achieve orbit. For takeoff and during initial acceleration, hydrogen-powered turbojets would power the plane. At about four times the speed of sound, the craft would switch to hydrogen-fueled ramjet propulsion, a system by which air is rammed into the combustion chambers of the engines by the simple forward movement of the plane. On leaving the atmosphere, the X-30 would accelerate to top speed using rocket engines fueled by a mixture of liquid hydrogen and liquid oxygen - the same fuel mixture used by the main engines of the shuttle.</p>
        <p>Liquid hydrogen is indispensible for any space plane system, Mr. Escher said, not only as a propellant but as a coolant to protect the skin of the craft from frictional heating as it passes through air at hypersonic speeds.</p>
        <p>Frigid liquid hydrogen moving from an insulated fuel tank inside the X-30's body to the plane's engines would first pass through a heat exchanger where it would chill a reservoir of liquid nitrogen. Heat absorbed from the liquid nitrogen would convert the hydrogen to a gas or a slushy mixture of gas and liquid, and the warmed hydrogen would flow to the engine for burning. The liquid nitrogen, chilled by the liquid hydrogen, would be ducted under critical areas of the craft's skin and into air-conditioning machinery to keep the X-30 from overheating.</p>
        <p>Historic hydrogen disasters notwithstanding, Mr. Escher believes that hydrogen is one of the safest of all fuels, provided it is properly used.</p>
        <p>''A few years ago some of us started a little group called the H#2 Hindenburg Society to change the image of hydrogen,'' he said. ''How many realize, for example, that two-thirds of the people on the Hindenburg survived because of the upward-lifting quality of the hydrogen gas that kept the flame away from the passengers?</p>
        <p>''Hydrogen is dangerous, of course,'' he added, ''but so are all fuels, and tests have shown that in an airplane crash, hydrogen would actually be safer than conventional fuels.''</p>
        <p>Whatever comes of hydrogen power in the United States, international interest appears to be increasing. The International Association for Hydrogen Energy, of which many American experts are members, will sponsor a World Hydrogen Conference in Moscow next September.</p>
        <p>''Regardless of what we do in America,'' Senator Matsunaga said, ''hydrogen's role as a key fuel in the coming century is assured. I hope we will keep pace with the nations that have already begun building hydrogen technologies.''  Hydrogen Space Plane of the Future  The proposed aerospace plane (shown in artist's rendering) would fueled by clean, renewable hydrogen rather than fossil fuels. Some aviation designers believe that more prosaic planes could one day benefit from hydrogen-fueled engines as well. Besides providing powerful thrust, liquid hydrogen would cool aerospace plane's skin.  To avoid contact between the ultra-cold liquid hydrogen and the plane's skin, the liquid hydrogen could cool liquid nitrogen that would circulate through skin panels.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
