<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S.-Canadian Trade Outpacing the Treaty</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="162404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MALCOLM, ANDREW H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DB133CF93BA25754C0A96E948260" item-length="1968" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S.-Canadian Trade Outpacing the Treaty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW H. MALCOLM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MALCOLM, ANDREW H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Canada, with the world's second-largest area, and the United States, with the world's largest free-market economy, are fast forging a colossal continental economy of nearly 260 million consumers. And they are doing this quietly, almost without noticing it themselves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Canada, with the world's second-largest area, and the United States, with the world's largest free-market economy, are fast forging a colossal continental economy of nearly 260 million consumers. And they are doing this quietly, almost without noticing it themselves.</p>
        <p>Canada, with the world's second-largest area, and the United States, with the world's largest free-market economy, are fast forging a colossal continental economy of nearly 260 million consumers. And they are doing this quietly, almost without noticing it themselves.</p>
        <p>Trade between the two countries exceeds $150 billion a year, resulting in the world's largest bilateral trading relationship. Their 5,524-mile undefended border is crossed about 75 million times a year. The United States trades more with the province of Ontario alone than it does with Japan. Canada buys one-fifth of all American exports, twice as much as Japan buys. The United States buys more than three-quarters of all Canadian exports.</p>
        <p>The American-Canadian economic relationship - interconnected by common telephone, computer and power lines, by satellites, contracts and cross-ownership and even by common professional sports allegiances - is so vast that government officials acknowledge they cannot keep track of its complex dimensions, let alone control them.</p>
        <p>Now legislatures in both lands are debating a free-trade treaty to eliminate remaining tariffs in 10 years. Trend Surprises Officials</p>
        <p>The rapid emergence of high-powered, closely linked economies within global regions has surprised officials trying to remove trade barriers between individual nations. In Europe, the Economic Community is creating a bloc with intimate connections and 350 million consumers who retain their national cultures. Japan, with the world's No. 2 free-market economy, leads Asian development.</p>
        <p>Mexico, a less-developed nation concerned about its infant industries, has rejected similar associations with its neighbors as premature.</p>
        <p>In many respects the American-Canadian treaty currently being considered by both countries' legislatures is merely the two governments' hurried attempt at political recognition of a snowballing economic integration. This bilateral integration, which now includes a significant flow of Canadian capital, is proceeding as fast as aggressive small businesses and huge multinational corporations in both countries decide is in their self-interest.</p>
        <p>''The free-trade debate is practically irrelevant from an economic standpoint,'' said Alan Rugman, professor of international business at the University of Toronto, ''because, with or without the formal agreement, Canada and the United States are rapidly integrating themselves anyway.'' U.S. Investment in Canada</p>
        <p>American investment has long been strong in Canada, which has $103 billion (Canadian) in foreign investment, 72 percent of it American. In fact, one-third of all American investment abroad is in Canada.</p>
        <p>Now Canada (its name comes from 'kanata,' the Huron-Iroquois word for settlement) is the fourth-largest foreign investor in the United States.</p>
        <p>For decades Canada worried about becoming the 51st state. Now Tennessee, seeking to attract Canadian investment, advertises itself as the ''11th province.'' Every week brings major new Canadian investment: Robert Campeau's celebrated slugfest to control Federated Department Stores or Conrad Black's quiet accumulation of nearly four dozen newspapers. Toronto's Ken Thomson owns an additional 110 newspapers in the United States.</p>
        <p>Garth Drabinsky's Cineplex controls 1,500 American movie screens. Olympia &amp; York, run by Toronto's Reichmann brothers, is Manhattan's largest commercial landlord, controlling 25 million square feet of prime office space in the borough - one square foot for every Canadian.</p>
        <p>Canadian Pacific, Northern Telecom, Bombardier, Seagram and other Canadian companies control thousands of jobs in both countries. Wide Business Cooperation</p>
        <p>Several American banks, ranging from Chicago's mammoth Harris Bankcorp to the First National Bank of rural Barrington, Ill., are controlled by Canadians.</p>
        <p>Canadian jewelers, druggists, clothing designers and outlets, cable television operators and insurance companies have successfully marched south. Canadian and American teams routinely compete in professional hockey and baseball. Human organs regularly cross the border for transplant.</p>
        <p>Canadian developers, in league with Canada's small fraternity of national banks, rebuilt much of several American downtowns. Tourism officials in Alaska and the Yukon Territory next door advertise jointly.</p>
        <p>Annual sales of Canadian-generated electricity to Americans now exceed $1.2 billion, with contracts for $32 billion more already signed by Hydro Quebec and Northeastern states. Toronto's Harlequin churns out romance novels for millions of readers on both sides of the border. The Canadian authors Robertson Davies, Margaret Atwood and Farley Mowat appear regularly on American bestseller lists, while other Canadians like Peter Jennings, Morley Safer, Rich Little and Michael J. Fox appear regularly on TV in American living rooms. Participation in Takeovers</p>
        <p>Often Canadian money quietly bankrolls American takeovers. When the modern merger era began, Canada's Dome Petroleum bid for Conoco. That unsuccessful effort disclosed the weakness of Conoco, which was acquired by E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company. Seagram now owns 23 percent of Du Pont.</p>
        <p>Vancouver's Belzberg brothers participated in corporate raids, sometimes with T. Boone Pickens.</p>
        <p>The aggressive spread of Canadian business should not be surprising. In a country 121 years old and with 25 million people, Canada's markets and many Canadian companies are essentially mature. Next door sits a market nearly 10 times larger with radically differing politics but a strikingly similar capitalist culture. The United States has the same profit motive and even the same name for its currency.</p>
        <p>Canada's breweries, in a stagnant domestic beer market, logically looked south. Studies indicated that by advertising Canada's crystal-clear water, by using green bottles (which Americans associate with fancy imports) and by hauling them across a bridge to Buffalo or Detroit, they could charge a premium price in valuable United States dollars. Today three of the American market's top 10 beer imports - Molson's, Labatt's and Moosehead - are Canadian. Aggressive Beer Marketing</p>
        <p>At projected growth rates, Canadian brewers may soon sell more Canadian beer in the United States than in Canada. New Brunswick's Moosehead beer, still unavailable in six of the 10 provinces, is already on sale in all 50 states.</p>
        <p>''The Canadian business community has definitely matured,'' said Professor Rugman, ''There is a deepening understanding that Canadian companies, especially the multinationals, can compete with anyone in the big leagues.''</p>
        <p>Rowland C. Frazee, former chairman of the Royal Bank, said, ''We used to be a large Canadian bank with international operations, but now we are a large international bank with a strong Canadian base.''</p>
        <p>When Toronto's Four Seasons luxury hotel chain decided to expand, it entered the tough United States market. ''Why not?'' said Isadore Sharp, the chain's founder who now runs five hotels in Canada and 14 in the United States, including the Pierre in New York.</p>
        <p>Such confidence is characteristic of a new wave of Canadian entrepreneurs. Many of them are immigrants and their children who did not attend the prep schools and colleges that traditionally guaranteed access to Canada's ruling business class and its clannish bank boards. New Confidence Displayed</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Brian Mulroney, reflecting the new confidence, deals with Americans less like a belligerent younger brother coming of age and more like an equal.</p>
        <p>A conservative in the Canadian political spectrum, which is liberal by American standards, Mr. Mulroney has built a strong, amicable working relationship with President Reagan.</p>
        <p>Both men are of Irish ancestry, both come from working class families in smaller heartland communities and, importantly, both had successful business careers before winning national political landslides.</p>
        <p>Canadians have long complained that Washington pays episodic attention to their country. Canadians seem to cherish American slights - President Johnson's introducing Lester B. Pearson as Prime Minister Wilson or President Carter's failure to ratify a fishing treaty with Canada.</p>
        <p>Canadians still criticize Washington for its differing priorities on such issues as acid rain. But American attention to Canada is growing. The first foreign trip Mr. Reagan took in both of his terms was to Canada, something rarely noted there. He elevated Canadian affairs within the State Department and pushed the trade treaty, actually Canada's idea. Officials Exchange Visits</p>
        <p>Cabinet members in Washington and Ottawa exchange routine visits, while state governors and provincial premiers regularly meet. There are now 450 programs in Canadian studies at American universities.</p>
        <p>Canadians, 75 percent of whom live within 150 miles of the United States, absorb floods of American news and culture, and millions of Canadians winter in Southern states, prompting Canadians to think they know Americans, only 12 percent of whom live within 150 miles of Canada.</p>
        <p>But free trade has yet to produce free thinking. Diplomats and businessmen complain that wide Canadian exposure to American news produces surprisingly little understanding. ''There is a stunning lack of sophistication,'' said one American official, ''about how all these American groups and forces relate and contend.'' The United States Government recently arranged financing for only the fourth chair in American studies at a Canadian university.</p>
        <p>Among Canadians, Professor Rugman's research has found, students are the most suspicious. ''They're idealistic and naive,'' he said. ''They say: 'Big business owns Canada. Big business is American. Big business is pro-free trade. Therefore, we're against it.' '' Multinationals' Major Role</p>
        <p>In a sense, they are correct. According to Professor Rugman, 70 percent of American-Canadian trade is done by multinational companies, mostly with themselves. A new wrinkle is that now many of these multinationals are Canadian, and most say their operations are largely insulated from free-trade problems even should the treaty fail.</p>
        <p>Canadian officials hope the international attention of last month's economic summit conference, along with last winter's Olympics Games in Calgary, Alberta, possibly the 1996 Summer Olympics in Toronto and Canada's foreign business successes will help dispel the stubborn sense of vulnerability that lurks in the Canadian psyche like a psychological permafrost.</p>
        <p>But mental adjustment is difficult. Generations of Canadian children have been taught that the United States twice invaded Canada and once sacked Fort York, now Toronto.</p>
        <p>As sure as Mounties wear ceremonial scarlet, some Canadian parents reminded their children last month that the 1812 Yankee attack occurred just two blocks down Front Street from the summit meeting site.  Partners in Prosperity  In 1987, Canada exported $71.26 billion in goods to the U.S., while importing $60.25 billion. Below are the top imported and exported Canadian commodities, in billions.*  CANADA'S U.S. EXPORTS</p>
        <p>Commodity</p>
        <p>Value</p>
        <p>Autos</p>
        <p>$10.6</p>
        <p>Auto Parts</p>
        <p>8.5</p>
        <p>Trucks</p>
        <p>4.8</p>
        <p>Newsprint</p>
        <p>3.9</p>
        <p>Crude Oil</p>
        <p>3.6</p>
        <p>Lumber</p>
        <p>3.2</p>
        <p>Industrial Machinery</p>
        <p>2.2</p>
        <p>Equipment and Tools</p>
        <p>2.0</p>
        <p>Natural Gas</p>
        <p>1.9</p>
        <p>Wood Pulp</p>
        <p>1.9</p>
        <p>CANADA'S U.S. IMPORTS</p>
        <p>Auto Parts</p>
        <p>$11.6</p>
        <p>Autos</p>
        <p>6.6</p>
        <p>Equipment and Tools</p>
        <p>4.2</p>
        <p>Office Machines, Computers</p>
        <p>3.4</p>
        <p>Industrial Machineryd</p>
        <p>2.9</p>
        <p>Trucks</p>
        <p>2.6</p>
        <p>Communications Equip.</p>
        <p>2.3</p>
        <p>Aircraft</p>
        <p>1.8</p>
        <p>Other End Products</p>
        <p>1.7</p>
        <p>Chemicals</p>
        <p>1.6</p>
        <p>Source: Statistics Canada  *Converted to American dollars at a 1987 exchange rate of .7541 to the Canadian dollar.  dDoes not include engines and turbines.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
