<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Pledges Efforts to Clean Up Air and Water</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="175967"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MICHIGAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLUSHA, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2D9163FF932A3575AC0A96E948260" item-length="578" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Pledges Efforts to Clean Up Air and Water</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN HOLUSHA, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLUSHA, JOHN</byline>
      <dateline>GIBRALTAR, Mich., Aug. 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: With a revived Lake Erie as a backdrop, Vice President Bush today pledged to increase government efforts to improve air and water quality, including strengthening the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: With a revived Lake Erie as a backdrop, Vice President Bush today pledged to increase government efforts to improve air and water quality, including strengthening the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>With a revived Lake Erie as a backdrop, Vice President Bush today pledged to increase government efforts to improve air and water quality, including strengthening the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>Speaking at Lake Erie Metropark, a regional recreation area where the Detroit River and the once heavily polluted lake meet, Mr. Bush took note of the unusually hot summer and the closing of beaches by medical wastes in several areas. ''1988, in a sense, is the year the earth spoke back,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He promised to put an end to the dumping of wastes in the ocean by 1991 and said that within four years of taking office he would try to exceed the E.P.A.'s nationwide goal of cutting wastes by 25 percent. ''We can waste less and reduce pollutants at their source,'' he said. ''The technology is there - what is needed there is the will.'' Vigorous Enforcement Called For</p>
        <p>Moreover, he said the environmental agency should be more vigorous in forcing operators of dumps for toxic waste to clean up the sites. The Government's current program for cleaning up toxic waste is too cumbersome and slow, he charged. ''For those who don't cooperate'' in cleanup efforts, he said, ''E.P.A. should use its authority to sue them for triple damages.''</p>
        <p>On the sensitive issue of acid rain, he promised a specific, detailed program ''to cut millions of tons of sulphur dioxide emissions by the year 2000,'' though he did not spell out any of those details. Speaking in the region whose industry generates much of the sulphur dioxide that has been identified as the source of acid rain, Mr. Bush quickly added that paying for the cleanup would have to be a national effort.</p>
        <p>''No one region should be hit unfairly with the cost of addressing a problem that affects all of us,'' he said. Elected officials in the industrial Midwest, which is only now recovering economically from the recession that began in the early 1980's, have expressed fears that efforts to curb acid rain would impose disproportionately high costs here.</p>
        <p>Describing himself as an avid fisherman who spent the four days preceding the Republican National Convention angling in Wyoming, Mr. Bush noted that efforts to curb waterborne pollution had led to the re-establishment of a vigorous walleye fishery in Lake Erie.</p>
        <p>He said the revival of the fish population, which was virtually exterminated by pollutants and overfishing in the 1960's and 1970's, was a demonstration that vigorous use of environmental controls can reverse the efects of past pollution. Plan for Worldwide Conference</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said he would call for a worldwide conference on the environment at the White House in the first year of a Bush administration and promised to attend it personally. The purpose of the meeting would be to organize multinational efforts like last year's Montreal Protocol, which was intended to curb production of chlorofluorocarbons. Those chemical compounds are linked to the trapping of excessive heat from the sun within the earth's atmosphere.</p>
        <p>One position staked out by Mr. Bush may not find favor with many environmentalists. He said he favored increased use of nuclear power along conservation and the use of ''clean'' coal as the means of curbing acid rain. He said continued use of nuclear power was dependent of the safe disposal of radioactive waste. However, he did not propose a method of disposing of the wastes, some of which will be dangerously radioactive for hundreds of years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
