<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Theater; Metaphor and Whimsy in 'A Murder of Crows'</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="67" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="180270"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SOUTH STREET THEATER (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUSSOW, MEL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MURDER OF CROWS, A (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2D81E39F93BA2575AC0A96E948260" item-length="672" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Theater; Metaphor and Whimsy in 'A Murder of Crows'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MEL GUSSOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GUSSOW, MEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As if old age, creeping senility and a battle between a father and his son were not enough to furnish a family play, imagine a case of chemical contamination on Golden Pond and one begins to see the trouble in store in ''A Murder of Crows.'' This new play by Ed Graczyk, author of ''Come Back to the Five and Dime, Jimmy Dean, Jimmy Dean,'' opened Wednesday night at the South Street Theater, 424 West 42d</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As if old age, creeping senility and a battle between a father and his son were not enough to furnish a family play, imagine a case of chemical contamination on Golden Pond and one begins to see the trouble in store in ''A Murder of Crows.'' This new play by Ed Graczyk, author of ''Come Back to the Five and Dime, Jimmy Dean, Jimmy Dean,'' opened Wednesday night at the South Street Theater, 424 West 42d</p>
        <p>As if old age, creeping senility and a battle between a father and his son were not enough to furnish a family play, imagine a case of chemical contamination on Golden Pond and one begins to see the trouble in store in ''A Murder of Crows.'' This new play by Ed Graczyk, author of ''Come Back to the Five and Dime, Jimmy Dean, Jimmy Dean,'' opened Wednesday night at the South Street Theater, 424 West 42d Street.</p>
        <p>Before Wallace, Ohio, is turned into a ghost town, the central characters - an elderly potato farmer and his wife - plan to ''go fishing,'' a euphemism for self-destruction. Metaphor collides with whimsy in this cracker-barrel version of an environmental nightmare. Mr. Graczyk has so overloaded his drama with symbolism (a dinosaur bone; a pack, or ''murder,'' of hovering crows) as to strain the scales.</p>
        <p>Harley Woodson (Michael Higgins) has contracted cancer as a result of the contamination. Lately he has also succumbed to delusions. He thinks he sees the dead returning to life at his favorite fishing hole. While Harley endures his pain, his surly son and his daughter-in-law - surprisingly cheerful considering the circumstances - are emptying the parental home of possessions, preparing to evacuate the couple to a trailer home.</p>
        <p>The characters are typecast - a stern, unyielding father, a doormat of a wife (Kim Hunter) and a resentful son who was forced to give up college to take charge of his father's failing farm. Add to that trio the daughter-in-law, who is a compulsive tag-saler, regarding her in-laws and their property as disposable relics.</p>
        <p>Despite the bleakness of the collective plight, we are asked to believe the characters have had rewarding lives, including the son, who is now the head of the paint department at a nearby Sears, Roebuck. The father and son, who share a mutual, lifelong disrespect, achieve a reconciliation when the father swallows his pride and praises Sears's paint. One coat lasts forever, he says admiringly, and the son accepts that as a compliment.</p>
        <p>Just as the playwright gives a semigloss to the real problems of the father and son, he does not confront the serious ecological issues he raises, in contrast, for example, to ''The Nest'' by Franz Xavier Kroetz, a compelling play about the effects of toxic waste on a family. Instead, cliches fall like acid rain.</p>
        <p>The play is momentarily enlivened by the entrance of a garrulous widow (Evelyn Page) pulling a child's wagon with her belongings en route to sanctuary in Florida. But her apparent cynicism is soon buried in the sediment of sentimentality. Suddenly she realizes that the town's gravedigger, whom she has known since childhood, might be a suitable romantic match.</p>
        <p>What the widow and the gravedigger (Jay Devlin) have in common is a fondness for Ralph Waldo Emerson. He quotes Emerson (along with tombstone epitaphs); she has named her cat Waldo. Emerson himself would be disconcerted to find himself discussed so familiarly in such less than transcendental company. It is Digger who delivers the play's message: ''Death goes on, the same as life.''</p>
        <p>For the potato farmer, life goes on long enough so that he and his wife can have an affectionate twilight conversation and a last dance. Under Edward Stern's restrained direction, Mr. Higgins and Ms. Hunter resolutely maintain their dignity. Mr. Higgins, in particular, is scrupulous about not playing for the audience's pity. But the actors are vanquished by ''A Murder of Crows,'' which circles its subject at the same time that it courts self-parody.  SEPTEMBER PLAY  A MURDER OF CROWS, by Ed Graczyk; directed by Edward Stern; sets by Ursula Belden; costumes by Kathryn Wagner; lights by Daniel Stratman; stage manager, Patricia Flynn. Presented by Eric Krebs and South Street Theater. At 424 West 42d Street.  Corey Woodson . . . Terry Layman  Doris Woodson . . . Susan Greenhill  Jennie Woodson . . . Kim Hunter  Harley Woodson . . . Michael Higgins  Luther (Digger) Briggs . . . Jay Devlin  Velma Mackey . . . Evelyn Page</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
