<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Television; An ABC Study of 'The Poisoning of America'</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="177605"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCUMENTARY FILMS AND PROGRAMS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN BROADCASTING COS INC (ABC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, WALTER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BURNING QUESTIONS: THE POISONING OF AMERICA (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDE133BF93BA3575AC0A96E948260" item-length="478" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Television; An ABC Study of 'The Poisoning of America'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ''Burning Questions: The Poisoning of America'' is a straightforward, forceful and only too timely documentary for the torrid, dry and dirty summer of '88. The ABC News special, which can be seen tonight at 10 o'clock on Channel 7, reviews in punchy fashion the assaults on air and water that threaten health and recreation today and that may threaten existence tomorrow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ''Burning Questions: The Poisoning of America'' is a straightforward, forceful and only too timely documentary for the torrid, dry and dirty summer of '88. The ABC News special, which can be seen tonight at 10 o'clock on Channel 7, reviews in punchy fashion the assaults on air and water that threaten health and recreation today and that may threaten existence tomorrow.</p>
        <p>''Burning Questions: The Poisoning of America'' is a straightforward, forceful and only too timely documentary for the torrid, dry and dirty summer of '88. The ABC News special, which can be seen tonight at 10 o'clock on Channel 7, reviews in punchy fashion the assaults on air and water that threaten health and recreation today and that may threaten existence tomorrow. The tone is one of outrage at a dire situation, which the narrator, Hugh Downs, attributes to ''apathy, greed and politics.''</p>
        <p>The report, produced by Clark Adams, Ann Opotowsky, Sylvia Patterson and Lisa Zeff, moves so briskly that you may have trouble keeping track of where acid rain leaves off and the greenhouse effect takes up. But the impact is nonetheless considerable. (ABC's regular news programs this week have also been featuring reports on the environment.) Early in the hour, we see graphic reminders of the dumping of toxic matter into soil and waterways and hear charges that under the Reagan Administration, the Environmental Protection Agency has become a pussycat. Democratic leaders in Congress also come in for criticism for protecting their local industries at the expense of air and water. It is pointed out that a group called Citizens for Sensible Control of Acid Rain, which lobbied against acid-rain legislation, is financed by the nation's utilities: the probable sources of acid rain.</p>
        <p>The so-called greenhouse effect is explained clearly and ominously. The effusions by factories and automobiles of carbon dioxide and other gases is having the effect of thickening ''the blanket that keeps earth warm''; it allows sunlight in but does not let heat back out. For the future, this may mean productive land turned into desert and a melting of polar ice caps that will cause severe coastal flooding. Nuclear power may offer a benign alternative to the continued reliance on fossil fuels, but how to dispose of nuclear waste remains troubling.</p>
        <p>There is more: holes in the ozone layer that protects Earth from cancer-producing ultraviolet rays; important bodies of water destroyed by the dumping of chemicals and untreated sewage; the killing of ocean life by plastic garbage, which will continue to float through the world for a century.</p>
        <p>Like most ABC News specials, this one ends with a few examples of communities trying to clean up their air and water. In light of the documentary's formidable array of problems, these efforts are not especially heartening. A national or international effort is plainly required. Mr. Downs reports toward the end of the hour that the Presidential candidates have lately been talking up the environment. That is standard in political campaigns, but perhaps some of the scenes and figures so effectively put together in ''Burning Questions: The Poisoning of America'' may hold the nation's attention beyond the campaign season.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
