<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Making Sure the Lights Go On</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="176662"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="NEW JERSEY Q &amp; A: WILLIAM J. VIERBUCHEN JR."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BROWNOUTS (ELECTRICAL)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">JERSEY CENTRAL POWER &amp; LIGHT CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARNEY, LEO H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">VIERBUCHEN, WILLIAM J JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1D81F39F937A3575AC0A96E948260" item-length="1450" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Making Sure the Lights Go On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEO H. CARNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CARNEY, LEO H</byline>
      <dateline>MORRISTOWN</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: WILLIAM J. VIERBUCHEN JR. and the Jersey Central Power and Light Company have had a very demanding summer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: WILLIAM J. VIERBUCHEN JR. and the Jersey Central Power and Light Company have had a very demanding summer.</p>
        <p>WILLIAM J. VIERBUCHEN JR. and the Jersey Central Power and Light Company have had a very demanding summer.</p>
        <p>Like other electric utilities in the state, including Public Service Electric and Gas Company and Atlantic Electric, Jersey Central surpassed all records for peak electrical demand this season starting in July. As the company's chief of system operations, Mr. Vierbuchen choreographs the sometimes complex and sometimes frantic interchanges of electrical supplies that are required among the company's own generating stations, other New Jersey utilities and generation sources as far away as Indiana.</p>
        <p>Power companies in New Jersey, New York, Pennsylvania, Maryland and Virginia share an interlocking pool of generators known as the PJM interconnection. Members exchange or buy supplies to provide power where it is most needed and through the most cost-effective means - from oil, coal, natural gas or nuclear-fired generators.</p>
        <p>From Jersey Central's system control center on the third floor of its headquarters here, Mr. Vierbuchen heads a team that monitors the month-to-month and day-to-day capacity of the company to provide electricity to 840,000 residential, commercial and industrial customers. They represent 2.1 million people.</p>
        <p>Its service area includes all or parts of Sussex, Passaic, Warren, Hunterdon, Morris, Essex, Union, Somerset, Middlesex, Mercer, Monmouth, Burlington and Ocean Counties. Mr. Vierbuchen began as a lineman for the company 31 years ago and, while having 10 children with his wife, Janet, also found the time to take special course to qualify him for his present position of responsibility.</p>
        <p>In the interview that follows, he discusses how the interstate grid of electrical companies works, the reasons behind the record output, and the statewide brown-out that occurred on Aug. 15 at the height of the heat wave.</p>
        <p>Q. What were the obvious and not so obvious reasons for the unprecedented demand for electricity this year?</p>
        <p>A. The obvious one was the weather, 42 days of high humity and temperatures 90 degrees and above. The second thing that is pretty obvious is that, for the first two or three days into a heat spell, people will tough it out and try not to use their air conditioners. After the second or third day, though, we see a real increase in the load when they turn them all on.</p>
        <p>What is not too obvious to the public is the part played by the sudden growth of the economy in New Jersey. The growth of the area we serve, from last year's peak to this year's, was 11 percent, which is a tremendous increase. A lot of these new office buildings that were built and went empty for so long are now filling up with people. That's a lot of new space and a lot of new air conditioning.</p>
        <p>Q. Can you predict when there will be a heavy demand and how do you prepare for one?</p>
        <p>A. When we set the record on that Monday, the previous Thursday we looked at what the National Weather Service had to say about the coming weekend, and Monday, and came up with a preliminary forecast of what we call our load demand.</p>
        <p>Based on that forecast, generation was scheduled throughout our system. We looked at temperature, humidity, wind direction and whether or not it was going to be overcast. The guys here (in the system control center) continually updated the weather.</p>
        <p>By Sunday afternoon, we knew about where we were going to be on Monday morning. No one tells you to come in early, but you do. We try to look at where we were going to be at our peak period which in the summer is 4 to 5 P.M. The day of the week has very little to do with when we peak.</p>
        <p>Also, throughout the year, you do your scheduling. You try to give yourself a two-year window on maintenance of you plants and other facilities, then you update that on a six-month or 30-day basis. And you look at your forecasted load for the month, how much generation you're going to have available.</p>
        <p>Then we have a required reserve that we try to keep. You can't store or can electricity and when someone turns on the switch, they want the lights to go on.</p>
        <p>Q. How does the PJM interconnection work?</p>
        <p>A. Many electric utilities act as one company, one big unit. They report regularly and schedule generation by price form outside sources, and interchange power among themselves. They figure out costs. The PJM is a free-flowing system that goes where it is needed the most by shifting or forcing generation through 500 KV or kilovolts (extra high voltage) lines coming from the west (into Salem County). In the northern part of the state, for example, it comes through phase angle regulators that we use to shift away or pull in the power.</p>
        <p>The pool sets up their purchases for the month or the day and tells each computer at each utility. We have what we call an area controller. As flow starts to come into or go out of an area where it's not supposed to be, the controller sends out automatic signals to the generator to raise or lower generation.</p>
        <p>Q. If the PJM interconnection is supposed to assure adequate and proper supplies, why was the statewide brown-out or voltage reduction necessary on Aug. 15?</p>
        <p>A. What happened then was not only was New Jersey's pool of generation stressed, but so were those in New York and Pennsylvania. Further to the south and west of us, they were running into the same weather conditions. We were just about at the saturation point.</p>
        <p>We weren't in any way shedding or lowering the load because we couldn't meet the demands. What we were doing was lowering it so that if we lost a station, we wouldn't lose customer altogether.</p>
        <p>The 5 percent voltage reduction (which dimmed lights and slightly reduced power to machinery throughout the entire PJM system) increased the reserve and gave us a margin of safety. It really didn't inconvenience anybody in any way and it was a lot better than putting the lights out.</p>
        <p>Q. Is the incidents of brown-outs or black-outs these days greater, lesser or the same as it was in the 1960's and 70's?</p>
        <p>A. They are less. In the 1960's we were still waiting for some of the new nuclear plants to come on line: Three Mile Island in Pennsylvania (owned by Jersey Central's parent company, General Public Utilities), Oyster Creek nuclear generating station, and Public Service Electric and Gas Company's Hope Creek, Salem 1 and Salem 2 stations, all in New Jersey, and Pennsylvania Electric's Limerick nuclear generating station.</p>
        <p>Our capacity has grown. The 500 KV transmission system was not completed throughout the whole state back in the 1960's and 70's, so we saw more voltage reductions then.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you subscribe to the notion, proposed by some scientists, that this summer's extraordinary heat and draught was symptomatic of the greenhouse effect, a global warming caused by airborne pollutants.</p>
        <p>A. It's a possibility. I guess everyone has his own theory about the weather. I'm more inclined to believe that the protracted hot spell was due to a shift in the jet stream, which moved to the north and pulled in the hotter air from the south.</p>
        <p>Q. What can you tell about your service area from monitoring the usage of electricity here and in the system control center?</p>
        <p>A. We can see shifts in our load. We would normally run a 50-50 split in usage between our northern and southern areas, for instance, but in the beginning of July you can see it go to 48 percent and 52 percent in the south. You can detect what kind of year you're having at the shore.</p>
        <p>We do a lot of planning. In March each year we do a planning study in which we put in each of the forecasted loads of our substations. That forecast is given to each of our operators and we go over it and over it to get an idea of what the system will look like in the months ahead.</p>
        <p>But, later on, we'll sometimes see something unusually high while monitoring the substations and, when you make a few quick phone calls, you find out that a new industrial park or condominium project went in a lot faster than planned.</p>
        <p>Q. With all the computerization, where does the human factor enter the picture in your job?</p>
        <p>A. The information we receive is brought in from remote terminals, fed into our computers and given to us as operators. How to cure the problems that the information presents, such as overloads, becomes a human decision where you have to start to move power around. That's the challenging part.</p>
        <p>We talk to each other and to other utilities. It's interesting because it's never the same on any day. It's very stressful, but also exciting because you're working closely with other people and it's real team work. You're dead at the end of the day sometimes, but you've accomplished something. You've kept the lights on for a lot of people.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY Q &amp; A: WILLIAM J. VIERBUCHEN JR.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
