<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WHERE THE SUN SHINES, SOLAR ACTIVITY IS STILL BRISK</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="147509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="IDEAS &amp; TRENDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOLAR ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW MEXICO</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROBBINS, CATHERINE C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DF1E3BF931A15756C0A96E948260" item-length="672" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WHERE THE SUN SHINES, SOLAR ACTIVITY IS STILL BRISK</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHERINE C. ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROBBINS, CATHERINE C</byline>
      <dateline>ALBUQUERQUE, N.M.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Nearly 10 years have passed since President Carter committed the nation to achieving a 20 percent reliance on solar and other renewable energy sources by the year 2000. His 1980 budget included $597 million for solar research, and for symbolic measure, Mr. Carter had solar panels installed in the White</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Nearly 10 years have passed since President Carter committed the nation to achieving a 20 percent reliance on solar and other renewable energy sources by the year 2000. His 1980 budget included $597 million for solar research, and for symbolic measure, Mr. Carter had solar panels installed in the White</p>
        <p>Nearly 10 years have passed since President Carter committed the nation to achieving a 20 percent reliance on solar and other renewable energy sources by the year 2000. His 1980 budget included $597 million for solar research, and for symbolic measure, Mr. Carter had solar panels installed in the White House roof to heat the water.</p>
        <p>Today, the Federal budget for solar energy is about $100 million, tax credits to promote the solar industry have been eliminated, and Mr. Carter's solar panels have been removed from the roof.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, energy experts say, solar technology is developing fast enough to promise competition with oil for some electrical generation.</p>
        <p>New Mexico, blessed with sunshine and a solar tradition, is a leading center for solar research and entrepreneurship. In the 11th century, the Anasazi Indians oriented their multistory buildings to the sun and chose materials that worked in blistering summers and frigid winters. A Santa Fe architect, William Lumpkins, designed his first solar house in 1935.</p>
        <p>Today, New Mexico architects continue to integrate solar principles into much of what is built here. In Albuquerque, scientists at the Sandia National Laboratories say they can use the sun to help destroy toxic wastes, and a solar manufacturer, Steve Baer, has a thriving business two years after the end of tax credits.  Treatment on Site</p>
        <p>At Sandia, a solar reflector will use the sun's heat and a catalyst to break down toxic compounds, including PCB's (polychlorinated biphenyls), into relatively benign byproducts. Resembling a mirror-lined satellite dish, the reflector could be installed on a plant site, eliminating the expensive and risky transport of wastes. It should be marketed in about five years, said Donald Schueler, manager of Sandia's solar energy department.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schueler said he is convinced that in time the nation will be forced to rely more heavily on solar energy. ''We have to be smarter than we were in 1980 when we went out and attacked the energy market,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Sandia is financing research for hardware that can be transferred to the marketplace. A private company, Luz International, has installed hundreds of collectors developed at Sandia in a solar field near Edwards Air Force Base in California that Southern California Edison is using at peak times. The project will eventually generate 500 megawatts of electricity for about 150,000 households.</p>
        <p>While the Department of Energy is proceeding with solar research at Sandia and the Solar Energy Research Institute in Boulder, Colo., this year's budget request is at its lowest point since the Reagan Administration began cutting the solar research effort.</p>
        <p>That does not bother Mr. Baer, an inventor and the president of Zomeworks Corporation, which manufactures passive solar equipment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baer believes not only that solar energy ''resists bureaucratization,'' but that government should not be involved at all in solar development. He calls Sandia's projects a ''waste of taxpayers' money,'' and he even opposes tax credits. ''It's such an insulting way to run a country -to steal from everybody and give to a few who claim to be able to do something that they couldn't,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baer was not unscathed by the cutoff of tax incentives. His company's sales dropped 28 percent last year. But this year has seen a recovery; sales of a specialized rack that holds photovoltaic cells are twice what they were in the same period last year.</p>
        <p>For architects, passive solar principles in design are taken for granted, according to Toby Pugh, the president of the New Mexico Society of Architects. For example, Mr. Pugh said, he recently designed two solar houses that in the 1970's might have been subjects for professional journals. ''Now they're just good houses,'' he said. ''More of us are doing good, conscientious solar design in residential and small commercial buildings and not making a big deal of it.'' ''It takes more thought,'' he said, ''but I don't think it takes more money.''  IDEAS &amp; TRENDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
