<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Long Island Faces a Financial Meltdown</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="152208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHUTDOWNS (INSTITUTIONAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RATES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SHOREHAM NUCLEAR POWER PLANT</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND LIGHTING CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LENT, NORMAN F (REPR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DA1331F93BA35755C0A96E948260" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Long Island Faces a Financial Meltdown</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Norman F. Lent; Norman F. Lent, Republican of New York, represents a Long Island district. He is the ranking minority member of the House Energy and Commerce Committee.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LENT, NORMAN F (REPR)</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The shortsighted decision to abandon the Shoreham nuclear power plant on Long Island before it produced even a single watt of commercial power means that businesses and consumers will be stuck paying for much of the $5.3 billion facility for years to come.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The shortsighted decision to abandon the Shoreham nuclear power plant on Long Island before it produced even a single watt of commercial power means that businesses and consumers will be stuck paying for much of the $5.3 billion facility for years to come.</p>
        <p>The shortsighted decision to abandon the Shoreham nuclear power plant on Long Island before it produced even a single watt of commercial power means that businesses and consumers will be stuck paying for much of the $5.3 billion facility for years to come.</p>
        <p>By crafting the deal, Governor Cuomo fell victim to the hysteria created by antinuclear forces. Instead of reducing Long Island's dependence on foreign oil, the region now faces the prospect of a financial meltdown, with businesses and residents leaving the area because they cannot afford the increased costs.</p>
        <p>As part of the deal to close Shoreham, New York State has guaranteed that the customers of the Long Island Lighting Company will be burdened with a 63 percent rate increase over a 10 year period in order to keep the company solvent. That means consumers will pay some $3.9 billion of Shoreham's costs, plus the estimated $444 million needed to decommission the plant, without one additional kilowatt of energy to show for it.</p>
        <p>This deal also has national ramifications. New York will support Lilco's request for a multibillion dollar Federal tax write-off designed to insure that the utility will not be contributing to Federal tax coffers for the next decade. In essence, taxpayers from Maine to Hawaii will pay for Governor Cuomo's deal for years to come. That's unfair to the rest of the nation and sets a bad precedent.</p>
        <p>Anti-Shoreham activists, having declared victory, say they are willing to live with this financial burden. But dismantling Shoreham is only the first step on a long and tortuous road. When it's time to fill the void of electricity created by the absence of Shoreham, costs will rise even higher.</p>
        <p>New York has carelessly discarded the nuclear option for Long Island without a coherent plan on how to provide alternative energy sources. State officials act as if they were unaware that the cost of these alternatives will be added to the billions already invested for a plant that would have generated 800 megawatts of clean, reliable energy.</p>
        <p>Throw in the 5 percent minimum rate increase Long Island consumers will be saddled with every year for the next decade, and one can readily foresee the cumulative fiscal burden they will suffer.</p>
        <p>The alternatives under consideration have shortcomings. For example, Canadian hydropower, probably the most heralded energy alternative, will not be available until 1995 - and that's only if the building of transmission lines across Long Island Sound is completed on schedule.</p>
        <p>Moreover, what will happen if this foreign supply falls short because of greater demand in Canada than is projected? That's no idle worry. In fact, it's already happened. Canada recently failed to provide power contracted for by several New England utilities because of unexpectedly high domestic consumption. That incident would suggest that New York State could face a similar problem.</p>
        <p>Another proposal would allow Lilco to burn less expensive, high-sulfur oil at existing plants. But this plan is particularly ironic in light of Governor Cuomo's well publicized stance against acid rain.</p>
        <p>Sulfur emissions from smokestacks are considered a major contributor to acid rain. Burning high-sulfur oil also produces nitrogen oxide, a chief cause of ozone pollution that can, with repeated exposure, harm public health, including causing respiratory ailments.</p>
        <p>Burning more high-sulfur fuel could create political pressure to control other sources of air pollution, including those generated by small businesses and schools, in order to meet Federal air quality standards established by the Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>Suffolk County betrayed the lessons it learned in the 1970's, when oil prices were high and gasoline lines were long. At that time, Suffolk County encouraged Lilco to build Shoreham, but political winds have shifted and the unpleasant memories have faded.</p>
        <p>Now, with Long Island approaching 95 percent dependence on imported oil for its power, residents have no-where to turn. In the end, a vocal minority gained control of the debate, tricked rate payers into believing they could make the utility absorb the whole cost of Shoreham and forced state and local governments to cast aside a clean and reliable energy alternative.</p>
        <p>The result is that, by dismantling Shoreham, Governor Cuomo is attempting to deny economic reality. The sensible thing to do is to move forward with our investment in Shoreham and allow the plant to operate. Instead, we are committing a cowardly act of political myopia that will ultimately damage - and very possibly destroy - Long Island's economic prosperity.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
