<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Renegotiating a North American Friendship</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="201767"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDD1138F934A15752C1A96E948260" item-length="1124" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Renegotiating a North American Friendship</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW H. MALCOLM</byline>
      <dateline>OTTAWA</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: PAUL ROBINSON, a former United States Ambassador to Canada, tells a story about the initial intelligence briefing for his assignment here. ''Do we spy on Canadians?'' he asked the American intelligence officer. The reply was, ''No.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: PAUL ROBINSON, a former United States Ambassador to Canada, tells a story about the initial intelligence briefing for his assignment here. ''Do we spy on Canadians?'' he asked the American intelligence officer. The reply was, ''No.''</p>
        <p>PAUL ROBINSON, a former United States Ambassador to Canada, tells a story about the initial intelligence briefing for his assignment here. ''Do we spy on Canadians?'' he asked the American intelligence officer. The reply was, ''No.''</p>
        <p>Next, the Ambassador asked, ''Do Canadians spy on Americans?''</p>
        <p>''No,'' said the officer. ''But they do spy on the people we would use if we did spy on them.''</p>
        <p>The wry tale, professing an unusual and genuine intimacy while simultaneously acknowledging a lingering sense of mistrust and sneakiness on both sides, hints at the special relationship that has developed between two very similar and very different lands since 13 of Great Britain's North American colonies rebelled and the two others, both units of Canada, did not.</p>
        <p>Now, thanks to the Canadian election last week that gave Prime Minister Brian Mulroney's Progressive Conservative Party a renewed parliamentary majority and a mandate to enact the free-trade treaty with the United States, the two nations' usually warm, sometimes strained, always complex relationship is on the brink of a new era holding opportunities and a few dangers.</p>
        <p>Over the next 10 years the treaty will eliminate duties on virtually all trade between the two countries, which already have by far the largest bilateral economic relationship in the world. The treaty will bring more than 270 million Canadian and American workers, their families and employers into a new level of open competition and efficiency expected to boost prosperity in both countries. Officials also hope the deal will encourage other multilateral and bilateral trade liberalization.</p>
        <p>But that depends on the successful implementation of the treaty at a delicate time when the countries' relationship, fueled by expanding and increasingly intertwined economies, is already changing.</p>
        <p>For its part the United States, busy with its global obligations, has been perceived as rarely devoting anything more than episodic attention to its neighbors. Lavishing attention on something as seemingly parochial as a fishing treaty with Canada was way down on the American priority list. As one result, the Carter Administration never bothered to get Senate ratification of that fishing treaty, which Canada, the largest fish-exporting country in the world, considered so vital. The inaction confirmed longstanding Canadian concerns.</p>
        <p>But to the Canadians' surprise, the Reagan Administration acted differently. The first foreign trip Mr. Reagan made in both terms was to Canada. He elevated the importance of Canadian affairs within the State Department and dispatched his blunt-spoken friend Mr. Robinson as Ambassador. Although he ruffled feathers, Mr. Robinson and his successors no longer sounded condescending, even in private. If Mr. Reagan never took the positive steps most Canadians consider essential to combat acid rain, he at least began talking about the issue, especially after the 1984 election of Mr. Mulroney.</p>
        <p>While Canadian officials can and do talk tough behind closed doors, they seem less inclined now to air grievances in Canada's nationalistic press, always so eager to spot David vs. Goliath confrontations. Led by Canada's Ambassador in Washington, Allan Gotlieb, the Maple Leaf brigade has also grown more savvy and less shy in the hardball lobbying and bargaining that thrives in the back rooms, cloakrooms and tennis circles of the American capital.</p>
        <p>''Just 10 years ago,'' said Geoffrey Stevens, managing editor of The Globe and Mail of Toronto, ''this kind of free-trade treaty would have been unthinkable.'' About then, as many Canadian economic sectors matured, a new generation of Canadian entrepreneurs arose, among them the Reichmann brothers, whose company, Olympia &amp; York, is Manhattan's largest commercial landlord, and Robert Campeau, the Canadian who bought both Allied Stores and Federated Department Stores.</p>
        <p>Many of the entrepreneurs, like Mr. Mulroney the offspring of ambitious immigrants, sought new growth by penetrating the larger American market.</p>
        <p>Their successes - Canada is now the fourth largest foreign investor in the United States - bred little-noticed but regular Canadian trade surpluses and a quiet self-confidence. This new attitude, also reflected in the election results, was in marked contrast to the kind of poor-cousin resentment and inferiority complex that long characterized the attitudes of many Canadians when they thought about the United States.</p>
        <p>Today, economic, cultural and social ties are so pervasive on both sides that neither government can fully monitor, let alone control, them. Canadian and American police computers, for instance, are linked 24 hours a day, as are the countries' electrical grids. Hospitals on both sides of the border routinely exchange human organs. Two-thirds of the donations to Buffalo's public television and radio stations come from Canada. There are more than 400 Canadian studies programs at American universities. New York City's subway patrons ride in Canadian-made cars. Florida's tourism economy depends on millions of Canadians. Border-area sports teams draw so many fans from the other country that ticket order forms routinely state which country's currency is preferred.</p>
        <p>This all creates a momentum for even closer ties, which concerns some Canadians who fear a homogenization of North American social values.</p>
        <p>''We have tremendous differences,'' said Pierre Sarrazin, a director who is writing a satirical movie script about a war between adjoining American and Canadian towns. ''In Canada we stress the tribe more, not your rampant individualism. We finance a huge social security net; yours is more every-man-for-himself.''</p>
        <p>There will no doubt be disagreements as the free-trade treaty takes effect; one provision is a dispute resolution process.</p>
        <p>''But with the Canadians,'' noted one senior American diplomat, ''the assumption always is that something can be worked out.'' As it was, in fact, in the summer of 1812 when the two countries were formally at war. Despite that conflict, Canadians and Americans continued their usual intimate relations on another level. The New Brunswick community of St. Stephen shipped gunpowder across the border so the citizens of Calais, Maine, could have a proper celebration on July Fourth.  COMMON INTERESTS, ON DIFFERENT SCALES  Economic figures are for 1987, in United States dollars</p>
        <p>U.S.</p>
        <p>Canada</p>
        <p>Population:</p>
        <p>243,800,000</p>
        <p>25,900,000</p>
        <p>Area:</p>
        <p>3,540,939 sq. miles</p>
        <p>3,851,809 sq. miles</p>
        <p>G.N.P.:</p>
        <p>$4,527 billion</p>
        <p>$707 billion</p>
        <p>Investment:</p>
        <p>$57 billion in Canada</p>
        <p>$22 billion in U.S.</p>
        <p>Exports:</p>
        <p>$62 billion to Canada</p>
        <p>$74 billion to U.S.</p>
        <p>(Sources: U.S. Department of Commerce, Embassy of Canada)  THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
