<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ithaca Debates Power Plant at Falls</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="194909"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DE1E3DF936A35752C1A96E948260" item-length="990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ithaca Debates Power Plant at Falls</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>ITHACA, N.Y., Nov. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Residents of this small upstate community were horrified years ago when developers first proposed to build a hydropower plant below its most cherished natural landmark, Ithaca Falls. But now the city itself wants to build the plant and is seeking voters' approval in a referendum Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Residents of this small upstate community were horrified years ago when developers first proposed to build a hydropower plant below its most cherished natural landmark, Ithaca Falls. But now the city itself wants to build the plant and is seeking voters' approval in a referendum Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Residents of this small upstate community were horrified years ago when developers first proposed to build a hydropower plant below its most cherished natural landmark, Ithaca Falls. But now the city itself wants to build the plant and is seeking voters' approval in a referendum Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The 130-foot waterfall is the symbol Ithaca chose this year to commemorate its centennial. It is a favorite fishing hole and a serene refuge near one of the city's most urban neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>City officials, however, say that the Federal Government is going to allow somebody to build a hydropower plant about 550 feet below the base of the falls, and that the city can best protect the falls by building the plant itself. The city would preserve public access to the falls, and keep water flowing at the same rate as it flows on a typical autumn day.</p>
        <p>''If the city doesn't do it, there'll be another developer,'' said Benjamin Nichols, a member of the Common Council. ''If it's going to be there, we want to have control over it.'' 'A Terrible Thing'</p>
        <p>But many residents are unconvinced. ''From an environmental and a community point of view, I just think it would be a terrible thing to have a power plant put in there,'' said Theresa Greenman, a registered nurse.</p>
        <p>The city's plant would use a dam built in 1813 at the top of the falls and a 200-foot tunnel drilled into the nearby cliffs in 1832 by Ezra Cornell, the university founder. The power from those projects supplied energy to local industries as late as the 1950's.</p>
        <p>Residents of this Finger Lake city of 30,000 people are accustomed to fighting to protect the area's natural beauty. Last summer the community took on Cornell's plan to build an eight-story supercomputer center at the rim of Cascadilla Gorge, and Cornell eventually changed its plan.</p>
        <p>The hydropower issue, however, has presented environmentalists with a quandary: Many have promoted hydropower as a clean, safe alternative to nuclear power and fossil fuels, only to do battle with such a plant in their own backyard. 'No Easy Choices'</p>
        <p>The city's director of planning and development, Matthys Van Cort, supports the plan only because, he said, ''There are no easy choices on energy.''</p>
        <p>''It will diminish somewhat the enjoyment of the falls,'' Mr. Van Cort said. ''I think it's an acceptable impact given the global situation. It's a perfect example of thinking globally and acting locally.''</p>
        <p>''My first inclination was to support hydropower,'' said Daniel Hoffman, a member of Common Council who protested at the Seabrook, N.H., nuclear power plant in 1977. ''On the other hand I was very attached to the falls. I live in that neighborhood, and would be saddened by anything that would reduce its beauty and natural state.''</p>
        <p>The first developer to file a proposal with the Federal Government was a Pennsylvania concern in 1981. Several others followed suit. The city still regards Cornell, the dominant force in many community issues, as the most likely to build a plant, though the university has said it has no plans to build a plant. So now the city holds a Federal license to build one. 'A Substantial Moneymaker'</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffman had wanted the city to fight harder against any hydropower development. Mr. Nichols, on the other hand, a professor of electrical engineering at Cornell, enthusiastically backs the project.</p>
        <p>The city could pay the construction costs within 20 years, Mr. Nichols said, and after that, ''It's going to be a substantial moneymaker,'' for the city.</p>
        <p>The city plans to sell the power it generates to New York State Electric and Gas, the local utility. Officials say the plant could generate 8.9 million kilowatt hours of electricity a year, the equivalent of 4,000 tons of coal. But some critics say the city pushed to put the referendum on the ballot next week to take advantage of favorable rates from the utility company that could decline next year.</p>
        <p>In that event, the critics say, private developers would probably not take any interest in the site. A Quiet Battle</p>
        <p>Mr. Nichols maintains that the economics will inevitably improve, and the city should not forfeit its chance to take advantage of current prices. He also notes the willingness of the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission to approve these projects.</p>
        <p>''The national policy is, small hydropower plants should be developed. Federal law does not give any exceptions,'' Mr. Nichols said.  Because of those Federal policies some say, the battle to stop the plant has been fairly quiet. The city has waged an ambitious advertising campaign, warning voters of the dangers of private development of hydropower.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nichols said the city may have headed off any protests by conducting extensive environmental studies and promising not to run the plant when the falls are at their weakest.</p>
        <p>''In advance, we moved the plant as far away from the stream as possible,'' Mr. Nichols said.  Some people remain bitter. David Banfield, an insurance agent, was a critic of the project when he served on Common Council.</p>
        <p>''If they wanted to stop it, they could,'' Mr. Banfield said. ''Federal policy provides enough loopholes that you could stop it.''</p>
        <p>Fishermen fear if water is diverted from the top of the falls and released into Fall Creek downstream, the fish will not swim all the way to the plunge pool. Mr. Van Cort said studies have shown that the flow over the waterfall called for in the city's proposal would still attract the creek's salmon, trout and bass.</p>
        <p>The ballot measure itself has created considerable confusion. Voters will be asked to authorize the city to set up a public utility. The ballot does not mention hydropower.</p>
        <p>Since the city could conceivably sell the power to the electric company without creating a public utility, the referendum may not be necessary. If the state rules that the ballot question is not needed, the city could proceed even if voters reject the proposal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
