<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Utilities Worried by Decision on Older Coal Plant</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="193429"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FACTORIES AND INDUSTRIAL PLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC UTILITIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REPAIR SERVICES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WISCONSIN ELECTRIC POWER CO</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Service Industries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DB1F30F932A05753C1A96E948260" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Utilities Worried by Decision on Older Coal Plant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In a decision dismaying to power companies throughout the country, the Government has told a Wisconsin utility that plans to repair its coal-burning power plant will subject it to the strict air pollution standards that apply to new plants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In a decision dismaying to power companies throughout the country, the Government has told a Wisconsin utility that plans to repair its coal-burning power plant will subject it to the strict air pollution standards that apply to new plants.</p>
        <p>In a decision dismaying to power companies throughout the country, the Government has told a Wisconsin utility that plans to repair its coal-burning power plant will subject it to the strict air pollution standards that apply to new plants.</p>
        <p>Utilities are worried because they fear that the decision could apply to hundreds of plants and might force them to close old plants, and to forgo needed repairs or incur huge expenses to meet the standards.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department said the decision could jeopardize future power supplies, but environmentalists said the Federal Government should have enforced the standards years ago to improve air quality.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency's decision last week was the first time the Federal Government has intervened in renovations at a coal plant. In the past, the agency has not become involved because state authorities administering the Federal Clean Air Act have never brought such projects to the its attention. Wisconsin is the first to do so.</p>
        <p>The environmental agency said the plant in this case, Wisconsin Electric Power Company's Port Washington plant near Milwaukee, should be covered by air standards for new plants because renovation work will result in an increase in current emissions of several pollutants, including sulfur dioxide, a major cause of acid rain. 'Setting a Precedent'</p>
        <p>The Wisconsin utility and the agency are discussing whether the company's plans for the repairs can be changed to avoid invoking the standards for new plants.</p>
        <p>''This will be setting a precedent for the entire country,'' said Bob Beck, environmental manager for the Edison Electric Institute, a trade association for the nation's private utilities.</p>
        <p>Wisconsin Electric, which had planned to spend about $71 million to replace cracked steam drums, says the work is routine maintenance and should not draw tougher air standards for new plants.</p>
        <p>Industry analysts said that meeting the tougher standards could cost the company $800 million.</p>
        <p>In a letter to the company, the agency's administrator, Lee M. Thomas, said, ''The agency is considering what steps may be necessary'' to address renovations at other coal plants since the Clean Air Act was written in 1971. Extending a Plant's Life'</p>
        <p>Utilities are increasingly relying on ''life extension'' projects to keep old plants running. Careful renovation can keep some plants running for 60 years.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department says that as much as 25 percent of the nation's fossil fuel capacity is produced at plants that are more than 30 years old. That number will jump to 90 percent in 2010.</p>
        <p>Edwin R. Anthony, spokesman for the trade group, said that of the nation's 821 coal-burning generating units, 360 are smaller than 200 megawatts and ''my guess is that most of these plants are over 35 years old.''</p>
        <p>Port Washington has five 80-mega-watt units 38 to 53 years old. The company would like to keep the plant running until 2010 instead of retiring the last unit in 1999.</p>
        <p>A Wisconsin Electric spokeswoman in Milwaukee, Lisa Fox, said the Federal agency's decision, ''could throw a monkey wrench into our plans,'' adding, ''We need the capacity.''</p>
        <p>J. Allen Wampler, Assistant Secretary of Energy for fossil energy, in a letter to the agency said its decision ''could result in aggravating an expected shortfall in electric generating capacity in the 1990's or, at best, in the construction of less economical methods of generating electricity.'' Switch to Oil or Gas Is Possible</p>
        <p>Ms. Fox said the negotiators for the environmental agency and Wisconsin Electric might be able to come up with a solution that would reduce air pollution while holding down costs. She declined to discuss specifics of the talks, but confirmed that switching from coal to oil or gas is an option.</p>
        <p>David Hawkins, an attorney for the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental group, said any agreement that did not adhere to the air standards exactly might be vulnerable to legal challenge.</p>
        <p>Though utility sulfur dioxide emissions have been falling since the mid-1970's, environmentalists said they would have been further reduced if utilities had replaced plants rather than extending their usage.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
