<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Give the Smokeless Cigarette A Chance</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="178179"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FOOD AND DRUG ADMINISTRATION (FDA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">RJR NABISCO INC</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DE1F38F933A2575AC0A96E948260" item-length="494" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Give the Smokeless Cigarette A Chance</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Should the Food and Drug Administration regulate RJR Nabisco's new ''smokeless'' cigarette, scheduled to be test-marketed this month under the name Premier? An impressive list of experts, including the Surgeon General and the American Medical Association, argue that the Premier is a hi-tech device for delivering nicotine, designed for addicts seeking a safer way to take the drug.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Should the Food and Drug Administration regulate RJR Nabisco's new ''smokeless'' cigarette, scheduled to be test-marketed this month under the name Premier? An impressive list of experts, including the Surgeon General and the American Medical Association, argue that the Premier is a hi-tech device for delivering nicotine, designed for addicts seeking a safer way to take the drug.</p>
        <p>Should the Food and Drug Administration regulate RJR Nabisco's new ''smokeless'' cigarette, scheduled to be test-marketed this month under the name Premier? An impressive list of experts, including the Surgeon General and the American Medical Association, argue that the Premier is a hi-tech device for delivering nicotine, designed for addicts seeking a safer way to take the drug.</p>
        <p>If the F.D.A. agrees, the company would legally be required to show that the product, like any other drug, is truly safe before it could be sold.</p>
        <p>The petitioners may have a legal case. But it would be unfortunate if the the F.D.A. asserted jurisdiction and, as is widely anticipated, RJR responded by withdrawing the new cigarette. For while smoking Premiers is more dangerous than not smoking at all, the new cigarette almost certainly offers those who can't stop a way to reduce the risks to themselves and to others.</p>
        <p>The Premier looks like an ordinary cigarette, but looks are deceiving. The smoker lights the tip, which contains a small chunk of carbon. The smoke from the burning carbon - mostly carbon dioxide and water vapor - is drawn through an aluminum tube containing beads coated with tobacco essence and other ''natural'' flavorings. The mixture that hits the smoker tastes like very hot tobacco smoke and delivers a modest dose of nicotine. But it includes almost no ''tar'', the witches' brew of chemicals that causes cancer and chronic lung diseases. It's unclear whether smokers will like the new cigarette. There's little doubt, though, that their friends, families and co-workers will. The Premier creates no ash. The sidestream smoke is non-irritating, almost odorless, and dissipates in seconds. And the recessed tip makes it difficult for a careless smoker to set a mattress on fire or burn a hole in the coffee table.</p>
        <p>RJR plans to advertise Premier as the ''cleaner'' cigarette, lacking compounds associated with what RJR calls the ''health controversy.'' Obviously, the idea is to appeal both to health-conscious smokers and to smokers who want to reduce the social hassle of puffing in public.</p>
        <p>Why are anti-smoking activists who used to decry the industry's failure to make a safer cigarette now so bitterly opposed to its sale? They fear that the no-tar cigarette will give smokers an excuse to maintain the habit. Equally important, they worry that Premier's benign public face will reduce the social pressure on smokers to quit.</p>
        <p>Those are real risks. But it is also possible that the sale of a safer cigarette will generally undermine cigarette sales, the way the promotion of decaffeinated coffee increased the perceived dangers of coffee-drinking.</p>
        <p>In any case, such calculations ignore the realities of nicotine use. Inhaled, nicotine is a fiercely addicting substance. Millions of addicts have quit, but the millions who can't deserve compassion, understanding, and the chance to choose a less risky, more socially acceptable alternative.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
