<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Seeks to Balance Oil and Environment</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="146004"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1988</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAX CREDITS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXPLORATION OF RESOURCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOYD, GERALD M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exploration of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D6163EF934A25756C0A96E948260" item-length="957" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Seeks to Balance Oil and Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD M. BOYD, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BOYD, GERALD M</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, May 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Vice President Bush, campaigning in the Northwest, has been urging greater domestic oil production and arguing that it can be achieved without endangering the environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Vice President Bush, campaigning in the Northwest, has been urging greater domestic oil production and arguing that it can be achieved without endangering the environment.</p>
        <p>Vice President Bush, campaigning in the Northwest, has been urging greater domestic oil production and arguing that it can be achieved without endangering the environment.</p>
        <p>That balancing act is expected to come under close scrutiny in the fall Presidential campaign because of Mr. Bush's long-standing ties to the oil industry, where he worked and prospered before going into politics. Oil and gas interests have served as a major source of Bush campaign financing over the years, including this one.</p>
        <p>The Vice President has already indicated that, if elected President, he would seek to change the landmark legislation that overhauled the Federal tax codes so that it would provide more incentives for domestic oil exploration.</p>
        <p>''We cannot say that we want more domestic oil, but always drill it someone else's area - we can't do that,'' he said recently. ''You have to take into consideration environmental concerns and then try prudently to do what is necessary for the energy base in this country.''</p>
        <p>''I do not want to see the United States become increasingly dependent on foreign oil.'' he said. Sunday on the River</p>
        <p>As he has campaigned in the West, the Vice President has sought to reassure skeptics that he is as committed to the environment as he is to energy exploration and development.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, he embarked on a seven-mile fishing trip in southern Oregon's Rogue River, an event that netted considerable media attention, but no fish.</p>
        <p>In addition, the Vice President has been telling audiences out here that he enjoys ''the outdoor life'' and would be a good President for the environment because he would use the White House as a ''bully pulpit'' to focus on environmental concerns.</p>
        <p>Today, he went further, saying in a speech before the Chamber of Commerce here that he did not believe that enough has been done in recent years to protect the environment. 'Push Harder' on Enforcement</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said a need exists '' to push harder'' on the enforcement of some Federal laws and regulations. He said he favored proposals to speed the cleanup of toxic waste dumps, protect groundwater and strengthen the commitment to reduce sulfur and nitrogen oxide emissions that cause acid rain.</p>
        <p>''A Bush Administration will enforce environmental laws aggressively,'' he said, ''putting the responsibility for cleanup where it belongs - on those who caused the problem in the first place. But it will also understand that micromanagement from Washington leads eventually only to paralysis.''</p>
        <p>Nowhere is Mr. Bush's balancing act more evident than in the case of pollution from the burning of coal and oil that is transformed chemically in the atmosphere to acidic rain, snow or fog.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said today that ''we can't afford to study the problem any more'' as the Reagan Administration has been advocating. But while calling for greater, if unspecified, efforts, he also urged continued reliance on coal for energy. 'Clean-Coal Technology'</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has sought to ease concerns over the pollution cause by coal by supporting a $5 billion program to develop new ''clean-coal technology.</p>
        <p>While indicating that he would redirect some aspects of the Reagan Administration's environmental policy, Mr. Bush has indicated he would continue its basic thrust.</p>
        <p>For example, he opposes prohibiting further leases for offshore oil drilling. Environmentalists favor a prohibition, and it has also been endorsed by Gov. Michael S. Dukakis, the probable Democratic nominee, and the Rev. Jesse Jackson. Aides to Mr. Bush have been working for months on an energy statement that is expected to include the urging of additional incentives for oil exploration. It also is to call for continued reliance on nuclear power, abolition of the windfall profits tax on oil, decontrol of natural gas and use of ethanol and methanol as alternative fuels.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has also indicated other minor differences with President Reagan. Today, for example, he said he supported the recommendations of the President's Commission on America's Outdoors. The panel made recommendations last year, but the Administration has delayed action on them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, however, has often sounded much like Mr. Reagan as he has dismissed some worries of environmentists.</p>
        <p>The Vice President said Saturday, for example, that environmentalists had been concerned about the damage the Alaska pipeline might do to caribou but that those fears were ill-founded.  DUKAKIS SEEKS MORATORIM</p>
        <p>BOSTON, May 16 - Governor Dukakis urged today that a moratorium on offshore oil drilling in the Georges Bank area of the North Atlantic be expanded and said such drilling should be a ''last resort'' as a means to produce energy.</p>
        <p>At a news conference here, Mr. Dukakis said the Reagan Administration was ''bound and determined to proceed to further lease sales and additional drilling in ways that we think are unwise and reckless and totally unnecessary.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dukakis announced his support for a proposal by Representative Gerry E. Studds, a Massachusetts Democrat, that would extend a Congressional moratorium on oil drilling in Georges Bank.</p>
        <p>The Governor asserted that the extension would ''effectively bar drilling'' in Georges Bank, a major fishing area off Massachusetts that Mr. Dukakis said was crucial to the fishing and tourism industries.</p>
        <p>But, with the California primary only three weeks away, Mr. Dukakis also directed his comments to the subject of offshore drilling in general. Asked under what circumstances he thought offshore drilling would be wise, he replied: ''Our backs have to be to the wall on the energy front before it would justify this kind of interference with the natural environment. You only go out there and drill as a last resort.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
