<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Tezisy Street</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="160213"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="ON LANGUAGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LANGUAGE AND LANGUAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENGLISH LANGUAGE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RUSSIAN LANGUAGE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Russian Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DB113DF933A25754C0A96E948260" item-length="1166" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Tezisy Street</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM SAFIRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A THESIS, IN LOGIC and rhetoric, is a proposition - a theme to be discussed and perhaps proved by maintaining its good sense in the face of anticipated challenge and argument.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A THESIS, IN LOGIC and rhetoric, is a proposition - a theme to be discussed and perhaps proved by maintaining its good sense in the face of anticipated challenge and argument.</p>
        <p>A THESIS, IN LOGIC and rhetoric, is a proposition - a theme to be discussed and perhaps proved by maintaining its good sense in the face of anticipated challenge and argument.</p>
        <p>In Russian, the word is substantially the same, transliterated by us as &gt;tezis to reflect the Russian pronunciation in our different alphabet. The English plural is &gt;theses, pronounced THEES-ese, and the Russian plural is &gt;tezisy, pronounced TEZ-is-ee.</p>
        <p>These days, Muscovites are on Tezisy Street. The hot new word in the vocabulary of &gt;perestroika is &gt;theses. Members of the world news media at the recent summit conference were handed pocket-sized maroon booklets titled ''Theses of the CPSU Central Committee for the 19th All-Union Party Conference.''</p>
        <p>Those who dared wade into the morass of bureaucratese denouncing bureaucracy were struck by the use of the &gt;thesis technique: 10 theses, presented like arguable commandments, to be chewed over at the once-in-a-half-century confabulation.</p>
        <p>Whence this word? The Greeks coined it for ''the act of laying down,'' from the verb for ''to put, place''; that meaning still exists, like a vestigial tail, in the language of music, in which a &gt;thesis is a downbeat.</p>
        <p>Along came the mathematicians Leonard and Thomas Digges in the 1500's with a translation of Copernicus's theory about the earth circling the sun. Thomas Digges published a work in 1579 that discussed ''The vulgare Thesis of the Earthes Stabilitie,'' a notion that Copernicus had been out to demolish. This sense of thesis as a ''debatable proposition'' is what the Soviets have picked up.</p>
        <p>However, most Americans think of the noun as meaning a paper or dissertation written to obtain a doctoral degree (hairsplitting academics say it's a master's thesis but a doctoral dissertation); that meaning was taken centuries ago to describe a paper written to prove a thesis. The academic reverence for such work was spoofed by Robert Hillyer in a poem addressed to Robert Frost: ''Make me immortal in thy exegesis-/ Or failing that, at least a Doctor's thesis.''</p>
        <p>Let us not confuse a &gt;thesis with a &gt;hypothesis. The latter comes first; that is, the prefix &gt;hypo- means ''under'' (not &gt;hyper-, ''above''), and a &gt;hypothesis is placed under a thesis, laying its foundation. Although the words are used interchangeably by those not steeped in logic, a nice distinction can be made: first comes the &gt;hypothesis, which can be pretty wild, a tentative explanation unsupported by fact, and then a &gt;thesis, which is a better-developed argument.</p>
        <p>Here comes Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel with his famous dialectic: after the assertion of the &gt;thesis comes the opposition of the &gt;antithesis - apparently contradictory - but followed by a third proposition, reconciling the seeming contradiction on some higher level of truth, known as a &gt;synthesis. That's sometimes how deals are done at party conventions.</p>
        <p>Curious that Mikhail Gorbachev should use &gt;theses as the verbal framework for his struggle to redirect power in the Soviet Union. The most famous historical use of the word was at the start of a reformation likely to prove more lasting: Martin Luther, on Oct. 31, 1517, affixed his ''95 Theses'' to the door of the church at Wittenberg's castle, implicitly attacking the sale of papal indulgences and starting a theological argument that persists to this day.</p>
        <p>Did the Soviet leader use that word deliberately to recall an earlier reform movement? Will his 10 theses wind up on what Leon Trotsky liked to call ''the ash heap of history''? Watch this space.  WIGGLE, WIGGLE</p>
        <p>WIGGLE ROOM IS NOT A free-play area in an especially permissive child-care center, but a frequently used phrase that means ''space in which to turn around; an implicit opportunity for later flexibility; a political position permitting interpretation leading to modification. Not quite an &gt;escape hatch or a &gt;way out.''</p>
        <p>That's how it was defined in this column four long years ago. But some people never get the word.</p>
        <p>The editorial page of The New York Times, exercising its diatribal rights, castigated Michael Dukakis for suggesting that the United States Embassy be moved from Tel Aviv to Jerusalem, which Israel has designated as its capital. The editorialist disagreed, but found some satisfaction in the vagueness of the candidate's formulation: ''He has thus left himself wriggling room should he be elected.'' &gt;Wriggling room is at best a prescriptive improvement, at worst a genteelism, that the editorialist picked up from an eminent lexicographer who did not have citations on hand for the correct dialect phrase, &gt;wiggle room.</p>
        <p>Let us play the language as it lays (lays is the idiom, not the grammatical lies). The term is &gt;wiggle room. No interpretations, no modifications, no slipping out of the commitment.  LITTERBUGS IN GREENHOUSES</p>
        <p>THE UNITED STATES Environmental Protection Agency's European program manager, David H. Strother, writes that he has been ''assigned action on a letter . . . from a Belgian looking for the origins of the word &gt;litterbug'' and has turned to me.</p>
        <p>I like action assignments, which are presumably less subtle and more satisfying than passive assignments.</p>
        <p>The headline ''47,000 Subway 'Litterbugs' Pay $107,000 in Fines in 1946 Drive'' appeared in The New York Herald Tribune on Feb. 16, 1947. That was the first recorded citation of the term, probably coined by a neologistic publicist or adman in the New York City Department of Sanitation. It was one of flackdom's finest hours.</p>
        <p>The coinage was based on &gt;jitterbug, a 1934 coinage in the title of a Cab Calloway song, ''Jitter Bug,'' describing those who enjoy the frenetic movements of a dance such as the Lindy. &gt;Jitterbug was coined in turn on the analogy of &gt;firebug, which was based on the 1841 &gt;tariff bug, a derogation of believers in trade barriers. As we can see, the slang noun &gt;bug has long meant ''enthusiast''; that sense has passed as the word has been used as a verb, meaning to eavesdrop upon or to annoy.</p>
        <p>In return for this service to the E.P.A., I would like to get from that agency the origin of &gt;greenhouse effect, the warming of the earth's temperature caused by the increase in carbon dioxide produced by the burning of what are always called ''fossil fuels.''</p>
        <p>Ever since learning that bibb lettuce was named after Maj. John Bibb, the noted horticulturist, I have been attuned to eponymy in coinage. However, it appears that nobody named Greenhouse was involved; the earliest sightings of the word were in a 1937 textbook by G.T. Trewartha, who wrote of the ''so-called greenhouse effect.''</p>
        <p>That means he picked it up from what people were saying. But who said it first, and where? A mystery; if the E.P.A. can find out, that would be helpful to those of us, here and in Belgium, who care about these things.</p>
        <p>If the world starts cooling off rapidly in the next few decades, that will be called the ''room heater that keeps blowing the fuses effect,'' its first use in this newspaper on this day.</p>
        <p>ON LANGUAGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
