<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Furor Over Bay Burial of Dredged Material</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="173562"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DREDGES AND DREDGING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK HARBOR</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ARMY CORPS OF ENGINEERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JAMES, GEORGE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Machinery and Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2DE133BF930A1575BC0A96E948260" item-length="1233" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Furor Over Bay Burial of Dredged Material</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JAMES, GEORGE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Army Corps of Engineers is exploring a plan to use underwater pits near the shores of Brooklyn, Queens, Staten Island and Monmouth County, N.J., to bury dredged material that does not meet Federal ocean dumping standards, and the plan has created a furor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Army Corps of Engineers is exploring a plan to use underwater pits near the shores of Brooklyn, Queens, Staten Island and Monmouth County, N.J., to bury dredged material that does not meet Federal ocean dumping standards, and the plan has created a furor.</p>
        <p>The Army Corps of Engineers is exploring a plan to use underwater pits near the shores of Brooklyn, Queens, Staten Island and Monmouth County, N.J., to bury dredged material that does not meet Federal ocean dumping standards, and the plan has created a furor.</p>
        <p>Corps officials insist the dredged material is not hazardous waste, sewage sludge, garbage or medical waste and therefore not a public health hazard. They point out that the sediment is already underwater, at the bottom of Jamaica and New York Bays, some of it contaminated by industrial discharges, and they maintain that it would be contained more safely covered by sand in what they call ''sub-aqueous borrow pits.''</p>
        <p>But since the plan comes at the end of a summer of stifling heat, ominous predictions about the ''greenhouse effect'' of airborne pollutants, and beaches closed by amphibious landings of medical waste and sewage, it has roused the fears of many who worry that the material is dangerous and the Corps of Engineers motivated more by expeditiousness than ecological purity.</p>
        <p>Calling the plan a ''potential ecological and economic disaster,'' the Brooklyn Borough President, Howard Golden, drew applause at a recent public hearing when he voiced a common fear about the dredged material: ''If it is so toxic it can't be dumped in the open ocean, how can we bury it 500 yards off our beaches?''</p>
        <p>More opposition is expected at hearings scheduled for today at Wagner College on Staten Island and tomorrow in the Middletown Municipal Courthouse in Monmouth County.</p>
        <p>Because New York Harbor has a natural depth of only 19 feet, according to the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, and modern vessels require a depth of 35 feet, up to 8 million cubic yards of silt must be dredged up of the ship channels every year. Without the shipping, the city and New Jersey would lose thousands of jobs and millions in taxes.</p>
        <p>Now, much of this sediment is dumped six miles off the coast of New Jersey. But about 10 percent of the dredge spoils are fouled by industrial discharges, including heavy metals and polychlorinated biphenyls, or PCB's, according to Port Authority estimates, and Federal regulations prevent it from being dumped in the ocean.</p>
        <p>Borrow pits - an old sand miner's term for pits left when harbor-bottom sand and gravel is dredged up, or ''borrowed,'' for construction or landfill - may be the only environmentally and economically sound alternative, the Port Authority has said.</p>
        <p>There are now about two dozen borrow pits, and the corps chose seven for study for potential use, including two at the east end of the Jamaica Bay Wildlife Refuge, abutting Kennedy International Airport. They are between 20 and 70 feet deeper than the harbor bottom. In addition, the corps is exploring two sites in New York Harbor for new pits 90 feet below the harbor bottom.</p>
        <p>But use of the Jamaica Bay pits might be scrapped because channels might have to be dredged and bridges rebuilt simply for barges to reach them.</p>
        <p>Less feasible alternatives, officials say, include building an island of dredge spoils in the harbor or trucking them upstate and dumping them in fields.</p>
        <p>The corps has experimented with borrow pits in Seattle, and a decision about New York Harbor will not be made for at least a year.</p>
        <p>But opposition to the plan is already fierce, something that appears to surprise and dismay corps officials, who have said they believe it is based on misinformation and emotions heightened by the summer's beach closings. Opposition Gathering</p>
        <p>A petition drive on the Rockaway peninsula by opponents to pits in Jamaica Bay has garnered nearly 10,000 signatures, said the drive's organizer, Lew Simon, a schoolteacher who is running for the State Assembly.</p>
        <p>And two public hearings Thursday at Kingsborough Community College in Brooklyn drew more than 300 opponents, including residents of waterfront neighborhoods in Brooklyn and Queens, environmentalists, fishermen and city and Federal officials.</p>
        <p>The Port Authority favors using the borrow pits, as does the Universal Maritime Service Corporation, which operates the Red Hook Container Terminal in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>The Army Corps of Engineers is charged by Federal law with regulating the dredging of navigable waterways. But corps officials said the plan was also being overseen by representatives of the Environmental Protection Agency and other Federal, New Jersey and New York governmental agencies. Cadmium and PCB's</p>
        <p>It is also being studied by the Public Involvement Coordination Group, which includes 500 representatives of government agencies, labor, industry, environmental groups and civic associations.</p>
        <p>At last week's hearings, Mario Paula, project manager for the corps plan, admitted that some of the dredge spoils may be contaminated with heavy metals, such as cadmium, tars or other petroleum byproducts heavy enough to sink, and some small amounts of PCB's.</p>
        <p>But he and other corps officials contended, at the hearings and in interviews, that although such toxins do kill fish, particularly bottom-feeders and shellfish and do accumulate in their tissues, the toxins are not present in high enough concentrations to be dangerous. For instance, the corps said PCB's were dangerous only at levels of 50 parts per million. But the highest level found in dredge spoils, officials say, is 10 parts per million, and they say it stays chemically bonded to the sediment.</p>
        <p>Since the materials are already in the water, Mr. Paula pointed out, pouring them into borrow pits and covering them with a thick layer of clean sand would seal them off from the marine environment better than they are now. 'Feathers in a Garbage Can'</p>
        <p>The pits in the bay are the safest alternative, he said, because the waters are so shallow that the dredged material would reach the bottom faster and not be scattered by currents.</p>
        <p>But Robert Wemyss, the secretary of the North Shore Baymen's Association, an organization of commercial shell fishermen on Long Island, testified at a hearing in Brooklyn that dropping sediment into the currents over the pits was ''like standing on a roof and trying to get feathers from my pillow into a garbage can.''</p>
        <p>Some environmental proponents believe that it is less dangerous to let heavy contaminants remain in bottom sediments than to dig them up and rescatter them, even with good intentions. 'One of the Most Dangerous'</p>
        <p>Representative Charles E. Schumer, a Brooklyn Democrat, testified that the Corps of Engineers' own environmental impact statement noted the procedure has yet to be verified in full-scale operation and that questions of safety remain.</p>
        <p>He said PCB's ''are one of the most dangerous and long-lived compounds'' that will be ingested by fish and people who eat the fish.</p>
        <p>A Manhattan Beach resident, Renee Margoleis, accused the corps of inadequately informing the public of the hearings.</p>
        <p>Corps officials replied that 1,800 public notices had been sent to elected officials, community boards, newspapers and others.</p>
        <p>The chief of public affairs for the New York district of the corps, Peter H. Shugert, said, ''The corps does not try to hide the facts, but if we were trying to pull one over on the public, we wouldn't do it at this time when everybody is sensitized to the trauma they've just gone through with beach closings because of vials of blood and syringes washing up on shore.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
