<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Privatization Faces Test in Britain</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="123335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NATIONALIZATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAINES, HOWELL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">THATCHER, MARGARET H (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880229T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDA1538F93AA15751C0A96E948260" item-length="891" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Privatization Faces Test in Britain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWELL RAINES, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAINES, HOWELL</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Feb. 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher's plan to end Government ownership of Britain's electrical power system is emerging as a major test of public satisfaction with her policy of privatization.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher's plan to end Government ownership of Britain's electrical power system is emerging as a major test of public satisfaction with her policy of privatization.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher's plan to end Government ownership of Britain's electrical power system is emerging as a major test of public satisfaction with her policy of privatization.</p>
        <p>Energy Secretary Cecil Parkinson opened a campaign Thursday to let private investors buy control of Britain's electricity industry, which has $47.5 billion in assets and 147,000 employees. Debate in the House of Commons will open March 9, and the Government is expected to offer legislation in November or December.</p>
        <p>Both critics and supporters of this privatization project, the biggest yet for Mrs. Thatcher, were warning Friday that the public would not stand for the kind of transfer of ownership that occurred with two other utilities - British Telecom and British Gas.</p>
        <p>Many analysts said privatization merely changed British Gas and British Telecom from unresponsive public monopolies with captive markets to unresponsive private corporations with captive markets. There have been complaints of declining telephone service, and critics say Mrs. Thatcher erred by trying to fix something that was not broken. Effect on the Consumers</p>
        <p>In a clear acknowledgement of this criticism, Mr. Parkinson stressed that his plan for the electrial service would ''put the consumer in the driver's seat'' by increasing competition between electricity suppliers and by authorizing financial rebates to customers who receive poor service.</p>
        <p>Chinto Veljanovski, author of ''Selling the State,'' a leading work on privatization, said Mr. Parkinson's approach was a response to the backlash over the Government's handling of the gas and telephone utilities.</p>
        <p>Economists and consumer advocates cautiously endorsed the plan Friday. Mr. Parkinson ''made a promise that we would not get another British Gas or Britsh Telecom, and that has to be applauded,'' said Jenny Kirkpatrick, director of the Electricity Consumers Council.</p>
        <p>The heart of the Parkinson plan calls for breaking up the monolithic Central Electricity Generating Board into two major generating companies and to take control of the national grid of transmission facilities away from it. Under the plan, the power grid would be owned by 12 regional power companies. Power-Generating Rights</p>
        <p>These companies would also have the right to generate their own electric power if the two new major generating companies failed to provide electricity at competitive prices.</p>
        <p>Graham Mather, director of the Institute of Economic Affairs, said the idea of giving power-generating rights to the 12 regional companies was ''ingenious and imaginative.''</p>
        <p>''It has the hallmark of success about it,'' he said, adding that the move would provide the competitive element missing in the British Gas privatization.</p>
        <p>Also, he said, Mr. Parkinson's plan for rebates to dissatisfied customers would prevent the lax service that has been attributed to British Telecom since it went private.</p>
        <p>''If Telecom doesn't connect you for 12 weeks, there is nothing you can do about it; that won't be the case for electricity,'' Mr. Mather said, predicting that the Thatcher Government might also turn to rebates to put pressure on other utilities to improve their service.</p>
        <p>Although public complaints do not yet pose a direct threat to the continuation of Mrs. Thatcher's program of privatization, they have dimmed its luster somewhat. So the electricity plan is a major test for both Mrs. Thatcher and Mr. Parkinson. Return to Political Arena</p>
        <p>It is the first major assignment in his political comeback, which began when he rejoined the Cabinet last summer. In 1983 he was forced to resign as Conservative Party chairman after fathering a child by his unmarried secretary.</p>
        <p>British Telecom, valued at $4.5 billion, went private in 1984. British Gas, valued at $12.7 billion, did so in 1986.</p>
        <p>Analysts noted that Mr. Parkinson's decision to allow one of the new generating companies to take 70 percent of the electricity board's assets was dictated by Mrs. Thatcher's commitment to nuclear power plants. Only a big company could continue operating the financially troubled nuclear plants and still appeal to stock-market investors, they said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Parkinson said he would require the 12 regional companies to buy about 20 percent of their electricity from the nuclear plants. The Thatcher Government believes that for reasons of national security Britain should not depend totally on fossil fuels for generating electricity.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Parkinson was being praised in some quarters for balancing a complex set of political and economic factors, the opposition Labor Party furiously denounced the plan. Charges of a Tax Scheme</p>
        <p>John Prescott, the shadow Energy Secretary who would be the real Secretary if his party came into power, said the huge selloff of public assets was intended to raise revenues to finance a tax cut for the wealthy.</p>
        <p>He also said that the errors of British Telecom and British Gas would be repeated by allowing a shift from a reliable public utility to a set of privileged private companies that would be indifferent to public needs.</p>
        <p>''It's called oligopoly,'' Mr. Prescott said. ''It's called control. It's not called competition.'' He said the next Labor administration would renationalize electrical service.</p>
        <p>''We want to keep it in public control and public ownership,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
