<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WHAT 3 WHALES DID TO THE HUMAN HEART</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="195272"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WHALES AND WHALING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIVESTOCK</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRUELTY TO ANIMALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARCTIC OCEAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Whales and Whaling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cruelty to Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DB143FF935A35752C1A96E948260" item-length="854" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WHAT 3 WHALES DID TO THE HUMAN HEART</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The recent operation to save three gray whales trapped in the frozen waters of the Arctic Ocean produced some highly unlikely heroes. Eskimo whale hunters chopped breathing holes in the ice. Oil companies, often accused of degrading the whales' habitat with offshore drilling, rushed in heavy equipment to clear a passage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The recent operation to save three gray whales trapped in the frozen waters of the Arctic Ocean produced some highly unlikely heroes. Eskimo whale hunters chopped breathing holes in the ice. Oil companies, often accused of degrading the whales' habitat with offshore drilling, rushed in heavy equipment to clear a passage.</p>
        <p>The recent operation to save three gray whales trapped in the frozen waters of the Arctic Ocean produced some highly unlikely heroes. Eskimo whale hunters chopped breathing holes in the ice. Oil companies, often accused of degrading the whales' habitat with offshore drilling, rushed in heavy equipment to clear a passage. And the Soviet Union, one of the last nations to drop large-scale whaling, dispatched the icebreaker that finally freed the animals.</p>
        <p>By the time the two surviving whales swam away last weekend -the third had disappeared and is believed to have died - more than $1 million had been spent to save them, by most estimates, and they had the sympathy of millions of people around the world.</p>
        <p>Yet a week or so earlier, when the Japanese announced plans to kill 300 minke whales this winter as part of what they described as a research program, there was scarcely a ripple of reaction in the United States or elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Why, in the face of all the ills that befall living things, should three luckless whales cause such a paroxysm of public concern?</p>
        <p>One answer is that television could, and did, translate an abstraction into an immediate reality.</p>
        <p>''People actually saw the whales sticking their heads out of a hole in the ice and crying for help,'' said Neville Williams, a spokesman for Greenpeace, the conservation group. ''Here was something that people could do and feel good about.''  Still Endangered</p>
        <p>While the gray whale is still on the Government's list of endangered species, its numbers have more than doubled over the past few decades, to about 20,000. So there was no concern that three of them would make a difference. But Craig Van Note, executive director of Monitor, a coalition of animal protection groups, said that the gray whales remain extremely vulnerable because of planned oil and gas development in their breeding area along the Pacific Coast of Mexico and summer feeding grounds off Alaska.</p>
        <p>Mr. Van Note also said most Americans do not pay much attention to endangered species except those they see on television, although he added that that is changing, particularly among younger people.</p>
        <p>Christine Stevens, president of the Animal Welfare Institute, a Washington-based advocacy group, said: ''These gray whales pop up on television. They are friendly, adorable, enormous and they need our help. There is a nice side to human nature that responds to this.''</p>
        <p>But, she added, a ''lazy side'' to human nature doesn't want to take the trouble to think about broader problems like Japanese whaling or the treatment of animals generally. Take pigs, for example.  ''Pigs,'' she insisted, ''are lovely, very interesting and intelligent animals. But they don't get any attention at all. They have the most hideous life. They are shut up in pens so small they can't even move for most of their lives. And then people eat them. It's pretty nauseating when you think about it.''</p>
        <p>The same sort of misery is inflicted on other domestic animals such as calves and chickens, said Ms. Stevens, who said she hoped that the United States would legislate more humane treatment for farm animals, as Sweden has done.  Concern, at Least</p>
        <p>Some people looked for deeper significance in the public response to the gray whales. Michael W. Fox, vice president for bioethics and director of the Center for Respect of Life and Environment of the Humane Society of the United States, said: ''The optimist in me says that this whale incident shows that a sense of humanity still is evident in our species and that there is increasing concern globally for the plight of the animal kingdom, whose fate is now inseparably connected to ours. The optimist in me also says that the international cooperation shown in trying to save the whales is an indication that we can cooperate on issues like global warming.</p>
        <p>''But the pessimist in me says that this is just a sentimental identification, not with the whales but their helplessness. What is needed is an identification with whales and with all creatures that is not sentimental but is based upon a much deeper respect and reverence for life. We need to make the connection that when we destroy the environment of whales and other animals with our lifestyles and our industries, we are destroying our own environment as well.''</p>
        <p>Robert Jay Lifton, professor of psychiatry and psychology at John Jay College in Manhattan, said he had the impression that ''the whales had come to symbolize survival.''</p>
        <p>''It was a kind of focused struggle that one could win,'' he said, ''and the survival of the whales became a broader affirmation of something we all could experience. When we see the homeless or beggars on the street and we walk by them, we experience discomfort, anxiety, a little bit of guilt. We can worry about the whales but it is a problem that doesn't directly affect or threaten us.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Lifton, who has written about responses to the Holocaust, said that ''many people have been struck by the dichotomy between the enormous emotion shown over the whales and the callousness with which we regard suffering in our society.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
