<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NASA Rules Out a Rescue Of Satellite Falling to Earth</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="207228"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTICS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SOLAR MAXIMUM MISSION (SATELLITE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4D8153CF934A25751C1A96E948260" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NASA Rules Out a Rescue Of Satellite Falling to Earth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The National Aeronautics and Space Administration has decided to abandon a 5,000-pound scientific satellite that is rapidly losing altitude. The decision means that debris from the satellite will crash to Earth sometime in 1990.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The National Aeronautics and Space Administration has decided to abandon a 5,000-pound scientific satellite that is rapidly losing altitude. The decision means that debris from the satellite will crash to Earth sometime in 1990.</p>
        <p>The National Aeronautics and Space Administration has decided to abandon a 5,000-pound scientific satellite that is rapidly losing altitude. The decision means that debris from the satellite will crash to Earth sometime in 1990.</p>
        <p>Dr. Leonard Fisk, the agency's associate administrator for space sciences and applications, said in a telephone interview that the Solar Maximum Mission satellite could be rescued only by mounting a special space shuttle mission, and that the approximately 10 missions planned from now until June 1990 were fully committed to other projects.</p>
        <p>Space scientists assailed the decision, contending the satellite was too valuable to abandon. Senator Timothy E. Wirth, Democrat of Colorado, informed of the decision by telephone yesterday, said he was appalled.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wirth, a member of the Energy and Natural Resources Committee as well as the Armed Services Committee, has advocated saving the satellite because it continues to deepen understanding of the processes in the Sun that may affect Earth's climate. Mission of Satellite</p>
        <p>The satellite was placed in a low orbit from which it has slowly and inevitably been descending. The chief plan for saving the satellite involved retrieving it aboard a space shuttle and carrying it to higher altitude for release again.</p>
        <p>The satellite, launched Feb. 14, 1980, measures fluctuations in solar radiation, the structure of the Sun's corona, distortions of the Sun's magnetic field and many other solar features. Scientists believe that the 11-year cycle of solar activity the satellite was launched to study affects the depletion of ozone that caused a severe hole in the ozone layer over Antarctica last year. The stratospheric ozone layer is Earth's most effective shield against dangerous ultraviolet radiation from the Sun that is known to cause cancer.</p>
        <p>The satellite has also provided some scientific bonuses. The satellite's television camera aimed at the Sun is equipped with a disk that obscures the Sun itself, permitting observation of the glowing coronal gases outside the Sun. By studying images recorded by this camera, scientists have discovered a cluster of ''sun grazing'' comets that apparently approached the Sun too closely and were drawn in to destruction.</p>
        <p>The latest such discovery was reported only yesterday by Dr. Christopher St. Cyr, an operations scientist at NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center, in Greenbelt, Md. Dr. St. Cyr said the comet, which evidently crashed into the Sun on Oct. 24, was the seventh such cometary disaster witnessed by the satellite since 1984. The discovery was made in the past few days as data from the satellite were analyzed. Data on Exploding Star</p>
        <p>The satellite also gave scientists valuable observations of the supernova that flared over the Southern Hemisphere in 1987, the closest such explosion of a star in four centurios.</p>
        <p>Dr. St. Cyr said he considered the abandonment of the satellite a serious loss to science, particularly since the Sun is now rapidly approaching its cyclic maximum of activity.</p>
        <p>''We had really hoped that money could be found to refurbish its instruments and reboost it to a higher orbit,'' he said, ''but the decision seems to have been in favor of other things,'' including the intelligence satellites, or ''black boxes some people want sent up.''</p>
        <p>The satellite was resuscitated once before, in 1984, by the ill-fated space shuttle Challenger. That rescue operation was considered a landmark for shuttle operations.</p>
        <p>Scientists estimate that the cost of raising the satellite from its current altitude of 254 nautical miles to a higher orbit from which it would not spiral rapidly into the atmosphere would be about $28 million.</p>
        <p>''But you have to consider that reboosting the S.M.M. would be only part of the cost the project would entail,'' Dr. Fisk said. ''It would also mean bumping some other scientific mission, possibly even the space telescope, and the cost of such a delay would have to be added in. We decided that since the S.M.M. is nearing the end of its planned working life, other projects have higher priority.''</p>
        <p>No one can predict exactly when the big satellite will re-enter the atmosphere and disintegrate in a meteor-like fireball. Its end will be hastened by the approach of the solar maximum, which heats Earth's upper atmosphere and moves atmospheric gases into the satellite's path. But scientists guess that the satellite will crash some time before June 1990.</p>
        <p>Most of the big space vehicle would burn up as it re-enters the atmosphere, but according to Dr. St. Cyr, some large components are made of titanium and would withstand the re-entry furnace. The chances of any of the surviving debris causing damage or injury on the ground are extremely remote but not impossible, he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. St. Cyr said the loss would be particularly regrettable in light of an Air Force decision to use another solar observation satellite, the P78-1, for target practice. This satellite, deemed by Government agencies to have outlived its usefulness, was destroyed by an experimental antisatellite weapon in Sept. 13, 1985.</p>
        <p>Senator Wirth said he believed until yesterday that there was still a chance that a rescue mission for the satellite could be mounted. ''I'm particularly concerned that this decision will affect the scientific observation of the ozone layer,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Fisk said: ''It was an easy decision for NASA to make. It was just a matter of priorities. It will be a shame to lose the S.M.M., but too many other things take precedence.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
