<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>POST-REAGAN ERA PAINTED IN BUDGET</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Front Page; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="118286"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEAR, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7D91138F931A25751C0A96E948260" item-length="1534" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>POST-REAGAN ERA PAINTED IN BUDGET</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PEAR, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President Reagan's new budget lays down a comprehensive blueprint for Federal policies in the post-Reagan era, including increased spending on education and science and a dramatic expansion of his campaign for the private sector to take over Government functions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President Reagan's new budget lays down a comprehensive blueprint for Federal policies in the post-Reagan era, including increased spending on education and science and a dramatic expansion of his campaign for the private sector to take over Government functions.</p>
        <p>President Reagan's new budget lays down a comprehensive blueprint for Federal policies in the post-Reagan era, including increased spending on education and science and a dramatic expansion of his campaign for the private sector to take over Government functions.</p>
        <p>For example, he wants private industry or other organizations to assume much of the Government's responsibility for the housing of military personnel, the mediation of tax disputes and the management of undeveloped Federal lands.</p>
        <p>Confidential galley proofs of the Budget Message, scheduled for submission to Congress next Thursday, show the President's proposals for the fiscal year 1989. The fiscal year begins Oct. 1, about four months before Mr. Reagan is to turn over the White House to the next President. Adheres to Deficit Accord</p>
        <p>In one sense, Mr. Reagan's new budget is more realistic than some of his previous budgets because it adheres to a bipartisan agreement for reducing the deficit that was negotiated with Congress last November. But he may have difficulty persuading Congress to accept the details; his political power has eroded because he is serving his last year in office and Democrats control both houses of Congress.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reagan expresses both candor and irritation at this in the Budget Message, saying that ''the budget process has so degenerated in recent years that the Presidential budget is routinely discarded'' by Congress.</p>
        <p>The budget calls for spending of $1.1 trillion in 1989 and envisions a deficit of $129.5 billion, down from $150.4 billion in the 1987 fiscal year. The President projects a deficit $146.7 billion in the current fiscal year. The Congressional Budget Office, using less optimistic economic assumptions, projects larger deficits. More for Air Traffic Control</p>
        <p>The deficit Mr. Reagan projects in 1989 is under the ceiling set by law, but in later years the deficit ceilings would be exceeded. ''This budget does not fully reflect my personal priorities,'' Mr. Reagan says, noting the constraints of the agreement with Congress.</p>
        <p>To upgrade the nation's air traffic control system, he proposes to spend $1.6 billion in 1989, an increase of 44 percent over the level for this year.</p>
        <p>In an effort to revitalize the nation's ailing space program, Mr. Reagan requests $11.3 billion, an increase of 25 percent, Mr. Reagan says.</p>
        <p>''To attack the scourge of AIDS,'' he says, ''I propose $2 billion for additional research, education and treatment in 1989 - a 38 percent increase over the 1988 level and more than double the Federal Government's effort in 1987.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reagan also requests $363 million in 1989 to begin construction of a $4.4 billion atom smasher, the Superconducting Super Collider, which he describes as ''the largest pure science project ever undertaken.''</p>
        <p>He describes education and training programs as ''one of our highest priorities.'' For 1989, he says, ''I propose an increase of $650 million over the $16.2 billion appropriated for 1988 for discretionary programs of the Department of Education.'' In 1982 Mr. Reagan proposed abolishing the department, then spending roughly $15 billion a year. Cuts on Farm Supports</p>
        <p>Mr. Reagan says he will ask Congress to cut back Federal programs that prop up commodity prices and protect the income of farmers. He says he will propose changes in the sugar price support program because it ''poses significant problems in the areas of trade policy and foreign policy.''</p>
        <p>Agriculture Department officials said the Government guaranteed farmers 18 cents for every pound of raw cane sugar even though the price on world markets was about 8 cents a pound.</p>
        <p>In his Budget Message, Mr. Reagan calls for the elimination of nine domestic programs he says are no longer needed. ''This is the case with the rural housing insurance fund, the Economic Development Administration, urban mass transit discretionary grants, Urban Development Action Grants, sewage treatment, Small Business Administration direct loans, housing development action grants, the housing rehabilitation loan program and economic development programs of the Tennessee Valley Authority,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reagan does not say how much money that would save, and he notes he has made similar proposals in the past with only limited success.</p>
        <p>Returning to a favorite theme, Mr. Reagan says, ''The Federal Government should depend more on the private sector to provide ancillary and support services for activities that remain in Federal hands.'' Therefore, he says, ''I am proposing the development of a private mediating institution to reduce the backlog of cases before the United States Tax Court.'' Managing Federal Land</p>
        <p>''I also propose the complete privatization of waste water treatment plant construction, defense employee housing, certain mass transit projects'' and other Federal programs, he says. Local authorities would be expected to finance sewage treatment plants by charging additional fees, he says.</p>
        <p>A new proposal in the President's 1989 budget would give private organizations an opportunity to help manage undeveloped Federal lands. The details have not been worked out. Under one idea, budget officials said, environmental and conservation groups, state and local agencies, energy companies and farmers could bid for the opportunity to manage grazing lands, forests, deserts and other public lands.</p>
        <p>At another point, Mr. Reagan says, ''I am proposing the sale not only of the Naval Petroleum Reserves, but also the Alaska Power Administration, the Federal Government's helium program,'' surplus Federal property and other Federal assets, including $5 billion of Government loans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reagan says he plans to ''study possible privatization of our uranium enrichment facilities, as well as ways of making the U.S. Postal Service more efficient through greater reliance on the private sector.'' The Budget Message does not give details on these proposals.</p>
        <p>Assessment of Contractors He says he would also take steps to increase the role of private enterprise in the operation of military commissaries and Federal prison factories, as well as in the maintenance of Coast Guard buoys.</p>
        <p>He plans to assess the feasibility of hiring private contractors to do work now performed by 40,000 Federal employees. He does not specify the type of work but says private contractors might provide better service at lower cost.</p>
        <p>Here are other highlights of Mr. Reagan's Budget Message:</p>
        <p>* For law enforcement directed at white-collar crime, organized crime and terrorism, he requests $4.5 billion, an increase of 6 percent over 1988.</p>
        <p>* to combat drug abuse, he seeks $3.9 billion in 1989 for prevention, treatment and enforcement programs. He says that is an increase of 13 percent.</p>
        <p>* The Internal Revenue Service, which has a budget of $5.1 billion this year, would get $241 million more next year. Mr. Reagan says the additional funds should increase tax collections by $3 billion in 1989.</p>
        <p>* Funds for construction and expansion of Federal prisons would more than double, to $437 million in 1989, from $202 million this year.</p>
        <p>* The Government program to clean up hazardous waste sites, would get an increase of $430 million in 1989. It has a budget of $1.5 billion this year.</p>
        <p>* Mr. Reagan requests $2.5 billion, to be spent over several years, for development of new technology to combat acid rain, which is caused by emissions of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxides from coal-fueled power plants and motor vehicles. 'Kept My Side of the Bargain'</p>
        <p>The space agency budget includes funds for a permanently manned space station and for the space shuttle, as well as for a new unmanned spacecraft that would carry a special research telescope above the Earth's atmosphere. The new project is known as the advanced X-ray astronomical facility.</p>
        <p>He calls on Congress to appropriate the full amount specified in the deficit-reducing agreement for the military budget, $299.5 billion in 1989. ''I have kept my side of the bargain and trust that Congress will keep its side,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reagan boasts that he has presided over 63 consecutive months of economic growth, the longest peacetime expansion in American history. In the last five years, he says, 14.8 million new jobs have been created and the unemployment rate has fallen to 5.8 percent, ''the lowest level in nearly a decade.''</p>
        <p>For the first time in several years, he predicts, the Federal debt as a proportion of the nation's total output of goods and services will decline slightly next year from its current level of about 43 percent. REAGAN'S BUDGET: PROJECTING THE DEFICITS  In billions of dollars for fiscal years, beginning Oct. 1. The figures for 1987 are actual, all others are the Administration's estimates. Figures have been rounded.</p>
        <p>19 87</p>
        <p>1988</p>
        <p>1989</p>
        <p>1990</p>
        <p>1991</p>
        <p>1992</p>
        <p>1993</p>
        <p>Receipts</p>
        <p>854.1</p>
        <p>909.2</p>
        <p>964.7</p>
        <p>1,044.1</p>
        <p>1,124.4</p>
        <p>1,189.9</p>
        <p>1,258.1</p>
        <p>Outlays</p>
        <p>1,004.6</p>
        <p>1,055.9</p>
        <p>1,094.2</p>
        <p>1,148.3</p>
        <p>1,203.7</p>
        <p>1,241.0</p>
        <p>1,281. 3</p>
        <p>Deficit</p>
        <p>150.4</p>
        <p>146.7</p>
        <p>129.5</p>
        <p>104.2</p>
        <p>79.3</p>
        <p>51.1</p>
        <p>23.3</p>
        <p>*2*Deficit target under budget</p>
        <p>law</p>
        <p>144.0</p>
        <p>144.0</p>
        <p>136.0</p>
        <p>100.0</p>
        <p>64.0</p>
        <p>28.0</p>
        <p>0.0</p>
        <p>(Source: Office of Management and Budget)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
