<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="197802"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">SUMMARY</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1D9103EF930A25752C1A96E948260" item-length="1059" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL/3-23</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL/3-23</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL/3-23</p>
        <p>The Khmer Rouge guerrilla group is moving Cambodians out of refugee camps in Thailand, apparently as part of a plan to re-enter Cambodia and seize territory as Vietnam withdraws its troops. Page 1</p>
        <p>Human rights abuses in Guatemala, including kidnappings, torture and murder, have increased sharply in recent months, especially in rural areas where the central government's authority is weakest.  1</p>
        <p>China is turning to U.S. educators associated with the Carnegie Foundation in an effort to overhaul its university system with a view to using Western innovations including an education tax and tuitions.  1</p>
        <p>U.S. policy towards the P.L.O was discussed in Algiers. Yasir Arafat, chairman of the P.L.O., urged President-elect Bush to change American attitudes and adopt ''a new policy, not a policy aligned with Israel.'' 22</p>
        <p>The Palestine National Council, founded in 1964 as a consultative body for Palestinians, has become the highest legislative body for the 5.5 million Palestinians dispersed around the world.  22</p>
        <p>An English law limiting store hours on Sundays has been the subject of a battle that is heating up again, with feelings about private enterprise, class, religion and race all running high and becoming complicated.  16</p>
        <p>People are starving in Kapoeta, a town of devastation wrought by two years of fighting that is the largest prize to fall to the Sudan People's Liberation Army in the five-year civil conflict that is devouring the Sudan.  3</p>
        <p>Whites-only places in South Africa may be brought back to towns that the Conservatives captured in the municipal elections, alarming South Africa's ruling National Party as well as opponents of apartheid. 5</p>
        <p>Pro-Solidarity demonstrators rallied in 10 cities to mark the day 70 years ago when Poland re-emerged on the map of Europe after more than a century of partition. In some places, they clashed with the police. 17</p>
        <p>Gangs of Jamaicans in the U.S., called ''posses,'' are one of the most vicious criminal forces in America, law enforcement officials say. They are major traffickers of crack, cocaine and guns. 15</p>
        <p>Polls show split in Canadian vote  6</p>
        <p>Conference of 35 nations puts global warming in sharp focus  11</p>
        <p>NATIONAL/26-39, 50-56</p>
        <p>The move to curtail discount fares by the airline industry once again raises concern that deregulation may in the long run force passengers to pay higher fares than they would have when the industry was regulated.  1</p>
        <p>The doctrine of natural childbirth, which once called for no medical intervention whatsoever during normal labor and delivery, is increasingly being bent to accommodate the advances in understanding and controlling pain. 1</p>
        <p>The Westinghouse Electric Corp., which has been hired by the Government to save the nation's two biggest nuclear weapon factories, concedes that it has been guilty of some of the same managerial lapses there. 38</p>
        <p>The resignation of the Atlanta editor, Bill Kovach, from the Atlanta Journal and Constitution prompted 200 marchers to march through the streets in a mock, New Orleans-style funeral, mourning the ''death of a free press.'' 26</p>
        <p>If the atom smasher is built in Texas, the Energy Department said that the oval, 53-mile tunnel should be dug around Waxahachie. Local residents say the town of 18,000 people would be transformed in ways few can predict.  26</p>
        <p>Politics 30-33</p>
        <p>President-elect Bush's cabinet is shaping up in a way that promises broad influence for James A. Baker 3d, the newly appointed Secretary of State, across many aspects of domestic, economic and foreign policy. 1</p>
        <p>The election marked major shifts in American political life: The ''Solid South'' is now Republican, racial polarization has been confirmed and some of the political changes wrought by the electoral history may prove fragile. 32</p>
        <p>Only half of those eligible voted in the Presidential election and even simplified registration procedures in many states did not make a difference, the Committee for the Study of the American Electorate reported. 32</p>
        <p>Mayor Koch's view of his chances of winning a fourth term came as attention in New York City shifted from Presidential to mayoral politics, spurred by a poll indicating that Mr. Koch's popularity continues to flag.  32</p>
        <p>Gun control backers say victory will spread to other states  30</p>
        <p>Some New Yorkers might be in Bush Administration  33</p>
        <p>REGIONAL/40-48, 57-61</p>
        <p>The art of Hispanic teen-agers in the South Bronx done under the rubric of ''Tim Rollins + K.O.S.'' - have not gone unnoticed in the international art world. Their painting-collages are based on literary classics.  1</p>
        <p>World's Fair buffs met in Flushing at the World's Fair Reunion Day where critics as well as idealists and sentimentalists came to see films, souvenirs and relics of the 1939-40 and 1964-65 New York World's Fairs. 42</p>
        <p>Closing arguments in the Davis trial are to begin after 16 weeks of testimony by 73 witnesses. Larry Davis is accused of the attempted murder of nine police officers in a shootout in the Bronx in 1986.  48</p>
        <p>Turning a Hilton hotel into a shelter for the homeless, a proposal made by a Westchester County legislator, has prompted the Hilton Hotels Corporation to accuse the county of interfering with its efforts to sell the hotel.  43</p>
        <p>Animal-rights activists are split between the older ideas and methods of the movement's past and the often more militant approaches and goals adopted by newer groups, according to people involved in the rights campaign. 40</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
