<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="139442"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DC1038F936A15757C0A96E948260" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International A2-10  Chernobyl still has problems two years after an explosion and fire. The nuclear power station is riddled with negligence, and managers have ignored safety regulations, the Soviet newspaper Pravda charged. Page A1  Soviet economic change has failed so far to produce much growth or raise living standards, despite the ambitious programs of Mikhail S.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International A2-10  Chernobyl still has problems two years after an explosion and fire. The nuclear power station is riddled with negligence, and managers have ignored safety regulations, the Soviet newspaper Pravda charged. Page A1  Soviet economic change has failed so far to produce much growth or raise living standards, despite the ambitious programs of Mikhail S.</p>
        <p>International A2-10  Chernobyl still has problems two years after an explosion and fire. The nuclear power station is riddled with negligence, and managers have ignored safety regulations, the Soviet newspaper Pravda charged. Page A1  Soviet economic change has failed so far to produce much growth or raise living standards, despite the ambitious programs of Mikhail S. Gorbachev, according to a U.S. intelligence analysis. D1  A careful call for religious freedom in the Soviet Union was delivered by Secretary of State George P. Shultz, who attended a Mass at the Georgian Orthodox Cathedral in Tbilisi before leaving for Brussels. A7  Anti-missile systems using rockets instead of lasers are vulnerable to equipment and computer software failures that would make them unworkable, according to a Congressional research agency. A8  President Mitterrand took the lead over Prime Minister Jacques Chirac in the elimination round of France's presidential elections and appeared to be the front-runner in a run-off vote against Mr. Chirac on May 8. A1  Yasir Arafat arrived in Damascus in an a effort to achieve a reconcilliation with Syria after a five-year rift. The P.L.O. chairman is expected to meet President Hafez al-Assad for talks on the Middle East. A1  Israel reopened the West Bank and Gaza Strip for the first time in a week and ended the 24-hour curfews. Army officials said the steps were rewards for ''relative calm'' in the occupied territories. A3  A gold rush in Brazil's jungles has drawn at least 500,000 people into the country's wild interior, where, with primitive tools, they have made Brazil the world's fifth-largest gold producer. A10  South Vietnam's middle class all but disappeared after the war ended in 1975. While many Southeast Asians have risen to higher income levels in the last decade, many in Vietnam have sunk to the peasantry. A4  Prime Minister Brian Mulroney will push Washington for more cooperation on the problem of acid rain when the Canadian leader meets President Reagan and addresses a joint meeting of Congress on Wednesday. A10  Toll in Lebanese explosion is 66; Moslems blame Christians  A2  Consultation is pledged on gulf role A3  A restive island tribe adds to Noriega's woes A6  National A14-19, B6-7  An explosion and fire aboard the sub-marine U.S.S. Bonefish yesterday left 18 sailors injured, three in serious condition, and 3 of the 92-member crew missing, according to the Navy. A1  Acid rain's effects on the Atlantic coastal waters is greater than previously recognized, according to a report, and contributed to large, temporary die-offs of marine life along the northeastern coast. A1  Overcrowding in the nation's prisons is forcing officials to reassess sentencing practices. But despite the costs of building new prisons, a widespread fear of crime makes a dramatic shift in policies unlikely. A1  Academic performance remains low in American primary and secondary schools, according to Secretary of Education William J. Bennett, despite movements over the last five years to raise standards. A1  Resignations of top Justice officials have left no one at the Department to push several important legal initiatives sought by the Reagan Administration but have not affected day-to-day operations, officials say. A16  A $1.2 billion takeover offer for J. P. Stevens &amp; Company, among the biggest textile producers in the country, has been accepted from West Point-Pepperell Inc., a major competitor. D1  Years Later, 'R.F.K. Remembered' A14  Politics B6  Pennsylvania has voted contrary to national political trends, voting more Democratic than the rest of the nation in Presidential elections since 1952. But Republicans have done better in statewide races. B6  Vice President Bush is on the verge of winning enough delegates to secure the Republican Presidential nomination in Tuesday's Pennsylvania primary, a week earlier than had been expected. B6  Dukakis stumps on message of hope B6  Jackson challenges Dukakis's plans for domestic projects B6  Washington Talk A18  Air force and Marines battle 'ticket-punchers'  Regional B1-5  Mayor Koch's political opponents acknowledge that it will not be easy to take advantage of his weaknesses as they look ahead to challenging him in the Democratic mayoral primary that is 17 months away. A1  A middle-class migration to Harlem has taken place over the past decade as a small but growing number of well-educated blacks has moved there, hoping, in part, to spark a renaissance. B1  Graduates of the 1968 student strike at Columbia University returned for a reunion, and 20 years after occupying five buildings on the Morningside Heights campus, many still proclaim their political involvement. B1  Problems in the prosecution's case will prevent the conviction of two men accused of murdering a New York City police detective, predicted a Queens minister who served on the jury that deadlocked in the case. B2  Public services in New York City are not equal to what the public pays, according to a report by a citizens group. It rated refuse collection excellent, street cleaning poor and other services passable. B3  Legislation to help single mothers move off welfare and find jobs, now in Congress, will provide some new funds but is unlikely to produce dramatic changes in New York City's welfare programs, officials say. B3  Metro Matters: Long Island grappling with growth B1  Orthodox Jewish psychotherapists and their conflicts B2  Love of guns and applause for Goetz B3</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
