<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reagan, in Switch, Agrees to a Plan on Acid Rain</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="168578"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NITROGEN OXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEARY, WARREN E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1D91339F934A3575BC0A96E948260" item-length="1047" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reagan, in Switch, Agrees to a Plan on Acid Rain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEARY, WARREN E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President Reagan has agreed to freeze emission levels of nitrogen oxide, an important air pollutant, for at least the next seven years. The action will allow the United States to join in a major international treaty to reduce acid rain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President Reagan has agreed to freeze emission levels of nitrogen oxide, an important air pollutant, for at least the next seven years. The action will allow the United States to join in a major international treaty to reduce acid rain.</p>
        <p>President Reagan has agreed to freeze emission levels of nitrogen oxide, an important air pollutant, for at least the next seven years. The action will allow the United States to join in a major international treaty to reduce acid rain.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said the President on Friday agreed to freeze emissions of nitrogen oxide at 1987 levels. The agreement, which was not formally announced, clears the way for the United States to take part in negotiations involving Canada, the Soviet Union and countries in Eastern and Western Europe.</p>
        <p>Environmental policy experts said the decision represents a policy reversal for the Administration, which in 1985 declined to take part in a similar protocol, endorsed by 16 nations, to cut emissions of sulfur dioxide, another major component of acid rain.</p>
        <p>The shift in policy is unlikely to have an immediate practical effect. According to projections by the Environmental Protection Agency, nitrogen oxide emissions were expected to fall steadily until the early 1990's because of previous pollution control efforts. In subsequent years, however, a rise was anticipated, reflecting industrial expansion and population growth.</p>
        <p>''The President has authorized the State Department to continue negotiations aimed at insuring U.S. participation in the protocol,'' said a White House official who requested anonymity.</p>
        <p>The issue has been under study by senior Administration officials and was presented to the President last week at a domestic policy council meeting, a White House spokesman said. He said the President did not make a decision at that meeting but agreed to go ahead on Friday at the urging of the E.P.A. Administrator, Lee M. Thomas.</p>
        <p>A White House official confirmed a report today in The Washington Post that Mr. Reagan has also agreed to other major provisions of a draft protocol proposed in Geneva in April by the Economic Commission for Europe, a United Nations group made up of the industrial nations of Europe, the United States and Canada. The official said negotiations would now continue, and Administration officials expect the treaty to be signed in October.</p>
        <p>At negotiations on the protocol in Geneva, Canada proposed a clause that would limit the amount nitrogen oxide pollution permitted to cross its border from the United States. The Canadian Government says more than 700,000 of its lakes have become acidified, and its forests, structures and even the haelth of its citizens are being damaged by acid rain, more than 50 percent of which Canada contends comes from the United States.</p>
        <p>But the United States maintained that it had already taken steps that put it ahead of the rest of the world in reducing nitrogen oxide from motor vehicles and other sources, and argued that it should not be required to restrain such pollution until the other industrial nations catch up.</p>
        <p>Like similar international conventions, the proposed protocol does not have an enforcement mechanism other than the pressure of international opinion, experts said. After freezing nitrogen oxide levels for seven years, the protocol would require signatories to convene in 1996 to negotiate further cutbacks.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. estimates 1987 nitrogen oxide emission levels in the United States at about 19 million tons, based on air samplings and mathematical projections. This figure represents a decline from previous years because of pollution controls on power plants and the use of catalytic converters on automobiles.</p>
        <p>Don Clay, an acting assistant administrator of the E.P.A., said the protocol would not mean an immediate change in how the United States controls pollution. ''We have already made a big nitogen oxide reduction because of cleaner cars and it is going to continue on a downward trend according to our projection until about 1995,'' he said. Called Election-Year Politics</p>
        <p>Representatives of environmental groups noted that Mr. Reagan's change in position, coming in an election year, could have an effect in the Northeast, where acid rain is a sensitive political issue.</p>
        <p>''With elections less than three months away, it is not a surprise,'' said Lester R. Brown, president of Worldwatch, an environmental study group in Washington. ''The public concern with environmental issues is rising. Acid rain, drought, and the possible change in climatic conditions - all these issues are escalating in public consciousness.''</p>
        <p>Joseph Goffman, a lawyer with the Environmental Defense Fund, a nonprofit group in Washington, described his group's reaction to Mr. Reagan's action as mixed.</p>
        <p>''In order to solve the acid rain problem that both U.S. and Canada suffer from, we need major cutbacks, not just a freeze,'' Mr. Goffman said. ''In terms of acid rain, it is a neutral step at best. We need substantial cutbacks. People shouldn't expect to wake up the day after the protocol is signed and find the acid rain problem solved.''</p>
        <p>Acid rain is air pollution, largely sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide from coal-burning power and industrial plants as well as from motor vehicle engines, that changes in the atmosphere and falls to earth as acidic rain, snow, fog or dry particles. Effects of Acid Rain</p>
        <p>Scientists generally agree that acid rain destroys plant and animal life in sensitive lakes and streams, and some scientists believe it also damages forests and man-made structures like buildings made of metal and stone. The effects of this pollution on human health is uncertain.</p>
        <p>Richard Mott of the Environmental Law Institute, who is an expert on the proposed protocol on nitrogen oxide, said most of the work on the agreement is completed and the United States participation should assure that the treaty is signed this fall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mott and other environmental specialists noted that some nitrogen oxides like carbon dioxide from burning fossil fuel contribute to the global warming that many scientists believe is now occurring.</p>
        <p>Therefore, a treaty affecting nitrogen oxide would be the second to indirectly address global warming, and could pave the way for more specific treaties, Mr. Mott said. The first such protocol was signed in Montreal last year by 37 nations to limit production and use of chlorofluorocarbons, chemicals that destroy the protective ozone layer of the atmosphere.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
