<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.P.A. Critic Enters the Lion's Den And Is Showered by Wild Applause</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="109634"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="WASHINGTON TALK: ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COMMONER, BARRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5D6113EF936A25752C0A96E948260" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.P.A. Critic Enters the Lion's Den And Is Showered by Wild Applause</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: It was as if the Christians led into the Colosseum for slaughter had suddenly turned on the Roman mob, or like Daniel's attacking the lions in the den.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: It was as if the Christians led into the Colosseum for slaughter had suddenly turned on the Roman mob, or like Daniel's attacking the lions in the den.</p>
        <p>It was as if the Christians led into the Colosseum for slaughter had suddenly turned on the Roman mob, or like Daniel's attacking the lions in the den.</p>
        <p>Barry Commoner, the environmental scientist, spoke by invitation to an S.R.O. crowd of Environmental Protection Agency employees earlier this week and treated them to a fairly savage critique of their efforts to protect the nation's health from pollution.</p>
        <p>Dr. Commoner, who rarely has a good word to say for the E.P.A., or for Government regulators in general, had none at all in his speech. He told his stony-faced audience that the agency practiced bad science and bad policy and was failing to protect the environment. Waiting for the Thunderbolt</p>
        <p>He even dared use, in proposing a solution for the nation's pollution problems, what he called ''the S-word: socialism.'' Then he paused to look heavenward, waiting, he said, ''for the thunderbolt to strike me.''</p>
        <p>Instead, at the end of his speech, he received thunderous applause from the audience he had so unsparingly criticized.</p>
        <p>Dr. Commoner is the director for the Center for the Biology of Natural Systems at Queens College of the City University of New York. He is also a widely read author on ecological issues, and a self-described radical who, in 1980 ran for President as the candidate of the Citizens Party. Stance on Dioxin Assailed</p>
        <p>He is a relentless critic of the environmental agency's policies and procedures, most recently assailing a decision to lower its estimate of the risks of dioxin, the highly toxic chemical byproduct.</p>
        <p>His speech was part of a continuing series of seminars held by the agency's office of toxic substances and its air and radiation program. But staff members who attended this one said they had not previously been subjected to the kind of verbal assault administered by Dr. Commoner on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Dr. Commoner said the basic problem with the E.P.A.'s approach to pollution was that it was trying to clean up the environment piecemeal after it had already been severely degraded. Such a task, he said was, virtually impossible. This, he added, was as much the fault of the environmental laws as of the way they are administered by the environmental agency. An 'Acceptable Level of Harm'</p>
        <p>The answer, he said, was to stop pollution before it is produced by ending ''the taboo against social intervention in the production system.'' The environment will not be protected, he insisted, by the current practice of finding an ''acceptable level of harm'' from an environmental pollutant and then issuing rules allowing industry to pollute to that level.</p>
        <p>Instead, he said, the rational way to protect the environment and public health is to prevent pollution from entering the environment in the first place. He asserted that it was technologically and economically feasible to build cars and power plants, to produce food and to use chemicals in ways that would not harm the environment.</p>
        <p>Remedying the nation's ''environmental failure,'' he said, would ''require the courage to challenge the taboo against even questioning the present dominance of private interest over the public interest.'' Reaction of Audience</p>
        <p>Several members of the audience expressed some skepticism about Mr. Commoner's views. One suggested his approach to the environment would place limits on economic growth. Dr. Commoner vigorously denied holding such a view.</p>
        <p>Hugh Kaufman, a civil servant in the agency's toxic waste program who is a frequent critic of the agency's policies, said the reason Dr. Commoner was applauded by the E.P.A. staff after he attacked them was that ''they agreed with 80 to 90 percent of what he said.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Commoner began his talk by noting that after World War 11, new industrial technology and acclerated economic activity began creating new, widespread forms of pollution such as smog, acid rain, excessive nitrate and phosphates in water supplies from agricultural fertilizers, pesticides and toxic chemicals in the food chain and accumulations of radioactive waste. Undoing the Damage</p>
        <p>''Then, in 1970, pressed by a newly aroused public, Congress began a massive effort to undo the damage. Now, nearly 20 years later, the time has come to ask an important and perhaps embarrassing question: How far have we progressed toward the goal of restoring the quality of the environment.</p>
        <p>''The answer is, in fact, embarrassing. Apart from a few notable exceptions, environmental quality has improved only slightly and in some cases has become worse.''</p>
        <p>While the quantity of some pollutants in the environment, such as lead, DDT and polychlorinated biphenyls or PCB's, has gone down sharply, he noted, air and water quality has in most cases improved only slightly and other toxic substances continue to be poured into the environment.</p>
        <p>In the end, Dr. Commoner said, ''it will require good science and wise policies'' to clean up the environment.</p>
        <p>''But, I suggest that we know how to begin,'' he said, ''by an open public discussion of what has gone wrong and why.''  WASHINGTON TALK: ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
