<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOOD NOTES</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="125958"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880309T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFD81F3EF93AA35750C0A96E948260" item-length="873" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOOD NOTES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Florence Fabricant</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  Villa Iacocca</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  Villa Iacocca</p>
        <p>Villa Iacocca</p>
        <p>Lee Iacocca's extra-virgin olive oil and red-wine vinegar - labeled Villa Nicola, the name of his estate in Tuscany - are now being imported, but are available only in New York. Plans are being made, however, for wider distribution.</p>
        <p>The oil and vinegar are being made for Villa Nicola by producers in Tuscany. Mr. Iacocca said his 403 olive trees made enough oil for family and friends but not for commercial sale. ''The project started as a lark,'' he said, adding that he likes the idea of marketing these products.</p>
        <p>The oil is a fashionably intense green with a hint of yellow, and has a fruity aroma and the merest suggestion of acid bite in the aftertaste. The red Chianti vinegar provides a mellow complement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Iacocca, the chairman of the Chrysler Corporation, bought Villa Nicola in 1984.</p>
        <p>In coming months a new and upgraded line of red and white wines bearing the Villa Nicola label will be released. The first red table wine produced on the estate is no longer available in retail shops.</p>
        <p>The oil and vinegar are sold in quarter-liter (8 1/2 ounce) cruets boxed together as a gift set for $15 at Grace's Marketplace, 1237 Third Avenue (71st Street). The olive oil is sold there in liter cruets for $28, half liters for $16.  Nutrition Reminders</p>
        <p>In observance of March as National Nutrition Month, the Greater New York Dietetic Association has opened a telephone line offering recorded messages on nutrition. Through Friday the message is about registered dietitians. Other messages will be about cholesterol, Monday through March 18; weight loss and exercise, March 21-25, and diet and cancer, March 28-31. The number is 212-549-1170.</p>
        <p>This month, a dietitian representing the association will offer nutrition advice at the Food Emporium, 68th Street and Broadway, from noon to 2 P.M. on Tuesdays and Saturdays.</p>
        <p>For nutrition month at 16 Kings Super Markets in New Jersey, children may submit original posters on the theme ''I'm a Healthy Kid.'' The contest will be judged in two categories, first through third grade, and fourth through sixth. Winners will be selected for each store and a grand prize winner will be chosen from the first-place winners.</p>
        <p>Savings bonds, cooking utensils and children's cookbooks are the prizes. The deadline for entries is Monday.  Well-Traveled Cuisine</p>
        <p>This is a quiz. Match the New York restaurant with the city (or cities) in which it has a branch or franchise. The answers are in the box below.  1.Joe Allen  2.Canastel's  3.The Palm  4.Mezzaluna  5.Stage Delicatessen  6.Maxwell's Plum  7.J. G. Melon  8.Jams  A.Bridgehampton, L.I.  B.Los Angeles  C.London  D.San Francisco  E.Dallas, Miami, Houston, Los Angeles, Chicago, Washington, San Francisco and East Hampton, L.I.  F.Aspen, Colo.  G.Paris  H.Miami</p>
        <p>This dispersal reflects a trend toward cloning that has been developing for nearly 20 years. The most recent additions to the list are Canastel's and Mezzaluna, both of which opened about two months ago. In each case, the new restaurant is larger than the original.</p>
        <p>The new Mezzaluna has a decor just like the New York parent, including the artwork based on a half-moon theme commissioned from a group of Italian artists. Mezzaluna is a franchise, but most branch locations are under the same ownership as the New York original.  A Chili Farewell</p>
        <p>While it is the fashion to salute spring, the East Meadow Public Library on Long Island plans instead to bid farewell to winter, giving the Devil his due, on March 20. The farewell is a chili tasting and judging with bluegrass music.</p>
        <p>Anyone with a chili recipe that's up to public scrutiny can enter the contest. Register by Tuesday at the library, at Front Street and East Meadow Avenue in East Meadow, L.I.</p>
        <p>The prizes include gift certificates for dinners in restaurants. Entry to the contest and tickets to the event, which begins at 2:30 P.M., are free. A limited number of tickets are available; they are at the library. Call 516-794-2570 for more information.  The Answers  1.G, 2.H, 3.E, 4.F, 5.B, 6.D, 7.A, 8.C.  BUY OF THE WEEK  LETTUCE</p>
        <p>This is a good week to fill the salad bowl. Several varieties of lettuce are now reasonably priced, among them Boston and iceberg (69 to 89 cents a head) and romaine and red leaf (69 to 89 cents a pound).  The Tomato in Winter: Something New</p>
        <p>A TOMATO in winter was once best ignored. Palatable imports from Israel sell for around $2.99 a pound. Now some tomatoes from Florida have been improved.</p>
        <p>The best, Nature's Prime, are sprayed before picking with a natural soluble enzyme that hastens ripening. These are $1.59 a pound at D'Agostino and $1.29 a pound at Kings Super Markets in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>The Sunrise brand tomato, vine-ripened in Florida, is sold at Chelsea Foods, 198 Eighth Avenue (20th Street), for $2 a pound.</p>
        <p>The Tomahto, ranging from $1.49 to $1.99 a pound at Pathmark, Grand Union and A.&amp;P. markets, comes in a special package that seals in carbon dioxide and oxygen to ripen the tomato. Yet they are decidely underripe when sold.</p>
        <p>Keep tomatoes at room temperature until fully ripe, up to a week. Natural Pak Produced Inc.(Tomahto)Sunrise Tomatoesd Inc.(Sunrise)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
