<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hole in Arctic Ozone Is Feared</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="146165"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDD1339F93BA25756C0A96E948260" item-length="373" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hole in Arctic Ozone Is Feared</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE, May 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A Canadian researcher says that a hole in the ozone layer may be developing in the stratosphere near the North Pole each winter just as a similar hole is created over the South Pole.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A Canadian researcher says that a hole in the ozone layer may be developing in the stratosphere near the North Pole each winter just as a similar hole is created over the South Pole.</p>
        <p>A Canadian researcher says that a hole in the ozone layer may be developing in the stratosphere near the North Pole each winter just as a similar hole is created over the South Pole.</p>
        <p>The researcher, W. F. J. Evans, a scientist with the Department of Environment in Canada, said Monday that instruments carried aloft by balloons indicated that a vast crater of depleted ozone forms near the North Pole in the winter months and could act as a ''sink'' for ozone throughout the Northern Hemisphere.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans said that the hole was discovered through measurements made from research balloons released from a base at Alert, a Canadian town near the North Pole, in the first four months of each year, starting in 1986.</p>
        <p>The researcher, who gave a paper on his findings at the spring meeting here of the American Geophysical Union, said that the Antarctic ozone hole might be causing a decrease in the level of ozone protecting the whole Southern Hemisphere.</p>
        <p>''If there is a similar hole in the Arctic, it could influence the ozone in the Northern Hemisphere in the same way,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Atmospheric ozone forms a natural barrier against the ultraviolet rays of the sun. Overexposure to this type of radiation is associated with skin cancer. Satellite and aircraft studies have found an ozone hole that develops in cold months over the South Pole. The loss of atmospheric ozone has been attributed to chemical reactions initiated by chlorofluorocarbons, a type of chemical used as refrigerants and to make plastic foam.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans said that because of a difference in weather patterns, there is normally about 15 percent more ozone in the atmosphere over the Arctic than over the Antarctic. The Arctic ozone loss is much smaller, he said.</p>
        <p>''Even if the effect is smaller in the Northern Hemisphere, the effect is more important because that is where most of the people are,'' he said of ozone depletion. The Northern latitudes contain most of the land mass and the human population.</p>
        <p>R. R. Stolarski, an atmospheric scientist at the Goddard Space Center, said Mr. Evans findings were important, but added that more study needed to be done to make sure that the ozone hole Mr. Evans had found was not just a ''cold weather phenomenon.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
