<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Greenhouse Effect? Real Enough.</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="156036"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2DC1238F930A15755C0A96E948260" item-length="607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Greenhouse Effect? Real Enough.</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A fierce drought is shriveling crops from Texas to North Dakota and has shrunk the Mississippi to its lowest levels on record. Dry years are part of nature's cycle. Still, it's time to take seriously another possible influence - the warming of the atmosphere by waste gases from a century of industrial activity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A fierce drought is shriveling crops from Texas to North Dakota and has shrunk the Mississippi to its lowest levels on record. Dry years are part of nature's cycle. Still, it's time to take seriously another possible influence - the warming of the atmosphere by waste gases from a century of industrial activity.</p>
        <p>A fierce drought is shriveling crops from Texas to North Dakota and has shrunk the Mississippi to its lowest levels on record. Dry years are part of nature's cycle. Still, it's time to take seriously another possible influence - the warming of the atmosphere by waste gases from a century of industrial activity. Whether or not the feared greenhouse effect is real, there are several preventive measures worth taking in their own right.</p>
        <p>The greenhouse theory holds that certain waste gases let in sunlight but trap heat, which otherwise would escape into space. Carbon dioxide has been steadily building up through the burning of coal and oil - and because forests, which absorb the gas, are fast being destroyed. There is no clear proof that the gases have yet begun to warm the atmosphere. But there's circumstantial evidence, and some experts think it is getting stronger.</p>
        <p>For example, four of the last eight years - 1980, 1981, 1983 and 1987 - have been the warmest since measurements of global surface temperatures began a century ago, and 1988 may be another record hot year. Still, there have been hot spells before, followed by a cooling.</p>
        <p>According to computer simulations of the world's climate, there should be more rain in a greenhouse-heated globe. The rain falls in different places: more at the poles and the equator, less in the mid-latitudes. The drought in the Middle West falls in with these projections. But it stops far short of proving that the greenhouse effect has begun. ''As far as we can tell, this is a tough summer well within the normal range of variability,'' says Donald Gilman, the Weather Service's long-range forecaster.</p>
        <p>That's the nub of the problem: It's hard to identify a small, gradual sign of global warming amid wide natural fluctuations in climate. Even over the long term, the evidence is merely indicative. The world has warmed half a degree centigrade over the last century. But the warming is less than some computer models predict, forcing defenders of the greenhouse theory to argue that the extra heat is disappearing into the oceans.</p>
        <p>With the greenhouse effect still uncertain, why take preventive steps, especially since the main one, burning less coal, would be enormously expensive? One answer is that it it may take years to acquire positive proof of greenhouse-induced climate change, and the longer society waits, the larger a warming it will have to adapt to if the greenhouse theory turns out to be valid. Even a small warming could produce violent changes in climate. At worst, the Gulf Stream might shift course, failing to warm Europe. Sea level could rise 20 feet if the West Antarctic Ice Cap melts, flooding coastal cities from New York to New Orleans.</p>
        <p>Several measures to slow the greenhouse warming are worth taking for other reasons: Cut production of freons, chemicals used as solvents and refrigerants. Important greenhouse gases, they destroy the life-protecting ozone layer. Protect tropical forests, which not only absorb carbon dioxide but also nourish a rich variety of animal and plant life. Encourage conservation of energy and use of natural gas, which produces half as much carbon dioxide as does coal. Develop cheaper, safer nuclear power; nuclear plants produce no carbon dioxide or acid rain.</p>
        <p>Many climatologists expect that the greenhouse theory will eventually prove true, but fear to issue alarmist warnings ahead of time. Their caution is justified. But there's an ample case for taking these initial preventive measures when the cost of such insurance is so low and the discomforts of abrupt climate change, as the drought demonstrates, so high.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
