<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Accord on Oil Has Benefits, Analysts Say</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="202476"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">QUOTAS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ORGANIZATION OF PETROLEUM EXPORTING COUNTRIES (OPEC) (OPEC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Quotas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2DB123FF93AA15752C1A96E948260" item-length="1126" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Accord on Oil Has Benefits, Analysts Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Fifteen years after the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries convulsed world oil markets and quadrupled oil prices by sharply reducing its output, many oil analysts say that the United States has less to fear from a strong OPEC than from one in disarray.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Fifteen years after the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries convulsed world oil markets and quadrupled oil prices by sharply reducing its output, many oil analysts say that the United States has less to fear from a strong OPEC than from one in disarray.</p>
        <p>Fifteen years after the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries convulsed world oil markets and quadrupled oil prices by sharply reducing its output, many oil analysts say that the United States has less to fear from a strong OPEC than from one in disarray.</p>
        <p>While OPEC ministers reached an agreement in Vienna to reduce oil production in the hope of raising prices, consumers are likely to enjoy several more years of fairly steady prices for gasoline and heating oil, industry experts said.</p>
        <p>If OPEC can hold to the production accord outlined yesterday, it will raise oil prices modestly, they say. But it probably cannot manage a cut sharp enough to cause an oil shock like those in 1973 and 1979, because worldwide production capacity has grown so much. Indeed, a bigger threat, at least in the near term, is the instability inflicted on troubled American oil producers and oil-exporting countries by their competition: OPEC producers whose overproduction has driven down prices.</p>
        <p>''If OPEC falls apart, it wrecks Texas and it tears apart Venezuela,'' said Charles Maxwell, a senior strategist at C. J. Lawrence, Morgan Grenfell Inc. That means a widespread inability to repay debts, he said, ''at a time that we need another big series of debt defaults like we need a hole in the head.'' Meaning of $5-a-Barrel Oil</p>
        <p>An OPEC collapse would mean oil at $5 a barrel, less than half the current price, Mr. Maxwell and other experts said, and that could wipe out much of the American oil industry.</p>
        <p>To be sure, a collapse in oil prices would be greeted in some corners with cheers. ''If you have lower oil prices, it's going to give an economic boost,'' said Edwin S. Rothschild, an energy expert at the Citizen/Labor Energy Coalition. ''On the consumer side, if you're paying less for natural gas and oil, you have more money to save, or to buy other products, like a new car or a house.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Rothschild, whose organization is a coalition of 200 labor unions, retirees' organizations and citizens' groups with a combined enrollment of about 10 million, said some benefit would accrue to major oil companies, pointing out that despite the sharp drop in the price of the crude oil they buy, the price of the gasoline they sell has been stable. In addition, he said, he doubted prices would be allowed to fall to $5, because of the risk to the national economy.</p>
        <p>''It's one thing to have some distress in the oil industry,'' he said, speaking of the current depressed condition, with a market price in recent weeks of $14 a barrel for American oil. ''It's another to have a collapse that would take with it all the weak banks and percolate out to other banks and financial institutions, and make a serious economic problem.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rothschild said it was not immediately clear whether the benefits of $5 oil would outweigh the costs. Move to Stop Plunge Seen</p>
        <p>Mr. Rothschild and others argue that the Bush administration would probably move to prevent a collapse. The last time prices fell below $10, in 1986, Vice President Bush went to Saudi Arabia to confer with King Fahd, they noted.</p>
        <p>Oil prices in the current range serve other useful functions, some analysts said. ''If OPEC hadn't been put into motion we would have had to invent it,'' Mr. Maxwell said. ''It's the only thing that stops us from consuming ourselves silly, until we've run through all of our cheap energy resources stupidly.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Maxwell and others said that if the ''greenhouse effect,'' a global warming trend, is indeed caused by the use of fossil fuels, then the world will have to use less, a trend that higher prices will encourage. The Oil Industry's Goals</p>
        <p>The domestic oil industry, however, wants more than the status quo. ''We ought to fear the long-run consequences most,'' said Charles J. DiBona, president of the American Petroleum Institute, the industry's main trade association. ''We're focusing on whether OPEC gets an agreement, but we ought to be focusing on whether Alaskan oil is available when the current surplus disappears, which it will.''</p>
        <p>The institute is lobbying Congress for access to the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, which the oil industry thinks is the last great untapped reserve in the United States.</p>
        <p>The institute, the industry's main trade association, also favors tax incentives for new drilling and relief from some pollution rules. But Mr. DiBona said winning support for those steps is difficult because the next supply and price crisis ''is not happening tomorrow.'' Still a Heavy Dependence</p>
        <p>While some experts advise that it is time to, in effect, root for OPEC, they are not concluding that the United States is invulnerable to supply interruptions that the group might organize, or that might result from wars, revolutions or natural disasters. The United States still depends heavily on imported oil; it will supply 41.4 percent of consumption this year, up from 31.5 percent just three years ago and near the peak of 48 percent reached in 1977.</p>
        <p>What is more, petroleum is still the biggest part of the national energy diet, at 42.9 percent last year, down from 46.1 percent at the time of the first oil shock, in October 1973, and from 47.1 percent at the time of the second, in 1979.</p>
        <p>The economy has grown more energy efficient in the last 15 years -gross national product is up about one-third while energy consumption is up hardly at all. But, from the gasoline in the automobile tanks to the petrochemicals in a compact disk, the economy is still heavily based in petroleum.</p>
        <p>But the relationship between OPEC and imports is complex. Some oil analysts point to the irony that a collapse of OPEC would mean more imports and therefore more vulnerability to supply interruption, rather than less.</p>
        <p>The experts think that it will be years before OPEC can threaten supply cuts large enough to move prices sharply. World production capacity is now about 60 million barrels a day, about 10 million barrels more than demand, and as OPEC's recent negotiations demonstrate, it is hard to reach agreement to cut that much supply.</p>
        <p>In contrast, the 1979 oil shock involved the sidelining of six million barrels a day of capacity, or 60 percent of today's surplus. And OPEC did not actually engineer that shortage; it piggybacked on the disruption in supply caused by the Iranian revolution.</p>
        <p>''A number of countries saw their market opportunities then and took them,'' said Daniel Yergin, of Cambridge Energy Research Associates, a consulting group in Cambridge, Mass.</p>
        <p>Nor could OPEC re-create the 1973 situation, he said. ''On the eve of the first oil crisis, the world oil industry was operating at 99.5 percent of capacity,'' he said. ''Today, it's around 80 percent. That's the difference.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
