<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tiny Electronic 'Noses' Promise Speedy Sensing</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="204285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SENSORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENZYMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DYES AND DYESTUFFS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">POLLACK, ANDREW</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5D71E3AF935A35751C1A96E948260" item-length="1576" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tiny Electronic 'Noses' Promise Speedy Sensing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">POLLACK, ANDREW</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A NEW generation of sensors that combine chemical and biological materials with electronics is under development to detect diseases in the body, toxic materials in the environment and contaminants in industrial processes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A NEW generation of sensors that combine chemical and biological materials with electronics is under development to detect diseases in the body, toxic materials in the environment and contaminants in industrial processes.</p>
        <p>A NEW generation of sensors that combine chemical and biological materials with electronics is under development to detect diseases in the body, toxic materials in the environment and contaminants in industrial processes.</p>
        <p>The new devices use fluourescent dyes, chemicals, enzymes and even the antennae of crabs or slices of banana to detect toxins and other chemicals.</p>
        <p>Much of the work is still at the laboratory stage, but some new sensing devices are already on the market.</p>
        <p>The new advances follow frustrating setbacks that have slowed the development of some once-promising devices and that have made it difficult to implant sensors permanently in the body.</p>
        <p>The sensors under development generally consist of two parts. One, the recognition element, is a chemical, antibody, enzyme or even a living cell that reacts with or latches onto the material to be detected. The second part, the transducer, converts the recognition reaction into an electrical or optical signal that can be measured.</p>
        <p>The goal is a whole new category of sensors that could instantly measure things that now often require complex chemical analyses.</p>
        <p>If such sensors can be perfected, they promise to have broad uses in medicine and industry. Scientists are already at work on sensors to measure the concentration of chemicals and drugs in blood, both inside the body and out, and to quickly detect infections and diseases like AIDS. In industry, such ''electronic noses'' could monitor pollutants in ground water, sound an alarm at the release of toxic gas in a factory, monitor the production of chemicals and drugs and test for spoilage of foods.</p>
        <p>Sensors have long been available to give quick readings of physical variables, like pressure and temperature. But measuring chemicals and biological substances like hormones and micro-organisms has usually entailed a complex procedure, often with sophisticated equipment like gas chromatographs or mass spectrometers.</p>
        <p>A biosensor would give faster readings. ''These things will turn up all over the place to speed up testing,'' said Dean Hafeman, a research scientist at Molecular Devices Corporation, a small biosensor company in Menlo Park, Calif.</p>
        <p>The company is working with E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company to develop devices toallow doctors to perform tests for diseases, infections and hormone levels in their offices, instead of sending blood samples to a laboratory. Pen-Sized Glucose Sensor</p>
        <p>Some quick medical tests are already being developed for use at home and in doctors' offices. They still require some manipulation of samples and often show their results by a change in color of a chemical. A sensor would go one step further by giving a digital readout.</p>
        <p>The Baxter Healthcare division of Baxter International this year began selling a pen-sized glucose sensor for diabetics to test their blood sugar levels. The user puts a drop of blood on a special disposable test strip at one end of the pen. Thirty seconds later, the glucose level is displayed in a tiny liquid crystal readout.</p>
        <p>Similar devices might also be able to give continuous readings, rather than from a single sample. And by taking advantage of modern techniques used to produce computer chips, such sensors might be extremely tiny and inexpensive.</p>
        <p>SRI International, a contract research institute in Menlo Park, and Cardiovascular Devices Inc. of Irvine Calif., are separately working on sensors so tiny they can fit inside a blood vessel and continuously monitor the oxygen, carbon dioxide and acidity in the blood. Such measurements are critical for patients undergoing surgery or in intensive care.</p>
        <p>Scientists say sensors are becoming critically important because modern electronics allows more and more equipment, from petrochemical production refineries to automobile engines, to be controlled by computers. But computer control is often useless unless the computer knows what is happening around it. 'Starved for Information</p>
        <p>Even though chemical production is monitored and controlled by computers, typically 10 percent of the production is of poor quality, said Bruce R. Kowalski, co-director of the Center for Process Analytical Chemistry at the University of Washington.</p>
        <p>''The problem is that the control systems are starved for information,'' said Dr. Kowalski, whose research center, financed by the National Science Foundation and about 40 chemical companies, is trying to develop better control systems for the chemical industry. The computers are fed information only on temperature, pressure and flow when what they really need to know is the concentration of various chemicals and impurities, he said.</p>
        <p>Similarly, scientists have long envisioned an electronic pancreas for diabetics. In this scheme, a tiny sensor inside a blood vessel would continuously sample the blood's glucose concentration. The information would be fed directly to a reservoir implanted inside the body that would dispense the proper amount of insulin. The technology for the reservoir already exists. ''The link that is missing is the reliable sensor,'' said Michael R. Neuman, associate professor of biomedical engineering at Case Western Reserve University.</p>
        <p>The glucose sensor sold by Baxter, one of the first such sensors to reach the market, contains a tiny patch of glucose oxidase, the same enzyme used in the body to help convert sugar into energy. The enzyme causes glucose to undergo a chemical reaction in which it loses electrons. Two tiny electrodes pick up the electrons to form an electric current. The more glucose present in the blood sample, the stronger the current. Crystals and Optical Fibers</p>
        <p>Instead of electrodes, other systems use optical fibers, wisps of glass that can transmit light signals. In the blood monitoring system made by Cardiovascular Devices, for instance, the tip of the oxygen-detecting fiber is coated with a fluorescent dye that gives back less light in the presence of oxygen. This end would be threaded into a blood vessel through a catheter. The more oxygen present in the blood, the weaker the fluorescent light that would travel back down the fiber to the end outside the body.</p>
        <p>Yet another approach is to use piezoelectric crystals, tiny pieces of quartz that vibrate when an electric current goes through them. The crystals can be coated with a material that absorbs the substance being sensed. As more material is absorbed, the crystal becomes heavier and vibrates more slowly.</p>
        <p>The materials used for recognition can also vary tremendously. Sensors that are already on the market generally use chemicals or enzymes. But some researchers say that since living organisms are so good at sensing things, more effort should be made to use natural sensing mechanisms.</p>
        <p>Dr. Garry A. Rechnitz, a professor of chemistry at the University of Delaware, connects antennae from blue crabs in Chesapeake Bay to tiny electrodes. When the antenna detects a toxin in the water, an electric signal is produced that provides a reading of the amount of toxin present. ''Nature has really done it for us, Dr. Rechnitz said. ''The living organism has extraordinary sensitivity.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Rechnitz has also fashioned other sensors using natural materials as sources for enzymes that can detect the presence of certain chemicals. One sensor, which he calls the ''bananatrode,'' uses a slice of banana and an oxygen sensing electrode to detect dopamine, a chemical in the nervous system. He has also made a sensor from cucumber leaves to sense the amino acid cysteine and a toad bladder-based sensor to detect the hormone vasopressin. Antibodies on a Silicon Chip</p>
        <p>Molecular Devices has experimented with using bacterial and human skin cells on top of semiconductor chips to detect toxins, a modern version of the old technique of putting a canary in a coal mine to detect toxic gases. Soldiers could use such a sensor to detect nerve gas.</p>
        <p>Perhaps more practical, however, is to use antibodies, the body's means of fighting invaders, which are very specific in latching on to particular substances. Molecular Devices is now testing a sensor consisting of antibodies on a silicon chip for use in testing for contamination in drugs produced by biotechnology. George Guilbault, a chemistry professor at the University of New Orleans, has coated piezoelectric crystals with antibodies to make experimental sensors to detect cocaine and the pesticide parathion in the environment.</p>
        <p>Despite the huge promise of chemical and biological sensors, however, obstacles are great and setbacks have been numerous. One approach to biosensors once considered most promising was to put the recognition element directly on a silicon chip, producing a complete sensor on a chip. But that approach has proven disappointing because the chemicals interfere with the electronics. Attacking the Sensor</p>
        <p>Making sensors that can be implanted in the body has also so far defied success because the body's defense mechanism attacks the sensor as an invader. ''The blood tends to clot right around the sensor,'' said Anthony A. Boiarski, project manager for optical sensors at Battelle Memorial Institute in Columbus, Ohio. That not only gums up the sensor, it poses a risk to the patient.</p>
        <p>Accuracy is another concern. Sometimes chemicals other than the one being tested give a positive reading. The sensors also tend to lose their calibration and must be adjusted for temperature changes and other variables.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
