<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.P.A. Chief Asks Total Ban on Ozone-Harming Chemicals</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="183049"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HALONS (CHEMICAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">THOMAS, LEE M (ADMR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DB103FF934A1575AC0A96E948260" item-length="1153" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.P.A. Chief Asks Total Ban on Ozone-Harming Chemicals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The head of the Environmental Protection Agency called today for the complete elimination of chemicals believed to be destroying the earth's ozone shield, rather than the 50 percent reduction that a recently negotiated international treaty would require.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The head of the Environmental Protection Agency called today for the complete elimination of chemicals believed to be destroying the earth's ozone shield, rather than the 50 percent reduction that a recently negotiated international treaty would require.</p>
        <p>The head of the Environmental Protection Agency called today for the complete elimination of chemicals believed to be destroying the earth's ozone shield, rather than the 50 percent reduction that a recently negotiated international treaty would require.</p>
        <p>The recommendation by the agency's Administrator, Lee M. Thomas, reflected a growing consensus that the threat to the ozone layer is even more serious than previously recognized, and an important American industry group of the chemicals' manufacturers and users went along with his suggestion.</p>
        <p>In a prepared statement, Mr. Thomas urged that the recent treaty be amended to provide for the phase-out around the world of chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, and halons - chemicals implicated in the destruction of ozone molecules in the upper atmosphere. What Treaty Provides</p>
        <p>Last year representatives of 46 nations meeting in Montreal signed an agreement to freeze production and use of CFC's and halons at 1986 levels starting in 1989 and then to gradually reduce their use by 50 percent.</p>
        <p>So far only eight countries, including the United States, have ratified the treaty, which requires ratification by at least 11 nations accounting for at least 60 percent of global production in order to be put into effect. The needed support is expected by year's end, however.</p>
        <p>But in the meantime a panel of scientists convened by the United States Government earlier this year reported that ozone was being destroyed over much of the globe at a rate exceeding that predicted by computer models.</p>
        <p>And last Friday, the Alliance for a Responsible CFC Policy, the chief industry trade group in the United States, representing both makers and users, wrote to Mr. Thomas saying that, given the status of scientific knowledge, ''responsible policy dictates'' phasing out CFC's to the maximum extent possible. E.I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company, the concern that introduced chlorofluorocarbons, has already announced its intention to phase out their production. New E.P.A. Study</p>
        <p>Mr. Thomas said a new analysis by his agency of recent scientific information about the effects of the chemicals ''paints an alarming picture of present and future global ozone levels.''</p>
        <p>''The depletion that has already occurred calls into question our earlier projections of future damage,'' he said. ''We must go further than a 50 percent reduction in these chemicals in order to stablize ozone levels.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Thomas also called for a worldwide freeze in the use of methyl chloroform, a widely used industrial solvent now recognized as an important source of the chlorine that is destroying the ozone but heretofore not included in international plans to protect the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Ozone in the upper atmosphere shields the earth's surface from some of the harmful ultraviolet radiation from the sun. If more radiation penetrated to the earth's surface, scientists have warned, it would cause increases in skin cancer and eye cataracts among humans as well as damage to forests, crops and wildlife.</p>
        <p>CFC's are widely used for refrigeration, insulation, packaging and solvents. The potential of these chemicals to destroy ozone in the upper atmosphere has been recognized by scientists since the early 1970's. In recent years, however, the discovery of what researchers describe as a large ''hole'' in the ozone over Antarctica has caused alarm and spurred intensified research. Limits Called Insufficient</p>
        <p>Now the E.P.A. analysis, based in large part on data presented by the panel of scientists convened by the Government, has concluded that the restrictions on CFC's and halons called for in the Montreal Protocol would not have the intended effect of stabilizing the amount of ozone-destroying chlorine, which is produced when the chemicals break down in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The analysis found that ''even with 100 percent participation'' in the treaty, the amount of chlorine in the atmosphere would grow to 8 parts per billion in less than a century from the current 2.7 parts per billion.</p>
        <p>''An immediate 100 percent reduction'' in the use of the CFC's and halons plus a freeze in the use of methyl chloroform ''would be needed to essentially stabilize chlorine and halon atmospheric abundances at current levels during the next 100 years,'' the E.P.A. study said. It noted that CFC's could remain in the atmosphere for 100 years or more.</p>
        <p>The report also said that, given current production trends, methyl chloroform would account for 80 percent of the growth of chlorine in the atmosphere caused by chemicals other than CFC's and halons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thomas did not give a suggested timetable for the phase-out. But Eileen B. Claussen, the agency's acting deputy administrator for air and radiation, said a 10-year period ''would not be unreasonable.''</p>
        <p>The United Nations Environmental Program, under whose auspices the Motreal Protocol was negotiated, and the Dutch Government are convening a meeting of scientists at The Hague next month to review and report on the state of scientific knowledge about the ozone layer. The report produced by that meeting is expected to serve as the basis for a review of the treaty by its signatories next year to determine if it should be revised. Response by Environmentalists</p>
        <p>Environmental groups welcomed today's call for action by Mr. Thomas but said the United States should not wait for a revision of the Montreal treaty to reduce CFC and halon production.</p>
        <p>''This new study shows we are in a lot more serious emergency than we thought we were, and adds much more urgency to the conclusion that the phase-out has to come more rapidly,'' said David D. Doniger, a lawyer and air pollution expert for the Natural Resources Defense Council, a national environmental group.</p>
        <p>Mr. Doniger said that his organization was calling for unilateral American action to phase out CFC's and would sue the E.P.A. to force it to revise its regulations on the chemicals to reflect the new information provided by its own study.</p>
        <p>Mike Clark, president of the Environmental Policy Institute, a group that last week published a report on the threat to the ozone layer, called Mr. Thomas's urging a change in the treaty ''too little, too late.'' He complained that the E.P.A. had omitted crucial requirements such as a ''rigid timetable'' for the elimination of CFC's.</p>
        <p>Arjun Makhijani, a co-author of the study, said that the call for a phase-out was ''very positive,'' but added that, to protect the ozone layer adequately, it would be necessary to curb production of still another widely used chemical, carbon tetrachloride.</p>
        <p>Used primarily in this country as a component of CFC's, carbon tetrachloride is now accounting for about 3 percent of the growth of atmospheric chlorine each year, Dr. Makhijani said. It can also be used as a substitute for many applications of CFC's, he noted, and thus would be more widely used as CFC's were phased out.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
