<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BY FITNESS OBSESSED</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Good Health Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="42" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="186153"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DB1739F93AA35753C1A96E948260" item-length="2819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BY FITNESS OBSESSED</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Stockton; William Stockton is an assistant financial news editor of The New York Times.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: I ONCE MET AN ULTRAMARATHONER who said he fights boredom on his runs by overtaking anyone ahead of him, no matter how painful the task. At the time, I thought such behavior a bit odd, perhaps more an obsession with fitness than a tactic for achieving it. A few months later, I was working out on a rowing machine and found myself losing badly in a silent race with a man next to me.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: I ONCE MET AN ULTRAMARATHONER who said he fights boredom on his runs by overtaking anyone ahead of him, no matter how painful the task. At the time, I thought such behavior a bit odd, perhaps more an obsession with fitness than a tactic for achieving it. A few months later, I was working out on a rowing machine and found myself losing badly in a silent race with a man next to me.</p>
        <p>I ONCE MET AN ULTRAMARATHONER who said he fights boredom on his runs by overtaking anyone ahead of him, no matter how painful the task. At the time, I thought such behavior a bit odd, perhaps more an obsession with fitness than a tactic for achieving it. A few months later, I was working out on a rowing machine and found myself losing badly in a silent race with a man next to me. When he finally left, I sneaked a look at the meter on his machine to see just how far he had rowed. Before I knew it I was sitting back down and rowing furiously to match his distance - and add another three miles.</p>
        <p>Soon after, I read that Gen. Alfred M. Gray, Commandant of the United States Marine Corps, had issued a directive that his troops further toughen their physical conditioning. ''I think,'' the general said, ''if we would run a little more each day we'd be the best-looking outfit ever to get run off a hill.''</p>
        <p>My first thought, as fitness columnist for The New York Times, was that here was something interesting to write about: I would apply to take the same fitness test that Marines take, and then recount my experiences in my column. How would an average amateur athlete of my age and build - 44 years old, 6 feet 2 inches, 180 pounds - stack up against the Marines? Would this not be an ideal way to measure one's fitness, and provide a shining standard against which to gauge one's physical condition? A good, crisp, clear motiviation, right? Well sure. But there was a nagging thought. Was I tacitly trying to take on the United States Marine Corps? Sneaking a look at the meter on their rowing machine? Was this the beginning of Ultramarathoner Syndrome?</p>
        <p>WHAT FITNESS IS, OF COURSE, CONTINUES to be a perplexing question. ''There are probably as many answers to the question as there are individuals,'' says Francois Haas, a physiologist at the Rusk Institute of New York University Medical Center. Doctors and physiologists have devoted considerable research to the subject. Dr. Ralph S. Paffenbarger Jr., an epidemiologist at the Stanford University School of Medicine, studied a large pool of Harvard University alumni, taking their exercise and medical histories and relating habitual exercise to health. He found that people who expended 2,000 calories each week on a variety of physical activities tended to live longer than those who did not. (Certainly, a valid yardstick.) Dr. Kenneth H. Cooper, founder of the Aerobics Center in Dallas, has created his own measurement system, awarding points accoring to the amount of physical activity performed each week. For example, a jogger between the ages of 30 and 49 who covers three miles in 29 minutes four times a week earns 57.6 points, placing him in the ''excellent'' category. (That amount of jogging represents about 1,200 calories a week.) The ultimate gauge of fitness is generally considered to be a treadmill test. While you exercise to the point of exhaustion, computers monitor the heart and measure how much oxygen is being consumed at maximum exertion. The higher the consumption, the greater your aerobic fitness.</p>
        <p>I ARRIVED AT CAMP LEJEUNE in North Carolina at dawn to join members of the Eighth Motor Transport Battalion. The Marine test is deceptively simple: do as many pullups as possible up to a maximum of 20 in one session on the overhead bar; as many bent-knee sit-ups as possible up to 80 in two minutes, and run three miles. A perfect score is 300 - which means doing the maximum number of pullups and sit-ups and running the three miles in 18 minutes. Lieut. Col. Orvis Doyle, battalion commander, who, as it turned out, is my age and build, regularly scores more than 260.</p>
        <p>The enlisted men began with pullups, and many easily logged 20. Then the officers stepped up one by one, and most did at least 15, some 20. Colonel Doyle finally strode forward, and methodically did 16, stopping, he said, because of tendinitis in one elbow.</p>
        <p>My apprehension intensified as I watched. As I took the bar, I sensed the entire company pausing to take this outsider's measure. I started easily enough, but my biceps quickly began to burn. Seven. Eight. Nine was a struggle. Ten: heaving upward, pulling, straining, kicking. ''Come on,'' I heard. ''You can do it. Pull hard!'' Chin almost to the bar. Then I lowered my body slowly and dropped, embarrassed. In the two remaining stages of the test, I did 53 bent-knee sit-ups in two minutes, well short of the goal of 80, and ran the three-mile course in 23:35. Colonel Doyle finished in 21:00. When we tallied the scores, I had 165 points, a modest (if passing, by Marine standards) performance. Colonel Doyle hit 262, only 38 points shy of the maximum. That was fitness. I had measured myself and fallen short.</p>
        <p>I DECIDED TO SPEND THE NEXT three months training, and then repeat the Marine test. I had to answer some basic questions about my physical abilities.</p>
        <p>I began running more, lifting weights, doing calisthenics and taking punishing bike rides. At the Rusk Institute, Haas agreed to put me on a treadmill. When I told him about my crusade, he said that he doubted I would see much change in my score on the test. ''The biggest effect is seen when someone who is not fit trains for several weeks,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Now let us be frank: running to the abyss of exhaustion is not every man's ecstasy; a delightful task clearly it is not. The nostrils are held shut with a clip; teeth are clamped on a rubber mouthpiece, which, along with a tube connected to a machine that measures exhaled air, is held in place with a helmet; electrocardiogram leads are taped to the chest and back. Throughout the test, saliva collects in the mouth and pressure builds in the ears.</p>
        <p>Anxiety is high as the treadmill starts slowly at a slight incline. Over the next 20 minutes, the machine steadily speeds up to 5.5 miles per hour, and the grade increases to 20 percent. But as incline and pace increased, I forgot the discomfort. I was concentrating on the run, determined to go as far as possible.</p>
        <p>Haas periodically offered encouragement as he studied a computer screen. ''Three more minutes . . . two more minutes. Hang on.''</p>
        <p>Then: ''You've crossed the anaer-obic threshold.'' My breathing suddenly became more difficult, and I found myself gasping. At that point, the amount of carbon dioxide produced by my body exceeded the amount of oxygen I was consuming, and the buildup of lactic acid in my muscles made exercise painful.</p>
        <p>Hearing Haas announce the anaerobic threshold was more than I could bear. I abruptly stopped my motion, straddled the moving belt and ripped off headgear and nose clip. I was, as we say, wasted.</p>
        <p>My maximum heart rate had reached 182 beats per minute; my oxygen consumption had hit 64.86 milliliters per minute per kilogram of body weight, and my METS score (the unit of measure of the body's metabolism when resting) had reached 18.56. During such a test, the heart rate of an elite athlete would not generally be any higher than mine, but his oxygen consumption would be in the high 70's or low 80's and his METS score closer to 23.</p>
        <p>''I would describe you as quite fit,'' Haas said. I, who had not forgotten Colonel Doyle's pulling away from me in the three-mile Marine run, was determined to improve.</p>
        <p>I decided to focus on three things: running a familiar, hilly 3.6-mile course near my home, trying to get my time below my customary 29 minutes; working toward doing 80 sit-ups in two minutes, and maintaining upper-body strength through weight lifting, pushups and an occasional set of pullups on an overhead bar. I grew to loathe the pullups, and I eventually abandoned them altogether. I knew this was a lapse in discipline that invited further humiliation back at Camp Lejeune, but I did not care. Had a crack begun to appear in my obsession?</p>
        <p>The running, however, was enjoyable. I had never run against the clock before, and I soon learned to pace myself, determining what my elapsed times should be at various landmarks. Next, I concentrated on maintaining my pace uphill and accelerating downhill. I realized that if I speeded up midway through the run, I could cut a few more seconds from my time. The last mile was a long, gentle incline and then a level stretch. Despite the fatigue, I forced myself to put on a final burst of speed.</p>
        <p>The technique of interspersing moderately paced running with harder running increases conditioning and overall speed. But running harder up hills can be painful, and I often found myself yearning to slow down or even walk. I began mentally rehearsing the run, imagining myself pushing up the hills, thinking of the relief that would come on reaching the top. On the course, I would repeat these mental movies as I approached each hill.</p>
        <p>PSYCHOLOGICAL FACTORS, OF course, play important, if complex, roles in all human performance. Colonel Doyle speaks of ''mental toughness,'' the inner strength needed for coping with adversity. For the Marines, it is the extra ability necessary to survive in combat. Indeed, mental toughness can make the difference between peak performance and good or average performance.</p>
        <p>I continued to give running what inner strength I had, yet I saw no dramatic changes in my time. I did lower it some, however - down to 28 minutes, 27:30, 27:15.</p>
        <p>Then late one afternoon, just before dusk, five weeks or so into the training, I somehow just felt fast. I all but flew down the road, and my time was 25:10. A few days later it was 24:50. I realized that I had my best runs at dusk, so I decided always to run at that time of day. New times: 24:15, then 24:00. Finally, about two months after I had gone to Camp Lejeune, I hit 23:35 - the fastest I had ever run.</p>
        <p>IT WAS DRIZZLING AND COOL the morning of my return to Lejeune. Expecting North Carolina's summer heat, Colonel Doyle had scheduled the test on the beaches of the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>I took cover in a van while the troops were put through light warm-up calisthenics, and I studied the awaiting overhead bars with undisguised disgust. Then I joined Colonel Doyle and his men as they lined up. Dread overcame me. I hadn't done any pullups in weeks, and my modest hope was to equal my last performance - nine.</p>
        <p>The rain was coming down harder now, and the bar was slippery. A sergeant standing below snapped out my count. One. Two. Three. I sensed that this time no one was watching, perhaps because of the rain. Six. Seven. My arms ached. I wanted to quit. I paused. ''Only seven?'' a voice said. Was it my voice? Or the colonel's? Eight. I paused again. ''You can do it. Give us another one.'' It was the voice of another officer. I pulled as hard as I could, struggling to edge my chin above the bar. ''Nine,'' came the count.</p>
        <p>One more? ''Give us 10.'' I tensed for a lunge at the bar - but dropped to the ground instead. ''That's enough,'' I muttered. A feeling of elation came over me. I had equaled my previous performance. The guilt I had felt for weeks dropped away. Might I redeem myself after all?  I turned to watch the colonel and was surprised to see him having difficulty, though his count had passed mine. Pain was etched on his face. ''Fourteen,'' the sergeant called. Then, sotto voce: ''Come on, Sir. You can do another.'' The colonel paused, struggled, suddenly looking ungainly and exhausted. His chin nearly reached the bar, perhaps even with it. ''Sixteen,'' the sergeant declared. The colonel dropped. ''Damn poor,'' he muttered.</p>
        <p>The enlisted men had paired up to take turns holding their partners' feet for the sit-ups; I lay in the wet grass, and the colonel held mine down. I adopted a moderate pace. My hope was to do 60 sit-ups, one every two seconds. The colonel counted as my shoulder blades hit the ground. Twenty-five. Twenty-six. ''One minute,'' the sergeant bellowed as I hit 33. My spirits continued to rise. Fifty. Fifty-one. Thirty seconds remaining. Fifty-eight. Fifty-nine. The muscles in my upper legs and my stomach were on fire, and I trembled involuntarily with each sit-up. Sixty. Sixty-one. ''Ten seconds.'' Sixty-two. Sixty-three. The whistle blew, and I fell backward into the grass. Ten more sit-ups than last time. I wanted to jump up and shout. Instead I held down Colonel Doyle's feet -while he knocked off 80. Heavy, cold rain swept down on us as we started the run at the edge of the surf, T-shirts plastered to our bodies, shoes soaked and filling with sand, vision cut to a few hundred yards. The youngest marines, aiming for 300 points, pulled well ahead; the colonel was a few paces in front of me.</p>
        <p>The run was not at all what I had anticipated. No roads, lawns or sidewalks, no rounded course returning to a starting point, no sergeant calling out how much time had elapsed. Worse, we did not know where the finish line was. This was another treadmill.</p>
        <p>The rain took its toll, and I sensed myself deteriorating. Within a few minutes my goal had shifted from keeping up with the colonel to merely finishing. I felt a stitch in my left side as I settled in alongside several enlisted men, and we weaved back and forth at the edge of the surf, searching for sound footing. The colonel was about 30 paces ahead.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, lightning flashed overhead and an explosive thunderclap rolled over us. Everyone jumped, and several marines surged forward in mock terror. The lightning really was frightening, however, and we all picked up our pace to get this over with.</p>
        <p>The pain in my side grew worse and my breath came in gasps. I must have started too fast, and now I continued to fall farther behind. Was it time for my famous mental movie? I tried to visualize the finish line - but what to visualize? The foreground was only rain and fog. Time seemed suspended.</p>
        <p>Another flash of lightning; another thunderclap. I had an intense desire to stop, to drop to a walk and catch my breath. I couldn't recall ever feeling so certain that I was unable to go on, so bereft of inner strength. But the lightning and thunder sent the marines running near me surging forward again, and I tried to pick up my speed. As much as I longed to quit, the thought of humiliation drove me onward.</p>
        <p>Finally, the lights of several vehicles parked at the edge of the water came into view. ''That's it,'' someone called. Then I saw an officer standing at the finish line with a stopwatch. He was shouting out the elapsed time, but I couldn't make out the words.</p>
        <p>A few more yards and it sounded as if he were calling out ''24:30. 24:35.'' What despair. The rain, the sand, my own poor preparation had defeated me. I would finish nearly two minutes slower than last time.</p>
        <p>But several paces later, the officer's voice became clear: ''20:45. 20:50.'' Here was the motivation I needed, the discovery that I was within striking distance of 21 minutes. ''20:55. 21:00.'' A few more paces. ''21:10,'' the officer said as I shot past him. Stumbling, catching my breath, I calculated that I had shaved 2:25 off my prior time, running in more difficult conditions. I was jubilant. I had held my own with the hated pullups and improved in the two other areas. The training had paid off. Colonel Doyle had crossed the finish line at 20:15, scoring 267, for a five-point gain. I had scored 192, a 27-point gain.</p>
        <p>DURING THE NEXT FEW days I felt enormous relief. It was clear to me that I had been training too hard, that I had grown to resent the extra workouts and the anxiety of facing the Marines again and falling short. There really was something a little mad about a man in his mid-40's driving himself as hard as I had. I came to see that at some point we have to accept ourselves, accept that our genes and our past impose limitations that no amount of training can overcome. We were not all meant to be United States Marines.</p>
        <p>My own obsession with fitness had taken a troubling, possibly even harmful, turn. If the first Marine test had set me off on a quest, the second had brought me back to reality. Standing in the slashing rain on the beach, waiting for the three-mile run to begin, I had quipped to Colonel Doyle, ''Whose idea was this?'' He gave me a level look and replied: ''Yours.'' The Marine tests proved to be an excellent measure of fitness, all right, but perhaps they were instructive of something more: that one man's pleasure is another's pain, and that getting fit and staying fit should be fun. Each person should listen carefully to his or her own body's needs and responses and pick a level of exercise that feels right. What others do is their business. If fitness isn't fun, something is wrong.</p>
        <p>As I was leaving Camp Lejeune, the colonel said, ''I would rather have someone with me in a tight spot who is mentally tough and has a so-so body than someone with a super body who lacks mental toughness.'' I took it as a backhanded compliment.</p>
        <p>Perhaps what all this meant was that I had been caught up in a game of vanity. Perhaps I had been futilely trying to slow the clock of age.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
