<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Burning of Rondonia</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="175257"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RONDONIA (BRAZIL)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AMAZON RIVER BASIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRAZIL</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru/Amazon Basin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D91431F93AA1575BC0A96E948260" item-length="608" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Burning of Rondonia</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A calamitous cycle of destruction is unfolding in Rondonia, the heavily forested Amazon province in western Brazil. The tragedy is a lesson to Brazil and to the international agencies that finance its projects that heedless development can wreak havoc with the global environment, not just Brazil's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A calamitous cycle of destruction is unfolding in Rondonia, the heavily forested Amazon province in western Brazil. The tragedy is a lesson to Brazil and to the international agencies that finance its projects that heedless development can wreak havoc with the global environment, not just Brazil's.</p>
        <p>A calamitous cycle of destruction is unfolding in Rondonia, the heavily forested Amazon province in western Brazil. The tragedy is a lesson to Brazil and to the international agencies that finance its projects that heedless development can wreak havoc with the global environment, not just Brazil's. Cattle ranchers and thousands of landless settlers recently brought in by the Government are torching the tropical forest to clear the land. The fires are so extensive that they add appreciably to the global pollution that now may be warming the earth's climate. The richly diverse forest, ancient home to a fifth of the world's plant and animal species, is being destroyed irreversibly, and its Amerindian inhabitants are dying from imported diseases. Stripped of the trees that recycle forest nutrients, the soil yields only a few years' crops before the settlers move on, to destroy more forest.</p>
        <p>A new picture of the damage has emerged from a NASA satellite sensitive to heat sources. Scientists at Brazil's Space Research Center, Marlise Simons has reported in The Times, have counted 170,000 fires last year in the western Amazon.</p>
        <p>The fires contribute twice over to the greenhouse effect, the feared warming of the world's climate that may already have begun in the recent string of hot summers. They contribute fully one-tenth of the global production of carbon dioxide, the principal greenhouse gas. And once the forest is burned, it can no longer absorb carbon dioxide from the air and turn it back into vegetation.</p>
        <p>Despite the richness and diversity of tropical forests, their soil is mostly poor. Shielded from the recurrent ice ages that repeatedly extinguished life in temperate zones, the animals and plants of the tropics have had millions of years in which to develop new species and complex interdependencies. The living systems now being destroyed in Brazil are the flower of some 50 million years of evolution.</p>
        <p>Cattle ranchers, responsible for 80 percent of the destruction, receive sizable tax breaks. Without such subsidies, the cattle ranches are ''inherently uneconomic,'' writes Robert Repetto of the World Resources Institute. Besides the ranchers, half a million settlers have invaded the Rondonian forest along the new Cuiaba-Porto Velho road, paved with a $250 million World Bank loan. The Bank's requests for protection of the forests and their tribes were ignored. Since the road was paved, the area of destroyed forest has tripled. Rondonia, endowed with one of the world's richest ecosystems, is already 17 percent deforested.</p>
        <p>The tragedy is that the forest could be preserved even as its resources are tapped. Permanent crops like coffee bushes do less damage than annual cropping or cattle. The valuable hardwood trees could be harvested instead of burned. Migrant settlers would hunger less for forest land if Brazil redistributed the 43 percent of its arable land now owned by just 1 percent of its population.</p>
        <p>The World Bank has learned from the disaster of the Rondonia road, but it and other lending agencies need to ensure that Brazil shares the lesson.</p>
        <p>An imaginative scheme of debt-for-nature swaps has been devised by Thomas Lovejoy of the World Wildlife Fund: the fund raises money to buy up the dollar-denominated debt of countries like Bolivia, Ecuador and Costa Rica, which it exchanges for local currencies to be used in establishing nature preserves.</p>
        <p>By such means, the headlong devastation of Rondonia can perhaps be halted before it becomes a wasteland that serves only to fuel the global greenhouse effect. The destruction of the Amazon forest is a crime from which no one benefits.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
