<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Forests of Vermont Severely Damaged By Flea-Size Insect</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="156147"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PESTICIDES AND PESTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SYRUPS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PEAR THRIPS (INSECT)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VERMONT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KUNIN, MADELEINE M (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DC1F30F930A15755C0A96E948260" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Forests of Vermont Severely Damaged By Flea-Size Insect</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
      <dateline>WESTMINSTER WEST, Vt., June 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As much as a fifth of Vermont's five million acres of forest has been defoliated by insects in recent weeks, raising concern about both the maple syrup industry and the fall foliage season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As much as a fifth of Vermont's five million acres of forest has been defoliated by insects in recent weeks, raising concern about both the maple syrup industry and the fall foliage season.</p>
        <p>As much as a fifth of Vermont's five million acres of forest has been defoliated by insects in recent weeks, raising concern about both the maple syrup industry and the fall foliage season.</p>
        <p>The culprit is the pear thrips, an insect smaller than a flea that is causing severe damage to sugar maple trees in several Northeastern states.</p>
        <p>''This is the most severe problem that I have seen in our forests in the last 25 years,'' said Bruce L. Parker, an entomology professor at the University of Vermont. About a half million acres have suffered moderate to heavy damage; the rest have been less affected.</p>
        <p>Government officials, researchers and sugar makers from the region will gather on Thursday in Bennington to discuss what to do. Governor Madeleine M. Kunin has created a working group, and research is starting on several fronts.</p>
        <p>It is too early to tell how costly the harm will be to the state's $12.5 million maple syrup industry, or how a less spectactular fall foliage season will affect tourism.</p>
        <p>The thrips is relatively new to Vermont, which has had its share of insect infestations over the years, including gypsy moths, forest tent caterpillars and aphids. The insects were first identified in the state in 1985, but became a major problem only this year. They were accidentally introduced into the United States from abroad in the early 1900's but remained primarily an orchard pest until about 10 years ago, when they became active in forests. No one knows why the thrips are unusually active this year.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of a mysterious thing,'' said Imants Millers, a field representative of the United States Forest Service in Durham, N.H. ''All of a sudden it showed up.''</p>
        <p>The thrips do their damage in the spring, boring into tree buds and sucking the juice from them. The result can be trees with no leaves or withered, discolored dwarf leaves that quickly die, leaving the trees bare and weakened. Many trees may die, particularly if they are subjected to other stress, such as a drought. Life Cycle of Insect</p>
        <p>Meantime, many trees are sprouting new leaves. But these are not expected by some experts to be as robust as the first round of leaves a sugar maple normally produces.</p>
        <p>The thrips larvae are in the ground now, 12 to 16 inches deep. Foresters are wondering how much damage to expect when they emerge as adults next spring. If the thrips follow this year's pattern, they will fly onto the sugar maple trees and enter the buds. After feeding on leaf tissue in the buds, the thrips will lay eggs and soon die. The eggs will hatch, then the larvae will feed on the leaf and fall to the ground, starting the cycle again. The term thrips is derived from the Latin word for woodworm, which comes from the Greek word thrips.</p>
        <p>Southern Vermont has been among the hardest hit areas, particularly Windham and Bennington counties, while northern Vermont has been mostly spared. Nearby parts of New York and Massachusetts, including the Berkshires area, have also sustained tree damage. New Hampshire, Connecticut and Pennsylvania, which first reported thrips infestation in the late 1970's, are also suffering this year.</p>
        <p>''There isn't any part of our property that hasn't been affected,'' said Daniel Crocker, a 30-year-old sugar maker here, whose family has been in the business almost 50 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crocker spoke of the defoliation as he walked through some of his 100 hilly, verdant acres of sugar bush, so-called because of the concentration of sugar maple trees. The southeastern Vermont hillside is crisscrossed with miles of thin tubing that connect the 5,200 taps sunk in the maple trees to a sugar house at the base of the slope, where sap is collected and processed.</p>
        <p>''You shouldn't be able to see through a maple tree,'' said Mr. Crocker, pointing up at newly growing leaves that remind one more of spring than of the beginning of summer. Closer to the ground, he reached for branches of a small maple that had the telltale shriveled brown leaves. ''It's all thripped out,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Sugar maples, designated the state tree in 1949, are as much a part of the patrimony of Vermont as vineyards are in France. #2 Major Industries Hundreds of thousands of tourists come to Vermont in late September and early October to view the colorful foliage, the most brilliant of which is produced by the sugar maple.</p>
        <p>The sugar maple also evokes images of rugged Vermonters tapping the trees and filling buckets with sugary sap each March and April. The sap becomes maple syrup, which Vermont produces in greater amounts than any other state. This year, the state's sugar makers made 370,000 gallons, with a value of $12.5 million.</p>
        <p>There has not been much research about thrips and their effect on sugar maples, so foresters and sugar makers are not quite sure how to respond. Some sugar makers think trees that used extra energy to regrow leaves this year will produce less sap next year, and they do not know whether to risk tapping the weakened trees.</p>
        <p>''Producers are asking me, 'Hey, should we sugar next year or not?' '' said Wilson Clark, a sugar maker in Pawlet, Vt., head of the Vermont Maple Sugar Makers Association. There are also questions about whether pesticides are available to kill thrips.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clark is concerned about whether the trees will produce their usual brilliant array of fall colors. ''These trees have been through hell,'' he said. The regrowth of leaves is giving some hope that the foliage season will be normal, at least to the untrained eye, said Brent Teillon, chief of forest protection for Vermont. But he said a drought could complicate matters.</p>
        <p>Researchers have already documented a long-term decline in sugar maples.Gretchen Smith, director of the acid rain research project at the University of Massachusetts at Amherst, said she had found that 70 percent of maples in sugar bushes showed signs of decline. She attributed the problems to the combination of stresses such as acid rain, ozone pollution, other insect problems and overtapping of trees.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
