<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush vs. Bush on the Environment</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="188035"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1988</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">OAKES, JOHN B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DE133FF936A25753C1A96E948260" item-length="591" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush vs. Bush on the Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John B. Oakes; John B. Oakes is former Editorial Page Editor of The New York Times.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">OAKES, JOHN B</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Though you would never know it from the Presidential ''debates'', the environmental question is as significant as any now facing the American voter, and more significant than most. The cumulative destruction and corruption of the earth's resources on the land, in the seas, and throughout the atmosphere present as much of a challenge to the survival of the human race as nuclear war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Though you would never know it from the Presidential ''debates'', the environmental question is as significant as any now facing the American voter, and more significant than most. The cumulative destruction and corruption of the earth's resources on the land, in the seas, and throughout the atmosphere present as much of a challenge to the survival of the human race as nuclear war.</p>
        <p>Though you would never know it from the Presidential ''debates'', the environmental question is as significant as any now facing the American voter, and more significant than most. The cumulative destruction and corruption of the earth's resources on the land, in the seas, and throughout the atmosphere present as much of a challenge to the survival of the human race as nuclear war. For the last eight years, Vice President Bush has served as second-in- command of the most viciously anti-environmental Administration in American history. As Candidate Bush, he now presents himself as a card-carrying environmentalist -again as recently as Thursday night.</p>
        <p>The environmental card he is carrying is a joker. It signifies nothing or anything, denoting whatever values immediate political expedience dictates.</p>
        <p>Candidate Bush says that this is the year that ''the earth spoke back.'' The earth has long been speaking back and in thundering crescendo, but until this year, Vice President Bush wasn't listening. As chairman of President Reagan's Task Force on Regulatory Relief, Mr. Bush led the Administration's attack on established environmental protection standards right across the board. Candidate Bush now poses as champion of the Clean Air Act; Vice President Bush has done everything in his power to gut it.</p>
        <p>At the behest of the automobile, chemical and other major polluting industries, Vice President Bush led the way in delaying enforcement of air pollution controls and subverting efforts to strengthen them.</p>
        <p>Vice President Bush's task force pushed the harassed and weakened Environmental Protection Administration to relax its efforts to eliminate lead in gasoline, ease restrictions on automobile emissions, and defer gasoline mileage requirements (which E.P.A. did again only a few days ago.) As chairman of the task force, Vice President Bush sought drastic softening of existing programs for pesticide registration, hazardous waste treatment and testing of toxic substances - all to make life easier for the polluting industries and harder for the polluted consumer.</p>
        <p>Vice President Bush made a special trip to Canada to try to explain away his Administration's refusal to join Canadians in a direct attack on the pollution that causes acid rain. Candidate Bush now swears he will call an international conference to ''talk about'' it.</p>
        <p>Yet as the smoke-belching utilities and industries of the upper Middle West continue daily to poison the lakes, forests and air of Canada, New York and New England, Vice President Bush refuses to commit himself to support legislative and administrative actions that would force immediate and specific reductions in these noxious emissions.</p>
        <p>As a Congressman many years ago, Mr. Bush did help establish a national preserve in the wooded areas of East Texas. Since then - and especially during these past eight years of Administration-sponsored pillage of the national lands and forests - Vice President Bush's role in land protection and conservation has been nil. His position on oil extraction in environmentally sensitive areas, both on land and offshore, reflects his former close association with the oil industry.</p>
        <p>Candidate Bush may now recognize the major environmental problems, but his record as Vice President is so poor that his judgment as an environmentalist can no more be trusted than his judgment in selecting a running mate.</p>
        <p>Given the record of the past eight years, could a Bush-Quayle Administration be expected to meet the environmental challenge?</p>
        <p>Not on your life.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
