<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Behind New York's Offer on Dumping</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="167787"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINES (PENALTIES)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ATLANTIC OCEAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAY, CLIFFORD D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUGHES, WILLIAM J (REP)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2DC173BF937A3575BC0A96E948260" item-length="1002" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Behind New York's Offer on Dumping</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD D. MAY, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MAY, CLIFFORD D</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: By pledging with great fanfare to stop dumping sludge in the ocean within a decade, New York is trying to shift the terms of a Congressional debate of enormous importance to the city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: By pledging with great fanfare to stop dumping sludge in the ocean within a decade, New York is trying to shift the terms of a Congressional debate of enormous importance to the city.</p>
        <p>By pledging with great fanfare to stop dumping sludge in the ocean within a decade, New York is trying to shift the terms of a Congressional debate of enormous importance to the city.</p>
        <p>Environmental pariahs as recently as Monday, New York officials today can contend that they, too, want to end ocean dumping. The disagreement, they can say, merely concerns the timing.</p>
        <p>''It was a strategic move on their part,'' said Representative William J. Hughes, Democrat of New Jersey and a sponsor of a bill that would outlaw ocean dumping in four years and impose hundreds of millions of dollars of penalties on violators. ''And I respect that. But I'm not impressed with New York's promises anymore.''</p>
        <p>Only in the very strictest sense can the proposal, which was issued Tuesday, be called new. More than two months ago, before hypodermic needles washed ashore and beach closings were ruining weekends and making news, New York quietly offered to stop ocean dumping by 1999, if Mr. Hughes and other New Jersey Representatives would withdraw their bill. New Jersey said no deal. Promise for the 80's So how is Mayor Koch's most recent ''commitment to get out'' of the ocean one year earlier different? By calling it a concession, city officials hope to win, at least, a measure of sympathy from the public and House and Senate members who are not from New Jersey, where the issue is a political fireball and where legislators also vividly recall a promise Mr. Koch made in the late 1970's to stop ocean dumping by the early 1980's.</p>
        <p>Beyond that, there is an outside chance that the New York offer might prompt enough debate on House and Senate versions of the bill to prevent its passage in the current session. More likely, the proposal could at least be used as leverage in New York's efforts to soften the final version of the bill.</p>
        <p>With New Jersey's calling for a halt no later than the end of 1992 and New York's saying it can and will stop by 1998, surely it is reasonable, New York Representatives argue, to set a deadline somewhere between the dates.</p>
        <p>Or, if for political purposes the New Jersey lawmakers prefer, the compromise might be less explicit. A slightly revised bill could ban ocean dumping by 1992, but delay painful penalties for those who violate the ban until years further down the road. 'I'm Not Optimistic'</p>
        <p>Such points were discussed and argued for almost three hours today by New York and New Jersey House members on the Water Resources Subcommittee of the Public Works and Transportation Committee, which is considering the anti-dumping measure.</p>
        <p>At a subcommittee session this afternoon, it was agreed to consider, at least when the House and Senate versions of the bill go to conference, any consent agreement between New York and the Environmental Protection Agency, to determine whether there is a good-faith effort to stop the dumping as quickly as possible.</p>
        <p>''We've agreed it's germane to discuss it, and that's all,'' Mr. Hughes said. ''Frankly, I'm not optimistic that New York will make the kind of commitments that would be acceptable.''</p>
        <p>Like some other members of the New Jersey delegation who have been fighting the ''sludge wars'' with New York Representatives for more than a decade, Mr. Hughes is probably also disinclined to make life easier for his colleagues from across the Hudson River, now with the gathering momentum of the anti-dumping movement.</p>
        <p>In addition, no New Jersey lawmaker wants to risk being characterized as a pushover for big bad New York, particularly in an election year. Floating Toward Europe</p>
        <p>Somewhat lost in the complicated political debate is the equally complicated question of what sludge is, what harm it does and what the alternatives are. Basically, sludge is treated and biodegradable sewage, a substance not nearly so hazardous as the ooze that routinely overflows from municipal sewage pipes in both New York and New Jersey when an excess of raw sewage combines with rainwater to overburden outdated systems. Today, a provision was inserted in the anti-dumping bill that would rule out the use of the Fresh Kills, S.I., Landfill for disposing sludge.</p>
        <p>Sludge contains no ''floatables,'' including none of the hospital waste that closed beaches this summer.</p>
        <p>''Not only does it do no damage, even if it flows in the direction of our shores,'' Mr. Koch said Tuesday. ''The fact is that the currents are such that after it is filtered down, the currents take it toward Europe,'' a revelation unlikely to enhance the Mayor's popularity in Ireland or England.</p>
        <p>Environmental advocates dispute Mr. Koch's assertions. ''It's voodoo science,'' said Clifton Curtis, president of the Oceanic Society, a research and conservation organization here.</p>
        <p>Dumping, Mr. Curtis said, has created a virtual dead zone around the previous disposal site, 12 miles offshore, ''and there are similar risks associated with the new site,'' 100 miles away, which New York has been using since the beginning of the year. Little Pressure on Industries</p>
        <p>How does one reconcile Mr. Koch's assertion that sludge is essentially harmless with environmentalists' findings that sludge has, in fact, done harm? According to some scientists, sludge from human waste is indeed relatively benign. But New York sludge, they said, also contains toxic industrial wastes. Those substances need to be specially treated before entering the municipal sewage system, the scientists added, but New York has not forced industries to do that.</p>
        <p>Another point sometimes neglected is that sludge dumping, whatever its long-term environmental effect, is clearly not the cause of the recent beach closings. Separate bills that would set up systems to track medical wastes have been gaining wide support.</p>
        <p>But many of the most serious sources of pollution in the waters of the New York metropolitan region, -urban and agricultural runoff, acid rain, discharges of raw sewage and insufficient treatment of sewage in outmoded plants - have yet to be seriously addressed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
