<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE COMMON HOUSE PLANT DOES ITS BIT FOR CLEANER AIR</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="164712"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUILDINGS (STRUCTURES)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GASES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE STATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTICS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2D81E3CF935A15754C0A96E948260" item-length="1153" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE COMMON HOUSE PLANT DOES ITS BIT FOR CLEANER AIR</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE lilies of the field may toil not, but those plants in the living room and office, philodendron and ficus, daisies and mums, are much more than decorative. Scientists are finding them to be surprisingly useful in absorbing potentially harmful gases and cleansing air inside tightly sealed modern buildings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE lilies of the field may toil not, but those plants in the living room and office, philodendron and ficus, daisies and mums, are much more than decorative. Scientists are finding them to be surprisingly useful in absorbing potentially harmful gases and cleansing air inside tightly sealed modern buildings.</p>
        <p>THE lilies of the field may toil not, but those plants in the living room and office, philodendron and ficus, daisies and mums, are much more than decorative. Scientists are finding them to be surprisingly useful in absorbing potentially harmful gases and cleansing air inside tightly sealed modern buildings.</p>
        <p>In studies of biological methods for purifying air in space stations, environmental specialists at the National Aeronautics and Space Administration have determined that several common houseplants reduce the amounts of formaldehyde, benzene, carbon monoxide and nitrous oxide in indoor air. They are expanding the research to other plants and pollutants, and also to down-to-earth applications of the new knowledge.</p>
        <p>The research is drawing attention beyond the space-engineering field because of rising concern over the health risks of indoor air pollution. Building materials and interior furnishings increasingly contain synthetic compounds that emit trace levels of organic chemicals. They are likely to reach high concentrations indoors because new homes and commercial buildings are now designed to be more air-tight and insulated to save energy and may not always be adequately ventilated.</p>
        <p>Dr. Anthony V. Nero Jr., a leader of indoor air quality studies at Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory in California, said, ''The risks posed by indoor pollutants are in fact comparable in magnitude to those associated with exposure to chemicals or radiation in industrial settings.''</p>
        <p>Seeing an opportunity to promote the greening of more homes and offices, the Associated Landscape Contractors of America, a trade organization based in Falls Church, Va., has joined with NASA in a two-year program to study popular ornamental plants for their effectiveness in cleaning indoor air. The studies are being conducted in experimental chambers at NASA's Stennis Space Center at Bay St. Louis, Miss.</p>
        <p>Scientists say polluted rooms cannot be cleaned up by plants alone. No amount of greenery, for example, is likely to reduce the smoke and dust in a room. Even when plants do filter specific chemicals, they are much more effective in the sealed conditions of a space station than in a house or an apartment, where the effects of ventilation usually far outweigh those of plants.</p>
        <p>Still, the new studies indicate that well-chosen greenery can reduce the levels of some dangerous contaminants.</p>
        <p>''It's a whole world of environment studies we're just beginning to touch,'' said Dr. B. C. Wolverton, the NASA investigator in charge of the plant research. ''If you put plants in buildings, will it help improve air quality? We say, from our tests, yes indeed. The more foliage, the healthier the environment is going to be.'' Role of Photosynthesis</p>
        <p>The first results of the new research, announced last month, showed that of eight plants tested with benzene, which is known to cause some human cancers, two, the Gerbera daisy and chrysanthemum, were rated ''superior'' in removing the pollutant from the experimental chamber in 24-hour exposure periods.</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Wolverton, the absorption of polluting chemicals by plants is part of the photosynthetic process in which plants, to live and grow, must continuously exchange gaseous substances with the surrounding atmosphere. The plant leaves take in carbon dioxide and exchange it for oxygen and water vapor, which is returned to the atmosphere. It now appears that plants can also take in other, more dangerous, gases through the tiny openings, or stomates, on the leaves.</p>
        <p>Benzene is found in gasoline and other petroleum-based products as well as many solvents. In the NASA test, the chemical was injected inside two airtight chambers and circulated by a fan. Different plants were introduced to the chambers, and their ability to absorb the contaminant was usually measured at intervals of 6 and 24 hours.</p>
        <p>Experiments with other pollutants have not been completed, but preliminary tests are encouraging, NASA scientists said. They show philodendrons ''are among the most effective plants tested to date.'' Absorbs Formaldehyde</p>
        <p>In the studies, the leaves of elephant ear, known scientifically as Philodendron domesticum, and golden pothos, or Scindapsus aureus, demonstrated their ability to remove benzene and carbon monoxide from closed chambers. The green spider plant, Chlorophytum elatum, was also effective in removing carbon monoxide.</p>
        <p>Two kinds of philodrendron, elephant ear and heart leaf, or Philodendron oxycardium, were found to absorb large quantities of formaldehyde from the air. People are constantly exposed to ths toxic chemical, which is used in certain foam insulations, plywood, particle board, grocery bags, waxed papers, facial tissues, carpet backing, fire retardants and permanent-press clothing.</p>
        <p>Aloe vera proved to be more effective than the others in removing formaldehyde at low concentrations, the scientists said.</p>
        <p>The experiments so far have been a straightforward testing of which plants absorb what pollutants. Scientists have not determined the exact process by which the plants perform their cleansing action, but they assume it is similar to the plants' metabolic transformation of carbon dioxide into oxygen and water vapor.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wolverton said tests are under way to determine if any of the plants emit any chemicals that might be more harmful than the substances they are absorbing. No such hazards have been identified in the common house plants being examined.</p>
        <p>The scientists are also mixing plants, as they might be in an office or home, to see if this produces a synergistic effect, either good or bad. They are also testing plants in combination with activated charcoal, the substance often used to cleanse spacecraft atmospheres.</p>
        <p>In the May issue of Scientific American, Dr. Nero assessed the risks and the need to regulate indoor pollutants. ''The health risks incurred merely by breathing the air at home can substantially exceed the general limits on risk that regulatory agencies impose in controlling pollutants in outdoor air or drinking water,'' he wrote.</p>
        <p>But in a telephone interview Dr. Nero questioned whether green plants would be more than marginally effective. Although the tests indicate some removal of pollutants, he said, the ''rates might be significant for a space station but not for a normal ventilated structure.''</p>
        <p>In the usual house, Dr. Nero said, the air is exchanged about once every hour or two. For the plants to affect air quality they must remove the contaminants faster than the normal ventilation system.</p>
        <p>Even so, Dr. Wolverton of NASA has put his scientific findings into practice. He built a solarium across the front of his house and filled it with palms, golden pothos, philodendron and other vegetation. The ventilation system was modified so that a fan pulls all the air in the house through the solarium and across the filtering leaves of green plants.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
