<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Americans Falter on Geography Test</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="165380"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOGRAPHY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ITALY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SWEDEN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WEST GERMANY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SOCIETY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED8143AF93BA15754C0A96E948260" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Americans Falter on Geography Test</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Young Americans 18 to 24 years old scored lower than their counterparts in a nine-country survey of geographic literacy, the National Geographic Society said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Young Americans 18 to 24 years old scored lower than their counterparts in a nine-country survey of geographic literacy, the National Geographic Society said today.</p>
        <p>Young Americans 18 to 24 years old scored lower than their counterparts in a nine-country survey of geographic literacy, the National Geographic Society said today.</p>
        <p>American adults ranked 6th in the study, ''Geography: An International Gallup Survey,'' conducted for the society by the Gallup Organization. The survey sought to determine how many people could find 13 selected countries, Central America and two bodies of water, the Pacific Ocean and the Persian Gulf, on an unmarked world map.</p>
        <p>''Have you heard of the lost generation?'' Gilbert M. Grosvenor, president of the National Geographic Society,'' asked at a National Press Club luncheon. ''We have found them. They are lost. They haven't the faintest idea where they are.''</p>
        <p>The survey, commissioned by the geographic society, tested 10,820 adults in Canada, France, Italy, Japan, Mexico, Sweden, the United Kingdom, the United States and West Germany How Countries Scored Of a possible score of 16 points, American adults averaged 8.6, about on a par with British adults, who scored an average of 8.5 points, the findings showed. Canadian adults scored 9.2. Americans in the 18-to-24-year group averaged 6.9 points, the lowest score of all youths tested and of all other age groups in the United States.</p>
        <p>Swedes tested the best, scoring 11.6 points, and Germans averaged second best, scoring 11.2 points. Only adults in Italy and Mexico scored lower than those in the United States. All participants were interviewed in their homes from late April through mid-May. To be considered statistically signficant, differences in scores among all adults must be at least six-tenths of a point apart. Thus the scores among adults from the United States and Canada are signficantly different, while those in the United States and the United Kingdom are not.</p>
        <p>''Our adult population, especially our young adults, do not understand the world at a time in our history when we face a critical economic need to understand foreign consumers, markets, customs, foreign strengths and weaknesses,'' Mr. Grosvenor said.</p>
        <p>A separate Gallup survey of a larger sample of Americans found a high degree of awareness of environmental issues. Almost all were aware of the depletion of the ozone layer of the Earth's atmosphere, and more than two-thirds knew about the problem of acid rain in North America.</p>
        <p>In a more comprehensive battery of 81 questions, asked only of the 1,611 Americans surveyed, those 18 to 24 years old again received the lowest scores. The series of questions were similar to those asked in a survey of American adults by the National Geographic Society 41 years ago. Questions Without Answers</p>
        <p>Among participants from the United States, no more than half those tested could answer correctly when asked to identify the country in which the Sandinistas and the contras are fighting; 52 percent were aware that the Soviet Union's war with rebel forces was in Afghanistan; 55 percent could identify South Africa as the country where apartheid is official government policy; only 25 percent could name four countries that officially acknowledge having nuclear weapons.</p>
        <p>The study also found that half the Americans could not list any of the seven Warsaw Pact countries, and only 20 percent could name four. More than one in 10 said the United States was a member of the Communist-bloc organization.</p>
        <p>The study concluded that fewer than half of all Americans knew that most United States immigrants today came from Mexico and Central America.</p>
        <p>Although nearly 70 percent of Americans surveyed said the ability to read a map was absolutely necessary in today's world, more than a third could not pick out the westernmost city on a map or calculate the distance between two designated cities, given a mileage scale.</p>
        <p>In addition, the survey cited the level of education as clearly the most important indicator of geographic literacy, with people having at least some college education scoring considerably higher. Exposure to maps, globes, travel experience and geography courses were also factors in geographic knowledge.</p>
        <p>''Given the generally higher level of education today, lack of overall improvement suggests that the situation is actually worse,'' said Jeffrey S. Friedman, senior study director for the Gallup Organization.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Grosvenor, the society president, was not beyond being lost in thought. Asked at the luncheon, along with the audience, to identify the states surrounding Texas, he named New Mexico, Louisiana and Oklahoma but failed to mention Arkansas.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
