<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scientists Dream Up Bold Remedies for Ailing Atmosphere</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="171262"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LASERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOLAR ENERGY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Laser (Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission of Radiation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DC173BF935A2575BC0A96E948260" item-length="1804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scientists Dream Up Bold Remedies for Ailing Atmosphere</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: AS scientists and public officials urge painful, expensive measures to prevent climate change -reducing energy use, developing alternative sources of power, curbing production of destructive pollutants - a breed of visionaries is dreaming of more direct, if seemingly fantastic, countermeasures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: AS scientists and public officials urge painful, expensive measures to prevent climate change -reducing energy use, developing alternative sources of power, curbing production of destructive pollutants - a breed of visionaries is dreaming of more direct, if seemingly fantastic, countermeasures.</p>
        <p>AS scientists and public officials urge painful, expensive measures to prevent climate change -reducing energy use, developing alternative sources of power, curbing production of destructive pollutants - a breed of visionaries is dreaming of more direct, if seemingly fantastic, countermeasures.</p>
        <p>These experts are exploring extraordinary ways to combat pollution in the earth's atmosphere and its threat of climatic upheaval. They envision environmental wars fought with lasers that blast apart harmful chemicals, satellites that beam safe energy to earth, microoorganisms that soak up pollutants and chemical-releasing airships that replace critical elements being removed from the earth's atmosphere.</p>
        <p>One aim is to counter the gases that produce the greenhouse effect, which is thought to be gradually warming the earth, threatening to raise oceans and damage agricultural production. Another is to halt the breakdown of the ozone layer, which blocks the sun's ultraviolet rays.</p>
        <p>Work on futuristic cures for these pollution problems started in the 1970's and has accelerated in the 1980's as concern has grown about potential damage to the atmosphere. Experts involved in the research stress that the ideas are often untested and in some cases could be risky. Most experts agree that for now, preventing the release of harmful gases into the sky deserves far higher priority than efforts to fix a damaged atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Yet the surge of creative thinking, they add, could ultimately play an important role in the battle to stabilize the earth's changing weather, especially if conditions take a dramatic turn for the worse.</p>
        <p>''Some of this is mighty speculative,'' said Thomas H. Stix, a Princeton University physicist. ''But if we have a couple of summers like we just had, people are going to get pretty panicky over what we should do about it.''</p>
        <p>Key questions are whether the techniques are safe and feasible, and, if so, whether the potentially huge cost of carrying them out would be economically justified. In addition, some experts warn that large-scale intervention in the earth's delicate and poorly understood cycles of climatic chemistry could trigger unwanted side effects.</p>
        <p>Backers of the research say its value often lies not so much in sparking concrete plans as in inspiring thought about how, ultimately, to deal with climate problems.</p>
        <p>''This area has been given little thought,'' said Wallace S. Broecker, professor of geochemistry at Columbia University. ''At a minimum, a rational society needs some sort of insurance policy on how to maintain a habitable planet.''</p>
        <p>One futuristic idea is to use giant lasers atop mountains to scrub harmful chemicals from the earth's atmosphere, a concept pioneered by Dr. Stix at Princeton. He calls it ''atmospheric processing.'' His lasers would be aimed at industrial chemicals known as chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, which are used mainly in refrigerants and in the manufacture of plastic foams. Once released in the air, they rise high into the stratosphere where they destroy protective ozone. Stratospheric ozone helps block ultraviolet light, which can cause skin cancer and eye damage and harm natural systems. Array of Infrared Lasers</p>
        <p>The laser system would break apart CFC's in the lower atmosphere before they had a chance to damage the ozone layer. The concentrated light would be tuned to a frequency most easily absorbed by CFC's, which is in the infrared part of the electromagnetic spectrum. Dr. Stix calculates that an array of infrared lasers around the world could blast apart as one million tons of CFC a year, equal to the current annual flow into the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>In terms of feasibility, Dr. Stix said: ''Some of the answers are known. Many aren't. A major question is whether you can get the laser's energy absorbed by CFC's and not other molecules, such as water vapor or carbon dioxide.''</p>
        <p>Another issue, he added, is to what extent the general atmosphere would absorb laser energy, limiting propagation of the beam. Plans to Replace Ozone</p>
        <p>A less exotic cure for ozone depletion would be to simply replace it. Experts have proposed that bulk ozone be produced on earth and lofted into the stratosphere in rockets, aircraft or balloons. Other ideas include firing aloft ''bullets'' of frozen ozone, or placing solar-powered ozone generators in high-altitude balloons. Since ozone consists of three oxygen atoms, and atmospheric oxygen has two such atoms, raw material would be plentiful.</p>
        <p>Leon Y. Sadler, a chemical engineer at the University of Alabama, writing recently in Chemical and Engineering News, proposed using a fleet of jets to dispense ozone. His calculations showed that the number of planes needed to replenish of the ozone would be equivalent to less than 2 percent of the aircraft that haul freight in the United States.</p>
        <p>But other scientists have calculated that the job would be many times larger. ''Ozone replacement would be a really massive, massive thing to do,'' said Michael C. MacCracken, head of atmospheric sciences at the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory in California For now, all scientists stress the importance of reducing emission of ozone-destroying chemicals, as called for in a recent treaty.</p>
        <p>On another front in the pollution war, scientists are proposing to counter the effects of carbon dioxide and other trace gases that are rapidly accumulating in the atmosphere. These chemicals, the by-products of fossil fuel combustion, other industrial activities and deforestation, trap heat from the sun that would otherwise be radiated back into space, acting like a greenhouse. Mimic Effect of Volcanoes</p>
        <p>One way to thwart such gases would be to increase the reflectivity of the earth's atmosphere so that more sunlight is reflected back into space, said Dr. Broecker, the geochemist at Columbia University. This happens naturally, he said, when volcanoes spew sulfur dioxide into the atmosphere. In 1982, for instance, El Chichon, a volcano in Mexico, pumped about 8 million tons of sulfur dioxide into the atmosphere, causing a slight planetary cooling.</p>
        <p>Dr. Broecker said about 35 million tons of sulfur dioxide would have to be transported to the stratosphere each year to counter the global warming produced by a doubling of the carbon dioxide in the earth's atmosphere, which is expected in the next century. The job, he said, would require a fleet of several hundred jumbo jets.</p>
        <p>''This is not a big expense compared to totally changing our reliance on fossil fuels,'' Dr. Broecker said in an interview. But the method would have major drawbacks, he added, noting that it would increase acid rain and give the blue sky a whitish cast.</p>
        <p>''The point is not that the strategy is necessarily a wise one, but, rather, that purposeful global climate modification lies within our grasp,'' Dr. Broecker wrote in his book, ''How to Build a Habitable Planet.'' He added: ''One hundred years from now the temptation to take such action may be high.'' Chips on the Oceans</p>
        <p>Other proposed ways to increase the earth's reflectivity are equally drastic. They include covering much of the world's oceans with white Styrofoam chips, which would reflect more sunlight back into space than regular ocean water, and painting the roofs of all houses white. It is not known to what extent such actions might offset global warming.</p>
        <p>Some dream of blocking sunlight before it ever reaches the earth. Giant orbiting satellites made of thin films could cast shadows on the earth, counteracting global warming. Scientists have calculated that a series of satellites with areas equivalent to 2 percent of the earth's surface could compensate for a doubling in carbon dioxide. Some space scientists have contemplated using such shields to make Venus less hot; the costs and benefits on earth have not been determined.</p>
        <p>Still another way of coping with greenhouse gases would be to try to remove them from the atmosphere. Measures to conserve and plant new forests, which absorb carbon, are already being discussed by public officials. More radical thinkers imagine encouraging the growth on a vast scale of tiny ocean organisms that soak up carbon dioxide. Already, the oceans are believed to be dissolving much of the extra carbon dioxide in the atmosphere. The bodies of microscopic creatures, for instance, incorporate carbon dioxide and, when they die, they sink to the bottom of the sea and turn into limestone.</p>
        <p>To increase this effect, scientists have proposed fertilizing the oceans to spur the growth of phytoplankton, microscopic plants that are a key element in the ocean's food chain. But this method has serious drawbacks. It would alter the marine food chain, and, if pursued too vigorously, the cascade of carbon dioxide into the deep ocean would eventually eliminate oxygen there, killing most life.</p>
        <p>One group of experts holds that proposals to counteract climatic damage are misguided, and that advanced technologies should be used to prevent such problems in the first place, mainly by eliminating dependence on fossil fuels. Harnessing Nuclear Fusion</p>
        <p>Dr. Peter E. Glazer, a vice president at Arthur D. Little Inc., a Cambridge, Mass., consulting and research firm, has long advocated building a fleet of solar power satellites in space. Illuminated by the sun 24 hours a day, these spacecraft would turn sunlight into electric power, which would be beamed to earth in the form of either microwave or laser beams, and then turned back into electricity. First proposed in the 1970's, the idea has recently aroused renewed interest because of its environmental allure.</p>
        <p>A more down-to-earth way to generate power without producing carbon dioxide is to harness nuclear fusion, the process in which hydrogen isotopes fuse together to release energy in the kind of process that powers the sun, the stars and hydrogen bombs. While conventional nuclear power plants also supply energy without carbon dioxide pollution, they are mired in political, environmental and economic disputes.</p>
        <p>The problem is achieving the fusion technique.</p>
        <p>''Fusion is still a matter for physicists to grapple with,'' Dr. Glazer said. ''On the other hand, solar power satellites are just a matter for aerospace engineers to design and build.''</p>
        <p>While futurists clash over the best way to save the planet with exotic technologies, other experts warn that the debate should not deflect attention from the more pragmatic approaches to dealing with climate ills.</p>
        <p>''It's reasonable to ask if there's anything to do to repair the damage,'' said said Michael Oppenheimer, an atmospheric physicist at the Environmental Defense Fund, based in New York. ''But the effort and scale of some of these things is huge. It's probably cheaper in the long run to rely on prevention rather than unusual cures.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
