<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unstable, Shifting Climate Defies Computer Models</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="129180"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATHLETICS AND SPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DC153FF933A15750C0A96E948260" item-length="741" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unstable, Shifting Climate Defies Computer Models</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: By changing the contents of the earth's atmosphere, humans are delivering a sharp kick to a machine that scientists now believe capable of rapid and unstable responses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: By changing the contents of the earth's atmosphere, humans are delivering a sharp kick to a machine that scientists now believe capable of rapid and unstable responses.</p>
        <p>By changing the contents of the earth's atmosphere, humans are delivering a sharp kick to a machine that scientists now believe capable of rapid and unstable responses.</p>
        <p>A central assumption of many scientists monitoring earth's climate has been that it would respond to human influence in a steady, gradual way. That assumption is now being undermined by the surprising ozone measurements and by a new understanding of the interaction of air and oceans.</p>
        <p>Changes in ozone are linked to climate processes as scientists discover that ozone chemistry can affect the circulation of the upper atmosphere. And the concern about ozone parallels another climatic issue, the warming of the atmosphere by carbon dioxide and other gases. Ice Evidence</p>
        <p>Some experts go so far as to argue that the climate can suddenly - within a century or less - flip into an entirely different state. Indeed, they say that evidence recently drawn from cores of ancient polar ice and ocean sediments show that past climates have already done just that.</p>
        <p>''What these records indicate is that earth's climate does not respond to forcing in a smooth and gradual way,'' Wallace S. Broecker of Columbia University's Lamont-Doherty Geophysical Institute wrote last July in the journal Nature. ''Rather it responds in sharp jumps which involve large-scale reorganization of Earth's system.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Broecker noted that some seemingly reliable weather patterns are quirks that could be unstable. For example, northern Europe is far warmer than it should be, because currents of the Atlantic Ocean circulate in just the right way. Those currents have sometimes reversed themselves, like a flywheel changing direction, rapidly chilling the continent.</p>
        <p>''We must consider the possibility that the main responses of the system to our provocation of the atmosphere will come in jumps whose timing and magnitude are unpredictable,'' Dr. Broecker wrote. Rare Complexity</p>
        <p>The recognition that the climate is a system of entangled and interlocking parts, scientists say, means it is capable of behavior that does not appear in simple computer models. By design, such models tend to change smoothly.</p>
        <p>The seasonal ozone hole that has appeared over Antarctica in the 1980's stands as the most dramatic example of an effect that the models failed to forecast, despite a decade of intense interest in calculating the effects of chlorine gases in the atmosphere. The chemical and meteorological processes responsible for the hole turn out to be too complex to have been predicted.</p>
        <p>''It's very unusual chemistry, and people are barely beginning to understand the processes,'' said Michael J. Prather, a NASA scientist responsible for the next generation of ozone forecasts. ''What we lack is an understanding of what the polar regions are like in a natural state. We've only gone there after it was a perturbed environment.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Prather's models are beginning to explore interactions between the chemistry and the circulation of air in the upper atmosphere, with striking and sometimes contradictory results.</p>
        <p>Interactions elsewhere in the climate system are just beginning to be understood. In the last decade, for example, scientists have recognized a cycle of changes in the oceans and atmosphere, known as El Nino, linking changes in water temperatures with rainfall patterns over areas as far apart as Latin America and southern Asia. Out of Equilibrium</p>
        <p>Until they better understand the changeable arms and gears of the climate machine, scientists worry that they can barely guess the ultimate consequences of human influences. The emission of chlorine gases and carbon dioxide are the two most serious influences: chlorine breaking down the ozone layer and carbon dioxide warming the earth.</p>
        <p>''We have a system that's guaranteed to be out of equilibrium,'' said Stephen H. Schneider, a climate expert at the National Center for Atmospheric Research. ''The physical system is going to be out of equilibrium, the biological system is going to be out of equilibrium, and so is the social system. Good luck, Charlie, trying to forecast that.''</p>
        <p>One possibility, he said, is that as ocean temperatures and land temperatures change at different rates, unexpected monsoon patterns may appear.</p>
        <p>''The lesson is, don't fool around with Mother Nature at unprecedented rates, or you get nasty surprises,'' Dr. Schneider said. ''There are probably other surprises out there.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
