<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Summer of Our Discontent</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="173894"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEASONS AND MONTHS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NINETEEN HUNDRED EIGHTY-EIGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DD1F3CF937A1575BC0A96E948260" item-length="357" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Summer of Our Discontent</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ''The summer of '88,'' our children will tell their children, ''started like any other summer. A little rain, a little shine, a little warm, a little chill. Then, in early July, something happened.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ''The summer of '88,'' our children will tell their children, ''started like any other summer. A little rain, a little shine, a little warm, a little chill. Then, in early July, something happened.</p>
        <p>''The summer of '88,'' our children will tell their children, ''started like any other summer. A little rain, a little shine, a little warm, a little chill. Then, in early July, something happened.</p>
        <p>''The heat. The humidity. The rain. The sodden days, the sleepless nights, the sure, if sudden, conviction that one was losing one's mind. And one was. How else to greet the news that the climate of New York City was now that of a tropical rain forest?</p>
        <p>''Worse, we were trapped. In another summer we might at least have had the beach on weekends. But the water kept bringing in syringes and vials of blood and strips of bandages, and who wants to swim in all that stuff?</p>
        <p>''The only consolation - some consolation! -was that doctors were saying this was no summer to hang around a beach anyway. Skin cancers from exposure to sunlight were increasing, perhaps because the upper atmosphere's ozone layer was letting in more ultraviolet rays.</p>
        <p>''Meanwhile air quality experts were muttering about the dense levels of lung-irritating ozone close to the ground - which might have done the world some good if only it had been a few miles farther up.</p>
        <p>''Then, children, there were the mosquitoes. Did I tell you about the mosquitoes? In June, dry weather had kept them dormant. In July wet weather had stirred them into hatching. In August they were rarin' to go. By the thousands.</p>
        <p>''About mid-August, however, a little breeze stole into town. From Siberia, most likely. People started to breathe again. To talk, to laugh, to get off their couches. And then it happened. The triumph of the mold spores.</p>
        <p>''The hay-feverish among us had been slapping themselves on the back because the hot sun had burned the ragweed. But mold spores, which grow on vegetation, flourish in high humidity. So there they were, leaving snuffling, sneezing and weeping in their wake.</p>
        <p>''In that whole long, miserable summer the only happy people to be found were the pharmacists, and the people who sell air-conditioners. Except that they ran out of air-conditioners to sell and . . . Hey! Where are you going? You haven't heard about the plague of locusts yet!''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
