<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>David Beat Goliath, Moynihan's Challenger Points Out</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="150813"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SENATE (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">REPUBLICAN PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MOYNIHAN, DANIEL PATRICK (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCMILLAN, ROBERT R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAY, CLIFFORD D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7D7113CF930A35755C0A96E948260" item-length="1543" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>David Beat Goliath, Moynihan's Challenger Points Out</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD D. MAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MAY, CLIFFORD D</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: At a news conference in Buffalo recently, Robert R. McMillan, the Republican who on Wednesday announced his candidacy for United States Senator, noticed a young woman who was taking notes but had not been introduced to him. He marched up to her and eagerly extended his hand. Was she covering the race for a local newspaper, he wondered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: At a news conference in Buffalo recently, Robert R. McMillan, the Republican who on Wednesday announced his candidacy for United States Senator, noticed a young woman who was taking notes but had not been introduced to him. He marched up to her and eagerly extended his hand. Was she covering the race for a local newspaper, he wondered.</p>
        <p>At a news conference in Buffalo recently, Robert R. McMillan, the Republican who on Wednesday announced his candidacy for United States Senator, noticed a young woman who was taking notes but had not been introduced to him. He marched up to her and eagerly extended his hand. Was she covering the race for a local newspaper, he wondered. No, the woman replied, a flush rising to her cheeks. She was on the staff of Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan.</p>
        <p>As he tells the story, Mr. McMillan a 56-year-old Long Island lawyer, is unabashedly elated by any sign he is being viewed as a serious challenger to Senator Moynihan. At this point, however, few political experts, Republican or Democratic, believe he stands much of a chance.</p>
        <p>''McMillan's fortunes are totally in Moynihan's hands,'' said Eddie Mahe, a Republican political consultant and former executive director of the Republican National Committee. ''Unless Moynihan manages to do something very silly, McMillan is destined to end up as a sacrificial lamb.'' Low Standing With Oddsmakers</p>
        <p>In several recent interviews, Mr. McMillan said that he was well aware of his low standing with the political oddsmakers but that he intended to prove them wrong. ''People say, 'Don't you feel like David up against Goliath?' '' he said. ''I say, 'Yeah. And David won.' '' Not the First Choice</p>
        <p>Mr. McMillan was not the first choice of New York State's divided and ailing Republican Party. No fewer than a dozen well-known or well-heeled Republicans - including United States Attorney Rudolph W. Giuliani, Representative Jack Kemp and the former Ambassador to Austria, Ronald Lauder - turned down the opportunity to challenge Mr. Moynihan. Now, Mr. McMillan is almost certain to be nominated formally by the Republican Party next week.</p>
        <p>Anthony J. Colavita, the Republican state chairman, said that while the search had been long and arduous, he was enthusiastic about the candidate finally settled upon.</p>
        <p>''I've gone over a lot of resumes,'' he said. ''And Bob McMillan really looks good. He is articulate, aggressive and well read. He has some name recognition on Long Island.''</p>
        <p>The stakes are not meager. A lopsided Democratic victory in the Senate race could insure that New York State goes Democratic in the Presidential election. ''If Moynihan could be defeated,'' Mr. Mahe said, ''and I'm convinced he could be by the right candidate, it could change the outcome of the race for Bush.''</p>
        <p>The last Republican challenger to Mr. Moynihan, Assemblywoman Florence M. Sullivan of Brooklyn, garnered less than a third of the vote.</p>
        <p>''What this is really about is the bankruptcy of the New York Republican Party,'' said John Buckley, a Republican political consultant in Washington and formerly an adviser to Mr. Kemp's Presidential campaign. 'I Have No Illusions'</p>
        <p>Mr. McMillan recognizes what he is up against. ''I have no illusions,'' he said. ''If this were a sure thing, politicians would be lined up 20 feet deep to do it, and I wouldn't have been given the chance.''</p>
        <p>State Senator John R. Dunne, Republican of Garden City, L.I., and Mr. McMillan's law partner, said the candidate had a mission. ''He's out there because he wants to present a message,'' Senator Dunne said.</p>
        <p>So far, the gist seems to be that Mr. Moynihan is a doddering old professor, aloof from the state's meat-and-potatoes concerns, low in energy, weak on follow-through, remote and didactic.</p>
        <p>''He's a Manhattan-Washington Senator,'' Mr. McMillan recently told a group of Republican party workers in Watertown, on the shore of Lake Ontario. ''His strength is writing and lecturing. Come January, maybe he can go back to Harvard and do that.'' Long Digressions</p>
        <p>At another point, Mr. McMillan lambasted Mr. Moynihan's habit of digressing at length. ''He can speak for 15 or 20 minutes and no one knows what he's talking about,'' Mr. McMillan told his audience. ''Am I right?'' A round of applause rang out in answer.</p>
        <p>Mr. McMillan's identification of the Senator's vulnerabilities may be on target, according to political analysts in Washington and New York. The hard part, they said, will be to persuade several million voters that they have a reasonable alternative in a lawyer from Nassau County whose only previous foray into electoral politics was a 1964 race for Councilman against Matthew Troy in Queens. Mr. Troy won by a margin of better than 2 to 1.</p>
        <p>Not that Mr. McMillan is unimpressive. Athletically trim, cleft-chinned, with pale skin and dark hair combed back from a sharp widow's peak, he comes across as personable and neighborly.</p>
        <p>The son of a Canadian immigrant who became manager of a Brooklyn bakery, Mr. McMillan was awarded a Bronze Star while serving as an Army first lieutenant during the Korean conflict. Returning home, he attended Brooklyn Law School at night, working as a court officer by day. He then worked his way up the corporate ladder at Abraham &amp; Straus, Mobil Oil Corporation and Avon Products. Was Assistant to Nixon</p>
        <p>Since 1986, Mr. McMillan has been a senior partner at a Long Island law firm whose other top partners include Senator Dunne and Birch Bayh, the former Democratic Senator from Indiana. Mr. McMillan has also served as a special counsel to Kenneth B. Keating, who represented New York in the Senate, and as a special assistant - answering letters from V.I.P.'s - to President Nixon.</p>
        <p>Mr. McMillan has been a member of numerous government commissions and boards, and has been chairman of Mr. Dunne's re-election finance committee for a decade, as well as a member of Vice President Bush's campaign steering committee since 1985.</p>
        <p>Mr. McMillan has been almost frenetically active in community affairs, serving on the the board of a local performing arts group, leading a drive for affordable housing on Long Island, supporting Nassau County's Boy Scouts and writing an opinion column for a chain of weekly newspapers. He and his wife, Jane, an elementary school teacher, have three children and live in Garden City.</p>
        <p>''I've known Bob for many, many years,'' said Representative Edolphus Towns, Democrat of Brooklyn. ''I met him when I was deputy borough president and he was a vice president with Abraham &amp; Straus.'' While he planned to support his own party's nominee and was not predicting a McMillan victory, Mr. Towns said he had ''tremendous respect for Bob, for his credibility.'' 'A Hard Worker'</p>
        <p>''He was respected by the whole community, blacks, whites, merchants,'' Mr. Towns said. ''He's a hard worker and very competent. Pat should not take this guy lightly.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McMillan said he did not want his campaign to be only an assault on Mr. Moynihan, that he hoped also to ''express myself on the important issues.''</p>
        <p>So far, however, the positions he has articulated do not appear to contrast strikingly with those of Senator Moynihan. He seeks a ''massive Marshall Plan'' to lift Central America from poverty, he wants tough legislation to combat acid rain and other pollutants and, like countless other politicians this year, he is talking tough on drugs.</p>
        <p>''Maybe we should say to Colombia, 'Shape up your act or we won't buy your coffee,' '' he told an audience in Plattsburgh. Asked if it would be fair or effective to punish legitimate Colombian farmers for the actions of criminals, he replied, ''Maybe it will make the legitimate businessmen put pressure on their Government to stop the drugs.'' Asked if he was certain that business leaders in Colombia wield influence over their Government in such matters, he said he believed they did. Investment, Not Contribution</p>
        <p>To convey these and other opinions competitively, Mr. McMillan will need to raise a great deal of money very rapidly. That could be tough.</p>
        <p>''Everyone talks about contributing to a campaign,'' Mr. Mahe said. ''But the fact is people don't contibute to campaigns, they only invest in them. And there is no use in investing in campaigns that are going to lose.''</p>
        <p>An experienced fund-raiser, Mr. McMillan said he was setting up a 50-member finance committee with each member responsible for bringing in between $10,000 and $50,000. If he can pull that off, he hopes to get up to $1.2 million from the Republican Senatorial Committee in Washington.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moynihan, by comparison, has raised more than $4 million, about half of which has been spent. He plans to raise at least $5 million, his office said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Contrary to some reports, Mr. McMillan does not plan to invest a fortune of his own in the campaign. His net worth, he said, is under $1 million. His income, as an equity partner in his law firm, totals about $300,000 a year, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. McMillan, in the eyes of some, is in a ''win win'' situation. If he should defeat Mr. Moynihan, he will be seen as a miracle worker. If he loses respectably and Mr. Bush goes on to the White House, there could be all manner of rewards - perhaps a Justice Department post or an ambassadorship - for a loyalist who rallied the Republican vote in New York under difficult circumstances.</p>
        <p>And even if he is roundly defeated and the Vice President goes down too, by January of next year, Bob McMillan is bound to be one of the best-known lawyers and Republican politicians from Lake Erie to Long Island Sound.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
