<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World History, as Tree Rings Tell It, Gains Accuracy</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="135343"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREES AND SHRUBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VOLCANOES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HISTORY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DF1631F931A25757C0A96E948260" item-length="1748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World History, as Tree Rings Tell It, Gains Accuracy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Recent studies of tree rings in Europe and the United States have given scientists astonishingly precise new gauges for reconstructing the history of volcanoes, climate and human endeavor in the last 8,500 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Recent studies of tree rings in Europe and the United States have given scientists astonishingly precise new gauges for reconstructing the history of volcanoes, climate and human endeavor in the last 8,500 years.</p>
        <p>Recent studies of tree rings in Europe and the United States have given scientists astonishingly precise new gauges for reconstructing the history of volcanoes, climate and human endeavor in the last 8,500 years.</p>
        <p>Tree rings, as distinctively patterned by fluctuations in the environment as bullets are by gun barrels, were recognized half a century ago as potentially useful historical markers. In 1930, Dr. Andrew Ellicott Douglas of the University of Arizona established the science of tree-ring dating, dendrochronology, when he used the rings discernible in ancient wooden artifacts to determine the age of a prehistoric Indian site.</p>
        <p>But only recently have scientists accumulated enough wood samples and other evidence from bogs, ice layers, medieval ruins, ancient campfires and many other sources to extend dendrochronology to objects almost as old as the last Ice Age. New understanding of the significance of tree rings has also allowed scientists to calibrate other less precise techniques for determining the ages of objects, thereby making the entire field of age determination more reliable and accurate.</p>
        <p>Archeologists are quickly putting the new knowledge to practical use. Last week, for example, Dr. Peter I. Kuniholm of Cornell University extracted tree-ring samples from the cedar planking of a boat built in Egypt in the 16th century B.C. The boat, owned by the Carnegie Museum in Pittsburgh, is believed to have been built while Egypt was ruled by the Hyksos ''shepherd'' kings, a time when few written records were kept, Dr. Kuniholm said. The tree-ring dating techniques he plans to apply to the samples may help archeologists sort out the detailed chronology of the Hyksos period.</p>
        <p>In Europe and the Middle East archeologists have started scores of new tree-ring dating projects. In one, Dr. Michael G. L. Baillie of Queen's University, Belfast, and his colleagues expect to determine the exact date of a neolithic roadway in Somerset, England. The wooden trackway, known as Sweet Track, was laid across a marsh around 3800 B.C., but with the help of tree rings, the scientists expect to determine the exact years in which its trees were felled.</p>
        <p>Tree rings have also provided geologists and climatologists with a new tool for answering some old questions. Among other things, they hope to learn whether the gigantic volcanic eruptions that have punctuated geological history have occurred as clusters in relatively short periods. Climatologists are also intrigued by fresh evidence from tree rings that huge ancient eruptions may have had far more lasting effects on climate than had been supposed.</p>
        <p>A major landmark in dendrochronology was reported last month in the British journal Nature by Dr. Baillie and his colleagues. The Belfast scientist reported that traces of at least five major eruptions in prehistoric or ancient times are clearly visible in the rings of Irish oaks that grew over the last 7,272 years.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the major eruption dates -4377 B.C., 3199 B.C., 1628 B.C., 1153 B.C. and A.D. 541 - almost perfectly match the years for which eruptions were also detected in the rings of North American bristlecone pines and in thin layers of acidic ice within the Greenland ice cap. C.U. Hammer and his colleagues in Denmark analyzed the Greenland ice.</p>
        <p>Dr. Malcolm K. Hughes, director of the dendrochronology laboratory at the University of Arizona, explained in an interview that large volcanic eruptions leave widespread permanent traces in at least two ways. First, volcanoes eject large amounts of sulfur dioxide which, when dissolved in water, is precipitated as sulfuric acid in rain or snow. On an ice cap, it is embedded in an ice layer that is gradually covered by successive layers of non-acidic ice. By drilling through the layers and measuring their acidity, scientists can estimate how long ago any given eruption may have spread acid rain over the earth.</p>
        <p>Erupting volcanoes also create dust veils that circle the planet, reducing sunlight and chilling the climate. In North America, this has caused brief periods of frost damage to pine trees, and such damage can be seen in a tree ring representing a single cold year. In Irish and German oaks, longer-term effects of volcanoes are discernible: after major eruptions, the rings for several successive years are thinner than normal because of slow growth in protracted periods of cold.</p>
        <p>Large eruptions have stamped sharply defined benchmarks on tree rings and ice, and these markers have permitted scientists to reconcile many dating techniques and improve the accuracy of all. Moreover, scientists in the United States and Ireland have discovered how to use tree-ring chronologies to greatly enhance the precision of carbon dating in determining the ages of organic objects by their radioactivity. Correcting Carbon 14 Errors</p>
        <p>Using tree rings, Dr. Gordon Pearson of Queen's College, Belfast, and Dr. Minsi Stuiver of the University of Washington, Seattle, have independently discovered an important relationship between the true age of a wooden object and its apparent age as determined by carbon dating. This means that archeologists, historians, geologists and other researchers will be able to apply known correction factors to ages determined by carbon dating, and thereby drastically reduce errors.</p>
        <p>Conventional carbon dating relies on the gradual decay of a radioactive form of carbon called carbon 14. All living things assimilate carbon from the environment, and a certain proportion is carbon 14. But when a plant or animal dies, it no longer assimilates carbon, and the carbon 14 it contains gradually decays, losing its radioactivity. By measuring this loss, a scientist can estimate the age of a bone, a piece of wood or any other carbon-based remnant.</p>
        <p>However, inaccuracies are caused by the fact that the ratio of radioactive carbon to ordinary carbon in the environment varies over the years. Dr. Pearson and Dr. Stuiver discovered that when the true ages of wooden objects, as calculated from tree rings, are plotted on a graph against the objects' apparent ages, as determined by carbon dating, a wiggly rather than a straight line results. The wiggles represent historic fluctuations in the environment that have continuously altered the ratios of carbon 14 to ordinary carbon.</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Hughes, these wiggles follow the same pattern in both Europe and America, and therefore provide a universal correction scale for carbon dating, at least in the temperate zone of the Northern Hemisphere. Unbroken Chronologies</p>
        <p>But before such achievements were possible, scientists needed to obtain complete tree-ring chronologies extending backward in time for thousands of years, in unbroken sequences. Only in the last few years have such chronologies been available.</p>
        <p>One, completed in Ireland in 1984, established an unbroken record of tree rings in oak trees extending from the present to 7,272 years ago. Another important chronology spanning about 8,500 years was established from tree rings in bristlecone pines in the White Mountains of California. Similar chronologies have been developed recently in two regions of West Germany.</p>
        <p>The task of assembling chronologies and then of matching them against samples of unknown age is staggering. Scientists must use computers both in measuring individual tree rings and in finding patterns that match.</p>
        <p>''Basically,'' Dr. Baillie said, ''when you're building a chronology, you start out by measuring the widths and distribution of rings in living trees. An oak tree typically lives about 250 years and a bristlecone pine may live up to 4,500 years. We like to work with the longest-lived species we can.</p>
        <p>''The next step is to find some old wood whose age overlaps that of living trees, so you can see where the ring sequences overlap. In Europe, a lot of the material we use in this stage of the chronology comes from beams and planks in historic buildings, and that takes us back through the Middle Ages.</p>
        <p>''You just keep looking for overlapping ring patterns in wood farther and farther back, but once you get to the time of Christ, you begin to run out of man-made wooden objects. So you look for dead trees naturally preserved in bogs. We find such bogs mainly in Ireland, England and Germany.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Baillie said the Irish project began in 1970 and took 14 years, while 6,000 wood specimens were collected to complete an unbroken chronology. Date of Huge Eruption</p>
        <p>One of the most significant markers in all the chronologies is a stunted ring or a group of narrow rings clustered around the year 1628 B.C. Investigators in Europe and the United States are now virtually certain that this was the year of the explosive eruption of a monster volcano on the Greek island of Santorini, known in ancient times as Thera. The Santorini eruption was recently estimated to have had three or four times the power of the famous Krakatoa eruption of 1883, one of the most violent in modern times.</p>
        <p>From the tree-ring evidence, scientists have concluded that the Santorini eruption sharply lowered global temperatures for several years a development that may have affected civilization in many ways.</p>
        <p>In any case, The new dating techniques have forced archeologists to revise chronologies of Minoan history, in which the Santorini volcano was traditionally dated around 1500 B.C. Wood Used by Dutch Masters</p>
        <p>The new analytical precision afforded by tree rings has even cast light on the old masters of English and Dutch painting, including Holbein and Rembrandt.</p>
        <p>Working with experts in several countries, Dr. Baillie undertook an examination of the oak panels on which many artists in Britain and the Low Countries painted in the 14th to 17th centuries. He found that these panels are slightly curved rather than flat, and that they contain identifiable sequences of tree rings.</p>
        <p>At first it seemed that the dates of many paintings, accurately known from historical records, failed to match their tree-ring dates. But then Dr. Baillie discovered that the tree-ring sequences of western Europe are six years out of phase with the comparable sequences of oak trees that grew in the East European Baltic states. It seems, therefore, that the Dutch masters imported their wood from Poland or Lithuania.</p>
        <p>''Of course,'' Dr. Baillie said, ''all these techniques are based on circumstantial evidence. But when you get this much of it, your case becomes strong enough to start hanging people.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
