<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Population Size Can't Be Overlooked as an Environmental Danger</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="193299"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POPULATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEGATIVE POPULATION GROWTH INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MANN, DONALD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DE1039F932A05753C1A96E948260" item-length="558" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Population Size Can't Be Overlooked as an Environmental Danger</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your editorial ''The Next Generation of Poison'' (Oct. 9) provides an excellent description of the environmental dangers that now threaten the earth's natural systems on which all life and economic activity depend.</p>
        <p>The remedies you feel are sensible - which include banning CFC's, saving tropical forests and using energy more efficiently - while they are necessary, fall far short of measures that must be taken to create an economy that would be sustainable for the very long term.</p>
        <p>You fail to mention the most necessary and fundamental measure of all - stabilizing United States and world population size at a sustainable level. This would require a substantial reduction in world population from the present number of more than 5 billion to perhaps 1.5 billion to 2 billion, and a reduction in United States population size from the present 245 million to between 100 million and 150 million.</p>
        <p>There is not one threat to our environment - whether global warming, acid rain or the depletion of the ozone layer - that would not be alleviated by a substantial reduction in United States and world population size. On the other hand, there is not one environmental threat that will not be intensified (perhaps to catastrophic proportions) by further population growth in an already vastly over-populated nation and world.</p>
        <p>It is a simple fact that man's impact on the environment is the product of two factors: the number of people multiplied by per capita consumption of resources, and per capita production of pollution. Our present impact is so far beyond a sustainable level that action must be taken to change both sides of the equation.</p>
        <p>Why is it so rarely recognized that population size is a variable just as, for example, per capita consumption of energy? Why is it always implicitly assumed that population size is as immutable as the heavens, and can no more be influenced by human will and action than the motion of the planets in their orbit around the sun?</p>
        <p>If we are to increase our chances of avoiding severe penalties (a lowered standard of living and quality of life) in the near future, plus the very real possibility of outright disaster (the destruction of the earth's life-support systems), we must no longer delay both in asking ourselves, and finding an answer to, a fundamental question:</p>
        <p>With present technology, at what level must United States and world population size be stabilized in order to permit the creation of a society and economy that would be sustainable over the very long term, with an adequate standard of living for all, in a sound and healthy environment?</p>
        <p>The answer to that question provides a good working definition of optimum population size, a concept that should be central to our plans to restore and protect our environment. Tragically, that concept is almost always completely absent from our deliberations.</p>
        <p>The great lesson of the Industrial Revolution, virtually ignored until now, is that vast numbers of people are simply incompatible with an industrial society. If we continue to ignore that lesson, we may succeed far sooner than we think in rendering our planet uninhabitable. That frightening prospect no longer seems as far-fetched as it would have even a year ago. DONALD MANN  President  Negative Population Growth Inc.  New York, Oct. 12, 1988</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
