<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When the Party's Over, The Wine Can Stay On</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="210626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="CONSUMER'S WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDBERG, HOWARD G</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CONSUMER'S WORLD PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881231T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DA1630F932A05751C1A96E948260" item-length="924" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When the Party's Over, The Wine Can Stay On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD G. GOLDBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDBERG, HOWARD G</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The guests are gone, and the partly empty bottles of still wine and Champagne have been carried to the kitchen. Unless the wines are properly tended, oxidation - shown by a musty aroma, flat flavor, discoloration - will quickly spoil them. How can this investment be protected?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The guests are gone, and the partly empty bottles of still wine and Champagne have been carried to the kitchen. Unless the wines are properly tended, oxidation - shown by a musty aroma, flat flavor, discoloration - will quickly spoil them. How can this investment be protected?</p>
        <p>The guests are gone, and the partly empty bottles of still wine and Champagne have been carried to the kitchen. Unless the wines are properly tended, oxidation - shown by a musty aroma, flat flavor, discoloration - will quickly spoil them. How can this investment be protected?</p>
        <p>Wine enthusiasts are increasingly turning to an array of devices. The manufacturers say they keep flavor and bouquet fresh for days, sometimes for several weeks. Commercial and personal experience shows that, by and large, the claims are accurate.</p>
        <p>At least four types of equipment for red and white still wine are available. Two more are designed to save Champagne and other sparkling wines. After any are used, white wines should be refrigerated and reds stored in a cool place. Dispensers should be flushed frequently with warm water to combat spoilage.  Removing the Air</p>
        <p>One of the most popular wares for still wine is the vacuum device typified by the Vacu-Vin, made in the Netherlands. It consists of rubber stoppers to be inserted in bottles, and a hand pump that sucks out air, creating a vacuum. It costs about $15 in Bloomingdale's and Zabar's, and is sold at some Neiman-Marcus stores and at wine stores like Schaefer's, in Skokie, Ill., a Chicago suburb.</p>
        <p>The most costly equipment is the so-called wine preservation and dispensing system familiar to patrons of wine bars and some restaurants. The most prominent models are made by the Cruvinet company of Santa Monica, Calif. Winekeeper, of Santa Barbara, Calif., makes similar products.</p>
        <p>As a push button, faucet or handle releases wine into a glass, nitrogen - an odorless, tasteless, inert gas - flows into the partly empty bottle, protectively blanketing the remaining wine and forcing oxygen out.</p>
        <p>A third apparatus is a $5.95 canister holding nitrogen and carbon dioxide. Known as Private Preserve, it is sold by the Wine Appreciation Guild in San Francisco. It has a nozzle to channel the gas into the bottle, which must be recorked immediately.</p>
        <p>A fourth type has a dispenser with a detachable balloonlike pouch that is suspended inside the bottle. As wine is poured out, air enters the pouch, which expands to replace the lost liquid. The product, named Wine-by-the-Glass, is sold in Los Angeles and will soon reach New York City, according to Robert D. Stackhouse, who said he helped invent it and whose company is in San Rafael, Calif. He sells it and three pouches for $29.95.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stackhouse and some analysts question the main claim on Vacu-Vin's package: ''Takes air out.''  'Only a Portion'</p>
        <p>''The pump does not take out all the air,'' he said. ''It takes out only a portion. Vacu-Vin is a faulty concept, because even if you could pull all the air out, you pull a lot of aroma off.''</p>
        <p>Anthony Lemme, the president of the Source Intermarketing Corporation, a Wallingford, Conn., company that imports and distributes the product, disagreed. ''No one ever claimed it will take out all the air,'' he said. ''When the pump is properly operated, less than 3 percent of the oxygen remains. The aroma is not removed.''</p>
        <p>Michael Aaron, the president of Sherry-Lehmann, the Manhattan wine shop, is a Vacu-Vin fan. ''It's unbelievable,'' he said. ''It kept a bottle of Jadot Meursault fresh for three weeks.''</p>
        <p>New York law bars the sale of such equipment in wine stores. But home Cruvinets are sold by Hammacher Schlemmer and Kedco Wine Storage Systems of Syosset, L.I., which also handles Winekeeper products.</p>
        <p>Carlo Russo's Wine and Spirit World in Fort Lee, N.J., sells nearly the entire two- and four-bottle Cruvinet line, as advertised in the Wine Spectator Collection's ubiquitous catalogue; the prices range from $199 to $1,495. The models' black plastic, oak and brass-finished cabinets hide the stubby nitrogen cylinder.</p>
        <p>The Wine Enthusiast, a nationally distributed catalogue, promotes the Vintage Keeper, a simple $49.95 nitrogen system. The stopper-and-dispenser unit connects to a canister that is supposed to service 25 bottles; extra canisters cost $9 each.</p>
        <p>Champagne's carbon dioxide bubbles can be kept alive several days by a resealing cylinder, popularly called a recorker, that clips to the bottle's lip and contains a spring that presses a disk onto the mouth. One version is $6.50 at Macy's Herald Square. The Wine Enthusiast offers a $25 hand pump that drives air through a stopper, creating high pressure and holding the fizz for two weeks, the company said.</p>
        <p>No protection is perfect: since wine is organic, it changes even when unopened. Where, then, is fine wine best preserved? That's easy, said James Trezise, president of the New York Wine and Grape Foundation, a promotion and research organization: ''Only in memory.''  SAVING MORE THAN VINTAGES</p>
        <p>If high tech helps preserve opened wine, low tech - no tech? - does so at least as well, specialists maintain.</p>
        <p>Mary Ewing Mulligan, the director of the International Wine Center, a recently reopened wine school in Manhattan, likes ''the simplest system of all: one wine collectors have long used.''</p>
        <p>''Pour off leftover wine into a clean half bottle and recork it,'' she recommended. ''If the bottle is filled nearly to the cork and sealed tightly, the wine will last much longer than it would under many modern systems.''</p>
        <p>An alternative is child's play: fill the bottle with sterilized marbles. They displace leftover wine into the narrow neck, minimizing the volume of air. Then recork the bottle. One caution: pour carefully so that a marble doesn't chip or shatter the wine glass.</p>
        <p>CONSUMER'S WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
