<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leonardo of the Links</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="197568"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOLF</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LANDSCAPE ARCHITECTURE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">JONES, ROBERT TRENT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JONES, ROBERT TRENT JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KIERSH, EDWARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2DB173FF930A25752C1A96E948260" item-length="4128" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leonardo of the Links</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Edward Kiersh: Edward Kiersh, a freelance writer, has just finished a book about the history of television.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KIERSH, EDWARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: STEERING A GOLF CART ACROSS THE PRECIPITOUS fairways of Bossey, his mountainous course in eastern France, just across the border from Geneva, Robert Trent Jones Jr. points to several sand traps and greens, explaining that he is the only landscaper capable of having designed them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: STEERING A GOLF CART ACROSS THE PRECIPITOUS fairways of Bossey, his mountainous course in eastern France, just across the border from Geneva, Robert Trent Jones Jr. points to several sand traps and greens, explaining that he is the only landscaper capable of having designed them.</p>
        <p>STEERING A GOLF CART ACROSS THE PRECIPITOUS fairways of Bossey, his mountainous course in eastern France, just across the border from Geneva, Robert Trent Jones Jr. points to several sand traps and greens, explaining that he is the only landscaper capable of having designed them.</p>
        <p>''Dirt is my office,'' he says. ''Because the terrain is so steep, the site was very difficult, a design puzzle that confounded other architects. While people were making these extravagant proposals that were way over budget, I got down into the earth and found solutions.''</p>
        <p>Jones, a balding, 49-year-old Californian with a jowly, tanned face, turns off a cart path and approaches a nearly vertical slope leading to the 12th green. The incline looks too steep to be negotiated, but he floors the accelerator anyway. Halfway up the slope, the motor dies and the cart lurches into reverse. It glances off a few trees, spills its passengers and golf paraphernalia and finally stops precariously at the edge of another steep descent. Undeterred, the architect hops back into the cart.</p>
        <p>Typically, Jones's persistence pays off. In the business of international golf-course design, where the competition, he himself says, is ''tooth and claw,'' Jones is a powerhouse, perhaps the most gifted architect and certainly the biggest hustler. With golf's popularity burgeoning abroad - an estimated 150 courses are now under construction, and hundreds more are on the drawing boards - Europe and the Pacific basin have become new battlegrounds for established American architects, who now compete for design contracts of up to $1 million or more from Spain's Costa del Sol to Japan's Karuizawa valley.</p>
        <p>During the last two decades, Jones has outflanked many of his rivals. He has more than 100 courses to his credit, and in addition to Bossey, his first European project, he has designed a Pharaonic ankh-shaped layout in Cairo, persuaded the Chinese to build the first course in Shanghai in nearly 40 years and, along with Dr. Armand Hammer, convinced the Russians to construct their first 18-holer. He's now working on 46 courses around the world.</p>
        <p>His is a glamorous orbit - jetting around the world for dealings with business magnates, statesmen and celebrities. Still, his most formidable rivals are close to home. As even he will admit, the manic traveling and bidding for projects are an effort to separate his identity from that of his younger brother Rees; and more crucially, from his father, builder of nearly 500 golf courses, the legendary patriarch of links design, 82-year-old Robert Trent Jones Sr.</p>
        <p>THOUGH THE GAME IS SCOTTISH IN ITS ancestry, golf has become an undeniably American pastime. An estimated 21.7 million Americans are golfers and, according to the National Golf Foundation, 8 million more will be playing by the year 2000. The surging interest in the United States prompts the construction of between 100 and 125 courses annually.</p>
        <p>Still, most of these are addenda to housing complexes or resort hotels, where land is limited, homes are sold on prime acreage and environmental restrictions are severe; there are few new ''pure'' golf sites.</p>
        <p>As a result, many of the top designers are looking to Europe and Asia, where there are not as many limitations on creativity, and where developers, anxious to exploit a growing and largely untapped market, are throwing big money at big-name architects. In the United States, construction costs have reached an unprecedented average of $2 million to $4 million per project; by comparison, developers in Japan have been known to spend $40 million on a single 18-hole course.</p>
        <p>Of the more than 150 golf architects in the United States (the profession is nascent elsewhere), only a dozen or so are viewed by international developers as having the marquee names that will help sell club memberships, homes and vacations abroad. Among (Continued on Page 84)4 these are Jones and his father; Pete Dye of Delray Beach, Fla., whose designs include several of those featured on the Professional Golfers' Association tour, and players-cum-designers like Jack Nicklaus and Arnold Palmer.</p>
        <p>Of these, Jones is the controversial showman, golf's hyperbolic Don King. He customarily likens his courses to ''artistic canvases,'' and sees himself as a Beethoven or Mozart. ''All my courses are symphonies with dominant themes,'' he says. ''They have crescendos and lulls, there are different rhythms, you can feel the changes.''</p>
        <p>These rhetorical flourishes rankle traditionalists in the golfing community. ''He does good work, even great work,'' says an editor at Golf Digest magazine, who refuses to speak for attribution. ''If only Bobby could learn to keep his mouth shut.''</p>
        <p>Whether he's selling golf to the Russians, or dropping the names of his friends in high places - Senator Sam Nunn, for instance, with whom he worked in 1986 on behalf of Corazon Aquino, then campaigning for the presidency of the Philippines - Jones does seem to crave headlines. As he says of his jaunts into golf's once-unexplored territory: ''I enjoy venturing out onto the frontier. I went to Japan first. I went to the Philippines in 64. I'm in Transkei. I urged my father to go to Spain before any American went. I like being out on the edge.''</p>
        <p>Wheeling around Bossey, a par-71, 6,700-yard course, Jones points to one architectural ''triumph'' after another, and it seems evident that he draws his massive ego from the daunting tasks that are always at hand. Confronted with mountains, swamps and deserts that are hostile to course construction, Jones is routinely asked to solve jigsaw puzzles, designing 18 holes that test varied golfing skills, then fitting them into a limited, 150-to-180-acre space and the developer's fixed budget.</p>
        <p>At Bossey, his chief problem was Mont Saleve, a range of cliffs looming over the course. From this granite wall, the thin slice of land at Jones's disposal sloped dramatically downward, through a thick forest. ''The trick here,'' Jones says, ''was to make the course easy to walk, while still preserving its alpine beauty and natural golfing challenges.''</p>
        <p>He employs a design team of five architects, one of whom customarily ''routes'' a course, plotting the various holes, and sketches the proposed contouring of the site. Jones oversees each facet of this work, and he visits every project to sketch the greens himself. During construction, Jones meets frequently with the site superintendent; they discuss design changes while walking the land.</p>
        <p>The work at Bossey began in 1981, and for four years Jones intermittently supervised the irrigation engineering, the bulldozing and the seeding of greens. Yet his chief contribution was the design plan. Fairways were narrowly tiered on the natural terraces leading up to the cliffs, creating expansive shadows that now make golf shots seem to soar directly into Mont Saleve. This makes it difficult for golfers to judge distances, and gives the layout a hint of mystery. But in addition to its esthetic triumph, the design stresses accuracy over raw power, and Bossey thus offsets the advantages granted by the new, titanium-shafted golf clubs and long-distance balls that many feel threaten the game's very integrity.</p>
        <p>''Bossey wasn't built to defeat the golfer; it's designed to make him think,'' says Jones. It's an attitude that puts him at great odds with his father, who is known for designing 7,000-yard layouts that reward big hitters. Jones feels these longer courses are only meant for ''heroes,'' and not for today's recreational players.</p>
        <p>''Golf is a game of attack and defense, and I'm the defender,'' he says.</p>
        <p>According to Ron Whitten, a contributing editor on golf architecture for Golf Digest, Jones differs from rivals by ''pushing around less earth.'' That is, he avoids the extensive bulldozing of topographical features. His fairways thus have a less-than-sculptured look; the artistic flair is expressed in the detailing of holes. At Bossey's 13th and 14th holes, for instance, dozens of large boulders seem to be cascading out of Mont Saleve. ''Punctuation points,'' Jones calls them. ''Music versus noise.'' Jones builds wavier, more sweeping sandtraps than other architects, and he's also known for his sprawling, dramatically contoured greens.</p>
        <p>''I don't impose my views on nature. I'm only dressing her up a bit,'' says Jones, who considers himself an environmentalist, and was, in fact, a delegate appointed by President Carter to the 1980 Helsinki accords conference in Madrid, which included in its studies international environmental problems.</p>
        <p>''When my father talks about the environment, he uses my quotes. He knows what sells. Nicklaus has an egocentric kind of philosophy. He's said, 'Let me make courses so tough they'll be remembered after I'm gone.' As for Pete Dye, he puts railroad ties on courses because it's going to be more photogenic. You don't need all this rococo stuff.</p>
        <p>''No other architect has served on a state parks commission, the Helsinki commission, or talked about things like ozone layers. Nobody understands these problems like I do.''</p>
        <p>DRIVING BACK TO THE clubhouse at Bossey, Jones talks about his new projects in India, Australia, Italy, France and England. But he's most animated about his course in Shanghai, where groundbreaking is imminent - and about how he angered Madame Mao Zedong.</p>
        <p>''The woman went absolutely crazy,'' Jones says, recounting what a Chinese Government official told him. ''She couldn't believe that this course was going to be built on the grounds of her favorite guesthouse. Then they told her the course would be designed by an American. She was up all night banging on the walls.''</p>
        <p>Madame Mao received this news in 1983, and Jones admits that the project was subsequently almost abandoned. A new course hadn't been built in Shanghai since 1949, and local authorities lost interest in developing a retreat for foreign businessmen.</p>
        <p>Finally, last May, after negotiating with the developer Prescott S. Bush Jr. (the Vice President's brother) and the Aoki Corporation (the Japanese firm that owns Westin Hotels and Resorts), the Shanghai Government agreed to an expanded construction plan at a different location. An $18 million resort complex will be built on the shores of Dian Shan Lake, about 30 miles outside Shanghai.</p>
        <p>''The new site is rather flat and bland,'' says Jones. ''The key will be to do a Florida-style course with lots of trees and mounds. I'll try to keep the lakes out of play, because I don't want the new Chinese players to lose lots of balls.''</p>
        <p>At lunch in the Bossey dining room, Jones sits between the course founder, Lucien H. Balthazar, and Max Friedersdorf, President Reagan's envoy to the Geneva disarmament talks, and discusses his other international coup - the first 18-hole course in the Soviet Union, the deal for which was completed last May, during the Reagan-Gorbachev summit, after a delay of more than a decade.</p>
        <p>''Whenever we'd bump into one another at our San Francisco club,  [ Secretary of State George ]  Schultz used to needle me, 'How's your Russian course coming, Bob?' '' says Jones, conceding that his proposed $4 million venture 18 miles from the Kremlin went nowhere for 14 years.</p>
        <p>''But then again, Napoleon also had a very tough time in Russia. Some of the bureaucrats we were dealing with just didn't understand the game; they associated it with capitalist privilege. So what  [ Armand ]  Hammer did was to simplify matters for them. He compared golf balls to missiles, tees to launching pads and greens to targets.''</p>
        <p>Evoking a burst of laughter from the assembled group, Jones continues.</p>
        <p>''The Russians wondered if the project would generate enough foreign currency to justify their investment, but they weren't just concerned with its financial potential. They asked a lot of questions about the environment, especially regarding the course's effect on water supply and the dangers of pesticides. But through all those meetings I really felt that these men were powerless to confirm the deal. They seemed to be waiting on some higher authority, and Hammer got disgusted. I had to convince him to stay.''</p>
        <p>Though frustrated himself, Jones didn't surrender to the fatigue of those prolonged negotiating sessions. At the same time as the Reagan-Gorbachev talks, Jones drew attention to his own project by passing golf balls and pencils around the negotiating table of his talks with the Russians - all inscribed with the name of the 170-acre ''Nahabino'' site.</p>
        <p>''Bobby's a terrific diplomat,'' says Dr. Hammer, who first suggested the course idea to then-Soviet leader Leonid I. Brezhnev in 1974. Back then, Jones and his father collaborated on the design plan, and Hammer chuckles when he recalls that Junior made a gift of golf clubs to both Brezhnev and the Mayor of Moscow. ''Bobby really knows how to make friends with everyone. His persistence made this project happen.''</p>
        <p>It was logic, however, that ultimately sold the Russians on golf. In this age of perestroika, the Kremlin is now seeking foreign travelers, especially American and Japanese executives, golf's most avid devotees. The arguments won Jones a $362,500 design fee. ''I'll get the money in U.S. currency,'' Jones says. ''But they really hammered me on the price,''</p>
        <p>During lunch, Jones announces he's already been asked to build other courses in the Soviet Union. He's warming to the idea, he says, of being the ''father of Russian golf.''</p>
        <p>THOUGH TRENT SR. had also worked on the original designs for Nahabino, he was noticeably missing from the Moscow festivities. The two Joneses have been feuding for years. The son once attacked his father's courses as ''out of touch with the American mainstream,'' and the Nahabino plan led to more wrangling.</p>
        <p>Jones, who claims his sparring with his father has eased, credits Don Knott, his staff's senior architect, with helping him style the 7,000-yard course. Trent Sr., meanwhile, reached at his Montclair, N.J., home, insists the Russians were more impressed with his designs, and that these drawings were crucial to the project's final approval.</p>
        <p>''Bobby got the headlines because I wasn't there,'' says Trent Sr. ''The reason I'm a better architect is that I played better golf as a youngster, and I have the ability to sketch anything. Bobby only has a little bit of that ability. He hasn't got to the point I have.''</p>
        <p>Told of his father's remarks, Jones looks as if he's just taken a punch below the belt. After a long strained silence, he says: ''My dad can say what he wants, I'm not going to get into this.''</p>
        <p>But in a roundabout way, he does. ''My dad was the artist, but without my mother  [ Ione, who died in 1987 ]  he couldn't have made it,'' Jones says. ''He was away a lot, and when he was around he could be very mercurial, very aloof. I got much closer to my mom. My dad was rarely encouraging, but because of her I went to Yale and started thinking of a public-service career, which golf architecture is all about.''</p>
        <p>Graduating from Yale in 1961, he attended Stanford Law School for a year, then decided to become a designer, although, he says, he realized ''there was the risk that I would forever be compared and confused with my father.'' Eventually he'd also feel challenged by another family member, his brother Rees, two years younger. Though the pair has always been fiercely competitive, as a golf architect Rees Jones has had little interest in globe-trotting, which has blunted their competing for the same projects. Still, he's resentfully viewed as an interloper by his older brother. ''Whatever I did, Rees followed,'' says Jones Jr. ''I was in the Boy Scouts. He went to the Boy Scouts. I went to Montclair High School and Yale. He went to Montclair and Yale. I went to California. Rees went to California. It's a little strange.''</p>
        <p>Rees has been successful in his own right, winning particular praise for remodeling The Country Club, site of this year's United States Open in Brookline, Mass. Asked to compare his designs with his older brother's, Rees says he works at making the particular challenges of each hole clearly evident to the golfer. ''Bobby's more of a deception designer, I'm more a definition designer,'' Rees says. ''He's more international, so he can't be as hands-on as I can. The point is the Joneses all do great work. And since my mother died, we've all cooperated with one another. Bobby's never remodeled a U.S. Open course, though. I didn't follow him there, did I?''</p>
        <p>In California, Robert Jones worked out of a small Palo Alto office, rented by his father, and saw himself as ''the sorcerer's apprentice'' as he traveled around the West looking for projects. But collaborations with his father at such courses as Mission Viejo in southern California and Lake Ridge in Reno were usually testy, and in 1973 the Joneses severed ties.</p>
        <p>To avoid further skirmishing, the two men acted like gang leaders, greedily protective of their respective turfs. They talked about using the Mississippi River as a boundary, proposing to do business only on opposite sides of this line.</p>
        <p>The accord never materialized, and ever since, Jones Jr. has been asserting himself both as a designer and a businessman. His first venture after the break, in Steamboat Springs, Colo., earned him $50,000. (These days, he says, he averages $450,000 per project.) Ironically, his career has repeated the pattern that led to the childhood estrangement from his father. Working frenetic 18-hour days and traveling more than 250,000 miles a year, he's been forced to leave his wife and two children - a daughter Tolly, now 14, and son Robert 3d, 21 -for weeks at a time.</p>
        <p>''I regret not spending more time with Robert, but I'm an all-out guy,'' Jones says. ''I've got to do this. Getting out of my father's shadow and coming into the sun has been a long, difficult process. I guess it will never be complete.''</p>
        <p>WITH SUCH ENORMOUS design fees at stake, the jousting among architects for contracts frequently gets ugly. From the spreading of rumors about rivals' design credentials and personal lives, to the willful underestimating of construction costs, the maneuvering to impress developers is intense, and Jones is among the most frequent targets of criticism.</p>
        <p>Tom Fazio, who has designed 95 courses in the United States, Canada and Central America, calls Jones ''the most aggressive guy you come across in this business, to the point he's obnoxious.'' Other are even more condemning. Recalling their duel with Jones over a course in Scottsdale, Ariz., in 1983, Jay Morrish and Tom Weiskopf say they had already won the contract when the developer, Douglas G. Simonson, received a phone call from Jones. ''Bob was saying that Tom and I were awful people, that I was nothing but a draftsman,'' bristles Morrish, summarizing the Simonson account of the conversation. ''He said Tom didn't want to work with me, and would've preferred to work with him. Boy, was he bad-mouthing me!''</p>
        <p>Simonson admits Jones called him, but refuses to elaborate. Jones himself angrily denies doing anything underhanded.</p>
        <p>''They're full of it,'' he says. ''Consider the source.''</p>
        <p>Jones will admit that having the same name as his revered father hasn't hurt, that in the early part of his career the confusion gained him more access to developers than he might have had otherwise. And he flaunts plaudits from the American Society of Golf Course Architects, an organization that chose 15 of his courses for its ''Top 130'' list, a total second only to Trent Sr.'s 34 - without mentioning that he headed the selection committee.</p>
        <p>Despite these resources, Jones still likes to cast himself as the underdog, especially in his battle with Jack Nicklaus. ''Jack gets publicity simply by showing up at a site. But I don't think he has the ability, knowledge or interest to use an extraordinary piece of property.''</p>
        <p>Looking increasingly annoyed, he goes on: ''I'm not the American hero, I don't make a million dollars a course. Even if Jack wants to make the most ridiculous design changes he gets his way. How many developers are going to say no to Jack Nicklaus?'' (Reached for comment, a spokesman for Nicklaus would say only that his firm, Golden Bear International, does not consider itself in competition with anyone for design contracts.) How Jones sells himself is best illustrated on California's Monterey Peninsula, at the site of an abandoned silica sand-mining operation. Lying only miles from such fabled links as Pebble Beach and Spyglass Hill, in 1982 this seaside property -now called Spanish Bay, for the body of water next to it - offered a rare opportunity to design a course where the views took precedence over condominiums. A project here was sure to attract wide media exposure, or, as Jones suggests, was akin to ''Michelangelo's painting the Sistine Chapel.''</p>
        <p>When the Pebble Beach Company began searching for an architect, Jones was convinced that Nicklaus had the inside track because of his friendship with former President Ford, a Pebble Beach regular. But he besieged the Pebble Beach managing partner Thomas J. Klutznick with phone calls.</p>
        <p>''I was getting 10 calls a day from him,'' says Klutznick today. ''He was pleading with me for an opportunity to sit down and talk, to describe the design team he'd assembled, his 'Holy Trinity.' ''</p>
        <p>The ''trinity'' included Jones and two partners whom he enlisted for the campaign: Tom Watson, the five-time British Open winner, and the former United States Golf Association president Frank (Sandy) Tatum.</p>
        <p>''Something dramatic had to be done to complement the site,'' Jones says. ''That's why I brought together two of the most respected men in golf. They both care about preserving the game's highest values.''</p>
        <p>The concept that won Jones the job, however, was his artistic break with American golfing tradition. In his conversations with Klutznick, he stressed the ''boldness of returning to golf's roots'' and proposed a Scottish-styled ''linksland'' course. Such a layout incorporates bristly grasses, hollows and sprawling dunes, and departs distinctly from America's meticulously manicured greenery. This approach was risky for Jones; he knew his design would inevitably be compared to Royal Troon, St. Andrews and other Scottish landmarks. Yet the plan suited a coastal backdrop and complemented Klutznick's own strategy for defusing local environmentalists.</p>
        <p>Such environmental concerns as wetlands preservation, pesticides usage and water pollution commonly trigger protests against developers. And for five years, the Pebble Beach Company had tried futilely to secure the necessary building permits from Monterey County and the California Coastal Commission.</p>
        <p>''American environmentalists are not seeing the forest for the trees,'' says Jones, who admits that current projects in Squaw Valley and Kauai, Hawaii, have been stalled by local protests. ''The focus should be on pollution by industry, problems like acid rain.''</p>
        <p>At Spanish Bay, he talked of restoring the dunes, not flattening them. The project was thus billed as an attempt to save recreational land, and this strategy worked. The coastal board approved the plan in March 1985. The course was completed in November 1987.</p>
        <p>Golf Digest's Ron Whitten hails The Links at Spanish Bay as ''a piece of hard rock that Jones transformed. Spreading around all that sand  [ for the dunes' restoration ]  was a monumental feat, and it looks like it was always there - that's the best thing.''</p>
        <p>Remembering that Trent Sr. was equally laudatory, Jones still cherishes his father's praise. ''My dad called the course a 'masterpiece.' This was ambrosia for me, nectar from the gods.''</p>
        <p>IN GRENOBLE, ON THE SITE of one of four courses he's now building in France, Jones stands in the middle of a sandtrap, suggesting modifications to his foreman.</p>
        <p>''I think the bunker is far too deep, George.'' he says. ''Flatten the top edge, too. I want players in here to see the green.''</p>
        <p>The two men discuss the leveling of a nearby fairway mound. Then they hop into a jeep, bound for one of the course's upper plateaus. Winding along a narrow dirt road, they arrive at the 13th hole, a broad meadow that offers sweeping views of valleys, and the distant, snow-capped Alps. Appreciating the vistas and fresh mountain air, Jones exults. ''Isn't this what it's all about, George? Doesn't a sight like this make you want to do the work?''</p>
        <p>Before George has a chance to respond, Jones climbs out of the jeep. ''This business can be very lonely,'' he says. ''And I might have a heart attack one day. The traveling, the problems with developers, the late-night phone calls. Still, look at how many men strive for immortality, and the few that get it. I will have left my imprint here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
