<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.P.A. Declines to Toughen Rule on Sulfur Dioxide</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="136338"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SULFUR DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7D71530F936A25757C0A96E948260" item-length="676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.P.A. Declines to Toughen Rule on Sulfur Dioxide</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Environmental Protection Agency announced today that it would not adopt tougher rules for reducing high levels of sulfur dioxide that occur in brief periods. It had been considering the rule to protect asthmatic people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Environmental Protection Agency announced today that it would not adopt tougher rules for reducing high levels of sulfur dioxide that occur in brief periods. It had been considering the rule to protect asthmatic people.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency announced today that it would not adopt tougher rules for reducing high levels of sulfur dioxide that occur in brief periods. It had been considering the rule to protect asthmatic people.</p>
        <p>The agency concluded, ''Based on the best data available, the existing set of standards is adequate to protect public health and welfare.''</p>
        <p>While the decision involving short-term exposure to high levels of pollution was not unexpected, it was assailed by environmentalists and some public health officials who said that it flew in the face of medical evidence showing that sulfur dioxide emissions threatened the well-being of thousands of asthmatic people and others sensitive to such pollution. They also said the decision violated the spirit and letter of the Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>Robert Yuhnke, a senior attorney for the Environmental Defense Fund, an organization that frequently litigates over environmental issues, said his group would sue to overturn the decision if it should become effective. Cost Would Have Been High</p>
        <p>The proposed standard for limiting sulfur emissions would have required extensive controls on the burning of coal and other fossil fuels by power plants, heating plants, smelters and other sources. Such a requirement would also have helped reduce other air pollution problems and would cost many millions, perhaps billions of dollars to carry out.</p>
        <p>But J. Craig Potter, Assistant Administrator of the environmental agency for air, said at a news conference today that the Clean Air Act prohibits the consideration of cost factors when regulating pollution and that such factors played no role in the decision by the agency's Administrator, Lee M. Thomas.</p>
        <p>The rule limiting exposure to sulfur dioxide was one of those that Congress ordered the environmental agency to review to see if it was adequate when it amended the Clean Air Act in 1977.</p>
        <p>The limit on sulfur dioxide in the air is now set for a 24-hour period, with the average not allowed to exceed an average of 0.14 parts per million. The agency had been considering a limit of 0.4 parts million over one hour, but Mr. Potter said that only asthmatic sufferers directly exposed to this high level of pollution while exercising were vulnerable to aggravated respiratory effects. He said such effects as shortness of breath, wheezing and coughing were ''transient and reversible'' and were not experienced by asthmatics using medication.</p>
        <p>The agency said that only 1 percent of the nation's asthsmatic people, or 100,000, would be in such situations as much as once as year. And only a portion of the exposed asthmatic people would suffer respiratory effects, the agency contended. #60-Day Comment Period Because relatively few people were affected and because the agency had to deal with much more serious air pollution problems such as smog, Mr. Potter said, it was decided that the current rules for sulfur dioxide did not have to be changed. He acknowledged, however, that the decision was a ''tough call'' and because of the difficulties the agency will take public comment for 60 days before making a decision final.</p>
        <p>David Hawkins, a lawyer for the Natural Resources Defense Council who was assistant administrator of the environmental agency for air in the Carter Administration, said the agency was substantially understating the number of asthmatics potentially at risk from sulfor dioxide.</p>
        <p>He said that this decision was based on ''this Administration's desire to protect the status quo because it is aware that a program requiring significant sulfur reduction has high political and economic significance.''</p>
        <p>Fran Du Melle, director of government relations for the American Lung Association, said. ''We believe that science has definitely established a link between increased health risks to asthmatics and short term exposure to sulfur dioxide.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Philip J. Landrigan, director of the division of environmental and occupational health at Mt. Sinai Medical School in New York called the E.P.A. decision ''a mistake''.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
