<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bolstering Clean Air Act: Fingers Point in All Directions After Latest Failure</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="185838"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4D61F3DF934A35753C1A96E948260" item-length="924" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bolstering Clean Air Act: Fingers Point in All Directions After Latest Failure</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Efforts to strengthen the Clean Air Act died this week, the victim of too little time, too little compromise and, by most accounts, too little Presidential leadership.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Efforts to strengthen the Clean Air Act died this week, the victim of too little time, too little compromise and, by most accounts, too little Presidential leadership.</p>
        <p>Efforts to strengthen the Clean Air Act died this week, the victim of too little time, too little compromise and, by most accounts, too little Presidential leadership.</p>
        <p>Despite growing public alarm about urban smog, acid rain, a thinning ozone shield and global warming, the 100th Congress was unable to fashion a compromise on clean air legislation that would be satisfactory to Eastern and Midwestern states, to coal miners, electric utilities, car makers and environmentalists.</p>
        <p>The legislation was added to the casualties of the 100th Congress's rush to adjourn with the announcement Tuesday that it had failed again to break a deadlock that began to form a year after the original bill was enacted in 1980. The revised measure would have addressed three serious pollution problems: acid rain, the inability of many cities to meet the law's limits on pollutants like ozone and carbon monoxide, and the largely uncontrolled pollution by toxic gases emitted by industry. Stronger Leadership Expected</p>
        <p>All sides agreed that clean air would be high on the agenda of the next Congress, and there is a widely shared conviction that the next President, whether it is Vice President Bush or Michael S. Dukakis, will exert stronger leadership than President Reagan has demonstrated in attacking the problem of air pollution.</p>
        <p>But this week, legislators, environmentalists and representatives of business groups were asking what went wrong and pointing fingers.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists contended that the legislation was killed by the lobbying of industry, particularly the electric utilities and the coal and auto industries, which adamantly opposed new pollution controls. Industry representatives said the blame lay largely with the intransigence of environmentalists and their Senate allies, who wanted their clean air bill or none. 'Rigid and Unyielding'</p>
        <p>Legislators from Northeastern states said that the problem was the selfishness of Midwesterners who did not want to invest in controls that would curb acid rain originating at their coal-burning power plants. Westerners said that the Eastern states were trying to impose a heavy economic burden on electric ratepayers in their states.</p>
        <p>Acid rain is pollution, largely oxides of sulfur and nitrogen, that change chemically as they travel through the atmosphere and fall to the ground as rain, snow, fog or dry particles.</p>
        <p>Senator George J. Mitchell, Democrat of Maine and chief architect of clean air legislation in the Senate, said when conceding defeat Tuesday that some of the blame must fall on those who ''remained rigid and unyielding, wholly unwilling to compromise, even when faced with the certainty that their rigidity would result in no action this year.''</p>
        <p>Almost all sides agreed that it was the absence of leadership from the White House that doomed the effort to revise the Clean Air law to failure. But after sporadic efforts in the first years of his Administration, President Reagan remained indifferent to the clean air issue, they said. 'Veto as a Backstop'</p>
        <p>William D. Fay, administrator of the Clean Air Working Group, the chief lobbying group for the business community on air issues, said that while President Reagan provided industry with ''the veto as a backstop'' against unacceptable legislation, the White House ''was not a player in this debate.''</p>
        <p>Gary L. Bauer, assistant to the President for policy development said that the White House legislative staff had worked on the clean air issue but that ''it is the unspoken rule in Washington that, when in doubt, blame the President.''</p>
        <p>Environmentalists insist that the public will not allow the next Congress to ignore these issues. The Environmental Protection Agency is already starting to ban the construction of new polluting factories in some of the cities that have not met the deadline for reducing ozone and carbon monoxide. New evidence indicates that airborne acids and ozone generated in urban areas is damaging forests and crops in many parts of the country. Air polluted by toxic chemicals represents a still unquantified but potentially significant public health threat. 'Coming Back Next Year'</p>
        <p>Richard E. Ayres, chairman of the National Clean Air Coalition, an alliance of environmental, public health and consumer groups, said that while he was very disappointed with the failure of this Congress to enact a stronger Clean Air law, the compromise bill worked out in the session's waning hours between Senator Mitchell, Senate Majority Leader Robert C. Byrd and the United Mine Workers Union ''was worse than existing law and not an acceptable solution.''</p>
        <p>Daniel Becker, a Washington representative of Environmental Action, a private environmentalists group, said: ''We are coming back next year to get a clean air bill that lives up to its name.''</p>
        <p>Prospects for action on clean air in the next Congress look promising. Both Presidential candidates have pledged strong action on acid rain and other pollution problems. Senator Byrd, who resisted acid rain legislation because of his concern over its impact on West Virginia's coal miners, has now, by accepting compromise legislation this year, at least agreed in principle to controls on coal-fired power plants. In any case, he is stepping down as majority leader next year.</p>
        <p>But Senator Mitchell, while delivering his obituary for the Clean Air Act on the Senate floor Tuesday, said the failure this year meant ''the health of more American children will suffer, more lakes will die, more forests will wither.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
