<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crusader on the Beach</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="64" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="203979"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEACHES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AREA PLANNING AND RENEWAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENGINEERING AND ENGINEERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WIND</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DUKE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">COLLIER, BARNARD L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PILKEY, ORRIN H JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Engineering and Engineers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wind</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5D61E30F937A35751C1A96E948260" item-length="3965" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crusader on the Beach</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY BARNARD L. COLLIER; Barnard L. Collier is a freelance writer living in New York.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COLLIER, BARNARD L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IT'S A GLORIOUS CLEAR AUTUMN DAY, 75 degrees, with light offshore breezes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IT'S A GLORIOUS CLEAR AUTUMN DAY, 75 degrees, with light offshore breezes.</p>
        <p>IT'S A GLORIOUS CLEAR AUTUMN DAY, 75 degrees, with light offshore breezes.</p>
        <p>Blessedly, today there is no fish odor blowing from the menhaden processing plant near Beaufort, N.C.</p>
        <p>Orrin H. Pilkey Jr. is standing beside his cockeyed captain's chair at the wheel of the Duke University Marine Laboratory launch. One of his coastal geology students and I are sitting on wooden slat benches as we bounce over the powerboat wakes on our way to Shackleford Banks, a seven-mile-long barrier island about a mile from the harbor.</p>
        <p>Pilkey is about 5 feet 4 inches tall and more than 3 feet around. His friends and family worry that, at the age of 54, the marine geologist is growing too big a belly. On the other hand, it's possible that Pilkey is simply assuming his natural form as a giant elf - complete with silver-brown beard, hazel eyes behind silver-rimmed glasses, and blacksmith arms. His belt buckle, posing bravely beneath a beachball bulge, is a brass scallop shell - to signify his status as America's foremost philosopher of the beaches, the sea bottoms and the coastal sands. He is such a winsome creature, in fact, that many of his adversaries - among them, developers, engineers and owners of coastal property who favor the laissez-faire development of beaches - say they can't help liking him. But Pilkey's crusade is challenging some long-held notions about the ways in which people use and maintain beaches. A decade ago, when he began warning of the dangers of ''beach degradation,'' he found little public support. Today, as concern for our shore environment grows, people are listening.</p>
        <p>At Duke University, where Pilkey is the James B. Duke Professor of Geology, coastal-geology studies have earned an international reputation. He has published more than 100 research papers in geological and oceanographic journals and in 1987 was awarded the Francis Shepard Medal for excellence in marine geology, for his studies of oceanic turbidity currents and their role in the formation of abyssal plains -the huge, flat areas on the ocean floor.</p>
        <p>With Wallace Kaufman, a real estate developer, Pilkey is the author of ''The Beaches Are Moving; The Drowning of America's Shoreline,'' which argues that beaches are nature's shock absorbers against waves, and that beach sands ''migrate'' relentlessly.</p>
        <p>He contends that man-made structures on the beaches are essentially temporary, and that most engineering schemes to restore or preserve beaches are last resorts that cost the public more than they are worth. In North Carolina, where he has brought the construction of sea walls to a near-standstill, he is particularly well known for campaigning against building protection for the famous candy-striped Cape Hatteras Lighthouse. When it was built in 1870, it was more than 1,500 feet from the shoreline; today, it's only 160 feet from the tides.</p>
        <p>Pilkey's position was summed up in the headline for his op-ed article last year in The Washington Post: ''Don't Stop the Ocean, Move the Light.''</p>
        <p>WE ANCHOR OFF SHACKLEFORD BANKS ISLAND. Pilkey jumps into the water in his running shoes and faded jeans. He leads the way ashore. He stops theatri-cally, turns his face to the warm sun, spreads his arms and shouts:</p>
        <p>''This is the most beautiful island in the world!''</p>
        <p>We march across the 700-yard-wide sandpile, southward toward the Atlantic Ocean. The island is newly protected from development, having just been added to the Federal Government's National Seashore lands. A horse path winds through the low vegetation, into a swampy maritime forest. We bow our heads beneath candelabra of live oaks encrusted with greenish-gray lichen; we step around fresh horse manure.</p>
        <p>Shackleford is home to wild horses descended from domestic stock left there when settlers abandoned Diamond City, a small village on the east end of the island, after three direct hits from hurricanes in 1899. A small cemetery is the only other trace that remains.</p>
        <p>We scramble up a tall dune to a painterly view: a tranquil sapphire sound on the left; gloomy green thickets among the hills of pale sand; and here and there, the mysterious skeletons of gray ghost cedars, all bone-dry heartwood rubbed smooth by the action of sand and wind. Faintly, in the distance, is Cape Lookout Lightouse. About 1,000 feet ahead, we spot a smudge of caramel. It is a wild horse grazing, curious, shy.</p>
        <p>At the feet of several dunes we come to a basinlike place covered with low, tender grasses and the bright green leaves of pennywort.</p>
        <p>''This is called a blowout,'' Pilkey says, pointing to the flat ground. He gets down on his knees and begins digging a hole in the pewter-colored soil with his hands. ''Blowouts are formed among barrier-island dunes when the winds from the ocean find a gap in the dunes and blow the sand away, almost down to the water table in certain places. In a blowout, you can fairly easily dig to fresh water, very good clean water trapped beneath the island.'' He peers into the hole. Water mirrors the sky. ''It will fill up after a while,'' he says. He reaches into the little well to get some water on his fingers and touches them to his tongue. I do, too. The water is sweet and cool.</p>
        <p>''Good to know when you're camping on a barrier island,'' he says, refilling the hole lest a horse step in it. HIS IS THE UMPTEENTH TIME</p>
        <p>Pilkey has led a field trip to Shackleford Island, and he has many, many more on his schedule. He has organized outings for small children, high school students, film and television crews, writers, scientists, tourists and lots of Duke University students. His vision of the beaches is so detailed and intimate, his passion for the subject so intense, that few who make these trips can ever again see or think about a coastal system in the same innocent way.</p>
        <p>Pilkey is the unofficial leader of what non-enthusiasts call a ''beach cult.'' They believe that beaches are, in a sense, alive and constantly involved with the wind, the water and the waves; that they must be allowed to change shape freely or they will slip away into the sea and be lost forever. According to Pilkey, engineering structures distort and obstruct free beach movement. The beaches continue to move, and man-made structures are reduced over time to rubble. ''Engineers never go back to examine their rubble,'' he grumbles.</p>
        <p>He sees a jetty sticking out from the beach and fumes: ''Atrocity!'' - as if it were an instrument of torture.</p>
        <p>He spies a $400,000 house on the site of a newly forming inlet, and he explodes: ''Madness! Madness!''</p>
        <p>He utters epithets like ''criminal!'' and ''fat capitalist pig'' when speaking of certain shoreline developers. He gets angry enough at the United States Army Corps of Engineers to say: ''They lie. They lie. They lie. They lie! And they get away with it.''</p>
        <p>If his enemies are coastal developers, engineers and some of the people who own the ''first tier'' of coastline properties along 14,000 miles of American ocean beaches, Pilkey has equally committed allies. They are the people who own property behind the beachfront; the farmer in Kansas who wants to be able to visit the beach with his children; and, not least, Pilkey's student disciples.</p>
        <p>By the turn of the century, Pilkey's code for living peacebly with the shore may be cemented into coastal laws worldwide. His graduate program at Duke draws many students from other countries - this year's are from Liberia, Jordan, England, Taiwan and Australia - who will go home to jobs in coastal planning.</p>
        <p>To pass with flying colors, Pilkey proteges must get up early and work hard and late. They must dig joyfully into the stinking organic matter at the mouths of creeks. They must draw maps and charts, and examine sand and mud and shells under microscopes. Pilkey will ask them to explain why they found mud in a given creek mouth and sand in the adjoining bay, instead of the reverse. He will quiz them on what the color and distribution of shells says about the history - and erosion - of a given area.</p>
        <p>The instruments coastal geologists use vary from crude wooden sticks used to measure the slope of a beach, to sophisticated electronic devices that record wave, sand and water movement in the ''surf zone.'' Yet, quite typically, Pilkey stresses: ''I want to instill a very healthy sense of skepticism for the tools we use to study our beaches. We also need healthy legs, tennis shoes that are always wet, a boat - hopefully seaworthy - and devices to take samples of the bottom. Very helpful are aerial photographs, and old charts, so that we can compare old and new beach configurations.''</p>
        <p>THE BASIC SCIENCE of shorelines - much of which has been learned in just the last 20 years - involves the interaction of sand and waves.</p>
        <p>''What happens on the beaches,'' Pilkey explains, ''is a complex interaction that varies according to frequency, size, duration and intensity of the waves, particularly in storms. On barrier island beaches, this is further complicated by the orientation of the island geographically. Does it lie parallel or crosswise to the prevailing winds? It makes a great difference.</p>
        <p>''Both the beaches and the entire island interact with oceanic waves that contain enormous power. In an hour, during a major storm, the waves can change the shape of millions of cubic yards of sand. During one storm, Oregon Inlet in North Carolina was widened from a half-mile to two miles in just hours, a mind-boggling event.''</p>
        <p>Much of this action, he notes, occurs where beachgoers can't see it, because beaches extend into the water to depths of 30 to 40 feet.</p>
        <p>''Waves and the currents they create push rivers of sand along the shore underwater,'' he says. ''During a big storm, sand may be moved so far offshore it is lost forever to the system. During fair weather, sand comes on shore, and that is when beaches build up.</p>
        <p>''We are trying to understand how this system actually works, and how the trappings of man - the jetties, groins, walls, piers, revetments - affect the interaction of wind, sand and waves. But as yet we are unable to predict how this system will behave in a time frame useful to mankind.''</p>
        <p>''The problems are even more complex when you deal with the open ocean shoreline, like the California coast,'' he adds, which has ''a much wider variety of situations - waves rolling up against hard rock cliffs; soft, crumbly rocks; wide strands, or narrow, pebbly ones.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Pilkey and other scientists are convinced that the level of the sea is rising steadily. The likely cause, they believe, is the so-called ''greenhouse effect,'' a global atmospheric warming trend spurred by human pollution: fossil-fuel gases collect above the earth and hold in radiated heat. Sea level, Pilkey believes, is creeping up about a foot each century. Such a rise could inundate many low-lying islands and eventually threaten established shoreline settlements such as Manhattan Island, Ocean City, Md., and Miami Beach. If the warming trend continues, can the sea be stopped by man's ingenuity?</p>
        <p>''We get firm but meaningless 'scientific' answers from the Corps of Engineers,'' Pilkey says.</p>
        <p>''The corps is one of Orrin's favorite targets,'' says Dag Nummedal, a member of the Coastal Engineering Research Board of the Army Corps of Engineers, a professor of geology at Louisiana State University and a good friend of Pilkey. He recalls that at a board meeting last year: ''Orrin spoke about his observations and view about how the corps should respond to the rising sea level. He was listened to with a great deal of respect. . . . The generals and the civilians liked him, and for the first time I can remember, I think he wore a tie.''</p>
        <p>In response to Pilkey's remarks, the corps decided to try to better calculate the value - and cost - of ''beach replenishment,'' pumping or trucking tons of sand to an eroded area. ''That ability is very, very, poor,'' Nummedal acknowledges. ''The American public deserves better than an error  [ margin ]  of plus or minus 100 percent.''</p>
        <p>Pilkey sees economic justification for these projects in metropolitan areas, where the beaches serve hundreds of thousands of people - in Miami Beach, for instance, where miles of beach have been ''replenished.'' But he opposes a proposed Corps of Engineers project for 220 beach houses at Westhampton, L.I., where the Corps estimates construction costs at about $60 million. Pilkey says the cost over the next 50 years will be somewhere between $500 million and $600 million; he calculates that the taxpayers' bill will come to about $3 million a residence.</p>
        <p>PILKEY LIKES TO boil his scientific observations down to ''truths.'' This may seem somewhat biblical in presentation, but Pilkey and Moses enjoy some common traits.  SHORELINE TRUTHS</p>
        <p>I. There is no erosion problem until a structure is built on the shoreline. Beach erosion is a common, expected event, not a natural disaster.</p>
        <p>II. Construction by man on the shoreline causes shoreline changes.</p>
        <p>III. Shoreline engineering protects the interests of very few, often at a very high cost in Federal and state dollars.</p>
        <p>IV. Shoreline engineering destroys the beach it was intended to save.</p>
        <p>V. The cost of saving beach property through shoreline engineering is usually greater than the value of the property to be saved.</p>
        <p>VI. Once you begin shoreline engineering, you can't stop.</p>
        <p>In ''From Currituck to Calabash,'' a book about the North Carolina shore, Pilkey writes: ''History shows us that there are two situations that may terminate shoreline engineering. First, a civilization may fail and no longer build and rebuild its structures. This was the case of the Romans, who built mighty sea walls. Second, a large storm may destroy a shoreline stabilization system so thoroughly that people decide to 'throw in the towel' and leave. In America, however, such a storm is usually regarded as an engineering challenge and thus results in more shoreline stabilization projects.''</p>
        <p>Some among Pilkey's critics believe his analogy between today's challenges and the Roman shore structures, which decayed after the empire fell, is both unsettling and illogical. It seems to them that Pilkey's philosophy represents a retreat from American dreams of engineering conquest.</p>
        <p>Tom Jarrett, a corps engineer, says Pilkey likes to use an absent-minded professor act to ''cover up his inability to explain things. He looks for a while like he's all clouded in with his logic, all befuddled, and then he'll come up with a clear, concise statement, like 'Jetties cause erosion.' And it will all seem to make sense, like magic.''</p>
        <p>Pilkey has critics among his colleagues, too. Robert L. Wiegel, a coastal engineer and professor emeritus at the University of California at Berkeley, says he likes Pilkey, ''but I tell him to his face that he ought to go out and do some science instead of politics. I don't think he does any serious data-taking anymore, which is what academics are supposed to do.''</p>
        <p>HOW ORRIN PILKEY Jr. survived to become noted and notorious is a subject people who know him find strange and funny. As a teen-ager, he was a smoke jumper in Montana. He majored in geology at Washington State University and followed that with a master's degree from the University of Montana and a doctorate from Florida State University. His first job, with the University of Georgia Marine Institute, took him to Sapelo Island, off the Georgia coast, where he did research on Continental shelf sediments. It was lonely there, he says, and he welcomed an offer from the geology department at Duke, where he has remained since 1965.</p>
        <p>Until 1986, when he began to concentrate solely on the beaches, his work included deep-water research. He made 40 grueling voyages aboard Duke Marine Lab research vessels, taking a thousand or more sea-floor samples at depths of up to 28,000 feet. The work was so important to him that he lived with severe seasickness for much of every trip. In accidents aboard ship, he lost the end of one finger and acetone and epoxy splashed in his face.</p>
        <p>Friends say he was a dangerously lunatic touch-football player, but his athletic pursuits ended one pretty day in 1984 when he took a group of junior-high-school students out to Shackleford Island.</p>
        <p>''To show them what a mature geologist could still do,'' he says, ''I climbed the mast and dove 40 feet into 6 feet of water.'' He broke his neck in several places and spent months in the hospital. He is still numb on his right side, and his left arm and hand are withered.</p>
        <p>Even before all that, in the early 1970's, both he and his brother had their thyroid glands removed because of cancer. Their father, Orrin Sr., now 84, was a civil engineer at the Hanford nuclear-weapons plant near Richland, Wash., when they were growing up. ''I am certain,'' says Pilkey, ''that we swam through slugs of radioactive water that was intentionally released by the Hanford engineers.'' A good portion of his anger and doubt about engineers traces back to Hanford.</p>
        <p>He wants to pass on his skepticism about engineering solutions. His father, who helps write and edit many of his books, will occasionally ask him testily if he isn't going ''too far'' in his criticism of engineers.</p>
        <p>There are also those who wonder about the eccentricities of a man whose farmhouse near inland Hillsborough, N.C., has a long, thick rope tied around the chimney and its other end fastened to a big sea anchor in the yard.</p>
        <p>HALF OF THE AMER-ican population lives within 50 miles of a coastal beach or a Great Lakes shore. In the years ahead, some experts project, more than 75 percent of all Americans will live in these areas. Beaches are becoming major municipal and county assets both for tax base and recreational lure. Nationally, a ''beach politics'' is developing that may eventually rival big-city politics.</p>
        <p>Pilkey's testimony before Congressional committees and his growing influence in environmental circles is helping to shape the debate. Already, he has guided North Carolina to a policy of forbidding the construction of coastal defense structures on its barrier-island beaches. Maine has done the same thing, and Texas and Florida are leaning in that direction.</p>
        <p>His many books about American beaches are sometimes called ''beach bibles.'' He has been the co-author or editor of a series of books, published by Duke University Press, on specific areas. So far explored in field-manual detail are Lake Erie, Louisiana, Texas, New Jersey, Alabama-Mississippi, South Carolina, West Florida, Puget Sound and the Georgia Strait, East Florida and the California coast. Books on the Chesapeake Bay, Maine and Massachusetts are scheduled for publication next year.</p>
        <p>A chapter in each book deals with coastal use and the law, discussing such legislation as the Coastal Barrier Resources Act of 1982, which prohibits spending Federal money ''for the construction of infrastructure that encourages barrier island development.'' No structure built in designated barrier areas after Oct. 1, 1983, is eligible for Federal flood insurance.</p>
        <p>''This law was supposed to slow down high-risk cottages and stacks o' shacks, but there are more of them going up now than before, it seems to me,'' Pilkey says. ''The developer will tell buyers that a 'private' carrier'' is willing to insure the property. ''But,'' he adds, ''the carrier may be a post office box somewhere. And when a second developer buys out the first, the first's promise is usually rescinded. There are a lot of beach scams going on, and that's the lesser of them.''</p>
        <p>He is nervous about what will happen when a major new oceanside project, such as a 100-room motel or high-rise condominium - is undermined sufficiently by erosion to endanger the inhabitants. Few of these big structures have been baptized by a hurricane or northeaster.</p>
        <p>''What we have are 'regulations' - administrative decisions, not laws - that prevent coastal armament in North Carolina and other states,'' he says. ''Let's see what happens when a Holiday Inn finds its whole resort complex in the middle of a newly formed inlet. Will a state regulator stand up to the pressure they can bring to build a wall? I don't know.''</p>
        <p>TO EXPLORE A place Pilkey calls ''the worst beach mess in North Carolina,'' we drive in his blue Nova down to the north end of Topsail Island. Topsail, 15 miles northeast of Wilmington, is a barrier island filling up with beach houses and ''For Sale'' signs. These are not, for the most part, weekend getaways in the traditional sense, but more imposing, expensive structures, crowded onto small lots. They boast a view of a bulldozed beach that will almost certainly disappear within the first few hours of the next very severe Atlantic storm.</p>
        <p>''Many of these houses will be splintered into driftwood and washed away,'' Pilkey predicts. ''What concerns me is that some people will build their shack, even if it's a $400,000 shack, where it's bound to be washed away or seriously threatened. Then they'll go crying to the state and Federal governments with their 'Act of God' bit, and the feds will fund a $1 million coastal engineering survey to find that $2 million in state-of-the-art sea walls and jetties will hold back the inevitable for from 8 to 50 years, except if a big storm comes along and wrecks things sooner. And who pays for this? Those of us whose grandchildren may have many, many fewer beaches. We, the American taxpayers.''</p>
        <p>Pilkey's beach code for commercial ventures can be exasperating. Orman Mann is from a family of fishermen that owns boats and property near Oregon Inlet, below Kitty Hawk, on the Outer Banks. He and others in the area want a new jetty to stabilize the inlet, which ''migrates'' south faster than navigational maps can follow, making the inlet tricky for visiting fishermen.</p>
        <p>''Jetties would stop the erosion,'' Mann insists with controlled anger. ''It would keep open the inlet for 500 boats that can be closer to the Gulf Stream. A jetty could mean a new industrial seafood park, a major new fish-processing plant, many more people with jobs and enough export items to affect the balance of trade.''</p>
        <p>Without the jetty, Mann says simply, ''The fishing industry is going down to Wilmington,'' while Pilkey and his anti-engineering brigade will claim a victory for the beaches. Mann scoffs: ''Pilkey never speaks in specifics. This sea-level rise of his is a fantasy. It's nothing you can sit down and rationalize. If what he is saying is true, I'd better pick up my shopping center, the grocery store, restaurant and bank and go 100 miles inland. That's what the Dr. Pilkeys of the world want us to do.''</p>
        <p>IT IS DAWN ON THE BEAUFORT docks. The Duke Marine Lab's cedar shingle buildings are lighted. Pilkey's graduate students are drinking coffee and preparing to present sediment maps and charts from bottom samples they collected in a creek mouth the previous afternoon.</p>
        <p>He asks them: ''What could you tell a community about their erosion problems, based on your maps and charts?'' He listens intently to their findings; the look on his face makes one think he is hearing something important, new and puzzling.</p>
        <p>''With rising sea level and the movement toward the coasts, there is going to be some major decision-making about the shore,'' he says later. ''I want my students to wear two hats in time: to think in geological time - 5,000, 50,000, 500,000 years -and in 1-, 2- and 3-decade chunks; to realize that for man, 100 years is a long period, although it's less than a finger snap for a geologist.''</p>
        <p>He wants, he says, for them to understand beach politics, to be smart enough to confront and control exploiters and to educate the public:</p>
        <p>''I want my students to have a vision that does not necessarily include a bunch of people jammed up against the shoreline.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
