<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; Long-Term View: Gloomy Forecasts</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="168065"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SILK, LEONARD</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DF153DF936A3575BC0A96E948260" item-length="928" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; Long-Term View: Gloomy Forecasts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Leonard Silk</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SILK, LEONARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A PRESIDENTIAL election year is always a time for peering into the future, and everybody's doing it. Despite the current surge of the economy, highlighted by this week's jump in the leading indicators, the longer-term prophecies are, on the whole, gloomy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A PRESIDENTIAL election year is always a time for peering into the future, and everybody's doing it. Despite the current surge of the economy, highlighted by this week's jump in the leading indicators, the longer-term prophecies are, on the whole, gloomy.</p>
        <p>A PRESIDENTIAL election year is always a time for peering into the future, and everybody's doing it. Despite the current surge of the economy, highlighted by this week's jump in the leading indicators, the longer-term prophecies are, on the whole, gloomy.</p>
        <p>One major worry is that continuing Federal budget deficits will undermine the economic growth. In a forthcoming book, ''Day of Reckoning: The Consequences of American Economic Policy Under Reagan and After,'' Prof. Benjamin M. Friedman of Harvard writes: ''Without economic growth, American society will ultimately lose its vibrancy, its dynamic sense of progress, its capacity to accommodate the aims and objectives of diverse groups within the population, its ability to offer such remarkable social mobility and individual opportunity. Without a strong and competitive economy, America as a nation will watch others take its place in the world order.''</p>
        <p>He doesn't see this happening in a sudden, jarring crash, but slowly, steadily, over a period of years, unless the nation changes its unbalanced fiscal policy. He sees this not only as an economic imperative but also as a moral one - an obligation to our children and our children's children.</p>
        <p>''The saddest outcome of all,'' he writes, ''would be for America's decline to go on, but to go on so gradually that by the time the members of the next generation are old enough to begin asking who was responsible for their diminished circumstances, they will not even know what they have lost.''</p>
        <p>In the current environment, good news arouses anxieties about bad news to follow. The economy's brisk advance, low rate of unemployment and high rate of capacity utilization give rise to worries about inflation, rising interest rates and recession after the election. The recovery of the dollar awakens fears that the recent improvement in the trade deficit, chiefly a result of the dollar's earlier decline, will cause the trade figures to go into reverse and send the dollar sinking again.</p>
        <p>Some economists say the dollar has been pushed up by the Reagan Administration to give the economy a healthier appearance in this election year -to hold down inflation and inflation fears, to enhance the attractiveness of dollar assets and keep foreign capital flowing in and to reduce pressures on the Federal Reserve to raise interest rates.</p>
        <p>A West German economic consultant, Kurt Richebaecher, and his associate, Harold van Buren Cleveland, formerly the chief international economist of Citicorp, call the rise of the dollar a ''speculative bubble'' and declare: ''Despite the re-emergence of predictions that the decline of the dollar is finally over, the central risk facing the world economy remains an eventual hard landing for the dollar,'' which, they predict, would cause United States interest rates to soar, Wall Street to crash and the economy to plunge into a recession.</p>
        <p>The new trade bill, which President Reagan is expected to sign, is intended to open markets wider for American goods, although some foreign officials and members of Congress fear that it may increase protectionism at home and abroad.</p>
        <p>While the American trade figures have improved, many economists are still fearful of the persistence of large deficits in the more comprehensive balance of payments on current account, which includes services and interest payments. C. Fred Bergsten, director of the Institute for International Economics, calls America's current-account deficit dangerous and wants urgent action.</p>
        <p>What bothers Mr. Bergsten and virtually all other economists is that America's heavy borrowing from abroad is being used to finance high consumption, which it can no longer afford, rather than productive investment, which would spur economic growth and help keep America competitive.</p>
        <p>But economists grow wary of predicting that disaster will strike at any particular time. Foreign capital still flows into the United States, sustaining the advance; when private capital inflow languishes, foreign central banks take over until it revives. Americans are troubled by keeping their economy moving by selling their assets, but the alternative of living within their means still seems too painful, economically and politically.</p>
        <p>The inflation rate is creeping upward, but some forces are likely to restrain the rise: spare production capacity in the world economy, greater oil supplies if the Iran-Iraq war ends and sterner post-election Fed policies to slow the economy down.</p>
        <p>Muddling through in the short run promises to continue, however much the economists may warn that in the long run disaster will arrive. Grover Gillett, a Dallas-based prophet, offers these more alarming ''visions of the future'':</p>
        <p>* A reduction of the burden of the national debt through monetary inflation.</p>
        <p>* A decline of G.N.P. in some nations because of the AIDS epidemic's effect on the work force.</p>
        <p>* An increase in the number of bankers and other professionals serving prison terms.</p>
        <p>* A re-regulation of banking in the United States. To such prophecies, one might add these: Economists will keep making conditional forecasts of disasters, urging corrective actions now.</p>
        <p>They will be partly successful. Governments will take half-measures to ward off disasters. If economic disasters actually strike, as they occasionally do, stronger corrective actions will be taken and the end of civilization will be staved off again.</p>
        <p>An ecological disaster would be far more serious - not enough time for an adequate response. When the ozone layer goes, there's no way to get it back.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
