<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Great Flood of Heat: 42 Days And 42 Nights, and Life Is Altered</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="170913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KERR, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6D81530F937A2575BC0A96E948260" item-length="1251" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Great Flood of Heat: 42 Days And 42 Nights, and Life Is Altered</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER KERR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KERR, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Six weeks now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Six weeks now.</p>
        <p>Six weeks now.</p>
        <p>Forty-two days when the sun and seas and sins of man have conspired to transform New York life into a seemingly endless slog through simmering broth.</p>
        <p>And yesterday, after six weeks of sweltering weather, people were talking less about the possibility of a break in the heat than how the coming of the Northeastern tropics has altered the way human beings work, play, sleep and attempt to escape.</p>
        <p>At Kennedy International Airport, technicians in charge of a monstrous machine that chills the air in 10 passenger terminals admitted that their mighty dynamo had just about pooped. Some street vendors selling ice cream acknowledged there may be such a thing as a season too hot for Popsicles. And thousands of New Yorkers who might have sought relief at the area's beaches stayed away, officials said, because of recent reports of pollution and medical waste washing ashore. Longing for Autumn</p>
        <p>Across the poorest sections of New York - neighborhoods where millions live without the cocoons of air-conditioned apartments and restaurants - children looked longingly at closed fire hydrants, and adults on stoops closed their eyes, envisioning a still distant fall.</p>
        <p>''You stay as cool as you can, that's all I can tell you,'' said 70-year-old Evelyn Qualls, as she sat on her stoop on 164th Street between St. Nicholas and Edgecombe Avenues, sipping an ice tea and smoking a cigarette. ''Don't get excited, stay out of the sun and take it real easy.''</p>
        <p>Fred Gadomski, a meteorologist at Pennsylvania State University, said New York City is enduring its worst heat wave since the mid-1950's. Some scientists have linked the unusually hot weather this summer and droughts in the Middle West to slow, long-term climatic changes brought about by man and often referred to as the ''greenhouse effect.'' It Just Won't Let Up</p>
        <p>What is most unusual about this summer's suffering in the Northeast, Mr. Gadomski said, is that in most years, days of intense heat are followed by a few cooler ones. In Newark, in fact, this is the longest spell of consecutive days of 90 degree heat on record. In Central Park, the National Weather service yesterday recorded a high of 96, tying the record for the day set in 1944.</p>
        <p>The only chance for cooling in the next several days is the possibility of isolated afternoon thunderstorms. Hope for real relief is truly distant: it is a front now over Siberia that would take at least four or five days to reach the Great Lakes and the Northeast.</p>
        <p>The heat and heavy use of air conditioners continued to strain the region's power system. Power failures in Queens affected 10,000 customers in Laurelton, Rosedale, Cambria Heights and St. Albans. Power was restored by 6:15 A.M. yesterday.</p>
        <p>Beach attendance was down dramatically at the five beaches in New York City that have been declared safe: Coney Island and Manhattan Beach in Brooklyn, Rockaway in Queens, Orchard in the Bronx and Wolfe's Pond in Staten Island. The total Saturday attendance at these beaches as of 2 P.M. was 48,813, compared with the normal crowd of about a half million on a hot summer's day. Polar Bears Envied</p>
        <p>Attendance was unusually heavy at the city's parks, and particularly popular was the newly opened zoo in Central Park, where visitors could choose to view animals in the tropical, temperate and polar habitats. Not surprisingly, polar bears and seals cavorting in their icy, blue pools were the most popular.</p>
        <p>Harold Tier, the supervisor for the north end of Central Park, said people have been staying in the park all night during the heat wave.</p>
        <p>At the International Arrivals Building at Kennedy Airport, the huddled masses yearning to breath free - as well as the United States citizens yearning to go home - waited to pass through immigration and customs inspections with the temperature in the mid-80's. The reason: one of the two machines with a cooling power equal to 5,500 tons of ice was out of action, and the other could not keep up with demands of 10 bustling airport terminals.</p>
        <p>''I was supposed to be wearing a tie today,'' said John Di Prima, a Lufthansa Airlines worker, as he cooled himself by unbuttoning his shirt and exposing most of his chest and abdomen. ''It's a sauna in here. This is my protest against the Port Authority.'' Less Is More Comfortable</p>
        <p>On the streets of Washington Heights in upper Manhattan and across the Harlem River in the South Bronx, outfits of shorts and T-shirts, or shorts and no shirts, were de rigueur.</p>
        <p>At the Fort Washington Hardware and Houseware store near 161st Street and Broadway, the most effective advertisement was an impressive array of fans and air conditioners lined up on the sidewalk.</p>
        <p>Luis Hernandez, the storekeeper said, ''The only thing that's moving is fans and fuses.''</p>
        <p>''It's not a rich neighborhood, you know,'' Mr. Hernandez said, by way of an explanation why air conditioners weren't being snapped up as well. His clientele, mostly emigrants from the Dominican Republic, he said, ''don't want fans, they want air conditioners - but they don't have the money.'' Blown Fuses</p>
        <p>The sale of fuses, needed to replace those burned out in power overloads, often required a brief lecture on the hazards of electricity, Mr. Hernandez said.</p>
        <p>''When a fuse goes out, they come in and ask for a stronger one. I have to try to convince them that if they do that they'll end up with a fire.''</p>
        <p>In New York, of course, there will always be the rich - or those inspired by the affluent.</p>
        <p>Al Schatzberg, an evening-wear manufacturer from Manhattan, his colleague, Lenny Wolf, and their two friends from Dallas, Cheree Roberts and Debbie Stanton, sat at one of the windowside tables on an air-conditioned ''mini-liner,'' a boat that offered a two-hour luxury luncheon in New York Harbor.</p>
        <p>''We're doing something touristy to entertain the gals,'' Mr. Schatzberg said. ''Regis Philbin talked on TV about taking his mother-in-law on this. If Regis can do it, I can do it.'' Tempers Are Also Hot</p>
        <p>In midtown, there was evidence to support the theory that temperatures and tempers tend to rise in tandem.</p>
        <p>''Wait a minute, you come in here and start out shouting - the first word out of your mouth was belligerent!,'' said a cashier at a drug store on 42d Street between Fifth and Sixth Avenues. A moment earlier, three young tourists had started shrieking that a sign in the store window misled them about the price of cigarettes. One of the tourists eventually apologized.</p>
        <p>''I'm sorry, but we've been pushed around by New Yorkers all day,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, some salesmen of ice cream and ices proferred a widely held theory inside their industry that prolonged, extreme heat waves actually diminish the public's desire for cool snacks.</p>
        <p>''The business has been down, down, down,'' said Mostapha Echawadi, 24, whose boysenberry cones were moving very slowly indeed at the corner of 48th Street and the Avenue of the Americas. ''The hot dog guys, the shish kebab guys, they are making a killing. I just don't know why.''</p>
        <p>A few blocks north, a crowd of protesters on their second-day vigil against the opening of the film ''The Last Temptation of Christ'' - which they argue is sacrilegious - sweated as they sang Christian songs but argued that the temperatures of recent weeks were modest in comparison to those that will be experienced by many souls at a later date.</p>
        <p>''This is just a light spring breeze, you know,'' said John Leone, 26 of Brooklyn. ''This is really nothing at all.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
