<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WASHINGTON TALK: Environmental Protection Agency; Soul-Searching int he Face of Outside Criticism</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="198140"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DB1E39F936A25752C1A96E948260" item-length="1122" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WASHINGTON TALK: Environmental Protection Agency; Soul-Searching int he Face of Outside Criticism</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In a city whose institutions are given more to self-congratulation than self-examination, it is rare to find a Government agency pausing for moments of introspection.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In a city whose institutions are given more to self-congratulation than self-examination, it is rare to find a Government agency pausing for moments of introspection.</p>
        <p>In a city whose institutions are given more to self-congratulation than self-examination, it is rare to find a Government agency pausing for moments of introspection.</p>
        <p>But the Environmental Protection Agency, one of the busiest and at times most beleaguered Federal regulatory bodies, has taken several critical looks at its own efficiency and effectiveness in recent years.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, the agency's top officials reviewed all anti-pollution activities and concluded that their priorities were frequently misplaced. They found that some of the more threatening and pervasive environmental problems, like indoor air pollution and pesticides, were not getting enough attention, while others were receiving more attention than warranted by the risks they presented to public health and the environment. The agency subsequently changed its priorities.</p>
        <p>Now the question is again being raised within the E.P.A. whether the agency is carrying out its mandate adequately or if it is capable of doing so. A Critical Examination</p>
        <p>The current EPA Journal, an official monthly publication, carries an article by a staff member that critically examines the agency's performance and offers advice on how it might do better. Other articles, by outside experts, also recommend ways the country might do a better job of protecting the environment.</p>
        <p>Despite substantial achievements in environmental protection over the last 20 years, there is still a general feeling of disappointment that more has not been done, according to an essay in the magazine by Michael Gruber, an official in the environmental agency's Seattle office. Mr. Gruber is serving there on temporary assignment from the Washington State's Department of Natural Resources.</p>
        <p>''There is a pervasive sense in the nation at large, and even within the ranks of E.P.A., that we should be doing better, that there is a continuing and even expanding gap between the expectation and what E.P.A. can deliver,'' Mr. Gruber wrote.</p>
        <p>The article cites a variety of reasons for the agency's failure to meet expectations. One is ''a patchwork'' legal structure that pulls the agency in different directions in dealing with pollution. As a result the agency deals with air, water and land pollution as separate issues. Another problem is that the agency is often forced to act without enough scientific data to determine how much risk a pollutant poses.</p>
        <p>Also limiting the agency's effectiveness, the article said, is a budget that has not increased in more than a decade, after allowing for inflation, while the jobs it is required to undertake have grown substantially. Conflicting Public Demands</p>
        <p>Finally, the public's conflicting demands - protection from the risk of cancer-causing substances but dependence on the substances that cause those risks - discourage boldness among agency policy makers, Mr. Gruber said.</p>
        <p>He also offered some suggestions for improving the agency's performance. For one, he contended, environmental policy must ''recognize the interconnectedness of the environment'' and adopt programs that do not simply move pollution from the air to the land or from the land to the water. Instead of seeking to control all pollution, which he contended is an unrealistic goal, the agency should strive to reduce the risks to both public health and the natural environment.</p>
        <p>Rather than devote much of its resources to making small reductions in the dangers from chemicals and other pollutants, Mr. Gruber said, ''the E.P.A. should refocus its resources and concentrate on the big problems again, both those that remain in the United States and those of the global community.'' Emphasis on Global Issues</p>
        <p>John H. Gibbons, director of Congress's Office of Technology Assessment, urged in a second article that the agency put more emphasis on protecting the global environment from threats like climate change caused by industrial gases and the destruction of the earth's ozone shield.</p>
        <p>In a third article, Raymond C. Loehr, professor of environmental and water resources at the University of Texas, wrote that the agency needs to shift its perspective from ''end-of-the-pipe'' pollution control - reducing pollution as it emerges from smokestacks, exhaust pipes and other sources -to preventing pollution from being created. The agency, and the nation, should also build a research and development program aimed at reducing environmental risks, Dr. Loehr said.</p>
        <p>The Administrator of the E.P.A., Lee M. Thomas, said in an interview that although the agency did ''an adequate job of protecting the environment,'' there were a number of factors preventing it from more efficiently carrying out its mandate.</p>
        <p>For one thing, he said, the resources given to the agency are not keeping pace with its added responsibilities. ''The agency just can't keep up with the increasing workload,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Mr. Thomas said, Congress has been giving the agency more things to do without telling it what its priorities should be. ''There are 75 different subcommittees up on Capitol Hill that claim jurisidiction over the E.P.A., but there is no institutional framework up there giving us a sense of priorities,'' he said. Penchant for Soul-Searching</p>
        <p>There are a variety of explanations for the environmental agency's penchant for soul-searching. For one, the agency was not created by an act of Congress but was established in 1971 to comply with an executive order issued by President Nixon. Lacking the foundation of a specific statute to give it shape and function, the agency has based its mission on a series of environmental laws passed by Congress. As a result, the E.P.A. appears to suffer a kind of perpetual identity crisis.</p>
        <p>More significant, perhaps, is the criticism the agency faces for virtually every action it takes. The E.P.A. can rarely make a regulatory move without being attacked, often through the courts, by industry or by conservationists. Environmental issues, particularly pollution issues, tend to provoke passionate responses, and the E.P.A. is generally caught in the middle.</p>
        <p>Finally, the agency was the object of substantial mistrust and scrutiny by the public and Congress in the early years of the Reagan Administration. A perception that the Administration was trying to weaken the agency and enforce the laws in ways more acceptable to industry than to the general public, led to Congressional investigations, an upheaval in the agency, including the resignation of its Administrator, Anne M. Burford, and a decline in morale among agency staff.</p>
        <p>Although the agency appears to have largely recovered from that trauma, the events of that period may have helped instill a practice of self-examination and criticism.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
