<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'89 Drought Feared as a World Catastrophe</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="184252"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DROUGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WORLDWATCH INSTITUTE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWN, LESTER R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DD1339F931A35753C1A96E948260" item-length="612" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'89 Drought Feared as a World Catastrophe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Another drought in 1989 would be catastrophic for the world's food supply and cause a scramble by needy countries for dwindling grain supplies, an economist said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Another drought in 1989 would be catastrophic for the world's food supply and cause a scramble by needy countries for dwindling grain supplies, an economist said today.</p>
        <p>Another drought in 1989 would be catastrophic for the world's food supply and cause a scramble by needy countries for dwindling grain supplies, an economist said today.</p>
        <p>The economist, Lester R. Brown, president of Worldwatch Institute, a nonprofit research organization based in Washington, said in a report that uncertainties lingered concerning a link between the earth's gradual warming trend and this year's drought.</p>
        <p>''The 1989 U.S. grain crop could be a bin-busting one - the largest ever,'' he said. ''Or it could be even smaller than the drought-reduced one in 1988.'' The report said that releasing carbon dioxide and other chemicals into the atmosphere was generally recognized as producing an effect in which the world's climate is warming up over the long term. ''Whether or not the crop-damaging summer heat and dryness experienced in North America and central China during 1988 is caused by the warming, it does indicate what we should expect as greenhouse gases accumulate,'' Mr. Brown said. Warm Years vs. Drought</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown said meteorologists had reported that, globally, the five warmest years of the past century occurred in 1980, 1981, 1983, 1987 and 1988, and the three American harvests most sharply reduced by drought since the middle of the century came in 1980, 1983 and 1988.</p>
        <p>''If the warming is under way and 1989 is warmer than 1988, just as it in turn was warmer than 1987, drought and heat could be even more destructive,'' Mr. Brown said. ''If the 1989 U.S. harvest were to be severely reduced by drought, exports would slow to a trickle.''</p>
        <p>The economist, who has written and given lectures about world food problems, acknowledged that there was ''a vast potential for expanding world food output,'' but he added that farmers were having trouble keeping pace with a growing population. 'Pipeline Supplies' Projected</p>
        <p>''If farmers had unlimited resources,'' he said, ''they could easily feed the projected increases in population, but they are entering the 90's with little prospect for expanding their cropland area, a scarcity of fresh water and no major new technologies to help them boost output.''</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Brown's computations, the global reserve of grain will be reduced to a 54-day supply by the time new harvests are ready in 1989. He described this amount as ''little more than pipeline supplies'' of food for much of the world. The grain he referred to is in stocks held over from harvests by various countries, primarily the United States. Mr. Brown said 250 million tons of grain would be left over at the end of this year's season, against an estimated world consumption of 1.673 billion tons of grain. Thus, the leftover stockpile would be about 15 percent of the year's consumption, or a 54-day supply. Agriculture Dept.'s Estimates</p>
        <p>Although the 54-day estimate of world grain is smaller than the 57-day supply in the early 1970's, when world grain prices skyrocketed, the latest figures by the United States Department of Agriculture show that stockpiles are somewhat better than Mr. Brown's projections. On the basis of indications at the beginning of September, the Agriculture Department says the world grain reserve may be about 62 days by the 1989 harvest. The department says that figure is based on world grain consumption of 1.655 billion tons and a leftover inventory of about 283 million tons, or a little more than 17 percent of estimated consumption.</p>
        <p>In either case, 54 days or 62 days means relatively low world grain inventories for 1989, against an 89-day supply at the start of 1988, and means more pressure will be exerted on farmers to produce bumper crops next year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
