<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Ozone Is Depleted, Much of Life Could Go With It</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="136911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="IDEAS &amp; TRENDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sun</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED8153CF934A25757C0A96E948260" item-length="986" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Ozone Is Depleted, Much of Life Could Go With It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THERE is scientific consensus now that certain industrial chemicals are destroying the atmosphere's protective ozone layer, leaving the earth and all the life upon it increasingly exposed to damaging ultraviolet radiation from the sun. But scientists remain largely in the dark about what effects that radiation will have on the earth's ecology.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THERE is scientific consensus now that certain industrial chemicals are destroying the atmosphere's protective ozone layer, leaving the earth and all the life upon it increasingly exposed to damaging ultraviolet radiation from the sun. But scientists remain largely in the dark about what effects that radiation will have on the earth's ecology.</p>
        <p>THERE is scientific consensus now that certain industrial chemicals are destroying the atmosphere's protective ozone layer, leaving the earth and all the life upon it increasingly exposed to damaging ultraviolet radiation from the sun. But scientists remain largely in the dark about what effects that radiation will have on the earth's ecology.</p>
        <p>A recent report by a panel of Government and academic scientists that was convened by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration found that chlorofluorocarbons and halons - chemicals used in the manufacture of refrigerants, foam insulation and solvents, among other things - are destroying atmospheric ozone more rapidly than computer models had anticipated.</p>
        <p>Ozone has declined by a global average of more than 2 percent, the panel reported, and will almost certainly drop further because tons of the chemicals have been released into the atmosphere and are rising slowly toward the ozone shield.</p>
        <p>Scientists generally agree that increased ultraviolet radiation will bring a sharp rise in skin cancers, largely among fair-skinned people. The Environmental Protection Agency has calculated that in the United States alone there will be more than 155 million additional cases of skin cancer and 3.2 million additional cancer deaths over the next century if the ozone destruction continues at its current pace.</p>
        <p>But damage to other organisms, especially those in the lower tiers of the earth's food chains, could ultimately prove far worse. F. Sherwood Rowland, a scientist at the University of California, Irvine, who first warned more than a decade ago that chlorofluorocarbons might be destroying the ozone layer, said in a recent interview that the consequences of this destruction would probably be even more severe for ecological systems than for human health.</p>
        <p>Dr. Thomas P. Coohill, recently elected president of the American Society for Photobiology, said that skin cancer in humans is often regarded as ''the most deleterious effect of ozone depletion.''</p>
        <p>''But in many ways humans can protect themselves from radiation,'' he said. ''I think that plants soaking up all that ultraviolet is more of a worldwide worry. Decreasing crop yields could lead to starvation in many parts of the world.''</p>
        <p>Scientists stress that very little research has been done on the threat of increased ultraviolet radiation to trees, grasslands and crops, mammals, fish, bacteria and the rest of the web of life upon which human existence depends.</p>
        <p>''This is difficult to research because it is a problem that has not happened yet,'' said Martyn M. Caldwell, a science professor at Utah State University who is on assignment at the National Science Foundation. ''My own opinion is that increases in ultraviolet radiation could add up to substantial changes in the ecosystems. But we just don't know.''</p>
        <p>Richard B. Setlow, senior biophysicist in the biology department of the Brookhaven National Laboratory, said: ''It is very clear that increasing ultraviolet will affect these systems, but the magnitudes of the effects are not known. Is it trivial? Is it a large amount?'' One of the unknowns, he said, is the degree to which organisms can adapt to increasing levels of radiation.</p>
        <p>The research that has been done indicates that the consequences of further ozone depletion could be severe, even catastrophic. The Antarctic Example</p>
        <p>Some of these findings have been reported by Dr. Sayed Z. El-Sayed, a professor of oceanography at Texas A&amp;M University who recently returned from Antarctica, where the ozone depletion is especially severe. Dr. El-Sayed studied the effects of ultraviolet radiation on marine phytoplankton, microscopic plants that flourish in the Antarctic Ocean.</p>
        <p>These tiny plants, which Dr. El-Sayed called ''the grass of the sea,'' are the food source of krill, a shrimp that abounds in the Antarctic waters. Krill, in turn, are the principal food of squid, fish, penguins, seals, whales and other animal life in the southern regions of the globe. The phytoplankton are also a major food source of zooplankton, microscopic marine animals that also form an important link in the food chain.</p>
        <p>Dr. El-Sayed's experiments showed that increasing radiation slowed the process of photosynthesis in the phytoplankton, and that they died off almost entirely when ultraviolet radiation was raised 10 percent. The smaller species of these plants, the kind forming the primary food source for the krill, were especially sensitive to the radiation, he found.</p>
        <p>If ultraviolet radiation continues to increase because of a thinning ozone shield, ''we are going to be in some trouble,'' Dr. El-Sayed said. ''I can't predict how much trouble, but it does not bode well. If anything happens to the krill, the whole ecosystem will absolutely collapse. We can say goodbye to the whales, to the seals, to the penguins, et cetera.''</p>
        <p>Research conducted by Dr. Alan F. Teramura, a professor of botany at the University of Maryland, suggests that food crops would also be jeopardized by increased ultraviolet radiation. In experiments on soybeans, Dr. Teramura found that an increase in radiation equivalent to what would result from a 25 percent loss of ozone reduced the yield of the soybean cultivar by 20 to 25 percent. There was also evidence, he said, that the radiation was damaging the quality of the grain, including its protein content, and might increase the plant's vulnerability to insects and weeds.</p>
        <p>While no similar research has been conducted on other crop plants, it has been estimated that two out of three plant species are sensitive to increased ultraviolet radiation, Dr. Teramura noted.</p>
        <p>''At a minimum, our data on soybeans, even as a worst-case scenario, shows us the potential damage of increased levels of ultraviolet radiation,'' the botanist said. ''We can only hope that the responses we found are the extreme case, not the general case.''  IDEAS &amp; TRENDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
