<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>6 Weeks of the Arts, Latin and Experimental</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="194492"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART SHOWS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LATIN AMERICA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">MUSEO DEL BARRIO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">YARROW, ANDREW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DB1739F937A35752C1A96E948260" item-length="1109" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>6 Weeks of the Arts, Latin and Experimental</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW L. YARROW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">YARROW, ANDREW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Experimental performance and visual art by Latin American and American Latino artists has rarely been seen in New York theaters or galleries. But such art is thriving, as a six-week exhibition and performance series opening today at El Museo del Barrio testifies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Experimental performance and visual art by Latin American and American Latino artists has rarely been seen in New York theaters or galleries. But such art is thriving, as a six-week exhibition and performance series opening today at El Museo del Barrio testifies.</p>
        <p>Experimental performance and visual art by Latin American and American Latino artists has rarely been seen in New York theaters or galleries. But such art is thriving, as a six-week exhibition and performance series opening today at El Museo del Barrio testifies.</p>
        <p>The program, Up Tiempo Performing and Visual Artists of the Americas, features large-scale art installations, 15 nights of free performances by experimental musicians, dancers, poets and others, and two video series. The artists come from throughout the hemisphere, yet all address such concerns of their communities as poverty, environmental blight, religion and AIDS.</p>
        <p>Because Up Tiempo is a collaboration between the museum and Creative Time, a nonprofit organization that presents experimental arts, it serves as a bridge between the avant-garde art world and the Latino community.</p>
        <p>''Not many Latino or black artists are involved in the downtown art scene,'' said Petra Barreras, the director of the museum, on upper Fifth Avenue. ''This is an opportunity to bring these artists to downtown or midtown audiences, and to show our audience that not every Hispanic artist is doing traditional painting or sculpture.'' This Time, Art in a Museum</p>
        <p>Cee Brown, the director of Creative Time, also sees the collaboration as a departure for both institutions. Not only will the museum be showing more avant-garde art than usual, but this will also be the first time that a museum space has been used by Creative Time, which is best known for presenting art in such unlikely places as the Brooklyn Bridge Anchorage and the old Battery Park City landfill. With the show's performances and large-scale installations, Mr. Brown said, ''we're activating a museum in a way museum spaces usually aren't.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Barreras and Mr. Brown emphasize, as the exhibition catalogue does, that this is not a Hispanic art show. '' 'Hispanic' is a problematic word that wasn't coined by Latinos, and not all artists in the show are of Spanish-speaking background,'' Ms. Barreras said. ''But the exhibition does deal with issues facing the Latino community, and, since it's being housed in El Museo - which is a museum of Puerto Rican and Latin American art - it's ironic to say that this isn't a 'Hispanic' show.''</p>
        <p>It is clear that the works included in Up Tiempo are all what Mr. Brown called ''art with a purpose.'' This is particularly true of ''The Passage,'' a work by Josely Carvalho and Catalina Parra, two South American artists, about the rape of Gaea, the Greek goddess of the Earth, and her revenge in the form of acid rain, ozone depletion and other environmental ravages. A U-shaped ramp is surrounded by tableaux of rabbit skins, dried fish and silk-screen images of Gaea's scream. Dolls and Nightmares</p>
        <p>One's worst nightmares are realized in a nearby gallery filled with about 20 bizarre and sinister ''sculptural dolls'' by Norma Bessouet. One is a Medusa-like creature with hair made of twigs; another has a rose for a face, and yet another is imprisoned in a bird cage. ''People are more afraid of dolls than sculptures because they seem closer to human beings,'' the Argentine artist said.</p>
        <p>The same gallery, which is normally devoted to folkloric saint figurines from Puerto Rico, is also being used for works by the New York artist Manny Vega dealing with the deities and ceremonial practices of Afro-Caribbean religion.</p>
        <p>Marcelo Llorens, an Argentine artist, says that his work, ''La Muerte,'' reflects the ''fact that, unlike European culture, our culture has gone through sudden death several times in the wake of conquering or overwhelming powers.'' In his shrinelike installation, lithographs of Argentine soldiers paper the floor, stencils of skeletons cover the walls and historic examples of cultural destruction -from the Spanish conquest to AIDS -are represented.</p>
        <p>AIDS-related issues are also presented, from the perspective of Latino and black children, in a corridor full of graphics and video works made by Act-Up, an acronym for an advocacy group called the AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power. Free Performances</p>
        <p>The free performance series begins tonight at 7:30 with works by three artists. James Luna, a Luiseno-Digueno Indian from California, will explore corruption and apathy among Indians in a performance piece and installation that simulates an Indian tribal meeting. Jonas dos Santos, a Brazilian performance artist, will delve into archetypes of macumba, a popular Afro-Brazilian religious cult. And Donald Woods, a New York poet, intends to ''speak to social and family issues, from racism to romance, with music from gospel to the Shirelles,'' he said, adding that he will be accompanied by an a capella group, Sons and Daughters.</p>
        <p>Chico Alvarez and Nosotros, an Afro-Cuban band; Kajou, a Haitian pop group, and Orquestra Broadway, a charanga band that combines African and Latin music with classical instrumentation, will highlight an evening of Caribbean dance music at 8 P.M. tomorrow. The host will be Al Angeloro, a disk jockey for WBAI, 99.5 FM, which is to broadcast the concert live.</p>
        <p>Performers in subsequent weeks are to include the Los Angeles Poverty Department, a group of skid-row drifters and homeless singers and writers (Nov. 10-12), and readings by Amiri Baraka, Miguel Algarin and other poets associated with the Nuyorican Poets' Cafe of the Lower East Side of Manhattan (Nov. 29 and 30).</p>
        <p>The Eddie Torres Latin Dance Company, known for its high-energy mambos, and the Manuel Alum Dance Company, a contemporary troupe informed by such far-flung cultural influences as Japanese Noh theater, are to perform together on Dec. 1 and 2. And the series is to conclude with a flourish on Dec. 10, when an evening of house music and voguing is presented by David Bronstein, a video director. Born in Latino and black underground nightclubs, these performance styles parody mainstream fashion and music. Videos on War</p>
        <p>Videos documenting eight years of war in El Salvador, shot by the El Salvador Media Project, are to be shown through Nov. 20, and highlights of the 1988 National Latino Film and Video Festival, organized by the museum, are to be presented Nov. 23 through Dec. 10.</p>
        <p>Up Tiempo is sponsored by the Philip Morris Companies, and the series' installations are interspersed among paintings and sculptures by Edgar Franceschi, a Puerto Rican-born artist whose recent work is on view through Dec. 4 at the museum.</p>
        <p>The museum is at 1230 Fifth Avenue, near 104th Street, and is open Wednesdays through Sundays from 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission is $2; $1 for students and the elderly. Information: 831-7272 or 619-1955.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
