<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>COMPANY BRIEFS</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="205206"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY BRIEFS (NYT COLUMN)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D9153DF93AA35751C1A96E948260" item-length="405" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>COMPANY BRIEFS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: * Airco, Murray Hill, N.J., the U.S. gases business of the BOC Group of Britain, agreed to buy the Industrial Gases and Carbon Dioxide divisions of Amerigas Inc., a subsidiary of UGI Corp., for about $171.5 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: * Airco, Murray Hill, N.J., the U.S. gases business of the BOC Group of Britain, agreed to buy the Industrial Gases and Carbon Dioxide divisions of Amerigas Inc., a subsidiary of UGI Corp., for about $171.5 million.</p>
        <p>* Airco, Murray Hill, N.J., the U.S. gases business of the BOC Group of Britain, agreed to buy the Industrial Gases and Carbon Dioxide divisions of Amerigas Inc., a subsidiary of UGI Corp., for about $171.5 million.</p>
        <p>* Amoco Corp., Chicago, said it had completed the acquisition of the Rocky Mountain division of Tenneco Oil Co. for $900 million. Amoco also said its Amoco Production Co. would lay off some workers next year and might consolidate its offices in New Orleans and Houston.</p>
        <p>* Citicorp said that through a debt swap it had acquired a 15 percent equity stake in Grupo Femsa, Mexico's largest beer producer.</p>
        <p>* FGIC Corp., said it had authorized its president, Gerald L. Friedman, to negotiate a definitive agreement for the sale of the company to the GE Capital unit of General Electric Co.</p>
        <p>* General Electric Co. received $234.7 million in military contracts, including a $225.1 million contract for Navy submarine combat systems.</p>
        <p>* General Motors Corp. said its Pontiac and Chevrolet division had extended their sales incentive programs.</p>
        <p>* Harris Corp., Melbourne, Fla., said it would furnish about 40 super-microcomputers for McDonnell Douglas to use in its Air Force contract.</p>
        <p>* Hart Holding Co. agreed to sell its consumer products group to Dawson International P.L.C. for $149 million plus the assumption of liabilities.</p>
        <p>* International Business Machines Corp. said it had shipped 25,000 of its new AS/400 mid-range computers since Aug. 24, a number that was slightly ahead of I.B.M.'s projections.</p>
        <p>* Maytag Corp., Newton, Iowa, sold its Jenn Industries subsidiary to Snyder General Corp., a privately held company based in Dallas. Terms were not disclosed.</p>
        <p>* McDermott International Inc., New Orleans, said its Babcock &amp; Wilcox subsidiary had received $300 million in Energy Department contracts.</p>
        <p>* Nevada National Bancorp, Reno, said the Federal Reserve Board had approved its $38 million merger with a unit of Security Pacific Corp.</p>
        <p>* Pennwalt Corp., Philadelphia, a chemical company, said it would buy 4.75 million shares of its common stock at $85 a share.</p>
        <p>* Philip Morris Cos. completed its acquisition of Kraft Inc. for $106 a share, or $12.9 billion total. The deal makes Philip Morris the world's largest consumer-products company.</p>
        <p>* Smith &amp; Nephew P.L.C., London, a health-care products group, said it would buy Ioptex Research Inc., a U.S. lens maker, for $236 million.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
