<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's a Corker</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="78" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="188252"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="WINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CORK</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PRIAL, FRANK J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cork</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DA1E38F935A25753C1A96E948260" item-length="947" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's a Corker</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK J. PRIAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PRIAL, FRANK J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: SOME YEARS AGO, IN A pleasant Stockholm restaurant, I ordered a bottle of Chablis to complement a good Swedish fish. The wine was fine; so was the fish. Still, something was wrong. It was the wine bottle. The Chablis had been imported by the Swedish Government monopoly and bottled with, of all things, a screw cap.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: SOME YEARS AGO, IN A pleasant Stockholm restaurant, I ordered a bottle of Chablis to complement a good Swedish fish. The wine was fine; so was the fish. Still, something was wrong. It was the wine bottle. The Chablis had been imported by the Swedish Government monopoly and bottled with, of all things, a screw cap.</p>
        <p>SOME YEARS AGO, IN A pleasant Stockholm restaurant, I ordered a bottle of Chablis to complement a good Swedish fish. The wine was fine; so was the fish. Still, something was wrong. It was the wine bottle. The Chablis had been imported by the Swedish Government monopoly and bottled with, of all things, a screw cap.</p>
        <p>Such is the power of suggestion. To any wine drinker - except, perhaps, those who work for the Swedish monopoly - a cork is immediately identified with first-quality wine, a screw cap with eminently lesser stuff. Last year, when the E. &amp; J. Gallo Winery wanted to upgrade its famous Hearty Burgundy, one of the first steps was to begin using corks.</p>
        <p>For wines that will be consumed within a year or two after they are sold, there is no need for corks. In fact, most of these inexpensive wines might be better without corks, which tend to bring problems of their own to the bottling process. But so fixed in the public mind as a symbol of quality is the lowly wine cork that most wine producers, particularly makers of sparkling wine and Champagne, spend great amounts of money buying, storing and inserting corks in their bottles.</p>
        <p>Do corks permit wine to ''breathe''? No. A good, solid cork, well fitted in the bottle, lets nothing in. Whatever changes take place in the wine over a period of years are caused by organic constituents of the wine and by the air present at the time of bottling. Old corks that have dried out and shrunk will let in air, but that process takes many years. Bordeaux chateaus estimate the life of a good cork to be about 30 years, and change the corks in their old wines about every 25 years.</p>
        <p>Some years ago, Chateau Lafite-Rothschild scored a publicity coup of sorts by sending a team to the United States to top off and recork old Lafites for their owners. Some very old Lafites took a new lease on life when they were topped off with young wines and given sturdy, new corks. Not that corks are always the answer to longevity: the chateaus find recorked bottles that have gone bad and, occasionally, very old wines under the original corks that are in splendid condition. Champagne makers would give anything to find an acceptable substitute for cork. The operative word is ''acceptable.'' There are excellent plastic corks available and, because most Champagne is consumed soon after it is purchased, plastic stoppers would be perfectly adequate. But there is no place for plastic in Champagne's carefully cultivated image of luxury. A good Champagne cork can cost up to 50 cents, and some producers ship millions of bottles of Champagne each year. A few of the old, traditional concerns, such as Bollinger and Krug, use two corks: one for the remuage, the period before the bottle is opened and the yeast cells are disgorged, and one to ship the bottle to be sold. Most Champagne firms use a metal cap for the remuage period, much like the cap on a bottle of Coca-Cola.</p>
        <p>A Champagne cork fashioned from a single piece of cork is rare. Most Champagne corks are made with cork agglomerate, a mixture of chopped cork and glue. Frequently, two natural cork disks are affixed to the bottom of the cork to serve as a buffer between agglomerate and the wine. The bottles have a flared ring just below the top so that the cork can be held in by a metal cap and wire hood.</p>
        <p>Without the wire, the pressure of the carbon dioxide in the Champagne would soon force the cork out. The pressure is about the same as that in a large truck tire: about 90 pounds per square inch. People who deal regularly with Champagne treat each bottle they are opening like a loaded gun.</p>
        <p>They know that a misdirected cork can cause severe injury. Cork is the bark of a</p>
        <p>Mediterranean oak tree. In dry weather, the cork separates from the wood and can be peeled off, but only once every nine years. According to a paper on corks prepared by researchers at Domaine Chandon, Moet &amp; Chandon's sparkling wine facility in California, it takes 25 years to grow a cork oak tree and another 18 to harvest cork good enough for wine bottles.</p>
        <p>Periodically, someone warns that we're running out of cork. Maybe we are, but if so no one seems to be doing much about it, except for using chopped up scraps instead of solid cork.</p>
        <p>What's more, the amount of wine bottled under cork continues to grow rapidly. It seems that the plain folks who drink screw-top wine are dying off and that the new wine drinkers are upscale types who associate corks with material success.</p>
        <p>One thing about the old jugs: you never had to send one back saying, ''It's corked.'' Corky wine is a fairly serious problem. The only thing that keeps it from being even more serious is the fact that a lot of people drink it and never say anything; they think it's supposed to taste like that.</p>
        <p>Corky wine has a smell and a taste variously associated with damp basements, rotten logs and dirty socks. Recent research indicates that a chlorine bleach used to sterilize the corks used for still wine combines with elements in the cork to produce the moldy smell and taste. The offending substance has been isolated, and there is even a fellow in California who will send you a sample of the foul stuff so you can recognize it when you meet it in a restaurant.</p>
        <p>Tell a French waiter ''this stuff is corky,'' (bouchonne is the word there), and he'll replace it without comment. Here, the manager comes out, then his partner, then his wife. They all smell and sip, looking at you over their shoulders. Finally, one of them says: ''Well, it may be a little off. We've decided to give you another one.''</p>
        <p>You are expected to reply, with a catch in your throat: ''I don't deserve it, but thank you.''  WINE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
