<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Battered and Abused</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="201470"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">OP-ED</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDA1331F936A15752C1A96E948260" item-length="743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Battered and Abused</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM WICKER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Presidential candidates did not mention and probably few Americans noticed a brief, chilling New York Times report from Beijing on Oct. 28: 20 million Chinese may starve and another 80 million will endure severe food shortages in the coming months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Presidential candidates did not mention and probably few Americans noticed a brief, chilling New York Times report from Beijing on Oct. 28: 20 million Chinese may starve and another 80 million will endure severe food shortages in the coming months.</p>
        <p>The Presidential candidates did not mention and probably few Americans noticed a brief, chilling New York Times report from Beijing on Oct. 28: 20 million Chinese may starve and another 80 million will endure severe food shortages in the coming months.</p>
        <p>A natural disaster? Yes, floods and droughts devastated China this year; but its coming ordeal is man-made, too.</p>
        <p>An area of China the size of Italy, about 129,000 square miles, has been denuded of forests and become a virtual desert in the last 30 years - the consequence of indiscriminate cutting for firewood, timber and agricultural clearance. That made floods and drought inevitable, and their consequences worse.</p>
        <p>To its credit, China has undertaken the world's largest reforestation project, more than 4.5 million hectares a year - including a 4,000-mile ''great green wall'' of trees, shrubs and other plantings. Whether the tide of sand, environmental destruction and death can be reversed is not certain - but the effort is surely coming too late for the millions of Chinese facing starvation this winter.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere, the deforestation of the earth - at its worst in the developing world -seems to be proceeding inexorably.</p>
        <p>The World Watch Institute has reported, for example, that ''in less than a decade forest cover within 100 kilometers of India's major cities dropped by 15 percent or more; the area surrounding Delhi lost a staggering 60 percent'' - mostly to firewood cutting.</p>
        <p>A new publication of the World Resources Institute and the International Institute for Environment and Development notes, moreover, that ''600,000 hectares of closed forests are lost each year'' in Indonesia alone. (A hectare is about 2.5 acres.) Around the world, 11 million hectares of tropical forest and other woodlands are lost annually. With world trade in wood and wood products projected to grow for the next 50 years, and with the world's rapidly growing population in dire need of more agricultural land and firewood - about half the world's population already relies on noncommercial firewood as its sole energy source -the desertifying of much of the earth is a real and present prospect.</p>
        <p>Deforestation is one of the worst environmental crises facing the nations of the world; but it is by no means the only one. Much has been written about the ''greenhouse effect,'' the ozone layer and acid rain - none of which honor national boundaries or even hemispheric differences. World Resources, 1988-1989, the new publication already referred to, points out in its summary alone that:</p>
        <p>* Over 60 percent of the world's productive drylands - rangelands, rain-fed croplands, and irrigated drylands - have suffered losses of biological productivity, possibly leading to desert-like conditions. In sub-Saharan Africa, over 80 percent of dry rangelands are desertified already.</p>
        <p>* A decade from now, the urban population of developing regions will be twice the size of the developed world's urban population; half the earth's population, compared to only 30 percent in 1950, will live in urban areas - the most potent generators of sewage, trash and industrial waste, which few cities in developing areas are properly equipped to handle.</p>
        <p>* Habitat losses of all types, mostly forest destruction, threaten species diversity, the loss of which endangers the richly intertwined ecosystems of the earth; in Southeast Asia, 68 percent of wildlife habitat has disappeared and in sub-Saharan Africa, 65 percent has been lost.</p>
        <p>* Worldwide fuel combustion at high temperature now emits into the atmosphere, every year, more than 20 million metric tons of nitric oxide - a major contributor to smog, acid rain and the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>* The world's strained and exploited resources, now supporting about five billion people in varying degrees of misery and affluence, will have to sustain life for more than eight billion by 2025 (a United Nations projection). Africa's population alone then will equal those of Europe, North and South America.</p>
        <p>These threats to life on this battered and abused globe are more ominous and immediate than the danger of nuclear holocaust. If President-elect Bush is determined to protect real national security, he can't relegate such crucial issues of survival to bureaucratic backwaters in the State Department or the Environmental Protection Agency. They belong on the President's own desk, the day he enters the Oval Office - an idea that calls for another article.</p>
        <p>IN THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
