<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="151792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DD113AF935A35755C0A96E948260" item-length="944" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-13  In French parliamentary elections, President Mitterrand's Socialist Party did not poll as well as had been expected in the first round. But itcould win a majority in the runoff vote next week. Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-13  In French parliamentary elections, President Mitterrand's Socialist Party did not poll as well as had been expected in the first round. But itcould win a majority in the runoff vote next week. Page A1</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-13  In French parliamentary elections, President Mitterrand's Socialist Party did not poll as well as had been expected in the first round. But itcould win a majority in the runoff vote next week. Page A1</p>
        <p>Iran is reassessing the war with Iraq in the face of severe international isolation. The top leaders seem preoccupied with a shrinking economy, growing unemployment and the succession to Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini. A1</p>
        <p>George Shultz failed to win support for an American peace plan in the Middle East from Israel's Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir, who remained adamantly opposed to the plan proposed by the Secretary of State. A1</p>
        <p>The decision to expel Mubarak Awad was upheld by the Israeli Supreme Court. The Palestinian-American advocate of nonviolence will be put on an airplane for the United States next Sunday. A12</p>
        <p>A more direct Soviet role in Angola was suggested by a senior Soviet official, who said Moscow was willing to act as co-guarantor of a peace settlement. A8</p>
        <p>New sanctions against South Africa are being pressed by Democratic leaders in the House. The sanctions would impose a sweeping trade embargo and ban virtually all American business investment there. A8</p>
        <p>A Mexican Socialist withdrew from the race for President. Heberto Castillo said he was ending his candidacy in an effort to unite the major left-wing and nationalist parties behind a single candidate. A3</p>
        <p>Two months of peace in Nicaragua have eased the tension that dominated in places like Esteli, in the heart of the war zone. Talks between the contras and the Government are due to resume tomorrow. A3</p>
        <p>Foz do Iguacu journal: A bootlegger's paradise A4</p>
        <p>At least 68 dead in Soviet train explosion A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A14-17, B6-7  More than $1 billion in insurance will be paid by the Government to the depositors of one or more savings institutions that will be shut soon, the chairman of the Federal Home Loan Bank Board said. A1</p>
        <p>A plan to reduce sources of acid rain has been worked out between Governor Cuomo and Gov. Richard Celeste of Ohio. It would require steep cuts in pollution from coal-fired power plants over the next 25 years. A1</p>
        <p>Two nuns will not be dismissed by their order for supporting the right of Roman Catholics to oppose the church's ban on abortion. The Vatican had threatened to discipline the two Americans. A14</p>
        <p>Obstacles to legislation on child care are holding up several bills in Congress that would increase the Federal role in helping working parents take care of their children. A14</p>
        <p>A vote to close a nuclear plant near Sacramento, Calif., could have significant implications for the nuclear power industry. Opponents of the Rancho Seco plant think the referendum may pass. D1  Berkeley journal: Who'll sell tofu puffs after co-ops are gone? A14</p>
        <p>Hearing begins into death of Naval recruit A15</p>
        <p>POLITICS B6-7  Vice President Bush is wealthy, with holdings worth just over $2 million. But because of his bearing, upbringing and years in the Texas oil business, he is often perceived as a man of much greater wealth. A1</p>
        <p>Candidates are wooing Latino voters in anticipation of November's Presidential election. A poll in California among Hispanic voters showed Vice President Bush trailing Gov. Michael S. Dukakis. B6</p>
        <p>Restrictions on registering to vote are being attacked by the Rev. Jesse Jackson, who said one of his goals at the Democratic Convention would be winning a commitment to eliminate virtually all procedural limitations on registration. B7</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON TALK A16  Congressman's stand on drugs  REGIONAL B1-5  Bronx Democratic leaders endorsed the interim prosecutor, Paul T. Gentile, for District Attorney, making him an early favorite in the race and bringing almost full circle the political maneuvers over the nomination. B1</p>
        <p>Fire destroyed a shanty at Yale that students built to protest apartheid in South Africa, and a Yale alumnus taking part in the 30th reunion of his class was arrested and charged with setting the fire. B1</p>
        <p>An emergency drill at Shoreham will begin early tomorrow even though Lilco has announced plans to abandon the nuclear plant. Critics are upset that the utility continues to spend millions of dollars testing the plant. B1</p>
        <p>A husband and wife were murdered in the living room of their Brooklyn apartment while their two children lay tied up in a bedroom. The couple were bound with an electrical cord and shot to death, police said. B1</p>
        <p>Giving free needles to addicts has not increased drug abuse, according to studies in foreign cities, and some needle recipients have even cut down on their frequency of injection. B3</p>
        <p>Congressional races in New Jersey include primary contests in Hudson County, where a 31-year-old lawyer is trying to unseat the 63-year-old incumbent, and in Essex and Union Counties to fill the seat of Peter Rodino, who is retiring. B3</p>
        <p>A new president for Hunter College is expected to be selected from a list of three candidates at the end of the month by the trustees of the City University of New York, City University officials say. B5</p>
        <p>For the Gaiety deli, a new lease on pastrami B2</p>
        <p>Giuliani withheld evidence on Wedtech scandal B2</p>
        <p>Cuomo is subpoenaed to testify on Brawley case B5</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
