<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Utility Planting 52 Million Trees</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="187254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREES AND SHRUBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GUATEMALA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FORESTRY ASSN, AMERICAN</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AES THAMES (CO)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">APPLIED ENERGY SERVICES INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service"></person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Guatemala</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Guatemala</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7D61731F931A25753C1A96E948260" item-length="697" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Utility Planting 52 Million Trees</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP;</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Concerned that its new coal-burning power plant in Connecticut will add to the trend toward a warming of the atmosphere around the globe, an electric utility has come up with an unusual response: it will pay to have trees planted in Guatemala.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Concerned that its new coal-burning power plant in Connecticut will add to the trend toward a warming of the atmosphere around the globe, an electric utility has come up with an unusual response: it will pay to have trees planted in Guatemala.</p>
        <p>Concerned that its new coal-burning power plant in Connecticut will add to the trend toward a warming of the atmosphere around the globe, an electric utility has come up with an unusual response: it will pay to have trees planted in Guatemala.</p>
        <p>The idea is that trees, 52 million of them, will do battle with carbon dioxide, the principal gas implicated in the warming of the globe, as though it were in a greenhouse.</p>
        <p>''Given the scientific consensus on the seriousness of the greenhouse problem, we decided that it was time to stop talking and act,'' said Roger Sant, chief executive of Applied Energy Services, at a news conference here today. Applied Energy Services of Arlington, Va., is the parent of AES Thames, a Connecticut based concern that is to contribute $2 million toward the planting of the trees over 385 square miles in Guatemala.</p>
        <p>Trees will absorb carbon dioxide from sources all over the world, no matter where they are planted. 'An Imaginative Experiment'</p>
        <p>James G. Speth, president of the World Resources Institute, a Washington based research and policy group that helped design the tree planting program, said that ''this is an imaginative experiment in the quest for solutions to the greenhouse effect.''</p>
        <p>''The project is also a viable solution to the serious deforestation problems of a developing country,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In a related development, the American Forestry Association, a conservation group whose members include foresters and woodland owners, will hold a rally here Wednesday to open a national campaign to encourage Americans to plant 100 million trees around the country by 1992. The association hopes the tree planting program will part of ''a major public policy effort aimed at reversing the greenhouse effect.'' Advances Will Be Slow</p>
        <p>The two programs are among the first in which business and industry has responded to the growing alarms being sounded by scientists and policy makers about the anticipated onset of global warming. But both would hardly make a dent in the problem.</p>
        <p>It is estimated that six billion tons of carbon dioxide from fossil fuels is entering the atmosphere each year. At the same time, 26 million acres of trees, which would otherwise absorb some of the carbon dioxide, are being cut down annually.</p>
        <p>To compensate for that much carbon dioxide being put into the atmosphere and that many trees being cut down, it would be necessary to plant as many as 3 billion acres of trees, an area bigger than all of the United States, according to the World Resources Institute, The tree planting program in Guatemala will be managed by CARE, the international relief and development organization, working with the Guatemalan Forestry Service and the United States Peace Corps. The sponsors said that some 40,000 small farmers in Guatemala would be involved in planting the trees on plantations and on small plots.</p>
        <p>In addition to the $2 million from the utility, $2 million cash or services will be contributed by CARE, $1.2 million by the Guatemalan Government, $3.6 million by the United States Agency for International Development and $7.5 million by the Peace Corps. Utility Seeks to Offset Plant</p>
        <p>Mr. Sant said the number of trees to be planted would be able to absorb at least as much carbon dioxide as would be emitted by a new generating plant being built in Uncasville, Conn. The 180 megawatt plant will emit an estimated 15 million tons of carbon dioxide over its 40-year lifetime.</p>
        <p>The consensus view at the moment is that if current trends in the emissions of carbon dioxide and other trace gases continue and if forests continue to be felled at the present rate, the global average temperature would rise by 3 to 8 degrees Fahrenheit toward the middle of the next century. This temperature, scientists believe, is likely to cause major changes in global climate patterns and cause the sea level to rise because of thermal expansion of the oceans and the melting of glaciers.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, environmental activists from 35 nations have gathered in Washington this week to begin mobilizing a worldwide political response to what a statement by its sponsors called ''the greenhouse crisis.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
