<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="175902"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="WASHINGTON TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PUBLIC INTEREST RESEARCH GROUP, US</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ACID RAIN, CITIZENS FOR SENSIBLE CONTROL OF</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GOELITZ, HERMAN, INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, LINDA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BINDER, DAVID</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON TALK PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DA123CF932A3575AC0A96E948260" item-length="634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE AND DAVID BINDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BINDER, DAVID; GREENHOUSE, LINDA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  10 'Good Guys'</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  10 'Good Guys'</p>
        <p>10 'Good Guys'</p>
        <p>The National Women's Political Caucus, which seeks to increase the number of women in public office, does not usually put the spotlight on men. But the caucus has come up with a list of 10 ''good guys,'' men who have made ''notable contributions to the advancement of women in politics, business, entertainment, labor and the media.''</p>
        <p>At a ''good guys awards dinner'' here on Sept. 13, the caucus will honor this select, bipartisan group:</p>
        <p>William E. Brock, the former Secretary of Labor, for supporting affirmative action programs; Gov. Bill Clinton of Arkansas, for supporting child care programs; Gary David Goldberg, producer of the television program ''Family Ties,'' for advocacy of employer-sponsored child care and parental leave; Representative Bill Green, Republican of Manhattan, for supporting feminists; Greg Howard, a cartoonist whose ''Sally Forth'' comic strip offers a wry look at working women.</p>
        <p>Also, John Irving, the novelist and advocate for abortion rights; Representative Peter W. Rodino Jr., Democrat of New Jersey, for leadership on civil rights; Hicks B. Waldron, chairman and chief executive officer of the Avon Corporation, for bringing women and blacks into top positions; William H. Wynn, president of the United Food and Commercial Workers Union, for backing job benefits for women; and Mayor Andrew Young of Atlanta, for making women ''senior participants'' in government.  A Jellybean President</p>
        <p>In Presidential elections, it is hardly unusual for businesses to strive to put Republicans in the White House. But there is an added incentive this year for the Herman Goelitz Corporation. The stakes for the California company may be nothing less than keeping its jellybeans in the White House.</p>
        <p>''Ronald Reagan put us on the map,'' said Peter Cain, a spokesman for the company, which produces Jelly Bellies, the multi-flavored jellybeans favored by President Reagan. ''Jelly Bellies have become one of the President's trademarks.''</p>
        <p>Large jars of the jellybeans have been put on the table at Cabinet meetings, and the President presents all guests who stay at Blair House with a container of the candies.</p>
        <p>''George Bush loves Jelly Bellies,'' Mr. Cain declared.  Asked about the prospects for jellybeans in a non-Republican White House, a spokesman for Michael S. Dukakis said the Democratic candidate was ''not a candy person.''  Fallout Over Acid Rain</p>
        <p>Two Washington-based groups have been lined up on opposite sides in a struggle over whether to adopt legislation to curb industrial emissions suspected of causing acid rain.</p>
        <p>On one side is the U.S. Public Interest Research Group, which describes itself as an environmental advocacy group; on the other side is Citizens for Sensible Control of Acid Rain, which describes itself as a public education group.</p>
        <p>Now, the Public Interest Research Group has turned its guns on on the Sensible Control group, accusing it of being a lobby group for the energy industry in the guise of a citizens' group.</p>
        <p>In a report issued Sunday, the Research Group said that Citizens for Sensible Control had spent $5 million in the last five years to defeat legislation to reduce acid rain, and that virtually all the money came from coal producers and electric utilities.</p>
        <p>Thomas L. Buckmaster, a public relations official representing Citizens for Sensible Control, acknowleged that most of the money came from energy companies. But he insisted that the source of the money was not as important as the citizen participation the group had encouraged. He said citizens, armed with information provided by the group, were the ones who were sending letters to members of Congress to achieve its goals. The group provides them with ready-made, postage-paid letters that need only be signed and mailed.</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON TALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
