<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="129478"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED91531F932A15750C0A96E948260" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-12  In elections in El Salvador, the ruling Christian Democratic Party appeared to have suffered a major defeat, according to Christian Democratic Party officials, diplomatic observers and other unofficial party observers. Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-12  In elections in El Salvador, the ruling Christian Democratic Party appeared to have suffered a major defeat, according to Christian Democratic Party officials, diplomatic observers and other unofficial party observers. Page A1</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-12  In elections in El Salvador, the ruling Christian Democratic Party appeared to have suffered a major defeat, according to Christian Democratic Party officials, diplomatic observers and other unofficial party observers. Page A1</p>
        <p>An Israeli soldier was shot dead in the Israeli-occupied West Bank as he stood guard duty at a Civil Administration office. He was the first Israeli soldier killed during the current unrest. A1</p>
        <p>Shamir assails his U.S. Jewish critics A12</p>
        <p>News analysis: Noriega's isolation has not led the Panamanian military leader to show any further willingness to end his country's 10-month political crisis by voluntarily relinquishing power. A1</p>
        <p>A teen-ager who was a Stalin saint has become, for many, a sinner. The teen-ager, Pavlik Morozov, was glorified as a model Communist for denouncing his father to the Soviet authorities as a class enemy in 1932. A1</p>
        <p>In Honduras, 700 American soldiers were deployed in the city of Jamastran, only 15 miles from the Nicaraguan border. The move was made to reinforce the Reagan Administration's demand that Nicaraguan troops withdraw. A9</p>
        <p>Military analysis: The contras were badly damaged by the Sandinista military offensive last week along the Nicaraguan-Honduran border because they violated an axiom of guerrilla war by allowing themselves to become a fixed target. A8</p>
        <p>In Belfast, Irish nationalists braced for a roundup of the funeral mob that killed two British soldiers Saturday. The Primate and clergy serving the largely Catholic pro-nationalist community said the deeds were plainly murderous. A3</p>
        <p>China's Communist Party chief, Zhao Ziyang, in his first major elaboration on China's political future since his appointment last November, called for the development of a type of town hall democracy for the country. A3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A13-17, B5-6  Ignition of a nuclear fusion reaction in tiny pellets of hydrogen isotopes, producing powerful bursts of energy, has been successfully achieved by Federal researchers in top-secret experiments. A1</p>
        <p>Chemicals depleting the ozone layer are having their uses curbed by industry in the United States and abroad. To their surprise, makers and users of the chemicals are finding that the mandated cutbacks may be relatively painless. A1</p>
        <p>Alcohol and breast cancer are not associated, according to a new study of 7,000 women. The finding contradicts one last year that linked even a few drinks a week to increased risk of breast cancer. A14</p>
        <p>A union organizer's wrestling fame is being used to try to add 1,300 janitors Atlanta's 56 biggest office buildings to union rolls. For many of the janitorial workers, Claude (Thunderbolt) Patterson's name resonates a quirky charisma. A14</p>
        <p>The killing of a gay San Franciscan has led members of the city's gay community to contend that the police investigation of the death demonstrated that the American judicial system often devalues the lives of homosexuals. A17</p>
        <p>The Watergate figure Jeb Magruder says his past was the perfect prologue to his new post as head of the Commission on Values and Ethics in Columbus, Ohio. It was formed after people scooped up cash that fell from an armored car. A16</p>
        <p>Echoes from Armenia in Southern California A13</p>
        <p>Valley Falls Journal: an annual ritual of life A14</p>
        <p>Whittaker Chambers's farm is proposed for landmark A14</p>
        <p>Supremacists force A.T.&amp;T. to set vote on hiring A17</p>
        <p>POLITICS B6-7  The star political money man in 1988 would have to be Robert A. Farmer, Michael S. Dukakis's campaign treasurer. He is the mastermind of what has become probably the most prosperous Democratic Presidential campaign in history. B6</p>
        <p>Jackson solidifies Presidential bid in Texas B6</p>
        <p>In Boston, it's dine and be dined on B6</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON TALK A16  G.S.A.'s rush to award pacts for phone network  REGIONAL B1-4, B7  Small entertainment businesses are being forced to close or move out of the theater district because of large real-estate development in the area. Critics fear that the district's character may be jeopardized. A1</p>
        <p>A man was fatally beaten by a mob of more than a dozen people. The 41-year-old man had just snatched $20 from the hand of a woman in an East Harlem bakery, when he was chased, caught and beaten by the crowd, the police said. A1</p>
        <p>Faced with rising campaign costs and hoping to intimidate potential challengers, top officeholders in New York State have geared up their fund-raising operations to run constantly, not just during election seasons. B1</p>
        <p>A battle against a drug empire in South Jamaica, Queens, is being carried out by hard-working people of the area. They are struggling against high odds to keep their dreams alive in the neighborhood. B1</p>
        <p>Public works projects are lagging in New York City. Most of them are badly behind schedule, adding costs and further delays to constructing bridges, sewers and public schools, according to a new report. B1</p>
        <p>A hall of fame for great Americans, which is situated in the Bronx, is showing flickering signs of a renaissance after years of erosion and neglect. The hall is on the campus of Bronx Community College. B3</p>
        <p>The New York Post may move part of the paper's operations out of Manhattan. The new owner, Peter S. Kalikow, has had preliminary discussions with city officials about the move. B3</p>
        <p>A 'spiritual' nightclub's opening has given the so-called higher consciousness crowd a place to hang out and maybe meditate to Tibetan gongs. But the club, Sanctuary, will still feature worldly pleasures like rock 'n' roll. B1</p>
        <p>Overcrowding pervades prison life in Connecticut B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
