<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lobbyists Spent Over $63 Million in '87</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="173485"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOBBYING AND LOBBYISTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL SECURITY (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SOCIAL SECURITY, NATIONAL COMMITTEE TO PRESERVE</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6D81138F930A1575BC0A96E948260" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lobbyists Spent Over $63 Million in '87</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Led by a group advocating a strong Social Security system, lobbyists spent more than $63.62 million trying to influence Congress in 1987.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Led by a group advocating a strong Social Security system, lobbyists spent more than $63.62 million trying to influence Congress in 1987.</p>
        <p>Led by a group advocating a strong Social Security system, lobbyists spent more than $63.62 million trying to influence Congress in 1987.</p>
        <p>The amount, compiled from reports filed with the House and Senate, represented a 4.5 percent increase from 1986, when an overhauling of the nation's income tax laws prompted big spending by registered lobbyists. The 1986 total of $60.87 million by 8,500 people and organizations was up from $49 million in 1985 and at the time was the highest total since The Associated Press began compiling the figures in 1983.</p>
        <p>The National Committee to Preserve Social Security led the lobbying groups last year with a reported outlay of $2.93 million, much of it for direct-mail campaigns aimed at Congressional offices. Draws Congressional Criticism</p>
        <p>The organization, headed by James Roosevelt, the son of Franklin D. Roosevelt, has drawn criticism from members of Congress who say it uses scare tactics to obtain contributions from the elderly. Mr. Roosevelt has defended the lobbying group, saying ''our cause is a good one, our methods are honest, our concerns are sincere.'' The group has fought proposed cutbacks in Social Security and Medicare since it was formed in 1982.</p>
        <p>The $2.93 million that Mr. Roosevelt's group contributed was slightly below the $3 million in lobbying expenses reported by the organization for 1986, when it finished second behind the $3.02 million spent by Citizens for Sensible Control of Acid Rain.</p>
        <p>That group, which is financed principally by electric utilities and coal companies, cut back its lobbying expenses in 1987 to $1.2 million, leaving it in eighth place among nine organizations spending more than $1 million last year.</p>
        <p>Common Cause, the public affairs lobby, was second among contributors in 1987. The group concentrates on government ethics and election finance reform and attributes its entire budget to lobbying.</p>
        <p>Common Cause spent $2.56 million last year, just ahead of the $2.55 million reported by Philip Morris U.S.A., a subsidiary of Philip Morris Companies Inc., which used direct-mail campaigns to oppose any increase in Federal excise taxes on tobacco products.</p>
        <p>The Committee to Protect the Family ranked fourth in overall spending last year with $1.95 million, followed by the Sierra Club's $1.5 million to support lobbying on environment and conservation issues. Biggest Spender Among Labor</p>
        <p>The biggest spender among organized labor last year was the National Association of Letter Carriers at $1.48 million. The other labor groups that spent large sums were the Fiber Fabric and Apparel Coalition for Trade, $1.24 million, and the Home Recording Rights Coalition, nearly $1.18 million.</p>
        <p>The continuing Congressional debate over handgun control again accounted for heavy lobbying expenses, with a group supporting restrictions on firearms, Handgun Control Inc., leading spending in this area with $900,343.</p>
        <p>The forces in favor of gun control were outspent, however, by total spending by their opponents: National Rifle Association of America, $668,058; Gun Owners of America, $608,672; and Citizens Committee for the Right to Keep and Bear Arms, $271,435.</p>
        <p>Other large spenders last year included these:</p>
        <p>American Petroleum Institute, $919,419; Project Cure, $909,018; Free the Eagle, $896,555; Railway Labor Executives' Association, $800,293; Rainbow Lobby, $765,329; and United States League of Savings Institutions, $728,803.</p>
        <p>Also, AFL-CIO, $576,504; American Israel Public Affairs Committee, $543,273; United Auto Workers, $539,451; Man-Made Fiber Producers Association Inc., $524,642; American Council of Life Insurance Inc., $513,281; and American Farm Bureau Federation, $512,671.</p>
        <p>Also, American Arts Alliance, $504,098; National Association of Home Builders of the United States, $490,062; American Bankers Association, $476,707; National Association of Realtors, $440,141; Air Transport Association of America, $412,175; and Disabled American Veterans, $405,168.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
