<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vast Amazon Fires, Man-Made, Linked To Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="170131"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREST AND BRUSH FIRES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SATELLITES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRAZIL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AMAZON JUNGLE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AMAZON RIVER BASIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMONS, MARLISE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru/Amazon Basin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7D8163DF931A2575BC0A96E948260" item-length="1427" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vast Amazon Fires, Man-Made, Linked To Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMONS, MARLISE</byline>
      <dateline>SAO JOSE DOS CAMPOS, Brazil, Aug. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Like eerie ghosts of the trees and animals dying below, thick clouds of smoke are rising over the rain forest as the man-made fires of the annual dry season are once again upon the Amazon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Like eerie ghosts of the trees and animals dying below, thick clouds of smoke are rising over the rain forest as the man-made fires of the annual dry season are once again upon the Amazon.</p>
        <p>Like eerie ghosts of the trees and animals dying below, thick clouds of smoke are rising over the rain forest as the man-made fires of the annual dry season are once again upon the Amazon.</p>
        <p>On some days, fires rage in thousands of places across the vast Amazon basin, following a broad belt where settlers and farmers are beating back the jungle frontier. For many, fire is the only tool for transforming forest into farm or pasture.</p>
        <p>From the flames, tons of fumes and particles are hurled into the sky, and at night, roaring and red, the forest looks to be at war.</p>
        <p>Now, Brazilian and American scientists in a new satellite monitoring program are for the first time pinpointing and measuring the effects of the fires. The destruction and burning of forest here is so vast, the scientists say, that it may account for at least one-tenth of the global man-made output of carbon dioxide, which is believed to be causing a warming of the earth through the greenhouse effect. Burning of fossil fuels accounts for most of the carbon dioxide released worldwide.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists have long warned of the destruction that is increasing with each new dry season, and witnesses every year report more cemeteries of trees. The scientists' findings show that in 1987 the burnings ruined more forest cover than previously thought and proved to be major polluters of the earth's atmosphere.</p>
        <p>In 1987, Brazilian scientists estimate, fires just in Brazil's part of the Amazon basin covered 77,000 square miles, an area one and a half times the size of New York State. Of these, at least 30,000 square miles were newly felled virgin forest, the researchers said. The remainder, they added, involved regrown forest on previously cleared land, savannas and fields.</p>
        <p>The pioneering studies, which include the most comprehensive estimates yet of the emissions from the Amazon fires, also found that pollution from the burnings traveled thousands of miles. This has raised questions about a possible link between the gigantic emissions from the fires in the South American tropics and the damage to the earth's protective ozone shield over Antarctica. Smoke Rises to 12,000 Feet</p>
        <p>Alberto Setzer, coordinator of the satellite data at the Space Research Center in this south Brazilian city, said smoke clouds from the Amazon fires often rose to 12,000 feet. Their gases and particles were then lifted up higher into jet streams and blown south across the South Atlantic, close to Antarctica. Many scientists now believe that several of these gases, including methane and nitrogen oxides, are among the reactive gases that can directly or indirectly deplete ozone, Dr. Setzer said.</p>
        <p>''There is no proof yet that the material is interacting with the ozone shield, which is much higher in the stratosphere,'' said Dr. Setzer. ''But we know the material gets to the Antarctic region, and we know that storms can pump it upward. We do not know yet how high it reaches. Several people are working on this.''</p>
        <p>American scientists who took part in the mission over Antarctica by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration in October said they had not searched for or found evidence of compounds from the Amazon. But NASA researchers are now searching for such traces by satellite.</p>
        <p>But even without the ozone question, Dr. Setzer said, the ''tremendous'' emissions coming off the Amazon pose serious problems. ''They are large enough to cause significant changes in the chemical balance of the atmosphere and influence the global weather,'' he said. A Doubly Harmful Effect</p>
        <p>In the case of carbon dioxide, for example, the forest destruction is doubly harmful, Dr. Setzer and other researchers noted. The dwindling forest cover becomes not only less efficient in absorbing and removing this ''greenhouse gas,'' but the fires also add new, huge volumes of it.</p>
        <p>A report prepared by the study group at the Space Research Center estimated that the fires in Brazil last year produced carbon dioxide containing more than 500 million tons of carbon. The fires also produced 44 million tons of carbon monoxide, more than six million tons of particles, almost five million tons of methane, two and a half million tons of ozone and more than one million tons of nitrogen oxides and other substances that can circulate globally and influence radiation and climate.</p>
        <p>''There is enough to compare it to the outburst of a very large volcano,'' Dr. Setzer said.</p>
        <p>The study results on deforestation and emissions from the fires so far cover only the Brazilian two-thirds of the Amazon rain forest. Still more of the pollutants are produced by fires in parts of the Amazon basin outside Brazil. Other Countries Studied</p>
        <p>''Our findings in general agree with those of Brazil,'' said Compton Tucker, a physicist who is part of a group studying deforestation and emissions at the Goddard Space Flight Center at Greenbelt, Md. The NASA group, he said, is now also analyzing satellite data of other countries of the Amazon basin, including Bolivia and Peru, where burnings have increased.</p>
        <p>''This phenomenon has been greatly underestimated, and until 1987 no one has ever tried to study this systematically,'' Dr. Tucker said. ''The satellite data are also there for other areas. There are no technical constraints. They just have not been processed yet.''</p>
        <p>The effects of the fires are felt clearly on the ground in areas where the pace of destruction is greatest, including the state of Para, in the eastern Amazon, and farther west in northern Mato Grosso and Rondonia. Here new roads have opened, and cattle and soybean farmers are felling huge areas.</p>
        <p>Newly analyzed data for the state of Rondonia, for example, show that in 1984, when paving was completed on a highway financed by the Inter-American Development Bank, deforestation jumped from 6,500 square miles and reached 10,500 square miles in 1985. By late last year it had affected 14,600 square miles, or 17 percent of the state surface. Respiratory Disease Rises</p>
        <p>In August and September in past years, when the thick haze over the region worsened, it has forced airports to close down, caused boat accidents on the rivers and brought a rise in respiratory diseases.</p>
        <p>Early this month, the annual drama of fire came to the fore as burning spread from a farm in Mato Grosso and set ablaze a national park, the Parques das Emas. The 335,000-acre park, which consists of easily flammable savanna rich in animal life, has only four wardens, who have been unable to maintain the fire corridor. The blaze lasted five days and, according to the forestry service, destroyed 65 percent of the park.</p>
        <p>As forestry experts explain it, spontaneous fires are rare in the moist rain forest. Rather, workers first cut the trees, leave them to dry and finally set fire to them during the dry season. Usually only the felled part is dry enough to burn, and fires remain confined to the intended areas. In the absence of transport or roads, the timber cannot be sold, and burning is the easiest way to clear the land.</p>
        <p>In the computer room at the Space Research Center here, researchers capture and analyze the satellite images every day. Marcos Pereira, one of the analysts, explained that the satellite registers the fires as points of intense heat. These appear as dots on the screen and permit researchers to pinpoint their location. Often, the ominous dots form a belt showing the boundary between the virgin forest and the settled areas. ''It is very striking how the fires follow the roads,'' an American researcher said. #170,000 Fires in 1987 On the worst day of 1987, Sept. 9, the satellite detected 7,603 fires. Dr. Setzer said that between June and October 1987, covering the whole dry season, the satellite registered more than 350,000 fires. Because burnings may last between 24 and 48 hours, many fires may have been registered more than once, Dr. Setzer said. Therefore, he added, his group is using a conservative estimate of 170,000 fires for 1987.</p>
        <p>As part of the new program, researchers send their findings every day to the National Forestry Service in Brasilia. Shocked by last year's data, the service has said that this year it will open a nationwide campaign and levy large fines for the burnings. Virtually all the fires are conducted illegally, without the required permits.</p>
        <p>But the service, which guards the largest forest on earth, has fewer than 900 wardens for a region larger than Europe. ''We would need 15,000 to 20,000 guards to be effective,'' said Carlos Marx Carneiro, a director of the service.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
