<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Calculating the Consequences of a Warmer Planet Earth; A Worst-Case Forecast</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="156827"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5D71731F935A15755C0A96E948260" item-length="329" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Calculating the Consequences of a Warmer Planet Earth; A Worst-Case Forecast</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: SCIENTISTS disagree over just how bad the greenhouse effect will be. According to some of the most dire predictions, this is how bad a summer day might be in the year 2030:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: SCIENTISTS disagree over just how bad the greenhouse effect will be. According to some of the most dire predictions, this is how bad a summer day might be in the year 2030:</p>
        <p>SCIENTISTS disagree over just how bad the greenhouse effect will be. According to some of the most dire predictions, this is how bad a summer day might be in the year 2030:</p>
        <p>The temperature in Washington, D.C., is over 100 degrees for the 10th straight day. Air conditioners are running at maximum around the clock, straining the generating capacity of electrical power plants and assuring another jump in already soaring utility rates.</p>
        <p>In New York City, heat is not the only problem. Workers are raising levees to hold back the rising tidal waters of the Hudson and East Rivers.</p>
        <p>In the South, another 100,000 acres of Louisiana wetland is being lost to the sea. But Chicago is suffering from another extreme. Evaporation has been causing Lake Michigan to recede from Lake Shore Drive, leaving behind an ever wider expanse of malodorous mud.</p>
        <p>For the Midwest, drought has become a way of life. To adapt, Kansas farmers are experimenting with biologically engineered grains to see if they will yield a profitable crop in the increasingly dry and dusty heartland.</p>
        <p>In Minnesota, Canada and Siberia, however, a longer and warmer growing season is producing bumper crops of corn and winter wheat. And residents of suburban and rural New England are fighting an infestation of insects caused by a mild winter.</p>
        <p>Fire consumes a dying conifer forest in Yellowstone National Park. Migration from the Southwest is increasing as high temperatures continue and water supplies are becoming inadequate to sustain the population.</p>
        <p>While North Americans and Europeans struggle with the effects of changing weather patterns, people in some of the poorer countries of Africa and Asia are being overwhelmed by the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>Rising waters drive millions of farmers from their tiny plots in the Nile Valley of Egypt and the Gangetic Delta of Bangladesh. The misery of the hungry people of the Sahel region of Africa deepens as rising temperatures push the Sahara farther south.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
