<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Life in a Giant Shadow Tests Lawmakers' Skills</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="137788"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="WASHINGTON TALK: THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSE SUBCOMMITTEE ON TELECOMMUNICATIONS AND FINANCE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSE COMMITTEE ON ENERGY AND COMMERCE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARKEY, EDWARD J (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DINGELL, JOHN D (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NASH, NATHANIEL C</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON TALK PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D6133DF933A15757C0A96E948260" item-length="1128" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Life in a Giant Shadow Tests Lawmakers' Skills</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATHANIEL C. NASH, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NASH, NATHANIEL C</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Some of the biggest shadows on Capitol Hill are cast by the chairmen of the most powerful committees, Congressmen of long standing who pride themselves on having their names on key pieces of legislation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Some of the biggest shadows on Capitol Hill are cast by the chairmen of the most powerful committees, Congressmen of long standing who pride themselves on having their names on key pieces of legislation.</p>
        <p>Some of the biggest shadows on Capitol Hill are cast by the chairmen of the most powerful committees, Congressmen of long standing who pride themselves on having their names on key pieces of legislation.</p>
        <p>The trick for those of lesser standing is to step out from under those dark spots and take an activist role in passing legislation, without causing offense to the shadow casters. By most accounts, Representative Edward J. Markey, Democrat of Massachusetts, is currently in one of those shadows - a very long one at that.</p>
        <p>For, as chairman of the House Subcommittee on Telecommunications and Finance, Mr. Markey has to answer to John D. Dingell, otherwise known as Big John, a gruff, cagey, 17-term Democrat from Michigan, who has been chairman of the House Energy and Commerce Committee for years, and who has expanded its reach and influence, making it one of the most powerful in the House. Dealing With a Crisis</p>
        <p>If these were tranquil times in the area of finance and the stock market, Mr. Markey might not be under much pressure to step out from under the Dingell shadow. But with the October stock market crash, which sent the Dow Jones industrial average plummeting 508 points, and with two subsequent days in which the Dow has fallen more than 100 points, the Massachusetts Democrat is coming under mounting pressure to prepare some kind of legislation that addresses the stock market crisis.</p>
        <p>At subcommittee hearings, Mr. Markey has repeatedly said that Congress needs to take action to dampen the volatility of the markets and to rearrange some regulatory jurisdiction, in an effort to restore the confidence of small investors and bring them back into the markets.</p>
        <p>''Forty percent of small investors have left the market since Oct. 19,'' Mr. Markey said in an interview. ''And it is becoming clear that the individual investors will not return to the market if they do not perceive that they are treated fairly.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Markey faces considerable obstacles if he pushes ahead with legislation.</p>
        <p>Time is running out on the legislative calendar. With the summer breaks for the Democratic and Republican conventions, and the early adjourning of Congress for the November elections, some calculate that there are fewer than 50 legislative days left in the session. Dingell's Interest in Issue</p>
        <p>Perhaps of greater significance, Mr. Dingell is keenly interested in the financial markets, and is considered the key player in the House on the subject. Many argue that Mr. Markey will not be able to move any legislation unless Mr. Dingell plays a large role in it.</p>
        <p>But so far, Mr. Dingell has been remarkably quiet on the issue of stock market reform, hardly indicating what he feels has to be done, and sending a signal to some that he feels there is little chance for a substantial law to be passed this year.</p>
        <p>''Let's face it, Dingell is the master conductor in the area of securities reform,'' said one Wall Street expert, who asked not to be identified. ''Dingell might let Markey play a solo or two, but don't forget who the conductor of the orchestra is.''</p>
        <p>Another securities expert said, ''John Dingell has such a specific interest in securities that he is looking over Markey's shoulder all the time.''</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Markey maintains that life under the chairmanship of Mr. Dingell is not all that bad, and that it has often worked to his advantage. Even though he is in only his second year as head of the Telecommunications and Finance subcommittee, he has been on the Energy and Commerce Committee for all of his 12 years in Congress and has worked with Mr. Dingell throughout.</p>
        <p>''I consider Dingell to be my personal friend and the best political ally that a subcommittee chairman could have in insuring that the substantitive work that I do is going to be turned into law,'' Mr. Markey said. Similarity of Views</p>
        <p>He says he and Mr. Dingell think along the same lines in most areas of legislation - both possessed of strong liberal streaks and both believing in government regulation to protect consumers. As such, he says he is confident that many of the legislative solutions to stock market reform he is working on will, in the end, be supported by Mr. Dingell.</p>
        <p>For example, Mr. Markey says he hopes to introduce a bill that will give the Securities and Exchange Commission regulatory jurisdiction over the trading in stock-index futures, which are now regulated by the Commodity Futures Trading Commission. He says he favors giving either the Federal Reserve Board or the S.E.C. the authority to set margin, or downpayment, requirements on stocks and stock-index futures.</p>
        <p>And he hopes to introduce legislation that will stiffen the penalties on insider trading and give small investors who have disputes with their stockbrokers a fairer hearing in the current arbitration process.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Markey declines to discuss specific strategy he has worked out with Mr. Dingell on introduction of any legislation, his colleagues contend that Mr. Markey's policies closely reflect the thinking of Mr. Dingell.</p>
        <p>Moreover, they say Mr. Dingell lets Mr. Markey play the lead role in circulating a legislative idea to see how it plays to various industry groups.</p>
        <p>''The interests of Ed Markey and John Dingell have been very compatible,'' said Representative Ron Wyden, an Oregon Democrat who is a member of the Energy and Commerce Committee. He said the two ''have been working very closely together this year'' on stock market legislation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dingell, in a telephone interview, confirmed that he and his staff were ''working closely'' with Mr. Markey and his staff on possible legislation. ''On securities issues, we tend to be very much in agreement,'' Mr. Dingell said.  Mr. Markey noted, however, that he has disagreed with Mr. Dingell's opposition to proposed legislation to control acid rain. But he apparently has not made it a point of contention. Reaction on Wall Street</p>
        <p>How the 41-year-old Massachusetts Democrat has been received on Wall Street is still somewhat unclear.</p>
        <p>Lobbyists here note that unlike any other time since the Depression, the issues of Wall Street are hotly disputed and hopelessly complex, and that Mr. Markey, along with regulators and even market participants, is taking a long time learning the intricacies of program trading, hostile takeovers and insider trading.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Senate-passed legislation that permits banking to get into securities underwriting gives Mr. Markey and Mr. Dingell yet another explosive financial issue to handle.</p>
        <p>''It's hard not to be sympathetic with Markey if you're a follower of the securities law,'' said another Wall Street expert. ''Considering that a year and a half ago he had no background in the markets at all, he has come a long way.''  WASHINGTON TALK: THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
