<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Toronto Agenda: One Eye on the Markets</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="155170"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2D61330F93AA25755C0A96E948260" item-length="353" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Toronto Agenda: One Eye on the Markets</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Here are some of the issues facing the seven leaders attending the Toronto economic summit conference.  Deficits and surpluses  All will probably agree on the need to do something about the American budget and trade deficits and the West German and Japanese trade surpluses, which impede steady growth of the world economy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Here are some of the issues facing the seven leaders attending the Toronto economic summit conference.  Deficits and surpluses  All will probably agree on the need to do something about the American budget and trade deficits and the West German and Japanese trade surpluses, which impede steady growth of the world economy.</p>
        <p>Here are some of the issues facing the seven leaders attending the Toronto economic summit conference.  Deficits and surpluses  All will probably agree on the need to do something about the American budget and trade deficits and the West German and Japanese trade surpluses, which impede steady growth of the world economy. But the imbalances have been receding a bit, and this leaves the leaders free to do little more than reaffirm past promises.  Trade  The leaders can be expected to voice opposition to protectionism, though all seven countries practice it and the United States appears close to enacting a more protectionist trade law. Specific commitments to relax restraints will be relegated to a 96-nation trade meeting in Montreal in December.  Farming  The leaders will consider President Reagan's proposal to ban by the year 2000 the subsidies that governments give farmers to help them export their goods. Western European countries, with proportionately more farmers than the United States, are opposed.  Third world debt  The leaders are expected to agree to set easier terms for the loans they have made to the poorest African countries. On the far larger question of the Latin American debt, they will probably only reconfirm their commitment to the market-oriented strategy of Treasury Secretary James A. Baker 3d.  The dollar and gold  Pleased about the dollar's current stability, the leaders will try to avoid disputes about interest rates and other matters that could unsettle the markets. They are also expected to say that they will use the price of gold to help them see if inflation is rising and if they should revalue their currencies accordingly. Some people see this as a step back toward the gold standard.  Other issues  Among noneconomic subjects expected to receive attention are President Reagan's recent talks with Mikhail S. Gorbachev, the tightening of sanctions against South Africa, the deterioration of the earth's ozone layer, education and Mr. Reagan's effort to stop drug traffickers from using Western banks.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
