<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Afar, Both Candidates Are Environmentalists . . .</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="182117"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DD1E31F937A1575AC0A96E948260" item-length="653" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Afar, Both Candidates Are Environmentalists . . .</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE BUSH; From the text of a speech delivered Aug. 31 in Erie Metropark, Mich.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Those who think we're powerless to do anything about the ''greenhouse effect'' are forgetting about the ''White House effect.'' As President, I intend to do something about it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Those who think we're powerless to do anything about the ''greenhouse effect'' are forgetting about the ''White House effect.'' As President, I intend to do something about it.</p>
        <p>Those who think we're powerless to do anything about the ''greenhouse effect'' are forgetting about the ''White House effect.'' As President, I intend to do something about it.</p>
        <p>In my first year in office, I will convene a global conference on the environment at the White House. It will include the Soviets, the Chinese, the developing world as well as the developed. All nations will be welcome - and indeed, all nations will be needed.</p>
        <p>The agenda will be clear. We will talk about global warming. We will talk about acid rain. We will talk about saving our oceans, and preventing the loss of tropical forests. And we will act.</p>
        <p>Acid rain is a problem that will require both international and national cooperation. The time for study alone has passed. We know enough now to begin taking steps to limit future damage; action we take today -even as scientific inquiry continues -is an insurance policy against future disaster.</p>
        <p>As President, I will ask for a program to cut millions of tons of sulfur dioxide emissions by the year 2000, and to significantly reduce nitrogen oxide emissions as well. I will work out the exact amounts and the exact methodology with Congress. But we must have a clear commitment to emissions reductions, on a clear timetable.</p>
        <p>Curbing acid rain is just one element in achieving cleaner air and cleaner water. Earlier this week, the Environmental Protection Agency moved ahead with mandated sanctions against an area of the country -Los Angeles - that is not meeting the standards of the Clean Air Act. This shows dramatically the need to press ahead with the battle for clean air. I support a reauthorization, correction and strengthening of our Clean Air laws - with realistic timetables and tools to get the job done.</p>
        <p>What about clean water? Groundwater provides more than half of the American public with its drinking water - and 97 percent of rural households. And yet it is threatened by toxic wastes, pesticides and fertilizers.</p>
        <p>Too many towns in America have had a nightmare with hazardous waste that is disposed of improperly. Well, I plan to attack the toxic waste menace with every ounce of energy I have, and with every enforcement tool at my disposal. When America moves into the 90's, I want to insure that ''zero tolerance'' is applied not only to those who poison our children's minds with drugs, but to those who poison our water with toxic chemicals.</p>
        <p>We have been losing wetlands at a rate of almost a half-million acres per year - although this should be reduced with the conservation-oriented ''swamp buster'' provisions in last year's farm bill. Much of the loss comes from inevitable pressure for development, and many of our wetlands are on private property. But we must act to conserve wetlands. Our national goal should be no net loss of wetlands. We can't afford to lose the half of America's wetlands that still remains.</p>
        <p>I want to increase the recreational opportunities provided by the great American outdoors. And in that task, I will pay special attention to the condition and management of our parks. I will look for ways to link our cities with greenways along abandoned railroad tracks and refresh them with urban parks.</p>
        <p>Our actions as individuals can affect our common destiny. We Americans produce 160 million tons of garbage every year. We can produce less. We can recycle. We can waste less. Japan's recycling rate is 50 percent, yet some feel the E.P.A.'s national goal of a 25 percent reduction in waste is excessive. I'd like to see us exceed that goal in my first term.</p>
        <p>We consume mountains of plastic packages, waste millions of gallons of water and produce barrel upon barrel of hazardous waste. We can waste less and reduce pollutants at their source. The technology is there, what is needed now is the will.</p>
        <p>We can instill a new spirit in the people of this country. A new appreciation for the land and water. A conservation ethic.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
