<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="158168"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3D71F3BF932A35754C0A96E948260" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A2-7  Dismissal of four Soviet leaders, including President Andrei A. Gromyko and the editor of Pravda, was urged by a Moscow conference delegate. His demand was broadcast on the main Moscow television news show. Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A2-7  Dismissal of four Soviet leaders, including President Andrei A. Gromyko and the editor of Pravda, was urged by a Moscow conference delegate. His demand was broadcast on the main Moscow television news show. Page A1</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A2-7  Dismissal of four Soviet leaders, including President Andrei A. Gromyko and the editor of Pravda, was urged by a Moscow conference delegate. His demand was broadcast on the main Moscow television news show. Page A1</p>
        <p>The Soviet television audience has been transfixed by coverage of the 19th Communist Party conference that included angry statements by a factory manager who indicted the Soviet bureaucracy for paralyzing the economy. A1</p>
        <p>The first major schism in the Roman Catholic Church in more than a century occurred as Archbishop Marcel Lefebvre consecrated four bishops in Econe, Switzerland, in defiance of orders from Pope John Paul II. A1</p>
        <p>Degradation of the atmosphere should be halted, according to Government officials, scientists and environmentalists from 48 countries, who set targets for global reductions in the burning of fossil fuels. A3</p>
        <p>Foreigners increased U.S. holdings by $195.4 billion last year to a record $1.54 trillion, while Americans increased overseas investments by only $96.4 billion, to $1.17 trillion, making the United States more of a debtor nation than ever before. D1</p>
        <p>After 174 years, 28 M.I.A.'s are returned to U.S. A3</p>
        <p>Iraq says U.S. supplied Iran with data on planned raid A2</p>
        <p>All sides in Nicaragua get plea from bishops A4</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A8-11, B6-7</p>
        <p>Drug use by White House guards while off duty was alleged by officials and three of the guards were suspended. Two National Security Council secretaries were dismissed earlier after admitting drug use. A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: Efforts to influence the Supreme Court by even strong Presidents seeking to leave their mark on an institution with principals who have indefinite appointments are only partly successful. A1</p>
        <p>The way to an Agent Orange accord between manufacturers of the herbicide and about 120,000 Vietnam veterans involving $180 million was provided by the Supreme Court. B7</p>
        <p>Two consultants obtained data from a Pentagon employee and used it to influence military contracts worth hundreds of millions of dollars, according to Federal court documents unsealed in Dallas. A1</p>
        <p>Commuter planes' 'crash recorders' will be much more common within three years, under new rules adopted by the Government to increase the chances of pinpointing causes of accidents. A9</p>
        <p>Two former bankers pleaded guilty in Chicago to bank fraud charges in a plea-bargaining agreement. The two, John R. Lytle and William G. Patterson, were officers at Continental Illinois National Bank and Penn Square Bank. D4</p>
        <p>The A.M.A., barring confidentiality, strongly urged doctors to warn the sexual partners of AIDS virus carriers of the danger if there is no other way to alert them. A1</p>
        <p>Athletes who gain and lost weight repeatedly may burden themselves with a slower metabolism, burning calories more slowly than normal, according to a study. B6</p>
        <p>A ban on the death penalty for all juveniles will be considered by the Supreme Court next fall, the Justices said in a dramatic epilogue to the their just-completed 1987-1988 term. B7  Kelso Depot Journal: Fighting for a railroad station A8</p>
        <p>2 of 5 Federal female employes report sexual harassment B6</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON TALK B7</p>
        <p>Book on Greek leader stires Washington dispute  REGIONAL B1-5  Mayor Koch is not favored by many New York City voters, a New York Times/WCBS-TV News Poll found. It put Mr. Koch's favorable rating at 36 percent, a drop of 30 percentage points from a similar poll taken two years ago. A1</p>
        <p>A $25.2 billion budget that depends in part on a $71.9 million property tax increase was agreed on by the Koch administration, the New York City Council and the city's Board of Estimate. B3</p>
        <p>The slaying of a grand jury witness last year resulted in the conviction of three young men. Mildred Greene, a 61-year-old car dispatcher, was killed Oct. 4 by shotgun blasts in South Jamaica. B1</p>
        <p>Three homeowners were convicted of setting fire to an unoccupied house on their block in the Flushing section of Queens to keep New York City from using the house to shelter foster-care infants. B1</p>
        <p>Bess Myerson was upheld in a ruling by a Federal judge who held the New York City Department of Investigation in contempt for failing to turn over investigative files to the defense in the judicial-tampering controversy. B3</p>
        <p>The television writers' strike may force the networks to present a fall season so different it will not be recognizable at a time they have been losing much of their audience to cable and videocassettes. C26</p>
        <p>2 S.I. men face sodomy and sex-abuse charges B2</p>
        <p>Biaggi could face a rigorous cross-examination B3</p>
        <p>14-year-old is convicted of manslaughter B3</p>
        <p>Friedman denied new trial B4</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
