<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. and Soviet Groups Joining for Quality of Life</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="205913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="WASHINGTON TALK: THE ENVIRONMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORBACHEV, MIKHAIL S</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON TALK PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDE1539F931A25751C1A96E948260" item-length="1121" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. and Soviet Groups Joining for Quality of Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Following Mikhail S. Gorbachev's call for international cooperation in solving global environmental problems, American conservation groups have let it be known here that they are ready to assist on environmental projects in the Soviet Union.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Following Mikhail S. Gorbachev's call for international cooperation in solving global environmental problems, American conservation groups have let it be known here that they are ready to assist on environmental projects in the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>Following Mikhail S. Gorbachev's call for international cooperation in solving global environmental problems, American conservation groups have let it be known here that they are ready to assist on environmental projects in the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>Many of this country's environmental organizations, which normally spend much of their time and money seeking to influence environmental decisions in Washington, are already taking advantage of the new Soviet openness inaugurated by Mr. Gorbachev to carry their mission to Moscow and beyond.</p>
        <p>In his address at the United Nations last week, the Soviet leader spoke of the ''frightening'' state of the environment in some regions of the world and called for international teams of experts and even space laboratory monitors to work in areas with a ''badly deteriorating environment.''</p>
        <p>Rafe Pomerance, a senior associate of the World Resources Institute, a Washington-based environmental research and policy group, said he welcomed Mr. Gorbachev's ''very positive rhetoric'' but cautioned that the ''true test of environmental protection within the Soviet Union remains.''</p>
        <p>That test, Mr. Pomerance said, would be the Soviet Union's commitment to solving internal environmental problems and working with the United States and other countries to reduce the buildup of carbon dioxide and other industrial gases that are causing the earth to warm. Hurdling the Bureaucracies</p>
        <p>Environmentalists here say that despite the recent easing of tensions between the superpowers and substantial agreements reached between Moscow and Washington on environmental matters, private undertakings between the two countries are still easier than overcoming bureaucratic obstacles.</p>
        <p>American environmental groups' assistance in the Soviet Union now ranges from helping to monitor agreements on nuclear testing to arranging exchanges of fishing trips. Judging by plans being developed, that involvement will increase markedly in the coming months.</p>
        <p>''There clearly is a lot of interest in the environment in the Soviet Union right now,'' said Jacob Scherr, a senior attorney for the Natural Resources Defense Council, the first United States private environmental group to station its own representative in Moscow.</p>
        <p>The council recently shipped $1 million worth of computer equipment to the Soviet Union to help in verifying nuclear testing limits, Mr. Scherr said, but he added that his group was also working with the Soviet Union to find ways to use energy more efficiently as one answer to the expected warming of the earth. Working Together on Fishing</p>
        <p>Trout Unlimited, another United States conservation group, is working with the All-Russian Union of Hunters and Fishermen, which was convened in September as a private scientific council in Moscow on fishery preservation. The two groups are also holding ''angler exchanges'' in which groups of fishermen travel to each other's country each year, said Stephen Lundy, president of Trout Unlimited. ''You don't get into any problems if you fish together,'' he said of the exchange.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lundy, who has made five trips to the Soviet Union in the last few years, said there were definite signs that Russians concerned about the environment were taking advantage of the opportunities created by the policy of glasnost in Soviet society. He spoke of a high Soviet fisheries minister making a speech about what the Government was doing to protect fish. After the speech a member of the group pulled out a picture of dead fish on a polluted lake and saying: ''You say you are protecting fish? How do you explain this?'' Seeded by Pollution Issues</p>
        <p>Many environmental groups are springing up around specific pollution issues or other threats to the environment in the Soviet Union, said Francis U. Macy, coordinator of the ecology program of the Center for U.S.-U.S.S.R. Initiatives. In Volgograd, there is a strong local movement against pollution of the Volga from a chemical plant, he said, adding that citizens in Latvia and Lithuania had organized to oppose expansion of a nuclear power plant near their mutual border.</p>
        <p>Mr. Macy's group plans to send a delegation of 25 to 30 representatives of environmentalists to the Soviet Union next March to meet with officials and unofficial environmental groups, he said.</p>
        <p>He said the trip would be ''an attempt to connect environmental activists in the Soviet Union and the United States.'' He added: ''There is a burgeoning movement for environmental protection, restoration and a more broadly ecological consciousness in the Soviet Union. This is a major outcome of the new acceptability of pluralism in the U.S.S.R.'' Saying It With Music</p>
        <p>The militant conservation group Greenpeace is taking a new tack in dealing with the Russians. In the past, the group sent its ship, Rainbow Warrior, to interfere with Soviet whalers, and another ship, the Sirius, into Leningrad harbor to protest nuclear testing.</p>
        <p>Greenpeace is now planning, with Soviet permission, to send its environmental message to the Russians along with a record of rock music. Peter Bahouth, executive director of Greenpeace-U.S.A., said a 16-page pamphlet about environmental issues would be enclosed in 4.5 million record albums to be released in the Soviet Union in January. The album, with selections from major rock groups, will be also be sold in the United States. Proceeds of the sale in the Soviet Union would help pay for a permanent Greenpeace environmental campaign in the Soviet Union, Mr. Bahouth said.</p>
        <p>He said little was known about overall environmental conditions in the Soviet Union. ''Certainly there are environmental problems from what I read, and they could be pretty severe,'' he said. ''Whether they are worse than they are here I can't say.'' It's Not a One-Way Street</p>
        <p>The flow of environmentalists will not be in one direction. Brent Blackwelder, vice president of the Washington-based Environmental Policy Institute, said his group had organized an exchange that will bring a group of Soviet environmental experts to this country in February to study urban environmental problems and large construction projects that harm the environment.</p>
        <p>The Soviet group will visit Washington and then will examine the Cross-Florida Canal as an example of what Mr. Blackwelder called ''a bad project for the environment.'' Later, an American delegation will visit Moscow and construction projects in the Soviet Union, Mr. Blackwelder said.</p>
        <p>He said his group had also been working with the Soviet authorities to set up a joint project to help developing countries protect their tropical forests. The idea has attracted wide support in Congress and in the Soviet Union, Mr. Blackwelder said.</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON TALK: THE ENVIRONMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
