<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For a Grand Foreign Policy Debate</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="174953"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1988</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUKAKIS, MICHAEL S (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DB1F3CF93BA1575BC0A96E948260" item-length="705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For a Grand Foreign Policy Debate</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Vice President Bush and Governor Dukakis have all the makings for a profound debate on foreign affairs, if they would only join the issues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Vice President Bush and Governor Dukakis have all the makings for a profound debate on foreign affairs, if they would only join the issues.</p>
        <p>Vice President Bush and Governor Dukakis have all the makings for a profound debate on foreign affairs, if they would only join the issues.</p>
        <p>George Bush seems to have a better understanding than his Democratic rival of the world as it is, a continuing cockpit of power and threats. Mr. Dukakis has not adequately explained how he would combine force and diplomacy to bargain with the Soviets on arms control or reassure friendly states in the Persian Gulf.</p>
        <p>Michael Dukakis appears more thoughtful than his Republican opponent about the world as it might be, offering possibilities for international cooperation to combat common threats to the environment and from economic competition, and new ways of working with Moscow. Mr. Bush portrays this thinking as naive but looks shortsighted himself.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Bush has already demonstrated that it's possible for candidates to become more, not less reasonable during a campaign. On Star Wars, for example, he has shown himself open to argument and fact. He told The Times last week that a full space-based defensive system would be ''very expensive'' and that decisions on deployment should await future research. This represents a commendable departure from ideological cheerleading and lays the basis for debate with an even more skeptical Governor Dukakis.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Bush remains guilty of campaign hyperbole when he charges that his rival favors ''appeasement'' and ''unilateral disarmament.'' It's true, though, that Mr. Dukakis has some blind spots when it comes to the measured use of American power.</p>
        <p>Take the Euromissile treaty. Was Washington's deployment of new missiles a key factor in Moscow's agreeing to eliminate its superiority in medium-range missiles? Mr. Dukakis thinks not and attributes Soviet concessions almost entirely to Mikhail Gorbachev and his economic plight. But Moscow had already paid for its missiles, and maintaining them would have cost little. Mr. Bush rightly argues that Mr. Gorbachev's incentive to give away his missiles flowed from U.S. deployments backed by both parties. Incentives will also play a big part in the continuing talks to halve strategic nuclear arms. Mr. Dukakis opposes further work on two new mobile land-based missiles, as being unnecessary and too costly. While these arguments have merit, Mr. Bush rightly counters that the weapons ought not to be canceled unilaterally.</p>
        <p>There's also the matter of U.S. leadership and toughness in a messy world. Mr. Dukakis didn't like the idea of sending the U.S. Navy into the Persian Gulf unilaterally. He would have sent in the ships only as part of a multilateral action. But Mr. Bush makes more sense in arguing that America had to go first in order to give allies and friends the necessary confidence to follow.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dukakis becomes more convincing when he looks ahead. With Moscow's new willingness to resolve regional disputes, he sees possibilities for strengthening the United Nations. Mr. Bush condemns this now (he didn't when he was U.N. Ambassador) as dangerous soft-mindedness.</p>
        <p>But it was the U.N., albeit backed by U.S. power, that played a critical role in engineering the Soviet withdrawal from Afghanistan, the truce between Iran and Iraq, and the emerging settlement in Namibia. And would Mr. Bush prefer American troops and not U.N. forces absorbing the casualties in southern Lebanon, Cyprus and around the globe?</p>
        <p>Mr. Dukakis is also clearsighted on the need for international cooperation to work out common solutions to problems like acid rain, ocean pollution, trade disputes and drug-trafficking. Mr. Bush surely should recognize the value of this kind of practical multilateralism.</p>
        <p>Neither candidate has been persuasive on Central America or the Middle East. Mr. Bush simply talks about beating Nicaragua over the head militarily, and that means endless war. Mr. Dukakis undervalues the role of force in bringing the Sandinistas to the bargaining table and now would deny the Nicaraguan rebels even economic aid. Neither has said anything useful about managing the next dangerous phases in Arab-Israeli negotiations.</p>
        <p>Respect, approbation and conceivably even votes await the candidate who will start a serious debate on these matters.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
