<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Smokestack in Poland Emits Odor of Indecision</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="114972"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FACTORIES AND INDUSTRIAL PLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUREAUCRATIC RED TAPE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHUTDOWNS (INSTITUTIONAL)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">POLAND</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LODZ (POLAND)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">TAGLIABUE, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bureaucratic Red Tape</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DB173EF932A35751C0A96E948260" item-length="929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Smokestack in Poland Emits Odor of Indecision</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TAGLIABUE, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TAGLIABUE, JOHN</byline>
      <dateline>LODZ, Poland</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Delta knitwear factory would simply be closed down, the article said, because environmental officials were tired of waiting for the company's management to put in chimney filters that stop soot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Delta knitwear factory would simply be closed down, the article said, because environmental officials were tired of waiting for the company's management to put in chimney filters that stop soot.</p>
        <p>The Delta knitwear factory would simply be closed down, the article said, because environmental officials were tired of waiting for the company's management to put in chimney filters that stop soot.</p>
        <p>Lodz residents had waited for years for such a decision, the newspaper, Dziennik Lodzki, went on, but the managers ''kept ignoring the deadlines.''</p>
        <p>It all appeared to be a bright victory for the cause of clean air in Lodz, a textile town where the air at this time of year hangs like a gray felt blanket.</p>
        <p>But this afternoon, as misty rain settled over the city's red brick mills, the Delta chimney, looking for all the world like some huge stogie, belched thick yellow-brown smoke.</p>
        <p>The problem, Jan Diehl, who heads the municipal environmental authority, explained, was simple. ''I issued my decision Jan. 5,'' he said in his office in City Hall. ''But I have no right to execute it, and management's rights include an appeal'' to the environmental minister in Warsaw.</p>
        <p>So, what appeared to be a clear-cut victory for health and hygiene turned into a blueprint for the kind of entanglement between Communist authorities, business management and local press that causes the bounds of competence and responsibility to blur.</p>
        <p>The Lodz paper published the articles, and the press agency controlled by the national Government repeated them, telling the world that Poland was getting tough about air pollution.</p>
        <p>Delta's management defended itself in television interviews, but one picture of the 150-foot brick chimney, which vents a heating plant that supplies steam to the textile finishing mill, appeared to leave little room for doubt about the seriousness of the problem. Soot in High Places</p>
        <p>The plant burns sulfur-rich lignite, a coal-like fuel, creating an acute pollution problem in this highly industrialized city of 900,000 people.</p>
        <p>Mr. Diehl appeared as a knight in shining armor in the accounts of the decision to get tough. But local environmentalists say a dose of political jousting probably also played a role.</p>
        <p>Complaints about the chimney, which has stood since well before World War II, started rolling in about 11 years ago, when the politically powerful Association of Polish Cooperatives decided to build a 10-story office building across from the smokestack. When employees of the cooperative open their windows wide, they get a desk full of soot, even though some are about 150 feet from the chimney.</p>
        <p>Even more important, the factory lies several hundred yards from the Polish Army medical academy, which trains doctors for the elite military hospitals that treat Communist Party functionaries.</p>
        <p>Stefan Samborski, deputy director of Delta and the villain to opponents of the smokestack, explained wearily that the company's management could not have installed the chimney filters even if it had wanted to.</p>
        <p>''Four, five years ago we installed cyclones to clean the smoke,'' he said in a conversation at Delta headquarters. ''In the first period, the cyclones functioned well. But they do not eliminate the sulfur. But the means are not at our disposal to resolve the problem.'' A Lack of Western Currency</p>
        <p>That, he explained, is because Poland does not produce the scrubbers the chimney needs, and the only ones available are made by a West German-Brazilian company that sells them for convertible Western currency.</p>
        <p>Convertible currency purchases for any equipment can only be made through a central ministry in Warsaw. Delta has repeatedly requested such purchases, Mr. Samborski said, but the ministry has responded that because Poland is so heavily indebted, it does not have the required cash.</p>
        <p>So now, Mr. Samborski said, Delta has come up with an alternate plan and hopes to merge the finishing operation with that of another company, Bistona, whose chimneys have scrubbers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Diehl, the local environmental official, said there have been dramatic improvements in cleaning up the air over Lodz in the last 15 years, particularly in bringing dust and sulfur dioxide under control. Sulfur pollution has been a particular problem because coal burned in the stoves of about 800 Lodz apartment buildings yields sulfur dioxide, which combines with rain water to form sulfuric acid, a component of acid rain.</p>
        <p>''Lodz was once proud to be called the city of smokestacks,'' he said. ''But over 200 of them have been liquidated.'' Some Smell Collusion</p>
        <p>Still, the Communist Party that manages the companies is the same party that runs the Government, and independent environmental groups complain they face a wall of collusion against cleanup efforts.</p>
        <p>This creates enormous delays. The textile industry pollutes immense amounts of water, but for lack of funds the city still has not completed a water treatment plant that was begun in 1976.</p>
        <p>It also creates vaguely surrealistic situations, as when a beltway project was jettisoned by city officials in an effort to defend the rising butter prices.</p>
        <p>Enviromentalists opposed construction of the beltway, which would have cut a swath through forested parks, residential neighborhoods, and near a large hospital.</p>
        <p>''Our protest in the beginning was totally ignored,'' said Piotr Lindner, a computer expert and member of the local environmental club. ''However, the protest coincided with an unwelcome price hike for butter. So the beltway was canceled and people thought less of the butter price increase.''</p>
        <p>''Of course,'' he went on, ''we do not really know whether we gained a victory. Perhaps it was just a general shortage of road building. But anyway, the road was not built.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
