<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE PROMISE OF WIND AWAITS A NEW ENERGY CRISIS</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19880605T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="147492"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="IDEAS &amp; TRENDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINDMILLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">REINHOLD, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Windmills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DB113BF931A15756C0A96E948260" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE PROMISE OF WIND AWAITS A NEW ENERGY CRISIS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT REINHOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REINHOLD, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>TEHACHAPI, Calif.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The fierce spring winds now whipping through California have brought little cheer to the hearty band of entrepreneurs who turn nature's power into electricity. Thousands of turbines, some shaped like eggbeaters, some like huge propellers, are humming now, driven by the winds that sweep across California's Central Valley, through Tehachapi Pass and into the Mojave Desert below.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The fierce spring winds now whipping through California have brought little cheer to the hearty band of entrepreneurs who turn nature's power into electricity. Thousands of turbines, some shaped like eggbeaters, some like huge propellers, are humming now, driven by the winds that sweep across California's Central Valley, through Tehachapi Pass and into the Mojave Desert below.</p>
        <p>The fierce spring winds now whipping through California have brought little cheer to the hearty band of entrepreneurs who turn nature's power into electricity. Thousands of turbines, some shaped like eggbeaters, some like huge propellers, are humming now, driven by the winds that sweep across California's Central Valley, through Tehachapi Pass and into the Mojave Desert below. The wind farms here feed electricity to homes as far away as Los Angeles, 110 miles southwest. But few new turbines are being built, a trend that even some environmentalists do not bemoan.</p>
        <p>Wind power, like solar, geothermal and other ''alternative'' sources of energy, lost its competitive edge after the collapse of world oil prices in the early 1980's and the expiration of Federal tax credits. Many manufacturers of wind-power equipment have gone out of business. But a half dozen large operators continue to make marginal profits, hoping for better times. ''We all read the oil pages,'' said Paul Gipe, West Coast representative of the American Wind Energy Association.</p>
        <p>Wind energy is still a priority in many oil-poor countries. Denmark is the leader, the Netherlands and India have ambitious programs, Israel is putting turbines on the gusty Golan Heights, and Egypt, Greece and Spain are all planning wind farms. But 80 percent of the world's wind generation capacity is in three areas of California - Altamont Pass east of San Francisco, San Gorgonio Pass near Palm Springs and here at Tehachapi. In all, 16,000 turbines provide about 1 percent of California's electric power, enough for more than 300,000 homes, and enough to cut air pollution from burning coal and other fuels by 200,000 tons a year, according to the industry.  Outpriced by Oil</p>
        <p>But for now the prospects of expansion appear bleak. Amid skyrocketing energy prices, the industry started to boom in 1981, encouraged by a Federal law requiring local utilities to purchase power from alternative-energy sources and by generous Federal and California tax credits. Thousands of investors rushed in, seeking tax shelters, before the technology was perfected. Then the bottom fell out in 1985 when the tax credits expired.</p>
        <p>Though wind power is still cheaper than solar, geothermal and nuclear power, it cannot compete with conventional sources. With debt service on investment, maintenance and the expense of leasing land, it costs about 7 to 10 cents a kilowatt hour for wind, compared with 2 to 3 cents for oil, gas and coal, according to Southern California Edison, which, along with Pacific Gas &amp; Electric in Northern California, purchases about 95 percent of the wind-generated electricity produced in the United States. The utilities, which are unenthusiastic about wind and solar energy, are paying much less than they used to. Only operators holding long-term contracts signed when prices were higher can keep afloat.</p>
        <p>As a result, the industry has been consolidated into a few large companies, such as U.S. Windpower, the largest, with 3,400 turbines, the FloWind Corporation, Zond Systems and SeaWest Industries. At the peak of the wind boom in 1985, 5,000 turbines were installed; this year, the surviving companies will put up only about 1,400.</p>
        <p>Despite the uncertain outlook and some spectacular failures with wind power in the past, the Government continues to experiment. This month, the Department of Energy's Sandia National Laboratories in New Mexico dedicated an experimental vertical-axis wind turbine, the largest ever built, at Bushland, Tex. Such vertical windmills, shaped like eggbeaters, have an advantage over the conventional propellers mounted on posts because they can ''accept'' wind from any direction.</p>
        <p>It is not without irony that some of the objections to wind farming come from environmentalists, who have long advocated ''renewable'' energy sources. According to Warren Liebold, chairman of the national energy committee of the Sierra Club, concerns about air and water pollution are sometimes at odds with worries about aesthetics and preserving public lands. Some consider windmills eyesores, and the roads and digging needed to install and maintain them scar the hillsides. Leslie V. Reid of Pine Mountain, a former national director of the Sierra Club, says that many windmills have become idle and derelict with the demise of the tax credits.</p>
        <p>The utilities complain, meanwhile, that wind power is not reliable enough. California's wind farms produce only 15 percent of what they would if the wind were blowing all the time. Still, because it is relatively cheap to harvest, wind power plays a far greater role than solar power in California - 1,200 megawatts of capacity versus just 20 megawatts for solar.</p>
        <p>Some experts, like Edgar De Meo of the utility-supported Electic Power Research Institute in Palo Alto, Calif., say engineering can bring the cost of wind power down. ''Oil and gas are cheap now,'' said Thomas O. Gray, executive director of the American Wind Energy Association in Alexandria, Va. ''But if the energy situation changes again, the song will change.'' Mr. Gray says he is not just tilting at windmills.</p>
        <p>IDEAS &amp; TRENDS  Correction:  June 5, 1988, Sunday, Late City Final Edition</p>
        <p>An article about alternative energy sources in The Week in Review on May 22 misstated the status of Federal income tax credits for investment in geothermal and solar power. The tax credits were extended at a reduced rate in 1985. They are scheduled to expire by the end of this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 5, 1988, Sunday, Late City Final Edition</p>
        <p>An article about alternative energy sources in The Week in Review on May 22 misstated the status of Federal income tax credits for investment in geothermal and solar power. The tax credits were extended at a reduced rate in 1985. They are scheduled to expire by the end of this year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
