<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="190944"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DB1638F937A15753C1A96E948260" item-length="1034" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A2-9  Progress in Jordanian-P.L.O. ties was reported by the leaders of Egypt and Jordan after unexpected negotiations Saturday with Yasir Arafat, chairman of the Palestine Liberation Organization. A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A2-9  Progress in Jordanian-P.L.O. ties was reported by the leaders of Egypt and Jordan after unexpected negotiations Saturday with Yasir Arafat, chairman of the Palestine Liberation Organization. A1</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A2-9  Progress in Jordanian-P.L.O. ties was reported by the leaders of Egypt and Jordan after unexpected negotiations Saturday with Yasir Arafat, chairman of the Palestine Liberation Organization. A1</p>
        <p>A debate between Israeli candidates for Prime Minister was dominated by questions about King Hussein's apparent endorsement of Foreign Minister Shimon Peres and his plans for Middle East peace. A8</p>
        <p>Bombing suspects seized by Israelis A9</p>
        <p>Hurricane Joan killed 111 people in Nicaragua and elsewhere around the Caribbean. It also left another 150 missing and 300,000 homeless across Nicaragua before heading out into the Pacific, renamed as Tropical Storm Miriam. A1</p>
        <p>Curtailing Soviet rule in Lithuania was called for in the founding platform of a grassroots political group in the republic, the Movement for the Support of Perestroika. A1</p>
        <p>Helmut Kohl is to visit Moscow today with a grand West German entourage for four days of talks with Mikhail S. Gorbachev and others. His hope is that West Germany can find a place at the forefront of East-West detente. A1</p>
        <p>An arms-deal suspect's role in possible efforts to free American captives held in Lebanon is being investigated by Italian officials. The suspect was to have received documents on several hostages, they said. A9</p>
        <p>An agreement to limit oil production collapsed over the weekend when Iran rejected the OPEC plan, which would have integrated Iraq into a production quota system. D1</p>
        <p>Services for a missing South African raised questions anew about his disappearance while in police custody. The authorities say Stanza Bopape escaped from three armed police officers. A3</p>
        <p>Pakistani elections for a new leader to replace President Zia, who died in a plane crash, are to be held next month and are likely to return the nation to civilian rule. A2</p>
        <p>Congress declined to help finance United Nations peacekeeping operations in southern Africa despite assurances from the Reagan Administration that it would continue to support the Angolan rebels, officials said. A3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A10-15, B5-7  Congress has reasserted its voice during the session which is coming to a close. Once overshadowed by President Reagan, the Congress enacted groundbreaking legislation in trade, welfare, civil rights and arms control. A1</p>
        <p>Kraft Inc. rejected a $90-a-share bid by Philip Morris. Instead it will offer stockholders a special dividend package it valued at more than $110 a share, or $14 billion. A1</p>
        <p>Ways to extend the supply of tritium, a radioactive gas that increases the explosive power of nuclear weapons, are being explored by the Reagan Administration. They include a reduction in the amount of the gas put in warheads. A1</p>
        <p>Some biologists questioned the value of the effort to rescue two whales trapped by ice in the Arctic Ocean. Meanwhile, new rescue equipment arrived and a Soviet icebreaker is due Tuesday. A15</p>
        <p>The Head of the Charles crew races were attended by 275,000 people. The races have turned into a major event in recent years for the reunions of area colleges and preparatory schools. A10</p>
        <p>Recycling has become fashionable, popular and practical in many areas. Markets for many recycled products may become saturated, however, and experts say some cities will not recycle unless forced to do so. A10</p>
        <p>The ''hole'' in the ozone layer over Antarctica appears to be less severe this year than last year, but the apparent improvement does not mean the threat of ozone depletion is reduced, Federal officials said. A12</p>
        <p>A cancer-causing toxin in corn has been detected in the new harvest in several states, raising concern among officials that contamination may be widespread. The toxin is created by a fungus that thrives in hot, dry weather. A11</p>
        <p>POLITICS B5-6  The Bush campaign was accused of using tactics that inflame racial fears. Democrats said the campaign has emphasized the case of a black prisoner who raped a white woman while he was on prison furlough. A1</p>
        <p>George Bush's strategy: No mistakes are to be made the final stretch of the Presidential campaign. The Vice President is keeping his candidacy in a protective bubble and sticking to carefully scripted events. B5</p>
        <p>The Dukakis effort in New Jersey has been reduced, increasing George Bush's strength in the state and some say endangering other Democratic candidates on the ballot. The Dukakis campaign denies that New Jersey has been written off. B6</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON TALK A14</p>
        <p>Proxmire bids a farewell  REGIONAL B1-4  Two Mexican officials were arrested in New York City late Saturday and charged with conspiring to import large amounts of Mexican heroin into the United States, Federal authorities said. A1</p>
        <p>A shelter for men with tuberculosis is to open in New York City next month on a renovated floor of the Bellevue Men's Shelter. The shelter will seek to stem the spread of the disease among the homeless. B1</p>
        <p>Renovation of the Grand Army Plaza between 58th Street and 60th Street is to begin today and will cost $3.3 million. The fountain there, the Fountain of Abundance, is expected to be repaired by the end of 1989. B3</p>
        <p>Housing for low-income Jerseyans remains an elusive goal 13 years after the state's Supreme Court outlawed exclusionary zoning. Resistance remains deep-rooted in many communities. B1</p>
        <p>Fans of old radio programs gathered at a convention at a Newark hotel. The convention included a re-enactment of ''Superman,'' and cassettes of old shows like ''The Lone Ranger'' were traded. B1</p>
        <p>The new movie ''Mystic Pizza'' opened in the Connecticut village where it was filmed, and it may upset the delicate balance between the tony and the touristy in the seaport. B1</p>
        <p>Conservationists laud efforts for the Hudson B2</p>
        <p>A stray bullet kills a woman in Queens home B3</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
