<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TV Notes</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="175875"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PUBLIC BROADCASTING SERVICE (PBS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MALLE, LOUIS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLAU, ELEANOR</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">AND THE PURSUIT OF HAPPINESS (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DD143CF932A3575AC0A96E948260" item-length="874" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TV Notes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eleanor Blau</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BLAU, ELEANOR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  Portrait of Emmigrants</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  Portrait of Emmigrants</p>
        <p>Portrait of Emmigrants</p>
        <p>Louis Malle, best known for such feature films as ''Pretty Baby'' and ''Atlantic City,'' has also made documentaries over the years and, he says, that means traveling light, especially recently. In 1986, setting out with a crew of three, he made a documentary for HBO, the pay-cable channel, on a topic that had long intrigued him: new immigrants to the United States.</p>
        <p>The French director joked the other day that he had had the ''good luck'' to have it broadcast in prime time on July 4, when almost everyone was watching fireworks marking the Statue of Liberty's centennial.</p>
        <p>So he was pleased that the film, ''And the Pursuit of Happiness,'' would get more exposure, on public television. It is scheduled for broadcast on Channel 13 and most other PBS stations on Sept. 9 at 9 P.M.</p>
        <p>The 55-year-old Mr. Malle, who has been based in New York in recent years and who said he felt ''sort of'' like an immigrant himself, dramatized the impact of Vietnamese immigrants on a Texas town in his 1985 feature film ''Alamo Bay.'' In the 90-minute ''Pursuit of Happiness,'' Mr. Malle - its producer, cameraman, director and narrator - presents real-life interviews with Asians, Africans and Latin Americans who tell of their attempts to achieve the American dream.</p>
        <p>''A hundred years ago, most immigrants to America were from Europe,'' he said by telephone from his summer home near Toulouse, France. ''Now they are from five continents. It has become such a bizarre patchwork of races, religions and cultures. I wanted to do a series of portraits with the greatest possible variety - people with different attitudes, backgrounds, people who have had success, and people who had hard times. What emerges for me is the tremendous influx of energy these people bring to America.''</p>
        <p>Meantime, he said, he is at work on two screenplays: a story of his own, based on France in the 1960's, and a comedy with the writer John Guare. ''It's about ex-patriots, a series of misadventures of an American family in Sicily,'' he said. ''It's sort of the opposite of the film about immigrants.''  Environmental Poison</p>
        <p>After a heat wave, a drought, beach closings because of medical waste and talk of the dreaded greenhouse effect, ABC News has decided to highlight environmental issues all next week. A special next Thursday at 10 P.M. called ''Burning Questions: The Poisoning of America,'' with Hugh Downs as anchor, will examine how much damage has been done to the environment and at what point that damage becomes irreversible. Such issues as illegal dumping, medical waste and air pollution will be addressed on other ABC programs including ''World News Tonight,'' ''Good Morning America,'' ''20/20,'' ''Nightline'' and ''Business World.''  'Vanity Fair' on A&amp;E</p>
        <p>Two Victorian friends, an upper-class girl and an orphan determined to rise in society, grow up, cross paths, trade fortunes and eventually seem to find what they sought. It will all take place over 21 weeks, as the Arts &amp; Entertainment cable network presents a BBC series dramatizing William Makepeace Thackeray's ''Vanity Fair.''</p>
        <p>The first of 21 half-hour episodes will be broadcast Sept. 11 at 9 P.M., Sept. 12 at 1 A.M. and Sept. 17 at 6 P.M. The dramatist is the novelist Alexander Baron, who also dramatized the television series ''Poldark,'' ''Oliver Twist'' and ''Jane Eyre.'' ''Vanity Fair'' stars Eve Matheson, Rebecca Saire and Sian Phillips.  Past and Future</p>
        <p>Looking back 25 years, to the minute, A&amp;E will re-broadcast NBC's news coverage of President Kennedy's assassination. The six-hour special, which will interrupt the network's regular programming, will start Nov. 22, at the same moment NBC broke into its schedule to report shots fired at the Presidential motorcade in Dallas.</p>
        <p>Looking to the future, the Fox Broadcasting Company, Channel 5, will begin a ''hi tech'' news magazine, ''Beyond Tomorrow,'' on Saturdays at 9 P.M., starting Sept. 10. The first program includes a clothes- washing machine that uses ultra-sound bubbles instead of detergent, a skateboard with wings and a pin-prick test said to detect diseases, including AIDS.  A Video Scoop</p>
        <p>It may sound like the cart before the horse, but Vestron Video yesterday released a video cassette of a program scheduled for broadcast Oct. 12 at 9 P.M. on public television.</p>
        <p>The 90-minute special, ''The Explorers: A Century of Discovery'' ($29.98), celebrates the centennial of the National Geographic Society. The program, narrated by E. G. Marshall and using rare archival material as well as new film, chronicles National Geographic expeditions over the last 100 years, including Robert E. Peary's attempt to reach the North Pole, Richard Byrd's flight to the South Pole, Hiram Bingham's discovery of an ancient Inca city in Peru and Robert Ballard's underwater exploration of the Titanic.</p>
        <p>A program on the Ballard venture, ''Secrets of the Titanic,'' was also released on home video before its broadcast in 1987. Since that broadcast got the highest rating on cable at the time, said Tim Kelly, vice president and director of National Geographic Television, ''We figured that releasing the video first doesn't hurt, and maybe helps promote the program.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
