<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY: March 20, 1988</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="129192"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">SUMMARY</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3D6153FF933A15750C0A96E948260" item-length="1003" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY: March 20, 1988</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL 3-19</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL 3-19</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL 3-19</p>
        <p>Panama's military leader, Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, has rejected an American offer to leave the country in return for a promise that the United States will not seek his extradition, senior Administration officials said.  Page 1</p>
        <p>Spain credits the U.S. with offer of asylum for Noriega  15</p>
        <p>Panama is widening its purge of the military  16</p>
        <p>Violence at a Belfast funeral erupted as two armed British security soldiers in civilian clothes were seized, beaten and finally shot to death after their car became trapped in the crowd of angry and panic-stricken mourners. 1</p>
        <p>Honduran Air Force jets bombed suspected Nicaraguan troop positions in the region along the Nicaraguan border where the Sandinistas have been attacking United States-backed rebels. 1</p>
        <p>The U.S. has deployed a battalion supported by artillery to a training area within 42 miles of the Honduran border with Nicaragua, positioning them to move swiftly if ordered to intervene, American military officers said. 16</p>
        <p>The use of American helicopters to transport Honduran troops to the battle zone where Sandinista forces have been fighting rebel guerillas over the last week has been rejected by the Reagan Administration, an official said. 17</p>
        <p>Israel blocked foreign journalists from working in the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip today, in an apparent effort to reduce coverage of more than three months of Palestinian protests. 1</p>
        <p>In the Mideast, a struggle for television  14</p>
        <p>Marxist guerrillas in El Salvador, stepping up their effort to stop national elections on Sunday, have killed one mayor and kidnapped two others in recent days, burned a mayor's office, and exploded several bombs. 3</p>
        <p>The Soviet Foreign Minister, Eduard A. Shevardnadze, is to arrive in Washington Sunday in search of a compromise that would ease the withdrawal of Soviet troops from Afghanistan. 18</p>
        <p>In a dispute over arms control, the White House has sent a sharply worded letter to Congress rejecting a move by Senate Democrats to attach a binding condition to the new missile treaty on a key arms control issue.  3</p>
        <p>From Jesuits to Zimbabweans: a gift of land  11</p>
        <p>A new view is offered on Yeltsin's undoing  19</p>
        <p>NATIONAL/20-31, 42-45</p>
        <p>The destruction of the ozone layer, set in motion by the release of industrial gases into the atmosphere, will continue for decades despite the best efforts of governments and industries to control it, scientists now agree. 1</p>
        <p>Hispanic-Americans continue to lag behind other minority groups in entering the mainstream of higher education, a fact that seriously hinders their own economic aspirations as well as the development of the nation's work force. 1</p>
        <p>A bill to help the uranium industry by forgiving payment of $8.8 billion owed the Government by the nuclear utility industry is expected to reach the Senate floor this week. Critics are calling the measure a giveaway of taxpayers' money.  20</p>
        <p>Mississippi Democrats in dispute over chairman  20</p>
        <p>Gimmicks become a tool for vaccinations  21</p>
        <p>Buddhist monk builds spiritual refuge in suburbia  24</p>
        <p>California town glad to win a radioactive dump.  29</p>
        <p>Part-time workers find a sweet workplace  43</p>
        <p>Politics 26</p>
        <p>Whatever happened to momentum? While Vice President Bush has it, none of the Democratic Presidential contenders seem to. Candidates win some primaries and a few headlines, only to be knocked down somewhere else. 1</p>
        <p>Senator Albert Gore's candidacy has been raising questions among even his own supporters in the wake of his anticlimactic showings in contests since Super Tuesday. Some are wondering if he is just a regional candidate. 26</p>
        <p>Michael Dukakis's industrial policy has been sketched out in recent days as the Presidential candidate tries to address the economic anxiety that pervades Michigan. So far, his speeches on industrial policy have been broadly thematic. 26</p>
        <p>Kansas caucuses won by Dukakis  27</p>
        <p>REGIONAL/32-39, 46-50</p>
        <p>A woman who died of lung cancer contracted the disease as a result of her cigarette smoking, a lung cancer specialist testified in a lawsuit against several tobacco companies brought by the woman's husband. 39</p>
        <p>A cover-up of safety deficiencies at an irradiation company was charged in an indictment. A former officer of Radiation Technology Inc. was indicted for conspiracy, obstruction of justice and other charges. 36</p>
        <p>R. H. Macy &amp; Company would sell 11 Abraham &amp; Straus stores in New York and New Jersey if it succeeds in acquiring A.&amp; S.'s parent company, Federated Department Stores Inc, executives from Macy's said. 34</p>
        <p>Procuring and distributing organs and tissue for transplants would be coordinated under a New York State plan in an attempt to distribute them among patients fairly, the Health Commissioner has announced. 33</p>
        <p>2,000 residents were evacuated in Berkeley Heights, N.J., as crews tried to isolate a potentially explosive gas-filled cylinder at a chemical plant. Officials said the residents would remain out of their homes until the danger passed. 32</p>
        <p>Lilco 's future remains clouded with questions  34</p>
        <p>New York City seeks more state aid for city's schools  37</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
