<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Autumn's Palette May be Muted</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="176607"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREES AND SHRUBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAPLE TREES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BATTISTA, CAROLYN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DC1339F937A3575AC0A96E948260" item-length="1086" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Autumn's Palette May be Muted</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLYN BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BATTISTA, CAROLYN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THIS year's fall foliage will probably start a little earlier and be a little dimmer than in some past years, the state's foresters say. The weather - especially dry weather - may have taken its toll, the foresters say, and sugar maples in particular have had several problems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THIS year's fall foliage will probably start a little earlier and be a little dimmer than in some past years, the state's foresters say. The weather - especially dry weather - may have taken its toll, the foresters say, and sugar maples in particular have had several problems.</p>
        <p>THIS year's fall foliage will probably start a little earlier and be a little dimmer than in some past years, the state's foresters say. The weather - especially dry weather - may have taken its toll, the foresters say, and sugar maples in particular have had several problems.</p>
        <p>Despite the difficulties, the color and conditions are expected to be good enough for a successful leaf-peeping season, barring bad weather - like the hurricane that one forester considers all too likely - in coming weeks.</p>
        <p>''It's going to be hard to predict,'' said the State Forester, Peter Babcock. ''I would say we're still going to have a lot of nice color, but it may not be as spectacular as some years, because of the dry spell. Some of the trees may change early, and the colors may not be as bright.''</p>
        <p>Some foresters cited forces besides weather that have affected Connecticut trees in recent months. ''Sugar maples - really the kings of foliage - took a major hit,'' said the forester at Great Mountain Forest in Norfolk, Starling Childs. Mr. Childs said difficulties began during the misty, cold weather of May, when leaves were maturing. ''A fungus, anthracnose, ran rampant through the sugar maples,'' he said. ''There was also a really high population of aphids, especially in western Connecticut. And we had some pear thrips, a kind of fly, in sugar maples.'' Mr. Childs said the thrip infestation could affect not only fall foliage, but also spring sugaring. He said the stressed trees had smaller-sized leaves and were ''shutting down'' early.</p>
        <p>''I'm looking out my window, and I see sick-looking maples,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''There's still going to be color,'' he said. But he said ailing trees with smaller leaves would cut down the display.</p>
        <p>The forester at the Pachaug State Forest in Voluntown, Clarence (Pete) Merrill, said that the eastern part of the state did not have as severe a dry spell as did the western part, and was not so badly affected by thrips and anthracnose simply because sugar maples were less prevalent in the east. But, he said, trees that were affected were showing ''distorted, short-sized leaves.'' He added, ''We might get some early drop.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Merrill said the hot, humid weather of August was more of a problem in industrialized areas, where the heavy air was laden with pollutants, than in forested regions. And he cited a plus this season in eastern Connecticut. For the first time in many years, he said, the area has escaped defoliation by gypsy moths.  Tolland County Report</p>
        <p>James Parda, a forester who covers Tolland County, in the north central part of the state, also cited the sugar maples' difficulties, but noted that those trees were few in his area. In general, he said, he expected normal foliage. He noted that the change in leaf color was ''based primarily on the length of the day.'' He said temperature and available water were second and third in influence.</p>
        <p>Experts point out that the weather in coming weeks can still affect foliage, a little or a lot. ''If trees are stressed late in the season, it won't hurt as much as early in the season,'' said a state climatologist, David R. Miller, who is a professor in the department of natural resources management and engineering at the University of Connecticut at Storrs. A late dry spell would cause only a little harm, Professor Miller said. However, he said, ''If it rains during the season, it can knock the leaves off.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Babcock said: ''If an early frost occurs, we could lose leaves before foliage season. And the way the weather has been, we're a prime target for a hurricane. The worst hurricanes have occurred in years of abnormal weather patterns, and we've had lots of abnormal weather this year.''</p>
        <p>When Hurricane Gloria swept the Connecticut coast in September 1985, it not only blew leaves from trees, but also killed remaining leaves - even on trees several miles inland from Long Island Sound - by whipping them with salt spray.  Adapting to Warming</p>
        <p>Professor Miller said that in coming decades, the warmer weather caused by the so-called greenhouse effect could change the nature of New England foliage. ''Vegetation will adapt,'' he said, ''with southern species migrating northward. But it will be gradual.''</p>
        <p>Now, most agree, New England foliage is spectacular. ''In other parts of the country they don't have the variety, the flaming colors, the numbers of trees,'' said a Connecticut Department of Economic Development spokeswoman, Barbara Beeching. She added, ''I'm from Indiana, and the leaves do change there, but there isn't anything like the spectacle here.''</p>
        <p>During the peak foliage season, from late September to mid-October, Connecticut inns and motels in scenic areas are often filled, especially on weekends. Some people make reservations a year in advance, Mrs. Beeching said.</p>
        <p>''The sales tax collected on lodgings goes up considerably,'' said the executive director of the Litchfield Hills Travel Council, Janet Serra. People call the council, she added, for more than just what weeks and what routes are recommended for foliage viewing. ''We have people ask, 'What is the best day?' '' Ms. Serra said.  Number for Foliage Reports</p>
        <p>By the second half of September, foresters around the state phone in regular reports to the Department of Economic Development, detailing what percentage of leaves have turned in their areas. During the foliage season, those who call the department at (800) 842-7492 get a report on foliage along with other tourism information.</p>
        <p>But despite the lively interest, such details as percentages do not really matter, according to Lewis Mandell, a professor of finance at UConn who follows Connecticut tourism. He said that although fall foliage provides an advertising theme for inns and attractions, it is too short to have a major impact on the economy. What does get people traveling around the state is simply fall.</p>
        <p>''It's a season when you can get out and see things,'' Professor Mandell said. ''Even if the foliage is disappointing, it doesn't matter. We're not all looking for a home run every time.''</p>
        <p>He said he expected the wet and hot spells of summer to have a beneficial effect on fall tourism. ''It's been such a wretched summer, people have been reluctant to go anywhere,'' he said. ''I think there's going be a pent-up demand.''</p>
        <p>And people will head out to look at fall color, no matter how spectacular or unspectacular it is, the professor said. ''It's an annual ritual,'' he said. ''It's habitual behavior.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
