<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CONSERVATIONISTS TO BACK DUKAKIS</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="179649"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1988</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDORSEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONSERVATION VOTERS, LEAGUE OF</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">REPUBLICAN PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUKAKIS, MICHAEL S (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DB153AF936A2575AC0A96E948260" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CONSERVATIONISTS TO BACK DUKAKIS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Rejecting Vice President Bush's recent assertion that he is an environmentalist, the political arm of the nation's major conservation groups will endorse the Presidential candidacy of Gov. Michael S. Dukakis of Massachusetts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Rejecting Vice President Bush's recent assertion that he is an environmentalist, the political arm of the nation's major conservation groups will endorse the Presidential candidacy of Gov. Michael S. Dukakis of Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>Rejecting Vice President Bush's recent assertion that he is an environmentalist, the political arm of the nation's major conservation groups will endorse the Presidential candidacy of Gov. Michael S. Dukakis of Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>The executive director of the League of Conservation Voters said today that the group's directors believed the Democratic nominee would better serve the environmental needs of the country. The group's directors voted on the endorsement Friday but the league has not officially announced its decision.</p>
        <p>The executive director, Jim Maddy, said the organization's review of the candidates' records established no reason to change the league's previous assessments of the two candidates. The league previously gave Mr. Bush a ''D'' grade and Mr. Dukakis a ''B'' for their leadership on environmental issues. Individual Support for Bush</p>
        <p>''The decision was based on an objective, honest, bipartisan appraisal of the records of both candidates,'' Mr. Maddy said. He added, ''Not to have endorsed Mr. Dukakis would have been to reward Vice President Bush for a poor environmental record and punish Governor Dukakis for a good record.''</p>
        <p>Some individual conservationists have announced their support for the Vice President. Three former environmental officials in Republican administrations have formed a committee of conservationists to advise Mr. Bush. They are William D. Ruckelshaus and Russell E. Train, who were Administrators of the Environmental Protection Agency, and Nathaniel Reed, who was an Assistant Secretary of the Interior.</p>
        <p>Interior Secretary Donald P. Hodel criticized the environmentalists' endorsement decision as ''totally and absolutely predictable.''</p>
        <p>''The environmentalists have been in the pocket of the Democratic national party since they signed on with Jimmy Carter and opposed Ronald Reagan in 1980,'' Mr. Hodel said. ''Most Americans support balanced and resposive environmental programs, a fact that is lost on these people who, in some cases, have made their organization into partisan organizations.'' Partisanship Denied</p>
        <p>Mr. Maddy insisted that his group was strictly nonpartisan and said that it was backing many Republicans in this year's Congressional elections. He noted it is giving its highest Congressional priority to the re-election of Senator John H. Chafee, Republican of Rhode Island.</p>
        <p>''The country cannot afford to lose John Chafee - he is too important for the environment,'' Mr. Maddy said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maddy said environmentalists' support could be decisive in crucial swing states like California and New Jersey, where voters have demonstrated a concern over pollution issues.</p>
        <p>He added that the endorsement means that millions of members of environmental organizations would be notified that Mr. Dukakis is the candidate to support. He also said environmentalists would be doing door-to-door canvassing and placing advertisements for the Democratic candidate.</p>
        <p>One national environmental group, Friends of the Earth, also decided to endorse Mr. Dukakis as an individual group. Alan Gussow, president of the organization, said the decision was based on the fact that ''Mike Dukakis has a good environmental record and George Bush does not.'' Bush's Actions Assailed</p>
        <p>''For the last last eight years,'' Mr. Gussow said, ''the Reagan-Bush Administration told the oil and coal companies to help themselves to the public lands, cut the environmental protection budgets and stopped enforcing environmental laws. Where on earth was Bush when the environment needed him? In charge of the campaign to deregulate environmental controls, that's where.''</p>
        <p>Another organization, Environmental Victory, made up of more than a thousand professionals and scholars in the environmental field in New York State, announced today that they would endorse Mr. Dukakis at a news conference Thursday morning.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush sought to seize the initiative on the environmental issue in a series of speeches two weeks ago in which he described himself as an environmentalist, promised specific actions, including a program to curb acid rain, and said pollution in Boston Harbor showed that Mr. Dukakis had questionable environmental credentials.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
