<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Quest for Fusion Energy, 2 Rival Techniques Fight for the Spotlight</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="145942"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUSION (NUCLEAR REACTION)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAGNETISM AND MAGNETS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LASERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fusion (Nuclear Reaction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Laser (Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission of Radiation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DB123FF934A25756C0A96E948260" item-length="4079" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Quest for Fusion Energy, 2 Rival Techniques Fight for the Spotlight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: FOR decades the costly field of controlled nuclear fusion has been rocked by ups and downs, promise and problems. But scientists are now confident enough of success to embark, albeit cautiously, on building a new generation of machines that would ignite fusion fuel for the first time, releasing controlled bursts of energy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: FOR decades the costly field of controlled nuclear fusion has been rocked by ups and downs, promise and problems. But scientists are now confident enough of success to embark, albeit cautiously, on building a new generation of machines that would ignite fusion fuel for the first time, releasing controlled bursts of energy.</p>
        <p>FOR decades the costly field of controlled nuclear fusion has been rocked by ups and downs, promise and problems. But scientists are now confident enough of success to embark, albeit cautiously, on building a new generation of machines that would ignite fusion fuel for the first time, releasing controlled bursts of energy.</p>
        <p>The aim is to harness for practical use the violent process that powers stars and hydrogen bombs.</p>
        <p>Over the years dozens of different types of machines have been devised to try to achieve this goal. Many are now gathering dust. In the United States, the elusive quest has recently produced two rival techniques that are rapidly moving toward the objective.</p>
        <p>The cost of building new, more powerful machines using these methods is estimated at more than $1 billion. Scientists hope they will be ready by the end of the next decade. Although each technique has different civil or military advantages, they are both seen as a general boon to research on nuclear physics and electrical power generation.</p>
        <p>''In the 21st century, these processes will profoundly change the future of the country and mankind,'' said Eric Storm, a fusion official at the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory in California.</p>
        <p>But today's cautious optimism about fusion coexists with a stark symbol of excitement gone awry: a $372 million fusion machine at Livermore that was never switched on and that now sits derelict in a giant building. Its demise was brought about by financial setbacks rather than scientific ones, a dead end for one American method of trying to harness the super-hot reactions at the heart of thermonuclear fusion.</p>
        <p>The two main methods that remain have made either steady progress or major advances. The result is that two rival groups of scientists are now courting Congress and the Administration, insisting that their next-generation machines should be financed despite increasingly tight Federal budgets.</p>
        <p>But skeptics say the ultimate payoff, no matter which method achieves ignition first, will be far less than advertised.</p>
        <p>''It's a scientific curiosity, not a practical pursuit,'' said Lawrence M. Lidsky, a nuclear engineer at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, who left the fusion field four years ago, disappointed with its prospects.</p>
        <p>While skeptics abound, scientists for decades have eagerly pursued the goal of controlled fusion because of its promise of nearly inexhaustible energy. For instance, a gallon of ordinary water contains enough deuterium, a hydrogen isotope commonly used in fusion fuel, that its thermonuclear burning would generate the energy of 300 gallons of gasoline. A Pair of Challenges</p>
        <p>The first challenge in controlled fusion is to create a plasma, a super-hot state of matter in which orbiting electrons are stripped from atoms, leaving a gas composed of free electrons and atomic nuclei. The problem is that these nuclei have a positive charge, making them avoid each other. However, if the plasma is very hot and dense, light nuclei like those of hydrogen will smash into one another and fuse to form larger nuclei like helium, releasing a burst of energy in the process, mainly in the form of speeding neutrons.</p>
        <p>Most often, controlled fusion seeks to join the nuclei of deuterium and tritium, another isotope of hydrogen. On earth, the requisite temperature for this reaction is about 100 million degrees Celsius.</p>
        <p>The second, greater challenge is to confine this super-hot plasma. Clearly, no earthly vessel is up to the task. Any kind of metal, ceramic or glass would quickly melt. So scientists at the outset of the quest turned to magnetism, creating increasingly powerful magnetic ''bottles.''</p>
        <p>Today, the most successful method of magnetic confinement centers on doughnut-shaped reactors called tokamaks. These set up two magnetic fields, an external one and an internal one that flows through charged particles to help keep the particles in place. The magnetic fields force the particles to circle around the hole in the doughnut. Princeton's Tokamak</p>
        <p>One of the world's most powerful tokamaks is at Princeton University. Built at a cost of $314 million and switched on in 1982, it has triggered fusion reactions just shy of scientific ''break-even,'' the point at which the amount of energy released in fusion reactions matches that pumped into the machine for plasma heating.</p>
        <p>''We're remarkably close to achieving the goal we set for ourself,'' said Harold P. Furth, director of the Princeton Plasma Physics Laboratory.</p>
        <p>Today, Princeton researchers are setting their sights beyond ''break-even'' to ''ignition,'' the point at which sufficient heat is generated by fusion reactions to make them self-sustaining. The $350 million machine meant to achieve this goal is the Compact Ignition Tokamak. It could be completed at Princeton by 1996, later if financing is delayed.</p>
        <p>At this delicate point, a key problem for the magnetic fusion community is the haunting specter of the idle $372 million machine known as the Mirror Fusion Test Facility, the largest and most expensive project in the history of the Livermore laboratory.</p>
        <p>The machine was not a doughnut-shaped tokamak, but an innovative approach to plasma confinement that seemed simpler and cheaper. Its cylindrical chamber was to guide plasma along straight lines rather than complex circular orbits, with a series of large magnets at each end, the ''mirrors,'' to keep the plasma from leaking out.</p>
        <p>After several small models proved successful, Livermore embarked on the big one, its central vacuum vessel being 175 feet long and 32 feet high. After nine years and $372 million, the machine was dedicated in February 1986, only to be immediately mothballed for lack of operating funds and fear that further spending would jeopardize the main effort, the tokamaks. Its electric bill alone would have come to $1 million a month.</p>
        <p>''There was first an energy crisis and then a budget crisis,'' noted the journal Science in describing the decade-long genesis of the fiasco. Livermore's Dark Horse</p>
        <p>Today, despite the setback, Livermore scientists have made substantial advances on an altogether different fusion path, leading them to envision the most expensive machine of all, costing up to $700 million. The technique was long considered a dark horse that could never rival the tokamaks.</p>
        <p>The idea is to use lasers or particle beams to bombard tiny fuel pellets for a split second, heating and squeezing them to the point of ignition. There are no complex magnets. Instead, the fuel pellet is held together by its own inertia for a billionth of a second before being consumed and flying apart in a burst of energy. The method is called inertial fusion and sometimes microfusion, since the fuel pellets are so tiny, being the size of a pea or smaller.</p>
        <p>Over the years Livermore has built a series of increasingly large lasers to explore the feasibility of the method. Today its $200 million Nova laser, the size of a football field, has 10 beams to bombard tiny fuel pellets. Nova is now approaching its goal of break-even. Encouraging Secret Test</p>
        <p>Results of an unorthodox test conducted two years ago have especially elated microfusion researchers, causing them to redouble their efforts. The secret experiment used a blast of radiation from an exploding nuclear weapon beneath the Nevada desert to trigger ignition for the first time. It clearly showed the microfusion goal was feasible, though the strategy was offbeat.</p>
        <p>The race now focuses on creating a laboratory laser big enough to achieve ignition. At Livermore, its name is Athena, a design for a $700 million laser bigger than Nova but based on the same general principles.</p>
        <p>''In both magnetic and inertial fusion, there is virtually no longer any doubt that the scientific feasibility is in hand,'' said Dr. Storm, the Livermore fusion official.</p>
        <p>Scientists say energy bursts from a working microfusion device, in effect tiny H-bombs, could be used to study plasma physics (and thus the forces at work in the sun and stars), to investigate the physics and effects of nuclear weapons, and to generate electricity. In contrast the tokamaks would have a more narrow application, mainly power generation. Economy and Safety</p>
        <p>The allure of futuristic power plants running on either magnetic or inertial fusion is not only their inexhaustible fuel supply but their relative safety. Today's nuclear power plants, which split large atoms like uranium into smaller ones, produce much radioactive waste. But experts say fusion reactors would produce minimal waste and it could decay to biologically safe levels in hundreds of years, as opposed to thousands of years for today's reactors.</p>
        <p>Moreover, no fusion reactor could go out of control, since its small fuel supply has to be constantly replenished. In contrast, fission reactors contain enough fuel for many years of operation, and sometimes many years of danger, as the Chernobyl reactor accident in the Soviet Union has demonstrated.</p>
        <p>The big hurdle is cost. Experts say it could take $20 billion or more to turn fusion from a laboratory curiosity into a practical source of electrical power. Dr. Lidsky, the nuclear engineer at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, said fusion reactors would always be ''big, ugly, expensive, complicated'' and less efficient than conventional rivals.</p>
        <p>Stephen O. Dean, president of Fusion Power Associates, a Maryland-based group that promotes the field, agreed that fusion in the 21st century would probably not be economically competitive with other energy sources. He added, however, that environmental factors would spark the birth of a fusion-power industry in the 21st century. Coal- and oil-fired plants, he said, make acid rain and warm the earth's atmosphere through the ''greenhouse effect.'' And conventional reactors make radioactive waste.</p>
        <p>''The thing that's going to make fusion are environmental factors,'' Dr. Dean said. ''That's what will eventually make fusion the winner.''  A Quest to Tame The Stars' Fury</p>
        <p>Scientists want to fuse elements together, as the sun and stars do, for research in physics and energy production. If hot enough, deuterium and tritium will fuse to form helium, releasing a burst of energy in the form of speeding neutrons. Despite decades of effort to achieve controlled fusion reactions, scientists have so far fallen short of achieving their goal.  Confining Fuel in a Magnetic 'Doughnut'</p>
        <p>The main hurdle has been building containers strong enough to hold super-hot fuel. To date, the most successful type of machine has been the doughnut-shaped tokamak, which sets up two opposing magnetic fields that contain the fuel better than anything else so far. A transformer in the machine's core induces one magnetic field in hot fuel, while giant coils around the ring set up another. The opposing magnetic fields force fuel particles to spiral around the hole in the doughnut.  Blasting Fuel Pellets With Lasers</p>
        <p>A rival technique abandons the magnetic confinement idea. Lasers bombard tiny fuel pellets for a split second, heating and squeezing them to the point of ignition. A pellet is held together by its own inertia for a billionth of a second before being consumed and flying apart in a burst of energy. The action is so fast that containment is no longer an issue.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
