<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ASTROCHICKEN AND ENERGY TREES</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="164090"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PENROSE, ROGER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DYSON, FREEMAN J (PROF)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">INFINITE IN ALL DIRECTIONS (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3D61138F937A15754C0A96E948260" item-length="1770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ASTROCHICKEN AND ENERGY TREES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROGER PENROSE; Roger Penrose is the Rouse Ball Professor of Mathematics at the University of Oxford.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PENROSE, ROGER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INFINITE IN ALL DIRECTIONS  By Freeman J. Dyson.  321 pp. New York:  A Cornelia and Michael Bessie Book/  Harper &amp; Row. $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INFINITE IN ALL DIRECTIONS  By Freeman J. Dyson.  321 pp. New York:  A Cornelia and Michael Bessie Book/  Harper &amp; Row. $19.95.</p>
        <p>INFINITE IN ALL DIRECTIONS  By Freeman J. Dyson.  321 pp. New York:  A Cornelia and Michael Bessie Book/  Harper &amp; Row. $19.95.</p>
        <p>Freeman J. Dyson is an original, versatile and thoughtful man, and what he writes is always interesting. Born into an English upper-middle-class musician's family, he started his professional life, in the early 1950's, in the theory of numbers. Then he turned his mathematical talents to physics, providing a fundamental unifying contribution to the newly emerging subject of relativistic quantum theory and subsequently confronting such basic questions as the stability of matter. Later he turned his attention to the planets and the stars, their nature and possible future explorations. More recently he has entered the field of biology and has been addressing the question of the origin of life. He is also an expert in the technology of nuclear and other military weapons. But he is no cold scientist. He has a love of literature and history and a distinct talent for writing. He is concerned about the future of mankind, both in the short term and in the very remote future. He puzzles over the meaning of life, the purpose of the universe and the nature of God. In short, he is a philosopher in the broadest sense. Moreover, he is an unbridled optimist. In his latest book, ''Infinite in All Directions,'' which is based essentially on the Gifford lectures he gave at the University of Aberdeen, Scotland, in 1985, Mr. Dyson addresses many of the above issues. And despite this apparent diversity of topics, there is one pervasive and unifying theme - ''diversity'' itself. Indeed, the original title of his Gifford lectures was ''In Praise of Diversity.'' Mr. Dyson considers his various topics in relation to unity-diversity, his sympathies being always on the side of diversity.</p>
        <p>To appreciate fully what he has in mind by his use of the term ''diversity,'' one must read this book through. But something of the flavor of his meaning can be gained if we think not of imposing mountaintops as revealed to us by the great unifying physical theories of Newton, Maxwell or Einstein, but of rich valleys like the rain forests of the Amazon, with bewildering varieties of creatures coexisting with even more bewildering varieties of plant life - or perhaps of just one species: the beautiful but humble butterfly, whose transformation from a caterpillar represents an intricate feat of nature's technology far beyond anything we have yet been able to achieve with our comparatively simple machines.</p>
        <p>As a physicist, Mr. Dyson is fully appreciative of the unifying influences of great scientists. But he argues that such unifications may have outlived their usefulness; future advances may come more from a new appreciation of nature's diversity. Referring to the now highly popular mathematical-physical theory of ''superstrings'' (a brave and flamboyant attempt to unify the whole of physics), he remains skeptical. He believes that while there will be further unifying advances in physics, a complete union is not possible. To him, the more we try to find unity underlying the structure of our world, the more diversity will be revealed.</p>
        <p>This picture of increasing diversity claims support from a modern physical idea called ''symmetry breaking,'' which holds that the universe is supposed to unfold from a highly unified and symmetrical state to a diverse and complicated asymmetrical one. Mr. Dyson disagrees with Einstein's sentiment that ''pure thought can grasp reality.'' He contrasts the abstract (unified) pure science of Einstein with the more concrete experimental physics of Ernest Rutherford, referring to the latter (for reasons not altogether clear to me) as ''diversified.'' He evokes a comparison, once made by Disraeli, between ancient Athens and the city of Manchester, England, during the Industrial Revolution, the first epitomizing unity and the second diversity; and he points also to the exciting science, particularly that of Rutherford, that came from Manchester at that time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dyson's main case for ''diversity'' comes from biology, which, by its very nature, is more diversified than physics. Only Darwin's theory of natural selection, or perhaps the discovery of the genetic code as revealed primarily through the work of Francis Crick, can qualify as profoundly unifying. Among other things, Mr. Dyson cites the theory of ''genetic drift'' of the Japanese geneticist Motoo Kimura, who believes that random statistical fluctuations in evolution have been more important than Darwinian selection. Mr. Dyson addresses a question I have always found puzzling: Why is life so complicated? If simple elegant solutions to problems are the best, then why does nature need go to the lengths she does in order to produce viable living structures such as ourselves? Mr. Dyson's answer lies in ''homeostatic systems'' - systems that maintain a constant local environment despite changing external conditions. He argues that homeostatic systems are a necessary prerequisite for life and that such systems are necessarily complicated, relying on diversity to maintain their equilibrium.</p>
        <p>He carries his preference for diversity to many nonscientific issues. He does not believe in world government as a feasible or even desirable aim as a means of avoiding global nuclear conflict, apparently preferring some form of widespread economic and moral re-evaluation to rid the world of its nuclear weapons. Nuclear weapons ''will be abolished as the missions for which they were designed come to seem unnecessary or absurd.'' ''Successful abolition becomes more realistic if it is understood that nuclear weapons are absurd rather than omnipotent.'' (Though I sympathize with his sentiments, such utopian hopes seem much less realistic than world government.) One might have expected that he would use his diversity-unity principle to provide unreserved arguments for the free market as opposed to a planned economy, but he chooses not to press this point. (Perhaps images of unbridled Thatcherism and Reaganomics do not entirely fit in with his visions of utopia.) But he is a strong believer in market forces and freedom for the individual, and does not fear the suffering caused to those who embark on unsuccessful ventures. He accepts the possibility that his own ideas may be part of nature's unsuccessful experiments, quoting William Blake: ''To be an Error and to be Cast out is part of God's Design.'' He is optimistic that individual enterprise and small, cheaply run projects can stand up to and be economically successful against large monolithic concerns.</p>
        <p>He applies this belief particularly to space research, arguing that the scientific values of missions in space have been more or less inversely proportional to their cost. He believes that it will be possible, in the dim but not too distant future, to use genetic engineering to design creatures that can exist and be self-supporting in space. Unabashed by the science fiction nature of such suggestions, he presents his ''scavenger turtle'' (with diamond-tipped teeth), ''energy tree'' and ''mining worm.'' His centerpiece is a one-kilogram spacecraft ''astrochicken,'' which will be ready to launch in 2016. It will not be built but grown by the use of genetic engineering, and it will depend on artificial intelligence and solar-electric propulsion for its operation. Accompanying it will be a ''Martian potato,'' a ''comet creeper'' and a ''space butterfly.'' He has a great faith in the value of artificial intelligence, but believes that human intelligence will ''remain far ahead . . . as far into the future as I can imagine.''</p>
        <p>And his imagination does indeed roam very far into the future. He believes that we will come to understand the nature of consciousness and make scientific use of this understanding: ''We will look at nature directly through the eyes of the elephant, the eagle and the whale. We will be able, through the magic of science, to feel in our own minds the pride of the peacock, the wrath of the lion.'' He believes that some form of intelligence, human or otherwise, will survive in the universe for all time and he asserts his clear preference for a universe that expands indefinitely rather than collapsing on itself to an all-consuming fiery end.</p>
        <p>His God is what he refers to as a Socinian God, not omnipotent, but growing with time, as the diversity and knowledge of the world increases. His God represents a third level of consciousness - the lowest being present in each particle as it makes ''quantum choices'' and the second, that which we experience in ourselves.</p>
        <p>Sometimes his writing has its elements of poetry. He describes the action of his own mind by this figure: ''a million butterfly brains working together in a human skull have the power to dream, to calculate, to see.'' Perhaps Mr. Dyson's display of ideas has, indeed, elements in common with his beloved butterfly - beautiful, intricate and something to be admired, but flitting delicately here and there. Moreover, Mr. Dyson's picture is not without paradox. Despite his avowed love of diversity, that he is himself a unifier is exemplified by his very striving to comprehend so much in terms of one unity-diversity polarity. Whether one sympathizes fully or partially with his grandiose and highly stimulating ideas - or even if one is of totally another mind - this is a book to be read, savored and appreciated.  ENZYMES AND NERVES</p>
        <p>The next hundred years will be a period of transition between the metal-and-silicon technology of today and the enzyme-and-nerve technology of tomorrow. . . . When I think of the space technology of tomorrow, I think of three concrete images. . . . First, the Martian potato, a succulent plant that lives deep underground, its roots penetrating layers of subterranean ice while its shoots gather carbon dioxide and sunlight on the surface under the protection of a self-generated greenhouse. Second, the comet creeper, a warm-blooded vine which spreads . . . over the surfaces of comets and keeps itself warm with super-insulating fur as soft as sable. Third, the space butterfly . . . acting as our agent in exploration and reconnaissance, carrying pollen and information from world to world just as terrestrial insects carry pollen from flower to flower. It is easy to dream of other inhabitants of the celestial zoo. . . . The Martian potato, the comet creeper and the space butterfly are merely symbols, intended, like the pictures in a medieval bestiary, to edify rather than to enlighten.  From ''Infinite in All Directions.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
