<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NOTABLE BOOKS OF THE YEAR</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="54" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="203748"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="CHRISTMAS BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DE173DF937A35751C1A96E948260" item-length="11100" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NOTABLE BOOKS OF THE YEAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: This list has been selected from books reviewed since the Christmas issue of December 1987. It suggests only high points in the main fields of reader interest and it does not include the titles chosen by the editors of The Book Review as the Best Books of 1988. Books are arranged alphabetically under subject headings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: This list has been selected from books reviewed since the Christmas issue of December 1987. It suggests only high points in the main fields of reader interest and it does not include the titles chosen by the editors of The Book Review as the Best Books of 1988. Books are arranged alphabetically under subject headings.</p>
        <p>This list has been selected from books reviewed since the Christmas issue of December 1987. It suggests only high points in the main fields of reader interest and it does not include the titles chosen by the editors of The Book Review as the Best Books of 1988. Books are arranged alphabetically under subject headings. Quoted comments are from The Book Review.  Autobiography &amp; Biography</p>
        <p>AFTER THE STROKE: A Journal. By May Sarton. (Norton, $16.95.) The latest in a series of journals by the novelist and poet records her struggle to regain health and strength after a serious illness. ''Living beside her in her illness . . . chastens and deepens the reader's spirit.''</p>
        <p>ALL THE RIGHT ENEMIES: The Life and Murder of Carlo Tresca. By Dorothy Gallagher. (Rutgers University, $24.95.) ''A first-class book, extraordinarily well researched,'' about the life and death of the Italian-born anarchist and newspaper editor.</p>
        <p>ANNA FREUD: A Biography. By Elisabeth Young-Bruehl. (Summit, $24.95.) ''A notable contribution to the burgeoning literature of psychoanalytic history, and a convincing portrait of a remarkable woman.''</p>
        <p>THE AUTOBIOGRAPHY OF ROY COHN. By Sidney Zion. (Lyle Stuart, $18.95.) Sidney Zion, a former New York Times reporter, was approached by Roy Cohn (who died in 1986) to help write his life story. This book about the chief counsel to Senator Joseph McCarthy ''should be read in tandem'' with ''Citizen Cohn'' by Nicholas von Hoffman.</p>
        <p>CAPOTE: A Biography. By Gerald Clarke. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $22.95.) An ''enthralling, novel-like biography'' of the writer ''in which nothing, nothing at all, was left out.''</p>
        <p>CHAUCER: His Life, His Works, His World. By Donald R. Howard. (Abrahams/Dutton, $29.95.) This life of the ''poet, courtier, soldier and diplomat'' offers ''much information and many pleasures.''</p>
        <p>CHEKHOV: A Spirit Set Free. By V. S. Pritchett. (Random House, $17.95.) ''This graceful, imaginative biography carries the mark of Chekhov's style. Mr. Pritchett approaches Chekhov's life . . . not through his plays, but through his short stories'' and ''argues persuasively that the heart of Chekhov is in these stories, and so is his life.''</p>
        <p>CITIZEN COHN. By Nicholas von Hoffman. (Doubleday, $19.95.) Nicholas von Hoffman ''set out to write an unauthorized biography and record the voices of all the players. . . . He seems alternately fascinated and repelled'' by Roy Cohn.</p>
        <p>DICKENS: A Biography. By Fred Kaplan. (Morrow, $24.95.) A ''scholarly and highly readable'' account of the life of the driven writer, ''who endlessly rewrites in his novels the few stories he has learned from the family Grand Guignol of his childhood.''</p>
        <p>ELIA KAZAN: A Life. By Elia Kazan. (Knopf, $24.95.) ''Relentless in self-revelation, introspection and confession,'' this life story of the director-author-actor is ''an indispensable account of American theater and film.''</p>
        <p>ELIOT'S NEW LIFE. By Lyndall Gordon. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $19.95.) The second part of the author's biography of the poet. '' 'Eliot's New Life' proposes to give us the pattern of Eliot's presence in the world - not merely the sum of his acts and observances.''</p>
        <p>THE FACTS: A Novelist's Autobiography. By Philip Roth. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $17.95.) ''A combined short novel, apologia pro vita sua, confession, exercise in nostalgia and reparation and informal reader's guide to the works of Philip Roth.''</p>
        <p>FREUD: A Life for Our Time. By Peter Gay. (Norton, $25.) A historian ''of considerable experience and great distinction'' has written a wide-ranging biography with ''a delightful freshness.''</p>
        <p>GREY IS THE COLOR OF HOPE. By Irina Ratushinskaya. Translated by Alyona Kojevnikov. (Knopf, $18.95.) ''This remarkable prose text is a memoir of the three and a half years . . . served in a work camp'' by the young Soviet poet.</p>
        <p>JEFFERSON AND MONTICELLO: The Biography of a Builder. By Jack McLaughlin. (Holt, $29.95.) An ''entrancing study of the bricks-and-mortar Thomas Jefferson'' that focuses on the third President's pursuit of the perfect home.</p>
        <p>THE LIFE OF LANGSTON HUGHES. Volume II, 1941-1967: I Dream a World. By Arnold Rampersad. (Oxford University, $24.95.) ''In his superlative study of Langston Hughes, the most prominent Afro-American poet of our century, Arnold Rampersad has performed that most difficult of feats: illuminating a man who, despite all his public visibility, was quite elusive.''</p>
        <p>MAKEBA: My Story. By Miriam Makeba with James Hall. (NAL/New American Library, $18.95.) The story of the South African singer ''underscore [ s ]  life lived as communal dialectic, a matter of African creative will set against bureaucratized repression.''</p>
        <p>MARY McCARTHY: A Life. By Carol Gelderman. (St. Martin's, $24.95.) ''A carefully researched, nicely paced and always readable work'' about the intellectual and author, written with the cooperation of the subject.</p>
        <p>MY CENTURY: The Odyssey of a Polish Intellectual. By Aleksander Wat. Edited and translated by Richard Lourie. Foreword by Czeslaw Milosz. (University of California, $35.) ''Aleksander Wat was a poet, and 'My Century' is a work of art - a rare thing for a book that is basically a sequence of reflections. And yet this text distinctly demands active reading.''</p>
        <p>NORA: The Real Life of Molly Bloom. By Brenda Maddox. (Houghton Mifflin, $24.95.) ''In this new and fascinating portrait'' of Nora Barnacle, wife of James Joyce, the author ''hold [ s ]  a torch for the wife of a 'funnominal' man for whom she was also that most miraculous amalgam - mother and muse.''</p>
        <p>OSCAR WILDE. By Richard Ellmann. (Knopf, $24.95.) The last 20 years of the author's life (he died in 1987) were spent ''uncovering new material and imagining Wilde's life artfully.'' This biography ''should give impetus to a view that Wilde was a writer of enormous significance and originality.''</p>
        <p>PRIVATE DEMONS: The Life of Shirley Jackson. By Judy Oppenheimer. (Putnam, $19.95.) The author, a former Washington Post reporter, has written a story of the novelist ''full of telling detail and illuminating anecdote. . . . Jackson emerges as a complex, gifted and tragic woman.''</p>
        <p>THE RAGMAN'S SON: An Autobiography. By Kirk Douglas. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $21.95.) ''The story of  [ the actor's ]  life is told with great candor and a healthy dose of self-deprecation.''</p>
        <p>REUNION: A Memoir. By Tom Hayden. (Random House, $22.50.) ''Mr. Hayden proved to be the single greatest figure of the 1960's student movement''; the author's look back ''is evocative, wordy, sometimes inconsistent. But what a story!''</p>
        <p>RODIN: A Biography. By Frederic V. Grunfeld. (Henry Holt, $35.) The author, who died in 1987, has written a ''free-flowing, well-orchestrated narrative'' of the life of the artist, who ''looms like a colossus over the world of sculpture at the turn of the present century.''</p>
        <p>SEAN O'CASEY: A Life. By Garry O'Connor. (Atheneum, $25.) This ''continuously interesting'' account of the playwright's life ''is informative and, where an occasion warrants severity, justly severe.''</p>
        <p>THE SECRET LIVES OF TREBITSCH LINCOLN. By Bernard Wasserstein. (Yale University, $27.50.) This life of an extraordinarily charming religious con man, written by a professor of history at Brandeis, ''is masterly, the model of a tale told most readably yet with no relaxation of scholarly standards.''</p>
        <p>THE STATUE WITHIN: An Autobiography. By Francois Jacob. Translated by Franklin Philip. (Basic, $22.95.) ''With this compelling story of a dramatic life,'' Francois Jacob, a winner of the 1965 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine, ''lays claim to being a first- rate writer as well as a major figure in contemporary molecular biology.''</p>
        <p>TILTING AT WINDMILLS: An Autobiography. By Charles Peters. (Addison-Wesley, $18.95.) The life story of the founder and editor of The Washington Monthly. ''The man who emerges from the pages of 'Tilting at Windmills' is an intensely human figure - passionate, opinionated, incurably restless and uncommonly creative.''</p>
        <p>A TIME OF CHANGE: A Reporter's Tale of Our Time. By Harrison E. Salisbury. (Cornelia and Michael Bessie/Harper &amp; Row, $19.95.) The memoirs of the former New York Times reporter are ''a lively and fascinating tale by a hard-working, exuberantly contentious journalist.''</p>
        <p>A TIME TO DANCE, NO TIME TO WEEP. By Rumer Godden. (Beech Tree/Morrow, $16.95.) The author of ''Black Narcissus'' and many other novels writes about the first 40 years of ''her astonishing life and times. She belongs in that small and exclusive club of women . . . who could do pretty well anything they set their minds to.''</p>
        <p>UNDER THE EYE OF THE CLOCK: The Life Story of Christopher Nolan. By Christopher Nolan. (St. Martin's, $16.95.) An ''extraordinary'' autobiography written by a young, severely disabled man ''blessed . . . with a radiant intelligence. . . . The story reads like an adventure, not a meditation.''</p>
        <p>WILLIAM F. BUCKLEY, JR.: Patron Saint of the Conservatives. By John B. Judis. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $22.95.) ''A solid and thoughtful biography'' of the acknowledged leader of America's conservatives.</p>
        <p>WINSTON S. CHURCHILL. Volume VIII: ''Never Despair,'' 1945-1965. By Martin Gilbert. (Houghton Mifflin, $40.) ''The eighth and final volume of the longest biography (9.2 million words) in the English language.'' The entire work is ''a stupendous achievement . . . of immense and permanent value.'' Children</p>
        <p>COMPANY'S COMING. By Arthur Yorinks. Illustrated by David Small. (Crown, $11.95.) Shirley has invited her relatives to dinner and Moe is tinkering in the backyard when a flying saucer lands. The hilarious dialogue in this storybook ''is as well timed as the best comedy act,'' and pen-and-ink illustrations capture the mayhem perfectly. (Ages 4 to 8)</p>
        <p>THE INCREDIBLE PAINTING OF FELIX CLOUSSEAU. Written and illustrated by Jon Agee. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $13.95.) Felix Clousseau's paintings come to life and create havoc in 19th-century Paris in a witty storybook with illustrations that make gray seem a dazzling color. (Ages 3 to 7)</p>
        <p>JOHN PATRICK NORMAN McHENNESSY: The Boy Who Was Always Late. Written and illustrated by John Burningham. (Crown, $12.95.) John Patrick Norman McHennessy is a little boy who faithfully ''sets off for school, traveling 'along the road to learn' '' and is waylaid by beasts and disaster. In this witty picture book, virtue triumphs. (Ages 4 to 7)</p>
        <p>LOOKING THE TIGER IN THE EYE: Confronting the Nuclear Threat. By Carl B. Feldbaum and Ronald J. Bee. (Harper &amp; Row, $14.95.) Two defense experts have written an admirably serious and clear history of the nuclear era, from the ''Trinity'' test in July 1945 to the present. (Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>ROUND BUILDINGS, SQUARE BUILDINGS, &amp; BUILDINGS THAT WIGGLE LIKE A FISH. By Philip M. Isaacson. (Knopf, $14.95.) The author sees buildings ''as beautiful objects and as pieces of social and cultural history'' and has written and taken the photographs for the best introductory book about architecture ''for either adults or children.'' (Ages 8 and up)</p>
        <p>SHAKA: King of the Zulus. Written by Diane Stanley and Peter Vennema. Illustrated by Diane Stanley. (Morrow Junior Books, $13.95.) This brilliantly illustrated storybook biography of the 19th-century African leader is also the history of ''the founding of a nation by a hero who was a scourge.'' (Ages 7 to 10)</p>
        <p>SPINKY SULKS. Written and illustrated by William Steig. (Michael di Capua/Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $13.95.) Something sets Spinky off and he has ''a world-class sulk,'' spending three days out on the lawn. Glorious, insightful, comic and wise. (Ages 3 and up)</p>
        <p>TAIL FEATHERS FROM MOTHER GOOSE: The Opie Rhyme Book. Edited by Iona Opie. (Little, Brown, $19.95.) A selection of verses - ''cordials and simples'' - from the Opie Collection of Children's Literature, illustrated with distinction by 62 artists, most of them British. (All ages)</p>
        <p>YONDER. By Tony Johnston. Illustrated by Lloyd Bloom. (Dial, $12.95.) Among the themes in this ''soothing, rhythmic'' picture book are ''life, death and the seasonal growth of a plum tree.'' The text is a simple and affecting verse that lingers in the reader's memory, as do the rosy illustrations. (Ages 4 to 8)  Crime</p>
        <p>BLACK HEARTS AND SLOW DANCING. By Earl W. Emerson. (Morrow, $17.95.) A small-town fireman filling in as temporary chief of police investigates a murder that involves the Seattle Fire Department. ''This is an expert, readable job with a likable hero.''</p>
        <p>BLOOD SHOT. By Sara Paretsky. (Delacorte, $17.95.) The hotshot private eye V. I. Warshawski is back in south Chicago for her high school reunion and on the trail of corporate villains. Sara Paretsky ''does her best and boldest work to date in creating a criminal investigation that is a genuine heroic quest.''</p>
        <p>DOWNRIVER. By Loren D. Estleman. (Houghton Mifflin, $15.95.) The Detroit private investigator Amos Walker is back, this time working for a client who says he was framed for murder. ''At his best Mr. Estleman is one of the major current practitioners of the tough- guy private-eye novel, and he is at his best here.''</p>
        <p>''E'' IS FOR EVIDENCE. By Sue Grafton. (Holt, $15.95.) Kinsey Millhone, a private detective in California, finds herself the apparent target of an elaborate frame-up. The plot ''keeps us turning pages and serves as a vehicle for the really interesting stuff, an unveiling of the characters' foibles by the worldly-wise but uncorrupt private eye. And this is where Sue Grafton shines.''</p>
        <p>MICHIGAN ROLL. By Tom Kakonis. (St. Martin's, $16.95.) A ''terrific'' first novel about a professional gambler who ''gets caught up in a grim cat-and-mouse game with two of the creepiest contract killers ever to put a man's hand down a garbage disposal.''</p>
        <p>THE NINTH CIRCLE. By N. J. Crisp. (Viking, $17.95.) Everyone is suspect in this deftly written thriller about moles, traitors and a British secret agent. ''The author keeps the physical action to a minimum, but when action is called for, it can be hair-raising.''</p>
        <p>ORDINARY MURDER. By Don Flynn. (Walker, $16.95.) A New York newspaperman looks into the murder of a friend's son in this ''very amusing'' novel. ''It is sophisticated, lively and as fast-moving as hurdlers off the starting block.''</p>
        <p>SAINT MIKE. By Jerry Oster. (Harper &amp; Row, $15.95.) A Federal narcotics agent whose husband, also an agent, has been killed in the line of duty infiltrates the top echelons of the drug culture. ''Mr. Oster is a superior writer and a wonderful storyteller.''</p>
        <p>SHAKEDOWN. By Gerald Petievich. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $16.95.) This ''absolutely superior piece of work'' by a former Treasury Department agent opposes an F.B.I. man and a Las Vegas mobster. '' 'Shakedown' is exciting, tough and gritty.''</p>
        <p>A THIEF OF TIME. By Tony Hillerman. (Harper &amp; Row, $15.95.) Lieut. Joe Leaphorn and Officer Jim Chee of the Navajo Tribal Police return in ''a skillful, provocative novel'' about ''a place and a people unlike any other.'' Tony Hillerman has a ''masterly way of telling a rousing story.''  Current Affairs &amp; Social Comment</p>
        <p>BANANA DIPLOMACY: The Making of American Policy in Nicaragua 1981-1987. By Roy Gutman. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $19.95.) This book, which ''offers a close-up portrait of the unending battles between Administration hard-liners and pragmatists over what to do about the Sandinista revolution . . . is, in fact, superb journalism.''</p>
        <p>BEHIND THE VEIL OF ECONOMICS: Essays in the Worldly Philosophy. By Robert L. Heilbroner. (Norton, $17.95.) A collection of essays ''rich in argument, in clear and provocative presentation of complicated issues, and . . . delightfully quotable.''</p>
        <p>BORROWED TIME: An AIDS Memoir. By Paul Monette. (Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, $18.95.) The author, a novelist and screenwriter, records the 19 months prior to his lover's death from AIDS. ''Mr. Monette has etched a magnificent monument to his lover's bravery, their commitment to each other and the plague of hatred and ignorance they had to endure.''</p>
        <p>BROTHERS: Black and Poor - A True Story of Courage and Survival. By Sylvester Monroe and Peter Goldman. With Vern E. Smith, Terry E. Johnson, Monroe Anderson and Jacques Chenet. (Newsweek/Morrow, $18.95.) A look at 12 black men who grew up poor on Chicago's South Side and the varied, often depressing paths their lives took. ''Society put  [ these men ]  in a box. Their fears keep them there. Only a fortunate few get out. . . . In 'Brothers' we come to understand why so few make it.''</p>
        <p>BUYING INTO AMERICA: How Foreign Money Is Changing the Face of Our Nation. By Martin and Susan Tolchin. (Times Books, $19.95.) The authors ''pack into this book an astonishing amount of information about just how much of America is being bought, and by whom.''</p>
        <p>BY SILENCE BETRAYED: Sexual Abuse of Children in America. By John Crewdson. (Little, Brown, $17.95.) ''A work that is stunning in its statement of the facts and unrelenting in its attacks on our myths'' about the abuse of children.</p>
        <p>CAN SOMEBODY SHOUT AMEN! By Patsy Sims. (Thomas Dunne/St. Martin's, $15.95.) ''Written without condescension, or sensationalism,'' the author's examination of small-town evangelists allows ''the timid yet curious reader to venture into the tents and tabernacles where revivals are under way.''</p>
        <p>CHILE: Death in the South. By Jacobo Timerman. Translated by Robert Cox. (Knopf, $15.95.) The author, ''a man of restless, passionate intelligence,'' reassesses the death of Chilean democracy and ''reminds us of the substratum of brutality on which the calm and order of Augosto Pinochet's Chile rests.''</p>
        <p>CLAIMING THE HEAVENS: The New York Times Complete Guide to the Star Wars Debate. By Philip M. Boffey, William J. Broad, Leslie H. Gelb, Charles Mohr and Holcomb B. Noble. (Times Books, $17.95.) An expansion of the New York Times series on the Strategic Defense Initiative, which won a 1986 Pulitzer Prize. '' 'Claiming the Heavens,' with a fairness that is admirable, competently exposes  [ S.D.I.'s ]  pitfalls.''</p>
        <p>DANGEROUS DOSSIERS: Exposing the Secret War Against America's Greatest Authors. By Herbert Mitgang. (Donald I. Fine, $18.95.) The New York Times cultural correspondent presents ''summaries of the F.B.I. files of some 35 American writers. . . . The existence of these indictments raises yet again the question of what the F.B.I. understands by 'freedom of thought.' ''</p>
        <p>A DEADLY SILENCE. The Ordeal of Cheryl Pierson: A Case of Incest and Murder. By Dena Kleiman. (Atlantic Monthly Press, $19.95.) ''With care, intensity and a novelist's sense,'' a New York Times reporter tells the story of a Long Island teen-ager, a victim of incest, who hired a classmate to murder her father.</p>
        <p>DISCOS AND DEMOCRACY: China in the Throes of Reform. By Orville Schell. (Pantheon, $19.95.) The author ''has written a chronicle  [ that ]  is nothing if not exhaustive.'' Mr. Schell, ''a master compiler and condenser,'' likes ''his China to be echt, unpolluted by the stuff he sees enough of back home.''</p>
        <p>THE ESSENTIAL GESTURE: Writing, Politics and Places. By Nadine Gordimer. Edited by Stephen Clingman. (Knopf, $19.95.) The author, an ''internationally renowned and acclaimed novelist and short-story writer'' who lives in South Africa, delineates ''the regime that she so tellingly describes as a 'pact of capitalism and racism' '' in ''this stimulating and timely collection of essays, articles and speeches.''</p>
        <p>ISRAEL'S FATEFUL HOUR. By Yehoshafat Harkabi. Translated by Lenn Schramm. (Harper &amp; Row, $22.50.) The author's ''thundering statement'' on the options faced by Israel in the Middle East conflict is ''a cogent policy analysis and prescription that is part politics, part religion. . . . It is the sort of book that is usually not read seriously enough until it is much too late.''</p>
        <p>LANDSLIDE: The Unmaking of the President, 1984-1988. By Jane Mayer and Doyle McManus. (Houghton Mifflin, $21.95.) ''Full of rich anecdote and telling detail,  [ the ]  most striking result of the authors' reporting is their portrait of the President as an astoundingly uninvolved figure with little interest in the business of government.''</p>
        <p>LAST DAYS OF THE SICILIANS. At War With the Mafia: The FBI Assault on the Pizza Connection. By Ralph Blumenthal. (Times Books, $18.95.) A New York Times reporter's investigation of the infamous heroin-smuggling case. ''A reader looking for a mob adventure tale'' will find that this one unfolds with a ''narrative drive''</p>
        <p>''more in accordance with human than legal logic.''</p>
        <p>LIFTOFF: The Story of America's Adventure in Space. By Michael Collins. (Grove, $25.) ''An informal history of the United States space program'' by one of ''perhaps two astronauts who qualify as writers.''</p>
        <p>THE MASTER OF THE GAME: Paul Nitze and the Nuclear Peace. By Strobe Talbott. (Knopf, $19.95.) The arms control negotiator Paul Nitze is the hero who emerges in ''this valuable potted history of the nuclear age'' by a senior correspondent for Time magazine who combines ''a gift for characterization and an eye for the revealing anecdote with a firm grasp of his subject.'' For later historians, ''this will be a standard text.''</p>
        <p>MEXAMERICA: Two Countries, One Future. By Lester D. Langley. (Crown, $19.95.) ''Drawing on his own childhood contact with Mexican-Americans,'' Lester D. Langley, a historian, ''gives us a sensitive and complex portrait'' of ''the cultural and psychic differences that have made the Hispanic experience in America so problematic.''</p>
        <p>MRS. THATCHER'S REVOLUTION: The Ending of the Socialist Era. By Peter Jenkins. (Harvard University, $25.) An ''ambitious enterprise, tantamount to a political history of Britain over the past 10 years. . . . Mr. Jenkins is a master of the shrewd political judgment.''</p>
        <p>NUCLEAR FEAR: A History of Images. By Spencer R. Weart. (Harvard University, $29.50.) ''A good and useful book'' about the ways in which ''Americans have responded to the new world of nuclear energy and its militarization. . . . This is a true history of our age -a cutting, indispensable, deeply troubling book.''</p>
        <p>A PLACE IN THE NEWS: From the Women's Pages to the Front Page. By Kay Mills. (Dodd, Mead, $19.95.) ''The history of women's emancipation from the style and society ghettos'' of American journalism is traced in ''an anecdotal account of our changing folkways in journalism.''</p>
        <p>POOR SUPPORT: Poverty in the American Family. By David T. Ellwood. (Basic, $19.95.) The author ''argues persuasively that although poverty is not a disease caused by a flawed welfare system, a major overhaul of our social-spending policies could go a long way toward curing it.''</p>
        <p>THE POWER GAME: How Washington Works. By Hedrick Smith. (Random House, $22.50.) With his portrayal of the ''hundreds, even thousands'' of power centers in the nation's capital, the former Washington correspondent for The New York Times Magazine ''effectively and at times brilliantly describes'' a ''clumsy, fragmented, untidy political world.''</p>
        <p>RACHEL AND HER CHILDREN: Homeless Families in America. By Jonathan Kozol. (Crown, $16.95.) The author takes on the crisis of America's homeless families in a book that ''is passionate and often unbearably moving.''</p>
        <p>SANCTUARY: A Story of American Conscience and the Law in Collision. By Ann Crittenden. (Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson, $21.95.) A ''compelling . . . account of the movement'' by Arizona church leaders to shelter Central American refugees in defiance of Federal law.</p>
        <p>A SEASON FOR HEALING: Reflections on the Holocaust. By Anne Roiphe. (Summit, $17.95.) A discussion of ''the Jewish response to the Holocaust in the post-Holocaust world.'' The issues the author addresses ''are unquestionably important, and the consequences of the Holocaust, still unfolding, are obviously large.''</p>
        <p>SECRETS OF THE TEMPLE: How the Federal Reserve Runs the Country. By William Greider. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $24.95.) ''With breathtaking energy and research,'' the author - a national affairs writer for Rolling Stone magazine - cracks the code of the independent institution that ''decide [ s ]  the largest questions of the political economy, including who shall prosper and who shall fail.''</p>
        <p>THE SHAH'S LAST RIDE: The Fate of an Ally. By William Shawcross. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $19.95.) ''A riveting account of the Shah's political and medical fate. . . . The story that Mr. Shawcross tells is sad and compelling.''</p>
        <p>THE SPY WHO GOT AWAY: The Inside Story of Edward Lee Howard, the CIA Agent Who Betrayed His Country's Secrets and Escaped to Moscow. By David Wise. (Random House, $18.95.) This ''version of the events pertaining to a young C.I.A. undercover agent . . . is as good as we can expect to get'' and leaves the reader ''in helpless rage at the arrogance and apparent incompetence of our homegrown spymasters.''</p>
        <p>UNDERSTANDING THE NEW ECONOMY. By Alfred L. Malabre Jr. (Dow Jones-Irwin, $19.95.) The author ''is the ideal guide for an expediton into the hostile wilderness of economics: he is expert but not arrogant; he knows the forest from the trees; he can converse with the natives in their language and translate into ours.''</p>
        <p>WE ARE NOT AFRAID: The Story of Goodman, Schwerner, and Chaney and the Civil Rights Campaign for Mississippi. By Seth Cagin and Philip Dray. (Macmillan, $22.50.) This book ''stirs anger and tears with a dramatic recounting'' of the murder of three civil rights workers in Neshoba County, Miss., in 1964.</p>
        <p>WILD BLUE YONDER: Money, Politics, and the B-1 Bomber. By Nick Kotz. (Pantheon, $19.95.) ''A masterly story of the failed attempts by America's finest engineers and Air Force strategists to design, sell, build and deploy a state-of-the-art bomber.''</p>
        <p>THE YELLOW WIND. By David Grossman. Translated by Haim Watzman. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $17.95.) An Israeli novelist records the thoughts and feelings of Palestinians living in the occupied West Bank. ''Even the most cautious readers - and even the most hostile - are bound to learn something about the conflict . . . deep and achingly, damningly, true.''  Essays, Letters &amp; Criticism</p>
        <p>THE ART OF THE NOVEL. By Milan Kundera. Translated by Linda Asher. (Grove, $16.95.) The first book of nonfiction from the Eastern European novelist describes ''with singular instructiveness . . . why novels are and should be written at all.''</p>
        <p>BENEATH THE AMERICAN RENAISSANCE: The Subversive Imagination in the Age of Emerson and Melville. By David S. Reynolds. (Knopf, $35.) ''A vigorous, sometimes exasperating exercise in what  [ the author ]  calls 'reconstructive criticism.' '' David Reynolds ''argues that the major authors  [ of 19th-century American literature ]  were not . . . alienated from popular culture, only from its polite expression.''</p>
        <p>BERNARD SHAW: Collected Letters, 1926-1950. Edited by Dan H. Laurence. (Viking, $45.) The last of four ''superbly edited'' volumes of correspondence by a man who ''was interested in everything.''</p>
        <p>''There is certainly God's plenty, not just plenty of pages, but plenty of topics treated with plentiful, staggering intelligence and wit.''</p>
        <p>THE DROWNED AND THE SAVED. By Primo Levi. Translated by Raymond Rosenthal. (Summit, $17.95.) This collection of essays, published after the author's death in 1987, is ''a precious footnote - a series of ripe meditations about the experience of Auschwitz,'' written ''with a purity of spirit for which we can only feel grateful.''</p>
        <p>LETTERS AND DRAWINGS OF BRUNO SCHULZ: With Selected Prose. Edited by Jerzy Ficowski. Translated by Walter Arndt with Victoria Nelson. (Harper &amp; Row, $25.) ''A book of remnants - a scrapbook of . . . drawings, letters and uncollected prose pieces'' by the Polish writer and critic, who was murdered in 1942.</p>
        <p>THE LETTERS OF T. S. ELIOT: Volume I, 1898-1922. Edited by Valerie Eliot. (Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, $29.95.) ''Though the book abounds in sharp detail, it's not by our thirst for information that we're drawn to its 600-odd pages. It's by our fascination with the complex, introspective young man living through what Eliot lived through.''</p>
        <p>NO MAN'S LAND: The Place of the Woman Writer in the Twentieth Century. Volume I: The War of the Words. By Sandra M. Gilbert and Susan Gubar. (Yale, $22.95.) ''With intelligence, daring and feeling,'' the authors of ''The Madwoman in the Attic'' examine the emergence of modernism and ''document a war on women's words.''</p>
        <p>SELECTED LETTERS OF EUGENE O'NEILL. Edited by Travis Bogard and Jackson R. Bryer. (Yale University, $35.) A collection of almost 600 of the playwright's letters. ''These letters are essential to any understanding of Eugene O'Neill, if only because they demystify him.''</p>
        <p>SELECTED LETTERS OF VIRGIL THOMSON. Edited by Tim Page and Vanessa Weeks Page. (Summit, $24.95.) A music critic and a freelance writer assemble several hundred letters by the composer and critic. ''Mr. Thomson's is a mind of unvarnished directness. . . .  [ He is ]  an accomplished and principled author as well.''</p>
        <p>UNSENT LETTERS: Irreverent Notes from a Literary Life. By Malcolm Bradbury. (Viking, $16.95.) A ''collection of memoirs masquerading as a collection of disconnected, satiric essays'' in which ''Mr. Bradbury's often hilarious wittiness remains.''</p>
        <p>WEBSTERS' FIRST NEW INTERGALACTIC WICKEDARY OF THE ENGLISH LANGUAGE. By Mary Daly with Jane Caputi. (Beacon, $35.) A ''howlingly funny book'' by the feminist, theologian and poet that proposes ''a linguistic revolution that will release the buried archaic meaning of words and . . . create a vivid awareness of the world as women see it.''</p>
        <p>A WRITER'S AMERICA: Landscape in Literature. By Alfred Kazin. (Knopf, $24.95.) '' 'A Writer's America' contributes significantly to the literature of conservation by showing that America destroys its culture as it destroys its landscape.'' Fiction</p>
        <p>ANTHILLS OF THE SAVANNAH. By Chinua Achebe. (Anchor/Doubleday, $16.95.) The Nigerian author's first novel in more than 20 years, set in an imaginary West African state, reveals ''a writer who . . . is gloriously gifted with the magic of an ebullient, generous, great talent.''</p>
        <p>THE ANTIPEOPLE. By Sony Labou Tansi. Translated by J. A. Underwood. (Marion Boyars/Kampmann, $18.95.) The story of a Zairian school principal and his eventual ruin. ''Dadou's falling star touches off some powerful lights on its path to oblivion. It is these lights that constitute the essential beauty of this novel, illuminating the truth . . . about Africa as a whole.''</p>
        <p>ANYTHING FOR BILLY By Larry McMurtry. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $18.95.) The author of ''Lonesome Dove'' takes on Billy the Kid. ''Larry McMurtry may be a great writer. . . . When a writer is as good as Mr. McMurtry is, even a relatively minor book is a major event.''</p>
        <p>THE ARK SAKURA. By Kobo Abe. Translated by Juliet Winters Carpenter. (Knopf, $18.95.) ''A large, ambitious work'' by a Japanese novelist of international reputation ''about the lives of outcasts in modern Japan'' that is ''grim and impressive, sickening and memorable.''</p>
        <p>THE ASSIGNATION. By Joyce Carol Oates. (Ecco, $16.95.) A collection of ''fugivite pieces . . . a famous writer's occasional writings and ephemera,'' infused with a ''radiant intensity.''</p>
        <p>BAD BEHAVIOR. By Mary Gaitskill. (Poseidon, $15.95.) A first collection of short stories, most of them set in New York City, by ''a vital and gifted new writer.''</p>
        <p>THE BEAN TREES. By Barbara Kingsolver. (Harper &amp; Row, $16.95.) ''An accomplished first novel'' about the daughter of a cleaning woman and the girl's escape from poverty and small-town life that ''contains more good writing than most successful careers.''</p>
        <p>THE BEAUTIFUL ROOM IS EMPTY. By Edmund White. (Knopf, $17.95.) The success of this novel ''lies in establishing two contradictory truths: gay men are very much like straight men; and gay men and straight men are fundamentally different.  [ The author ]  does so by the meticulous reconstruction of the very texture of his sexuality.''</p>
        <p>BE-BOP, RE-BOP. By Xam Wilson Cartier. (Available/Ballantine, Paper, $4.95.) ''Jazz informs the style as well as the subject'' of this first novel about a black woman's childhood and adolescence, which demonstrates ''the deep connections between music and narrative.''</p>
        <p>BLACK BOX. By Amos Oz. Translated by Nicholas de Lange with the author. (Helen &amp; Kurt Wolff/Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, $19.95.) ''One of Israel's foremost novelists,'' Mr. Oz has ''no reason to fulfill  [ the ]  comfortable expectations we have for novels. His voice is rich, passionate, committed.''</p>
        <p>THE BOOK AND THE BROTHERHOOD. By Iris Murdoch. (Viking, $19.95.) The writer's 23d novel, set in contemporary England, is ''that rarest of fictions these days: a social and political novel that is not journalistic. . . . The book is finally a triumphal celebration of literacy as a social bond.''</p>
        <p>BORN BROTHERS. By Larry Woiwode. (Michael di Capua/Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $19.95.) ''A serious novel'' about family ''written in a strong and lyrical voice.''</p>
        <p>BREAKING GENTLE. By Beverly Lowry. (Viking, $17.95.) In its portrayal of a Texas family, the author's fifth novel ''has delicately and inventively enacted the ambiguous possibilities of its title, while displaying itself as a strong and graceful performance.''</p>
        <p>BREATHING LESSONS. By Anne Tyler. (Knopf, $18.95.) The novelist returns to her preoccupation with family life in this story of a Baltimore wife and mother. ''Anne Tyler . . . is blessedly prolific and graced with an effortless-seeming talent at describing whole rafts of intricately individualized people.''</p>
        <p>THE CAPTAIN AND THE ENEMY. By Graham Greene. (Viking, $17.95.) ''In this short, skillful book we enter those disparate worlds Mr. Greene has made his own - the England of 'Brighton Rock' and 'Ministry of Fear,' and the exotic Central American territories in which his restless talent has so often roamed.''</p>
        <p>CHATTERTON. By Peter Ackroyd. (Grove, $17.95.) In four ''elaborately interlinked'' tales about the 18th-century poet, the author constructs a ''superb'' and ''wonderfully vivid book, continuously at home in its many lives.''</p>
        <p>THE COMING TRIUMPH OF THE FREE WORLD. By Rick DeMarinis. (Viking, $19.95.) A collection of stories that is ''consistent, original, seductive and delightfully sad.''</p>
        <p>CURFEW. By Jose Donoso. Translated by Alfred MacAdam. (Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson, $18.95.) ''The exile's return to his native land is the subject of some of the best writing from Latin America. . . .  [ The author ]  has created a small masterpiece in the familiar genre.''</p>
        <p>THE DEATH OF METHUSELAH: And Other Stories. By Isaac Bashevis Singer. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $17.95.) ''This cunning, pungent new collection of stories . . . adds a characteristic twist to the materials of a long career.''</p>
        <p>EMPEROR OF THE AIR. By Ethan Canin. (Houghton Mifflin, $15.95.) Not all of the nine stories in this first collection are successful, ''yet one comes away from reading the best of them with the refreshing sense of having encountered a writer devoted to his craft.''</p>
        <p>EMPIRE OF THE SENSELESS. By Kathy Acker. (Grove, $17.95.) ''A difficult and upsetting novel, one that insults and may even injure its readers. But they will not be disappointed by it.''</p>
        <p>FAIR AND TENDER LADIES. By Lee Smith. (Putnam, $17.95.) The life of a Virginia mountain woman. ''Readers will be sorry when this literate, intelligent, insightful and entertaining novel draws to a close. It is as true to life as the high, sweet sounds of mountain music in a gathering dusk.''</p>
        <p>A FAR CRY FROM KENSINGTON. By Muriel Spark. (Houghton Mifflin, $17.95.) Set in a London rooming house in the mid-50's, Mrs. Spark's 18th novel ''follows the rules of art right down the line and illuminates the human condition, etc. But it also meets a trickier challenge, that of being superb entertainment.''</p>
        <p>THE FIFTH CHILD. By Doris Lessing. (Knopf, $16.95.) The author's 35th book deals ''in her customary forthright fashion with our flawed and crumbling social fabric.'' The tale of a ''monster-child born to  [ a ]  nice normal British couple'' is ''a moral fable.''</p>
        <p>FIREFLY SUMMER. By Maeve Binchy. (Delacorte, $19.95.) This saga of a large Irish family ''is a fine treat for . . . any season.''</p>
        <p>THE FLOATPLANE NOTEBOOKS. By Clyde Edgerton. (Algonquin Books of Chapel Hill, $16.95.) The author's third novel ''is warmly humorous, gossipy and rich - a book with the soul of a family reunion.''</p>
        <p>FREAKY DEAKY. By Elmore Leonard. (Arbor House/Morrow, $18.95.) Cops, drug dealers and student revolutionaries from the 1960's collide in Elmore Leonard's ''spectacular'' novel. ''The plot of 'Freaky Deaky' races along, constantly changing course and doubling back on itself.''</p>
        <p>GOOD HEARTS. By Reynolds Price. (Atheneum, $18.95.) This novel about a long-married couple ''is superb storytelling by an enduring craftsman . . . a study of life and the placement of individuals within life.''</p>
        <p>THE HEARTS AND LIVES OF MEN. By Fay Weldon. (Viking, $18.95.) In this ''full-blown commentary of delicious wit and wisdom on the follies of our time,'' Fay Weldon shows herself to be ''a brave writer who . . . can address her reader directly and assume the role of storyteller.''</p>
        <p>THE HEAT DEATH OF THE UNIVERSE: And Other Stories. By Pamela Zoline. (McPherson, Cloth, $20; Paper, $10.) A ''defiant, dazzling first collection . . . that revitalizes the labels 'post-modern' and 'feminist.' ''</p>
        <p>HE GOT HUNGRY AND FORGOT HIS MANNERS: A Fable. By Jimmy Breslin. (Ticknor &amp; Fields, $17.95.) An ''astringent'' novel by the newspaper columnist about wealth and poverty in New York, ''written with verve and laced with a fine rage.''</p>
        <p>HERB 'N' LORNA: A Love Story. By Eric Kraft. (Crown, $17.95.) The continuing saga of the author's protagonist Peter Leroy, this novel is ''a historical farce . . . as graceful, complicated and exhilarating as a quadrille.''</p>
        <p>HER OWN TERMS. By Judith Grossman. (Soho, $16.95.) This first novel about a ''bright, ambitious woman'' growing up and going to Oxford in the 50's and early 60's is ''far better than the dramatic opening suggests it might be, far more ambitious, more serious.''</p>
        <p>THE HIGH ROAD. By Edna O'Brien. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $18.95.) In this novel focused on ''expatriate and vacationing northern Europeans on a Spanish island,'' the author's ''rich prose is laid on the surface of her narrative like the flourishes of technical brilliance that fade last when the vision of an age begins to slide away.''</p>
        <p>THE IMMORTAL BARTFUSS. By Aharon Appelfeld. Translated by Jeffrey M. Green. (Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson, $15.95.) The Israeli novelist ''creates a spiritual portrait of a man who survived the Holocaust and now resides in Israel. . . . Mr. Appelfeld . . . offers an extraordinary adventure in character portrayal.''</p>
        <p>JACK OF DIAMONDS: And Other Stories. By Elizabeth Spencer. (Viking, $15.95.) Short stories by ''a Southern writer who doesn't always write about the South. . . . Far from nostalgic,  [ these stories ]  treat the past as the actual substance of which the present and future are made, a quality that permits them to convey not only lyric moments of experience but the quality of entire lives.''</p>
        <p>KISSES OF THE ENEMY. By Rodney Hall. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $19.95.) The noted Austrialian writer ''has turned his extravagant imagination to a very different world and time, leaping across the century to the 1990's. . . . Shuttling between fantasy and grim realism, Mr. Hall projects a shocking picture of his country's future in a high-flying mixture of farce and fury.''</p>
        <p>KRAZY KAT: A Novel in Five Panels. By Jay Cantor. (Knopf, $16.95.) ''How can an innocent albeit hedonistic Kat like Krazy go on being a professional ditz in an age of nuclear anxieties? Despondent Krazy's answer is that she can't.'' This novel-cum-homage to the comic-strip character is ''sprightly, delightful and insightful.''</p>
        <p>LABRADOR. By Kathryn Davis. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $17.95.) ''A brief, passionate novel'' about two sisters growing up in 1950's New England. ''Kathryn Davis has taken the sad and binding stuff of many a first novel . . . and fashioned genuinely new embodiments for it.''</p>
        <p>THE LAST TO GO: A Family Chronicle. By Rand Richards Cooper. (Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, $16.95.) This first novel, which ''spans nearly 30 years of change within one family,'' is ''a wonderful book to read.''</p>
        <p>THE LETTER LEFT TO ME. By Joseph McElroy. (Knopf, $16.95.) ''By the end, this strange narrative has become a true interior oddyssey - an accounting, after loss, of what is left. . . . Mr. McElroy seems to have released a private mystery into the realm of universal quest.''</p>
        <p>MAMA DAY. By Gloria Naylor. (Ticknor &amp; Fields, $17.95.) ''A big, strong, dense, admirable novel'' about a ''wise, crotchety, comforting'' old woman and her family on the ''wondrous island'' of Willow Springs.</p>
        <p>MEMORIES OF AMNESIA. By Lawrence Shainberg. (Paris Review/British American Publishing, $16.95.) ''A great deal of the charm of  [ this ]  curious novel . . . lies in the arcana of the neurosurgeon's technical life, and a great deal in the witty metaphysics of the narrator. It is a novel in which a consciousness reports on its own deterioration.''</p>
        <p>THE MIDDLEMAN: And Other Stories. By Bharati Mukherjee. ''On one level . . . a consummated romance with the American language,'' this affecting collection of stories by an Indian immigrant writer ''is also a romance with America itself, its infinitely possible geography, its license, sexiness and violence.''</p>
        <p>MIDNIGHT SWEETS. By Bette Pesetsky. (Atheneum, $17.95.) ''If it's possible to create a novel whose structure is based on cookies,  [ the author has ]  done it. . . . Her story is nothing less than a parable of the life of the female artist as she moves from the private domestic realm into the public world, where art translates into commerce.''</p>
        <p>THE MYSTERIES OF PITTSBURGH. By Michael Chabon. (Morrow, $16.95.) A first novel about coming of age by ''a talented young writer'' whose ''control over  [ the ]  story is often astonishing.''</p>
        <p>NELLY'S VERSION. By Eva Figes. (Pantheon, Paper, $8.95.) ''The account of a woman who has so bowed to male views of what she should be that she has lost her own identity,'' this novel, first published in Britain in 1977, is ''engrossing.''</p>
        <p>OF SUCH SMALL DIFFERENCES. By Joanne Greenberg. (Holt, $18.95.) An ''affecting'' novel about a deaf and blind man that ''calls attention to the slow, painful movement that charts our struggles from isolation toward connectedness.''</p>
        <p>OSCAR &amp; LUCINDA. By Peter Carey. (Harper &amp; Row, $18.95.) This third novel by the Australian writer has ''that magnificent vitality, that ebullient delight in character, detail and language that turns a novel into an important book.''</p>
        <p>PAINTED TURTLE: Woman With Guitar. By Clarence Major. (Sun &amp; Moon Press, $14.95.) ''A fresh tale of the spiritually transforming power of love told without sanctimony or sentimentality.''</p>
        <p>PARIS TROUT. By Pete Dexter. (Random House, $17.95.) In his story of a racist store owner and the small Southern town that shields him, the author ''remind [ s ]  us, with lucidity and stinging frankness, the lengths to which we will go to deny our own racism.''</p>
        <p>THE PLACE IN FLOWERS WHERE POLLEN RESTS. By Paul West. (Doubleday, $19.95.) ''A remarkably ambitious and troubling work, one that fully supports the idea . . . that  [ the author's ]  is one of the most original talents in American fiction.''</p>
        <p>THE PREACHER'S BOY. By Terry Pringle. (Algonquin Books of Chapel Hill, $15.95.) ''Laughter is what the author . . . intends as the answer to parent-child conflicts'' in this first novel about a preacher's son and his adolescent desires.</p>
        <p>PUSHKIN HOUSE. By Andrei Bitov. Translated by Susan Brownsberger. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $22.50.) At once ''a complaint about . . . contemporary Russian life'' and ''a treatise on fiction,'' this novel, ''full of fiery intelligence,'' is ''a work of formidable complexity.''</p>
        <p>QUINN'S BOOK. By William Kennedy. (Viking, $18.95.) ''Large-minded, ardent, alive on every page with its author's passion for his place and the events that made it,'' this story of 19th-century Albany ''is a novel to savor.''</p>
        <p>REAL ESTATE. By Jane DeLynn. (Poseidon, $17.95.) Jane DeLynn's second novel is ''an on-target, wickedly funny tale of musical apartments, malfunctioning appliances and misplaced passions'' in the New York of the 80's.</p>
        <p>S. By John Updike. (Knopf, $17.95.) An epistolary novel about a middle-aged woman, Sarah, and her search for self-fulfillment. ''Sarah is like a review of a certain kind of contemporary woman.''</p>
        <p>SELECTED STORIES. By Andre Dubus. (Godine, $22.50) The author, ''a quietly appreciated literary presence for over 20 years,'' has assembled a group of stories that ''in its reaches of sympathy, as well as in its resolute plainness . . . has a certain daring.''</p>
        <p>SHINE HAWK. By Charlie Smith. (Paris Review/British American Publishing, $17.95.) ''A rich, fatiguing novel about 'rich fatigue' '' set in the author's native Georgia.</p>
        <p>THE SILENCE IN THE GARDEN. By William Trevor. (Viking, $17.95.) ''The reader feels as if she's flitting along slightly above a very good story, or several, and only the shrewdest management of the novel's underlying tensions averts disaster.''</p>
        <p>SNAP. By Abby Frucht. (Ticknor &amp; Fields, $17.95.) This first novel by the author of the short-story collection ''Fruit of the Month'' is ''very strange . . . but in an enchanting and edifying way. . . . In addition to the book's structural muscle, the writing itself is packed with detail, insight, images.''</p>
        <p>SOFT WATER. By Robert Olmstead. (Vintage, Paper, $6.95.) The first novel from a writer with a collection of short stories to his credit is the tale of an orphan and a recluse ''that, for all its violence and darkness, somehow manages to retain the gentleness of a fairy tale.''</p>
        <p>SPENSE + LILA. By Bobbie Ann Mason. (Harper &amp; Row, $12.95.) A short novel about a rural couple by the author of ''In Country.'' ''Miss Mason weaves various themes into the unhurried narrative with characteristic skill.''</p>
        <p>THE SUGAR MOTHER. By Elizabeth Jolley. (Harper &amp; Row, $16.95.) The eighth novel by the British-born Australian writer, about an academic and his young obstetrician wife, ''is written in her characteristically beautiful and controlled prose, and the story it tells is wonderfully engrossing.''</p>
        <p>SUMMER'S LEASE. By John Mortimer. (Viking, $19.95.) ''In 'Summer's Lease'  [ Mr. Mortimer ]  is the novelist as entertainer, chronicling the antics of British summer residents and expatriates in Tuscany. He has a jolly good time at it.''</p>
        <p>THE SWIMMING-POOL LIBRARY. By Alan Hollinghurst. (Random House, $16.95.) ''An exceptional novel'' that ''deepens our understanding of the coupling of romance and elegy.''</p>
        <p>THE SYKAOS PAPERS. By E. P. Thompson. (Pantheon, $19.95.) ''A first novel by the eminent English historian and antinuclear activist E. P. Thompson  [ that is ]  part love story, part tale of spaceship wreck and pilgrimage, part meditation on the claims of the imperial self versus the claims of the social aggregate.''</p>
        <p>TRACKS. By Louise Erdrich. (Holt, $18.95.) ''Ever since her first novel,'' the author ''has been populating a specific place . . . with characters as strong and orginal . . . as any who have recently graced the American literary landscape. . . . Ms. Erdrich is, as always, the generous kind of storyteller, passing along not only everything her characters know, but the story of the stories as well.''</p>
        <p>THE TRUTH ABOUT LORIN JONES. By Alison Lurie. (Little, Brown, $18.95.) A satire of feminist politics involving a museum worker who sets out to research a painter's life. ''This book is funny, intelligent and packed with incident arranged in a suspenseful plot  [ about ]  the sin of pride and the folly it can inspire.''</p>
        <p>THE TWENTY-SEVENTH CITY. By Jonathan Franzen. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $19.95.) ''An impressive debut by a gifted young writer. Although the novel is cast in the form of a commercial thriller, its author . . . is after larger literary game.''</p>
        <p>TWILIGHT. By Elie Wiesel. Translated by Marion Wiesel. (Summit, $17.95.) The story of a Holocaust survivor who ''comes to America and becomes a scholar of mystical tradition. . . . We experience in Mr. Wiesel's novel how good the family is, how good people are. Utterly without sentimentality, he gives us a small but real measure of what the world's loss has been.''</p>
        <p>TWO AGAINST ONE. By Frederick Barthelme. (Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson, $17.95.) The author's newest work of fiction, a dissection of marriage, ''is by far the most powerful, disturbing and interior of Mr. Barthelme's fictions, inviting us to be flies on the wall of a particularly shadowy and unwelcoming corner of its hero's psyche.''</p>
        <p>TWO BY ASTLEY: A Kindness Cup &amp; The Acolyte. By Thea Astley. (Putnam, $18.95.) ''Two superbly intelligent, compassionate novels,'' both of which won awards in the author's native Australia. The novels ''take opposite tacks in their exploration of conscience muscled away by mob mentality.''</p>
        <p>UNDER THE JAGUAR SUN. By Italo Calvino. Translated by William Weaver. (Helen &amp; Kurt Wolff/Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, $12.95.) ''A nervous, narrow, grandly unsettling volume'' of three stories on the senses, written by the novelist shortly before his death in 1985.</p>
        <p>VANISHED. By Mary McGarry Morris. (Viking, $16.95.) This first novel about a man, a woman and a kidnapped child ''is a nightmare of relentless savagery, brutality and suffering untempered by mercy or compassion. Ms. Morris is a writer to reckon with.''</p>
        <p>WHEAT THAT SPRINGETH GREEN. By J. F. Powers. (Knopf, $18.95.) ''The utterly down-to-earth story'' of a priest. ''If you've been daunted by our current fictional choices . . . then this sparkling draft of honest incident and clear, cold prose is for you.''</p>
        <p>WOMEN AND CHILDREN FIRST. By Francine Prose. (Pantheon, $16.95.) The author of seven previous novels offers a ''striking'' collection of stories ''with acerbic humor and a . . . bold pursuit of the bizarre that lurks beneath the surface of the mundane.'' History</p>
        <p>THE AGE OF EMPIRE: 1875-1914. By E. J. Hobsbawm. (Pantheon, $22.95.) ''A virtuoso performance'' that is the culmination of the author's ''vastly ambitious project to write a grand, synthetic history'' of the ''long nineteenth century'' stretching from 1776 to 1914.</p>
        <p>AMERICA INVULNERABLE: The Quest for Absolute Security From 1812 to Star Wars. By James Chace and Caleb Carr. (Summit, $19.95.) A former editor of The New York Times Book Review and an independent researcher theorize that ''America's current foreign and defense policies are an inherited national characteristic.'' The chapters ''on recent policies . . . make this book worth reading.''</p>
        <p>ANCESTORS: 900 Years in the Life of a Chinese Family. By Frank Ching. (Morrow, $22.95.) A Chinese- American journalist's ''stunning accomplishment in which, by recounting lives of members of his own clan, Mr. Ching brings to life the last nine centuries of Chinese history and culture.''</p>
        <p>ART FOR THE MASSES: A Radical Magazine and Its Graphics, 1911-1917. By Rebecca Zurier. (Temple University, $29.95.) The story of the New York-based journal ''is a compelling study of art and politics in the innocent, optimistic years before the Bolshevik Revolution and America's involvement in World War I.''</p>
        <p>BORN GUILTY: Chidren of Nazi Families. By Peter Sichrovsky. Translated by Jean Steinberg. (Basic, $17.95.) ''Guilt is the dominant theme'' of this group of interviews with men and women whose fathers were in varying degrees guilty of active participation in crimes of the Nazi regime. ''A powerfully affecting little book.''</p>
        <p>DEALERS AND DREAMERS: A New Look at the New Deal. By Joseph P. Lash. (Doubleday, $24.95.) The last book by the Pulitzer Prize-winning historian, who died in 1987, is an examination of the New Deal that ''aims not at comprehensiveness but at authentic evocation'' of ''the felt experience of the New Dealers themselves - Roosevelt's young, idealistic, joyously disputatious movers and shakers.''</p>
        <p>HEROES OF THEIR OWN LIVES. The Politics and History of Family Violence: Boston 1880-1960. By Linda Gordon. (Viking, $24.95.) This examination of varied family violence reveals women's ''extraordinary resourcefulness in resisting and even overcoming male aggression. The result is a book whose importance extends far beyond its specific focus.''</p>
        <p>INTIMATE MATTERS: A History of Sexuality in America. By John D'Emilio and Estelle B. Freedman. (Harper &amp; Row, $24.95.) ''This thoroughly documented and accessible book establishes that the 'good old days' were never as straitlaced as we sometimes like to think.'' The authors ''deserve our gratitude for putting sex in its proper place.''</p>
        <p>KIDDUSH HASHEM: Jewish Religious and Cultural Life in Poland During the Holocaust. By Shimon Huberband. Translated by David E. Fishman. Edited by Jeffrey S. Gurock and Robert S. Hirt. (KTAV Publishing/Yeshiva University, $35.) These writings of a Warsaw rabbi, who recorded the martyrdom of Polish Jews during World War II, are ''as original, as penetrating as any documents from that time.''</p>
        <p>MUCH DEPENDS ON DINNER: The Extraordinary History and Mythology, Allure and Obsessions, Perils and Taboos, of an Ordinary Meal. By Margaret Visser. (Grove, $19.95.) This ''lively and perceptive'' book uses the menu of a typical meal as ''a window onto thousands of years of human history.''</p>
        <p>THE PROUD DECADES: America in War and Peace, 1941-1960. By John Patrick Diggins. (Norton, $19.95.) ''The story Mr. Diggins tells of these neglected decades is nuanced with insights and judgments that will pain any true believer in a pure, essential American way.''</p>
        <p>RECONSTRUCTION: America's Unfinished Revolution 1863-1877. By Eric Foner. (Harper &amp; Row, $29.95.) This ''splendid book, the first major overall treatment of the controversial era in 40 years,'' establishes the author as ''the pre-eminent historian of Reconstruction.''</p>
        <p>THE SCHOMBURG LIBRARY OF NINETEENTH-CENTURY BLACK WOMEN WRITERS. Henry Louis Gates Jr., general editor. (Oxford University, $19.95, individual volumes; $595, set.) These 30 volumes of essays, novels, personal narratives, poetry and journals by black women ''provide a stunning new collective portrait of the Afro-American rise from slavery to freedom.''</p>
        <p>SHORES OF REFUGE: A Hundred Years of Jewish Emigration. By Ronald Sanders. (Holt, $27.95.) ''For all the hardships and even tragedies it recounts, 'Shores of Refuge' is a comforting book . . . a testimony to the courage'' of millions of Jews ''who have found a safe resting place.''</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON GOES TO WAR. By David Brinkley. (Knopf, $18.95.) Written by the television commentator, this history of how the nation's capital ''managed successfully to run World War II'' is told with ''endearing detail and sneer-free humor.''  Poetry</p>
        <p>APRIL GALLEONS. By John Ashbery. (Elisabeth Sifton/Viking, $15.95.) ''Increasingly, of late,  [ John Ashbery ]  has seemed easier to read. Has . . . he collectively mesmerized us to the swing of his diction?'' These poems ''seem to incubate some obscure Jamesian dramas we can trace without quite following them to the heart of their disturbance.''</p>
        <p>THE ARKANSAS TESTAMENT. By Derek Walcott. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $14.95.) ''The saddest book Derek Walcott has ever written, but . . . his best since 'The Star Apple Kingdom.' . . .  [ He ]  is a citizen of the world, at home in exile. . . .  [ His ]  reach is Elizabethan.''</p>
        <p>COLLECTED POEMS. By Louis Simpson. (Paragon House, $24.95.) Louis Simpson re-creates ''stories of ordinary people . . . living out lives of quiet desperation. . . . In his own ironic and understated way, he has been working to fulfill the ancient epic role of the poet. He is singing about heroes; he is using the common language to tell the tale of his tribe.''</p>
        <p>THE COLLECTED POEMS 1931-1987. By Czeslaw Milosz. (Ecco, $30.) '' 'Who serves best does not always understand': the subtlety, modesty and (so far as may be) realism of Mr. Milosz's mind are summed up in this line. . . . It is because he has persisted in his 'unnamed need for order, for rhythm, for form,' as all that can be opposed to 'chaos and nothingness' that he has left, over so many years now, so valuable a deposit as a poet.''</p>
        <p>THE RAIN IN THE TREES. By W. S. Merwin. (Knopf, Cloth, $16.95; Paper, $8.95.) SELECTED POEMS. By W. S. Merwin. (Atheneum, Cloth, $22.95; Paper, $12.95.) ''W. S. Merwin is our strongest poet of silence and doubt . . . a master of erasures and negations, a visionary of discomfort and reproof, the Samuel Beckett of postwar American poetry.'' Yet ''in 'The Rain in the Trees'  [ he ]  becomes a poet who not only traces the dark night of our collective soul, but also welcomes the morning afterward.''</p>
        <p>SELECTED POEMS II: Poems Selected &amp; New. 1976-1986. By Margaret Atwood. (Houghton Mifflin, Cloth, $16.95; Paper, $9.95.) These poems ''are marked by an unflinching inspection of the world, especially of the body in its self-protective carapace. Again and again  [ Margaret Atwood ]  returns to its pounding, pumping, inevitably faulty heart.''</p>
        <p>THE SISTERS: New and Selected Poems. By Josephine Jacobsen. (Bench Press, Cloth, $18; Paper, $9.) ''Josephine Jacobsen's poetry has always been a matter of the cool ear over the fanciful eye. . . . Her most recent poems  [ are ]  among the strongest she has written. . . . In Ms. Jacobsen's craft, language seems as flawless as silence.''</p>
        <p>THE WEST DOOR. By Alfred Corn. (Viking, $17.95.) ''Mr. Corn's sensibility is cultivated and ironic. . . .  [ His poems ]  pace themselves gracefully, without a ripple of excess. . . .  [ His ]  stance is that of a civilized man confronting and honoring nature without losing any of the accouterments of culture and education.''  Popular Culture</p>
        <p>AN EMPIRE OF THEIR OWN: How the Jews Invented Hollywood. By Neal Gabler. (Crown, $24.95.) ''In this enthralling book of social history . . . Hollywood's founding fathers come vividly to life.''</p>
        <p>DAVE BARRY'S GREATEST HITS. By Dave Barry. (Crown, $16.95.) Humor and commentary from the Pulitzer Prize-winning columnist. ''Mr. Barry is the funniest man in America and we should encourage him.''</p>
        <p>GEORGE WASHINGTON SLEPT HERE: Colonial Revivals and American Culture 1876-1986. By Karal Ann Marling. (Harvard University, $39.95.) ''Our overall perception of the complex functions filled by American history in popular culture is exuberantly enhanced'' by this survey of colonial ephemera and its reappearance in American culture.</p>
        <p>A HISTORY OF NEWS: From the Drum to the Satellite. By Mitchell Stephens. (Viking, $24.95.) ''An extended effort to define those aspects of the news that are eternal, universal, common to the village square and the fully wired condominium. . . . As a critical historian,  [ Mr. Stephens' ]  analysis is not only astute, but often eloquent.''</p>
        <p>NEWS THAT MATTERS: Television and American Opinion. By Shanto Iyengar and Donald R. Kinder. (University of Chicago, $19.95.) Two political scientists investigate ''how television takes command of political discourse and judgment in . . . America.'' The result is ''possibly groundbreaking.''</p>
        <p>ROMANTIC COMEDY: In Hollywood, From Lubitsch to Sturges. By James Harvey. (Knopf, $35.) In this ''encyclopedic survey'' of the romantic comedies of the 1930's and 40's, ''Mr. Harvey at his best is as good a writer as the movies could ever hope to have.''</p>
        <p>TIME AND THE DANCING IMAGE. By Deborah Jowitt. (Morrow, $22.95.) The author, a dance writer for The Village Voice for more than 20 years, ''has made a new kind of broad cultural history that incorporates dance. Her book is a major contribution.''</p>
        <p>WHO KILLED CBS? The Undoing of America's Number One News Network. By Peter J. Boyer. (Random House, $18.95.) The author, a former television reporter for The New York Times, ''quickly and decisively answers the question he poses'' in this chronicle of how ''the house that Murrow built became a journalistic slum.''  Science Fiction</p>
        <p>THE BRIDGE OF LOST DESIRE. By Samuel R. Delany. (Arbor House/Morrow, $17.95.) This addition to the author's Neveryon series ''display [ s ]  one of science fiction's finest writers at the top of his form.''</p>
        <p>DROWNING TOWERS. By George Turner. (Arbor House/Morrow, $18.95.) A major new novel set in ''a 21st-century Melbourne awash in a rising sea.'' This cautionary tale about the unchecked consequences of the greenhouse effect is also ''a deftly written story of ordinary and not-so-ordinary human beings coping with the end-of-the-world-as-they-know-it.''</p>
        <p>THE GOLD COAST. By Kim Stanley Robinson. (St. Martin's, $18.95.) The author sets his story in Orange County, Calif., in a designer-drug-ridden, quietly desperate future. ''Our attention remains on  [ the protagonist ] , a thwarted poet whose aspirations are as formless as the pleasures to which he is addicted.''</p>
        <p>ISLANDS IN THE NET. By Bruce Sterling. (Arbor House/Morrow, $18.95.) In this ''second-generation 'cyberpunk' novel'' about ''people who must bear the brunt of a dizzyingly rapid changeover from a product-driven to an information-driven society,'' the author ''reveals himself . . . to be a serious and insightful futurist.''  Science, Medicine &amp; Psychology</p>
        <p>THE AGES OF GAIA: A Biography of Our Living Earth. By James Lovelock. (Norton, $16.95.) ''Gaia is the Greek goddess of the earth. For James Lovelock she is the embodiment of a hypothesis: the earth is not merely the abode of life but is a single living organism.''</p>
        <p>THE DARK SIDE OF THE UNIVERSE: A Scientist Explores the Mysteries of the Cosmos. By James Trefil. (Scribners, $17.95.) ''In his easy, conversational style,  [ the author ]  describes some of the most elegant, if tentative, conclusions that the new cosmologists have reached as they search for the grail of a grand unified theory.''</p>
        <p>ELEPHANT MEMORIES: Thirteen Years in the Life of an Elephant Family. By Cynthia Moss. (Morrow, $22.95.) ''Ms. Moss keeps the elephants on center stage.'' Her book is ''natural history elaborated so as to invite . . . readers to identify with these close-knit family bonds.''</p>
        <p>GETTING BETTER: Inside Alcoholics Anonymous. By Nan Robertson. (Morrow, $17.95.) ''The first serious examination of A.A.,'' by a Pulitzer Prize-winning former reporter for The New York Times - herself a recovering alcoholic. ''There is much fresh, valuable and entertaining material here.''</p>
        <p>THE MAN WITH NO ENDORPHINS: And Other Reflections on Science. By James Gorman. (Viking, $15.95.) Lighthearted thoughts about serious science. ''Whether you are the sort of person who studies mosquitoes or the sort who swats them, this is funny stuff.''</p>
        <p>NATURAL OBSESSIONS: The Search for the Oncogene. By Natalie Angier. (Peter Davison/Houghton Mifflin, $19.95.) A former science reporter for Time and Discover magazines ''skillfully leads the reader through the mechanics of experimentation and the race for discovery. . . . One does not have to be a molecular biologist or follow every step to enjoy the fun or appreciate the beauty.''</p>
        <p>SOLITUDE: A Return to the Self. By Anthony Storr. (Free Press, $17.95.) A meditation on the benefits of being alone, written as a challenge to those ''psychoanalytic thinkers  [ who ]  underrate solitude and overrate relationships in gauging the ingredients of contentment.''</p>
        <p>THE TRIARCHIC MIND: A New Theory of Human Intelligence. By Robert J. Sternberg. (Viking, $19.95.) ''A lively popular account,'' by a professor of psychology at Yale, of his work on intelligence.  Sports</p>
        <p>CLASSIC BASEBALL CARDS: The Golden Years 1886-1956. By Frank Slocum. Foreword by Yogi Berra. (Warner, $79.95.) This collection is a ''graceful and informative'' book covering 70 years of baseball cards.</p>
        <p>THE DUKE OF FLATBUSH. By Duke Snider with Bill Gilbert. (Zebra, $17.95.) ''I was no more able to resist . . . Duke Snider's memoir of his days in center field . . . than I would be able to refuse a hot-fudge sundae with whipped cream.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA INNINGS. By Frank Robinson and Berry Stainback. (McGraw-Hill, $16.95.) A baseball biography and a sharp indictment of racism in the sport, by the manager of the Baltimore Orioles. ''There are few people better qualified than he to address the issue of why blacks . . . have had such difficulty clearing a path to positions of authority in the sport.''</p>
        <p>THE GODDESS AND THE AMERICAN GIRL: The Story of Suzanne Lenglen and Helen Wills. By Larry Engelmann. (Oxford University, $21.95.) An ''overlong, overdue dual biography'' of two tennis rivals who, in the 1920's and 30's, ''were bigger headliners than Jack Dempsey or Babe Ruth.''</p>
        <p>REMEMBRANCE OF SWINGS PAST. By Ron Luciano and David Fisher. (Bantam, $17.95.) The fourth book by the former American League umpire ''is irreverent, at times funny . . . a pleasant companion.''</p>
        <p>SEASON TICKET: A Baseball Companion. By Roger Angell. (Houghton Mifflin, $18.95.) ''Page by lucidly written page,'' these essays about baseball, written for The New Yorker, ''create a sense of  [ the game's ]  elegant and arduous complexity.''  Travel, Nature &amp; Adventure</p>
        <p>THE ARCTIC GRAIL. By Pierre Berton. (Viking, $24.95.) A Canadian historian's investigations have produced ''a highly readable compendium of northern exploration, and a much-needed one, too.''</p>
        <p>BEHIND THE WALL: A Journey Through China. By Colin Thubron. (Atlantic Monthly Press, $18.95.) ''By turns witty, melancholic, lyrical and cynical,'' this chronicle of a year's travel in China was written by ''a true China hand'' whose ''literary gift is so formidable that some scenes are more compelling through his eyes than they are in reality.''</p>
        <p>A BOOK OF BEES: . . . And How to Keep Them. By Sue Hubbell. (Random House, $17.95.) '' 'A Book of Bees' is an amiable volume, but the real masterwork that Sue Hubbell  [ a commercial beekeeper ]  has created is her life.''</p>
        <p>EQUATOR: A Journey. By Thurston Clarke. (Morrow, $20.95.) This record of several journeys by the author ''along the earth's great midline . . . includes both adventure and thought, social commentary and digressions into equatorial exotica. . . . His book evinces a conscience not often found in the work of American travel writers.''</p>
        <p>THTHING TO DECLAREMeMemoirs of a Woman Traveling Alone. By Mary Morris. (Houghton Mifflin, $18.95.) ''What Mary Morris achieves . . . is the union of a travel book and a journey into the self. The vibrancy of this union is on every page of her memoir-cum-travelogue.''  CHRISTMAS BOOKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
