<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Under Bush, Some See a Return of Enlightened Big Business</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="201773"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2DA1138F934A15752C1A96E948260" item-length="1014" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Under Bush, Some See a Return of Enlightened Big Business</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATHANIEL C. NASH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IN the 1920's, President Coolidge said that ''the business of America is business.'' And so it is today, especially after two Reagan terms marked by lower taxes and less Government regulation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IN the 1920's, President Coolidge said that ''the business of America is business.'' And so it is today, especially after two Reagan terms marked by lower taxes and less Government regulation.</p>
        <p>IN the 1920's, President Coolidge said that ''the business of America is business.'' And so it is today, especially after two Reagan terms marked by lower taxes and less Government regulation.</p>
        <p>And while economists and Government officials agree that no big shift will take place in the Bush Administration, they disagree over how deeply even the smallest changes will be felt.</p>
        <p>''Bush will be very close to President Reagan in terms of the business environment he will create,'' said James C. Miller 3d, a former director of the Office of Management and Budget in the Reagan Administration and now a fellow at Citizens for a Sound Economy, a conservative advocacy group.</p>
        <p>''There will inevitably be changes, but they will be more in style than in policy.''</p>
        <p>But some other economists are not so sure that any changes will be merely cosmetic. Mr. Bush comes to office at a time of rising concern about what some see as unseemly profiteering on Wall Street, in some cases tied to the growing practice of using huge amounts of borrowed money to gain control of gigantic corporations, and new worries about how effectively American industry will compete around the world in the next decade.</p>
        <p>Indeed, seldom since 1901, when J. P. Morgan cut the $1.4 billion deal - $22.9 billion in 1988 dollars - that created the United States Steel Corporation, has there been so much concern that corporate growth and efficiency are being replaced by the mere rearrangement of financial assets in larger and larger pools through mergers and buyouts.</p>
        <p>In one light, considering these issues in the context of Mr. Bush's promise of a kinder and gentler nation - plus the fact that he will have to deal with a Democratic Congress -many expect at least a little tightening of controls that were loosened in the Reagan years. ''Undoubtedly there will be a small but noticeable movement in the direction of restraint,'' said Robert B. Reich, a professor of political economy and management at the John F. Kennedy School of Government who advised Gov. Michael S. Dukakis during the campaign. ''But don't expect anything bold.'' Some of that movement could come with the encouragement of Mr. Bush's close allies in matters involving the economy and finance, James A. Baker 3d and Nicholas F. Brady, his Secretary of State and Treasury Secretary designates. It might involve somewhat stricter regulation of the securities markets and the banking industry. Mr. Baker was Treasury Secretary during last year's stock market collapse. Mr. Brady was the author of the White House Task Force report on Black Monday and its aftermath; it recommended giving the Federal Reserve Board greater authority over the markets.</p>
        <p>The Democrats sometimes criticized the Reagan Administration for de-emphasizing antitrust enforcement. In the view of some economists, both liberal and conservative, the current wave of huge mergers, such as the bids that exceed $21 billion for RJR Nabisco Inc., or the leveraged buyouts involving Pillsbury and Interco, could push Mr. Bush's antitrust policy in the direction of challenging the trend. (Why Wall Street cares about RJR Nabisco, page 8.) But by far the biggest change the next Administration is expected to push for will come in workplace improvements, such as more employer-sponsored day-care centers and more stringent restrictions on chemical waste and emissions.</p>
        <p>Murray L. Weidenbaum, former chairman of President Reagan's Council of Economic Advisers, for one, would not necessarily welcome such changes. He worries that while new restrictions and requirements might be made palatable to big business, they may be far too costly for small firms and entrepreneurs.  Worries About Scale</p>
        <p>''The three B's of Republican economics - Bush, Baker and Brady - have true big business backgrounds, while Reagan's orientation was to the entrepreneur and independent business executive,'' said Mr. Weidenbaum, who is now a Distinguished Scholar at the Center for Strategic and International Studies in Washington.</p>
        <p>''I think his vision of a kinder and gentler nation is definitely taking a more enlightened attitude toward things like the environment, acid rain, child care,'' he said. ''But the impetus for that has to come from big business. Big business can afford a better environment because it has economies of scale, versus very small entrepreneurial firms that can't.'' Mr. Weidenbaum predicts that the Business Roundtable, an association of top executives, will be the dominant voice of commerce in Washington, as opposed to the National Federation of Independent Businesses, an association for small businesses which had the ear of the Reagan Administration.</p>
        <p>Also, economists say that Mr. Bush's emphasis on corporate responsibility, and the ability of members of his team to strike compromises, might sit well with Congress, where bills requiring companies to give parental leave and other benefits are expected to be issues.</p>
        <p>But some economists are worried that in the end, attention to the workplace will come at the expense of what they see as the issue of the 1990's - whether industry in the United States will be competitive in global markets.</p>
        <p>Paul W. MacAvoy, dean of the University of Rochester's William E. Simon Graduate School of Business Administration, faults the Bush team for not yet addressing the issue of competitiveness. ''Everyone is saying we want greater concern for worker protection, 90-day notice before a plant is closed, more dedication to the community from business,'' he said. ''But what no one is saying is that we need a more competitive economy.''</p>
        <p>Joseph A. Grundfest, a commissioner at the Securities and Exchange Commission, echoed these sentiments. ''The new reality is that we are not supremely dominant in the international market place as we once were,'' he said. ''In setting policy, we have to start looking outward, to make ourselves more competitive with Japan and West Germany and the new Europe of 1992. If we continue to delude ourselves that we are the only economic force in the world, we will pay a high price.''  THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
