<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Private Incentives As Pollution Curb</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="189283"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="ECONOMIC SCENE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STAVINS, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WIRTH, TIMOTHY E (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HEINZ, HENRY JOHN 2D</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ECONOMIC SCENE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DC1F3CF93AA25753C1A96E948260" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Private Incentives As Pollution Curb</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IN this year of needle-strewn beaches and radon-poisoned parlors, every candidate who reads the polls is a self-proclaimed environmentalist. George Bush and Michael Dukakis are not exceptions: Both favor tougher enforcement of air and water quality standards and a moratorium on oil drilling off the coast of vote-rich</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IN this year of needle-strewn beaches and radon-poisoned parlors, every candidate who reads the polls is a self-proclaimed environmentalist. George Bush and Michael Dukakis are not exceptions: Both favor tougher enforcement of air and water quality standards and a moratorium on oil drilling off the coast of vote-rich</p>
        <p>IN this year of needle-strewn beaches and radon-poisoned parlors, every candidate who reads the polls is a self-proclaimed environmentalist. George Bush and Michael Dukakis are not exceptions: Both favor tougher enforcement of air and water quality standards and a moratorium on oil drilling off the coast of vote-rich California.</p>
        <p>But while environmentalism is suddenly 1980's-chic, the character of the policy debate has not changed much since Earth Day. To the dismay of most economists, the focus remains on fairness rather than efficiency - on how to trash the bad guys rather than how to get the biggest antipollution bang with the fewest bucks. That's why a new environmental report, christened ''Project 88: Harnessing Market Forces to Protect Our Environment,'' could prove so significant.</p>
        <p>The study outlines a dozen ways in which private incentives could be used to contain pollution at lower cost. And who says it is as important as what it says: The two sponsors, Democrat Timothy Wirth of Colorado and Republican John Heinz of Pennsylvania, are ambitious, well-connected Senators, who calculate the odds before they take chances. Their imprimateur confers a new political legitimacy on economists' ways of thinking about environmental problems.</p>
        <p>The first round of environmental legislation in the early 1970's followed a simple logic. Pollution threatened human health and animal survival. It was up to Washington to decide how much was too much and then to pick the best technology for keeping it in check. In some cases - urban sewage, for example - Uncle Sam would subsidize the cleanup. In most, state and Federal authorities would regulate private compliance.</p>
        <p>By some measures, the approach has worked. Auto emission controls have reduced the amount of lead, sulfur dioxide and carcinogenic soot in the air. Roughly half of all sewage is now treated before being dumped in rivers.</p>
        <p>But blitzkrieg successes have given way to depressing trench warfare. Private and public expenditures on pollution control exceed $65 billion annually. Yet many cities can't meet clean air standards and, nationwide, air pollution from stationary sources is worse than ever. What's more, additional environmental problems are arising at a frightening rate. Just as Washington is coming to terms with toxic waste dumps and the hole in the ozone layer, along comes the greenhouse effect . . .</p>
        <p>Both Presidential candidates have pledged to be tougher on polluters than the softies in the Reagan Administration. Neither, though, is proposing to load huge new costs onto businesses or local governments. And neither seems eager to squeeze more money from a deficit-pinched budget.</p>
        <p>That's why the Project 88 report could prove such a political winner. The report, drafted by Robert Stavins at Harvard's Kennedy School of Government, should help refocus the debate from how much to spend to how to get more from scarce public and private antipollution dollars.</p>
        <p>Take, for example, the Project 88 approach to acid rain caused by smokestack emissions of sulfur oxides. The Clean Air Act of 1970 sets stringent standards for new plants. But there is near-unanimous agreement among scientists that a major reduction in emissions from older sources will be needed to save fragile lakes and forests from killing doses of acid.</p>
        <p>The obvious solution, bitterly resisted by electric utilities, is to tighten controls uniformly on the old plants. The Project 88 alternative would set an overall limit on sulfur emissions from industrial sources and let the private market make the micro decisions of who would clean up.</p>
        <p>Polluters would have a choice of installing better technologies, buying low-sulfur coal or leasing antipollution credits from industries that could cut pollution at lower cost. The market for the credits would, in effect, set an efficient price for pollution, creating an incentive to fix plants that were easiest to fix, and by the least expensive means. According to the Environmental Protection Agency, such a system would cost half as much as an acceptably tough uniform emissions standard. Projected savings in 1995: $3 billion a year.</p>
        <p>Market-based antipollution incentives aren't new. Economists have been cooking up schemes for antipollution credits and effluent taxes since the late 1960's. William Drayton, the chief planner in the Carter E.P.A., pursued such incentives in the face of bitter hostility from orthodox regulators. And a limited market in local air pollution rights has been functioning with tepid support from the Reagan E.P.A.</p>
        <p>What is new is the growing understanding in Washington that market-based incentives could win votes as well as good marks from economics professors. Senators Heinz and Wirth, long identified with opposite poles of the traditional regulatory spectrum, are betting the time is right to fashion a new consensus.</p>
        <p>ECONOMIC SCENE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
