<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Theater; Fervid Frivolity in a Tour de Farce</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="171289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUSSOW, MEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">EICHELBERGER, ETHYL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FIASCO (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DA103BF935A2575BC0A96E948260" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Theater; Fervid Frivolity in a Tour de Farce</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MEL GUSSOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GUSSOW, MEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Fresh from playing Abraham and Mary Lincoln in his one-man play, ''The Lincolns,'' in the Serious Fun festival at Lincoln Center, Ethyl Eichelberger is taking a flier at Corneille. At P.S. 122, in a costume melodrama called ''Fiasco,'' he reinterprets Corneille's ''Nicomedes'' in inimitable Eichelberger manner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Fresh from playing Abraham and Mary Lincoln in his one-man play, ''The Lincolns,'' in the Serious Fun festival at Lincoln Center, Ethyl Eichelberger is taking a flier at Corneille. At P.S. 122, in a costume melodrama called ''Fiasco,'' he reinterprets Corneille's ''Nicomedes'' in inimitable Eichelberger manner.</p>
        <p>Fresh from playing Abraham and Mary Lincoln in his one-man play, ''The Lincolns,'' in the Serious Fun festival at Lincoln Center, Ethyl Eichelberger is taking a flier at Corneille. At P.S. 122, in a costume melodrama called ''Fiasco,'' he reinterprets Corneille's ''Nicomedes'' in inimitable Eichelberger manner.</p>
        <p>As a framework for this brief romp, he uses a version of the Kaufman-Ferber ''Royal Family,'' featuring himself and stand-ins for Divine (Katy Dierlam, playing a man playing a woman) and Charles Ludlam (Michael Osano). The imitation of these late actors is intended as an homage, which is more than can be said about Mr. Eichelberger's sendup of Corneille. The name of the great French dramatist is intentionally pronounced as if it were spelled Corny.</p>
        <p>There is no harm done to the reputation of the playwright or to that of Mr. Eichelberger. But one cannot say that, as a tour de farce, ''Fiasco'' is as amusing as the author-actor's other works, like his one-man ''King Lear,'' in which he played all the roles beginning with the King, the Fool and Cordelia.</p>
        <p>The plot of ''Fiasco,'' which is secondary to the performance, has something to do with two brothers competing for the same throne, and it has a resolution that expresses the sentiment that ''love conquers all.'' Chiefly, this is an excuse for fervid frivolity, most of it provided by Mr. Eichelberger himself.</p>
        <p>He introduces the play within the play, acts several roles, redirects the comedy in midperformance and spices the dialogue with asides. It is not always clear which are the prepared lines and which are the ad-libs. For example, his plaintive cry ''Is the ozone layer gone?'' may have been improvised for our benefit.</p>
        <p>Dashing on and off stage, he plays various musical instruments including the accordion and sings several exuberant songs. Although he does not do a back flip or a cartwheel, he does eat fire, an especially daunting feat under the climatic circumstances. On opening night, the temperature inside the theater approximated that of the interior of a pizza oven.</p>
        <p>While the rest of the audience continued to swelter, two theatergoers walked out in the middle of a scene. Mr. Eichelberger, stepping out of character - as is his wont - shouted, ''Lock the door!'' and, miscounting, he said, ''One of them is getting away.'' Then he added, in reference to another performance artist appearing simultaneously at P.S. 122: ''They have air-conditioning upstairs. I'll get you a ticket to Eric Bogosian.'' Although the heat wilted the audience, it seemed to have little noticeable effect on the performers, all of whom share Mr. Eichelberger's enthusiasm and his heightened style of acting. Ms. Dierlam, a veteran of the Ridiculous Theatrical Company, may be the weightiest person performing on a New York stage. At one point, caught up in her role, she started to kneel. Mr. Eichelberger quickly warned her: ''Don't do it, Katy. You'll never get up.'' At other moments, Ms. Dierlam demonstrates that she has a pleasant singing voice. Mr. Osano, who years ago played the Fool to Morris Carnovsky's Lear in Stratford, Conn., does an affectionate impersonation of Mr. Ludlam.</p>
        <p>By the end of the show, less than an hour had passed, and the star, apparently eager to give the audience more of its money's worth, played an encore on his accordion. With a little encouragement, Mr. Eichelberger - though still wearing an Oriental topknot on his head - might have reprised his ''Leer'' or his Lincoln.  No Cartwheels, Just Fire Eating  FIASCO, written and directed by Ethyl Eichelberger; production stage manager, Joan Moossy; costumes by Mr. Fashion-Gerard Little; Oriental backdrop by Jay Klein; ''Fiasco'' backdrop by Mr. Eichelberger; lighting design by Joel Giguere. Presented by Performance Space 122. At 150 First Avenue, at Ninth Street.  Illy Fiasco...Ethyl Eichelberger  So Sinewy...Helen Shumaker  The Oracle as Room...Gerard Little  Low Dee Chee...Katy Dierlam  A Tilly Tell Tale...Michael Osano</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
