<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Place for Radicals in This Campaign</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="190458"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">REPUBLICAN PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LIBOV, CHARLOTTE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, NANCY L (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRIFFIN, JAMES L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DB1F3AF930A15753C1A96E948260" item-length="1768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Place for Radicals in This Campaign</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLOTTE LIBOV</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LIBOV, CHARLOTTE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE Congressional race in the Sixth District is a battle of moderates: Nancy L. Johnson, a three-term incumbent who calls herself a moderate Republican, and James L. Griffin, a political newcomer who says he is a moderate Democrat. Part of the battle is that they disagree on what moderate means.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE Congressional race in the Sixth District is a battle of moderates: Nancy L. Johnson, a three-term incumbent who calls herself a moderate Republican, and James L. Griffin, a political newcomer who says he is a moderate Democrat. Part of the battle is that they disagree on what moderate means.</p>
        <p>THE Congressional race in the Sixth District is a battle of moderates: Nancy L. Johnson, a three-term incumbent who calls herself a moderate Republican, and James L. Griffin, a political newcomer who says he is a moderate Democrat. Part of the battle is that they disagree on what moderate means.</p>
        <p>For Representative Johnson, being a moderate Republican means she leans to the local.</p>
        <p>''I think the difference between a moderate Republican and a moderate Democrat is that I believe much more strongly in local government,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Griffin says she has it wrong. His being a moderate Democrat, he says, means he favors both a strong defense and active social programs. ''I believe in guns and butter,'' he said. ''I find no conflict between having a compassionate face on social and domestic issues and a strong face on defense and foreign policy.'' The Importance of Being Moderate</p>
        <p>''Moderate'' is an important word in the Sixth Congressional District, where Representative Johnson has built a string of victories based on her ability to attract Democrats. Mr. Griffin needs not only to win those Democrats back, but to woo Republicans and unaffiliated voters as well.</p>
        <p>More than a year ago, Mr. Griffin made the rounds of state political leaders to find out who was thinking of taking Mrs. Johnson on. What he found was that no one else wanted the task; Nancy Johnson was considered unbeatable.</p>
        <p>So Mr. Griffin, a 38-year-old Bristol native and West Point graduate, offered himself.</p>
        <p>''I came forward because I knew she was doing a poor job,'' he said, ''and I knew how to do it correctly. I've never once paused or looked back over my shoulder.''  A Big District</p>
        <p>So, with the days dwindling until the Nov. 8 election, Mr. Griffin and Representative Johnson each are spending long, punishing days on the campaign trail, crisscrossing the sprawling Sixth District, which includes 45 towns; only the Second District, with 57, has me.e.</p>
        <p>Not only does the district include a large number of towns, but it also is big, stretching from Salisbury, in the western corner of the state, across to Somers, in the northeastern part of Connecticut.</p>
        <p>The economic characteristics of the towns also vary widely, ranging from blue-collar communities like Enfield, Bristol, Southington and New Britain, which is Mrs. Johnson's homebase, to the affluent towns of Litchfield County.</p>
        <p>The district is considered Democratic. With about 41 percent of the voters registered as Democrats, and the remainder split between Republicans and unaffiliated voters, Mrs. Johnson was considered an underdog when she won the first of her three terms in the State Senate, becoming the first Republican in 30 years to be elected to the General Assembly. She became the first Republican in 12 years to be elected United States Representative when she beat State Senator William Curry of Farmington in 1982.</p>
        <p>Representative Johnson's image as a moderate Republican is borne out by her votes. Earlier this year, the Congressional Quarterly studied the 1987 voting records of members of the House and the Senate and found that on 99 key votes, she supported President Reagan's position 47 percent of the time, compared with an average of 62 percent for all House Republicans. Mr. Griffin faults her performance. ''I knew before even looking at her record that she was vulnerable on the issue of retaining manufacturing jobs in the area,'' he said, ''but I was surprised to find out just how much her performance in Washington was out-of-step with the values and needs of the men and women of this district on social issues as well.''</p>
        <p>Representative Johnson points to a list of accomplishments, and contends that she is a supporter of a cleaner environment, the elderly and such issues as improved child care. She is also considered an effective campaigner in behalf of her constituents; she has worked for legislation to help Connecticut's Visiting Nurse Associations, as well as promoted a National Purple Heart Museum in Enfield, a new traffic control tower at Bradley International Airport and expanding Federal courthouses in Hartford and Bridgeport.  A Job Change Coming</p>
        <p>Mr. Griffin recently stepped down from his post as a vice president for government relations at Phoenix Mutual Life Insurance in Hartford, becoming a consultant for the company. He said that his contract expires Nov. 8, and that he would either head for Washington as the new Representative or resume his former post at Phoenix Mutual.</p>
        <p>Mr. Griffin's father was a member of the United Auto Workers for 40 years, and the son recalls his father being out on strike, ''and having to get by with a union paycheck.''</p>
        <p>After graduating from Bristol Eastern High School, he entered West Point. He attended Army Ranger School, an experience he counts among the most useful as training for the rigors of campaigning, ''because you go for long periods with no sleep and little to eat,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He was a platoon leader in Texas, and then he was stationed in Maryland, where he directed an intelligence unit at the Army's Foreign Science and Technology Center. He also received a master's degree in international relations from Georgetown University.  Major in the Reserve</p>
        <p>He completed active military service, but remained in the Army Reserve, where he is now a major. He became legislative assistant for national security affairs to United States Senator Richard G. Lugar, an Indiana Republican, and after that was hired at the Federal Office of Management and Budget, where he served as a strategic programs analyst and adviser on arms control and weaponry.</p>
        <p>Such experience, he contends, would give him a head start in representing the needs of his district in Washington, and his party affiliation - Democrat in a Congress controlled by Democrats - would help him achieve committee chairmanships, which Representative Johnson, being in the minority party, has not had.</p>
        <p>Representative Johnson maintains that despite being in the minority, she has been, and is, effective.</p>
        <p>Now 53, Mrs. Johnson is a Chicago native who moved to her husband's hometown in 1966, where she brought up three children. She became involved in community affairs, organizing programs in the public schools. She was active in the United Way, raised money to build an expansion for the local library and taught Sunday School. She decided to run for public office because, she said, ''I understood the key role good government could play in helping small cities like New Britain with their economic problems.''  The Ball-Bearing Issue</p>
        <p>Throughout the campaign, Mr. Griffin has challenged Representative Johnson on her record in the struggle of the ball-bearing industry, a mainstay of the district's industrial base.</p>
        <p>Mr. Griffin says the district's ball-bearing industry has shrunk to a small fraction of its former level, because of the illegal dumping of cheaply priced foreign products.</p>
        <p>''My district is the home of the nation's bearing industry, which once employed about 14,000 people and now that has declined to 3,500,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Representative Johnson contends that the sharpest decline in bearing workers occurred before she was elected to Congress, and that she has steadfastly fought for the industry, helping to establish the Congressional Bearing Caucus, an informal group of about 40 House members that was successful in persuading the Pentagon to adopt regulations requiring the military to buy United States-built bearings. Mr. Griffin notes that the use of bearing in the defense industry is small compared with commercial use.  Clash on Gun Control</p>
        <p>The two also clash on the issue of gun control, with Mr. Griffin chastising Representative Johnson for her vote against the so-called Brady Amendment, which would provide for a seven-day waiting period before allowing the purchase of handguns.</p>
        <p>''Her half-baked, wrong-headed excuse for voting against the bill is that it did not require a mandatory check,'' he said. ''The nation's police chiefs agreed to strike the word 'mandatory' as a concession to the National Rifle Association, but they intended that it would be a mandatory check.''</p>
        <p>Representative Johnson, however, contended that the Brady bill would have been ''symbolic,'' and that what was needed were computer checks of handgun purchasers at the counter, an idea Mr. Griffin spurns as ''ludicrous'' and a danger to the welfare of handgun dealers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Griffin also takes issue with Representative Johnson's record on the environment, contending she is a late convert to such causes as clean air, clean water and the Superfund to clean up toxic waste. Representative Johnson, however, disagrees, saying she pushed for acid rain legislation, and helped lead the battle against the Iroquois pipeline, a proposed natural-gas pipeline that would pass through Connecticut.  Helping the Elderly</p>
        <p>Among other issues the two clash on is aid for the elderly, with Mr. Griffin maintaining that Representative Johnson did not best represent the needs of the aged when she voted against a bill dealing with generic drugs. Representative Johnson, however, says the bill would have required the use of generics, which would not be in the best interests of some elderly who might be better served with brand-name drugs.</p>
        <p>Throughout the campaign, Mr. Griffin has tried to shake Representative Johnson's reputation as a shoo-in, and get voters to look beyond that, both at her current record and future prospects.</p>
        <p>''The Democrats control the agenda in the House,'' he said. ''If we have a member in the minority party, she will never head a committee, never have the ability to influence how legislation shapes up, never sit in where decisions are made. She will always be standing in the hall.''</p>
        <p>But while Representative Johnson admits there are frustrations about being in the minority, she says it has not stopped her from being an effective legislator.  'Good Ideas Get Heard'</p>
        <p>''The big difference between being in the minority and being in the majority is that your ideas come out with a Democratic name on the bill, but good ideas do get heard,'' she said. ''It's discouraging, but it's not a handicap.''</p>
        <p>Also campaigning for the Sixth District Congressional seat is Louis J. Marietta, 67, of New Britain, who is running on the Independent Party line. Mr. Marietta qualified for the ballot by circulating petitions. Using that process, he has run frequently, although unsuccessfully, before: three times for the Sixth Congressional District seat, twice for mayor of New Britain and once for mayor of Bristol.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
