<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senators Announce Accord on Acid Rain Bill</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="161261"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUOMO, MARIO M (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CELESTE, RICHARD F (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDA143CF937A25754C0A96E948260" item-length="647" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senators Announce Accord on Acid Rain Bill</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Seeking to break a long deadlock over efforts to strengthen the Clean Air Act, a bipartisan group of 28 senators today announced a compromise proposal to resolve the divisive issue of acid rain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Seeking to break a long deadlock over efforts to strengthen the Clean Air Act, a bipartisan group of 28 senators today announced a compromise proposal to resolve the divisive issue of acid rain.</p>
        <p>Seeking to break a long deadlock over efforts to strengthen the Clean Air Act, a bipartisan group of 28 senators today announced a compromise proposal to resolve the divisive issue of acid rain.</p>
        <p>Senator George J. Mitchell, Democrat of Maine, author of the compromise legislation, said he was making substantial modifications in a tougher acid rain bill he introduced previously because ''this country - and the world - is in an air pollution crisis.''</p>
        <p>The compromise is similar in some respects to a plan put forward last month by Governor Cuomo of New York and Governor Richard Celeste of Ohio, two states that have been on opposite sides of the long debate over what to do about acid rain. It includes, for example, a plan to share the costs of controlling acid rain among all the states instead of making polluters pay all of them.</p>
        <p>At a news conference in the Capital today, the two governors announced that their legislation was being introduced in the House by Representative Sherwood L. Boehlert, Republican of upstate New York, and Representative Louis Stokes, Democrat of Ohio. Damage to Forests</p>
        <p>Acid rain is pollution from power plants, as well as from other industrial sources and motor vehicles, that is transformed chemically as it moves through the atmosphere and returns to earth as acidic rain, snow, fog or dust. It has been found to destroy life in fresh water in the Northeast and Canada, and scientists say it may play a role in damaging forests and man-made structures as well as threatening human health.</p>
        <p>Much of this pollution comes from coal-fired power plants in industrial areas of the Midwest, including Ohio. But most of the damage documented so far is in the Eastern states. As a result, New York and New England have been demanding action, but the Midwestern states, backed by industry and the Reagan Administration, have been resisting the expense of controlling the pollution.</p>
        <p>Last month, Mr. Cuomo and Mr. Celeste proposed a solution that would require reductions in the pollution that is causing acid rain to fall on Eastern states. But the plan would share on a national basis the costs that would have to be borne by the Midwestern states to adopt the necessary controls.</p>
        <p>The legislation previously introduced by Senator Mitchell and reported by the Senate Environment and Public Works Committee would require that the polluters pay the entire cost. The compromise introduced today would provide a subsidy to the polluting utilities to help them pay for the necessary controls. Surtax on Electricity</p>
        <p>Under the Mitchell bill, the money for the subsidy would come from a surtax on electricity based on the emissions of pollution by each electric utility. The more pollution from the utility smokestacks, the higher the tax on electricity. The Cuomo-Celeste approach would raise the money from a tax on oil imports.</p>
        <p>For nearly eight years acid rain issue has been the chief obstacle to Congressional efforts to amend the Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>An Aug. 31 deadline by which cities must meet the ozone standard or else face sanctions by the Federal Government had been thought to be a sufficient incentive for Congressional action this year. But even with that deadline rapidly approaching, Congressional action has stalled.</p>
        <p>Today, Senator Mitchell and 14 other senators, including New York's Daniel Patrick Moynihan and Alfonse M. D'Amato, said the new compromise proposal should break the logjam.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups said today that they would prefer more stringent controls but would support the Mitchell bill in order to get action in the 100th Congress.</p>
        <p>''We can accept lower pollution-reduction goals in the spirit of legislating quickly,'' said Michael Fischer, executive director of the Sierra Club.</p>
        <p>Business and industry groups, however, said today that they strongly opposed the Mitchell and Celeste-Cuomo proposals.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
