<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Worry Chic</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="107686"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NINETEEN HUNDRED EIGHTY-EIGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDC1F3DF934A35752C0A96E948260" item-length="233" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Worry Chic</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Don't relax. There's always something to worry about. Herpes, crack and nuclear holocaust have not gone away but have become passe worries. A trendy era obeys fashion even in its fretting. Here are some worries that have already infected 1988.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Don't relax. There's always something to worry about. Herpes, crack and nuclear holocaust have not gone away but have become passe worries. A trendy era obeys fashion even in its fretting. Here are some worries that have already infected 1988.</p>
        <p>Don't relax. There's always something to worry about. Herpes, crack and nuclear holocaust have not gone away but have become passe worries. A trendy era obeys fashion even in its fretting. Here are some worries that have already infected 1988.</p>
        <p>There may be urethane in the wine.</p>
        <p>There may be parasites in the sushi.</p>
        <p>Radon, an insidious, invisible, radioactive gas, could be seeping into your basement.</p>
        <p>There is too much ozone in the air you breathe, which damages the lungs.</p>
        <p>There is too little ozone in the stratosphere, which lets in ultraviolet rays that burn the skin.</p>
        <p>The world may get too warm, because sunlight is being trapped, as in a greenhouse, by the growing veil of gases spewed out by burning coal.</p>
        <p>The world will get too cold if the next ice age arrives before the greenhouse effect does.</p>
        <p>The dollar may make a strong recovery, ruinously reversing improvements in the balance of trade.</p>
        <p>You may suffer a heart attack if you exercise too little.</p>
        <p>You may suffer a heart attack if you exercise too much.</p>
        <p>Even if the wine has no urethane, it probably contains sulfites. Or the beer may. And in any case, both are laden with a more pernicious chemical -alcohol.</p>
        <p>Does all this mean that modern life is burdening Americans with more and more worries? No -just different ones. Worries grow stale and need to be changed. It's the disposition to worry that endures.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
