<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York Area Is Ranked High on Environment</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="50" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="123212"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENERGY AND ENVIRONMENT, FUND FOR</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIDLEY, SCOTT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DE1330F93BA15751C0A96E948260" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York Area Is Ranked High on Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: For the second year in a row, New York, New Jersey and Connecticut ranked among the top six states in efforts to establish and enforce environmental programs, according to a report released this week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: For the second year in a row, New York, New Jersey and Connecticut ranked among the top six states in efforts to establish and enforce environmental programs, according to a report released this week.</p>
        <p>For the second year in a row, New York, New Jersey and Connecticut ranked among the top six states in efforts to establish and enforce environmental programs, according to a report released this week.</p>
        <p>The report, prepared by the Fund for Renewable Energy and the Environment, indicates that some states have been more creative and successful than others in developing programs to protect the environment.</p>
        <p>Because of reductions in Federal aid, however, more states must ''get tough'' by demanding that polluters pay for a greater amount of environmental damage, according to the report.</p>
        <p>The author of the report, Scott Ridley, said the Reagan Administration was playing ''Humpty Dumpty economics'' with the environment by ''picking up the pieces instead of preventing the problem where it starts.'' New Jersey Ranked First</p>
        <p>Shifting greater liability to polluters would encourage ''more widespread waste minimization, neutralization, and recycling at the source,'' according to the report.</p>
        <p>The fund, a private, nonprofit educational group, held a news conference here Tuesday to release the report and present awards to governors, senators and Congressmen from the states with the best records.</p>
        <p>In preparing the report, the group ranked the states on six environmental topics: surface-water protection, pesticide contamination, land-use planning, indoor pollution, highway safety and energy pollution. Last year's report covered different topics.</p>
        <p>New Jersey ranked first among the states for its efforts to eliminate indoor pollution. Governor Kean, accepting an award for his state's performance, said New Jersey's past efforts concentrated on addressing environmental threats outside the home. ''Now we're beginning to understand threats inside the home and workplace may be even worse,'' he said. Indoor Pollution Identified</p>
        <p>The report identified indoor pollutants as tobacco smoke, radon, lead in water and paint, asbestos and formaldehyde.</p>
        <p>New Jersey has instituted a ban on the use of lead in drinking water systems and has tested children for elevated levels of lead in blood. The report also states that New Jersey ''is among those with the best developed policies to limit smoking.''</p>
        <p>New Jersey placed third in the overall ranking of the 50 states. Connecticut ranked fifth, followed by New York.</p>
        <p>Massachusetts and Wisconsin both ranked first for their overall environmental efforts. Wyoming had the worst overall ranking.</p>
        <p>Wyoming has established no program to testing for pesticides in ground water. It has no provisions to protect wellheads and wetlands and does not oversee hazardous waste plants. Wyoming ''lacks even most basic no-smoking laws,'' according to the organization. Highway Safety Also Ranked</p>
        <p>State governments usually do not develop tough environmental policies until faced with a crisis, according to the report, which identifies no-cost and low-cost policies that can minimize environmental damage and protect public health.</p>
        <p>Such policies include bans on certain pesticides, increased fuel efficiency standards for cars and trucks, land-use planning goals and regulations to protect wellheads, aquifers and forests, and lower speed limits and the use of seat belts.</p>
        <p>Although not traditionally thought of as an environmental issue, highway safety was included in the report, Mr. Ridely said, because automobile exhaust fills the air with hazardous chemicals and automobile accidents are a leading cause of death.</p>
        <p>New Jersey was one of the seven best states for efficient and safe highways. Maryland ranked first in that category. New York, which ranked first last year for ground water protection, was among the seven best states for reducing the danger of pesticides. California ranked first in reducing pesticide contamination. State and county expenditures to regulate pesticides total more than $40 million annually in California, according to the report. This is about the same size of the annual budget of the Federal Environmental Protection Agency's Office of Pesticide Programs, said Gov. George Deukmejian of California.</p>
        <p>North Carolina ranked first in its efforts to protect surface water, and Oregon was first in land-use planning. Massachusetts was found to have the best energy pollution control measures.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
