<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="187288"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDD1531F931A25753C1A96E948260" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-13  Israeli measures have not worked to quell Palestinian uprisings in the occupied territories. As the disorders enter the 11th month, some in the military concede that the tough measures may add to the violence in the short run. Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-13  Israeli measures have not worked to quell Palestinian uprisings in the occupied territories. As the disorders enter the 11th month, some in the military concede that the tough measures may add to the violence in the short run. Page A1</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-13  Israeli measures have not worked to quell Palestinian uprisings in the occupied territories. As the disorders enter the 11th month, some in the military concede that the tough measures may add to the violence in the short run. Page A1</p>
        <p>Pope John Paul II was denounced at the beginning of a speech to the European Parliament. The Rev. Ian Paisley, the Northern Ireland Protestant politician, called him ''the Antichrist.'' A3</p>
        <p>Charges of Serbian nationalism, made by Slovenians were denounced by Serbian leaders. Tension throughout Yugoslavia rose with the approach of an important Communist Party session. A6</p>
        <p>A new Czechoslovak Prime Minister was appointed by the nation's Communist Party. He is Ladislav Adamec, the Premier of the Czech portion of western Czechoslovakia. A5  ''Election-rigging'' in Armenia was proclaimed by the Communist Party there in the case of a write-in candidaate who won more votes than the Party's nominee. A3</p>
        <p>A credit line to the Soviets of $1.6 billion, the largest ever from the West, was completed by West German bankers to help Moscow modernize its food and consumer goods industries. D1</p>
        <p>Army civilian admits passing weapons data to South Africa A8</p>
        <p>Indian opposition parties form coalition to oust Gandhi A10</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A14-25  A team to correct safety failures at the Savannah River Plant was appointed by the Energy Secretary. It is to put an impotant reactor back into operation by January. A1</p>
        <p>Security lapses at nuclear labs involving foreign visitors were conceded by Energy Department officials. Classified information was not disclosed, they said. A20</p>
        <p>A bank holding group was charged with conspiring with cocaine dealers to launder millions in drug money in a network reaching the United States, Europe and Latin America. A1</p>
        <p>Sale of the Eastern Airlines shuttle to Donald J. Trump, the New York real estate developer, for more than $300 million, is expected to be announced today by Texas Air Corporation. A1</p>
        <p>Mathematicians solved a big problem by using hundreds of computers on three continents, successfully splitting a number 100 digits long into two large, prime factors. A1</p>
        <p>Trees in Guatemala for a coal plant in Connecticut is the trade off developed by an electric utility concerned about the effects of carbon dioxide. The trees, it reasons, would negate the effect of its power plant. A14</p>
        <p>Texas's economy is likely to grow, led by a booming petrochemical industry, despite recent falls in oil prices, a leading state economist said. A16</p>
        <p>A famous Chicago bar may be saved from demolition for a new baseball stadium. The state has promised that the bar, McCuddy's, will get a new spot across the street from Comiskey Park. A15</p>
        <p>Stricter screening for impaired drivers sought A14</p>
        <p>16-month strike leaves legacy of bitterness A14</p>
        <p>Former hostage in Iran says Marine Corps is forcing him out A18</p>
        <p>Justice to rule on press liability in naming rape victim A21</p>
        <p>POLITICS A24-25  George Bush spoke about his style in a recent interview, expressing little discomfort with the sweet-and-sour approaches he has used in his Presidential campaign. A1</p>
        <p>Many firm Republican state bases give the Bush campaign an advantage in Electoral College votes greater than Mr. Bush lead in the polls, party members say, calling this the ''electoral lock.'' A1</p>
        <p>George Bush said Michael Dukakis is trying ''to scare'' the public with his brand of economic nationalism, which Mr. Bush called ''protectionist demagoguery.'' A24</p>
        <p>Michael Dukakis said the economy is in need of a ''second Declaration of Independence'' from trade deficits, Federal debt and from ''over-reliance'' on foreign capital. A24</p>
        <p>Bentsen assails Bush for ''playing politics'' with crime A25</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON TALK A22</p>
        <p>Gary L. Bauer keeps the conservative flame alive  REGIONAL B1-7  Agreement over the Shoreham plant and its future has become more likely as the talks between Governor Cuomo and state legislators appear headed toward compromise. A1</p>
        <p>Metro-North police morale is low, shaken by a series of scandals, and the department is in the midst of a crisis of goals and leadership, an independent report said. B2</p>
        <p>The police technology revolution is just beginning in New York City, where advances were set back by the fiscal crisis of the 1970's. Computers are being used for analysis and to speed investigations. B1</p>
        <p>New Jersey Congressional challengers, always hard pressed in contests with incumbents, are having an even worse time this year because of the competition for attention from the Presidential and Senate races. B2</p>
        <p>A try to ''set up Warren Anderson,'' the New York State Senate majority leader, was described by a State Senator under indictment. He said F.B.I. agents sought his help. B1</p>
        <p>A black youth may have been killed in a chase by a white group angered after an argument on Staten Island, the police said. B3</p>
        <p>Dawkins and Lautenberg debate B1</p>
        <p>Witness says Mrs. Capasso's lawyer aided judge B1</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
