<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Alaska Journal; Marketing Glacier Ice Is a Hot New Industry</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="176256"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GLACIERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALASKA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Glaciers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDD1131F931A3575AC0A96E948260" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Alaska Journal; Marketing Glacier Ice Is a Hot New Industry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>ANCHORAGE, Sept. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: About 100,000 glaciers cover nearly 5 percent of this vast state. It's hard to see the ice cubes for the bergs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: About 100,000 glaciers cover nearly 5 percent of this vast state. It's hard to see the ice cubes for the bergs.</p>
        <p>About 100,000 glaciers cover nearly 5 percent of this vast state. It's hard to see the ice cubes for the bergs.</p>
        <p>But enterprising businessmen, seeing gold in those frozen hills, have created a fledgling industry, marketing glacier ice as an upscale approach to chilling the world's drinks.</p>
        <p>''Who would have thought that Perrier would be such a big deal?'' said State Commerce Commissioner Toney Smith. ''Well, this is Alaska's Perrier.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith and other officials give credit for the new industry to Mark Wilson, general manager of Wetco, a small manufacturing and chemical distribution company in Anchorage.</p>
        <p>One of Wetco's divisions sold water treatment equipment in the oil fields. When oil prices fell in 1986, they took Wetco and much of Alaska's economy down with them. But Wetco also manufactured one-gallon plastic milk containers. So, thought Mr. Wilson, why not bottle pure Alaska water and ship it to the lower 48 states and Asia?</p>
        <p>To publicize the new product, Mr. Wilson hit on the idea of marketing it with a chunk of ice from a glacier.</p>
        <p>''We thought it would be kind of fun and exciting for people to see a big chunk of ice in front of a grocery store,'' he said, ''and we would sell our water, glacier fresh.''</p>
        <p>''Originally, it was just kind of a sideline business that generated a little freight,'' said Tim Dimond of the Dimond Ice Company in Juneau, another ice entrepreneur. But the reaction was so favorable in Japan, where the image of Alaska is one of purity, that the business took off.</p>
        <p>Wetco and another ice entrepreneur, Jamie James of Seward, sought out the lighter colored ice that crashed into the sea from the upper portions of a glacier. That ice is filled with tiny pockets of air, and as it warms in a drink the air expands and cracks the ice, giving off a distinct popping sound.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Dimond first took his barge, a crane and a steel net out to Tracy Arm south of Juneau last year, he scooped up deep blue icebergs, 60,000-pound chunks at a time. The ice comes from deep in a glacier's depths, formed under great pressure. Because of its density, it lasts twice as long as ice made in a refrigerator.</p>
        <p>''The water from Alaska glacier ice is as pure as any water that can be found on the face of the earth,'' said Jim Harper of Ak-Pacific Inc. in Seattle, Mr. Dimond's joint-venture partner. ''It's thousands of years old, long before there was any acid rain, long before we had any pollutants in the atmosphere. Because it's formed under such immense pressure, that also adds an ability to protect the contents.''</p>
        <p>In July 1987, Mr. Dimond applied for a state permit to collect the ice. There was no precedent, and certainly no regulation requiring it, but Mr. Dimond wanted to assure Japanese investors of his long-term access to the ice fields.</p>
        <p>That's when ice harvesting became controversial.</p>
        <p>''When this thing first started over a year ago, we just thought it was some kind of a crank, quite frankly,'' said Bart Koehler, executive director of the Southeast Alaska Conservation Council in Juneau. ''But somebody wanted to plunk icebergs out of an area that is adjacent to designated wilderness. It's introducing a new industrial use into an area that was set aside to be protected from such uses.''</p>
        <p>It turned out there was little Mr. Koehler could do. The Tracy Arm-Fords Terror Wilderness was on national forest land, but the state controlled the water where the Dimond Ice Company sought its permit.</p>
        <p>The permit was granted on July 29. Mr. Dimond was directed to work away from the glacier face and the shore, and not collect ice when tour boats were operating.</p>
        <p>In addition to its overseas business, Dimond Ice has been making inroads on the West Coast, where its 7-pound bags sell for about $2.50, according to Mr. Harper. (The home-grown variety is about half that price.) Distributors in New York, New Jersey and Texas have also expressed interest in the ice, he said.</p>
        <p>''It's really something of a phenomenon,'' said Robert Poe, director of the Alaska Office of International Trade. ''It's a market niche. I don't think it's going to be an industry that employs thousands in Alaska, but maybe hundreds.''</p>
        <p>Just as important, Mr. Poe said, is the reawakening of the Alaska business spirit.</p>
        <p>''I think Alaskans became a little complacent after the oil boom,'' he said. ''Alaskans are realizing that oil isn't here forever and that they can't live off that source of economic stimulation forever. I think that what the ice thing really shows is that some entrepreneurs were out there, they recognized a market opportunity and they acted on it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
