<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Next Big Crisis</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="165207"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="FOREIGN AFFAIRS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, FLORA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DE1030F934A15754C0A96E948260" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Next Big Crisis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Flora Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, FLORA</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The cold war isn't over. But even as the political climate is warming, so is the world's physical climate. There are many signs that the next general international crisis is going to be about the environment. It can become as abrasive, dangerous and costly as the arms race.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The cold war isn't over. But even as the political climate is warming, so is the world's physical climate. There are many signs that the next general international crisis is going to be about the environment. It can become as abrasive, dangerous and costly as the arms race.</p>
        <p>The cold war isn't over. But even as the political climate is warming, so is the world's physical climate. There are many signs that the next general international crisis is going to be about the environment. It can become as abrasive, dangerous and costly as the arms race.</p>
        <p>There have been warnings about environmental abuse for decades, but concerns were separated from high politics and security. Now convergence has begun. Environment is changing from a noble, usually local cause to an international political issue that can be seen gathering force. It is already a major domestic issue in a few countries, notably West Germany.</p>
        <p>The key difficulty at this stage is that there are so many different aspects of the problem and no overall approach. Nobody really knows how various causes and effects fit together, and how to assign responsibility. There has been much talk about the greenhouse effect, ozone depletion, acid rain and toxic wastes, not to mention nuclear accidents. But the nations have yet to develop a concept of coordination.</p>
        <p>For example, the Inter-Action Council, a group of eminent former government leaders, recently recommended a new look at nuclear energy. They concluded that accumulating atmospheric deterioration caused by burning ever more coal and oil is more dangerous than expanded use of nuclear energy under proper safety rules.</p>
        <p>But there is no solid body of scientific information on what is really happening, how much of the damage comes from industrial emissions, how much from deforestation and changing use of land, how much from new chemical compounds.</p>
        <p>Some scientists say there are much more efficient ways of burning coal that would produce more energy with far less pollution, but utilities are reluctant to make the investment because of their big losses resulting from initial euphoria about atomic power. Some say a crash program for controlled fusion, the principle of the hydrogen bomb, is best. Others say fusion energy is still far away and will always be too expensive.</p>
        <p>Deforestation is an important element in worldwide climatic change. But the suggestion that the powers impose conservation of rain forests would obviously provoke fierce north-south conflict. These dense stretches of greenery are mostly in developing countries, whose retort is that they cannot bear the burden of protecting rich countries from the effects of earlier development.</p>
        <p>Underworld pollution has started. It is a new kind of trafficking where unscrupulous dealers pay off irresponsible third-world officials to accept storage of poisonous wastes at cut rates. Lebanon has asked Interpol to arrest a man who fled under suspicion of dumping thousands of barrels of toxic and radioactive material in its waters. Some of the barrels turned up on beaches in Cyprus.</p>
        <p>Environmental damage is becoming a political issue in the Soviet Union, where central planning authorities long ignored the effects of their decisions. Daniel N. Nelson, a Soviet specialist at the University of Kentucky, says it has become a more important focus of opposition than human rights or religious dissidence.</p>
        <p>Informally, Soviet officials say the West ought to help them clean up since it is ahead in the technology and its own interests would be served. Chancellor Helmut Kohl of West Germany plans to propose sales of equipment, presumably on favorable credits, when he visits Mikhail Gorbachev in October.</p>
        <p>Seventeen national space agencies are planning an International Space Year for 1992, with the emphasis on ''mission to planet Earth.'' This will be the first attempt to coordinate the mass of satellite-gathered information and to document all available details of environmental change.</p>
        <p>Reversing damage will be expensive and may change world economic patterns. The poor countries won't renounce development, and the rich are likely to face a high premium to maintain standards. Unless a system is worked out for international responsibility, quarrels can become as explosive as old territorial triggers of war.</p>
        <p>A West German woman who wrote a sensitive, personal book about her girlhood experience, and acceptance, of Nazism was trying to explain to hostile students a while back how it was possible not to recognize the evil from the start. ''It was the times,'' she said, ''the attitudes of the society all around us. Now you can look back. Think how people will look back on us in 50 years or so and wonder how we could have tolerated what we are doing to the earth, just going on with everyday life.''</p>
        <p>There is a difference in motive. The result can be as awful.</p>
        <p>FOREIGN AFFAIRS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
