<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reagan to Seek Reduction on Capital Gains Tax</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="112588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CAPITAL GAINS TAX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEAR, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Gains Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DB173DF937A15752C0A96E948260" item-length="1322" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reagan to Seek Reduction on Capital Gains Tax</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PEAR, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President Reagan will ask Congress next week to reduce the tax on capital gains, White House officials said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President Reagan will ask Congress next week to reduce the tax on capital gains, White House officials said today.</p>
        <p>President Reagan will ask Congress next week to reduce the tax on capital gains, White House officials said today.</p>
        <p>Such reductions ''should be a cornerstone of tax reform for the 1990's,'' Mr. Reagan says in a confidential draft of his legislative message to Congress. The document is to be delivered to Congress when Mr. Reagan delivers his State of the Union Message on Monday; it contains more detail than the speech.</p>
        <p>Capital gains are now taxed as ordinary income. The top rate for most individuals is 28 percent, although some wealthy individuals must pay 33 percent on some income.</p>
        <p>''Experience suggests that lowering the capital gains tax may mean increased, rather than decreased, tax revenue,'' Mr. Reagan says in the draft of his legislative message. ''When capital gains taxes increase, investors tend to hold rather than sell their assets, passing their untaxed gains on to their children. In this case, no taxes are paid, and investors are locked into old investments.'' Numbers to Be Negotiated</p>
        <p>In his proposal, Mr. Reagan does not specify the ''optimum rate'' on capital gains, saying that should be worked out in consultation with Congress as soon as possible.</p>
        <p>While campaigning in October, Vice President Bush called for reduction of the tax on capital gains, the profits achieved through the sale of stocks and bonds, real estate and other assets held mainly for the purpose of investment. But the Administration took no position on the proposal at that time.</p>
        <p>Aides to Representative Dan Rostenkowski, chairman of the House Ways and Means Committee, said the Illinois Democrat was willing to listen to arguments in favor of a reduction in the capital gains tax. But they anticipated that he would not support such a proposal, in part because of concern that it might reduce Federal tax collections.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, the White House drafted a separate proposal to abolish the Federal estate tax paid after the death of wealthy individuals. But that idea was dropped a few days ago in response to concerns expressed by Treasury and budget officials, who were worried about the possible loss of nearly $7 billion a year in revenue, a senior White House official said today. Relief for Murdoch Sought</p>
        <p>In his legislative message, Mr. Reagan will also call on Congress to repeal part of a new law that, in effect, requires Rupert Murdoch to sell media properties in New York and Boston. The White House official said Mr. Reagan would assail that provision of the law as a severe blow to First Amendment rights and a ''last-minute appendage'' to a catch-all spending bill passed by Congress on Dec. 21.</p>
        <p>The law prevents the Federal Communications Commission from loosening rules that prohibit anyone from owning a daily newspaper and a television station in the same city. Mr. Reagan's message says the law would inhibit the free market of ideas and could actually force the closing of a newspaper, though he does not mention Mr. Murdoch or The New York Post by name.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reagan's legislative message is organized around the themes in the preamble to the Constitution. The tax proposals are described as an effort to ''promote the general welfare'' by giving individuals more freedom to control their own resources.</p>
        <p>''When the capital gains tax rate was doubled in 1969, it led to a steady decline in the Government's revenue from this tax,'' Mr. Reagan asserts. ''By contrast, a reduction in the capital gains tax rate in 1978 and again in 1981 led to increases in capital gains tax revenue.'' Effects Are Debated</p>
        <p>However, Joseph J. Minarik, an economist at the Urban Institute, a research center here, said there was no consensus among experts on the effects of such reductions. ''I believe that cutting capital gains tax rates right now would lose revenue,'' said Mr. Minarik, who was formerly a tax analyst at the Congressional Budget Office.</p>
        <p>Most of the Republican candidates for President have supported a reduction in the capital gains tax, arguing that it would stimulate investment and help create jobs. Liberal Democrats ridicule that idea, saying that higher-income individuals would benefit most from a cut in the tax, and that unearned income should not be given a preference over income earned through hard work.</p>
        <p>An aide to Mr. Reagan said, ''The President's supporters who want him to remain in an aggressive posture in his last year in office will be quite pleased'' with the legislative agenda he sets forth on Monday.</p>
        <p>In his weekly radio address today, Mr. Reagan said he would again urge Congress to endorse a constitutional amendment requiring a balanced budget. He will also repeat his plea for Congress to give him the power to kill selected items in spending bills. And he said he ''may have a surprise,'' a way for Congress to show it is serious about ''putting the Government's house in order.'' But he did not elaborate.</p>
        <p>White House officials said Mr. Reagan would also make these points in his legislative message:</p>
        <p>* Congress should provide money for a major expansion of Federal prisons, which are seriously overcrowded. Federal prisons have nearly 44,000 inmates, or about 60 percent more than they were designed to hold.</p>
        <p>* The United States Sentencing Commission, an independent Federal agency, should adopt new procedures that would permit Federal judges to impose the death penalty for certain crimes. The Supreme Court has held that the penalty is unconstitutional when it is imposed in a random, capricious, unpredictable manner.</p>
        <p>* Congress should impose new restrictions on the Legal Services Corporation to curtail what Mr. Reagan sees as inappropriate political activity by some recipients of Federal funds. But he does not renew his proposal, repeatedly rejected by Congress, to abolish the Government's legal aid program for the poor.</p>
        <p>* The United States will deploy a ''Star Wars'' missile defense system when the equipment and weapons are ready. Mr. Reagan is asking Congress for money to continue research and keep up momentum on the system.</p>
        <p>* Congress should provide $2.5 billion for a program to combat acid rain, which is caused by emissions of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxides. Federal agencies will encourage development of new technology to reduce such emissions.</p>
        <p>* The Administration will begin a major effort to sell public housing and other subsidized housing to low-income families who live in such buildings.</p>
        <p>* The Federal Government will strongly support private efforts to build and operate a small space station, as both a laboratory for scientific experiments and a factory with countless uses by private industry. The Government would lease part of the commercial space station, which could be orbiting the Earth in the early 1990's, at least five years before a more ambitious project designed by the Government.</p>
        <p>* Federal workers with experience in the space program should be allowed to take a year off so they could teach schoolchildren about the wonders of space.</p>
        <p>* Congress should establish a permanent tax credit for businesses that increase their spending on research and experimentation. Mr. Reagan also wants to establish ''Thomas A. Edison prizes'' for people who devise innovative uses of technology to imporve the quality of life.</p>
        <p>* The Administration will look for new ways to address the child-care needs of working parents. The new Secretary of Labor, Ann Dore McLaughlin, will work with state and local agencies and private employers to meet these needs, consistent with the President's effort to strengthen the family as an institution. Restriction on Activity</p>
        <p>In his legislative message, Mr. Reagan also warns Congress against efforts to lift restrictions on political activities by Federal employees. In November, the House of Representatives passed a bill to relax some of those restrictions, originally imposed by the Hatch Act in 1939. The Senate is considering the bill.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
