<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Poll Finds Americans Are Ignorant Of Science</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="191121"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SCIENCE FOUNDATION, NATIONAL</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DD143BF936A15753C1A96E948260" item-length="462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Poll Finds Americans Are Ignorant Of Science</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Oct. 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Nearly 500 years after Copernicus postulated that Earth revolves around the Sun, millions of Americans say otherwise, researchers have found. They said their poll suggests that many of the nation's adults are ''scientifically illiterate.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Nearly 500 years after Copernicus postulated that Earth revolves around the Sun, millions of Americans say otherwise, researchers have found. They said their poll suggests that many of the nation's adults are ''scientifically illiterate.''</p>
        <p>Nearly 500 years after Copernicus postulated that Earth revolves around the Sun, millions of Americans say otherwise, researchers have found. They said their poll suggests that many of the nation's adults are ''scientifically illiterate.''</p>
        <p>Many Americans also mistakenly say that laser beams are focused sound waves and that atoms are smaller than electrons, said Jon Miller, director of the Public Opinion Laboratory at Northern Illinois University, who conducted a nationwide survey for the National Science Foundation.</p>
        <p>In a July telephone survey, 2,041 adults 18 or older were asked more than 70 questions on basic science. The survey had a margin of error of plus or minus 3 percentage points.</p>
        <p>Asked whether the Earth goes around the Sun or the Sun around the Earth, 21 percent replied incorrectly; 7 percent said they did not know.</p>
        <p>In the early 16th century, the Polish astronomer Nicholas Copernicus laid the foundation for modern astronomy with his theory that the planets revolved around the Sun.</p>
        <p>The results of the survey have not yet been fully tabulated, but it appears that 93 percent to 95 percent of those sampled lacked fundamental knowledge of scientific vocabulary, methodology and an understanding of science's impact on the world, Mr. Miller said. A similar survey in 1985 survey found that 95 percent lacked such knowledge.</p>
        <p>The results indicate that many Americans may have little idea of what presidential candidates are talking about when they list key issues such as the Strategic Defense Initiative, acid rain, the greenhouse effect and the space race, he said.</p>
        <p>On other questions, the survey found that 43 percent said correctly that electrons, which are components of atoms, are smaller than atoms; 20 percent said they were larger and 37 percent said they did not know which was larger.</p>
        <p>The survey also dealt with lasers, an essential component of the proposed Star Wars defense system. In a true-or-false segment, respondents were read a statement suggesting that lasers work by focusing sound waves; 36 percent correctly said the statement was false, while 29 percent said it was true, and 35 percent did not know. Lasers work by focusing light waves. In fact, the name stands for Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission of Radiation.</p>
        <p>Of those surveyed, 76 percent answered correctly that light travels faster than sound; 19 percent mistakenly said that sound moves faster.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller said some of the responses indicate the lack of scientific knowledge could present some practical problems.</p>
        <p>For example, 63 percent said incorrectly that antibiotics kill viruses as well as bacteria. So when doctors tell patients their illness is caused by a virus, they may take antibiotics in a fruitless effort to cure their ailment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
