<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="156357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5D6163DF937A15755C0A96E948260" item-length="881" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International A2-9</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International A2-9</p>
        <p>International A2-9</p>
        <p>The 1986 immigration law is falling to curb the illegal flow of Mexicans into the United States and may be creating new problems by distorting traditional immigration patterns, Mexican and American researchers say. Page A1</p>
        <p>The East is ready to make greater cuts than NATO in conventional forces in Europe to remove imbalances and enhance the prospects for an arms-reduction agreement, a senior Soviet weapons control official said. A1</p>
        <p>300 Turks were feared dead after half a million tons of mud and rock cascaded down a rain-soaked mountain and crashed into the village of Catak near the Black Sea. A8</p>
        <p>Iran sought to revive ties with the West by appointing an Ambassador to France and welcoming a group of British legislators for talks in Teheran this week. A3</p>
        <p>A fossil specimen of the primordial bird Archeopteryx has been discovered in West Germany. Paleontologists believe the finding should dispel any lingering notion that fossils found earlier were an elaborate 19th-century hoax. A12</p>
        <p>Canada expels another Soviet official A7</p>
        <p>Berlin airlift remembered A7</p>
        <p>National A10-14</p>
        <p>The earth has been warmer this year than in any comparable time in the last 130 years, and the heat has been generated by the ''greenhouse effect'' caused by atmospheric pollutants, a space agency scientist reported. A1</p>
        <p>The drought is raising the prices of some food items and will accelerate, officials say. But they predict that the crop shortages will not have a major impact on inflation, expected to be about 4.5 percent this year. A1</p>
        <p>With farmers and utilities pressed by the low water level in the Mississippi River, the Governor of Illinois proposed that the level be raised by diverting water from Lake Michigan. A14</p>
        <p>A major 1976 civil rights precedent is backed by 60 senators, 119 representatives, 47 state attorneys general, the American Bar Association and more than 100 civil rights, religious and civic groups. A1</p>
        <p>The inquiry into Pentagon fraud has entered a new phase in which the investigators will begin sifting through reams of documents to confirm or elaborate on statements overheard on wiretaps. A11</p>
        <p>The F.B.I. searched the offices of a Long Island paper company and the homes or offices of three people as part of a bribery inquiry involving Pentagon officials and major military contractors. A11</p>
        <p>The Navy's procurement apparatus changed under the Reagan Administration, with key shifts in the structure of the bureaucracy, the way sup-pliers were chosen and the terms on which contracts were written. A11</p>
        <p>10 million military medical records that duplicate some lost in a 1973 fire have been found, the Veterans Administration announced, adding it would review disability claims that were rejected because of lost files. A10</p>
        <p>Bayport journal: Newsroom behind bars A10</p>
        <p>Politics A12</p>
        <p>Democrats avoided battles over national convention credentials while the Rev. Jesse Jackson again offered cryptic comments about his attitude toward the Vice Presidency. A12</p>
        <p>Dukakis backs two measures to raise Massachusetts taxes A12</p>
        <p>Aide says Jackson seeks to avoid clash over Mideast A12</p>
        <p>Washington Talk A13</p>
        <p>Election-year ritual snags Reagan appointments  Regional B1-6</p>
        <p>Crack has overwhelmed the police in New York City. Officials say the problem is so intractable that the police are trying only to keep some neighborhoods from descending into outlaw rule by drug dealers and gangs. A1</p>
        <p>Paul T. Gentile will not seek election this fall to remain the Bronx District Attorney. Mr. Gentile acknowledged he was ''a terrible politician.'' A1</p>
        <p>Robert T. Johnson, who resigned as a Criminal Court judge to join the race for District Attorney of the Bronx, is described by friends and colleagues as a hard worker, a ''straight-shooter'' and a ''decent human being.'' B3</p>
        <p>Major events in the Bronx District Attorney race B3</p>
        <p>Pupils did slightly better this year on reading and mathematics tests in New York City than last year, but officials expect the reading scores to continue to lag far behind the statewide average. B1  A view that children learn differently because of differences in cultural backgrounds has set off a bitter political and intellectual debate among New York State officials and educators. B1</p>
        <p>Prosecutors have cleared the way for the testimony of Samuel M. McClease, who says he made secret tape recordings of Tawana Brawley's lawyers voicing doubts about her case, law-enforcement officials said. B2</p>
        <p>As one black victim of the Howard Beach racial attack testified in a Queens court, another was sought by officials in Virginia on charges that he seriously wounded his brother in a dispute over money. B3</p>
        <p>Comptroller Harrison J. Goldin took the initiative from Mayor Koch, saying that he will accept no corporate campaign contributions at all for the 1989 election. B1</p>
        <p>Memos detail ex-Meese lawyer's efforts for Wedtech B1</p>
        <p>Bus workers' idleness is still a problem B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
