<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Los Angeles Penalized for Pollution</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19880831T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="175401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON MONOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES (CALIF)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DD1F39F933A0575BC0A96E948260" item-length="1220" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Los Angeles Penalized for Pollution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Environmental Protection Agency announced today that it would bar all new construction of major sources of air pollution in the Los Angeles area when a stopgap Congressional moratorium on such sanctions expires Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Environmental Protection Agency announced today that it would bar all new construction of major sources of air pollution in the Los Angeles area when a stopgap Congressional moratorium on such sanctions expires Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency announced today that it would bar all new construction of major sources of air pollution in the Los Angeles area when a stopgap Congressional moratorium on such sanctions expires Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The agency said similar sanctions might soon be imposed on 13 other metropolitan areas that have failed to lower ozone or carbon monoxide pollution to levels required by the Clean Air Act. These include three areas facing possible action before the end of this year: Ventura County in California and suburbs of Chicago in Illinois and Indiana.</p>
        <p>The action is unlikely to have an immediate effect on Los Angeles or any other city. It would affect only the construction of big industrial plants such as oil refineries or chemical plants that produce 100 tons or more of an offending pollutant a year. Most companies with plans to build such plants have already filed applications for permission to do so under the Clean Air Act and would not be affected by the expiration of the moratorium Aug. 31. 'Impact of Essentially Zero'</p>
        <p>Because much of the pollution comes from small sources such as cars or shops that use paints and solvents, the E.P.A. sanction would do little if anything in the short run to clean the air. Over the long run, the sanctions could encourage states and cities to adopt more rigorous antipollution programs, including such difficult steps as limiting private vehicle traffic, in order to lower their pollution levels enough to allow industrial construction.</p>
        <p>In Los Angeles, which has the nation's worst problem with ozone, a major component of smog, the Federal agency's action ''will have an impact of essentially zero,'' said James M. Lents, executive officer of the state agency that oversees air quality in Southern California. He said that few large industries had tried to build plants in the area in recent years because the state already has tight air pollution rules.</p>
        <p>Ozone, a three-atom form of oxygen, is formed when sunlight reacts with hydrocarbons in motor vehicle emissions or from solvents, paints, gasoline and other volatile organic chemicals. Medical researchers have found that ozone in the lower atmosphere can cause serious upper respiratory problems. As smog, it also reduces visibility. In the upper atmosphere, however, ozone shields the earth from damaging ultraviolet radiation from the sun.</p>
        <p>Carbon monoxide, which comes largely from vehicle exhaust, reduces the ability of the body to absorb oxygen and can cause heart problems. Levels Exceeded in 100 Cities</p>
        <p>The environmental agency estimates that 100 metropolitan areas still have not lowered ozone or carbon monoxide pollution to the required levels. But for the time being, the agency is planning to impose sanctions only against those cities that have failed to prepare a government-approved plan for lowering pollution to mandated levels or that it deems are not making a good-faith effort to carry out such a plan.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. said that the construction ban against Los Angeles would take effect automatically with the expiration of the deadline because of a Federal appeals court decision last year ordering the agency to disapprove the area's plan for meeting the clean-air goals. New York Plan Challenged</p>
        <p>Lee M. Thomas, Administrator of the agency, urged Congress to amend the Clean Air Act this year to give cities more time to achieve the goals of the law. Noting that the hot, dry weather this summer had contributed to sharp increases in ozone pollution in many parts of the country, Mr. Thomas said, ''Failure to reauthorize the Act could lead to many more sanctions on areas as well as mandatory Federal pollution plans and litigation, which will only further the goal we all want: clean air.''</p>
        <p>New York City is not immediately threatened with a construction ban because it has an approved plan to meet the goals of the Clean Air Act. But the Natural Resources Defense Council, a national environmental group, has filed a court challenge to the adequacy of the New York and New Jersey state plans and to the efforts being made to carry them out. If the environmental group prevails, New York and New Jersey could be subject to sanctions. Disagreements Over Legislation</p>
        <p>Besides Ventura County and the Chicago suburbs, areas facing possible sanctions are Denver; the Reno area; the Bakersfield, Calif., area; East St. Louis, Ill.; Indiana suburbs of Louisville, Ky.; Cleveland; Sacramento, Calif.; Fresno, Calif.; Dallas-Fort Worth, and Atlanta.</p>
        <p>Construction bans for failure to produce an adequate plan or to implement a plan are already in effect in Kentucky suburbs of Cincinnati, some parts of Illinois, St. Cloud, Minn., and Albuquerque, N.M.</p>
        <p>Legislation is pending in the Senate to amend the Clean Air Act, including provisions to give cities more time to meet the ozone and carbon monoxide standards but to require them to take more effective measures to reach the goals. But disagreements over provisions that would require sharp cuts in the pollution that causes acid rain has kept the bill from the floor of the Senate. And in the House, such disagreements have kept the measure in the Energy and Commerce Committee.</p>
        <p>Senator George J. Mitchell, Democrat of Maine and chief author of the Senate bill, said he hoped today's announcement ''will encourage Congress to act on what is an increasingly serious problem.''</p>
        <p>Representative Bill Green, Republican of Manhattan, who has been pressing for a amendments to the Clean Air Act this year, said there was a general feeling that the current deadlines for meeting the ozone and carbon monoxide goals were not realistic. Now, he said, it is not just a question of extending the deadlines but ''seeing that the job gets done this time.'' 'Will Not Clean the Air'</p>
        <p>Congress has already extended the deadlines twice before. When the last deadline expired on Dec. 31, it acted to prevent sanctions from being imposed until Aug. 31, to give itself a chance to change the law and extend the deadline yet again.</p>
        <p>David Hawkins, a lawyer for the Natural Resources Defense Council and the E.P.A.'s former Assistant Administrator for Air during the Carter Administration, said that the construction ban announced today ''will galvanize political attention but will not clean the air.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hawkins said the agency had the authority but was not acting to force cities that do not meet the clean air standards to take more stringent measures, such as reducing pollution from motor vehicles and plants using solvents.</p>
        <p>S. William Becker, executive director of the State and Territorial Air Pollution Program Administrators, said: ''We are concerned because imposing sanctions on an area like Los Angeles, which has the most innovative and aggressive air pollution control program in the country, seems inequitable. It clearly indicates the need for Congressional action.''</p>
        <p>The environmental agency has other sanctions at its command to use against areas that do not meet clean air deadlines, including withholding Federal highway and sewer funds. So far it has taken the position that these other sanctions are not mandatory under the law.</p>
        <p>It has, however, proposed withholding highway funds from areas that fail to adopt adequate programs to assure that motor vehicles comply with the law.</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 31, 1988, Wednesday, Late City Final Edition</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 31, 1988, Wednesday, Late City Final Edition</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
