<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suddenly, the World Itself Is a World Issue</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="209251"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5D8163BF936A15751C1A96E948260" item-length="958" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suddenly, the World Itself Is a World Issue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: AFTER decades of neglect, environmental issues are moving from the periphery of geopolitics toward center stage. Several recent events demonstrate that the superpowers and other nations are starting to address problems like the greenhouse effect, acid rain and the thinning of the ozone shield with some of the same seriousness once reserved for international security and economic affairs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: AFTER decades of neglect, environmental issues are moving from the periphery of geopolitics toward center stage. Several recent events demonstrate that the superpowers and other nations are starting to address problems like the greenhouse effect, acid rain and the thinning of the ozone shield with some of the same seriousness once reserved for international security and economic affairs.</p>
        <p>AFTER decades of neglect, environmental issues are moving from the periphery of geopolitics toward center stage. Several recent events demonstrate that the superpowers and other nations are starting to address problems like the greenhouse effect, acid rain and the thinning of the ozone shield with some of the same seriousness once reserved for international security and economic affairs.</p>
        <p>''We are seeing a greening of geopolitics,'' said Rafe Pomerance of the World Resources Institute, a Washington-based research and policy group. Frederick M. Bernthal, the Assistant Secretary of State who handles environmental matters, said that issues like global climate change and the ozone hole over the Antarctic are producing a growing ''international consensus on viewing the planet as a single ecosystem.''</p>
        <p>These kinds of concerns, Mr. Bernthal said, ''used to be the backwater of diplomacy.'' Because of the dawning recognition that air pollution does not respect national boundaries and that the destruction of tropical forests threatens the ecological health of the entire world, environmental issues once relegated to low-level bureaucrats are now appearing on the agendas of summit meetings.</p>
        <p>Secretary of State George P. Shultz recently spent an hour discussing global warming with a State Department advisory group, Mr. Bernthal noted. ''That indicates the level of attention that issue is now getting,'' he said. If scientists confirm that the earth is warming rapidly because of industrial gases accumulating in the atmosphere, he said, ''The potential is there for this to become a major if not the major issue in the 21st century.'' Third World Polluters</p>
        <p>To many leaders of third world nations, environmentalism used to be regarded as a luxury that could be afforded by only wealthier countries. Some of today's worst environmental offenders are developing countries coming of age in a world that is growing much less forgiving of abuse. Increasingly, leaders of these countries are accepting that development cannot be sustained without protecting natural resources.</p>
        <p>In the Soviet bloc, large stretches of ecological wasteland created by the crash industrialization drives of state socialism have led to a grassroots environmental movement that is pressuring leaders to consider the consequences of decades of neglect.</p>
        <p>In his speech to the United Nations on Dec. 7, Mikhail S. Gorbachev, the Soviet leader, mentioned the environment more than 20 times, comparing its degradation to such threats as war, hunger and disease. In the week after the speech, the science academies of the United States and the Soviet Union announced the formation of a committee on global environmental concerns. Mr. Gorbachev, no doubt, realizes that environmentalism plays well in the West. But there is growing evidence that these pronouncements are more than empty gestures toward detente.</p>
        <p>On Sept. 28, Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze said in a speech to the United Nations that the threat to the global environment is ''equal to that of the nuclear and space threat'' and called for the creation of ''an international regime of environmental security.'' Promises From Bush</p>
        <p>The same day, Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher of Britain, a nation long criticized by environmentalists for slowness in adopting pollution controls, told the Royal Society that protecting the balance of nature is ''one of the great challenges of the late 20th century.'</p>
        <p>Many environmentalists were equally surprised - and skeptical -when George Bush promised during his campaign to convene a world conference on the environment that would include the Soviet Union and China. But environmental groups said they were encouraged by Mr. Bush's appointment last week of William K. Reilly, a conservationist with credentials in global environmental issues, to head the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>Some international efforts are already under way. Government officials and scientists from 35 countries met in Geneva last month to begin working toward an agreement on dealing with the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>Last year, 42 countries meeting in Montreal agreed to limit production and use of the chemicals that are breaking down the ozone layer, which protects the earth from the sun's damaging ultraviolet radiation. On Dec. 16, the European Community announced that it would join the roster of nations agreeing to abide by the pact, which will go into effect next month.</p>
        <p>With nations sharing common problems like the greenhouse effect or the export of toxic wastes, ''it is no longer possible to draw a sharp line between foreign and domestic policy,'' said William A. Nitze, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Environment, Health and Natural Resources. ''I don't want to be Pollyannish,'' he said. ''Environmental cooperation will not limit other sources of conflict. But these issues will help nations be more open and pragmatic and help them to think of less ideological strategies. In my view, this is one area where the next administration could make headway and do good for itself, the country and the world.''</p>
        <p>But in the world of diplomacy, environmentalism can be a two-edged sword. Michael Heseltine, a member of Britain's Parliament and a power in its Conservative Party, said in a speech on Nov. 23 that the Soviet Union's new public concern with ''ecological security'' represents ''a well thought out, carefully crafted attempt to hijack the environmental agenda, partly for ulterior purposes.'' ''The fact is that Mr. Gorbachev has spotted that the West has a long and vulnerable flank in its environmental record,'' Mr. Heseltine said. ''We are witnessing the birth of green geopolitics. We must be sure we are well prepared.''  THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
