<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Agrees to Limit Pollutant Linked to Acid Rain</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="193924"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NITROGEN OXIDE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DC143CF931A35752C1A96E948260" item-length="1066" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Agrees to Limit Pollutant Linked to Acid Rain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The United States joined with 24 other industrialized nations today in signing an international protocol to freeze the rate of emission of nitrogen oxides, a major source of acid rain and other serious air pollution problems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The United States joined with 24 other industrialized nations today in signing an international protocol to freeze the rate of emission of nitrogen oxides, a major source of acid rain and other serious air pollution problems.</p>
        <p>The United States joined with 24 other industrialized nations today in signing an international protocol to freeze the rate of emission of nitrogen oxides, a major source of acid rain and other serious air pollution problems.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement signed in Sofia, Bulgaria, starting at the end of 1994 the participating nations will limit nitrogen oxide to levels no higher than those prevailing in 1987.</p>
        <p>Today's signature marked the first time the United States had entered into a binding international agreement to limit nitrogen oxide pollution, and a leader of an environmental organization said today it was its first binding commitment to Canada to reduce acid rain. Rollback Rejected</p>
        <p>The United States did not join with a group of 12 Western European nations that agreed yesterday in Sofia to go beyond the freeze and roll back emissions of nitrogen oxides by 30 percent over the next 10 years. The Reagan Administration also has declined to join an earlier protocol to reduce emissions of another pollutant, sulfur dioxide, contending that this country has already cut such pollution substantially.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists called on the United States today to join other governments in cutting nitrogen oxides by 30 percent, and the Canadian province of Ontario today asked a Federal appeals court to order the Environmental Protection Agency to reduce both nitrogen oxide and sulfur dioxide.</p>
        <p>Parties to the protocol signed today will place a high priority on research to determine what levels of nitrogen oxide in the atmosphere are harmful to people and to ecological systems like forests. If agreement is reached that the 1987 levels are too high, the participating countries will resume negotiations to reduce them.</p>
        <p>Nitrogen oxides are produced in great quantity from the burning of fossil fuels in motor vehicles and industrial plants. They have been found to have a number of adverse effects on human health and the environment.</p>
        <p>Lee M. Thomas, Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, who signed the protocol for the United States, issued a statement saying: ''This historic agreement will benefit all nations. It begins to globally address environmental problems associated with nitrogen oxides, which play a role in the formation of acid rain, urban smog problems, and, as a greenhouse gas, contribute to global warming.''</p>
        <p>Agency officials and environmentalists said the agreement would have no immediate direct impact on the United States, which already is reducing nitrogen oxide pollution under the requirements of the Clean Air Act of 1970.</p>
        <p>But Richard Mott of the Environmental Law Institute, who is attending the Sofia meeting, called this country's signature on the protocol ''the first positive development in the United States' stance on acid rain controls'' and ''the United States' first binding commitment to Canada on acid rain.''</p>
        <p>The United States has not responded to frequent Canadian requests to reduce nitrogen and sulfur oxide emissions that originate in country, cross into Canada and fall to earth as acidic rain, snow or fog. 'A Lot to Gain'</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency statement said that the United States ''has a lot to gain'' by signing the nitrogen oxide protocol, adding that it represents ''an early and successful multinational effort to grapple with global environmental problems.''</p>
        <p>While nitrogen oxide pollution has declined in this country, the United States still produces more of this gas annually than any other nation by a wide margin. Moreover, nitrogen oxide emissions are projected to start rising again in the middle of the next decade because the number of automobiles and other sources of pollution will be substantially greater.</p>
        <p>Environmental Protection Agency officials said that under the protocol signed today, the United States was given a ''credit'' for having acted on its own in reducing nitrogen oxide pollution. The credit allows it to use a higher emissions level, that of 1978, as if it were the same as that of 1987. Nitrogen oxide emissions totaled 20.3 million metric tons in 1978, as against the 1987 level of about 19.3 million tons. Under current trends they are expected to decline to 18.7 tons by 1990 but then rise again to 20.2 million tons by 2000.</p>
        <p>However, if research shows serious impacts on health and the environment, the United States and other countries are obligated under the protocol to enter negotiations to make reductions in nitrogen oxide production.</p>
        <p>Today's protocol becomes part of the Long-Range Transboundary Air Pollution Agreement negotiated in 1981 under the auspices of the United Nations Economic Commission for Europe, which includes East and West European Countries, the United States, Canada and the Soviet Union. The Soviet Union was one of today's signatories.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency officials said that under the Clean Air Act, the United States could become a party to the protocol without consent of the Senate. Groups Seek Further Cuts</p>
        <p>Despite the nitrogen oxide reductions already achieved in the United States, critics are calling for even sharper cutbacks in nitrogen and sulfur pollution.</p>
        <p>The World Wildlife Fund and the Conservation Foundation, conservation groups dedicated to preserving wildlife on an international scale, today called on the United States to join with other governments in cutting back nitrogen oxides by 30 percent. Konrad von Moltke, a senior fellow of the foundation, said that ''if pollution cutbacks are not made soon, several important South American and Asian tropic ecosystems and highly endangered species will be affected by acid rain.''</p>
        <p>Canada's Ontario Province today petitioned the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia to order the E.P.A. to enforce the Clean Air Act and prevent acid rain. Jim Bradley, Ontario's Minister of the Environment, said he took the action because the Environmental Protection Agency ''failed to respond satisfactorily to a petition we filed last April, directly requesting that the agency begin legal procedures necessary to force American acid rain polluters to clean up.''</p>
        <p>The suit was joined by two United States environmental groups, the Sierra Club Legal Defense Fund and the Izaak Walton League of America. Nine state governments and other environmental groups are expected to join the suit in support of Ontario.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
