<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If Heat Weren't Enough, Mosquitoes Are Worse, Too</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="171073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOSQUITOES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RAIN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY METROPOLITAN AREA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">UHLIG, MARK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7D91738F936A2575BC0A96E948260" item-length="1119" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If Heat Weren't Enough, Mosquitoes Are Worse, Too</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK A. UHLIG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">UHLIG, MARK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: If you're parading your cool summer whites in Manhattan, you might have a fighting chance. But if you're sweating in dark clothes on Staten Island or in New Jersey, you may as well face facts - the mosquitoes are going to find you.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: If you're parading your cool summer whites in Manhattan, you might have a fighting chance. But if you're sweating in dark clothes on Staten Island or in New Jersey, you may as well face facts - the mosquitoes are going to find you.</p>
        <p>If you're parading your cool summer whites in Manhattan, you might have a fighting chance. But if you're sweating in dark clothes on Staten Island or in New Jersey, you may as well face facts - the mosquitoes are going to find you.</p>
        <p>After a dry June and an unusually wet July, the mosquito population around New York has surged to as much as four times its normal level, adding even more buzzing, biting annoyance to the miseries of a hot summer.</p>
        <p>Entomologists said mosquito eggs that would normally have matured in early summer remained dormant in the dry June weather. The heavy rains of July then prompted an abrupt and massive hatching process, sharply increasing the number of adult insects filling the summer air. More Sweat Means More Bites</p>
        <p>Local officials said some areas of New York City itself have been spared the worst of the onslaught. And scientists said certain people make less-attractive targets than others, because of their skin type or even the brightness of their clothing.</p>
        <p>But for everyone else, the odds of getting a mosquito bite have grown right along with the temperature, and then grown again because of it. The recent hot, humid weather has speeded up the breeding cycles of the newly matured female mosquitoes, increasing their appetite for what entomologists like to call a ''blood meal.'' It has also covered human beings with the perspiration that helps the hungry pests find their mark.</p>
        <p>So, in case you were expecting relief, the calculus of discomfort works like this: The more you sweat, the more you'll itch.</p>
        <p>Entomologists and weather experts said the problem began when New York City received only 1.29 inches of rain in June, compared with the 3.23 inches that normally falls in that month. The eggs of floodwater mosquitoes, which must be flooded before they start to mature, did not have enough moisture to hatch, and lay dormant until July, when New York was inundated with 8.14 inches of rain - more than twice the normal amount.</p>
        <p>The result has been a multiple batch of floodwater mosquitoes, sharply increasing the number of flying nuisances that swarm around evening picnics, riverside strollers and the light-and-fan traps that scientists use to track the progress of the mosquito season.</p>
        <p>'''A typical night's catch would be 150 or 200,'' said Dr. Wayne J. Crans, an associate research professor at the Mosquito Research and Control unit at Rutgers University. ''But in periods like this, they can go up into the thousands.''</p>
        <p>Areas that have been particularly hard hit include central New York State, where floodwater mosquitoes predominate, and parts of Long Island, Staten Island and New Jersey. The latter areas also have salt marshes that are flooded only by twice-monthly lunar tides, making for a regular cycle of dry and wet conditions that acts as a virtual mosquito factory.</p>
        <p>Low-lying coastal areas that are flushed each day by tidal flows, like Block Island, Fire Island and some Long Island beaches, have less of a problem, as do Manhattan and other central parts of New York City, where the urban landscape provides fewer good breeding grounds for mosquito larvae, scientists said. Only a Fraction Really Bite</p>
        <p>Health authorities in New York City have treated heavily infested areas on Staten Island and the Rockaways this year with a bacterial larvacide in an effort to kill mosquitoes before they reach adulthood. But since the dangers of chemical spraying have become apparent, more drastic methods of control have been sharply curtailed and are now reserved for the rare cases where there is a proven danger of mosquito-carried disease.</p>
        <p>No such diseases have been reported lately in the New York City region, according to mosquito control officials at the New York City Department of Health.</p>
        <p>Luckily, the number of mosquitoes out looking for your blood at any one time is just a fraction of the total population.</p>
        <p>In contrast to common belief, mosquitoes feed on plant nectar, not blood. Only female mosquitoes partake of the ''blood meal,'' and then only to provide protein for a new batch of eggs - or about two to four times in a lifetime. So for every mosquito that bites, there are at least a hundred with no wish except to buzz irritatingly and benignly around your head. Human Breath Provides a Lure</p>
        <p>Lest it seem a gratuitous cruelty, the buzz, too, has its purpose, serving as a siren's song that brings love-minded single mosquitoes together.</p>
        <p>Scientists say mosquitoes are attracted above all by the carbon dioxide of human breath, followed closely by the acids in human sweat, as in the case of a jogger exercising in Central Park.</p>
        <p>''As the jogger is running along the street, there is an ever-expanding trail of breath and body odors behind him,'' said Dr. Dennis White of the State Department of Environmental Conservation. ''The mosquito will cross through this path several times at right angles, each time moving closer toward the higher concentrations that are near the jogger. Then, within a few feet, the mosquito receives a visual cue and attempts to land, much like an airplane coming in on a landing.''</p>
        <p>For those who would like to avoid that sequence of events, scientists say many commercial insect repellents can help dissuade the mosquito from landing. So, apparently, does bright or light-colored clothing, although research on that subject is still sketchy, Dr. Crans said. Good News About Gypsy Moths</p>
        <p>If the problem seems intractable and neighborhood-wide, residents of New York City can call the Health Department Hotline, (212) 285-9503, to request help from a city exterminating squad. Or is it a swat team? On the happier, if more obscure, side of recent bug world developments is the relative decline of the gypsy moth, whose larvae destroyed the foliage of so many Long Island oak trees that the insects ran low on food.</p>
        <p>According to Mike Birmingham, an entomologist with the State Department of Environmental Conservation, the subsequent competition for food provoked an epidemic of a stress-related virus that caused the moth population to collapse. The smell that pervaded Long Island's oak stands in June came from the rotting carcasses of millions of gypsy moths.</p>
        <p>Dr. Birmingham noted, however, that joy over that development has been somewhat offset by the unexpected appearance of a Southern insect, the Hemlock Woolly Adelgid, that is being described as a dangerous foreign parasite comparable in effect to Dutch elm disease two decades ago. The adelgid infests and destroys hemlock trees, which are commonly used as residential hedges and ornamental foliage. The pest is thought to have been brought to New York from Southern states by hurricane winds two years ago.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
