<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amazon Settlers Turn Forests To Ash in Name of Progress</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="186922"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREST AND BRUSH FIRES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRAZIL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AMAZON RIVER BASIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AMAZON JUNGLE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">REDENCAO (BRAZIL)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMONS, MARLISE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru/Amazon Basin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DA153DF932A25753C1A96E948260" item-length="1103" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amazon Settlers Turn Forests To Ash in Name of Progress</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMONS, MARLISE</byline>
      <dateline>REDENCAO, Brazil</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The fires that have raged around this frontier town for the last three months have once more pushed back the jungle and turned forests into black and sapless land. But the mood of Redencao is anything but mournful.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The fires that have raged around this frontier town for the last three months have once more pushed back the jungle and turned forests into black and sapless land. But the mood of Redencao is anything but mournful.</p>
        <p>The fires that have raged around this frontier town for the last three months have once more pushed back the jungle and turned forests into black and sapless land. But the mood of Redencao is anything but mournful.</p>
        <p>The farmers who set the fires in this part of the eastern Amazon have opened up new space for cattle grazing and, in the process, have increased the value of their property.</p>
        <p>This year, the fires here and across the Amazon basin have caused alarm among environmentalists in Brazil and abroad as evidence has grown of their enormous size and their voluminous emissions of carbon dioxide, which has contributed to the greenhouse effect or warming of the Earth.</p>
        <p>But in many new towns, it is the link between deforestation and development that makes the yearly rituals of destruction so difficult to prevent.</p>
        <p>Redencao, which was just an airstrip in the bush and some shacks 10 years ago, today has 100,000 people. First the gold diggers came, then the road and the lumbermen. They were followed by cattle ranchers, who in this region get generous Government subsidies.</p>
        <p>''Everybody around here sets fires because flames can do what the hand cannot,'' said Bolival Alves, a tinder merchant. ''It is easier and cheaper. Only the valuable wood is pulled out.'' Forest trees are piled high in the local timber yards here where saws scream their way through huge mahogany trunks. Giant Brazil nut trees are not spared, even though this tree is protected and the law forbids cutting it. Workers at a large yard said that, once cut into planks, the Brazil nut tree is shipped under a different name. ''The yard makes up false documents,'' a truck owner confirmed. ''I never had any trouble with that.''</p>
        <p>While for a number of years international concern has grown about waste and destruction in the Amazon rain forest, for the first time it has become a national political issue in Brazil. The press has drawn attention to the manmade fires and forced debates in Brazil's National Security Council.</p>
        <p>In late September the head of the Government Environmental Agency resigned to protest the absence of an environmental policy. 'Average of 5,000 Fires a Day'</p>
        <p>Brazilian scientists who began a new program to monitor fires via satellite are still compounding this season's damage. Recently they reported that in 1987, 77,000 square miles of land burned, close to 40 percent of it virgin rain forest. They said that this year, in the last three months of the dry season, fires have been worse.</p>
        <p>''We are still recording an average of 5,000 fires a day,'' said Marcos Pereira, one of the scientists. ''The rains are very late. Last year by the middle of September, the burning had dropped off.''</p>
        <p>Other reasons for the enormousness of the fires offer insights into the methods by which the frontiersmen are conquering Brazil's vast hinterlands.</p>
        <p>Foresters have asserted that land owners rushed to clear forests before the country's new Constitution went into effect in early October, because new articles bring greater legal protection for the environment.</p>
        <p>Speculators regularly destroy forest to increase the resale value of their land, according to the foresters, or they clear it as a device to assert their ownership over land for which they have no legal documents. Land 'Improvements'</p>
        <p>Conversations with landowners in this region also give the strong impression that the recent congressional debate on land redistribution has scared many owners. Fearing that ''unused'' lands will be expropriated, landowners and speculators admit that they clear the land to demonstrate their intention to use it and thus protect themselves. Under Brazilian law, which favors homesteaders, felling trees is considered a form of ''improvement'' and therefore use of the land.</p>
        <p>From the air, much of the region near Redencao and wide swaths across the south of Para State appear to have undergone such ''improvements.'' Vast dents have been carved into what was a solid forest cover less than 15 years ago. A thick haze from the fires recently sat over the town and the outlying ranches like a brown umbrella.</p>
        <p>''I never saw so many fires and such big fires as this year,'' said Hamilton Lopez, a bush pilot who has flown for more than 15 years in this region. He was swearing as he dipped and swerved his Cherokee Pathfinder and searched for a landing strip hidden somewhere below the polluted air. To the north, he said, he had seen a ranch on the road to Xinguara burn 15,000 acres. ''It took almost a week,'' he said, ''and another like it was burning near Maraba.''</p>
        <p>Farther north, Para, Brazil's second largest state, still has large stretches of virgin jungle. But according to the new satellite survey, Para, along with the states of Mato Grosso and Rondonia farther west, are the areas most rapidly suffering deforestation. Huge new projects in south Para include a large dam and the world's largest iron ore mine. Environmentalists have protested plans for 20 iron smelters that will use wood in the form of charcoal as their main source of energy.</p>
        <p>According to the Government, 14 percent of Para, or about 180,000 square kilometers, was deforested between 1975 and 1986. In the 100 years before that, settlers had cut 18,000 square kilometers. 'What a Waste, What a Waste'</p>
        <p>Around Redencao, the vast stretches of empty, blackened land have baffled the Indians who have inhabited this region since long before the white conquerors from Portugal landed five centuries ago.</p>
        <p>''What a waste, what a waste,'' said Beptopup, an aging medicine man of the Kaiapo Indians, expressing his grief on a recent visit to old Indian sites. Those lands north of Redencao had now turned into a parched landscape with charred stumps in place of trees.</p>
        <p>''I am too old to understand the white man,'' said Beptopup, staring at smoke and ashes. He said he would have to tell everyone in his village that ''the place of our grandfathers is gone.''</p>
        <p>In Redencao logging and cattle prevail as the local business. ''The soil is no good, too acid for planting,'' said Agenor Brito, a new ranch owner. ''You can improve it, but the markets are too far in any case.''</p>
        <p>But for all the growth here, the lumbermen are beginning to feel the pinch of a harvest that is running out. Three years ago, Redencao had almost 60 sawmills. But half of them have left because the area is running out of mahogany and other hardwood trees.</p>
        <p>Brazil's Forestry Agency recently made its own nationwide assessment. In the Amazon, it said, only 5 percent of the trees reach the market. Ninety-five percent are either burned or left to rot.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
