<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HIS BIG IDEA</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="182497"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FLANAGAN, DENNIS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LOVELOCK, JAMES</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">AGES OF GAIA, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DB113AF936A1575AC0A96E948260" item-length="1138" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HIS BIG IDEA</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNIS FLANAGAN; Dennis Flanagan is the author of ''Flanagan's Version: A Spectator's Guide to Science on the Eve of the 21st Century.''</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FLANAGAN, DENNIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  THE AGES OF GAIA  A Biography of Our Living Earth.  By James Lovelock.  Illustrated. 252 pp. New York:  W. W. Norton &amp; Company. $16.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  THE AGES OF GAIA  A Biography of Our Living Earth.  By James Lovelock.  Illustrated. 252 pp. New York:  W. W. Norton &amp; Company. $16.95.</p>
        <p>THE AGES OF GAIA  A Biography of Our Living Earth.  By James Lovelock.  Illustrated. 252 pp. New York:  W. W. Norton &amp; Company. $16.95.</p>
        <p>Gaia is the Greek goddess of the earth. For James Lovelock she is the embodiment of a hypothesis: the earth is not merely the abode of life but is a single living organism. He proposes that all living species are components of that organism, as cells are components of the human body.</p>
        <p>The idea is not so outlandish as it might seem. When the earth was young, its oxygen was locked up in compounds such as water and carbon dioxide. Then, 3.5 billion years ago, there arose bacteria capable of photosynthesis - harnessing the energy of sunlight to build themselves out of water, carbon dioxide and a pinch of salts. The waste product of photosynthesis is the gaseous oxygen (O#2) that constitutes 21 percent of the earth's atmosphere. Of equal import is that the percentage of oxygen in the atmosphere has been constant for at least 200 million years, maintained by the photosynthetic bacteria and their multifarious plant descendants.</p>
        <p>So much is consensus; indeed, earth scientists before Mr. Lovelock were familiar with the concept that the crust, atmosphere and oceans of the earth are maintained in a steady state by processes both biological and nonbiological. Where Mr. Lovelock differs is in arguing that the level of oxygen, the level of carbon dioxide and other gases, the temperature of the earth's surface, the formation of clouds, the rate of rainfall, the saltiness of the oceans and many other things may all be actively controlled by biological processes. He believes living organisms create the optimum conditions for their own existence, and in so doing create the superorganism Gaia.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Lovelock advanced his ideas in the early 1970's (mainly in his first book, ''Gaia: A New Look at Life on Earth''), they made many people's hair stand on end. Not all the hair has relaxed, but Mr. Lovelock is certainly not a pariah in scientific circles these days. He has many scientist collaborators, and symposiums about the Gaia hypothesis are held at scientific meetings. The hypothesis has suggested many potentially fruitful researches, some of which are being pursued by Mr. Lovelock himself.</p>
        <p>An example has to do with the control of the earth's climate. It is well known that carbon dioxide in the atmosphere traps solar energy and thus acts to warm the earth - the ''greenhouse effect.'' Clouds do the opposite; they reflect sunlight and thus cool the earth. How do clouds form? It is not enough to say that when the water-vapor content of air gets high enough, the vapor condenses into the droplets of clouds. If that were all there is to it, few clouds would form. What is needed for abundant clouds is condensation nuclei: tiny particles, for example dust or particles of sea salt, on which water molecules can start to collect.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lovelock and others suspect that such nuclei are also provided by a compound - dimethyl sulfide - that is excreted in vast quantities by marine microorganisms. In the atmosphere dimethyl sulfide is oxidized into droplets of sulfuric acid, which are excellent condensation nuclei. In this way the microorganisms could influence the climate: the more dimethyl sulfide they excrete, the more clouds there are, the more sunlight is reflected back into space and the cooler the earth is. Mr. Lovelock and his colleagues have been actively investigating this possibility.</p>
        <p>The ages in Mr. Lovelock's title are the great epochs in the history of life: the Archean (when the only life was bacteria), the ''Middle Ages'' (when many-celled plants and animals emerged) and Modern Times. ''The Ages of Gaia'' also has a lot to say about the epochs of Mr. Lovelock's life. As a matter of fact, one of the most interesting things about the book is what Mr. Lovelock's life suggests about how science advances.</p>
        <p>In science there is always a fugue between facts and big ideas. The double helix of DNA is a fact; Darwinian evolution is a big idea. Sometimes facts suggest a big idea, and sometimes a big idea suggests where to look for facts. Sometimes a big idea leads to the discovery of facts that show the big idea is wrong. A well-known example is the steady-state cosmology introduced by the astronomer Fred Hoyle and his colleagues in the 1940's; it stimulated the gathering of facts that showed the rival big-bang cosmology is right.</p>
        <p>The Gaia hypothesis may be a big idea rather like the steady-state cosmology; even if it is wrong, it may stimulate much fact-gathering that will show what is right. It is doubtful that Mr. Lovelock would be happy with such a result. He is the type of scientist who sees himself as a lonely battler against the establishment. Although he is a fully frocked Ph.D., he chooses not to work in a scientific institution but to live with his wife and grown son on 30 much-loved acres in the West Country of England. In his book he makes many slighting references to scientists in general. At the same time he is quite respectful of individual scientists, particularly those who agree with him.</p>
        <p>In fact, he is a man torn. His big idea is stated with much grandiloquence and little qualification, but his arguments in favor of it are modest, qualified, plausible and above all illuminating. As one might expect, the Gaia hypothesis - particularly in being named after a goddess - has attracted many people with a mystical streak. This Mr. Lovelock discusses in a chapter titled ''God and Gaia.'' Although his own approach is not mystical, he appears to be sympathetic to such people because they share his reverential attitude toward the earth as a living system. Yet he is far from being a conventional environmentalist; for example, he thinks fears of a depleted ozone layer and radiation from nuclear power plants are much exaggerated.</p>
        <p>The point is that in science, as in other walks of life, it takes all kinds.  POSITIVELY AGNOSTIC</p>
        <p>For the present, my belief in God rests at the stage of a positive agnosticism. I am too deeply committed to science for undiluted faith; equally unacceptable to me spiritually is the materialist world of undiluted fact. Art and science seem interconnected with each other and with religion, and to be mutually enlarging. That Gaia can be both spiritual and scientific is, for me, deeply satisfying. From letters and conversations I have learnt that a feeling for the organism, the Earth, has survived and that many feel a need to include those old faiths in their system of belief, both for themselves and because they feel that Earth of which they are a part is under threat. In no way do I see Gaia as a sentient being, a surrogate God. To me Gaia is alive and part of the ineffable Universe and I am a part of her.  From ''The Ages of Gaia.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
