<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Steps Take Aim At Rare, Fatal Reaction To General Anesthesia</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19880826T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="173437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="THE DOCTOR'S WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURGERY AND SURGEONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HYPOTHERMIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANESTHESIA AND ANESTHETICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOSPITALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DANTROLENE (DRUG)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CALCIUM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CELLS (BIOLOGICAL)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALTMAN, LAWRENCE K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Anesthesia and Anesthetics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anesthesia and Anesthetics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DF1538F930A1575BC0A96E948260" item-length="1189" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Steps Take Aim At Rare, Fatal Reaction To General Anesthesia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN, M.D.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ALTMAN, LAWRENCE K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IT was a key moment in the history of modern anesthesia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IT was a key moment in the history of modern anesthesia.</p>
        <p>IT was a key moment in the history of modern anesthesia.</p>
        <p>A 21-year-old Australian who needed general anesthesia for his broken leg refused ether because 10 of 24 relatives who had received the gas died during surgery. Instead, his doctors used another anesthetic.</p>
        <p>But several minutes into the operation in 1960, the man's blood pressure dropped and his temperature rose dramatically. The doctors stopped the operation, halted the anesthesia and cooled him with ice packs, saving his life.</p>
        <p>The next day, Dr. Michael A. Denborough, Dr. Roger R. H. Lovell and their colleagues in Melbourne, Australia, began studying records of the patient's relatives. These consultants and other researchers pinned the man's problem to a rare hereditary biochemical condition now known as malignant hyperthermia. It can strike unpredictably in patients who receive general anesthesia for any procedure in any hospital or out-patient facility.</p>
        <p>The condition, which has been included in the International Classification of Diseases for only five years, is increasingly gaining attention. As it is being diagnosed more often and as more susceptible people are being identified among relatives, experts are taking several steps to reduce the death rate, to avoid complications among survivors, and to prevent cases from developing.</p>
        <p>Although the name malignant hyperthermia implies that the condition is a cancer, it is not. In medical parlance, malignant means fast-moving and deadly; malignant hyperthermia got its name because it rapidly raises a patient's body temperature to lethal levels.</p>
        <p>People affected by the condition appear to have no symptoms unless they receive certain common anesthetics and drugs. These can lead to stiffened muscles, dangerous heart rhythms, temperatures that reach 110 degrees Fahrenheit, kidney failure, bleeding, a variety of other complications, and death.</p>
        <p>Doctors have determined that the medical problems result from an excess of calcium in the muscle cells. But the underlying cause of the condition and why certain general anesthestics trigger it is still unknown.</p>
        <p>The death rate dropped dramatically and steadily after the introduction of a drug called dantrolene in 1979. The drug blocks the build-up of calcium in the cells. Now recovery, not death, is the general rule if dantrolene is injected into the veins in time.</p>
        <p>Many experts urge that dantrolene be kept in all operating rooms, warning that valuable time may be lost if the drug is not at hand. Yet, by one estimate, one hospital in five does not stock dantrolene, largely because of the drug's cost and the rarity of malignant hyperthermia.</p>
        <p>Precise statistics on the number of cases each year are lacking. In the United States, the estimated incidence varies widely, from 1 in 7,000 operations, to 1 in 200,000, depending on the source of the estimate. Malignant hyperthermia seems to be more frequent in men than women and can strike at any age.</p>
        <p>Studies indicate that each child born to a parent with malignant hyperthermia has an even chance of inheriting the condition. But variations occur.</p>
        <p>Because the condition is rare, busy physicians may practice for many years before they see a case, and some doctors still do not know about the condition. Many other physicians who have heard of it fail to identify it in patients becasue they have not asked the patients enough detailed questions about family members who suffered adverse anesthetic reactions or who died during surgery.</p>
        <p>But a greater interest among pediatricians, neurologists and other specialists has spurred further research to seek an easy test that could identify susceptible patients before they receive anesthesia. A small number of medical centers now perform a laboratory test to identify susceptible people among affected families. The test is not practical for routine use, however, because a person must undergo an operation to remove pieces of muscle.</p>
        <p>To help relatives determine if they are susceptible, and to further research efforts, a registry is being established at the Pennsylvania State University College of Medicine at Hershey.</p>
        <p>In addition, the Malignant Hyperthermia Association of the United States, a non-profit organization in Darien, Conn., provides information to patients, their relatives and physicians. The association has set up a telephone hot line, (209)634-4917, for doctors to get immediate advice about the emergency treatment of malignant hyperthermia.</p>
        <p>Two particular drugs are often cited for causing malignant hyperthermia: the anesthetic halothane and a muscle-relaxing drug called succinylcholine that is often administered as part of surgery or before electroshock therapy. But the condition probably can be triggered by any inhaled anesthetic agent.</p>
        <p>Complications are usually recognized in the operating room, but may not develop until the patient is in the recovery room. Sometimes the symptoms last for days and relapse even after treatment.</p>
        <p>Most experts feel it is safe to administer local anesthetics in susceptible patients, said Dr. Henry Rosenberg of Hahnemann University Hospital in Philadelphia. But the experts cannot explain why the local anesthetics do not trigger the condition.</p>
        <p>Alternative general anesthetics, like nitrous oxide, are available for those susceptible to malignant hyperthermia. Doctors also do not know precisely why these anesthetics do not usually trigger the condition. But, like all drugs, they carry their own risks.</p>
        <p>New research indicates that malignant hyperthermia may underlie some symptoms previously thought to be related to a person's job. Dr. Denborough, who now works in Canberra, recently reported a case involving the father of a girl who survived an episode of malignant hyperthermia. The man suffered malaise and stiffness and weakness of his forearms and hands after he began working in a factory that made fire extinguishers.</p>
        <p>Dr. Denborough's team linked the symptoms to a chemical in the extinguisher that was closely related to an anesthetic called halothane. The symptoms disappeared after the man changed jobs.</p>
        <p>Research has been aided by recognition of malignant hyperthermia among pigs, which can develop the condition without receiving a triggering drug. Scientists are also trying to learn whether malignant hyperthermia may be a factor in some cases of heat stroke and sudden infant death syndrome.</p>
        <p>As the researchers gain experience with malignant hyperthermia, they have found that the temperature rise is usually a late development. If they watch for tightened jaw muscles and other changes in patients, they usually can diagnose the condition earlier and prevent catastrophes.</p>
        <p>Now unexplained changes in the blood pressure, heart rate and the amounts of carbon dioxide and oxygen in the blood raise warning flags, as do abnormal heart rhythms. When problems develop during surgery, doctors stop anesthesia, inject dantrolene and take other emergency steps.</p>
        <p>As Dr. F. Richard Ellis, an anesthesiologist at the University of Leeds, England, said in the British Journal of Anesthesia, ''Malignant hyperthermia can no longer be thought of as an act of God.''  THE DOCTOR'S WORLD  Correction:  August 26, 1988, Friday, Late City Final Edition</p>
        <p>A picture caption with The Doctor's World column in Science Times Tuesday misidentified a rare, fatal reaction to general anesthesia. It is malignant hyperthermia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 26, 1988, Friday, Late City Final Edition</p>
        <p>A picture caption with The Doctor's World column in Science Times Tuesday misidentified a rare, fatal reaction to general anesthesia. It is malignant hyperthermia.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
