<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In U.S., Low-Key Calls for a Yes Vote in Canada</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="199150"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEAR, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7D71239F93BA25752C1A96E948260" item-length="1090" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In U.S., Low-Key Calls for a Yes Vote in Canada</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PEAR, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Canadian rejection of the free-trade agreement with the United States would derail years of efforts by Washington and Ottawa to achieve much closer economic and political cooperation at a time the European Community is moving to form a single, unified market.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Canadian rejection of the free-trade agreement with the United States would derail years of efforts by Washington and Ottawa to achieve much closer economic and political cooperation at a time the European Community is moving to form a single, unified market.</p>
        <p>Canadian rejection of the free-trade agreement with the United States would derail years of efforts by Washington and Ottawa to achieve much closer economic and political cooperation at a time the European Community is moving to form a single, unified market.</p>
        <p>Moreover, American officials say that rejection of the pact would be a notable rebuff to the Reagan-Bush Administration, which invested great efforts in negotiating the agreement and steering it through Congress.</p>
        <p>President Reagan made a pitch for the agreement in a speech today, and other American officials said they were distressed to see the growth of Canadian opposition to the pact, which would eliminate virtually all tariffs between the two countries over 10 years. The Americans feel frustrated and helpless because they cannot lobby for the accord, lest they be accused of meddling in Canada's internal affairs.</p>
        <p>And indeed in Quebec, John Turner, the Liberal Party candidate and a bitter critic of the pact, denounced Mr. Reagan's remarks today as ''a major breach of courtesy between the two nations, and the President should have known better.'' A Major Blow to Baker</p>
        <p>Rejection would be particularly irritating to James A. Baker 3d, the man chosen by President-elect Bush to be Secretary of State. As Secretary of the Treasury, Mr. Baker was a zealous supporter of the agreement and rescued it when negotiations nearly collapsed earlier this year.</p>
        <p>A variety of experts said the agreement is expected to increase jobs, exports and output while lowering prices for American consumers. If the agreement is defeated, they said, it may well be more difficult for Mr. Bush to resist protectionist pressures on other fronts.</p>
        <p>The United States and Canada have the world's largest two-way trading relationship, and Canada is the United States' fastest-growing export market. Trade in goods and commodities totaled $131 billion last year, and that does not include the value of services, which is more difficult to measure.</p>
        <p>The trade agreement is the central issue in Canadian elections on Monday. Prime Minister Brian Mulroney's Progressive Conservative Party staunchly defends the pact, while the Liberal Party opposes it and says it would repudiate it. Would Go Into Effect Jan. 1</p>
        <p>The agreement, if approved, would go into effect Jan. 1. Canadian critics say it would turn Canada into a virtual colony of the United States and would endanger Canada's network of social programs, including health insurance and old-age pensions. They also say that the bulk of Canadian exports already enter the United States tariff-free, and that a thriving two-way trade would continue, regardless of the pact's fate.</p>
        <p>Proponents here and in Canada assert that the trade pact is essential to building an even greater economic partnership between the two countries. Senator John Glenn, Democrat of Ohio, said the agreement would ''make both of our economies more competitive.''</p>
        <p>The debate over the agreement comes as the European Community is tearing down its internal trade barriers and moving to form a single, unified market of more than 320 million people by 1992. Advocates of the United States-Canada pact say it is all the more important for the North American neighbors to cooperate because they might be locked out of a protectionist ''fortress Europe.'' Which Products Would Be Sent</p>
        <p>American lawmakers see new opportunities to export California wine, West Virginia coal and Oregon lumber, not to mention computers, telecommunications equipment and countless types of fruits and vegetables.</p>
        <p>Senator John H. Chafee, Republican of Rhode Island, has praised the agreement because it would provide New England with secure energy supplies, hydroelectric power and natural gas. Senator Lloyd Bentsen, Democrat of Texas, has said it would give the United States ''almost unlimited access to invest in Canadian energy'' resources.</p>
        <p>No one seems to believe that rejection of the pact would cripple the enormous on-going trade between the two countries. But proponents do warn that dealings between the two neighbors might be reduced to an unending series of squabbles over minor trade issues.</p>
        <p>''Canada wanted this agreement in the first place, and they wanted it more than we did,'' said Senator Max Baucus, a Montana Democrat who supports the agreement with some reservations. ''If Canada now turns around and rejects it, and if they come forward with a proposal in another area like acid rain, it would be a bit more difficult. Americans may think: 'Here they come again. We listened to their entreaties on trade; they backed down and said no. How can we be sure they'll follow through?' '' Energy Department Concerns</p>
        <p>United States Government agencies strongly supported the trade agreement, but a few had reservations. Some Energy Department officials, for example, and some members of Congress said the pact could hurt American producers of uranium and natural gas by making it easier for Canada to export those products to the United States.</p>
        <p>American officials and academic experts spoke more in sorrow than in anger about the possibility that Canada might reject the trade agreement.</p>
        <p>''When the bilateral relationship does not go well, the Canadians tend to take separate, independent and sometimes even arbitrary directions in their foreign policy,'' said Lansing Lamont, director of Canadian affairs at the Americas Society in New York, a forum for discussion of Western Hemisphere affairs.</p>
        <p>If Canada rejects the pact, he said, ''there are a lot of areas where both countries might decide to flex their nationalist or independent feelings.'' Turn to Europe and East Asia</p>
        <p>Alan K. Henrikson, a professor at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy at Tufts University, said that if Canada rejected the pact, it would probably seek better access to markets outside North America, in Europe and East Asia.</p>
        <p>Members of Congress and academic experts predicted also that there would be increased pressure for protection of domestic industries in the United States and Canada if the pact dies.</p>
        <p>Prof. Charles F. Doran, director of the Center of Canadian Studies at Johns Hopkins University, said, ''Any aggrieved party, any interest group that feels it's been treated badly in this arrangement will come to Congress and ask for protectionist measures, to make sure that a free-trade agreement like this never happens to them again.'' Such industries might include producers of uranium, wheat, oil, natural gas, steel and car parts, he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
