<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chemicals Affecting Ozone Face Limits on Production</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="167149"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HALONS (CHEMICAL)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DF103FF931A3575BC0A96E948260" item-length="507" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chemicals Affecting Ozone Face Limits on Production</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Environmental Protection Agency today announced final regulations for cutting production and use of chemicals widely believed to be depleting the earth's protective ozone layer. The move would bring the United States into compliance with an international agreement to curb the substances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Environmental Protection Agency today announced final regulations for cutting production and use of chemicals widely believed to be depleting the earth's protective ozone layer. The move would bring the United States into compliance with an international agreement to curb the substances.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency today announced final regulations for cutting production and use of chemicals widely believed to be depleting the earth's protective ozone layer. The move would bring the United States into compliance with an international agreement to curb the substances.</p>
        <p>The regulations require initially freezing production of the chemicals at 1986 levels and then reducing production in stages over a period of years. They do not propose eliminating the chemicals, but the agency hopes industrial users will eventually turn voluntarily to substitutes.</p>
        <p>Industrial and developing nations drafted a treaty in Montreal last September to cut worldwide production and consumption of two families of chemicals: chlorofluorocarbons, which are widely used in refrigeration and air conditioning, and halon, used in fire-extinguishing foam. U.S. Ratified Treaty</p>
        <p>The treaty was signed by 37 nations and has been ratified by six, including the United States. The E.P.A. regulations are to take effect next July 1 if international ratification is completed as expected by Jan. 1.</p>
        <p>The agency said it was seeking comment on ways to eliminate what could be multibillion-dollar windfall profits to chemical producers as an unintended result of the production cutbacks.</p>
        <p>Prices will increase as a result of more demand for a dwindling supply of chemicals, and E.P.A. officials said they wanted comment on two methods that could take excess profits from the companies and put them in the Treasury. A regulatory fee similar to a tax would be one method considered; auctioning production rights another.</p>
        <p>Excess profits, some fear, could create an incentive for producers to delay the introduction of substitute chemicals with lower profit margins.</p>
        <p>Regulators hope restricted supplies, higher prices and the availability of substitutes will move users to the alternatives, said Eileen Claussen, acting E.P.A. deputy assistant administrator for air and radiation. But if these measures fail to move some large industries to alternatives, the agency would consider restricting or banning use of the older chemicals in some circumstances, she said.</p>
        <p>Scientists believe the chemicals drift to the upper atmosphere and destroy ozone, which filters out some of the harmful ultraviolet rays of the sun.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. estimates that the new regulations will prevent 3.7 million deaths in the United States by 2075, primarily by preventing skin cancer.</p>
        <p>The Natural Resources Defense Council, a Washington-based environmental group, called the scheduled 50 percent cut in chlorofluorocarbon production by 1998 inadequate, saying at least 85 percent of the chemical's emissions must be cut just to keep atmospheric ozone at current levels.</p>
        <p>The Alliance for Responsible CFC Policy, an industry group representing the seven American makers of the chemicals, supported the regulations as cost-effective and the least-disruptive method of complying with the international accord, but said any discussion of windfall profits was premature.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
