<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Real Issues</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="178351"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="ABROAD AT HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1988</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG ADDICTION AND ABUSE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, ANTHONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUKAKIS, MICHAEL S (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DF173BF932A2575AC0A96E948260" item-length="767" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Real Issues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anthony Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, ANTHONY</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: What are the serious problems facing this country? Put that question to Americans, whatever their party or voting inclination, and I think their answers would tend to focus on the same main points.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: What are the serious problems facing this country? Put that question to Americans, whatever their party or voting inclination, and I think their answers would tend to focus on the same main points.</p>
        <p>What are the serious problems facing this country? Put that question to Americans, whatever their party or voting inclination, and I think their answers would tend to focus on the same main points.</p>
        <p>1. Economic uncertainty. Enormous debt overhangs the United States, at home and in the world. Unending budget deficits have swollen the national debt. The trade deficit has been financed by borrowing from abroad to the extent that we now have the largest foreign debt of any country.</p>
        <p>People may not be sophisticated about those things - I am not - but we are right to worry about their consequences. We know that, because of the debt, any financial incident - a large bank failure, another stock-market plunge - is more likely to threaten confidence. And we know that our reliance on foreign capital limits our independence as a nation.</p>
        <p>2. Competitiveness. Our old faith in the superiority of American products has been shaken. We fear that Japan and others have passed us in design and price. In our fear we become defensive, protectionist. And underneath we wonder whether, and how, we can recover our competitive edge.</p>
        <p>Writing last February in The New York Review of Books, Felix Rohatyn said that Japan and West Germany had gained increasing economic power and independence, relative to the U.S., on the basis of ''surplus capital, technology, education and discipline.'' Those are the very areas in which Americans are concerned about what has happened to our society.</p>
        <p>3. Education. For family after family across the country this is the deepest concern. We read about Japanese education, and we know we are way behind in scholastic achievement and discipline. But of course the concern is not just national but personal: for our children.</p>
        <p>Too many American schools are disaster areas today. In languages, mathematics, history, achievement is far behind a state school in Europe.</p>
        <p>4. Drugs. The menace of narcotics eats at our society as it does not that of Japan or Germany or France or Korea. It corrupts urban life, and now the suburbs, too.</p>
        <p>Our jails are filled, but drugs are still easily available. Politicians talk about using the armed forces to patrol the borders against drugs -when cocaine is so easy to bring in that no conceivable program will stop the supply. The need is to reduce demand: that is, to make this a saner, less drug-dependent society. And how do we do that?</p>
        <p>5. The Environment. This summer of sickened oceans and thinning ozone layer and the greenhouse effect has made us acutely aware of what we are doing to our surroundings. We know that action is needed on a large scale, nationally and internationally.</p>
        <p>Those are some of the problems on the minds of Americans today. Not on that list is what George Bush has tried to make the prime issue of 1988: his opponent's patriotism. Governor Dukakis's veto of an unconstitutional bill to make teachers lead students in the Pledge of Allegiance has nothing to do with the major problems ahead.</p>
        <p>The patriotism ''issue'' is there, we know, because slinging mud can be effective in American campaigns. Or at least it can until people recognize the slime and its authors for what they are.</p>
        <p>But listing the real issues makes it clear that there is another reason for the Vice President's descent into the mud. Insinuations about ''patriotism'' distract attention from a record that would be hard to defend on many of those real issues.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush served in an Administration that rolled up more national debt than all the other U.S. Governments combined, from President Washington on, so that is not a comfortable subject. The same Administration turned the United States into a debtor nation. Having failed to generate American savings and capital, it borrowed abroad.</p>
        <p>Education? This Administration cut back funds and tried to abolish the Education Department. Its last Secretary of Education, who said he wanted to lift our sights, instead takes the mucker pose and mocks respect for the Constitution.</p>
        <p>Drugs? This Administration, and Mr. Bush's own aides, worked with drug-runners in their lawless efforts to supply the Nicaraguan contras. George Bush, who went to private schools that did not recite the Pledge of Allegiance, acts as if that were our educational problem - while in the real world teachers struggle to keep their classrooms free of drugs.</p>
        <p>On the environment, there have been eight years of pillage and obfuscation. And here, as on the other issues, the record is barren of any sign that Vice President Bush has ever urged the Administration to face the real issues.</p>
        <p>ABROAD AT HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
