<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Time of Challenge</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="162002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="ABROAD AT HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, ANTHONY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3D9143AF934A25754C0A96E948260" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Time of Challenge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anthony Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, ANTHONY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In the convention season of American politics we are preoccupied with tactics. Elections have to be won.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In the convention season of American politics we are preoccupied with tactics. Elections have to be won.</p>
        <p>In the convention season of American politics we are preoccupied with tactics. Elections have to be won.</p>
        <p>But something deeper touches our consciousness this summer. We are beginning to understand that new realities in the world challenge some of our most familiar ways of thinking, our premises. A time of fundamental change will confront the next President, whoever that is.</p>
        <p>One example is in world politics. For the last 40 years the basic fact of international life has been the conflict between the United States and the Soviet Union. Tension has waxed and waned, but the struggle for advantage in military power and political influence has never stopped.</p>
        <p>Now the Soviet Union is in an uproar of change. No one thinks that Mikhail Gorbachev is about to transform his country into a Western democracy, but even the most skeptical of American Kremlinologists agree that something real is happening. For the first time in 60 years differing voices are being heard in the U.S.S.R.</p>
        <p>The relationship between the two superpowers has already been affected. Who would have believed, a few years ago, that the Soviet Chief of Staff would spend a week in the United States, consult at the Pentagon and be welcomed at the White House by Ronald Reagan?</p>
        <p>Marshal Sergei Akhromeyev has just made that visit. It ended with an agreement to form a joint military working group that will seek ways of preventing dangerous incidents. The Chairman of the U.S. Joint Chiefs, Adm. William Crowe, is to return the visit next year, and U.S. and Soviet military commanders in Europe will meet.</p>
        <p>Such occasions do not signify affection. They do signify a new perception of common interests - in reducing the mutual fears and distortions that endanger both countries and that feed their arms race.</p>
        <p>The idea of common interests is growing in the broader diplomatic field, too. If there is a chance now to end the terrible war in Angola and bring Namibia to independence -and there seems to be - it is because the U.S. and the U.S.S.R. are both pushing for a settlement. We think about the possibility of such collaboration in addressing the Israeli-Palestinian conflict.</p>
        <p>Even the beginnings of change in the superpower relationship pose great questions for American policy. How do we seize the chance to reduce our armories, and the burden of military costs, while maintaining our security and our allies' confidence? How can we most effectively encourage the political process begun in the Soviet Union by Mr. Gorbachev?</p>
        <p>There may be large domestic consequences, too. The Massachusetts economic miracle in which Governor Dukakis rightly takes such pride was based in part on high-technology defense work. If that declines, how can we encourage innovative civilian production? America's economic future may depend on the answer.</p>
        <p>A second example of new realities, even more profound, is the stress in the world's environment - or, more exactly, our awareness of that stress.</p>
        <p>Day after day, this summer, we have had warnings of danger to the natural order that supports life.</p>
        <p>Miles of beaches near New York have been closed because of waves of sewage and hospital debris in the water. Forests in New England and Canada have shown appalling signs of damage by acid rain.</p>
        <p>''The environment is trying to say something,'' a scientist remarked after a massive fish kill in the ocean off New Jersey. Each incident tells us that nature can no longer handle the consequences of unthinking human behavior.</p>
        <p>Beyond the individual instances of pollution there is the broad scientific agreement, in recent months, that the burning of fossil fuels is creating a ''greenhouse effect'' on Earth. Temperatures are going to climb to the point where there will be devastating damage unless we switch to other sources of energy.</p>
        <p>The challenge in all this is to collective action. Individually, we are selfish. The Edison Electric Institute, a trade organization, says with ineffable blindness: ''Current scientific evidence shows there is no acid rain crisis.''</p>
        <p>In other words, it is a political challenge. Over these last years we have luxuriated in the belief that private action can solve all problems if only government gets out of the way. But it will require government, of the highest order, to deal with realities of these dimensions.</p>
        <p>ABROAD AT HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
