<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deregulation Has Gone Too Far, Many Tell the New Administration</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="205828"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAZARDOUS AND TOXIC SUBSTANCES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERKE, RICHARD L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D91330F932A25751C1A96E948260" item-length="1529" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deregulation Has Gone Too Far, Many Tell the New Administration</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERKE, RICHARD L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President-elect Bush faces growing Congressional and public pressure to revitalize the Federal regulatory machinery, which as the Reagan Administration's apostle of deregulation he himself partly dismantled.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President-elect Bush faces growing Congressional and public pressure to revitalize the Federal regulatory machinery, which as the Reagan Administration's apostle of deregulation he himself partly dismantled.</p>
        <p>President-elect Bush faces growing Congressional and public pressure to revitalize the Federal regulatory machinery, which as the Reagan Administration's apostle of deregulation he himself partly dismantled.</p>
        <p>Lawmakers and analysts say the pressure is fed by a heightened public uneasiness about deregulatory shortcomings that touch the daily lives of millions of Americans: from delays at airports and strains on the air traffic control system to the presence of hazardous chemicals in the workplace to worries about the safety of money deposited in savings institutions.</p>
        <p>Many lawmakers, especially Democrats, have long questioned the concept of broad deregulation itself and are poised to push for new controls, particularly those dealing with the savings and loan industry, the environment and public health and safety.</p>
        <p>''There is not the enthusiasm for deregulation that there once was,'' said Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan, Democrat of New York. ''Try to get a flight to Albany from Washington, and you'll know why.'' D'Amato in Agreement</p>
        <p>He gets agreement from his fellow New Yorker in the Senate, Alfonse M. D'Amato, a Republican. ''I don't see deregulation as a driving force anymore,'' Mr. D'Amato said.</p>
        <p>Representative Dan Glickman, a Kansas Democrat, said that based on his conversations with constituents and reading of opinion polls, ''a majority of Americans do not want to stay on the course of deregulation.'' The Congressman, who headed a House panel that recently concluded that deregulation had jeopardized public health and safety, vowed to push for more Government jurisdiction in those areas and added, ''I don't think you can ask the free market to make sure that airplanes are working or that the cockpit crew is rested.''</p>
        <p>The unfettering of industry and the Federal bureaucracy from red tape was a priority of Ronald Reagan, who was elected President in 1980 with a promise to ''get the Government off the backs of the people.'' On his third day in office, he appointed Mr. Bush chairman of the Task Force on Regulatory Relief, which over the next several years identified for the President those areas deemed most in need of a relaxation or outright freedom from Government controls. It is uncertain whether Mr. Bush will seek further limits on the authority of some 100 regulatory agencies, boards and commissions that are independent. But there is some evidence that he will not.</p>
        <p>He did not emphasize deregulation as an issue in the Presidential race, although a campaign flier did say that one of his ''proudest accomplishments as Vice President has been to help eliminate needless Government regulations.''</p>
        <p>On occasion, in fact, Mr. Bush seems inclined toward some greater regulation himself, as when he pledges more aggressive efforts to clean up the environment. Another signal came in his decision to keep Treasury Secretary Nicholas F. Brady, whose appointment in August followed his chairmanship of a Presidential commission that studied the stock market crash of October 1987 and urged stiffer regulation of Wall Street. Retaining the Gains</p>
        <p>Some advocates of deregulation are even pushing to loosen Government control in areas like telecommunications and natural gas.</p>
        <p>C. Boyden Gray, who served on the deregulation task force and has been designated by the President-elect as White House counsel, said he expected Mr. Bush to have a ''continued commitment to minimal regulation'' except where public health and safety or Congressional mandate makes it impossible. Deregulation has been a great success, Mr. Gray said, explaining that there was little need to mention it in the fall campaign because ''the system is fairly ingrained now.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Gray and others who fought regulations in the Reagan years now talk less of expanding that effort than of resisting Congressional moves to reimpose them.</p>
        <p>''Regulatory relief was one of the major priorities for the Reagan Administration,'' said James C. Miller 3d, who was executive director of the deregulation task force before serving as director of the White House Office of Management and Budget. ''It certainly does not have that level of priority right now. We have to preserve what has been accomplished and hold the largely deregulatory gains in areas such as airlines and trucking.''</p>
        <p>That sentiment is put more bluntly by William A. Niskanen, a former member of Mr. Reagan's Council of Economic Advisers who is now president of the Cato Institute, a research group here that promotes free-market policies. ''I don't expect much deregulatory initiative from the Bush Administration,'' he said. ''Deregulation seems to be one of those things where the political costs are higher than the payoffs.'' Blistering Critique</p>
        <p>The outcry for renewed regulation comes not only from some members of Congress but also from interest groups like Public Citizen, an organization founded by Ralph Nader that recently published a scathing critique of deregulation's effects. And the nonpartisan General Accounting Office, Congress's investigative arm, recommended last month that Mr. Bush strengthen or improve enforcement by several agencies. For example, it concluded that relaxation of limits on the powers of banks had resulted in ''a risky hodgepodge of banking and other functions that could imperil the safety and soundness of the banking system.''</p>
        <p>Some analysts praise the drive to deregulate. Murray L. Weidenbaum, former chief economist to Mr. Reagan, argues that the deregulation efforts of the last decade, many of which originated in the Carter Administration, have resulted in ''remarkable benefits for the American economy.'' Focus of New Pressure</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the Bush Administration will be prodded to impose new regulations, or to tighten those already in place, in these and other areas:</p>
        <p>ENVIRONMENT: Mr. Bush himself has pledged to clean up the environment with programs to preserve wetlands, reduce acid rain and curb global warming caused by industrial gases. Mr. Gray says some of these goals can be accomplished through ''market incentives'' that do not involve regulation, like user fees, but acknowledges that ''it would be fair to contemplate'' that there may be some new environmental regulation. For its part, the General Accounting Office concluded that the Interior Department ''must put more teeth into enforcement of environmental standards relating to surface mining,'' and called upon the Environmental Protection Agency to address ''widespread and persistent noncompliance with hazardous waste regulations.''</p>
        <p>SAVINGS AND LOANS: Many Democrats place blame for the savings and loan crisis on inadequate Government supervision of the effects of the thrift industry's deregulation. They say approval of relief measures sought by the industry will have to be linked to new regulation. ''Banking deregulation has enriched scoundrels and knaves and created an ongoing scandal that could fill the jailhouses,'' said Representative John D. Dingell, the Michigan Democrat who heads the House Energy and Commerce Committee. And the General Accounting Office, in concluding that nearly a third of the nation's savings and loan institutions were ''insolvent or nearly so,'' cited ''poorly implemented deregulation'' as a cause.</p>
        <p>PUBLIC HEALTH AND SAFETY: Congressman Glickman, who headed the panel that faulted Mr. Bush's task force, said there was a consensus in Congress for greater Government involvement in areas like food inspection, workplace safety and transportation. He added that ''when it comes to pure economic things, I am less troubled'' by deregulation than when public safety is involved. In its study, Public Citizen asserted that Mr. Bush's task force had shown ''a callous disregard for the value of human life and a shocking readiness to apply an accountant's spread sheet to rules that protect our lives.'' In one of dozens of examples, it said, ''At least 40,000 deaths and one million injuries can be traced to the Administration's delay in requiring air bags and automatic safety belts in cars.''</p>
        <p>Partly because deregulation of major industries like the airlines, telephones and trucking was achieved early, the pace of the Reagan Administration's own effort has slowed in recent years, at least in terms of formal action. Much of what the Administration has done involves de facto deregulation: rather than repeal rules, it has reduced technical staffs and inspectors at a number of agencies.</p>
        <p>The Administration has also achieved a form of deregulation through relaxed antitrust enforcement, which has been criticized as a boon to corporate takeover efforts. Mr. Bush said little in the campaign about antitrust enforcement, and analysts disagree whether he will pursue it more vigorously.</p>
        <p>But Senator John C. Danforth, Republican of Missouri, says it is unlikely that the new President will tolerate Congressional moves for broad re-regulation of major industries.</p>
        <p>''The fact that George Bush will be in the White House,'' Mr. Danforth said, ''should say to a lot of people in Congress that while re-regulation is something people talk about, it's not something that's going to happen.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
