<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cuomo's War; Lilco's Victory?</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="199642"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SHOREHAM (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SHOREHAM NUCLEAR POWER PLANT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FELDMAN, RONALD (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFD91538F933A15752C1A96E948260" item-length="352" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cuomo's War; Lilco's Victory?</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Mario Cuomo's comments about Shoreham make clear that our Governor does not have the courage to be a political leader. Knowing that most Long Islanders oppose the opening of a nuclear plant, he lists a number of reasons why it shouldn't. Perhaps most disingenuous is the notion that we shall pay more if Shoreham opens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Mario Cuomo's comments about Shoreham make clear that our Governor does not have the courage to be a political leader. Knowing that most Long Islanders oppose the opening of a nuclear plant, he lists a number of reasons why it shouldn't. Perhaps most disingenuous is the notion that we shall pay more if Shoreham opens.</p>
        <p>Mario Cuomo's comments about Shoreham make clear that our Governor does not have the courage to be a political leader. Knowing that most Long Islanders oppose the opening of a nuclear plant, he lists a number of reasons why it shouldn't. Perhaps most disingenuous is the notion that we shall pay more if Shoreham opens. He neglects to mention the debt service for buying the plant.</p>
        <p>A more compelling argument for nuclear power is safety. The possibility of harm from radioactivity is extremely remote, as close to impossible as any threat we face. The reality of illness resulting from the burning of fossil fuels is upon us. People are already dying from the effects of air pollution and the greenhouse effect, due in large measure to the increased amount of carbon dioxide generated by oil or coal burning.</p>
        <p>Another alternative is to give up much of our air-conditioning and other electric powered comforts. I have seen no serious suggestions from any public figure that we consider this.</p>
        <p>If we compare the proven safety of nuclear power - France generates almost three-quarters of its electricity in nuclear plants - with the proven danger of burning coal and oil, it takes little imagination to decide which is the greater hazard.</p>
        <p>It may take another or several summers of increasing numbers of victims of heat illness to convince a majority of Long Islanders that they are better with nuclear power.</p>
        <p>If we had political leaders who were willing to take unpopular courses of action, they might encounter greater electoral hazards, but would protect our population from greater health hazards.</p>
        <p>The specter of Chernobyl should not deter us, because that plant was utterly primitive, in terms of safety, by the standards of even our very first plants built in the 50's. Our newest plant designs eliminate the chances of human error and containment are completely effective.</p>
        <p>What remains to be done is to convince the public of these facts. This is clearly more difficult than playing the game of political expediency despite the costs in human misery.  RONALD FELDMAN, M.D.  East Norwich</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
