<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AS POLLS PLUMMET, MULRONEY ATTACKS</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="194254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURNS, JOHN F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MULRONEY, BRIAN (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DE143EF930A35752C1A96E948260" item-length="825" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AS POLLS PLUMMET, MULRONEY ATTACKS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BURNS, JOHN F</byline>
      <dateline>VANCOUVER, British Columbia, Nov. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: With opinion polls showing their prospects for re-election in jeopardy, the governing Progressive Conservatives have begun to fight back against opposition assertions that they have endangered Canada's future in the free-trade pact with the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: With opinion polls showing their prospects for re-election in jeopardy, the governing Progressive Conservatives have begun to fight back against opposition assertions that they have endangered Canada's future in the free-trade pact with the United States.</p>
        <p>With opinion polls showing their prospects for re-election in jeopardy, the governing Progressive Conservatives have begun to fight back against opposition assertions that they have endangered Canada's future in the free-trade pact with the United States.</p>
        <p>In a campaign swing through British Columbia, Prime Minister Brian Mulroney has unveiled a tough new approach to the opposition Liberals and New Democrats.</p>
        <p>The Conservatives' allies in the business establishment have pitched in with a new advertising campaign to persuade the country's 17 million registered voters that rejecting the trade pact would jeopardize the two million Canadian jobs that are said to depend on American trade.</p>
        <p>In a speech to an enthusiastic crowd here Tuesday night, Mr. Mulroney described as ''despicable'' the opposition leaders' warnings that the accord would invite United States attacks on the country's social programs, including its old-age pensions, its system of support for depressed regions and its medical insurance program.</p>
        <p>The Tory Prime Minister noted that ''universal'' social programs are specifically protected under international trading rules, and said it was ''in the extreme dishonest'' to suggest otherwise.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mulroney also ridiculed suggestions by John N. Turner of the Liberals and Edward Broadbent of the New Democrats that Canada's independence is at stake. ''They wrap themselves in the Canadian flag in the hope that you won't notice that they're naked underneath,'' Mr. Mulroney said. A Strained Conversation</p>
        <p>Referring to Mr. Turner's pledge to discard the pact if his party is elected, the Prime Minister sardonically imagined Mr. Turner explaining his action at the White House.</p>
        <p>''By the way, I've just torn up the free-trade agreement, but how would you like negotiate an acid rain treaty?'' Mr. Mulroney suggested his opponent saying. He added: ''That's for juvenile delinquents. This is not for Canada.''</p>
        <p>The pact, already signed by President Reagan, is to go into effect Jan. 1, but Mr. Turner has said he would follow a Liberal election victory with an early trip to Washington to reassure the United States.</p>
        <p>The attacks marked a shift in electoral strategy by the Conservatives, who entered the campaign for the Nov. 21 election with a low-key approach.</p>
        <p>Because polls in the last year had showed low ratings for Mr. Mulroney when he displayed an instinct for combative politics, the party's original plan for the election had him campaigning in what aides described as a ''prime ministerial'' fashion, sticking carefully to prepared scripts and paying little heed to the opposition.</p>
        <p>Because polls also showed uncertain levels of support for the free-trade agreement, the strategy also stressed the broader Government record, primarily its success in sustaining a six-year economic boom. Quickly Recast Strategy</p>
        <p>But after a series of polls last weekend began showing the Conservatives' 10-point lead in the polls evaporating and the Liberals moving into a tie or better, the 49-year-old Prime Minister and his advisers met hurriedly and decided to confront opposition attacks on the trade agreement head-on.</p>
        <p>The change in approach was hastened after telephone calls from alarmed business leaders who feared the previously unthinkable - that the pact might not be ratified.</p>
        <p>Business concerns sharpened on Monday, when the Canadian dollar dropped sharply against the United States dollar.</p>
        <p>The Canadian Alliance for Trade and Job Opportunities, one of many business groups supporting the pact, said it would spend $1.3 million on a pamphlet to be enclosed in leading newspapers citing the dependence of many Canadian jobs on American trade.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mulroney, who had been carrying the Conservatives' national campaign almost singlehandedly, got new assistance in promoting the pact from his two top economic aides, Finance Minister Michael Wilson and Trade Minister John Crosbie.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilson told a business group in Ottawa that an opposition victory would invite the United States to accede to pressures from auto-producing states to cancel the 1965 auto trade pact, which has helped Canada maintain substantial merchandise-trade surpluses with the United States.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Crosbie warned that Canada would be throwing away an opportunity to become the only nation other than Israel to have ''tariff-free access to the world's largest market.''</p>
        <p>The Conservatives' anxieties were compounded by polls showing that support for free trade had slipped badly even in those provinces where it was previously strong - including Alberta, Saskatchewan and Quebec.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Mulroney found support from an unusual ally, Premier Robert Bourassa of Quebec, a Liberal who has made little secret of his hope that Mr. Mulroney will win the election.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bourassa said Canada will face ''very serious consequences'' if the Liberals win the election and refuse to proceed with some form of liberalized trading agreement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
