<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World Debates How to Trade a Food Supply in Jeopardy</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="205742"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GRAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CROP CONTROLS AND SUBSIDIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crop Controls and Subsidies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DE1E31F932A25751C1A96E948260" item-length="864" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World Debates How to Trade a Food Supply in Jeopardy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE H. FARNSWORTH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</byline>
      <dateline>MONTREAL</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IN the United States, grain stockpiles are down 135 million tons from their record high in 1986, largely because of last summer's drought. In the rest of the world, grain stocks have fallen an additional 50 million tons, creating what some see as a precarious balance between the world's supply of food and the demand for it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IN the United States, grain stockpiles are down 135 million tons from their record high in 1986, largely because of last summer's drought. In the rest of the world, grain stocks have fallen an additional 50 million tons, creating what some see as a precarious balance between the world's supply of food and the demand for it.</p>
        <p>IN the United States, grain stockpiles are down 135 million tons from their record high in 1986, largely because of last summer's drought. In the rest of the world, grain stocks have fallen an additional 50 million tons, creating what some see as a precarious balance between the world's supply of food and the demand for it.</p>
        <p>Comparisons are being made to the food crisis year of 1973, and some are invoking the name of Thomas Malthus, who warned 200 years ago that population growth was destined to outpace the world's ability to feed itself.</p>
        <p>Yet policy makers in the United States, Canada, Australia and other major food-producing countries, particularly outside Europe, say a pessimistic view of world food supplies is as unjustified today as it was in the days of Malthus.</p>
        <p>They make these arguments:</p>
        <p>* Farm productivity has been growing; in the United States it has risen 30 percent in the last decade.</p>
        <p>* Future advances in technology offer the prospect of new plant varieties resistant to insects, heat, drought, frost and disease.</p>
        <p>* Wider use of technology now available could also increase food production.</p>
        <p>Thus the experts, particularly in the United States, say the drought is masking what they consider the main problem of the future for agricultural trade policy - not a lack of food but an oversupply, stimulated by the $220 billion a year that developed countries pay to subsidize farmers.</p>
        <p>''In a world of subsidized agriculture, the long-term tendency to over-production lurks only slightly below the surface,'' said Ewen M. Wilson, the Agriculture Department's top economist.</p>
        <p>Such views are sharply contested by other experts, who argue that changes may be taking place in the world's environment that will make it more difficult for underdeveloped countries to produce food or gain access to it at reasonable prices.</p>
        <p>Still, in global talks in Montreal last week, trade ministers from 96 countries were arguing over American demands that the subsidies and other measures that distort trade in agriculture be phased out early in the next century. The main opposition came from the European Community, which rejects the notion that farm protection should ever end.</p>
        <p>When Europeans talk of farm subsidies, their arguments include the notion that the world cannot be certain of an oversupply of food. They are also deeply interested, for domestic political and social reasons, in preserving the economic survival and way of life of their farmers.</p>
        <p>In Montreal, the United States and the 12-nation European bloc were left in deadlock. Trade ministers had some successes in other aspects of the negotiations, whose aim was to advance a new round of trade liberalization talks. But, in the end, the negotiators adopted a United States proposal to put everything on hold for four months to give them a chance to break the farm stalemate.</p>
        <p>Washington is pressing Brussels on agriculture, American officials say, because of ''near chaos'' in global agriculture - a condition they trace largely to European policies. These policies, they say, stimulate overproduction, which in turn results in the unloading of surpluses on the world. The Americans say this undercuts the long-run ability of farmers in other countries to make a living.</p>
        <p>Argentina and Uruguay export wheat and beef and are regarded as being among the world's lowest-cost producers. Yet Barber B. Conable Jr., the World Bank president, noted in Montreal that their share of the world market dropped from 11 percent to 3 percent over the last 15 years while the European Community became one of the world's largest exporters. The United States also takes some blame, for example, for tighter American import quotas that have cost Caribbean islands $250 million in annual sugar exports.</p>
        <p>But freer trade in agriculture has become such an important goal for the United States that it has said it would drop its protection for sugar, dairy and other American farmers if other countries cut supports as well.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, the North American drought, by raising prices and thus reducing the cost of export subsidies, has curbed some of the pressure on Western Europe to restructure agriculture. Some experts argue that the effects of the drought were made more severe by the so-called greenhouse effect, described as a slow warming of the world that results particularly from the burning of fossil fuels. In this view, the effort to get rid of subsidies is misplaced because last summer's disaster will be repeated and the world needs to protect agriculture in the interests of preserving food security.</p>
        <p>''The talks in Montreal were focused on surpluses that may no longer exist, or if they do exist are not real in the sense that they are being produced with the unsustainable use of land and water,'' said Lester R. Brown, president of the Worldwatch Institute.</p>
        <p>Those who want farm trade policies restructured counter that the efficient exporters who are best able to respond to shortages are the ones who could be forced under by heavily subsidized competition. William M. Miner, a Canadian agricultural expert, put the argument this way: ''Bad weather is not an excuse for bad policies.''  THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
