<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suit Seeks to Force U.S. to Order Rules To Curb Acid Rain</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="200798"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND CLAIMS AGAINST GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7D6133BF930A15752C1A96E948260" item-length="465" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suit Seeks to Force U.S. to Order Rules To Curb Acid Rain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Nine states have filed a new lawsuit against the Environmental Protection Agency in their five-year legal effort to force the agency to order new measures to curb acid rain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Nine states have filed a new lawsuit against the Environmental Protection Agency in their five-year legal effort to force the agency to order new measures to curb acid rain.</p>
        <p>Nine states have filed a new lawsuit against the Environmental Protection Agency in their five-year legal effort to force the agency to order new measures to curb acid rain.</p>
        <p>The states, joined by the National Audubon Society, asked the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia on Monday to review the environmental agency's refusal to act on their petition seeking the curbs.</p>
        <p>That petition called on the agency to publish for public comment the determination of the enviornmental agency's chief in the Carter Administration that sulfur dioxide emissions from plants and factories in the United States were harming Canada. Such a publication is the first step in drafting a regulation.</p>
        <p>The Canadian province of Ontario and two environmental organizations filed a similar lawsuit in the same court on Nov. 1.</p>
        <p>In the new suit, the plaintiffs are New York, New Jersey, Minnesota and the six New England states.</p>
        <p>A few days before leaving office in January 1981, Douglas Costle, the chief of the Environmental Protection Agency, wrote the Secretary of State at that time, Edmund S. Muskie, that the sulfur dioxide emissions were harming Canada because they were being transformed chemically in the atmosphere into sulfuric acid and falling to the earth as acid rain in eastern Canada. Formal Ruling Is Sought</p>
        <p>Many of these sulfur dioxide emissions originate in coal-fired plants and factories in the Middle West.</p>
        <p>In their new suit the states are, in effect, trying to force the agency to make the same determination that Mr. Costle made. Once that determination is made, the law requires the enviornmental agency to order the states involved to revise their air pollution control plans to eliminate the offending emissions.</p>
        <p>The appeals court, in a decision upheld by the Supreme Court, ruled earlier that a letter to the Secretary of State was not formal enough, and any such determination had to be made in formal proceedings leading to a regulation.</p>
        <p>Ontario, the nine states and various environmental groups all petitioned for such formal proceedings, but in October the environmental agency said it would not act on those petitions because it still did not know enough to tell states in the Midwest how to revise their air pollution control measures.</p>
        <p>Scientists say acid rain has killed fresh water life in hundreds of lakes in the Adirondack Mountains of New York State and in other lakes in the Northeast and Canada. Canada says 14,000 lakes in the eastern half of that country have been damaged.</p>
        <p>David Wooley, an Assistant Attorney General of New York State, said in Albany that the states are entitled to sue because they are harmed by the same pollutant harming Canada. He said he had asked that the state's lawsuit be consolidated with Ontario's.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
