<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plastics Industry, Under Pressure, Begins to Invest in Recycling</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19880831T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="175513"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLASTICS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KLOCKENBRINK, MYRA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2DE1330F933A0575BC0A96E948260" item-length="1183" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plastics Industry, Under Pressure, Begins to Invest in Recycling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MYRA KLOCKENBRINK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KLOCKENBRINK, MYRA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: UNDER pressure from anti-pollution legislation and shrinking landfill space, the plastics industry is moving rapidly to develop technology for recycling its products, like beverage bottles and plastic bags, after they have been used by consumers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: UNDER pressure from anti-pollution legislation and shrinking landfill space, the plastics industry is moving rapidly to develop technology for recycling its products, like beverage bottles and plastic bags, after they have been used by consumers.</p>
        <p>UNDER pressure from anti-pollution legislation and shrinking landfill space, the plastics industry is moving rapidly to develop technology for recycling its products, like beverage bottles and plastic bags, after they have been used by consumers.</p>
        <p>Plastics manufacturers are investing research funds, and entrepreneurs are already exploiting existing techologies to draw profits from recycled plastics. Some companies are recovering pure resin polymers from plastic carbonated beverage bottles to create products like fiberfill for pillows, as well as plastic textiles and carpet facing. The industry is also converting mixed and layered types of plastics into plastic lumber for picnic tables and other outdoor uses.</p>
        <p>But it is still unclear how much the plastic industry's recent foray into recycling can reduce the burden of waste that is overtaxing the nation's disposal capacities. Critics of the industry question whether recycling will be feasible on a scale large enough to make a difference, and they say that limiting the use of plastics must have the highest priority.</p>
        <p>Although the newspaper and aluminum industries began intensive recycling efforts more than 20 years ago, the plastics industry is only now beginning to look at recycling used consumer products. Less than one percent of all plastics are currently recycled, as against 29 percent for aluminum and 21 percent for paper. Bottle Legislation</p>
        <p>Separating and collecting reusable plastics from garbage is a major challenge. So far, the industry has primarily relied on legislation in nine states requiring deposits on beverage containers, thus encouraging consumers to return them. But plastic beverage bottles represent only three-tenths of one percent of the plastic produced in the United States.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists, on the other hand, say the chief way of eliminating plastic pollution should be reducing the amount and type of plastics produced. ''Recycling only takes care of the problem once it's been created,'' said Jeanne Wirka, a research analyst for the Center for Environmental Education in Washington. She added that plastic production is projected to rise to about 75 billion pounds in the year 2000 from about 50 billion pounds in 1988.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists also assert that plastics are too widely dispersed, too mixed in composition and too inexpensive to be profitably recycled. ''The very adaptability of plastics is the enemy to recycling efforts,'' said Barry Commoner, director of the Center for the Biology of Natural Systems at Queens College in New York.</p>
        <p>But spokesmen for the plastics industry say the potential for recycling has only begun to be explored. They say markets have been created for recycled plastic products and that once collection technologies improve, new markets will emerge. To ease one of the main problems in recycling - sorting different types of plastics from one another - the Society of the Plastics Industry in Washington recently initiated a voluntary coding system that identifies plastic containers by resin. Encouragement of Industry</p>
        <p>Plastic waste, which can take up to four centuries to degrade, contributed 6.8 percent of the weight and 25.4 percent of the volume of the nation's solid wastes in 1984, according to a study by the International Plastics Consultants Corporation of Stamford, Conn.</p>
        <p>In addition to recycling, the plastics industry is also working to develop degradable products that would reduce disposal burdens. Although degradable plastics may take over some uses, the interest in recycling remains high. In fact in a reversal of its former opposition, the plastics industry is now urging states and cities to include plastics in their mandatory recycling programs, said Dr. Darrell Morrow, director of the Center for Plastics Recycling Research at Rutgers University.</p>
        <p>Legislation aimed at reducing plastic garbage has prompted the research effort. Recently Suffolk County, N.Y., banned the use of polystyrene foam packaging, and about 20 states have proposed bills that would either ban or restrict some plastic packaging.</p>
        <p>''No doubt about it, legislation is the single most important reason why we are looking at recycling,'' said Wayne Pearson, Executive Director of the Plastics Recycling Foundation, a consortium of 45 companies including plastics manufacturers like Du Pont and such beverage manufacturers as Coca-Cola and Pepsi. Producing New Products</p>
        <p>Inside plastics factories, scrap materials have long been recycled. Only now, though, is technology being used to turn post-consumer plastics from bottles, bags and automotive parts into new products. GE Plastics, a division of General Electric is studying the possibility of cars with recyclable plastic parts and houses built from recycled plastics.</p>
        <p>In the major commercial recycling operation today, 150 million pounds of carbonated beverage bottles are being recycled by six companies in the United States to recover polyethylene terephthalate or PET, a pure plastic resin designed to prevent carbon dioxide in the beverages from leaking out. Wellman Inc. of Johnsonville, S.C., the largest PET recycling company, has been recovering the material since the first bottle bills were passed in Oregon, Iowa and Michigan in 1979. Last year Wellman recycled 100 million pounds of plastic from the 890-million-pound beverage bottle industry into fiberfill and carpet facing.</p>
        <p>High-density polyethylene is also being recovered from industrial scrap and from communities with recycling efforts. Though often mixed with other plastics, the recovered material is being turned into a plastic lumber that can be used for fences, picnic tables and highway hardware like sign posts. System Developed in Europe</p>
        <p>Plastic Recycling Inc. of Iowa Falls, Iowa, uses 15,000 pounds of plastics a day to create car stops for parking lots as well as other products.</p>
        <p>Three years ago the Plastics Recycling Foundation approached the recycling center at Rutgers University to help industry develop technology for the recycling of plastics packaging. The center studies all aspects of recycling including collection, sorting, reclamation and marketing. But reclamation has attracted the most attention.</p>
        <p>In a technique similar to that being used commercially, the center is experimenting with a recycling system developed in Europe to turn mixed plastics into plastic lumber. Ground and dried plastics are drawn through a hydraulically driven extruder, similar to a hand-operated meat grinder, where the plastic melts through internal friction. The melted plastic is forced into a mold on a circular carriage that passes through a water bath to solidify the molded plastic.</p>
        <p>The center, unlike most of the companies that use recycled plastics, makes their research available to industry. Until now, most plastics recycling technology has been proprietary, hindering development.</p>
        <p>''We have a long way to go,'' said Dr. Morrow of the Rutgers center. ''But plastics recycling has come a long way in a short time. What was once thought of as non-recyclable is now being recycled.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 31, 1988, Wednesday, Late City Final Edition</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 31, 1988, Wednesday, Late City Final Edition</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
