<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Giving Thanks, Some Remember the Indians</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="201245"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THANKSGIVING DAY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDIANS, AMERICAN</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DULLEA, GEORGIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Thanksgiving Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDC123FF937A15752C1A96E948260" item-length="946" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Giving Thanks, Some Remember the Indians</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGIA DULLEA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DULLEA, GEORGIA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Navajos in northeastern Arizona have sent 6,000 sprigs of sage, a sacred plant, to a cathedral in Manhattan. The Onondagas of upstate New York are sending the Ankle Deep singers, with their water drums. And Indian nations from the North, South, East and West are sending chiefs and other tribal leaders to mark Thanksgiving</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Navajos in northeastern Arizona have sent 6,000 sprigs of sage, a sacred plant, to a cathedral in Manhattan. The Onondagas of upstate New York are sending the Ankle Deep singers, with their water drums. And Indian nations from the North, South, East and West are sending chiefs and other tribal leaders to mark Thanksgiving</p>
        <p>Navajos in northeastern Arizona have sent 6,000 sprigs of sage, a sacred plant, to a cathedral in Manhattan. The Onondagas of upstate New York are sending the Ankle Deep singers, with their water drums. And Indian nations from the North, South, East and West are sending chiefs and other tribal leaders to mark Thanksgiving Day.</p>
        <p>The occasion is a ceremony of spiritual reconciliation between descendants of Native Americans and those of the Pilgrims, whom some involved are calling the first boat people.</p>
        <p>''It should be an amazing moment,'' said the Rev. James Parks Morton, Dean of the Cathedral of St. John the Divine, where 4,000 American Indians and others are expected to join tonight in a circle dance of friendship. ''We, the boat people, will be thanking the natives for giving us Thanksgiving, giving us their tradition, and asking forgiveness for the ways in which they have been mistreated by the newcomers with respect to their lands, and with respect to respect.''</p>
        <p>The ceremony is among a handful of unrelated interfaith observances being held across the country to redefine Thanksgiving, organizers say, in light of what has happened to Native Americans since they left the historic harvest table in Plymouth, Mass., in 1621. A New Realization Cited</p>
        <p>''They tried to stamp out our ways, to destroy our culture,'' said Oren Lyons, chief of the Onondagas who will be joined in the ceremony at St. John the Divine by leaders of the Hopi, Northern Cheyenne, Tewa Pueblo and other tribes. ''They took away our children, burned our sacred objects, put our sacred objects in museums. Our sufferings have been severe.</p>
        <p>''So we come to 1988, and people are realizing the validity of traditional Indian ways in northern America. When people come forward and say, 'We're sorry, we don't think we did right,' that's very significant.''</p>
        <p>Part of the impetus for the ceremonies, Dean Morton said, is a ''heightened consciousness of the necessity of different religions working together to save our planet.'' Citing forecasts of ecological disasters, the greenhouse effect, for example, he added, ''The time has come for people to recognize that Native Americans are a treasure of wisdom about Mother Earth.''</p>
        <p>In Seattle last month, Christian church leaders gathered with Indian tribal leaders to commemorate a formal apology offered last year to the Indian and Eskimo peoples of the Pacific Northwest. That Thanksgiving Day proclamation, signed by 10 bishops of nine major denominations, acknowledged the churches' ''long-standing participation in the destruction of traditional Native American spiritual practices.'' It pledged to help the Indians reclaim and protect their religious legacy.</p>
        <p>The church and Indian leaders exchanged gifts at the commemoration - blankets from the bishops, salmon from chiefs - and renewed promises, said Jewell James, a Lummi leader. Cultural Diversity</p>
        <p>With more than 300 recognized tribes in this country, Native Americans remain ''as diverse culturally as Norwegians are to Italians,'' said LaDonna Harris, executive director of Americans for Indian Opportunity, a Washington-based advocacy group.</p>
        <p>She and others whose jobs take them from reservation to reservation say Indians are of mixed minds about Thanksgiving. Since the national holiday coincides with time of traditional Indian harvest ceremonies, some celebrate in that spirit. For others, it is merely a day off from work and for still others, it is a day of mourning.</p>
        <p>''There's still a lot of pain out there about Thanksgiving because we've not been treated as equals in American society,'' said Ms. Harris, who is of Comanche descent. ''But the Native American attitude is to be positive about the situtation you find yourself in.'' Correcting Myths</p>
        <p>Tribal leaders generally agree. In Tahlequah, Okla., Wilma P. Mankiller, principal chief of the 92,000-member Cherokee nation said: ''We celebrate Thanksgiving along with the rest of America, maybe in different ways and for different reasons. Despite everything that's happened to us since we fed the Pilgrims, we still have our language, our culture, our distinct social system. Even in a nuclear age, we're still a tribal people.''</p>
        <p>For years, Indian parents have spent the holiday correcting myths taught their children in public schools. Michael Dorris, a novelist of Modoc descent who lives in Cornish, N.H., recalls the day several years ago that his son, Sava, brought home a mimeographed report on the ''first Thanksgiving'' written by a third-grade teacher.</p>
        <p>''It said the Pilgrims ate turkeys and squash and pumpkins and corn,'' Mr. Dorris said, ''and then parenthetically, 'the Indians never had such a feast.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dorris sent back a note saying: ''Au contraire, the Pilgrims never had such a feast. Those were Indian foods.'' Speaking at Schools</p>
        <p>Although textbooks still do not reflect fully the contributions of Native Americans, they are improving, Indians say. Increasingly, Indian parents are being asked by schools to speak about Thanksgiving. It is ''our day in the sun,'' one mother said.</p>
        <p>But holiday talks are a sour point with some American Indians, who see them as stereotypical. Bruce Duthu, who heads a campus organization for the 104 Indian students at Dartmouth College in Hanover, N.H., says the students have mixed reactions to the requests to speak to schools and other groups around Thanksgiving.</p>
        <p>''A lot of them say, don't send me out in November,'' Mr. Duthu said, ''because that's when they expect to see an Indian. They would rather speak at special times on the Indian calendar or on historic occasions, such as the commemoration of Wounded Knee.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
