<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cooler Reality Contradicts Greenhouse Theory</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="169925"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DF1730F932A2575BC0A96E948260" item-length="379" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cooler Reality Contradicts Greenhouse Theory</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>There was a mind-boggling discrepancy between your July 19 Science Times article on the warming ''greenhouse effect'' and your news about climate trends the same day. You reported on 61 sites for which the July 18 temperatures were available, and for 35 of those, the daily maximum temperatures were cooler than for the norm in the table. The unusually cool temperatures were distributed throughout the globe, from Lisbon (23 degrees Fahrenheit below normal), to Sydney, Australia (6 degrees below normal).</p>
        <p>Further, since at least 1952 the urban heat-island effect has been well known among meteorologists. According to this theory, thermometers in or near cities are as much as 18 degrees (10 degrees Centigrade) warmer than those in the surrounding countryside, with the degree of elevation related to a city's population size. Thus, Los Angeles, for example, has become 4 degrees warmer than the surrounding countryside in the last 60 years.</p>
        <p>If the world were indeed warming, city temperatures would have to be markedly warmer than the norm throughout the world for there to be evidence of anything other than local warming because of waste heat from furnaces, air-conditioning plants and waste heat from engines.</p>
        <p>The National Weather Service has identified a set of rural stations that are judged suitable for drawing inferences about climate trends. Almost all show markedly lower temperatures since 1940. Further, those lower rural temperatures explain a wide variety of news stories of the last decade, from the elevated lake levels of the Great Salt Lake and the Great Lakes to the increased probability of citrus-killing frosts in Florida and the space shuttle Challenger disaster, which occurred because of extraordinary chilling, not heating, at 28 degrees north of the equator, at sea level and on the Gulf Stream.</p>
        <p>The long-run trends at Titusville, Fla., a few miles from Cape Canaveral, suggest more problems with the shuttle until the National Aeronautics and Space Administration becomes aware of the dramatic climatic downturn in northern Florida and the Gulf States. KENNETH E. F. WATT  Davis, Calif., July 23, 1988  The writer is professor of zoology and environmental studies at the University of California, Davis.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
