<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deadly Combination Felling Trees in East</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19880807T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="164250"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EASTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">OHIO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">TENNESSEE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRUCK, ROBERT I (PROF)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DD173AF937A15754C0A96E948260" item-length="1641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deadly Combination Felling Trees in East</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>MOUNT MITCHELL, N.C., July 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Thousands of dead trees, their barren trunks and branches stark against a hazy sky, stand like an army of skeletons as far as the eye can see along the crest of this mountain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Thousands of dead trees, their barren trunks and branches stark against a hazy sky, stand like an army of skeletons as far as the eye can see along the crest of this mountain.</p>
        <p>Thousands of dead trees, their barren trunks and branches stark against a hazy sky, stand like an army of skeletons as far as the eye can see along the crest of this mountain.</p>
        <p>Five years ago a red spruce forest covered the top of Mount Mitchell, the highest mountain east of the Mississippi. Today, only raspberry and blackberry bushes, clumps of sedge and a few young trees, brown and dying, cover the ground near the summit.</p>
        <p>This stark evidence is forcing many scientists to accept a conclusion that seemed only a possibility five years ago: air pollution, including acids in the air, is combining with natural stresses to cause heavy damage to forests throughout the East.</p>
        <p>''What you see here is happening all along the crest of the Appalachians from Maine to Georgia,'' said Prof. Robert I. Bruck of North Carolina State University, a plant pathologist.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bruck observed early symptoms of the decline of Mount Mitchell's spruce and fir five years ago. Now the ecological system at the summit has collapsed, he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bruck said he was ''90 percent certain'' that manmade air pollution traveling from the Ohio and Tennessee valleys, particularly low-level ozone and acidic moisture in clouds, was combining with such natural stresses as the high temperatures and drought of recent years to create an environment in which the trees cannot survive.  'Canary in the Coal Mine'</p>
        <p>So far, the effects are chiefly visible at high altitudes, where natural stresses are greatest and acidic clouds are nearest. But a number of scientists who believe that high levels of air pollution are instrumental in destroying coniferous forests at high altitudes in the East also expressed another fear in interviews over the past few days.</p>
        <p>They warned that the death of the mountaintop spruce and fir forests might be what several of them called ''the canary in the coal mine'' - an early warning that forests of low altitudes, including hardwood forests, are also in danger of being damaged by a combination of man-made and natural stresses.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bruck said the damage he is seeing on 6,684-foot Mount Mitchell seems similar to the early stages of the mass destruction of forests in recent years in central Europe. Dr. Bruck and the other scientists inteviewed said that the role of air pollution in killing the trees was still a hypothesis rather than a scientific fact. But virtually all contended that prudence dictated action.</p>
        <p>Of most serious concern, the scientists said, are ozone and acidity in clouds, rain, snow and dust. Ozone is formed at ground level by the reaction of sunlight with manmade pollutants from automobile exhaust, industry and a variety of small sources.</p>
        <p>While ozone in the upper atmosphere shields the earth from damaging ultraviolet radiation from the sun, ground level ozone contributes to smog, respiratiory damage to people and damage to trees and crops. Acid rain, clouds, snow and dust are formed when pollutants, chiefly oxides of nitrogen and sulfur from coal-fired power plants, are transformed chemically as they travel through the atmosphere. Acid rain has been found by scientists to be destroying life in lakes and streams in the Northeast and Canada.</p>
        <p>But while the ill effects of these pollutants have been documented, scientists say it is difficult to separate their influence from climate or other possible factors. The problem is complicated by the fact that scientists only began intensive studies of forests a decade ago.  'We Should Not Wait'</p>
        <p>Volker H. Mohnen, a professor of atmospheric science at the State University of New York at Albany, who has watched half the spruce trees atop Whiteface Mountain in upstate New York die in recent years, said that while it has not been conclusively proved that air pollution added to natural stress is killing the trees, ''I would advocate housekeeping before all the answers are in.''</p>
        <p>''We should not wait,'' he said. ''We must address the problem holistically.''</p>
        <p>He said that a variety of pollutants released by the combustion of fossil fuel, including sulfur, nitrogen and carbon, might not only be damaging forests but also might be contributing to other crucial problems like urban smog, acidic lakes and global warming, the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>There are, Dr. Mohnen said, ''economic and technological solutions to improve our fossil fuel-based society by increasing efficiency and, at the same time, decrease emissions of sulfur, nitrogen and carbon.''</p>
        <p>There is also growing evidence that air pollution may be damaging or slowing the growth of trees in other parts of the country, according to David L. Radloff, a United States Forest Service representative on the Administration's program to study acid rain. He said evidence in recent years supported the hypothesis that high ozone concentrations were contributing to the declinging growth rate of southern yellow pine trees, one of the nation's more important commercial species. There are also indications that ozone and other airborne pollutants are damaging trees along virtually the whole length of the Sierras in California, he said.  Opinion Has Evolved</p>
        <p>Forest Service officials had been extremely skeptical until recently that air pollution might play a significant role in slowing the growth of trees and damaging forests. Dr. Radloff said that the evidence linking the declining health of forests and the high levels of pollution reaching those forests was still ''circumstantial.''</p>
        <p>But the discovery in the past couple of years that ozone pollution was reaching very high levels in rural as well as urban areas and the discovery that clouds could be significantly more acidic than acid rain has caused opinion in the Forest Service to ''evolve,'' Dr. Radloff said. The World Research Institute, a Washington-based research and policy group, has had a team of scientists investigating the potential effect of multiple air pollutants on trees and field crops. Mohamed El-Ashry, the group's vice president for research and policy, said that the research over the last two years had demonstrated ''systematic links'' between air pollution and the destruction of trees and crops in all parts of the country.</p>
        <p>Dr. El-Ashry also said the deaths of trees reflected the end of a long process reflecting the accumulated stress of air pollution stretching back for decades. ''By the time we see visible damage it is the beginning of the end,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Acid air pollution and ozone, Dr. El-Ashry said, had been found to weaken trees to the point where ''they cannot avoid destruction by natural causes such as frosts, high winds, insects and disease.''</p>
        <p>He also said the group's researchers had been finding that the forests dying along the Eastern Seaboard cannot regenerate because of high levels of lead and other heavy metals in the soil.  Scientific Disagreement</p>
        <p>Not all those with an immediate interest in the nation's forests agree that air pollution is a threat to the nation's forests. Robert C. Kaufman, director of the air quality program of the American Paper Institute and National Forest Products Association, industry groups, said that ''there is no evidence that acid deposition is affecting the soil of commercial forests.''</p>
        <p>He asserted, ''We do not see conclusive evidence air pollution in general is causing reduced productivity in commercial forests.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaufman added that the industry saw no need for a regulatory program to curb acid rain, but that it did support more research into the effects of acid rain.</p>
        <p>Walter L. Warnick, who represents the Energy Department on the Administration's acid rain study program, said that the death of trees on a large scale ''is not unprecedented in history.'' He also said that the scientific consensus that pollution from fossil fuels is damaging trees is ''shaky.''</p>
        <p>Several scientists have contended that the trees are dying because of climatic factors, particularly the hot summers and cold winters of recent years.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Michael Oppenheimer, an atmospheric physicist with the Environmental Defense Fund, a national environmental group, said that mounting evidence shows this: ''Forests all along the Eastern seaboard and into Canada are experiencing stress at high and low altitudes. The stress comes from air pollution and from climate extremes we have seen in recent years from the greenhouse effect. What is going on is an indicator that the natural environment is in very, very deep trouble due to air pollution.</p>
        <p>''Those mountain tops sit in a chemical soup made of ozone, acid fog and acid deposition, which puts them under continual stress. It is starting to look as if those stressed systems are snapping like rubber bands.''  Destructive Summer</p>
        <p>The soup has been especially potent on the top of Mount Mitchell in this hot, dry summer. It is widely agreed, Dr. Bruck said, that ozone levels of 55 parts per billion in the air are enough to cause physiological damage to spruce and fir trees. Measurements taken by his research team, he reported, have shown that since May 1, ozone levels have been above that level 90 percent of the time; more than 120 parts per billion 28 percent of the time, and once reached a high of 178 parts per billion. Moreover, the ozone has remained over the mountain through the night instead of dissipating as it normally does in lower latitudes, he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bruck has also noted a rapid deterioration of the forest down the slope, all the way to the transition line between the coniferous and hardwood trees. Dr. Bruck said he had observed some damge to the hardwood trees but that there had not been any studies of the extent or the cause of the damage to these trees.</p>
        <p>Standing at the edge of a bowl of dead and dying trees several thousand feet below the summit of Mount Mitchell, Dr. Bruck said, ''This is not supposed to be happening.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 7, 1988, Sunday, Late City Final Edition</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 7, 1988, Sunday, Late City Final Edition</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
