<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OHIO GETS DEADLINE ON POLLUTION PLAN</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="207513"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">OHIO</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFD9133FF93BA25751C1A96E948260" item-length="455" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OHIO GETS DEADLINE ON POLLUTION PLAN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Environmental Protection Agency has given Ohio officials two months to adopt a plan to inspect automobiles for pollution emissions in the Cleveland area or face a cutoff of $20 million in Federal highway funds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Environmental Protection Agency has given Ohio officials two months to adopt a plan to inspect automobiles for pollution emissions in the Cleveland area or face a cutoff of $20 million in Federal highway funds.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency has given Ohio officials two months to adopt a plan to inspect automobiles for pollution emissions in the Cleveland area or face a cutoff of $20 million in Federal highway funds.</p>
        <p>Unless the State Legislature complies with the Federal Clean Air Act by ordering the auto inspections in populous Cuyahoga County, which includes Cleveland, the Federal highway money to the county will be blocked.</p>
        <p>In addition, the smokestack industries that release carbon dioxide into the atmosphere will be denied new construction permits, and grants to Ohio for air pollution controls will be reduced by $64,000 under the sanctions given final approval Thursday by the environmental agency.</p>
        <p>If those penalties do not persuade state lawmakers to enact an auto pollution bill, the agency said, it is ready to impose another penalty, the loss of Federal money for sewer construction, which could be as much as $20 million. Governor Predicts Action</p>
        <p>Debra Phillips, press secretary to Gov. Richard F. Celeste, a Democrat, said the Governor believed the state could beat the 60-day deadline.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the Ohio Environmental Protection Agency, Jennifer Lane Maier, said the agency was working with the Governor's office on draft legislation to meet the Federal Government's demands. She said the state agency hoped to introduce the legislation as early as possible in January.</p>
        <p>Cuyahoga County was singled out because of violations of Federal air pollution standards, specifically levels of carbon monoxide.</p>
        <p>State Senator Lee Fisher, a Democrat from Cleveland, said previously that many of his colleagues believed the Government had engaged in ''a form of Federal blackmail.'' Dizziness and Nausea</p>
        <p>But he said he would not be suprised if an auto inspection bill was the ''first piece of legislation we deal with in January.''</p>
        <p>In high concentrations, carbon monoxide can cause dizziness, nausea, blurred vision, headache and delayed reaction time.</p>
        <p>Inspection of autos for emissions is considered an effective antidote to high carbon monoxide levels because 85 percent of the gas comes from the exhaust fumes of cars and trucks.</p>
        <p>Although no other city is facing the loss of highway construction money, there are about 10 other areas that are under bans on construction of industry that produces carbon dioxide. These include Cincinnati's Kentucky suburbs, Chicago and some of its suburbs, Albuquerque, N.M., and St. Cloud, Minn., said Chris Rice, a spokesman for the enviornmental agency.</p>
        <p>Sanctions against Albuquerque on Federal highway funds were lifted recently after a year and a half. Four areas in California were under the same restrictions for nearly two years, Mr. Rice said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
