<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Pollution Garden Grows So Ozone Can Run Amok</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="186754"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BOTANICAL GARDEN, NY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ECOSYSTEM STUDIES, INSTITUTE OF</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDE1F3BF933A25753C1A96E948260" item-length="727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Pollution Garden Grows So Ozone Can Run Amok</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</byline>
      <dateline>MILLBROOK, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ''Become an Ozone Damage Detective,'' beckons a sign at the entrance to the Air Pollution Garden, an exhibit at the Institute of Ecosystem Studies in this Dutchess County village.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ''Become an Ozone Damage Detective,'' beckons a sign at the entrance to the Air Pollution Garden, an exhibit at the Institute of Ecosystem Studies in this Dutchess County village.</p>
        <p>''Become an Ozone Damage Detective,'' beckons a sign at the entrance to the Air Pollution Garden, an exhibit at the Institute of Ecosystem Studies in this Dutchess County village.</p>
        <p>This year, that sleuthing has proved particularly easy.</p>
        <p>On potted tomatoes and morning glories, on spinach and petunias here, the effects of what scientists call ''ozone stress'' are plain: discoloration, spots that looked burned or bleached, and small yields of seed and fruit.</p>
        <p>The symptoms are more graphic than those that might be found in a household garden because the institute, a division of the New York Botanical Garden in the Bronx, purposely grew varieties sensitive to ozone pollution and, for comparison, grew them next to varieties resistant to it. Ozone Is Easily Dispersed</p>
        <p>The institute had no problem coming up with the ozone. It simply comes from the air in this rural area 80 miles north of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Ozone is easily dispersed from the cities where most of it is generated, so that even in small towns with little industry, it becomes a health problem. On 16 days this past summmer, Millbrook's air had more than the Federal safety levels for ozone - about half as many times as that happened in New York City. Any reading over .125 parts per million is considered unsafe.</p>
        <p>Those conditions were ''great for demonstrating the point of our pollution garden,'' said Dr. Gene E. Likens, the director of the institute. ''They were not great in terms of anything else.'' Acid Rain Study Ponds</p>
        <p>The garden was started last year, primarily as an educational display, said Dr. Likens. Several projects at the institute involve advanced research into pollution, including pioneering work on acid rain, but most cannot be easily shown to the public.</p>
        <p>Near the garden are the Acid Rain Study Ponds - 100-gallon troughs in the ground that are filled with water. Into the troughs go different solutions of sulfuric acid and rocks with varying abilities to neutralize acid.</p>
        <p>The ponds are an educational exhibit, like the gardens, although, as researchers note, the scientific purity of the display has been compromised somewhat by bullfrogs, which have been jumping from pond to pond at night. Frog urine skews test results, the researchers complained. Most Plants Are on View</p>
        <p>Both displays are open to the public, as is much of the 2,000 acres of the Mary Flagler Cary Arboretum, where the institute is located. While the first days of fall frost mean that the growing season ends, in the ozone garden most of the plants are still on view, with technical descriptions of the damage by pollution.</p>
        <p>''Ozone sensitive,'' reads the sign next to a Tiny Tim tomato plant. ''Symptoms of stress include leaf chlorosis and necrosis (bleaching and death), delayed fruit seed, reduced yield.''</p>
        <p>Next summer, said Laury Zicari, the coordinator of research displays, the institute plans to add a new feature to the garden: ozone-free chambers that look vaguely like hospital breathing tents and are kept free of the pollution by fans. These chambers will allow visitors to compare samples of the same variety of plants, she said.</p>
        <p>Throughout the grounds, in serene groves of trees or alongside quiet creeks, visitors can see evidence of research. There are towers from which measurements of air quality are made and basins that collect rainfall for readings of acid content.</p>
        <p>One of the more intriguing devices is a bag with nonstick coating that encases the branches of a white pine tree and another that surrounds the branch of a sugar maple. By artificially controlling the amount of ozone that enters the enclosed area, researchers have been able to pinpoint its effects, said Dr. Gary M. Lovett, a plant ecologist and designer of the project. The ozone acts inside the leaves to harm the membranes of cells, temporarily decreasing the tree's ability to take in necessary nutrients.</p>
        <p>Ozone is created when gas vapors and other hydrocarbons react with sunlight and heat. Besides destroying plant tissue and stunting growth, as the gardens demonstrate, it can destroy plant immune systems. It has been implicated in the decline of forests in parts of Europe and North America.</p>
        <p>Scientists believe that the high levels of ozone this past summer were largely induced by stagnant weather and the lack of wind and rain that normally help prevent its buildup.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
