<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A.M.A. Asks States to Ban 'Smokeless' Cigarette</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="194379"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECALLS AND BANS OF PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARIZONA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MISSOURI</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN MEDICAL ASSN (AMA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">REYNOLDS, R J, TOBACCO CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMIDT, WILLIAM E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DC1331F930A35752C1A96E948260" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A.M.A. Asks States to Ban 'Smokeless' Cigarette</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM E. SCHMIDT, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMIDT, WILLIAM E</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Nov. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The American Medical Association filed petitions with regulatory officials in Arizona and Missouri today seeking to ban the sale and distribution of a new ''smokeless'' cigarette now being test marketed in the two states.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The American Medical Association filed petitions with regulatory officials in Arizona and Missouri today seeking to ban the sale and distribution of a new ''smokeless'' cigarette now being test marketed in the two states.</p>
        <p>The American Medical Association filed petitions with regulatory officials in Arizona and Missouri today seeking to ban the sale and distribution of a new ''smokeless'' cigarette now being test marketed in the two states.</p>
        <p>In a step underscoring the association's continuing assault on smoking and tobacco use, the medical association contends the product, marketed by the R. J. Reynolds Tobacco Company as an alternative to ordinary cigarettes, should be regarded as a ''drug delivery system'' intended to introduce nicotine into its users.</p>
        <p>The petition argues that the Arizona State Board of Pharmacy and the Missouri Department of Health have an obligation to ''evaluate whether the dangerous health effects of the product preclude its sale'' in their states. Missouri Official Receptive</p>
        <p>Dr. Robert Harmon, the Director of the Missouri Department of Health, said today he agreed with the A.M.A. and did not consider the product to be a safer alternative to ordinary cigarettes. He said he was considering seeking an injunction against the sale of the product, which is sold under the brand name Premier, pending a full evaluation of its safety.</p>
        <p>In Arizona, Joe Rowan, the deputy Director of the state Pharmacy Board, said the medical association's petition had been referred to the state Attorney General for further study.</p>
        <p>The A.M.A. filed a similar petition with the Food and Drug Administration in April, asking the Federal Government to assert its own jurisdiction over the product. That petition is still under review.</p>
        <p>Premier looks and feels like an ordinary cigarette, but does not burn tobacco and therefore produces none of the tars that have been associated with lung cancer and other diseases. But smokers do inhale a dose of nicotine, as vapors from a burning carbon tip are flavored by a small amount of tobacco inside the cigarette .</p>
        <p>Officials of the Reynolds Company replied today that Premier is a cigarette ''designed for smoking pleasure and enjoyment'' and that state agencies therefore had no basis for regulating the product. Reynolds began test marketing Premier on Oct. 1 in Phoenix and Tucson, Ariz., and St. Louis.</p>
        <p>The A.M.A.'s challenge to Premier foretells what could be a major battle between the medical community and the tobacco industry. The A.M.A. and other anti-smoking groups are pushing for stronger regulation of tobacco and tobacco products, at the same time the industry is attempting to devise a substitute cigarette acceptable to nonsmokers.</p>
        <p>Although the Reynolds Tobacco Company, a subsidiary of RJR Nabisco, makes no health claims for Premier, it says the smoke from the cigarette produces virtually none of the ash or smoke that nonsmokers find annoying. Company Challenges Reasoning</p>
        <p>''Reynolds Tobacco finds it difficult to understand how the A.M.A. can, in good faith, suggest that Premier be banned when, in fact, it addresses many of their criticisms,'' said the Reynolds statement.</p>
        <p>But since nicotine is an addictive drug associated with with high blood pressure, strokes and heart attacks, the medical association says the new product should be subject to regulation by state health agencies, which can require R.J. Reynolds to prove it is safe before introducing it on the market.</p>
        <p>Dr. M. Roy Schwarz, the A.M.A.'s executive vice president for medical education and science, said that the Premier was being marketed as an alternative to conventional cigarettes. ''People on the street think, 'Aha, it's much safer,'''said Dr. Schwarz. ''But that's misleading. because the long-term health impacts of this product just are not known.''</p>
        <p>He said smoke from Premier contained 31 chemicals and argued that Reynold's own studies showed that smoking the cigarettes resulted in blood levels of nicotine and carbon dioxide nearly as high as in regular cigarettes. The company, however, said the level of nicotine in Premier was lower than in 97 percent of cigarettes being sold.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
