<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High Hopes, Hair Nightmare</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="129291"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND OPINION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEAUTY SALONS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHIELDS, BARBARA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty Salons</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED91730F933A15750C0A96E948260" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High Hopes, Hair Nightmare</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA SHIELDS; Barbara Shields lives in Rockville Centre.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHIELDS, BARBARA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: I REMEMBER William Holden telling Grace Kelly in ''The Country Girl'' that there are two kinds of women in the world: those who pay too much attention to themselves and those who don't pay enough.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: I REMEMBER William Holden telling Grace Kelly in ''The Country Girl'' that there are two kinds of women in the world: those who pay too much attention to themselves and those who don't pay enough.</p>
        <p>I REMEMBER William Holden telling Grace Kelly in ''The Country Girl'' that there are two kinds of women in the world: those who pay too much attention to themselves and those who don't pay enough.</p>
        <p>Being the mother of three small childen, as well as a part-time consultant, sometime teacher and small-time cottage-industry proprietor, I often find myself in the second category. Especially where my hair is concerned. What should be my crowning glory resembles something between Billy Idol and the last rose of summer.</p>
        <p>A few weeks ago, I decided to give up my place in line at the barber shop and opt for a dryer at one of those chic little salons on Northern Boulevard. I had an appointment to join the high priestesses of haute hair, where I was confident I would emerge hours later, transformed into a perfectly coiffured ice goddess.</p>
        <p>The moment I walked in the door, I knew I was in trouble. The manicurist at the desk handed me a cup of espresso and a client profile to fill out. I ignored questions like age and weight and went straight for the good stuff: name of current cosmetologist (I don't have one, but I know a great psychic); makeup regimen (whatever we're having for breakfast); physical-fitness program (running in and out of pizzerias and Chinese restaurants doesn't count), and hair-care products used (Brand X always works for me).</p>
        <p>From the orientation area, I was ushered into a large mirrored back room, where I was instructed to change into a pink hospital-type gown and join the staff for a consultation. A pretty young hairdresser named Susan interviewed me for about 15 minutes. She explained that the data I provided about my life style (was she kidding?) was vital to the ''look'' they would create for me.</p>
        <p>I thought if I gave her enough information she'd get scared and ask me to leave. First I recounted the day the Fire Department came to the house to get the kids out of the bathroom. She was implacable. Even when I described the dead raccoon blocking the driveway the afternoon I had to drive my mother to the airport, she didn't blink an eye. I saved the best for last. I told her about the morning the gas man almost killed himself trying to read the meter in our basement. That happened right after the disk drive on my computer blew and the car was stolen. Her insouciance collapsed like a cheese souffle.</p>
        <p>''You need a soft perm,'' she said quietly. ''Something you can just wash and wear.'' ''Right,'' I said, just as quietly. As she washed my hair and towel-dried it, I remembered why I had spent my entire life avoiding beauty parlors. The pulling, primping and pouffing were simply too much to bear. I used to watch as my mother was tyrannized at the hands of her hairdresser and manicurist. I vowed I would never suffer needlessly for the sake of style.</p>
        <p>The use of potions and elixirs fascinated me, though. After Susan cut my hair, she applied some kind of blue-green gel. After that, she wrapped my forehead in absorbent cotton reminiscent of an Egyptian ritual and began the laborious task of setting my hair. When that was done, she brought me back over to the sink and told me to close my eyes. More icky-smelling potions were painted on my scalp. She set a timer for 20 minutes. More mysterious creams oozed from tubes with French-sounding names.</p>
        <p>''Don't worry,'' said Sal. ''We use only natural ingredients.'' He was the tall, good-looking one with the gold chains and the filigree bracelet. I just smiled. About as natural as acid rain.</p>
        <p>Susan and I chatted sporadically throughout this entire process. Her own hair was a study in modern Renaissance painting: Titian meets Andy Warhol. When I admired her nails and asked if they were real, she answered, ''Of course not.'' I looked at mine, which were rather appalling, and gracefully declined her offer of a manicure. ''I use organic nail polish,'' I lied. Somewhere a bell rang. Mercifully, it tolled for me.</p>
        <p>Off came the cotton. I felt my hair burst forth from the plastic rollers like a litter of puppies. This was not a good omen. I looked at my reflection with trepidation. A French poodle stared back at me from an unforgiving mirror. I waited for the comb-out. There was none. ''Oh, you don't touch a perm,'' Susan said. ''Whatever you do, don't put a brush to your hair. And don't wash it for three days. When you do, just mold it with your fingers.''</p>
        <p>I was horrified. When I got home, I did everything I could to reverse the effects of all those secret salon formulas, but my efforts were in vain. Nothing worked. My little friend Annie stopped by the other day. When she saw my Shirley Temple curls, she recovered from her shock and said my hair was very nice. Then she asked, ''Will you look that way for the rest of your life?''</p>
        <p>I wish we could ask William Holden.</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND OPINION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
