<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Midwestern Nuclear Projects Suggest a Use for Shoreham</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="160377"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MICHIGAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">OHIO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SHOREHAM NUCLEAR POWER PLANT</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDC123EF933A25754C0A96E948260" item-length="1124" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Midwestern Nuclear Projects Suggest a Use for Shoreham</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L.WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IF Shoreham is never to split an atom, can it be put to some other use?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IF Shoreham is never to split an atom, can it be put to some other use?</p>
        <p>IF Shoreham is never to split an atom, can it be put to some other use?</p>
        <p>Failed nuclear projects in Michigan and Ohio are taking shape this summer as generating stations powered by fossil fuels, with their builders citing the same demand for electric power that once impelled them toward completion of the reactors, despite rising costs and technical difficulties.</p>
        <p>Long Island has many of the same reasons for proceeding with conversion, including growing demand for power and a utility hurt by the long struggle to build a reactor. Explaining the decision to convert the Zimmer plant, in southern Ohio, to coal, William S. White, the chairman of American Electric Power, one of the three partners in the project, said: ''Had we had to abandon the thing completely, we wouldn't have been in a position to build anything. Yet we recognized that we were going to need the power in the early 90's.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. White and other utility officials in the Midwest and at the Long Island Lighting Company stress that the solutions to the problem of an abandoned reactor are ''site specific,'' or particular to the plant involved. And Lilco is pessimistic about converting Shoreham.</p>
        <p>The project getting under way this summer in Midland, Mich., where Consumers Power Company is turning a 425-megawatt reactor into a 1,370-megawatt gas-fired plant, which will also produce up to 1.35 million pounds per hour of steam for use at an adjacent Dow Chemical plant. Financing was completed in June and the work is about 5 percent done.</p>
        <p>In its new incarnation, Midland is 49 percent owned by the utility, Consumers Power Company. Most of the rest is owned by large vendors who will profit from the conversion, including Coastal Corporation, an oil and gas company, and Panhandle Eastern, a pipeline company. A subsidiary of Dow holds another 10 percent.</p>
        <p>Such ownership is attractive at Midland because it will bring in more revenue than a standard plant. In part because it makes steam and is only partly owned by the utility, the plant has won a special regulatory status as an independent power producer under the Public Utilities Regulatory Policy Act, and will be paid for its electricity on an ''avoided cost'' basis, based on what Consumers would have paid to build and operate a new plant.</p>
        <p>Such status is unlikely for Shoreham, because there is no market for steam nearby.</p>
        <p>Nor is there gas. At Lilco, Russell C. Youngdahl, the president, who was formerly at Consumers Power in charge of energy supply operations, said he follows the progress of Midland closely. He said that if Shoreham were converted to gas, it would double Long Island's consumption, and unlike Michigan, the transmission is not now available on Long Island.</p>
        <p>A better model might be Zimmer, in Moscow, Ohio, on the banks of the Ohio River 23 miles southeast of Cincinnati. It was as close to a twin as Shoreham ever had, with the same General Electric reactor in essentially the same containment structure, although Zimmer has a cooling tower, while Shoreham, with an ocean of cooling water handy, was equipped with a diffuser pipe extending into Long Island Sound.</p>
        <p>Zimmer's new coal boiler will produce steam that is hotter and under higher pressure than what comes out of a reactor. But after the steam has run through an 800-megawatt turbine generator, according to engineers here, its temperature and pressure will resemble steam made in a reactor, and it can then be routed through what was meant to be the turbine-generator system of the reactor. The cooling requirements are about the same as a reactor's, and the plant, like Shoreham, is already hooked up to the transmission grid.</p>
        <p>Zimmer's builders expect to salvage about half of the $1.7 billion they spent when it was a nuclear project. ''We just felt we couldn't let it sit there, particularly with the transmission in place,'' said Mr. White. ''We had to make use of this resource.''</p>
        <p>Another constituency is plant employees. Zimmer had a skeleton staff when nuclear construction stopped in 1983, and will have a permanent staff of 330 when finished. Its construction force will peak at 2,000. Shoreham now has 700 Lilco employees.</p>
        <p>There is also a noneconomic factor, the esthetic appeal of putting past effort to use. ''As an engineer, you'd like to see something run the way it was intended to,'' said John R. Jones, the project manager for American Electric Power, which is managing the conversion. If it won't run as a nuclear plant, he said, ''the biggest shame would be to do nothing at all.''</p>
        <p>But the prospect of re-using Shoreham is less certain. Mr. Youngdahl said that neither gas nor coal presented insurmountable technical barriers. But he said that the cost would be too high, and added that environmental objections might preclude coal on Long Island, unless experimental technologies like fluidized bed combustion became available.</p>
        <p>Lilco appears not to have much taste for another expensive tangle with environmentalists. ''You'd meet with a different group, and probably a very vocal group,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Midwestern utility companies that were building Zimmer faced a political as well as financial problem with the reactor. Choosing coal helped solve that, by providing a market for more than 500 tons an hour. At the current price of about $30 a ton, that comes to $105 million a year for the next 40 years.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Youngdahl put it, ''When you are parked on top of coal mines, as they are, it has a big influence. The trades want it, the coal miners want it, and the public wants it.''</p>
        <p>But, he added, ''there are very few coal miners on the Island rooting for something like this.''</p>
        <p>The rolling hills of southern Ohio have something else that money can't buy on Long Island: space to bury the ash and limestone-acid mix that the pollution equipment keeps from going up the stack. The utilities in Ohio bought 660 acres three miles away, which will be connected to the plant by a private road. They plan to use 450 acres for landfill over 40 years, with 210 acres as a buffer zone. Persuading local residents that the dump would not be objectionable required taking 100 of them on a bus tour of the repository at a similar coal plant in West Virginia, but that task was small compared with the travails of disposing of waste from Long Island.</p>
        <p>Long Island may, in fact, burn coal some time soon. Plans submitted by Lilco and by the Long Island Power Authority both envision two coal plants, probably of 400 megawatts, before the end of the century. But according to Mr. Youngdahl, starting from scratch would provide more flexibility and better economics.</p>
        <p>But there is at least one constituency for some kind of conversion, he said: ''The architect-engineers would love to do it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
