<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brazil Burns the Future</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="209944"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREST AND BRUSH FIRES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRAZIL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AMAZON JUNGLE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MENDES FILHO, FRANCISCO</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3D81139F93BA15751C1A96E948260" item-length="415" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brazil Burns the Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Brazilian governments commonly shrug off criticism of the cowboy strand in their society. That strand is evident in the environmental holocaust sweeping the Amazon rain forest and the cold-blooded murder of a trade unionist who dared to challenge slash-and-burn land developers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Brazilian governments commonly shrug off criticism of the cowboy strand in their society. That strand is evident in the environmental holocaust sweeping the Amazon rain forest and the cold-blooded murder of a trade unionist who dared to challenge slash-and-burn land developers.</p>
        <p>Brazilian governments commonly shrug off criticism of the cowboy strand in their society. That strand is evident in the environmental holocaust sweeping the Amazon rain forest and the cold-blooded murder of a trade unionist who dared to challenge slash-and-burn land developers.</p>
        <p>If Brazil wants the world's sympathy on matters of debt and democracy, it cannot ignore the international outrage at assaults on the environment and those who defend it. The World Bank now places environmental conditions on its lending. Others who would help Brazil are also right to insist on respect for the common planetary heritage.</p>
        <p>Little has come so far from President Jose Sarney's public pledge to halt the calamitous burning by cattle ranchers of the heavily forested western Amazon, where 170,000 fires were counted last year. Rondonia, endowed with one of the world's richest ecosystems, is now 17 percent deforested.</p>
        <p>Nor is there much confidence in the Sarney regime's capacity to vigorously prosecute the killing of Francisco Mendes Filho, or adequately protect others who follow in his path. Mr. Mendes, a trade unionist, defended the traditional rights of freelance rubber tappers who have literally fought to save their forests from bulldozers. A few weeks ago he was warned that local landowners had hired gunmen to kill him; he was shot last Thursday even as police guards sat in his kitchen.</p>
        <p>The 30,000 tappers Mr. Mendes helped organize were, like himself, descended from migrants who were drawn by the great rubber boom that peaked before World War I. From 1890 to 1911, Brazil and its rubber barons dominated production of ''black gold,'' driving prices so high that the jungle city of Manaus became a byword for extravagance. But those same high prices led the British to sneak rubber tree seedlings to Ceylon and Malaya, breaking Brazil's monopoly. Brazil was abruptly undone by the planters' shortsighted greed.</p>
        <p>History repeats. In a calamitous cycle, burning rain forests adds to the greenhouse effect, disrupts the process that transforms carbon dioxide into oxygen, kills a profusion of species and devastates the homes of Amerindians. Stripped of a nurturing canopy, jungle soils are soon infertile. Cattle ranches are thus inherently uneconomic without generous subsidies. These subsidies were recently suspended - but not voided - by President Sarney.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mendes will be mourned not just by Brazilians. In a real sense, he was defending the very air the world breathes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
