<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stove Dies, a Victim of Its Emissions</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="158674"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOVES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">VERMONT CASTINGS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">VERMONT LIFE (MAGAZINE)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CALTA, MARIALISA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SLAYTON, THOMAS K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFD6173EF930A35754C0A96E948260" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stove Dies, a Victim of Its Emissions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARIALISA CALTA, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CALTA, MARIALISA</byline>
      <dateline>RANDOLPH, Vt., June 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: When the energy crunch met the back-to-the-land movement in the 1970's, one of the byproducts was a demand for wood stoves.Now one of the byproducts of wood stoves, emissions, has spelled the end of the line for one of the most popular models, the Defiant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: When the energy crunch met the back-to-the-land movement in the 1970's, one of the byproducts was a demand for wood stoves.Now one of the byproducts of wood stoves, emissions, has spelled the end of the line for one of the most popular models, the Defiant.</p>
        <p>When the energy crunch met the back-to-the-land movement in the 1970's, one of the byproducts was a demand for wood stoves.Now one of the byproducts of wood stoves, emissions, has spelled the end of the line for one of the most popular models, the Defiant.</p>
        <p>Thomas K. Slayton, a native Vermonter and editor of Vermont Life magazine, recalled that in the late 1970's, the Defiant stove, made by Vermont Castings Inc., ''was the symbol that you were serious about burning wood.''</p>
        <p>The last Defiant wood stove was assembled at Vermont Castings this week, before new Federal regulations governing wood stove emissions take effect. The Defiant does not meet the new standards and is being replaced by a model that does. ''It is the end of an era,'' Mr. Slayton said.  'A Life Style Statement'</p>
        <p>To Duncan Syme, owner of Vermont Castings, the Federal regulations are ''an arbitrary marker to separate the old from the new.'' He sees the first Vermont Castings customers as those whose primary interest was in using renewable energy resources to heat, living close to nature and saving money. To today's customers, he said, a stove is not a necessity, but ''an extra.'' ''It's a life style statement,'' he said. The wood stove craze peaked in 1979, then subsided after oil prices stabilized. Michael J. Herschel, past president of the Wood Heating Alliance, an industry trade group, estimated that of the 500 domestic manufacturers in business in 1979, fewer than 100 are still operating.</p>
        <p>Mr. Syme said current annual sales for his company total $50 million. The company has sold about half a million stoves, 100,000 of them Defiants.</p>
        <p>The Defiant, the company's first and most famous stove, was designed by Mr. Syme, a Yale graduate who started Vermont Castings Inc. in 1976 with his brother-in-law, Murray Howell. In an abandoned foundry in this small town in central Vermont, the two partners and a handful of employees began executing Mr. Syme's design for a stove that would be easy on the eye and on the heating bill as well. Aesthetics and Mystique</p>
        <p>''Prior to the Defiant, there were plenty of good-looking stoves, and plenty of air-tight stoves, and plenty of stoves you could open and view the fire,'' Mr. Syme said. ''What we did was put it all together in a package.''</p>
        <p>The package sold despite a price tag of about $500, nearly twice the going rate for wood stoves at the time, Mr. Herschel said. The stoves now retail at nearly $1,000.</p>
        <p>''They originated a concept of an aesthetic wood stove at a higher price, which many old-timers in the industry thought would not sell,'' said Mr. Herschel. ''They created the mystique of a country group of good old boys who were hand-crafting stoves, making them the way stoves should be made. They made it so people were proud to own them.'' 'It Was a Fad'</p>
        <p>The mystique held, he said, despite the fact that Vermont Castings now has nearly 600 employees, and what Mr. Herschel calls the ''most sophisticated production equipment in the industry,'' producing a line of a half-dozen models, stove accessories and fireplace inserts.</p>
        <p>''It was a fad, and people knew the name and wanted a Defiant even if was the wrong stove for their home,'' says Christine A. Stearns, manager of the Chimney Sweep Fireplace Shop in Shelburne, Vt., which carries Vermont Castings stoves. Mrs. Stearns likes the line, but says the ''fadiness of it went to far.''</p>
        <p>The Defiant, she said, was too big for many smaller, energy-efficient homes. Heating a small space with such a stove, she said, tempted people to burn the stove at a less efficient heat, causing creosote buildup, which in turn can cause fires. ''The Defiant,'' she said, ''is something of a dinosaur. Its time has come and gone.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
