<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WASHINGTON TALK: ENVIRONMENT</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="254448"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DB1231F93AA15756C0A96F948260" item-length="659" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WASHINGTON TALK: ENVIRONMENT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Philip Shabecoff</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: When the National Security Council set up a committee on oceans, environment and science earlier this year, it gave expression to a growing awareness among policy makers in Washington and around the world that the traditional definitions of national security are no longer adequate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: When the National Security Council set up a committee on oceans, environment and science earlier this year, it gave expression to a growing awareness among policy makers in Washington and around the world that the traditional definitions of national security are no longer adequate.</p>
        <p>When the National Security Council set up a committee on oceans, environment and science earlier this year, it gave expression to a growing awareness among policy makers in Washington and around the world that the traditional definitions of national security are no longer adequate.</p>
        <p>In the past, security was largely defined as strength of arms, firmness of alliances and economic health. Now, with the world threatened by global warming, acid rain, climate changes and the destruction of the protective ozone shield, environmental matters are seen as a serious threat to the internal political stability of some nations and as a source of friction between neighboring countries.</p>
        <p>Writing in the current issue of Foreign Affairs, Jessica Tuchman Mathews, a former member of the National Security Council, contends that the post-World War II assumptions about national security are a ''poor fit'' with emerging environmental problems.</p>
        <p>''Environmental strains that transcend national borders are already beginning to break down the sacred boundaries of national sovereignty,'' said Ms. Mathews, who is now vice president of the World Resources Institute, an environmental policy and research center in Washington.</p>
        <p>A report issued yesterday by the Worldwatch Institute, a Washington-based environmental research group, takes a similar tack. In the report, Michael Renner, an associate of the institute, writes, ''Environmental security offers a more fruitful basis for cooperation and security among nations than military security because it is both a positive and inclusive concept.''</p>
        <p>''While military security,'' he says, ''rests firmly on the competitive strength of individual countries at the direct expense of other nations, environmental security cannot be achieved unilaterally: it both requires and nurtures more stable and cooperative relations among nations.'' Mr. Renner writes.</p>
        <p>Dr. Peter H. Gleick, a senior associate of the Pacific Institute for Studies in Development, Environment and Security in Berkeley, Calif., put it this way in remarks to the State Department's Foreign Service Institute:</p>
        <p>''By focusing solely on military threats to security, nations ignore other internal and external threats that may be even more threatening -threats such as conflicts over limited fresh water resources, access to increasingly scarce mineral and energy resources and conflicts caused by massive population migrations and refugees.''</p>
        <p>Worldwatch and similar groups have been urging a redefinition of national security for years, although world leaders and policy makers have only recently begun to take serious note. Mikhail S. Gorbachev, the Soviet leader, is calling for a new emphasis on ''ecological security.'' And President Bush and Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher of Britain are seeking to build public support for a treaty to address global warming.</p>
        <p>But no leader of the great powers has suggested taking unilateral action.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups have been scrutinizing American foreign policy with an increasingly critical eye.</p>
        <p>Last week, for example, the Environmental Project on Central America criticized American aid to El Salvador for a military emphasis that, the group contends, ''totally exacerbates the environmental disaster that is undermining the country's future.''</p>
        <p>Brent Blackwelder, a vice president of the Environmental Policy Institute/Friends of the Earth, said political unrest in Central America is based in large part on land and resource problems that United States foreign policy does not take into account.</p>
        <p>Senator Al Gore, Democrat of Tennessee, recently told a National Academy of Sciences meeting on global climate change that ''throughout the world we are witnessing the emergence of a new political will to take a different course in order to avoid the slope toward environmental destruction.''</p>
        <p>''We feel strongly pulled toward ecological collapse by the policies we are now pursuing,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
