<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turning On the Research Switch</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="249841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JOINT VENTURES AND CONSORTIUMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANTITRUST ACTIONS AND LAWS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ELECTRIC POWER RESEARCH INSTITUTE (EPRI)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FEDER, BARNABY J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDD1730F937A25756C0A96F948260" item-length="1717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turning On the Research Switch</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARNABY J. FEDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FEDER, BARNABY J</byline>
      <dateline>PALO ALTO, Calif.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Time was when most companies felt that research and development was something they had to do for themselves and technology developed by others was adopted only as a last resort. However, as international competitive pressures have grown and research has become more expensive, that ''not-invented-here'' syndrome has faded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Time was when most companies felt that research and development was something they had to do for themselves and technology developed by others was adopted only as a last resort. However, as international competitive pressures have grown and research has become more expensive, that ''not-invented-here'' syndrome has faded.</p>
        <p>Time was when most companies felt that research and development was something they had to do for themselves and technology developed by others was adopted only as a last resort. However, as international competitive pressures have grown and research has become more expensive, that ''not-invented-here'' syndrome has faded.</p>
        <p>Today, with the encouragement of Congressional legislation that has swept away antitrust concerns, consortiums to develop everything from semiconductors to manufacturing systems are becoming a regular part of the business landscape. A consortium to develop high-definition television has recently been proposed.</p>
        <p>Here at the Electric Power Research Institute a visitor gets a good picture of the stresses American businesses are bound to face in trying to make such joint research efforts work. A picture emerges as well of some of the potential benefits.</p>
        <p>Founded in 1972, the institute is the oldest of the nation's major research consortiums and its second largest after Bellcore, the joint research arm of the seven Bell operating companies. At any given time, the institute is helping to finance about 1,500 projects, overseen by a staff of about 350 technical experts.</p>
        <p>''This has been absolutely the right model for the utility industry,'' said Roland Schmitt, the former head of research for the General Electric Company. Mr. Schmitt, who is now president of the Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute in Troy, N.Y., noted that G.E. had worried when the nonprofit institute was founded that it would interfere with the traditional reliance of utilities on equipment suppliers to meet most of their research needs.</p>
        <p>These days, suppliers welcome contact with the institute as an efficient way to understand the industry's needs. They also welcome its underwriting of product development at a time when slow growth makes research spending harder for the companies to justify.</p>
        <p>The institute counts among itsJU notable achievements its role in developing the technology to design a power plant to burn coal cleanly. Work with G.E. and New York State led to the development of a new transformer that cuts energy losses enough to save utilities $19 billion if it were installed nationwide. And more recently, the institute and the Carrier Corporation have cooperated to produce a residential heat pump - due on the market later this year - that is 30 percent more efficient than existing models and more durable.</p>
        <p>The institute is different from many of the newer consortiums in that its primary job is managing research contracted out to laboratories and consultants around the country, not performing it at its campus-like office complex in the hills overlooking San Francisco Bay. And its members, for the most part, do not compete with each other.</p>
        <p>However, most of its biggest problems are exactly those other consortiums will face as they mature. How does it quantify the benefits of its work to members? How does it transfer results to them? How does it prevent non-member utilities from becoming free-riders who gain the benefits of the research without supporting it? How does it establish a reputation for reliable research uncolored by the special needs of its most powerful members? And, certainly not least, how does it attract funding when many of its members face unanticipated financial pressures?</p>
        <p>''The cost pressures are a real threat to the collaborative approach to research,'' said Richard E. Balzhiser, the institute's president and chief executive, who said that a handful of companies drop out of the group each year because of financial pressures. ''It's always easier to cut money from your budget if it is being spent outside the company.''</p>
        <p>The institute, which currently has 669 members and an annual research budget of about $280 million, estimates that it manages about half of all research funding in the electric utility sector. That figure may rise somewhat if a few major holdouts that have pursued their own programs, such as the American Electric Power Company of Columbus, Ohio, finally join up.</p>
        <p>Until last month, non-members could obtain the results of institute research, albeit sometimes at a stiff price. Executives at the group say the concept of varied charges was too difficult to administer.</p>
        <p>The new policy is to distribute information and services to members only. How strictly it will be enforced remains to be seen. ''I assume we wouldn't apply it to safety issues,'' said Karl Stahlkopf, director of the institute's Nuclear Power Division.</p>
        <p>As part of a drive to be more business-like, the institute is trying to make it easier for clients to use its results. It has begun a pilot project, for example, to embody some of its research in so-called expert system programs that utility employees can tap into with personal computers.</p>
        <p>The first expert system, which covers 50 types of common problems that show up in aging nuclear power plants, will be available by the end of this month. By typing responses to a series of questions, a plant engineer would need just a half-hour to find out everything the institute knows about, say, a cracking problem caused by a particular form of corrosion. Currently, it might take the engineer 20 hours to ferret out such information from the institute's reports.</p>
        <p>''We have learned that E.P.R.I. is as much in the information business as research and development,'' said Richard Rudman, an institute vice president whose Business Management Group is charged with overseeing technology transfer and measuring the benefits provided to members.</p>
        <p>One lesson from the institute's experience is the importance of flexibility. The utility industry grew up in a world in which the cost of electricity dropped steadily and the main challenge was adding power plants fast enough to keep up with demand, which doubled every 10 to 15 years. That world has disappeared under the hammer-blows of oil crises, inflation and growing environmental problems. To make matters more complicated, deregulation encouraged companies and investors to develop private generating capacity and has allowed utilities to expand into new businesses.</p>
        <p>Today, most utilities are striving to find ways to pare their operating costs and to avoid building new power plants as long as possible. Their suppliers, faced with a prolonged period of depressed demand, have cut back on product research. And Government funding for research on energy technology, which was plentiful in the 1970's, has been pinched by efforts to control the Federal deficit.</p>
        <p>The institute has relied on advisory groups staffed by its members and an Advisory Council made up of regulators, academic experts and others not associated with its members to help it constantly reshape its mission in response to such change.</p>
        <p>These days, general research funding for new generating systems has been cut back, although the institute is deeply involved in an industry-wide effort to develop standard specifications for a new generation of safer and more reliable nuclear power plants. More attention is being paid to programs to extend the life of existing plants and increase their efficiency. Other projects include developing energy-efficient electric equipment for consumers and business customers, such as refrigeration systems for supermarkets and electric vans.</p>
        <p>In addition, millions of dollars have been devoted to research on environmental problems that never crossed the minds of the institute's founders, including acid rain, the greenhouse effect, the potential health impact of electromagnetic radiation from power lines and the possibility of using genetically-engineered bacteria to clean up toxic wastes from transformers.</p>
        <p>The institute's adjustment to changing times has been eased by its early decision to concentrate on contract research. Although it owns a number of testing facilities around the country, such as a model coal plant for testing environmental controls in Barker, N.Y., and operates others, like the High-Voltage Transmission Research Center in Lenox, Mass., it has generally avoided investing in laboratories. Thus, whenever a project is being organized, the institute is free to support whichever researchers in industry, government or academia appear to be the most likely to produce valuable results.</p>
        <p>''We invested in brains rather than bricks and mortar,'' said Richard Claeys, the institute's director of communications. ''That made us more nimble as technology and the industry's needs changed.''</p>
        <p>Institute executives claim that contracting out research has other benefits as well. If a major energy user like General Motors is the institute's partner in developing an electric processing technology, other potential users are more likely to adopt it. And if an independent scientist is retained by the institute to study acid rain, that study is likely to be regarded as more credible than research performed by the institute itself or one of the utilities.</p>
        <p>But contracting out creates its own problems. For instance, any time the institute works with a company to develop a product, the institute and its partner have to negotiate issues like ownership, royalties and manufacturing rights. If the incentives given to the company to commercialize the results are not sweet enough, the research investment may be largely wasted.</p>
        <p>Nor is contracting out a perfect shield against criticism of the value of the institute's research, especially on issues involving the environment and alternative energy sources.</p>
        <p>''They are contributing to the solution but not in a very aggressive way,'' said William Moomaw, director of the climate, energy and pollution program for the World Resources Institute in Washington. ''On issues like acid rain and global climate change, they tend to try to mobilize the arguments that exonerate the power industry. They have the centralized power station perspective on most things.''</p>
        <p>In response to such criticisms, institute executives say their job is to pursue the utilities' research agenda, not that of environmental groups or anyone else. The institute's goal on such sensitive issues is to make sure it is producing scientifically defensible results. ''Our attitude is that if we have problems, we are better off being the first to learn about it,'' said Mr. Balzhiser.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
