<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Future They See Works Like Today</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="267168"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WORLD FUTURE SOCIETY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIAMS, LENA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1D91431F93AA25754C0A96F948260" item-length="1199" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Future They See Works Like Today</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LENA WILLIAMS; Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILLIAMS, LENA</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: They came to glimpse another time, to explore a world that does not yet exist, to examine new frontiers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: They came to glimpse another time, to explore a world that does not yet exist, to examine new frontiers.</p>
        <p>They came to glimpse another time, to explore a world that does not yet exist, to examine new frontiers.</p>
        <p>Not Captain Kirk and the Starship Enterprise, but more than 3,000 futurists from 80 countries, members of the World Future Society.</p>
        <p>They converged on the Sheraton Washington Hotel this week to talk about the final years of the 20th century and the dawning of the 21st. The four-day conference, ''Future View: The 1990's &amp; Beyond,'' is the sixth held by the organization of 30,000 thinkers, dreamers and experts in business, energy, education, technology, science, defense and health.</p>
        <p>With the year 2000 only 11 years away, futurists themselves have become more conservative in their forecasts. Where 25 years ago they might have envisioned a world akin to that of the Jetsons, the science-fiction television cartoon family, with personal space vehicles, and meals delivered to the table via robot, today they are thinking and talking in more conventional terms.</p>
        <p>''What we are talking about is gently taking place now,'' said Dr. Marvin Cetron, president of Forecasting International Inc., a research analysis concern and co-author with Owen Davies of ''American Renaissance: Our Life at the Turn of the 21st Century,'' published this month by St. Martin's Press.</p>
        <p>In the book Dr. Cetron and Mr. Davies, by extrapolating from 74 current trends, provide an overview of the changes that will transform the United States by the 21st century.</p>
        <p>Among the trends are the use of personal computers for voting, for filing income-tax returns and for taking college examinations; 32-hour work weeks; modular plastic housing that can be packed and shipped to any locale; and the use of robots for mundane commercial and service jobs, environmentally dangerous jobs and repair of space stations in orbit.</p>
        <p>And what are some of the other developments foreseen by the society's seers?</p>
        <p>While there may be single-family homes underwater and in space, there will also be Tudor and Colonial-style homes. Time and Vogue will still be sold at newsstands, but they will also be available on floppy disks that allow ''readers'' to sift through the information on their personal computers. People will still drive cars, not space vehicles, but the cars last 30 years.</p>
        <p>''We are discovering things happening across the board, current trends and life-style patterns that are strong indicators of where we will be heading in the future,'' Dr. Cetron added. ''Our attitude is to see how we can help.''</p>
        <p>While Dr. Cetron and many of his colleagues share a guarded optimism about a future that offers Americans more career and educational opportunities, longer life spans and better health, many of the problems that have bothered and baffled American society for years - drug abuse, an unstable economy, environmental pollution - will follow it into the next century unless efforts are made now to reverse current trends.</p>
        <p>The conference, which opened Sunday night and ends Thursday, was organized around workshops with titles like biosphere, politisphere, technosphere, econosphere and futuresphere. The participants could choose among some 200 gatherings, ranging from luncheons and small workshops to large plenary sessions.</p>
        <p>In the exhibition hall, conferees could interact with the Droid Genesis, a household robot with a $12,500 price tag that cleans the house, washes your car, draws your bath and answers the phone. Or they could be polled by the Consensor, a computerized system that elicits the opinions of a group without revealing the views of individuals. Or they could be tested for their suitability to help colonize Mars.</p>
        <p>Throughout the conference, the Society, many of whose members are experts in business, energy, education, technology, science, defense, health and other fields offered possible solutions and ways in which America and the world could change course for the future.</p>
        <p>Among the proposals discussed in workshops were these: the decriminalization of drugs; extending the school day to seven hours through a longer school year; job retraining programs to upgrade skills and knowledge to keep pace with changing technologies and changing demands in the workplace; worldwide national policies to require less use of fossil fuels, develop more efficient energy technologies and combat deforestation.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rashmi Mayur, president of Global Futures Network in Bombay, India, and an adviser to the Mayor of Bombay, was a member of a a group that studied 21st-century issues in 31 nations.</p>
        <p>Noting that 90 percent of the Society's members are Americans and recognizing the difficulties the organization has had in recruiting members from third world countries, Dr. Mayur said at a news conference, ''We need the peoples of Asia, Africa and India in order to make our dialogue meaningful.''</p>
        <p>''In 1980, we had great expectations of world technologies,'' he continued. ''The problem is not with the technologies, but with people - human resources: illiteracy, infant and child mortality, debt. Future thinking and future research much be on a global level.'' Judging from the crowded workshops, the sold-out luncheon addresses and the wait for taxicabs, the conference organizers met their goals of attractinng participants, but not everyone was happy.</p>
        <p>''The problem with this conference is that it's all head,'' said Robert Theobald of Wickenburg, Ariz., who said he has been studying the future for 30 years and has written 15 books on the subject. ''People aren't getting a chance to participate.''</p>
        <p>Donna Bird, part-time instructor on the future at the Hartford College for Women and a community planner for the United Way of Hartford, said, ''What I'm seeing is that the rhetoric acknowledges the fact that change is needed, but the structure of the conference - experts on a stage, with the audience listening like in a college lecture - doesn't allow for enough audience input, give-and-take between the panelists and us.''</p>
        <p>On another front, Ms. Bird and Mr. Theobald said they were surprised at the numbers of women, blacks and other minorities in attendance, and both called attention to predictions that by the year 2000 present-day minority groups will have become the majority in the United States and, with women, will dominate the work force.</p>
        <p>Although the futurists have been wrong in the past, they have had their successes. Back in 1967, one year after its founding, the World Future Society said that people would soon walk on the moon, that non-Western cities would experience population explosions and that medical science would permit artificial organs to be implanted.</p>
        <p>''Part of the problem was that futurists of the past sometimes painted an incorrect view of the future,'' said Tim Willard, a spokesman for the Society, which has its headquarters in Bethesda, Md. ''They led people to believe that the new would replace the old, and it turned off a lot of people. At one time, we predicted that people could take a pill or seaweed and wouldn't have to eat anymore. Well, a lot of people like eating, yours truly included, and they couldn't stand the thought of giving that up. I think they're comforted by knowing steak and potatoes will still be around.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
