<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Let's Not Count on the Earth to Heal Itself; Wolf in the Greenhouse</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="271322"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HANSEN, JAMES E (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WADE, NICHOLAS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6DD1130F932A3575BC0A96F948260" item-length="652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Let's Not Count on the Earth to Heal Itself; Wolf in the Greenhouse</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Nicholas Wade, in ''Crying Wolf in the Greenhouse'' (Editorial Notebook, July 3) leaves the impression that I have used a single hot summer to argue that greenhouse warming is altering global climate. He also misrepresents alterations by the Office of Management and Budget to testimony I delivered to Congress this year.</p>
        <p>During the drought of 1988 I cautioned Congress not to blame the greenhouse effect for a specific heat wave. However, from numerical climate simulations at our institute and other laboratories, historical observations, paleoclimate records and studies of other planets, I argued that the growing greenhouse effect increases the likelihood of such events. If our estimates are approximately correct, increased frequency of warm seasons will be obvious to the man in the street in a decade.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wade quotes a single caveat the Office of Management and Budget inserted into my testimony: that climate simulations ''should be viewed as estimates from evolving computer models and not as reliable predictions.'' For the climate of a specific region, yes. But my conclusions did not require precise climate simulations. Thus, the function of the censor's caveat was to obfuscate my testimony.</p>
        <p>O.M.B. also inserted a statement suggesting that increases in greenhouse gases may be a natural phenomenon and altered my recommen-dation for steps to reduce the greenhouse effect, specifically phaseout of chlorofluorocarbons, improved energy efficiency and reduced deforestation.</p>
        <p>The principal conclusion of my testimony this year was that a growing greenhouse effect increases the intensity of both heavy rainfall, floods and storms, on the one hand, and droughts on the other. Over the ocean and wet regions, added greenhouse heating increases evaporation. Thus, precipitation increases in marine areas, as well as in land areas supplied by moist air masses from the ocean. In such regions, added water vapor and higher ocean temperatures increase the potential for storms driven by latent heat of condensation, such as hurricanes and thunderstorms.</p>
        <p>But droughts are also expected to intensify as greenhouse gases increase. Added greenhouse heating of the earth's surface intensifies hot dry conditions in dry land areas. Global models confirm the increased occurrence of both a strong drought index and intense precipitation as the greenhouse effect grows. Although the models cannot provide precise information, such as when fluctuations from dry to wet conditions will occur, they are valuable for testing our understanding of climate mechanisms.</p>
        <p>In defense of global models, in more than 20 years of such three-dimensional simulations, the estimates that the earth will warm by about 3 degrees Celsius for a doubling of carbon dioxide have varied by less than a factor of two. And the first simple model calculations, by the Nobel Prize winner Svante Arrhenius in the 1890's, were within that range.</p>
        <p>The danger of crying wolf too soon, which much of the scientific community fears, is that a few cool years may discredit the greenhouse issue. But I believe that decision makers and the man in the street can be educated about climate variability, and the fact that regional variability exceeds greenhouse warming.</p>
        <p>A greater danger is to wait too long. The climate system has great inertia, so we have realized only part of the climate change that will be caused by gases we have added to the atmosphere. Add to this the inertia of the world's energy, economic and political systems, which will affect any plans to reduce greenhouse gas emissions. I am optimistic that we can still avoid the worst-case climate scenarios, but the time to cry wolf is here. JAMES E. HANSEN  New York, July 14, 1989</p>
        <p>The writer is head of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration Goddard Institute for Space Studies and an adjunct professor at Columbia University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
