<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>President Bush Breaks the Reagan Ice</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="220436"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MISSILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE WEAPONS (STAR WARS)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DB1031F937A35751C0A96F948260" item-length="496" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>President Bush Breaks the Reagan Ice</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush has been working for weeks to distance himself from Ronald Reagan, mostly in terms of symbolism and style. His restless energy, folksy ways with Congress (''just call me George'') and affable handling of the press have won favor even from his opponents. Now there are plausible signs of substantive changes as well.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush has been working for weeks to distance himself from Ronald Reagan, mostly in terms of symbolism and style. His restless energy, folksy ways with Congress (''just call me George'') and affable handling of the press have won favor even from his opponents. Now there are plausible signs of substantive changes as well.</p>
        <p>President Bush has been working for weeks to distance himself from Ronald Reagan, mostly in terms of symbolism and style. His restless energy, folksy ways with Congress (''just call me George'') and affable handling of the press have won favor even from his opponents. Now there are plausible signs of substantive changes as well.</p>
        <p>The most dramatic break concerns Star Wars. John Tower, the Defense Secretary-designate, told Congress that he and Mr. Bush regarded as ''unrealistic'' Mr. Reagan's scheme to build an electronic shield against enemy missiles. Regrettably, Mr. Tower left open the possibility that he might accept a more modest version; even a small system would be destabilizing. But Mr. Reagan's cherished Star Wars fantasy is dead - killed, without tears, by Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Another break, approximately as dramatic, concerns acid rain. William Reilly, Mr. Bush's choice to head the Environmental Protection Agency, says the Administration will propose legislation to curtail it. Acid rain from industrial sources in the Middle West is as real as Star Wars was illusory; there are dead lakes in Canada and the Northeast to prove it. Yet for eight years Mr. Reagan casually ignored the evidence, as if the issue were the invention of crazed environmentalists. He did nothing beyond urging more superfluous research.</p>
        <p>The new look in policy was reflected also in Secretary of State James Baker's first public appearance. He urged international cooperation against the dangers of global warming through reduced emissions, improved energy efficiency and reforestation. This, too, is an issue the Reagan Administration virtually ignored.</p>
        <p>There are other signs of dramatic policy change. Off the record, the President's aides say he will not seek renewed military aid to the Nicaraguan rebels, a crusade that cost Mr. Reagan heavily. On the record, Mr. Bush has urged his officials to abide by strict ethical standards, in implicit contrast with the shabby performance of high Reagan officials.</p>
        <p>Some things haven't changed. Like Mr. Reagan, President Bush continues to oppose the Supreme Court's 1973 decision legalizing abortion. Judging by his commitment to cut the capital gains tax, he has not retreated from his faith that the nation can grow out of its deficit problems without new taxes - a notion he once called sorcery. Still, it's hard to pick up a newspaper without finding another new report of another different Bush course.</p>
        <p>For now, these statements are just promissory notes. Nobody knows how much Mr. Bush is prepared to spend, for instance, on problems like drug abuse and child care, and they won't until he unveils his budget Feb. 9.</p>
        <p>Even so, the new President has offered up what Senator Alan Simpson calls ''real, uncontrived changes in policy'' on several striking issues. Two weeks do not an administration make. But in a matter of days, Mr. Bush has served welcome notice that he's determined to break his way out of years of Reagan ice.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
