<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Drought Worry: No Snowpack In the Catskills</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="232602"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DROUGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHORTAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESERVOIRS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SNOW AND SNOWSTORMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CATSKILL MOUNTAINS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUOMO, MARIO M (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WOLFF, CRAIG</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waterways and Other Bodies of Water</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DE1E31F93BA25750C0A96F948260" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Drought Worry: No Snowpack In the Catskills</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG WOLFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WOLFF, CRAIG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: With reservoirs at half their capacity and forecasters predicting a typical spring, the drought that has struck lower New York State this year looks no more foreboding than previous dry spells. But there is a difference: The snows did not come this winter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: With reservoirs at half their capacity and forecasters predicting a typical spring, the drought that has struck lower New York State this year looks no more foreboding than previous dry spells. But there is a difference: The snows did not come this winter.</p>
        <p>With reservoirs at half their capacity and forecasters predicting a typical spring, the drought that has struck lower New York State this year looks no more foreboding than previous dry spells. But there is a difference: The snows did not come this winter.</p>
        <p>Therefore, there will be no snowpack to nourish the water supply, and the reservoirs may hit lows never seen before. There are normally 8 to 10 inches of snow lying ready to run downhill in spring.</p>
        <p>''The snowmelt is at absolutely zero,'' said Edward C. Scheader, the deputy director of New York City's Bureau of Water Supply. ''I don't see anything that will spare us, not soon.''</p>
        <p>In the next few months, the watershed's luck with storm fronts could change. All winter it was unlucky - snowstorms hit areas in and around New York, but just missed the highlands of the Catskill Mountains, which remain cold enough to build up a spring snowpack and from which the city ultimately gets 90 percent of its water. Perilous Statistic: 3.35 Inches</p>
        <p>When Gov. Mario M. Cuomo signed the executive order on Thursday declaring a drought emergency, the third in the last 10 years, he was persuaded to do so by one perilous statistic: From Jan. 1 to March 16, the total precipitation in the upstate watershed was 3.35 inches, the lowest in history and more than four inches below normal. Precipitation is the amount of rain plus the amount of water that any snow that fell would melt into.</p>
        <p>That figure makes even the droughts of 1964, 1981 and 1985 seem dewy by comparison. In 1964, for example, when the state endured its most prolonged drought, there were 9.32 inches from Jan. 1 to March 16.</p>
        <p>''This is at least as serious as 1964,'' Mr. Cuomo said. ''It'll go away only if we make it go away - by not using water.''</p>
        <p>A normal ''water year'' - which begins on June 1, when reservoirs are at their fullest - has peaks and valleys. A drought, however, results from a multitude of factors: climate, the size of the reservoir system, population and consumption trends.</p>
        <p>The current drought is aggravated by New York City's water demand, which has grown to 1.5 billion gallons a day. It was about 1.2 billion a day in 1965.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, restrictions on water use may be imposed next week in 200 communities in the western third of the state that are part of the Delaware River Basin. Reservoirs are at 50 percent of normal there. But reservoirs in the heavily populated northeastern corner of the state are at 84 percent of capacity, the State Department of Environmental Protection said.</p>
        <p>In Connecticut, Stamford, with reservoirs at 60 percent of capacity, has had restrictions on lawn-watering and car-washing in effect since October. Reservoirs in Greenwich, Danbury and Norwalk are at better than 90 percent capacity, and no other section of the state is facing restrictions like Stamford's.</p>
        <p>If New York's drought worsens, the city will be forced to activate a Chelsea, N.Y. pumping station to draw water from the Hudson River.</p>
        <p>Before the 1960's, droughts arrived about once a decade. But Thomas D. O'Connell, the chief of strategic services for the Bureau of Water Supply, refers to the 1960's as ''one long drought.'' The city's system was smaller than it is today and water-profligate suburbs connected to it grew.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Connell, who, like Mr. Scheader, considers himself a student of the state's drought history, recalled that during the 1960's the final blocks of the Delaware System were still being added to the Catskills system, a project that would ultimately give New York City 550 billion gallons in reserve capacity. Before the work could be completed, a drought hit the entire Northeast. It began in 1961 and persisted until 1967, with the worst stretch between 1964 and 1965.</p>
        <p>On March 16, 1964, the reservoirs were at 68.8 percent of capacity. In a year, they were down to 38 percent. The normal level for this time of year is about 89 percent.</p>
        <p>Then came the wettest period in the state's history, which ran from 1967 into 1980.</p>
        <p>The first drought emergency calling for restrictions on businesses and residents was declared on Jan. 19, 1981. By February 1, reservoirs reached 28.7 percent, their all-time low. Then 11 inches of rain and snow soaked the watershed, and by March 16, reservoirs were at 65.9 percent of capacity.</p>
        <p>Officials lacked a sense of urgency in 1985, perhaps because, as Mr. Scheader said, ''We never believe it's going to be as bad as the last one.''</p>
        <p>The reserve then was barely above where it is now, at 57.2 percent, but Mr. Cuomo did not declare an emergency until April 26.</p>
        <p>With a third drought emergency this decade, some officials are concerned that New York has become the victim of the greenhouse effect. They expect more water shortages in the future.</p>
        <p>But Mr. O'Connell, for one, dismisses these fears, saying that New York is in this crisis only for want of a few snowstorms in the right spots.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
