<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Next Refrigerator May Take a Step Back</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="228446"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFRIGERATORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREEZERS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLUSHA, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6DA1F38F937A35750C0A96F948260" item-length="1189" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Next Refrigerator May Take a Step Back</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN HOLUSHA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLUSHA, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In recent decades, refrigerators have gotten bigger, more stylish and - since the mid-1970's at least -more energy efficient as well. But a growing conflict between rules intended to improve the energy efficiency of appliances and measures to protect the earth's ozone layer may produce a new generation of more costly, less convenient refrigerators and freezers in the 1990's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In recent decades, refrigerators have gotten bigger, more stylish and - since the mid-1970's at least -more energy efficient as well. But a growing conflict between rules intended to improve the energy efficiency of appliances and measures to protect the earth's ozone layer may produce a new generation of more costly, less convenient refrigerators and freezers in the 1990's.</p>
        <p>In recent decades, refrigerators have gotten bigger, more stylish and - since the mid-1970's at least -more energy efficient as well. But a growing conflict between rules intended to improve the energy efficiency of appliances and measures to protect the earth's ozone layer may produce a new generation of more costly, less convenient refrigerators and freezers in the 1990's.</p>
        <p>That, at least, is the view of many appliance makers, who must deal with the prospect of a forthcoming ban on both the fluid used in refrigeration units and a principal component of the insulation in the walls and doors of the units.</p>
        <p>Both the refrigerant and the insulation component are chlorofluorocarbons, members of a family of chemicals that have been identified as major contributors to ozone depletion. Ozone in the stratosphere protects the earth from harmful ultraviolet radiation. Although alternatives for the two substances, known as CFC 11 and CFC 12, are being developed, manufacturers say none appear to be as energy efficient or problem free as the materials now in use. European Community Agreement</p>
        <p>The likelihood that the use of chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, will be tightly restricted in the near future increased this week when the 12 countries of the European Community agreed to cease production by the end of the century and cut usage by 85 percent as soon as possible.</p>
        <p>American officials are also considering a complete phase-out by 2000. Last year, a larger group of nations attending a conference in Montreal agreed to a 50 percent cutback by the end of the century, but new evidence of damage to the ozone layer has prompted the calls for more drastic reductions.</p>
        <p>The need to switch to less efficient substitutes for CFC's comes at a time when domestic manufacturers of refrigerators and freezers are facing higher Federal energy standards and may be forced to meet even more stringent requirements in 1993. The rules would reduce the number of kilowatt-hours of electrical power each appliance could use annually. Sales of new refrigerators and freezers by American manufacturers totaled over $3 billion in 1987, the last year for which figures are complete. Choice: Efficiency or Ozone</p>
        <p>The loss of the CFC materials, best known as Freon, the Du Pont Company's brand, will make it difficult to reach even the 1990 standard, manufacturers say. ''We've used more and more Freon to get to higher efficiency levels,'' said Fred Hallett of White Consolidated Industries. ''Now we have a public policy dilemma. Do we want to protect the ozone or have greater energy efficiency? It's a real Catch-22.''</p>
        <p>Although Freon and similar materials from other manufacturers are most widely known as refrigerants, their greatest use in recent years has been in insulation. Insulation in modern refrigerators and freezers is a rigid foam that is injected as a liquid during the manufacturing process and allowed to expand into place. CFC 11 is used to help disperse the foam throughout the cabinet and, locked in the closed cells of the foam, acts as an insulator.</p>
        <p>The use of foam insulation has permitted thinner walls, and consequently larger interior volumes, than were possible with older types of fiberglass insulation. Indeed, the foam is an important part of the structure of modern refrigeration units, helping support the thin metal outer walls and plastic interiors. A Typical Refrigerator</p>
        <p>A typical refrigerator now has two and a half pounds of CFC 11 in its insulation and about eight ounces of CFC 12 in its cooling system.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency has proposed a sharp reduction in the production and use of CFC's, with a view to their eventual elimination. Some key manufacturers, including Du Pont, the largest single manufacturer of the chemicals, have pledged complete phase-outs of production, regardless of regulations.</p>
        <p>''Everyone is scrambling around for solutions,'' said Marian Stamos, an official of the Association of Home Appliance Manufacturers, a trade group. ''We have a classic case of a design that has worked well, but now an essential part of it has been found to be a bad thing.''</p>
        <p>CFC 12, in fact, is essentially unchanged since it was developed in the early 1930's by what later became the Delco division of the General Motors Corporation. Heavier Refrigerator, Higher Cost</p>
        <p>Since all the compounds that have been offered as substitutes for CFC 11 have less insulating value, manufacturers fear they may have to design thicker refrigerator and freezer walls to meet energy efficiency standards. ''We are probably going to end up with heavier, bulkier refrigerators,'' said Robert Gants, another official at the association. Prices will probably be higher as well, he said, because of the costs of redesigning the appliances and retooling production lines.</p>
        <p>Indeed, according to the association, just redesigning compressors and other parts of the cooling system to accommodate substitutes for CFC 12 will add $100 to $120 to the price of a typical refrigerator.</p>
        <p>''The new molecules won't insulate as well as CFC 11,'' said C. A. McCain, who is in charge of developing alternatives for CFC's at Du Pont. ''They should provide about 90 percent of its insulating value.'' The proposed substitutes are expected to be more expensive as well, with alternatives to CFC 12 costing about twice as much, and CFC 11 substitutes three to five times as much. Federal Controls Accepted in 1987</p>
        <p>The appliance industry agreed to Federal controls on energy efficiency in 1987, in part to pre-empt efforts at regulation at the state level. ''Our members sell to a national market,'' Mr. Gants said, ''and we felt that a single national standard was preferable to many state standards.''</p>
        <p>But that was before the connection between CFC's and ozone depletion was firmly established. Faced with the loss of CFC 11 and CFC 12, refrigerator makers said they were stunned when the Department of Energy proposed late last year to increase energy-efficiency requirements by as much as 32 percent starting in 1993. ''We said, 'You have got to be kidding,' '' Mr. Hallett of White Consolidated said.</p>
        <p>The department also has the option of keeping the 1990 standards, which require a 3.6 percent increase in refrigerator efficiency and a 7.5 percent increase in freezer efficiency, in place after 1993. The industry is hoping that option will be chosen. 'A Timing Problem'</p>
        <p>''It is really a timing problem,'' Ms. Stamos said. ''Right now we do not know how to meet the higher standards. In two or three years we may be able to deal with it.''</p>
        <p>Because consumers expect refrigerators and freezers to work for 15 to 20 years without service, manufacturers say they must carefully test any new refrigerant or insulation for long-term compatibility with other components. ''If one little elastomer fitting is not compatible, it could cause problems in the field,'' Mr. McCain said.</p>
        <p>But some regulators think the imminent disappearance of CFC 11 and CFC 12 and tougher energy-efficiency rules will force the appliance industry to re-examine the basic design of its products.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
