<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; Murky Choices On Methanol</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="271410"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ECONOMIC SCENE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DA1F3BF931A3575BC0A96F948260" item-length="804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; Murky Choices On Methanol</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IS methanol the fuel in your future?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IS methanol the fuel in your future?</p>
        <p>IS methanol the fuel in your future?</p>
        <p>If President Bush has his way, one-third of the vehicles in heavily polluted cities will someday be powered with cleaner-burning alternatives to gasoline and diesel fuel. And if key officials at the Environmental Protection Agency have their way, that alternative fuel will be methanol - the solvent also known as wood alcohol.</p>
        <p>Methanol, its fans say, offers an efficient way to reduce the ozone pollution that fouls car-congested regions from Los Angeles to the surburban sprawl of Connecticut. But not all the experts share their enthusiasm.</p>
        <p>There is some dispute over the hazards of handling methanol and its probable impact on ozone formation. And, as an internal White House memo argues, there is a looming and not easily resolvable question about the cost of a methanol fix.</p>
        <p>Much depends on the future price of natural gas, the raw material used to synthesize methanol. If cheap, reliable sources are available, the switch to methanol would be virtually painless. If the energy-equivalent price of natural gas were even close to that of oil, however, methanol would become incredibly expensive. And regulations to enforce its use would be a nightmare to administer.</p>
        <p>When the hydrocarbon molecules in gasoline and other volatile chemicals are exposed to sunlight, they form ozone. Unlike the friendly layer of ozone in the upper atmosphere that protects children and other living things from ultraviolet radiation, ozone at ground level is hard on the lungs.</p>
        <p>Hydrocarbon leakage into the atmosphere can be slowed in a variety of ways. But many environmental scientists are convinced that safe ozone levels cannot be reached at reasonable cost in pollution-prone areas without a switch in auto fuels.</p>
        <p>Methanol is a prime candidate, and for good reason. The range of a methanol car would be far greater than one operating on electricity or compressed natural gas. Moreover, cars that burn both methanol and gasoline would cost just a few hundred dollars extra to build - far less than other alternatives.</p>
        <p>Best of all, methanol might provide an environmental free lunch. Much of the natural gas extracted in the Persian Gulf and the Soviet Union is an unwanted byproduct of oil production. It is thus flared at the wellhead, worsening the greenhouse effect. But with a guaranteed American market for methanol, it would pay to convert this waste gas to the alcohol fuel.</p>
        <p>The American Petroleum Institute disputes claims that methanol is no more toxic than gasoline. And it questions the validity of studies showing that methanol vehicles would be less polluting than gasoline-powered ones equipped with sophisticated emissions controls. But even accepting the Environmental Protection Agency's more favorable health and safety conclusions at face value, there remains a serious issue about the economics of methanol.</p>
        <p>Richard Schmalensee, a member of the President's Council of Economic Advisers, argues in a May 30 memo that if methanol remains cheap and gasoline prices rise, the methanol fix would prove costless. But if growing demand for natural gas as a heating fuel eventually gives foreign producers the leverage to charge as much for gas as American producers already charge, methanol would become an economic fiasco.</p>
        <p>The cost of substituting methanol to reduce tailpipe emissions would reach tens of thousands of dollars a ton, many times more than the cost of containing the pollution from industrial sources.</p>
        <p>What is more, the economic disaster would be mirrored in regulatory trauma. Since methanol provides fewer miles per gallon than gasoline, the price at the pump would have to be adjusted to persuade the owners of flexible-fuel vehicles to use methanol.</p>
        <p>Fuel distributors or service stations could be ordered to equalize the prices, increasing the markup on gasoline and using the revenue to subsidize methanol. If the underlying cost difference were large, however, there would be powerful incentives to bootleg gasoline from outside the methanol-mandated region.</p>
        <p>A way out of the bind would be to tax gasoline nationally, with the proceeds used to subsidize methanol in high-pollution cities. It might not be easy, though, to persuade drivers - and voters -in places with clean air to share the tab.</p>
        <p>The uncertainties with methanol are not unique, and switching to any alternative fuel would involve risks. But as one Administration analyst argues, the risks should be weighed against the potential gains.</p>
        <p>It might, for example, pay to start cautiously, building the alternative-fuel fleets and the means to distribute the fuel in a single city - most likely Los Angeles. It might also pay to try less-radical approaches to ozone control to see how far cities can go without opting for an expensive, difficult-to-reverse change in technology.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
