<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Malibu Journal; Where 'Making Waves' Means Something Else</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="267769"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURFING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MALIBU (CALIF)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SURFRIDER FOUNDATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MYDANS, SETH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Surfing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Malibu</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surfing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDD113AF932A15754C0A96F948260" item-length="713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Malibu Journal; Where 'Making Waves' Means Something Else</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MYDANS, SETH</byline>
      <dateline>MALIBU, Calif., July 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Much of Southern California has been paved over to create smooth rides, so why not the bottom of the ocean?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Much of Southern California has been paved over to create smooth rides, so why not the bottom of the ocean?</p>
        <p>Much of Southern California has been paved over to create smooth rides, so why not the bottom of the ocean?</p>
        <p>A surfing organization is studying whether it would be practical to build an underwater reef that would insure a constant supply of smooth, even waves the way a baseball pitching machine pops out endless strikes.</p>
        <p>Backers of the $2 million project and other experts on the subject insist there is an urgent need for what they say would be the first permament artificial reef for surfing.</p>
        <p>The surf in California, they say, is down.</p>
        <p>Over the past 20 years, construction of harbors and piers and oceanside freeways has destroyed some classic surfing spots. Dams and dredging on rivers have deprived coastal areas of the silt that helps create surf, and the popularity of the sport has created competition for waves that has been likened to gang warfare.</p>
        <p>With a long-range perspective not usually associated with surfers, the project's backers are also worrying about global warming and the rising level of the ocean.</p>
        <p>''It's common knowledge that a place like Malibu does not have the waves it had 20 years ago,'' said Kevin Sweeney of the Surfrider Foundation, which is working on plans for the reef.</p>
        <p>A $25,000 study commissioned by the foundation and financed by Yvon Chouinard, a mountain-climbing enthusiast who is president of the outdoor-clothing maker Patagonia, proposed building a rounded, triangular 300-yard-long reef 100 yards off Emma State Beach in Ventura.</p>
        <p>It would be constructed from 5- to 10-ton concrete blocks lashed together with plastic and steel chains and would remain at least four feet below the surface at low tide.</p>
        <p>Its special engineering would guarantee waves that would lengthen for a smooth glide perhaps 100 yards long.</p>
        <p>At the Topanga Canyon beach near here, for one example, the waves should be at their peak, but surfers were squeezing out rides of 10 or 20 yards the other day.</p>
        <p>The model proposed by the initial study is not the last word, said Michael Harrelson, a spokesman for Patagonia. Other studies are needed, particularly focusing on safety questions so as to obtain state and local licenses for the project.</p>
        <p>''Quite a few people feel that it is kind of unnatural to do this, to throw a bunch of concrete down to create good waves,'' said Matt Warshaw, managing editor of Surfer Magazine.</p>
        <p>But he said at least a dozen of the world's best locations for waves, from California to Hawaii to Australia, were man-made - ''happy accidents'' that resulted from the construction of piers or jetties or the offshore dumping of construction waste.</p>
        <p>Indeed, he said, at least as many fine waves had been created as destroyed in California through oceanside construction, although he agreed that this did not make it right to spoil the beaches.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, though, Mr, Warshaw said, the surfing population has grown until ''there's too many rats in the cage.''</p>
        <p>''It's vicious, you know,'' he said. ''You've got to completely leave your civility on the beach if you're going to go out there and get what might be considered your fair share of waves.''</p>
        <p>One dodge is night surfing, which he described as ''ghostly, just silver and shadows.'' Last summer, Mr. Warshaw said, he found himself jostling with 14 other surfers for the best waves at 1 A.M.</p>
        <p>If the Surfrider Foundation's plan crosses its various hurdles and goes into construction in perhaps one or two years, its backers said, it could serve as the model for reefs up and down the coast that would improve waves and reduce crowding.</p>
        <p>It still needs approval not only from various local governments but also from the Army Corps of Engineers, the United States Fish and Wildlife Service, the State Department of Fish and Game, the State Department of Parks and Recreation and the State Coastal Commission.</p>
        <p>The foundation is therefore trying to broaden the project's appeal by modifying its design to aid in fish conservation and in preventing coastal erosion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sweeney says the very character of California is at stake.</p>
        <p>''As the world becomes more homogeneous, you want to have things that establish and mark your area as different,'' he said. ''How does an individual know that he is a Californian? Surfing is one of the things that has helped define the state.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
