<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PORTRAIT OF THE 1980's; Selections From 10 Years of History</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="311693"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NINETEEN HUNDRED EIGHTIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D7103AF937A15751C1A96F948260" item-length="5628" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PORTRAIT OF THE 1980's; Selections From 10 Years of History</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: What happened? Morning in America, hole in the ozone, Oliver North, AIDS, terrorists, contras like Founding Fathers, $640 toilet seats, triumph of democracy, just say no.  1980  It's America vs. the Soviet Union, Khomeini, Castro, inflation and Jimmy Carter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: What happened? Morning in America, hole in the ozone, Oliver North, AIDS, terrorists, contras like Founding Fathers, $640 toilet seats, triumph of democracy, just say no.  1980  It's America vs. the Soviet Union, Khomeini, Castro, inflation and Jimmy Carter.</p>
        <p>What happened? Morning in America, hole in the ozone, Oliver North, AIDS, terrorists, contras like Founding Fathers, $640 toilet seats, triumph of democracy, just say no.  1980  It's America vs. the Soviet Union, Khomeini, Castro, inflation and Jimmy Carter.</p>
        <p>January: The U.S. embargoes grain and high-technology exports to the Soviet Union in retaliation for its occupation of Afghanistan at the end of 1979. President Carter warns that the U.S. might boycott the summer Olympics in Moscow.</p>
        <p>After criticizing Moscow's move into Afghanistan, Andrei D. Sakharov, the most prominent Soviet dissident, is arrested in Moscow and ordered into internal exile in the city of Gorky.</p>
        <p>February: In a sweeping inquiry into suspected bribe-taking and other corruption, 31 public officials, including a U.S. Senator and seven representatives, are reported to be subjects of an F.B.I. undercover operation called Abscam.</p>
        <p>March: A sniper kills the outspoken Archbishop of San Salvador, Oscar Arnulfo Romero. The country's polarization intensifies and soon turns into civil war.</p>
        <p>April: President Carter breaks relations with Iran after Islamic militants continue to hold American Embassy employees taken hostage in November 1979. A rescue mission fails.</p>
        <p>After 90 years of white rule, Rhodesia becomes the independent nation of Zimbabwe, led by an elected leader, Robert Mugabe.</p>
        <p>May: Fidel Castro allows a flood of Cubans to leave the port of Mariel for the United States. Mr. Carter welcomes them with ''open arms,'' but the mood changes after it becomes known that criminals and mentally ill people are included.</p>
        <p>Mount St. Helens in Oregon blows its top, spewing steam and ash 60,000 feet in the air.</p>
        <p>August: Caving in after two weeks of crippling strikes, the Polish Government agrees to give workers the right to strike and form independent unions - the first time such a right has been granted in the Soviet bloc. The strikes were led by Lech Walesa, an electrician.</p>
        <p>September: Iraq, taking advantage of the turmoil in Iran to strike a blow against its hated neighbor, attacks Iranian oil and air fields, and war begins. In November oil prices reach $43 a barrel on the spot market, the 1980's peak, as Persian Gulf tanker traffic is threatened.</p>
        <p>October: Ronald Reagan, who capitalized on frustration over double-digit inflation, a gasoline crisis and the failure to rescue the hostages in his campaign for President, has the most memorable line in the debate with Mr. Carter: ''Are you better off than you were four years ago?''</p>
        <p>November: Mr. Reagan wins in a landslide, carrying 43 states, and is the first candidate since Franklin D. Roosevelt to defeat an incumbent. The Democrats lose the Senate for the first time since 1954.</p>
        <p>The world learns that Saturn has scores of rings, not six, from the spectacular pictures sent back by Voyager 1.</p>
        <p>In China, Deng Xiaoping enjoys the trial of his hard-line nemeses: Mao's widow, Jiang Qing, and other members of the Gang of Four.</p>
        <p>December: Three Roman Catholic nuns and a lay worker from the U.S. are murdered in El Salvador. Right-wing death squads are blamed. The U.S. halts new aid and calls for a reshuffling of the military-civilian Government. Jose Napoleon Duarte becomes its leader.</p>
        <p>Violent deaths: Dr. Herman Tarnower (shot by Jean Harris); Anastasio Somoza Debayle, deposed Nicaraguan leader (shot in exile in Paraguay); John Lennon (shot by a disturbed fan).  1981  Enter Reagan, 'Dynasty' and brief notice of an unusual malady among homosexual men.</p>
        <p>January: ABC introduces ''Dynasty,'' a celebration of glamour and greed. It becomes a huge hit.</p>
        <p>On his last day in office, President Carter says an accord has been reached for releasing the hostages. Criticizing the deal, a Reagan adviser says, ''This Administration will not negotiate with barbarians or terrorists.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reagan, sworn in as 40th President, promises an ''era of renewal,'' and warns of tremendous ''upheavals'' if the deficit continues to grow.</p>
        <p>Minutes after his inauguration, the hostages are released, after 444 days in captivity.</p>
        <p>March: John W. Hinckley Jr. shoots President Reagan and his press secretary, James S. Brady, in Washington.</p>
        <p>May: Pope John Paul II is shot in St. Peter's Square by a Turkish terrorist.</p>
        <p>June: In what will later be recognized as the first official notice of AIDS, the Centers for Disease Control prints a short report on the ''unusual'' occurrence in five homosexual men in Los Angeles of a deadly form of pneumonia.</p>
        <p>Baseball's first midseason strike begins. It lasts until July 31.</p>
        <p>''We love your adherence to democratic principle,'' Vice President George Bush tells Ferdinand E. Marcos after the Philippine President's re-inauguration.</p>
        <p>July: Prince Charles and Lady Diana Spencer are married and for a brief time even the London tabloid press believes in fairy tales.</p>
        <p>In a masterly triumph for President Reagan, Congress approves the deepest tax and budget cuts in American history.</p>
        <p>Brig. Gen. Omar Torrijos Herrera of Panama is killed in a plane crash. In the struggle that follows, it is clear that Col. Manuel Antonio Noriega, the country's most feared figure, is the ultimate arbiter of power.</p>
        <p>August: MTV, cable television's first 24-hour music channel, goes on the air.</p>
        <p>President Reagan dismisses striking air traffic controllers, breaking their union and dealing a devastating blow to labor.</p>
        <p>September: Responding to cuts in the school lunch program, the Agriculture Department says ketchup can be counted as a vegetable. After an uproar, the President withdraws the plan.</p>
        <p>The Senate raises the Federal debt limit to $1.08 trillion, the first time the ceiling is raised over the $1 trillion mark.</p>
        <p>The Senate confirms Sandra Day O'Connor for the Supreme Court. She becomes the first woman to become a justice.</p>
        <p>October: Anwar el-Sadat is killed by Muslim militants. The Egyptian presidency passes to Hosni Mubarak.</p>
        <p>November: David A. Stockman, the White House budget director, pays ''a visit to the woodshed'' for statements undermining Administration policy that appeared in a magazine.</p>
        <p>December: After a year of unrest, Gen. Wojciech Jaruzelski declares martial law in Poland. Solidarity is outlawed, and Lech Walesa and other oppositionists will spend months or years in prison, or go underground.  1982  In a recession year, Dr. Koop and Jane Fonda are ascending, and stocks are up, too.</p>
        <p>January: The White House says it approves of giving tax-exempt status to Bob Jones University of South Carolina and other schools that are accused of racial discrimination.</p>
        <p>February: In his budget address, President Reagan calls for less social spending and a lot more military spending.</p>
        <p>The Surgeon General, C. Everett Koop, calls smoking the most important health issue of the day and warns of the dangers of ''passive smoking'' - breathing someone else's tobacco fumes.</p>
        <p>April: Argentina's governing junta announces it has seized the Falkland Islands from Britain, which sends a flotilla of warships the next day.</p>
        <p>May: Jane Fonda's aerobic exercise book is a hit and the fitness craze goes into its ''no pain, no gain'' phase.</p>
        <p>June: Israel invades Lebanon in a campaign that will drive Yasir Arafat and the P.L.O. from their base in Lebanon, while failing to secure a friendly Christian government. Syria, not Israel, will eventually be the power broker in Lebanon.</p>
        <p>The Government announces stiff penalties on steel imports in an attempt to help struggling American steelmakers.</p>
        <p>An estimated 750,000 people demonstrate against nuclear arms in Central Park in New York. The freeze movement becomes a cause celebre.</p>
        <p>Argentina is humiliated by Britain and surrenders in the Falklands. The defeat hastens the demise of the military dictatorship.</p>
        <p>The deadline passes for the Equal Rights Amendment, which falls three states short of the number needed for ratification.</p>
        <p>September: Bashir Gemayel, Lebanon's Israeli-backed President, is assassinated. After Israeli troops move into West Beirut, Christian militiamen massacre hundreds of Palestinians in the Sabra and Shatila refugee camps there.</p>
        <p>Princess Grace of Monaco dies after an auto accident.</p>
        <p>October: President Reagan announces a war on drugs.</p>
        <p>John Z. Delorean is charged with cocaine trafficking and racketeering. Prosecutors say he was trying to raise money to save his automobile company. He is later acquitted.  November: Recession and high unemployment help the Democrats pick up 26 seats in the House and seven governorships during the midterm elections.</p>
        <p>The so-called Volcker recession reaches a painful climax when unemployment hits 10.8 percent in November, the highest since 1940. But interest rates have fallen, inflation is down and the stock market is bullish.</p>
        <p>Leonid I. Brezhnev dies at 75. The Soviet leader's rule was marked by increasing stagnation and corruption and a huge military buildup. He is succeeded by Yuri V. Andropov, the former head of the K.G.B.</p>
        <p>A black granite memorial etched with the names of the 57,939 soldiers killed or missing in Vietnam is dedicated in Washington.</p>
        <p>December: Dr. Barney B. Clark becomes the first recipient of a permanent artificial heart, but dies less than four months later.</p>
        <p>Congress approves the Boland Amendment, prohibiting the C.I.A. and Defense Department from financing the overthrow of the Nicaraguan Government.  1983  The 'evil empire' and 'Star Wars' appear and Grenada winds up the year, with hostilities between.</p>
        <p>January: Michael Jackson's ''Thriller'' joins the Billboard Top Ten, where it will stay for a year and a half, becoming the best-selling album in history.</p>
        <p>February: Under Congressional investigation for conflicts of interest and mismanagement, Rita M. Lavelle, the head of the Environmental Protection Agency's Superfund program to clean up toxic waste, is fired by President Reagan. A month later Anne McGill Burford, the E.P.A. Administrator, is forced to resign. Miss Lavelle later serves four months in prison for lying to Congress.</p>
        <p>The final show of ''M*A*S*H'' displaces the ''Who Shot J.R.'' episode on ''Dallas'' as the most watched segment of a television series.</p>
        <p>March: Mr. Reagan tells an evangelical group that the Soviet Union is ''the focus of evil in the modern world'' and ''an evil empire.''</p>
        <p>Two weeks later, he proposes a space-based missile defense system and ''Star Wars'' is born.</p>
        <p>The digital compact disk player makes its debut in American retail stores.</p>
        <p>April: Chicago elects its first black mayor, Harold Washington.</p>
        <p>May: In an 8-to-1 ruling, the Supreme Court decides that the Administration policy of granting tax exemptions to private schools that practice racial discrimination is illegal.</p>
        <p>June: In a smooth flight of the shuttle Challenger, Sally Ride becomes the first American woman in space.</p>
        <p>July: Economic recovery is gathering steam, with jumps in the gross national product and unemployment falling to under 10 percent.</p>
        <p>August: Benigno S. Aquino Jr., an archrival of Ferdinand E. Marcos, returns to the Philippines and is shot to death as he leaves the plane.</p>
        <p>September: Korean Air Lines Flight 007 is shot down by a Soviet fighter after it strays into Soviet air space; all 269 people on board are lost.</p>
        <p>October: Secretary of the Interior James G. Watt, who fought to open Federal lands to private drilling and other exploitation, quits in an uproar after he is heard describing members of a coal-leasing commission this way: ''I have a black, I have a woman, two Jews and a cripple.''</p>
        <p>Nancy Reagan, who is fighting an image as a maven of fashion and wealth, unveils a slogan for her anti-drug campaign: ''Just say no.''</p>
        <p>A suicide terrorist in a truck full of explosives blows up the U.S. barracks in Beirut, killing 241 Americans, most of them marines on a peace-keeping mission.</p>
        <p>The U.S. invades the Caribbean island of Grenada after a power struggle in the Marxist leadership turns bloody and, the U.S. says, threatens the lives of American medical students.</p>
        <p>November: ABC airs ''The Day After,'' a dramatization of a nuclear holocaust; afterward, Secretary of State George P. Shultz tells viewers that the movie does not represent the future ''at all.''</p>
        <p>Stores are running out of Cabbage Patch dolls, the latest rage in toys.</p>
        <p>December: A year and a half after its military rulers were disgraced in the Falkland war, Argentina returns to democracy with the swearing in of an elected civilian, Raul Alfonsin, as President. The move from military dictatorship to democracy sweeps South America.</p>
        <p>In a new twist on Japan's penetration of the U.S. auto market, Washington decides that General Motors and Toyota can jointly build Japanese-designed cars at a California plant without violating antitrust laws.  1984  Yuppies and Bernhard Goetz become news; bad foreign news includes Ethiopia and Bhopal.</p>
        <p>January: In response to a court order, A. T. &amp; T. is broken up into seven regional companies.</p>
        <p>February: Yuri Andropov dies after only 15 months in power; Konstantin U. Chernenko, a doddering Brezhnev loyalist, takes over.</p>
        <p>March: The word ''yuppie'' becomes part of public discourse, often used to describe the young, upwardly mobile supporters of Gary Hart, a Democratic Presidential candidate.</p>
        <p>April: Dr. Robert Gallo of the National Cancer Institute announces that his team has shown a new virus to be the cause of AIDS. Outraged French researchers say they had previously discovered the virus and linked it to AIDS. Later the two groups agree to share credit.</p>
        <p>May: The Government rescues the nation's eighth largest bank, Continental Illinois, a victim of bad loans.</p>
        <p>In Salvadoran presidential elections, Mr. Duarte beats Roberto D'Aubuisson, an ultra-rightist linked to death squads.</p>
        <p>June: Bruce Springsteen's ''Born in the U.S.A.'' hits the Top Ten, and politicians steal its best lines.</p>
        <p>September: NBC trounces the competition with the premieres of two shows. ''Miami Vice'' makes network television seem avant-garde, and ''The Cosby Show'' becomes a fixture.</p>
        <p>October: Doctors transplant the heart of a baboon into a 12-day-old infant known as Baby Fae. She dies 20 days later.  Prime Minister Indira Gandhi of India is murdered by two bodyguards, both Sikhs. More than a thousand people, mostly Sikhs, are killed in the ensuing sectarian violence. Her son, Rajiv, is elected two months later.</p>
        <p>November: President Reagan and Vice President Bush win in a landslide over Walter Mondale and Geraldine Ferraro, the first woman nominated for vice president on a major-party ticket.</p>
        <p>A heart-rending BBC news clip on the Ethiopian famine airs on NBC, finally focusing American attention on the vast tragedy.</p>
        <p>December: Bell Laboratories says it has perfected a one-megabit chip, which can store an unprecedented amount of information on a tiny piece of silicon.</p>
        <p>December: Toxic fumes from a Union Carbide insecticide plant kill more than 3,000 people in Bhopal, India.</p>
        <p>Britain and China sign an agreement transferring the colony of Hong Kong to Chinese sovereignty in 1997.</p>
        <p>Madonna begins her ascent to pop culture's pinnacle when ''Like a Virgin'' zooms to No. 1 on the charts.</p>
        <p>U.S. leaves Unesco, calling the United Nations agency wasteful and anti-democratic.</p>
        <p>In a case that stirs debate on crime and civil liberties, Bernhard H. Goetz, who is white, shoots and wounds four teen-age boys - all black - who he says were trying to rob him on a New York subway. Mr. Goetz later serves eight months on a gun charge.  1985  The year the Soviet Union gets a new leader, an agriculture expert named Mikhail Gorbachev.</p>
        <p>January: In his second Inaugural Address, Mr. Reagan says the nation is ''poised for greatness.''</p>
        <p>February: Two Senators reveal that the Navy paid $640 each for toilet seats. An investigation of defense contracting uncovers widespread fraud.</p>
        <p>March: Mr. Reagan, in a bid to win military aid for the Nicaragua contras, calls them the ''moral equals of our Founding Fathers.'' A few months later, Congress bars use of American aid for arms and ammunition, setting the stage for White House efforts to supply the contras in secret.</p>
        <p>British scientists report a giant ''hole'' opening in the ozone layer over Antarctica each spring. The thinning of protective ozone is later linked to chlorofluorocarbons and other products.</p>
        <p>Capital Cities Communications buys ABC -the first takeover of a television network. In December General Electric acquires RCA Corporation, owner of NBC, and in 1986 Laurence A. Tisch takes over CBS, which fought off a bid by Ted Turner.</p>
        <p>After the death of Mr. Chernenko, Mikhail S. Gorbachev, a 54-year-old agricultural specialist with no experience in foreign affairs, becomes the Soviet leader. He promises to follow in the path of his predecessors.</p>
        <p>April: Coca-Cola says it is replacing its 99-year-old formula for Coke, the world's best-selling soft drink, with a new one. But the public protest is so great that the company brings back the ''old'' Coke as ''Coke Classic.''</p>
        <p>May: In West Germany, Mr. Reagan visits the Berlin wall, a concentration camp and, to a chorus of dismay at home, a cemetery at Bitburg where 49 Waffen SS officers are buried.</p>
        <p>June: Mr. Gorbachev indirectly criticizes his predecessors and calls for sweeping economic changes.</p>
        <p>Shiite Muslim extremists hijack a T.W.A. airliner. A U.S. Navy diver is killed in the 17-day standoff.</p>
        <p>Karen Ann Quinlan, who has been at the center of the ''right to die'' debate, dies in New Jersey. Courts had allowed removal of the comatose woman's respirator in 1976, but she lived nine more years.</p>
        <p>July: Mr. Reagan undergoes surgery for colon cancer. His doctors say his recovery is ''spectacular.''</p>
        <p>A marathon rock concert, Live Aid, raises $70 million for starving Africans.</p>
        <p>Summer: Depressed farm prices and high debt focus attention on the plight of the American small farmer. Many farmers are forced to give up their farms in the mid-1980's.</p>
        <p>September: Pete Rose passes Ty Cobb's 4,191 career hits.</p>
        <p>A quake measuring 7.8 on the Richter scale causes devastation in and around Mexico City. More than 5,000 people die.</p>
        <p>October: Palestinian terrorists seize an Italian cruise ship, the Achille Lauro, in the eastern Mediterranean, and kill an American, Leon Klinghoffer.</p>
        <p>Rock Hudson, 59, dies of AIDS, forcing the new disease into public consciousness.</p>
        <p>November: A volcano eruption in Colombia kills 25,000 people.</p>
        <p>In the largest civil judgment ever, Texaco is told to pay $10.53 billion in damages to the Pennzoil Company. Pennzoil had charged that Texaco induced the Getty Oil Company to back out of a deal to merge with Pennzoil and accept Texaco's offer of a higher price.  1986  Americans witness disaster (the space shuttle) and the birth of two interesting scandals.</p>
        <p>January: Scientists at I.B.M. laboratories in Zurich discover a material that is superconducting, able to carry electricity without resistance, at temperatures much higher than ever before. Their discovery, quietly published in a European journal, sets off furious international competition to improve on the new materials and grandiose dreams of levitating trains and cheap energy, but commercial applications remain elusive.</p>
        <p>Martin Luther King Day is observed for the first time.</p>
        <p>The shuttle Challenger explodes, killing all seven aboard, including Christa McAuliffe, a teacher. The space program comes to a halt.</p>
        <p>February: Jean-Claude Duvalier of Haiti flees into exile, ending his family's 28-year dictatorship. Violence blocks steps toward democracy.</p>
        <p>In the Philippines, President Marcos is forced into exile after he tries to steal the election from Corazon C. Aquino. Riding the crest of ''people power,'' she becomes President.</p>
        <p>April: The U.S. bombs Libya after President Reagan blames Col. Muammar el-Qaddafi for an attack on American soldiers in West Berlin.</p>
        <p>Tears flow when Vladimir Horowitz performs in the Soviet Union, which he left in 1925. Under Mr. Gorbachev's glasnost, Soviet intellectual life has begun to flower.</p>
        <p>A reactor at the Chernobyl nuclear plant in the Soviet Ukraine explodes, spreading a cloud of radioactive debris. The Soviets do not acknowledge the disaster until after high radiation is reported in Scandinavia.</p>
        <p>June: Len Bias, a top college basketball player, dies of a cocaine overdose.</p>
        <p>July: Oil prices bottom out at $7.20 a barrel.</p>
        <p>August: Lethal gas erupts from a volcanic lake in Cameroon, killing some 1,500 people.</p>
        <p>A surrogate mother, Mary Beth Whitehead, goes to court in an unsuccessful attempt to keep the baby girl - known as Baby M - whom she agreed to carry to term for $10,000. The father, William Stern, and his wife later retain custody.</p>
        <p>September: The Senate confirms William H. Rehnquist as Chief Justice and Antonin Scalia as an associate justice of the Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>Congress overrides Mr. Reagan's veto of sanctions against South Africa. The United States and Europe act after Pretoria declares a state of emergency because of unrest.</p>
        <p>Mergers and economic troubles disrupt the airline industry, which is still adjusting to the new age of deregulation. Frank Lorenzo of Texas Air announces a deal to acquire People Express.</p>
        <p>Congress overhauls the tax system, changing brackets and eliminating many deductions.</p>
        <p>October: The rapid spread of crack prompts Congress to pass new anti-drug legislation.</p>
        <p>At a summit meeting in Iceland, Mr. Reagan and Mr. Gorbachev come startlingly close to agreeing on deep limits in nuclear arsenals.</p>
        <p>November: A Beirut magazine reports that the U.S. sent spare parts and ammunition to Iran. A subsequent investigation reveals that other arms sales were made to Iran and the profits were diverted to the Nicaraguan contras, and the Iran-contra scandal is born.</p>
        <p>Portending the end of a free-wheeling era in finance, the insider trading scandal climaxes with news that Ivan Boesky agreed to pay $100 million and plead guilty to a criminal count, and aided prosecutors by taping his conversations. Other indictments follow, including that of Michael R. Milken, the junk bond king at Drexel Burnham Lambert, who is awaiting trial.</p>
        <p>December: Mr. Gorbachev calls Andrei Sakharov to tell him he is free to leave Gorky, where he has been in internal exile.  1987  The stock market crash, and Robert H. Bork's Supreme Court nomination; the intifada begins.</p>
        <p>January: The nation's first trillion-dollar budget is proposed by President Reagan.</p>
        <p>February: Signaling a worsening debt problem, Brazil, the third world's largest debtor nation, suspends interest payments on loans from foreign banks.</p>
        <p>April: In a field near Monterey, Calif., scientists spray a strawberry patch with bacteria to prevent frost, the first experimental release of genetically altered bacteria in the United States.</p>
        <p>June: Margaret Thatcher is re-elected, becoming the first British Prime Minister in the 20th century to win three consecutive terms.</p>
        <p>July: Three Congressmen bash a Toshiba radio with sledgehammers on Capitol Hill after revelations that Toshiba sold sensitive technology to the Soviets.</p>
        <p>Millions watch the testimony of Lieut. Col. Oliver L. North during the Congressional inquiry into the Iran-contra affair. He is later convicted of destroying Government documents among other charges, He is sentenced to community service and fined.</p>
        <p>August: Five Central American countries sign an accord intended to resolve the region's conflicts. Oscar Arias Sanchez of Costa Rica will win the Nobel Peace Prize for his efforts.</p>
        <p>September: In a victory for the global environment, many nations agree in Montreal to protect the ozone layer by phasing out chlorofluorcarbons and other chemicals.</p>
        <p>October: The stock market crashes. The 22.6 percent plunge in the Dow Jones Industrial Average is the largest one-day decline since 1914.</p>
        <p>The Senate rejects Mr. Reagan's nomination of Robert H. Bork to the Supreme Court; critics say he is insensitive to individual rights and liberties and supporters see an unfair campaign against him. A second nominee, Douglas Ginsburg, will withdraw after acknowledging that he smoked marijuana. A third nominee, Anthony M. Kennedy, will be confirmed.</p>
        <p>December: At the White House, President Reagan and Mr. Gorbachev sign a treaty to eliminate the superpowers' medium-range intermediate nuclear forces.</p>
        <p>Rioting breaks out in the Israeli occupied territory of Gaza after a truck driven by an Israeli kills four people near a Palestinian refugee camp. Unrest spreads to the West Bank. The intifada - or uprising - begins.  1988  Politics takes up the year, and there is a time when it doesn't look good for George Bush.</p>
        <p>February: Federal grand juries in Miami and Tampa indict Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega, charging that he protected and assisted the Medellin drug cartel. The United States tries to oust him with economic and military pressures.</p>
        <p>March: Jesse Jackson's upset victory in the Michigan Democratic caucuses is the first triumph by a black Presidential candidate in a big state, establishing him as a serious contender for the nomination.</p>
        <p>April: Pakistan and Afghanistan sign agreements in Geneva calling for the withdrawal of Soviet troops.</p>
        <p>As safety in the sky and aging aircraft fleets become concerns, a gaping hole opens in the fuselage of a 19-year-old Aloha Airlines Boeing 737 over Hawaii, sweeping a stewardess to her death.</p>
        <p>May: On the last day illegal aliens can apply for amnesty under a new immigration law, more than 100,000 people rush to submit applications, which could lead to legal status and eventual citizenship. In all, nearly 1.4 million illegal aliens seek amnesty.</p>
        <p>June: Congress approves legislation aimed at protecting the disabled and the elderly against catastrophic health costs. A year later the program is repealed after an outcry from elderly people who objected to paying the surcharge.</p>
        <p>George Steinbrenner fires Billy Martin, ending Mr. Martin's fifth term as Yankee manager.</p>
        <p>July: A missile fired by a U.S. Navy cruiser in the Persian Gulf destroys an Iranian airliner, killing 290 people. Navy crewmen say they thought the plane was an Iranian jet fighter.</p>
        <p>Iran and Iraq agree to a cease-fire in the eight-year war.</p>
        <p>After his nomination as the Democratic Presidential candidate, polls show Gov. Michael S. Dukakis of Massachusetts with a double-digit lead over Vice President Bush, who awaits the Republican nomination in August.</p>
        <p>August: In Pakistan, President Mohammad Zia ul-Haq and the United States Ambassador are killed in a plane crash, apparently an act of sabotage. Three months later Benazir Bhutto, Zia's sworn enemy, becomes president.</p>
        <p>October: RJR Nabisco is bought by Kohlberg, Kravis, Roberts &amp; Company. At a price of $24.9 billion, it is the largest leveraged buyout ever.</p>
        <p>November: After the campaign in which he pledges not to raise taxes - ''Read my lips'' -George Bush is elected the 41st President, with 56 percent of the popular vote.</p>
        <p>December: An earthquake measuring 6.9 on the Richter scale devastates Soviet Armenia, killing an estimated 25,000 people.</p>
        <p>Pan Am Flight 103 explodes over Lockerbie, Scotland, killing 270 people. Investigators say a bomb was in the luggage compartment.  1989  The wall falls and freedom spreads at a dizzying pace, despite a setback in China.</p>
        <p>January: George Bush is sworn in as the 41st President. In his Inaugural Address, he calls for ''a new engagement in the lives of others.''</p>
        <p>February: Gen. Alfredo Stroessner, Paraguay's leader since 1954, is ousted and sent into exile.</p>
        <p>A 20-year-old man is the last person to be shot trying to escape across the Berlin wall. The last Soviet troops leave Afghanistan.  Ayatollah Khomeini denounces the novel ''Satanic Verses'' as blasphemy and calls for the execution of the author, Salman Rushdie.</p>
        <p>March: Time Inc. and Warner Communications announce a merger that creates the world's largest media conglomerate, with interests in books, magazines, television, cable and movies.</p>
        <p>For the first time in 70 years, the Soviet people are given a choice of competing candidates. The winners make up part of the new Congress.</p>
        <p>The tanker Exxon Valdez strikes a reef in Prince William Sound in Alaska, resulting in one of the worst oil spills in history.</p>
        <p>April: Thousands of Chinese students mourn the death of Hu Yaobang, a deposed reformist leader. The protests grow, and students camp out in Tiananmen Square in Beijing.</p>
        <p>After a year of unrest, the Polish Government legalizes Solidarity and sets elections. Lech Walesa and General Jaruzelski shake hands.</p>
        <p>May: General Noriega engineers a fraudulent election, and his forces beat up oppositionists.</p>
        <p>In a reflection of Washington's new concern over Congressional ethics, House Speaker Jim Wright announces he is resigning after a long-running dispute over a lucrative book deal.</p>
        <p>June: The Chinese military, on orders from Deng, launches a savage assault on the demonstrators in Tiananmen Square, killing an unknown number and crushing dissent.</p>
        <p>Ayatollah Khomeini dies; his funeral turns into pandemonium as frenzied mourners try to kiss his corpse.</p>
        <p>Poland's first free election since the Communists took over brings overwhelming victory for Solidarity. In August, Tadeusz Mazowiecki, a Walesa associate, will become Prime Minister in a Government with the Communists. In Hungary, Imre Nagy, the leader of the 1956 uprising, is given a hero's reburial.</p>
        <p>Testimony in Congress paints a lurid picture of influence-peddling and political favoritism in the Department Housing and Urban Development.</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court decides flag burning is protected by the First Amendment, causing a political uproar.</p>
        <p>July: By 5 to 4, the Supreme Court rules that states can put new restraints on a woman's right to have an abortion, though it does not overturn Roe v. Wade.</p>
        <p>August: After gunmen kill a popular politician, Colombia declares war on drug traffickers. The next month, Mr. Bush declares war on drugs in a strategy that emphasizes law enforcement.</p>
        <p>Congress passes a 10-year $166 billion package to rescue foundering savings and loans.</p>
        <p>President P. W. Botha of South Africa is pushed aside, and F. W. de Klerk succeeds him. Mr. de Klerk promises change but opponents of apartheid press him to move faster.</p>
        <p>Pete Rose, the Cincinnati Reds coach, is banned from baseball after a 225-page report chronicles his gambling activities.</p>
        <p>September: Vietnam says its forces have left Cambodia, 10 years after occupying the country. The withdrawal creates fears that civil war will explode and that the dreaded Khmer Rouge may fight their way to power.</p>
        <p>Hungary opens its border with Austria to allow the exit of East Germans gathered at the West German Embassy in Budapest.</p>
        <p>Hurricane Hugo devastates part of the Caribbean and the Carolinas.</p>
        <p>The Sony Corporation, which had acquired CBS Records in 1988, buys Columbia Pictures.</p>
        <p>October: As a World Series game is about to begin, San Francisco suffers an earthquake measuring 7.1 on the Richter scale. Sixty-seven people die, many of them in the collapse of a freeway.</p>
        <p>As East Germany celebrates its 40th anniversary, huge protests break out and thousands of refugees flood routes to the West. By the end of the month, Erich Honecker is out as party chief.</p>
        <p>The Hungarian Communist Party changes its name and Parliament decides to allow a multiparty system, with elections in 1990.</p>
        <p>The Rockefeller Group, owner of Rockefeller Center, Radio City Music Hall and other mid-Manhattan office buildings, sells control of the company to the Mitsubishi Estate Company of Tokyo for $846 million in cash.</p>
        <p>November: After defeating Mayor Edward I. Koch in the primary, David N. Dinkins becomes the first black to be elected mayor of New York.</p>
        <p>East Germany opens the Berlin wall, on which ecstatic Berliners dance and drink champagne. In Czechoslovakia, demonstrations force the Communist Party to cede its absolute power. A vote in Hungary forces revision of the party's schedule for elections, and in Bulgaria a Stalinist leader, Todor Zhivkov, is forced out.</p>
        <p>December: President Aquino of the Philippines survives a coup attempt, thanks in large part to American military assistance.</p>
        <p>Upheaval continues in East Germany, where revelations of corruption at the highest level disgrace Mr. Honecker and force his successor, Egon Krenz, to step down.</p>
        <p>For the first time since 1970, Chileans freely elect a new leader, Patricio Aylwin, and the Pinochet era ends. In the first direct elections for President in Brazil since 1964, Fernando Collor de Mello, a free-market crusader, wins.</p>
        <p>Andrei Sakharov, at 68, dies of a heart attack after a grueling day in the Soviet Congress; Mr. Gorbachev laments the loss of ''a man of conviction and sincerity.''</p>
        <p>After a U.S. serviceman is shot by Panamanian forces, the United States invades Panama, asserting a right to protect citizens and defend the canal. General Noriega flees into hiding and a new President is sworn in on a U.S. base. Chaos consumes the country as thousands of American troops struggle to establish control.</p>
        <p>In Rumania, the last holdout against reform in the East bloc, angry crowds of pro-democracy demonstrators, backed by some army units, force the hard-line leader, Nicolae Ceausescu, to flee Bucharest. Thousands are reported to have been killed in unrest days earlier; fighting continues between rival security forces.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
