<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rain and Fines, but Mostly Rain, Slow Burning of Amazon Forest in Brazil</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="283773"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINES (PENALTIES)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRAZIL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AMAZON RIVER BASIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKE, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru/Amazon Basin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DA153BF934A2575AC0A96F948260" item-length="1342" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rain and Fines, but Mostly Rain, Slow Burning of Amazon Forest in Brazil</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKE, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>MANAUS, Brazil</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Plumes of gray smoke are once again rising over the green sea of Amazonian rain forest surrounding this city. But preliminary survey figures from this year's dry season point to a new trend: a marked drop in burning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Plumes of gray smoke are once again rising over the green sea of Amazonian rain forest surrounding this city. But preliminary survey figures from this year's dry season point to a new trend: a marked drop in burning.</p>
        <p>Plumes of gray smoke are once again rising over the green sea of Amazonian rain forest surrounding this city. But preliminary survey figures from this year's dry season point to a new trend: a marked drop in burning.</p>
        <p>Rain, fines and reversals in public policy are combining to slow deforestation by fire, according to Brazilian and American environmentalists interviewed at a scientific conference here in late August.</p>
        <p>''In 1989, there has been a considerable reduction in burning,'' Alberto Setzer told the gathering. Mr. Setzer directs a three-year-old Brazilian project to monitor Amazon forest fires through photographs taken by a satellite of the National Oceanic Atmospheric Administration. Smaller, but Still Huge</p>
        <p>In June, to the surprise of many Amazon watchers, Mr. Setzer's researchers reported that fires during the 1988 dry season destroyed 37 percent less forest than in 1987. The drop was from 80,000 square miles to 50,000 square miles.</p>
        <p>The downward trend appears to be continuing. During the first half of this year's four-month dry season, the satellite recorded that 59,000 fires destroyed 13,000 square miles of forest.</p>
        <p>Although reduced, this area is still large - the equivalent of New Jersey and Connecticut combined.</p>
        <p>Fires in the Amazon became a worldwide concern last year after studies showed that the burning produces about one billion tons of carbon dioxide annually. Many climatologists believe that carbon dioxide building up in the atmosphere will trap the earth's heat, producing the greenhouse effect. Rain, the Great Preserver</p>
        <p>Despite international protests over the fires, rain - not people - appears to be a major factor in preserving the forest. Last year, the Amazon received little rain during the traditional dry season, mid-June through early October.</p>
        <p>This year, preliminary reports indicate that much of the Amazon - a region that covers 1.9 million square miles in Brazil, an area about the size of the United States west of the Mississippi - is undergoing the wettest ''dry season'' in a decade. Generally, a farmer needs five consecutive days without rain before he can burn a stretch of jungle.</p>
        <p>''This is going to be an unusually wet year,'' said Paulo Nogueira Neto, an ecology professor at the University of Sao Paulo.</p>
        <p>In addition, Brazil has made several policy changes that are believed to be slowing the burning. Government Moves to Slow Fires</p>
        <p>This year, Brazil suspended tax incentives that made it artificially profitable for landowners to clear large expanses of jungle for cattle ranches.</p>
        <p>Last year, it adopted a Constitution that did not penalize owners of unproductive land. During a constitutional debate in 1987, landowners' fear of losing title to ''unimproved'' lands is believed to have contributed to a record level of burning - 80,000 square miles.</p>
        <p>''Every indication is that the burning is going down, because of weather, enforcement and the lack of new project incentives,'' said Thomas E. Lovejoy, assistant secretary for external affairs of the Smithsonian Institution.</p>
        <p>This year, in the face of international pressure, Brazil began a highly publicized campaign to slow the burning.</p>
        <p>Using 5 helicopters and 60 pickup trucks, forestry agents from the Brazilian Institute of Environment and Renewable Natural Resources have handed out $10 million in fines in the last month to landowners who burn forest lots without a permit from the institute.</p>
        <p>''I visited a farm 60 miles from here yesterday where they wanted to burn,'' said Mr. Nogueira, a pioneer in Brazil's environmental movement. ''The farm workers were talking among themselves about whether the helicopter would come.'' Forestry Agent Slain</p>
        <p>A measure of the institute's success is the growing resistance to those who levy the fines. A hail of bullets greeted a helicopter sent in August to investigate a report of an illegal forest fire in Maraba, in Para state. Elsewhere in the state, which has had 13,500 fires this summer, hired gunmen killed a forestry agent.</p>
        <p>After an attempted killing last May, the institute's representative in Acre state, Paulo Beninca de Sales, began leaving his house only under police guard. The president of the agency, Fernando Cesar Mesquita, has started to receive death threats.</p>
        <p>''In Rondonia, there are rumors among the settlers that the fines are now so heavy that they will have to sell their land to pay the fines,'' said Philip M. Fearnside, an American ecologist who works here at the National Institute for Research in the Amazon.</p>
        <p>Brazil's fire-prevention campaign was strengthened this summer by an $8 million low-interest loan from the World Bank, which was matched by an appropriation from Brazil's Congress. The money was used to rent helicopters, buy pickup trucks and pay salaries for forestry agents. Posters Give Warning</p>
        <p>Mr. Mesquita said 500,000 posters and 500,000 pamphlets were distributed throughout the Amazon this year, warning the region's 15 million residents that fire permits must be obtained from the newly created Environment Institute.</p>
        <p>''Any requests to clear more than 200 hectares never get farther than my desk drawer,'' Mr. Mesquita said. The cutoff point he referred to is equal to just under 500 acres.</p>
        <p>''This year, you are going to have a lot fewer fires than last year,'' Mr. Mesquita said, running his finger down a report of ranchers and farmers fined for burning without a permit.</p>
        <p>To help Mr. Mesquita's forestry agents, the National Institute of Space Research in Sao Paulo state sends daily telexes to all Amazonian states. The telexes list the locations of all known fires detected by satellite.</p>
        <p>''We can send the information within two hours,'' said Mr. Setzer, who gets his photographs from a satellite of the National Oceanic Atmospheric Administration. ''However, there is not always the manpower to follow up. Sometimes a telex to one state can be five meters long.'' Incentives Are Opposed</p>
        <p>Rather than depending on police action or on the vagaries of rainfall, many environmentalists here argue that forest burning can best be reduced by withdrawing economic incentives. They say that tax incentives should be ended - not just suspended - for farms, cattle ranches, sawmills and pig-iron projects, that higher taxes should be imposed on land sales to cool land speculation, and that road building should be restricted to areas with soils suitable for support agriculture.</p>
        <p>''They have to go the whole way from suspending incentives for new projects to ending existing incentives,'' said Mr. Lovejoy, an ecologist with 20 years' experience in the Amazon. ''Around Manaus this week, I have seen at least three fires where ranchers were burning second growth.'' He said they were marginal operations, which would not be viable without the tax incentives.</p>
        <p>The environmental meeting here received an unexpected visitor on Aug. 28, its opening day - Amazonino Mendes, Governor of the state of Amazonas.</p>
        <p>In June, the Governor angered environmentalists when he announced that he would distribute 4,000 free power saws to local farmers to win support in elections next year. Reacting to an earlier giveaway, some Brazilian legislators tried unsucessfully to give chain saws the same legal status as firearms. In Brazil, guns require ownership permits. Nature Reserves Planned</p>
        <p>Making peace with the environmentalists, Mr. Mendes announced plans to convert about 6 percent of Amazonas - 40,000 square miles - into nature reserves for tourism and scientific research. Of seven reserves planned, one has been approved by the state legislature and two others are to be considered within a month, he said.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, many Brazilian Government officials remain sensitive over international concern about the Amazon.</p>
        <p>Early in August, Air Force helicopters intercepted a French research balloon that was hovering over the jungle near here. On landing, the nine French researchers, who had entered Brazil on tourist visas, were ordered to pack up their balloon and leave the country.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
