<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="297303"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DC133EF930A35752C1A96F948260" item-length="895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-11  A Brazilian television star has entered the Presidential election, only two weeks away, and a poll shows that he could win. Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-11  A Brazilian television star has entered the Presidential election, only two weeks away, and a poll shows that he could win. Page A1</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-11  A Brazilian television star has entered the Presidential election, only two weeks away, and a poll shows that he could win. Page A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: Nicaragua's move to break the cease-fire violated peace accords, but the United States has itself resisted vital steps required by those accords. A8</p>
        <p>Hondurans reject Nicaragua call for talks on rebels A8</p>
        <p>Salvadoran rebels pulled out of talks with the Government and accused it of the bombing of a labor federation headquarters in which at least nine people were killed. A7</p>
        <p>Ford will buy Jaguar for $2.38 billion, it announced. The deal reflects the continuing consolidation of the world auto industry. D1</p>
        <p>Israel indicated it may be amenable to the American plan for Israeli-Palestinian discussions after Secretary Baker offered some minor modifications. A3</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Lebanon's Speaker of Parliament called on lawmakers to ratify a peace agreement on Saturday, but the Christian army commander threatened to take ''decisive measures'' to block the session. A3</p>
        <p>A speech critical of Soviet conduct in regional conflicts was given by a Defense official. It was much more pointed than recent speeches by Secretary Baker. A10</p>
        <p>An illegal strike by Soviet miners has presented authorities with their most serious test of a new law restricting labor walkouts. A11</p>
        <p>More East Germans seek passage through Prague A10</p>
        <p>Turkey and its Kurds still have a fragile relationship, even as the country has begun to acknowledge a distinct Kurdish identity. A6</p>
        <p>A report that rebels entered Namibia in advance of elections next week was played down by South Africa. A5</p>
        <p>Athens journal: Widow proudly picks up a banner A4</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A12-23, D19  Plans for a capital gains tax cut this year were abandoned by Senate Republicans in an important setback for President Bush. A1</p>
        <p>A $305 billion military spending bill has been agreed to in Congress, lawmakers said. It reduces spending for ''Star Wars'' for the first time. A1</p>
        <p>A special prosecutor was requested by Democrats to investigate charges of political favoritism and perjury against former Housing Secretary Pierce. A12</p>
        <p>The elderly's influence on Congress would be diminished under a proposal by an powerful lawmaker. A12</p>
        <p>Washington at Work: Security adviser redefines the role A16</p>
        <p>For collectors of U.S. data, a close call last month D1</p>
        <p>Acid rain measure would share cost A21</p>
        <p>The largest study measuring fitness suggests that even modest amounts of exercise can substantially reduce the chances of dying from heart disease, cancer or other causes. A1</p>
        <p>Limits on computer stock trades were announced by the New York Stock Exchange in an effort to reduce wild price swings that have unsettled the financial markets in recent weeks. A1</p>
        <p>Leveraged buyout leader shifts attention D1</p>
        <p>L. Douglas Wilder would become the nation's first black elected governor if he wins the Virginia contest, but he tends to de-emphasize race and focus on other issues. A1</p>
        <p>A child-molesting trial, the nation's longest-running criminal proceeding ever, went to the jury in Los Angeles after two and half years. A18</p>
        <p>Gay man wins bias case A17</p>
        <p>Metallurgical mystery in plane crash A13</p>
        <p>Head of prison is suspended in aftermath of riot A23</p>
        <p>Watsonville journal: A tent city created by quake A12</p>
        <p>Ship aground in Florida coral could cause wider damage A18</p>
        <p>REGIONAL B1-8, B22  Rudolph Giuliani's public image has softened in recent weeks. While he was once perceived as hard-nosed and cold, he now seems more relaxed. A1</p>
        <p>Mayoral candidates act to widen their appeal B3</p>
        <p>Donations inundate Dinkins campaign B3</p>
        <p>The fate of Joseph Doherty, who was convicted of murder in Northern Ireland and is now in a Manhattan jail, has become an issue in the mayoral race. B5</p>
        <p>The Upper West Side of Manhattan, traditionally a bastion of activism, has undergone many changes in attitudes and concerns. Those changes may be reflected by the candidate residents support for mayor. B1</p>
        <p>Koch weighs speaking and ad offers B3</p>
        <p>A Yonkers City Council election is widely seen as a referendum on the housing desegregation plan that has dominated local politics in recent years. B1</p>
        <p>Two moderates battle for top Westchester post B4</p>
        <p>State agency budget cuts of 2 percent were ordered by the Cuomo administration, saying it had overestimated tax revenue and faced a potential deficit of almost $300 million. B1</p>
        <p>A rule restricting family planners in New York State from receiving Federal funds if they provide abortion information was upheld. B1</p>
        <p>Strike begins to squeeze Nynex D1</p>
        <p>''Remarkable recovery'' reported for jogger in attack B3</p>
        <p>Prisoner escapes and rapes woman, police say B3</p>
        <p>Three are indicted over money transfers D1</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
