<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After a Cliffhanger Countdown, Shuttle Launches a Venus Probe</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19890506T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="247117"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE SHUTTLE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATLANTIS (SPACE SHUTTLE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAGELLAN VENUS RADAR MAPPER (SPACECRAFT)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALKER, DAVID M (CAPT)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRABE, RONALD J (COL)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLEAVE, MARY L (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">THAGARD, NORMAN E (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEE, MARK C (MAJ)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DE103CF936A35756C0A96F948260" item-length="1103" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After a Cliffhanger Countdown, Shuttle Launches a Venus Probe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla., May 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: After waiting nearly an hour for the clouds to part, the astronauts of the space shuttle Atlantis rocketed into orbit today and sent a radar-mapping spacecraft on a 15-month, 795-million-mile journey to Venus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: After waiting nearly an hour for the clouds to part, the astronauts of the space shuttle Atlantis rocketed into orbit today and sent a radar-mapping spacecraft on a 15-month, 795-million-mile journey to Venus.</p>
        <p>After waiting nearly an hour for the clouds to part, the astronauts of the space shuttle Atlantis rocketed into orbit today and sent a radar-mapping spacecraft on a 15-month, 795-million-mile journey to Venus.</p>
        <p>The launching occurred at 2:47 P.M., with just five minutes to spare before Earth and Venus would have moved out of alignment and the mission would have had to be postponed again. The liftoff had been delayed six days by a faulty fuel pump that stopped the initial countdown last Friday.</p>
        <p>Once the Atlantis was safely in orbit, the astronauts opened the cargo bay doors and deployed the 7,700-pound Magellan spacecraft. An hour later, as the shuttle began its sixth orbit, a 32,500-pound solid-fuel rocket attached to Magellan fired, first one stage and then another, lifting the unmanned spacecraft on a trajectory to Venus at an initial velocity of more than 24,000 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>The Magellan marks the first American planetary expedition in 11 years. The craft's radar system was designed to penetrate the cloud-veiled planet and produce photograph-like images of its mysterious surface.</p>
        <p>The launching of the Atlantis was the 29th in the space shuttle program and the fourth since the resumption of operations last fall after the Challenger accident in January 1986. The mission is scheduled to last four days, with a landing Monday at Edwards Air Force Base in California.</p>
        <p>The five astronauts are Capt. David M. Walker of the Navy; Col. Ronald J. Grabe of the Air Force; Dr. Mary L. Cleave, an engineer; Dr. Norman E. Thagard, a physician, and Maj. Mark C. Lee of the Air Force. All crew members, except Major Lee, are veterans of previous shuttle flights.</p>
        <p>They had to wait patiently as the original launching time, 1:48, passed and low-hanging clouds continued to cover the Kennedy Space Center. The main concern was visibility at the runway, where the shuttle might have to land in case of an emergency several minutes after liftoff.</p>
        <p>Finally, winds herded the clouds south. The countdown was resumed with five minutes to go before the eventual launching. When the shuttle engines ignited, in a rush of orange flame, the Atlantis rose into blue sky with only a few patches of high, fluffy clouds.</p>
        <p>Describing what he called the countdown ''cliffhanger,'' Robert B. Sieck, the launching director, said: ''I'm an optimist when it comes to the weather. It does change if you just wait long enough.''</p>
        <p>Otherwise, Mr. Sieck said at a news conference, the countdown was virtually trouble-free. The replacement pump in the shuttle fuel system performed flawlessly.</p>
        <p>Moments after the Atlantis lifted off, Mr. Sieck thanked launching controllers in the firing room, saying, ''The tougher they are, the more rewarding they are.'' One Minor Failure</p>
        <p>The only reported malfunction in the ascent was the failure of one of the 44 steering thrusters on the Atlantis. These are fired to make minor course corrections and orient the shuttle in orbit. Space officials said there were sufficient backup thrusters for all planned operations.</p>
        <p>It had been an even longer wait for scientists in charge of the Magellan mission, which was started in 1981, canceled once and grounded by the Challenger disaster.</p>
        <p>In checking the Magellan's control systems two weeks ago, engineers detected and corrected one potentially catastrophic problem. A design flaw was found in the software for the spacecraft's computer. If the craft were to lose its proper orientation to the Sun and Earth, the flaw could have prevented the computer from issuing commands for the Magellan to regain its bearings. The result could have been the loss of the spacecraft, as it failed to get enough solar energy to run its electronics and thus could no longer keep its antenna pointed to Earth. A 'Patch' to Overcome Flaw</p>
        <p>Project officials said engineers devised a ''patch,'' a substitute set of computer instructions, to override the design flaw.</p>
        <p>John H. Gerpheide, the Magellan project manager at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena, Calif., said: ''We're convinced we've got a good solution to the problem. The fix has been tested and thoroughly reviewed. We don't have any concern at all.'' Errors in flight computer instructions were said to have caused the failure of Phobos 1, an unmanned Soviet spacecraft, as it was headed for Mars last September. The spacecraft tumbled out of control. Communications with Earth were disrupted. And the craft, unable to keep its solar panels pointed to the Sun, ran out of electricity.</p>
        <p>The companion craft, Phobos 2, made it to an orbit of Mars and then failed as it was maneuvering to drop scientific instruments on the tiny Martian moon Phobos. Soviet scientists who were here to view the launching of the Atlantis said the cause of the Phobos 2 loss was still unclear. Steps to Reduce Risks</p>
        <p>Mr. Gerpheide said the Magellan's control system incorporated many measures to reduce the risks of the kinds of problems that afflicted the Soviet mission.</p>
        <p>If all goes well, Magellan should reach Venus in August 1990 and swing into an orbit of the planet. The spacecraft is to complete a revolution of Venus once every 3 hours 9 minutes, with the altitudes of the orbit ranging from as far out as 5,000 miles and as close to the surface as 155 miles.</p>
        <p>The radar mapping is to be done for a 37-minute period on each orbit, when the Magellan is closest to the planet. The primary mission will last 243 Earth days - a single Venusian day -and include photograph-like radar images from 1,852 mapping swaths. From these images, cartographers expect to produce a map of at least 90 percent of the Venus surface and show any features that are larger than a football field. Previous Images of Planet</p>
        <p>Previous American and Soviet spacecraft have used radar to penetrate the hot carbon dioxide clouds and produce coarse images of some Venusian features, but nothing smaller than continent-size highlands and rolling plains.</p>
        <p>''It was like Columbus coming back and saying we know there's land there, but we still don't know anything about it,'' said James W. Head 3d, a professor of planetary geology at Brown University who is a member of the Magellan science team.</p>
        <p>Scientists hope the Magellan survey will determine whether Venus ever had oceans of water and whether it has active volcanoes. They also hope to determine whether it has crustal plates that move, like those that cause continental drift on Earth. But the overriding objective is to learn why Venus and Earth, the closest of planetary neighbors and roughly the same size, evolved into such extremely different worlds.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 6, 1989, Saturday, Late City Final Edition</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about the space shuttle misstated the reason its launching had to occur by 2:52 P.M. or be postponed. The concern was that emergency landing fields in Spain and Morocco would grow dark, not that Earth and Venus would move out of proper alignment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 6, 1989, Saturday, Late City Final Edition</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about the space shuttle misstated the reason its launching had to occur by 2:52 P.M. or be postponed. The concern was that emergency landing fields in Spain and Morocco would grow dark, not that Earth and Venus would move out of proper alignment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
