<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Experts See Nuclear Energy as Cure for Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="285933"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6DC103AF936A1575AC0A96F948260" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Experts See Nuclear Energy as Cure for Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>MONTREAL, Sept. 21-</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The cure for the greenhouse effect, the warming of the atmosphere that is believed to be caused by the burning of fossil fuels, is a huge shift to nuclear-generated power, speaker after speaker told delegates at a World Energy Conference meeting this week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The cure for the greenhouse effect, the warming of the atmosphere that is believed to be caused by the burning of fossil fuels, is a huge shift to nuclear-generated power, speaker after speaker told delegates at a World Energy Conference meeting this week.</p>
        <p>The cure for the greenhouse effect, the warming of the atmosphere that is believed to be caused by the burning of fossil fuels, is a huge shift to nuclear-generated power, speaker after speaker told delegates at a World Energy Conference meeting this week.</p>
        <p>But a few speakers predicted that more efficient electrical and electronic consumer products would make a big shift to nuclear power unnecessary, while others criticized the cost of reactor-generated electricity.</p>
        <p>For the most part, however, the consensus at the weeklong 14th congress of the London-based organization, which has members in 80 countries, was that greater reliance on nuclear power is needed. Essential for Third World</p>
        <p>Bong-Suh Lee, South Korea's Minister of Energy and Resources, said nuclear power was the solution to environmental and supply problems and that ''this is especially so for resource-poor developing countries.''</p>
        <p>John Wakeham, Secretary of State for Energy in Britain, said his country was requiring that its Government-owned electricity industry, which is now being sold to the public, generate electricity without burning fossil fuels. ''The developed world may well have to turn increasingly to nuclear energy to protect our environment in the years ahead and make room for more use of fossil energy in countries with less-suitable infrastructure,'' he said.</p>
        <p>W. Henson Moore, the United States Deputy Energy Secretary, said it was essential to resume reactor construction, which has nearly halted in both the United States and Canada and has slowed markedly elsewhere. ''Given some time and concerted effort, we can again make nuclear energy a viable choice,'' Mr. Moore said.</p>
        <p>Lord Marshall of Goring, the chairman of the Central Electricity Generating Board in Britain, said: ''The design of nuclear reactors has now reached an advanced, sophisticated and mature level. For the public at large, the risk is to all intents and purposes zero.''</p>
        <p>But those who opposed nuclear power generally said that rather than replace generators fired by coal, oil and natural-gas with reactors, it would be less expensive to retire the old non-nuclear generators by decreasing the demand for electricity through use of more efficient motors, lights and other electrical and electronic products.</p>
        <p>Some opponents of nuclear power also took issue with its cost.</p>
        <p>''Nuclear power throughout the world's market economies, and even in Communist countries, is dying of an incurable attack of market forces,'' said Amory Lovins, a consultant who specializes in efficiency technologies.</p>
        <p>Wall Street discounts the stock and debt issues of companies with nuclear investments, he said, and investors would remain skeptical ''until promoters bring money in themselves and stop importuning the Treasury to put our money where their mouth is.'' Nuclear plants would not be built in the United States, he said, without insurance concessions and other advantages given by Congress.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lovins and other speakers said third world electricity producers and users were markedly less efficient than those in industrialized countries. Nuclear Slowdown</p>
        <p>A World Energy Conference study estimated that reactors would provide 7 or 8 percent of energy supplies in 2020; six years ago, the group said it would be 12 percent. Currently, about 400 reactors are operating, providing about 4 percent of the world's energy supplies. About 100 more reactors are under construction.</p>
        <p>The construction rate is far short of what would be required to use reactors to halt global warming. Alvin Weinberg, an energy expert at Oak Ridge National Laboratories, calculated that in 100 years, if the world were to institute stringent efficiency measures and cut fuel burning to the level required to stabilize the atmosphere, 5,000 reactors would be needed.</p>
        <p>But he concluded that current designs would not be adequate. He said the chance of a meltdown at a given plant is great enough that if multiplied by 5,000, it would produce an unacceptably high risk.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
