<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Bush Budget Will Stick To Themes From Campaign</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="311767"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG ADDICTION AND ABUSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SAVINGS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CAPITAL GAINS TAX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENBAUM, DAVID E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Savings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Gains Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DC173DF937A15751C1A96F948260" item-length="1210" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Bush Budget Will Stick To Themes From Campaign</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. ROSENBAUM, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENBAUM, DAVID E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Sticking to the themes he developed in his election campaign last year, President Bush will emphasize in his budget message to Congress next month new proposals to encourage personal saving and modest spending increases for drug control, education, science, research and the environment, Administration officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Sticking to the themes he developed in his election campaign last year, President Bush will emphasize in his budget message to Congress next month new proposals to encourage personal saving and modest spending increases for drug control, education, science, research and the environment, Administration officials said.</p>
        <p>Sticking to the themes he developed in his election campaign last year, President Bush will emphasize in his budget message to Congress next month new proposals to encourage personal saving and modest spending increases for drug control, education, science, research and the environment, Administration officials said.</p>
        <p>And in keeping with his campaign pledges, Mr. Bush will propose no broad additional taxes. But he plans to call for raising a small amount of money with new taxes that he calls ''user fees,''</p>
        <p>He also plans to modify slightly his proposal that was blocked by Congress this year to cut the capital gains tax rate and to recommend a new long-term, tax-free savings account.</p>
        <p>The President will assert that the lower capital gains tax and the new savings account are essential aspects of the Government's strategy to increase personal savings that can be used for long-term investment. Budget Message on Jan. 22</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is still tying up loose ends of the budget, which he is to submit to Congress on Jan. 22, and some Cabinet members and agency heads say they still do not know how much they will have to spend in the fiscal year 1991, which begins next Oct. 1. The basic themes of the Bush proposals were gleaned from interviews with White House officials as well as others.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush will stress, they said, that the $6 billion to $8 billion in cuts that he plans to propose for the military need to be used entirely for deficit reduction, not for new domestic spending. He will call for a spending freeze in most domestic programs and will propose no expensive initiatives.</p>
        <p>Overall, the budget is expected to call for spending only slightly more than the $1.1 trillion in the current budget, and to project a deficit just below the $64 billion limit set by the budget-balancing law. The Administration estimates that without any cuts in spending or increases in revenue, the deficit for the fiscal year 1991 would be $105 billion.</p>
        <p>The Administration's budget will provide a framework for Congress, but from recent experience the specific elements of the final budget Congress approves will bear only the vaguest resemblance to those the President submits.</p>
        <p>Here, based on interviews with many officials, are the budget proposals in various areas:</p>
        <p>MILITARY. Mr. Bush is expected to ask Congress to approve $295 billion in budget authority for the Pentagon and to propose actual spending of $292 billion. Budget authority is the amount of money Congress approves in a particular year; at the Pentagon the money is often spent over several years.</p>
        <p>Those figures are slightly above the $291.2 billion in budget authority and $288.4 in spending in this year's budget. But they are 2 percent to 3 percent below the amount needed to keep pace with inflation and thus, in the odd way budgets are calculated, are counted as a cut of $6 billion to $8 billion.</p>
        <p>HEALTH. The President will propose limiting health spending to $5.5 billion below what would be necessary to keep up with inflation, the largest budget reduction outside the military. Hospital reimbursement rates and payments to some physicians under Medicare would be lowered, and Federal money for medical education and capital improvements for urban hospitals would be reduced.</p>
        <p>Spending for alcohol and drug abuse would increase slightly, to $2.5 billion, but financing of AIDS research would not be increased. The Food and Drug Administration would be allowed to spend slightly more than this year.</p>
        <p>TAXES. To gain more political support for his capital gains proposal, Mr. Bush plans to recommend lowering the tax rate not only for profits from the sale of securities but also those from the sale of real estate, timber and most other assets. His capital gains proposal this year was limited to securities like stocks and bonds. Capital gains are now taxed at the same rate as other income, 28 percent for the wealthiest taxpayers but as high as 33 percent for others. Mr. Bush would reduce the rate to below 20 percent.</p>
        <p>The new savings plan would let couples make contributions of about $5,000 a year to a special account, and interest and dividends would be exempt from taxation if the deposits were left in the account for at least 10 years.</p>
        <p>The budget will also propose raising $2.5 billion in additional taxes by requiring all state and local government employees to pay the Medicare payroll tax now required of all other workers. Some of those workers are now exempt from the health insurance tax.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush will ask Congress to approve several small new taxes - user fees. For example, he will suggest a sales tax on pleasure boats, recreational vehicles and some camping equipment, with the money to be used for various environmental and recreational programs. Additional fees will also be proposed for processing certain Government forms. Congress has rejected several user fees that former President Ronald Reagan, as well as Mr. Bush, proposed over the last several years.</p>
        <p>ENVIRONMENT. In the 1988 campaign Mr. Bush pledged to be the environment President, and his budget message will highlight the environment, showing, for the first time, a tally of all Federal environmental programs. The budget will include a substantial increase in the operating budget of the Environmental Protection Agency, which is about $2 billion this year. Much of the additional money will be earmarked for research on toxic substances, global warming, acid rain and pollution control. More money will also be allotted for enforcement programs.The budget will also include more money for cleaning up pollution at nuclear weapons plants and for acquiring, operating and maintaining national parks.</p>
        <p>EDUCATION. As a candidate, Mr. Bush also pledged strong support for education. This year he proposed small amounts of money to reward successful schools, recognize superior teachers and otherwise improve education. These proposals were rejected by Congress, which preferred to place the limited resources on compensatory education programs for poor children.</p>
        <p>The President is expected to resubmit the proposals that failed this year and to recommend additional support for health and nutrition for preschool children as well as an expansion of the preschool program Head Start.</p>
        <p>DRUG CONTROL. He will call for more money for prison construction, law enforcement and intelligence operations related to the use and trafficking of illegal drugs. He wants a larger allocation for the Border Patrol and more military and economic assistance to Colombia, Peru and Bolivia, the sources of much of the cocaine in the United States.</p>
        <p>SCIENCE AND RESEARCH. Mr. Bush will stress applied research to improve the competitive position of American industry internationally. He will call for an increase in the budget of the National Science Foundation, and will seek additional money for developing hardware for a space station, to be completed late in the 1990's.</p>
        <p>BUDGET PROCEDURES. Mr.. Bush will suggest that the budget-balancing law be modified so that spending added after the start of a fiscal year would make it more difficult to reach the law's deficit target in the next year. And he will ask for increased authority to block spending approved by Congress that he does not favor.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
