<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Alternative-Fuel Vehicles Move From Fancy to Fact</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="238100"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHANOL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TESTS AND TESTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3D71E38F934A35757C0A96F948260" item-length="1846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Alternative-Fuel Vehicles Move From Fancy to Fact</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In British Columbia, drivers of about 8,000 vehicles are using natural gas instead of gasoline. To fill up, the drivers pull into one of 50 service stations equipped with natural-gas pumps.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In British Columbia, drivers of about 8,000 vehicles are using natural gas instead of gasoline. To fill up, the drivers pull into one of 50 service stations equipped with natural-gas pumps.</p>
        <p>In British Columbia, drivers of about 8,000 vehicles are using natural gas instead of gasoline. To fill up, the drivers pull into one of 50 service stations equipped with natural-gas pumps.</p>
        <p>Because the vehicles emit mostly carbon dioxide and water, they are being hailed by environmentalists concerned about air pollution as a good alternative to gasoline-powered cars.</p>
        <p>The British Columbia experience is the most highly developed example of the use of less-polluting fuels. But other programs -in California, Washington state and New York City - also illustrate how natural gas, electricity and methanol, which is made from natural gas, can be alternatives to gasoline and diesel fuel. California Plan an Incentive</p>
        <p>Less-polluting vehicles have received more attention since Southern California adopted a stringent air-quality program last month that could eventually ban cars, trucks and buses that burn gasoline and diesel. The California plan is widely regarded as a precursor of measures that other urban areas will have to take.</p>
        <p>''The clean-air issue is turning a passing fancy with these alternate-fueled vehicles into a genuine interest,'' said Alfred A. DelliBovi, Administrator of the Urban Mass Transit Administration, who is about to become Under Secretary of Housing and Urban Development.</p>
        <p>To be sure, alternatives to gasoline-powered cars will require dramatic changes. For all three, fueling stops would have to be more frequent than with gasoline-powered cars. And the electric vehicles, while pleasingly quiet and vibration-free, will probably never accelerate as fast as gasoline cars.</p>
        <p>Such changes would also require a huge retooling in the auto industry and big alterations in the mix of petroleum products produced. Fuel marketing would have to be different, too.</p>
        <p>But if and when pollution or economics provides the impetus for the changes, engineering experts say, American industry already has the technological ability to produce less-polluting cars, trucks and buses.</p>
        <p>One challenge in coming years will be winning acceptance among some consumers for a vehicle for which fuel will not be widely available until more drivers are won over. The engineering experts say the nation lacks the infrastructure to produce and support large numbers of alternative-fuel vehicles - necessities like factory assembly lines to make the vehicles and garages to fix them. In fact, manufacturing capacity is so limited that the demand for demonstration models has outpaced producers' ability to make the engines.</p>
        <p>The first large test of alternative fuels is likely to come when the Environmental Protection Agency puts into effect pollution standards for new buses in 1991. Similar rules for trucks are to follow in 1994.</p>
        <p>No diesel engine now on the market for buses can meet the standards, and major manufacturers are not sure engines can be modified to meet the rules in time.</p>
        <p>But diesel engines converted to burn methanol could meet the standards, the experts say.</p>
        <p>''The inventions are all done,'' said David F. Merrion, senior vice president of the Detroit Diesel Corporation, a diesel engine manufacturer that is beginning to produce methanol and natural gas versions. ''The invention was made back in the early 80's. We're now at the stage of manufacturing studies, production feasibility, evaluation of cost and determination of reliability and durability.'' An Electric Van</p>
        <p>On another front, the electric utility industry has been working with automobile manufacturers to develop a battery-powered electric van that can be driven up to 70 miles on a single charge of its batteries. Two of the vans are being tested, and within two years the van could be in use by small businesses like plumbers, florists and delivery companies.</p>
        <p>Such vehicles are best suited for local driving, situations in which they can be recharged overnight. ''We're looking at putting vehicles into niche markets,'' said Larry O'Connell, manager of the transportation program at the Electric Power Research Institute, a utility consortium in Palo Alto, Calif., that has led the electric van effort.</p>
        <p>Electric cars are ideal for stop-and-go traffic, according to their proponents. Internal combustion engines get zero miles per gallon when stopped but idling, as at a traffic light. But when cars with electric motors are not moving, they use no energy.</p>
        <p>Natural gas engines produce almost no soot, the bane of diesel fuel, and less carbon monoxide, nitrous oxides and hydrocarbons than gasoline engines.</p>
        <p>What is more, the supply of natural gas currently exceeds demand. Presumably, an increase in demand for transportation use would eliminate the surplus and drive up prices, but it would also stimulate exploration. Unlike oil, for which additional demand is met by increasing imports, gas can be produced in greater quantities in the United States and Canada, experts say. Some Drawbacks</p>
        <p>However, there are drawbacks to alternative fuels. For example, while methanol is cleaner than gasoline, it does produce formaldehyde and other poisons. And it introduces unique safety problems. For example, it burns without producing visible flames, and so is usually blended with gasoline as a safety measure. In addition, if it leaks, fumes collect at ground level, rather than dispersing, as does gasoline.</p>
        <p>What is more, gasoline- and diesel-powered vehicles are currently far cheaper to buy than those modified to run on other fuels. That means that initially, ending air pollution with alternative-fuel cars will be more costly. For natural gas and methanol vehicles, the problem is that they are not mass-produced. With electric vehicles, the technology is a step behind.</p>
        <p>But advocates of natural gas say that a mass-produced car need not be any more expensive. And the price of the fuel, like the price of gasoline, would depend on supply and demand, although the price of natural gas could be lower because it does not require as much refining. Cost of the Fuels</p>
        <p>Methanol vehicles do not appear to require more labor or materials than gasoline vehicles. The fuel, however, will always cost more than natural gas, because it is produced from the gas. But at some point, if natural gas becomes more costly, methanol might be made from coal at an economically competitive price.</p>
        <p>Electricity as a fuel might also be competitive. If batteries are charged at night, when generating capacity would otherwise be idle, power can be sold for electric cars at low cost. But gains in cost and efficiency of batteries would be required for an economically competitive electric vehicle. Reluctance Among Car Makers</p>
        <p>Critics of the major auto makers, who have spent hundreds of millions of dollars to bring the gasoline engine to its current state of development, contend that the manufacturers are not enthusiastic about starting over with a new fuel.</p>
        <p>''Right now, there isn't enough enthusiasm in the mainstream of manufacturing,'' said Harvey W. Schultz, Commissioner of New York City's Department of Environmental Protection. He and others pointed out that because there is no market for the vehicles, there is no mass production, and therefore no product at an attractive price.</p>
        <p>''The talk in the business is that we'll have alternative-fuel vehicles when G.M. wants to build them,'' Mr. Schultz said.</p>
        <p>The growing issue of air pollution may produce regulations that help alternative-fuel vehicles. The British Columbia Project</p>
        <p>But one technology, natural gas, is flourishing on simple economics, at least in some locations. The crucial hurdle for alternative vehicles, fuel availability, appears to have been crossed in British Columbia, where the 50 service stations offer natural gas pumps next to pumps with leaded and unleaded gasoline. The stations, bearing familiar names like Shell and Texaco, take the gas from the underground mains that supply homes.</p>
        <p>''We sell it entirely on an economic basis,'' said Roger B. Anastasiou, a fueling-systems engineer with British Columbia Gas, a utility in Vancouver. Natural gas is sold in a unit equivalent in mileage value to gasoline but at half the price. The price difference includes a small tax break.</p>
        <p>Auto specialty stores that convert cars to run on natural gas charge about $2,500 for the job, and the province and the utilities will contribute about a third of the cost, after which the conversion is still expensive. But the cost would drop sharply if auto makers mass-produced the cars, Mr. Anastasiou said. The First U.S. Moves</p>
        <p>In the United States, about 25,000 vehicles owned by utilities for meter readers and the like run on natural gas, according to Alan Streb, Deputy Assistant Secretary for Conservation in the Department of Energy. Many vehicles are also running on methanol.</p>
        <p>Other vehicles that run on natural gas include some Pierce Transit buses in the Tacoma, Wash., area.</p>
        <p>Pierce Transit, a government agency, converted two of its 150 buses to natural gas two years ago, the first bus operator in the nation to do so, to Don S. Munroe, the executive director, said. After ironing out a few early problems, Pierce decided it would like to try more of the buses, and last month the agency won a grant of $8.3 million from the Urban Mass Transit Administration to buy them.</p>
        <p>The grant was the first under a $46.8 million program approved last year by the Federal Government to foster buses running on alternative fuels. The program has already attracted requests for financing of 406 buses around the country, according to Mr. DelliBovi, the Administrator.</p>
        <p>In Brooklyn, Command Bus Lines is running two natural gas-powered buses provided last year by Brooklyn Union Gas, and the utility recently displayed a gas-powered taxi that will enter service soon. Methanol Ventures</p>
        <p>The Triboro Coach Corporation is running six methanol-powered buses, built by General Motors, on various routes around New York City. And General Motors has just shipped the first dozen of 2,200 methanol cars to the state government in California, which plans to use them in government fleets and monitor their performance. The state hopes to put 5,000 on the road in the next few years.</p>
        <p>Last month, with a formal ceremony, Gov. George Deukmejian of California unveiled a methanol pump at an ARCO convenience store in Sacramento. According to the California Energy Commission, it is the nation's fifth.</p>
        <p>But on a per-mile basis, the fuel cost for a methanol vehicle can be five times the cost to run on diesel.</p>
        <p>Mr. DelliBovi said the new Environmental Protection Agency pollution standard for buses ''really creates a window for a niche market.''</p>
        <p>The window is exciting for the gas companies. For example, Columbia Gas, a utility in Ohio, has just given a test bus to the Central Ohio Transit Authority, at a cost of $300,000, in hopes the authority will buy more. The company stresses the reliability and economy of the fuel. And each bus on the road uses as much gas as 10 houses that use the fuel for heating and cooking, said William F. Morse, vice president for research.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
