<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="219451"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DA1331F932A35751C0A96F948260" item-length="940" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International A2-10</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International A2-10</p>
        <p>International A2-10</p>
        <p>Changes in Britain's health service announced by the Government would apply free-market methods to the state-financed system. The changes would be the most far-reaching since the service was founded. Page A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: In Nicaragua, cutbacks announced by the Sandinista Government were just what its opponents wanted. But the decision bore the mark of a Government that is still confident of its popular support. A1</p>
        <p>Panama's human-rights picture is being improved as jails are cleaned up in anticipation of a key inspection by international observers. A6</p>
        <p>To try to end civil war in the Sudan, senior Bush Administration officials have met in the last few days with a leading representative of the Sudanese guerrilla forces. A1</p>
        <p>As Soviet troops leave Afghanistan, a fresh stream of refugees is struggling through the mud, ice and snow of Nawa Pass and into Pakistan. They are fleeing the fighting around Jalalabad. A10</p>
        <p>A last diplomatic effort in Pakistan to forge a political compromise among warring factions in Afghanistan is expected to take place, culminating with a visit by the Soviet Foreign Minister on Saturday. A10</p>
        <p>Mikhail Gorbachev's salary was reported and his wife's stylish wardrobe defended in an interview published by a newspaper in the Soviet republic of Moldavia. Mr. Gorbachev is paid more than 1,500 rubles a month, the equivalent of about $2,500. A10</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Noboru Takeshita of Japan left for Washington to become the first foreign leader to meet with President Bush, amid concerns in Japan about new strains in its alliance with the United States. A3</p>
        <p>Investigations concluded in Korea into corruption and human rights abuses of the last eight years. The chief prosecutor said his office had arrested 47 people on charges of corruption or abuse of power. A3</p>
        <p>A sinking Argentine ship, which ran aground off Antarctica, is in danger of spilling more than 250,000 gallons of diesel fuel, causing the continent's first environmental crisis, the National Science Foundation said. A3</p>
        <p>National A12-18</p>
        <p>The U.S. population will likely peak at about 300 million in a half century and then begin to slide downward, the Census Bureau projected. It was the bureau's first projection of such a trend. A1</p>
        <p>Legislation to curb acid rain will be proposed shortly by William K. Reilly, nominated to head the Environmental Protection Agency, signaling a sharp break with Reagan Administration policies. A1</p>
        <p>Dr. Louis Sullivan's confirmation hearings were postponed at the request of the White House, but officials said it did not signal any softening of President Bush's support for his Health and Human Services nominee. A14</p>
        <p>John Tower's confirmation hearing took an unexpected turn when witnesses and Senators were drawn into a discussion of allegations of womanizing and drunkenness against the Secretary of Defense-designate. A14</p>
        <p>General Motors has agreed to settle a class-action lawsuit covering present and former black managers, profes-sionals and clerical staff. The plan includes the use of a computer model to monitor personnel actions. A1</p>
        <p>Oliver North's trial officially began with a halting first attempt to interview and select 12 jurors and 6 alternates. Many of the interviews were followed by objections from Mr. North's defense lawyers. A12</p>
        <p>Judge seen reinstating U.S. policy that left aliens at border</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Viruses growing resistant to drugs A15</p>
        <p>Washington Talk A18</p>
        <p>Regional B1-5</p>
        <p>A study of infants in foster care who entered New York City's child-welfare system in 1985 found that three years later the majority still remained without permanent homes, their cases often testimony to poor social work. A1</p>
        <p>The jury in the Joel Steinberg case spent eight tense days engaged in an ordeal of stubborn arguments relieved at times by bursts of laughter following the three-month trial in the death of 6-year-old Lisa Stienberg. A1</p>
        <p>As her legacy, Lisa Steinberg left an increased awareness of child abuse and a new readiness to report cases in which abuse is suspected. Experts said that concern about child abuse has been at an all-time high. B4</p>
        <p>News analysis: When are people responsible for their actions?</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>James Florio is a leading candidate to occupy the governor's mansion in New Jersey next January. Representative Florio, who lost to Thomas H. Kean in 1981, has been perfecting his public persona. B1  Benjamin Ward offended a group of Hispanic people, again, this time at a fence-mending meeting that was prompted by the Police Commissioner's remark last year about Hispanic people and drug dealing. B1</p>
        <p>A new leader for Riverside Church was unanimously chosen by the search committee and the deacons of Riverside. He is the Rev. James A. Forbes, a 53-year-old professor of preaching at Union Theological Seminary. B1</p>
        <p>A tall West Side apartment tower is at issue in the closing chapter in the epic of the West Side Urban Renewal Area. What would result is a structure almost twice as big as the building planned 10 years ago. B3</p>
        <p>Lack of snow slows winter festivals B1</p>
        <p>West Paterson ponders changing its name B2</p>
        <p>Koch complains about Cuomo's budget B2</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases A19</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
