<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Industry Coalition Frays</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="291096"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOBBYING AND LOBBYISTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D7103DF936A25753C1A96F948260" item-length="733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Industry Coalition Frays</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE battle over strengthening the Clean Air Act is placing enormous strain on the industry coalition that has worked together in the 1980's to lobby successfully against stronger air pollution laws.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE battle over strengthening the Clean Air Act is placing enormous strain on the industry coalition that has worked together in the 1980's to lobby successfully against stronger air pollution laws.</p>
        <p>THE battle over strengthening the Clean Air Act is placing enormous strain on the industry coalition that has worked together in the 1980's to lobby successfully against stronger air pollution laws.</p>
        <p>Industries, and in some cases companies within industries, have been set against each other by legislation pending in Congress to control acid rain, smog and toxic emissions into the air. In recent years, industries have resisted cutting separate deals with Congress that might harm other businesses.</p>
        <p>But the new political climate, driven largely by President Bush's support for a new Clean Air Act, is making it more difficult for them to maintain a unified front. ''This coalition is fundamentally unstable,'' said Representative Henry A. Waxman, a California Democrat who has supported stronger air pollution legislation for 10 years.</p>
        <p>The clean air fight has caused splits within the utility and coal industries. The coal and natural gas industries are at odds with each other, as are the oil and auto companies. Clean air legislation has always generated bitter industrial and regional differences. But industry had an active ally in the Reagan Administration, which made it much easier to paper over differences.</p>
        <p>In the 1982 fight over the Clean Air Act, industry managed to stay together because ''everyone got a break'' under proposed legislation, Mr. Waxman said. Under current proposals, if there are breaks for industry, they are unevenly divided. Most businesses recognize that new anti-pollution laws are inevitable and have ordered their Capitol Hill lobbyists to strike the best deals they can.</p>
        <p>The shape of things to come is already apparent in Congress. The House health and environment subcommittee recently ended a 12-year stalemate by agreeing to tighter automobile tailpipe emission standards, a measure Detroit auto makers vehemently opposed. Industry reaction following the vote suggested how divisive the Clean Air debate could become. Ronald R. Boltz, a vice president at the Chrysler Corporation, said the auto companies were easier targets than other industries that contribute to smog. ''It is essential that other industries join the auto industry'' in cleaning up the air, he said.</p>
        <p>The auto companies lost a fight with the oil industry in the subcommittee on a provision to install special canisters on cars to control pollutants emitted at the gasoline pump. Detroit favored special nozzles on gasoline pumps to capture smog-producing vapors emitted during refueling; oil companies, which own many gasoline stations, supported the canisters.</p>
        <p>In a demonstration of how fast alliances can shift, the oil and auto industries came together last week to lobby successfully against President Bush's plan to require the production of cleaner-burning fuels and vehicles that could burn them. At one point, the auto companies had good words for alternative fuels because they thought they could avoid tighter tailpipe standards. On the other hand, oil companies have huge investments in producing gasoline and not much incentive to spend money to develop competitive products. But Detroit backed away from alternative fuels after the subcommittee voted to tighten tailpipe standards anyway. Warring Factions</p>
        <p>While tighter regulations will force many companies to spend millions of dollars to clean up emissions, others could make out handily, setting the stage for more conflict. Producers of natural gas, viewed as a cleaner burning fuel than coal and a potential alternative motor vehicle fuel, are possible beneficiaries of a toughened clean air law at the expense of coal companies. So are producers of low-sulfur coal, who are poised to carve out a bigger chunk of the market at the expense of dirtier-burning, high-sulfur coal.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the biggest area for conflict lies in legislation to control acid rain, an issue that has split Congress throughout the decade. Much of the cost and cleanup burden would fall on utilities in the Middle West that burn high-sulfur coal, a source of the sulfur dioxides that cause acid rain.</p>
        <p>As a result, they are asking that their cleanup costs be subsidized by utilities and, ultimately, consumers in other parts of the country in the form of a national tax or fee. These proposals are being firmly resisted by utilities that have already spent billions on antipollution systems to reduce sulfur-dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
