<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Move for Parental Choice in Schools Gains</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="240422"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">EDUCATION, DEPARTMENT OF (NJ)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">VAN TASSEL, PRISCILLA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KEAN, THOMAS H (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DA1039F935A25757C0A96F948260" item-length="1456" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Move for Parental Choice in Schools Gains</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PRISCILLA VAN TASSEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VAN TASSEL, PRISCILLA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: FOR the last six years, Joyce Caesar has been battling Irvington public school officials over her daughter's education. Continually in trouble at school, suspended several times for defiance of school rules and ostracized by her classmates, the girl, now in the 11th grade, is currently receiving home instruction until a better alternative is found.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: FOR the last six years, Joyce Caesar has been battling Irvington public school officials over her daughter's education. Continually in trouble at school, suspended several times for defiance of school rules and ostracized by her classmates, the girl, now in the 11th grade, is currently receiving home instruction until a better alternative is found.</p>
        <p>FOR the last six years, Joyce Caesar has been battling Irvington public school officials over her daughter's education. Continually in trouble at school, suspended several times for defiance of school rules and ostracized by her classmates, the girl, now in the 11th grade, is currently receiving home instruction until a better alternative is found.</p>
        <p>''I have watched a child who loved school grow into one who would pretend to be sick to get out of going to school,'' said Ms. Caesar, who attributes the problem to poor chemistry between Irvington's school administrators and her daughter.</p>
        <p>Ms. Caesar is one of a number of New Jerseyans who feel that no one public school is right for all children and that parents should have some choice in the schools their children attend. At a public hearing earlier this year, she urged State Department of Education officials to make provisions for children like her daughter to attend schools in other districts.</p>
        <p>The hearing was part of the department's yearlong study of ''choice,'' or the ability of parents to select the schools their children attend. In his 1988 State of the State Message, Gov. Thomas H. Kean asked the department to explore the concept, and in this year's message, he spoke out more forcefully on the subject, indicating he hoped to see a workable choice plan in place by the time he leaves office in January. Mr. Kean said he would announce his plan for choice by the end of this month.</p>
        <p>''We know that choice works,'' Mr. Kean said in a speech before the Education Writers Association in Washington this month. ''Now is the time to put the idea in place before choice becomes the equivalent of acid rain in education - all talk and no action.''</p>
        <p>State Department of Education officials would not comment on the precise nature of Mr. Kean's plan, but he is expected to confine his initial efforts to intradistrict programs. The only choice options Mr. Kean has so far publicly ruled out are vouchers and tuition tax credits, two plans to help parents of children in private schools.</p>
        <p>The notion of choice in public schools has been gaining popularity in recent years, with at least 23 states now offering or considering some form of parental discretion on the schools their children attend. Some of the plans are ambitious interdistrict efforts that shuffle around thousands of students and involve millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>In Minnesota, a leader in the choice movement, the state pays for high school juniors and seniors to take courses at public and private colleges. California elementary school students can attend school in districts where their parents work as long as there is no negative impact on desegregation. Suburban districts surrounding Milwaukee are required to provide space for city students. In New Jersey, the few choice efforts have been restricted to more modest intradistrict exchanges. For the last 13 years, parents in Atlantic City have been able to select any of the district's seven elementary schools for their children, and Montclair has had a highly successful magnet system since 1977.</p>
        <p>Dr. Frank Esposito has taken a sabbatical from his post as vice president of Kean College to direct the study for the Education Department. He said he had received numerous letters from parents, urging the state to provide more choice in public schools. In one letter, a woman on a fixed income of $7,155 described how she is paying $4,450 for her grandson, of whom she has custody, to attend a public school in a nearby town. The district, like many others in New Jersey, accepts out-of-town students on a tuition basis.</p>
        <p>''I won't say where she lives, because it will seem like we are coming down on that school district,'' Dr. Esposito said. ''But it is revealing of something that is occurring in the state. Parents are paying on a tuition basis, even at great personal sacrifice, to make a choice right now.''</p>
        <p>Most of the choice plans nationally were begun as a means of promoting integration. New Jersey's primary interest in the concept, however, is as a means of improving education through greater personalization. Proponents argue that by matching students' needs with particular schools, schools become revitalized, dropout rates are reduced and parental involvement is increased.</p>
        <p>But critics maintain that choice systems are costly and often difficult to administer. Despite reassurances from Mr. Kean that choice will not adversely affect the racial balance in schools, they also fear that choice may even increase racial polarization if white urban students elect to go to the suburbs.</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Esposito, the more than 60 hours of public hearings on choice resulted in no clear consensus on how loosely structured New Jerseyans would like their school lines to be. He said that while intradistrict plans provoked little concern, there was considerable controversy over the logistics and expense of interdistrict plans.</p>
        <p>''If I were to characterize the reaction, it would be cautious, especially among school board members,'' Dr. Esposito said. ''They raised a lot of very good implementation questions.''</p>
        <p>One major concern was the appropriateness of a costly new initiative in the face of a possible budget crisis. Mr. Kean's recommendation to pare $234 million from state aid to public schools for 1989-90 has spawned outrage from a number of state education associations and at least one lawsuit, brought by the New Jersey School Boards Association.</p>
        <p>''If New Jersey can't meet its basic obligations to public schools, how could it hope to help fund a school choice program?'' asked Dennis Giordano, president of the New Jersey Education Association, at the final public hearing on choice in Secaucus last month.</p>
        <p>Even with full financing of the state aid-to-education formula, the association is against interdistrict plans.</p>
        <p>''Let's make sure students receive equal educational opportunities regardless of where they attend school, instead of working toward decimating some districts which may lack the resources of other districts,'' Mr. Giordano said.  Often Expensive to Run</p>
        <p>Few educators deny that even the simplest choice systems are often expensive to operate. Busing costs for magnet programs in Chicago and Los Angeles, for example, run about $1,000 a student.</p>
        <p>But to many, the extra costs are worthwhile, especially in light of the lawsuit, Abbott v. Burke, which is seeking to tie educational opportunity to financial resources and declare New Jersey's system of financing public education unconstitutional because it favors property-rich districts.</p>
        <p>''It seems to me the two are a marriage made in heaven,'' said Dr. Margaret Tannenbaum, an assistant professor at Glassboro State College's School of Education and Professional Studies and an advocate of choice. ''If quality of schooling is in any way related to expenditure and the process of funding schools is moved fully to the state level, it is quite conceivable to me that even with transportation, a choice system would not cost any more than education presently does.''</p>
        <p>Since many current choice plans have succeeded in promoting racial balance, Department of Education officials have been surprised by the large number of urban parents and school officials who have spoken out against interdistrict initiatives.  Uncontrolled Choice Opposed</p>
        <p>At the public hearings, Larry Leverett, Superintendent of Englewood Schools, was one of many urban representatives speaking out against uncontrolled choice.</p>
        <p>''We've discovered that parental school choice is not often racially neutral,'' said Mr. Leverett, whose district is locked in litigation with Tenafly and Englewood Cliffs over a sending-receiving relationship. ''We know that white parents often perceive that schools with substantial minority enrollments are poor-quality schools.''</p>
        <p>While Englewood and other receiving districts involved in sending-receiving agreements may fear the loss of students under an interdistrict choice plan, most sending districts around the state appear to be in favor of increasing their options.</p>
        <p>''The majority see it as a vehicle to provide greater flexibility, either to get out of a sending-receiving agreement or to supplement it with choice in some other way,'' Dr. Esposito said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Esposito would not comment on whether he recommended mandatory or voluntary choice systems or on any other aspect of his confidential final report to Commissioner of Education Saul Cooperman, other than to say that it contained specific recommendations and their budget implications.</p>
        <p>As to New Jersey's commitment to choice, he would only say that his contract with the department, which was to have ended on Feb. 15, has been extended until June 1990.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
