<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Search of A Better Law To Clear the Air</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19890604T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="249547"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NITROGEN OXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SULFUR AND SULFUR COMPOUNDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CLEAN AIR ACT</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6D61639F937A25756C0A96F948260" item-length="1526" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Search of A Better Law To Clear the Air</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: AFTER more than a decade of legislative deadlock, Congress and the White House may finally come to terms this year on an important revision of the Clean Air Act, a path-breaking but imperfect law enacted almost 20 years ago with the goal of sweeping pollution from the sky.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: AFTER more than a decade of legislative deadlock, Congress and the White House may finally come to terms this year on an important revision of the Clean Air Act, a path-breaking but imperfect law enacted almost 20 years ago with the goal of sweeping pollution from the sky.</p>
        <p>AFTER more than a decade of legislative deadlock, Congress and the White House may finally come to terms this year on an important revision of the Clean Air Act, a path-breaking but imperfect law enacted almost 20 years ago with the goal of sweeping pollution from the sky.</p>
        <p>The outcome of the debate will affect air quality in the United States for decades to come. It will determine how many billions of dollars industry will have to spend to reduce pollution and may affect the way millions of Americans live.</p>
        <p>''What is at stake in this legislation is the health of over 135 million people in this country who live in areas that have not attained the ozone standard,'' said S. William Becker, executive director of the State and Territorial Air Pollution Administrators. ''What is at stake,'' he continued, ''is over 2,500 excess cancers alone just from routine day-to-day exposure to toxic air pollution. What is at stake is the deterioration of thousands of miles of streams, thousands of lakes'' from acid rain.</p>
        <p>While Congress will have the last word on a new clean air law, President Bush's proposal, which he will issue at the end of this month or early in June, will establish the general tenor of the debate and provide the first and probably decisive test of his campaign pledge to be a strong environmental leader.</p>
        <p>The contradictory forces tugging at him were apparent last week in the debate over a related environmental challenge. It was disclosed that the White House's Office of Management and Budget had changed the testimony of a Government scientist to soften his warnings about global warming, which may be largely a result of the burning of fossil fuels. But the President later changed course and called for United States leadership in preparing the way for an international treaty to confront the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is under pressure from industry groups, who feel that they are already bearing too much of the cost of cleaning up the atmosphere. Some $35 million a year is now being spent, largely by the private sector, to control air pollution. According to estimates by the Environmental Protection Agency, the options now being considered for strengthening the Clean Air Act would require additional spending of $2 billion to $8 billion a year on acid rain, $8 billion to $20 billion on smog control and $1 billion to $6 billion on toxic air pollution. Some experts as well as industry spokesmen argue that the costs of further controls may in some cases, like the battle against smog, outweigh the benefits. ''At stake is our hides,'' said William D. Fay, administrator of the Clean Air Working Group, the main industry lobbying organization.  Atmospheric Threats</p>
        <p>The Clean Air Act, passed in 1970, is widely credited with having made the air much cleaner than it would otherwise be. But even as amended in 1977, the law has not addressed some critical problems and it has failed to provide adequate tools for reaching some goals it set. The legislation now being considered is an attempt to come to grips with three kinds of air pollution that continue to threaten public health and the environment.</p>
        <p>* Acid Rain. For more than a decade, Government officials have been debating what to do about oxides of sulfur and nitrogen, mainly from coal-fired power plants, that change chemically in the atmosphere and fall to earth as acidic rain, snow, fog or dust. Acid precipitation kills life in lakes and streams, erodes buildings and, many scientists believe, damages forests and threatens human health. In his campaign, Mr. Bush said the time for action had arrived.</p>
        <p>* Smog. Volatile chemicals from gasoline vapor and various industrial and commercial sources react with sunlight creating ozone, a chief ingredient of smog. Although the latest of many extended deadlines for meeting the law's goals for reducing ozone pollution expired last summer, most large metropolitan areas have been unable to bring smog levels down to meet prescribed limits. Ozone has been shown to damage the lungs of children and adults.</p>
        <p>Smog rose to record levels in many cities during last summer's heat wave.</p>
        <p>* Toxic air pollution. Each year, industry spews about 2.7 billion pounds of toxic chemicals, some of them cancer-causing, into the air, the E.P.A. reported earlier this year.</p>
        <p>Although the 1970 law required the agency to control such emissions, it has issued regulations for only seven of the more than 300 chemicals that Congress has determined to be a health threat. The reason for the glacial regulatory pace, agency officials say, is their inability to come up with a consistent definition of what constitutes a risk to human health.</p>
        <p>Administration officials are still working on options to present to the President. There are said to be sharp differences among those drafting the legislation, with William K. Reilly, the Administrator of the E.P.A., and Energy Secretary James D. Watkins pressing for tougher controls, and the Office of Management and Budget and the White House domestic policy staff worried about the cost.</p>
        <p>According to Administration officials, Mr. Reilly is arguing for a reduction of 10 million tons by the turn of the century in the amount of sulfur dioxide emitted each year by power plants, the chief source of acid rain. In 1980, power plants accounted for 15.5 million tons of the more than 21 million tons of sulfur dioxides emitted into the air.</p>
        <p>All proposals for controlling acid rain also include a provision for reducing nitrogen oxides.</p>
        <p>The agency task force working on the issue is considering other ideas including a smaller reduction and a later deadline, according to Administration sources. They said that any acid rain proposal would give utilities or states flexibility to decide how to meet the goals and would make use of market incentives, like trading rights to pollute, to encourage compliance with the law. With so many of the old standards still unmet, some Administration and industry officials have questioned whether new programs to deal with smog and toxic air emissions are worth the cost. But Mr. Reilly of the E.P.A. has insisted that reaching the goal set by law is necessary to protect human health. A central feature of any Administration smog control proposal would be to encourage the use of cleaner fuels like methanol and ethanol.</p>
        <p>Proposals being considered by the Administration for dealing with toxic pollution include dropping the health standards of the current law and considering the risks and costs on a case-by-case basis, or requiring that controls be installed to reduce emissions of more than 300 chemicals.</p>
        <p>Putting these ingredients together in a way that will satisfy environmentalists without alienating industry will be a difficult balancing act.  THE LAW THAT STARTED IT ALL</p>
        <p>WHEN the Clean Air Act was put into effect in 1970 it was hailed as a landmark in the country's struggle against the alarming and accelerating degradation of the environment. Nearly 20 years later, despite increasingly apparent shortcomings, that first assessment is still valid.</p>
        <p>While it is one of the more complex pieces of legislation ever devised, the law established a simple precedent: the Federal Government has the right and duty to set and enforce national standards defining clean air. Before then, fighting pollution was largely left to state and local governments.</p>
        <p>What the new law did, Bernard S. Cohen of the American Trial Lawyers Association said at the time, was to provide ''the legislative tools which will form the jurisdictional foundation and the procedural building blocks with which to wage war on pollution.''</p>
        <p>Adopted unanimously in the Senate and with only one dissenting vote in the House, the law provided many tools for attacking air pollution, the most important of which was a set of maximum levels for six pollutants: lead, solid particles, sulfur dioxide, carbon monoxide, nitrogen oxide and ozone.</p>
        <p>Airborne lead has declined by nearly 90 percent since 1970, in large part because its use as a fuel additive has been banned. Reductions in other pollutants have been relatively modest, and in the case of nitrogen oxide there has been no improvement at all.</p>
        <p>But it is widely agreed that without controls imposed on industry and automobiles by the Clean Air Act, many areas of the country would now be blanketed by pollution as thick and noxious as that choking the people of Mexico City.  Reaching a Plateau</p>
        <p>Officials of the Environmental Protection Agency, which administers the law, as well as environmentalists, warn that the improvements in the quality of the air may slow or stop in the near future unless the law is strengthened.</p>
        <p>The chief reason for this, they explain, is that much of the improvement in air quality has come as more and more new cars equipped with pollution control devices have replaced old cars that spew uncontrolled exhaust into the air.</p>
        <p>But within the next few years, the turnover of the car fleet will be all but complete and no measurable new gains will be made.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, more cars will be driven more miles, putting more pollution into the air.</p>
        <p>THE WORLD  Correction:  June 4, 1989, Sunday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>An article on May 14 about the Clean Air Act misstated the amount being spent, largely by private interests, to control air pollution in the United States. It is $35 billion a year, not $35 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 4, 1989, Sunday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>An article on May 14 about the Clean Air Act misstated the amount being spent, largely by private interests, to control air pollution in the United States. It is $35 billion a year, not $35 million.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
