<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Men's Style; THE HEAT IS ON</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="78" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="264688"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROGERS, FRANCES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0D8133FF93AA35754C0A96F948260" item-length="324" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Men's Style; THE HEAT IS ON</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCES ROGERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROGERS, FRANCES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In an era of global warming trends and equatorial summers, men's clothing is following suit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In an era of global warming trends and equatorial summers, men's clothing is following suit.</p>
        <p>In an era of global warming trends and equatorial summers, men's clothing is following suit.</p>
        <p>''We're seeing more variety than ever,'' says Peter Rizzo, senior vice president and general merchandise manager of men's wear at Barneys New York, ''and it's definitely geared toward comfort.'' In suits, that means a continuation of the popular full silhouette, with its broader shoulder and roomier seat, in natural fibers like cotton, linen and silk. Jacket linings are often reduced to partial facings along the front panels and yoke. ''It's a lot cooler than a full rayon lining,'' says Rizzo, who thinks a sumptuous cotton gabardine in this construction is a handsome alternative to wash-and-wear cotton poplin.</p>
        <p>In Florida, where Don Johnson's T-shirt and beard stubble still haunt retailers, Charles Goldstein, owner of the 24 Collection specialty stores in Boca Raton and Bal Harbour, sees salvation in summer suits, particularly linen and silk blends in brown and olive. Sales are up from last year, partly because of ''a self-consciousness among customers who want to distance themselves from the 'Miami Vice' look that was so obvious and overdone.''</p>
        <p>''You don't see much of the Don Johnson look here,'' says Greg Blackwell, manager of Brooks Brothers in New Orleans. More in keeping with the character of the city and its ''relentless'' heat is a white cotton and linen plantation suit - much like the one Clark Gable wore in ''China Seas'' - designed especially for the New Orleans market.</p>
        <p>The Southwest, as Dallas-based Neiman Marcus envisions it, embraces a more ''European trans-Atlantic look'' in summer suits, says Derrill Osborn, vice president and director of men's clothing. ''Cotton is the most important fabric for us, especially in some of the new plaids and checks and herringbone patterns. They've added a lot of excitement to the category.'' Anything J.R. Ewing might endorse? ''We wouldn't dress J.R.,'' says Osborn.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
