<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Schools, New Emphasis on Environment</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="303006"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, KIRK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DE113CF932A15752C1A96F948260" item-length="1279" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Schools, New Emphasis on Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSON, KIRK</byline>
      <dateline>COLUMBIA, Conn.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The group of boisterous 7-year-olds from the Horace W. Porter School straightened up when Tom Callinan strummed the guitar chords. It was a song they had sung before, a song about garbage and the endangered habitats of river and forest animals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The group of boisterous 7-year-olds from the Horace W. Porter School straightened up when Tom Callinan strummed the guitar chords. It was a song they had sung before, a song about garbage and the endangered habitats of river and forest animals.</p>
        <p>The group of boisterous 7-year-olds from the Horace W. Porter School straightened up when Tom Callinan strummed the guitar chords. It was a song they had sung before, a song about garbage and the endangered habitats of river and forest animals.</p>
        <p>''Better love it while we still have it,'' they sang along. ''Or rat-a-tat-tat our habitat's gone.''</p>
        <p>Educators and environmentalists say that schools across the country are reporting an increase in classroom demand for environmental education as teachers struggle to explain complex and often frightening issues in the news, from global warming and acid rain to leaking landfills and endangered species.</p>
        <p>Government officials and other spokesmen, sometimes dressed like magicians or superheros, go to schools with messages of garbage awareness. Utilities, which spend millions of dollars a year on educational programs, have expanded their efforts.</p>
        <p>In one of the most ambitious programs, administrators at the Porter School in this eastern Connecticut town of 4,000 have declared global awareness and environmentalism the themes for the school year. Assemblies, songs and posters reinforce the message that pupils must conserve, recycle and save the earth by saving their own back yards. Several teachers describe the campaign as brainwashing for a good cause.</p>
        <p>''You see the message sinking in as they sing, 'recycle, recycle, recycle,''' said Mr. Callinan, an environmentalist, folk singer and former teacher who came here with his wife, Ann Shapiro, to perform for the pupils. His songs and patter, he said, are directed at young, impressionable minds.</p>
        <p>''It's not very subtle,'' he said. ''But it works.''</p>
        <p>But educators say that with so much at stake in environmental or energy policies, from corporate profits to the ecosystem, the renewed classroom interest is also drawing inevitable questions about bias and point of view.</p>
        <p>''The greenhouse effect and all that has triggered the demand side on how to respond in our classrooms,'' said Roy Rustum, director of the Science, Technology and Society Program at Pennsylvania State University. ''Because the university world is asleep as usual, by and large the environmental groups are active and moving into education.''</p>
        <p>Those groups, however, have attacked not only most industry-sponsored programs as biased toward company interests, but also one another over their own goals: whether children should be taught to conserve and recycle, or be prepared for a new relationship between human beings and the environment.</p>
        <p>''The difference is between shallow environmentalists and deep ecologists,'' said Dr. Steve Van Matre, chairman of the Institute for Earth Education of Warrenville, Ill. ''The shallows say, 'Clean up our mess, and everything will be fine. The deeps say, 'How can we live in more harmony with our planet?' ''</p>
        <p>The Humane Society of the United States has entered the fray, lobbying against what it calls the pro-hunting and trapping bias of the most widely used nature-study curriculum, Project Wild, which is used in 47 states. That bias, it says, is reflected in the curriculum's suggestion that nature needs human management to keep animal populations in balance. Scenes Deemed too Intense</p>
        <p>Teachers also walk a delicate path between inspiring students and scaring them. At the Porter School, where teachers screen their materials, they recently voted to restrict a rented film to third-graders and up because scenes of earthquake devastation and forest fires were deemed too intense.</p>
        <p>The environmental message has hit home. Among a group of six pupils assembled from the Porter School's second, fifth and eighth grades for a discussion, all but one said they had talked to their parents about recycling during the school year, and some of those had begun sorting household glass and newspapers as a result.</p>
        <p>Asked about the need for cleaning up the environment, Elizabeth Smith, a fifth-grader, began, ''We have to, or soon our whole life span is going to go,'' and ended with a sputtering noise and a slicing motion of her hand.</p>
        <p>Questions have also arisen about whether actions can match words. Faced with a tightened budget and labor shortage three years ago, the Porter School eliminated dishwashers and reusable plates and began using disposable plates, cups and tableware. 'Response to the Kids' Concerns'</p>
        <p>This year's environmental theme was born, in part, from a pupil's letter-writing campaign about the trash.</p>
        <p>''The kids were concerned about using Styrofoam,'' said Liga Jahnke, a teacher overseeing the environmental project. ''This was a response to the kids' concerns.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Jahnke said that as part of the effort, this month pupils began separating lunchroom waste. A company collects the hard plastic and polystyrene products, mostly knives, forks and containers, for recycling. Other materials, like the softer plastics used to wrap food and paper contaminated by food, are still thrown away.</p>
        <p>At least one pupil, Eric Johnson, an eighth-grader, has continued to pursue his concerns, with letters to the recyling company and to the State Department of Environmental Protection asking about filtering systems and the possible release of chlorofluorocarbons during the plastic-recyling process. The substances have been linked to depletion of the earth's ozone layer. 'There's Enormous Waste'</p>
        <p>''If we're trying to train children to take care of the environment, the place to have plastics isn't the school,'' First Selectman Adel Urban said. ''There's enormous waste.''</p>
        <p>Teachers said the two main variables affecting the program were time and money. They said that with so many mandatory subjects, shoehorning the environment into the program often meant abbreviating or deleting something else, unless the topic could be worked into other subjects like art.</p>
        <p>This year, the Porter School's $3.7 million budget was cut $150,000, endangering $5,000 that had been set aside for environmental programs like Mr. Callinan's, which cost $400. The principal, Ron Choiniere, said he intended to argue with the Board of Education to restore some of the money.</p>
        <p>Many schools, if not most, are on similarly tight budgets, making it difficult to buy or rent environmental materials. That can leave students and teachers dependent on what is provided free by the state or by utilities. A Pro-Nuclear Stance</p>
        <p>''Nobody has the resources that the utilities do,'' said Michael Mariotte, executive director of the Nuclear Information and Resource Service in Washington. The group publishes a teachers' guide to films and courses that, Mr. Mariotte said, balance the utility industry's pro-nuclear stance.</p>
        <p>Northeast Utilities, which serves much of southern New England, says it will reach about six times as many students this year with information on nuclear energy as it did two years ago.</p>
        <p>The Duke Power Company in Charlotte, N. C., described by trade officials as having a major educational commitment, has doubled its summer workshops for teachers since 1987.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the utility, Mary Kathryn Scarborough, said that through the weeklong all-expenses-paid workshops, which started 15 years ago, Duke Power has ''seen 930 teachers and influenced 1,552,320 students.''</p>
        <p>An unknown, education officials said, is whether the demand will continue to grow or fade, as it did after a similar surge in the early 70's.</p>
        <p>''People are asking for it now, and lots of wonderful educators are out there pushing,'' said John Hoskyns-Abrahall, president of Bullfrog Films, a distributor of environmental and energy films in Oley, Pa. ''But changing a curriculum is a huge job.. By 1991, I expect it to cool off again.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
