<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>White House</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="262433"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="WASHINGTON TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIDES AND EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEINRAUB, BERNARD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUNUNU, JOHN H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON TALK PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7DF1139F933A05755C0A96F948260" item-length="645" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>White House</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bernard Weinraub, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEINRAUB, BERNARD</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: They are the White House's political ''A list,'' a select group of Republicans who receive copies of major speeches, proposals and initiatives from John H. Sununu, the chief of staff, often with a note saying, ''Let me know what you think of this.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: They are the White House's political ''A list,'' a select group of Republicans who receive copies of major speeches, proposals and initiatives from John H. Sununu, the chief of staff, often with a note saying, ''Let me know what you think of this.''</p>
        <p>They are the White House's political ''A list,'' a select group of Republicans who receive copies of major speeches, proposals and initiatives from John H. Sununu, the chief of staff, often with a note saying, ''Let me know what you think of this.''</p>
        <p>The group includes Washington consultants and lobbyists, friends of President Bush's as well as members of the Bush family - a kitchen cabinet organized by Mr. Sununu to offer advice and, perhaps more important, to thwart criticisms that the chief of staff is failing to reach out to the Republican Party's ''inside the Beltway'' network.</p>
        <p>Previous chiefs of staff, including Donald T. Regan, have sometimes been criticized as isolated and aloof. As a Washington newcomer with a reputation for abrasiveness, Mr. Sununu has made it plain that he has no intention of falling victim to such sniping.</p>
        <p>''Sununu isn't worried about the perception of being isolated - he's worried about the reality of it,'' said Eddie Mahe Jr., a Republican consultant on Mr. Sununu's list. ''Besides, you have a President who makes every effort not to be isolated; he's always on the phone. Sununu understands that if he's not aggressive, his boss will be ahead of him. Sununu has got to make his knowledge base as broad as the President's.''</p>
        <p>Charles Black, another Republican political consultant on the list, said the Reagan White House tended toward an even more informal approach: ''Occasionally I'd get a call asking, If Reagan called for A, B and C, how will it play in Florida and Texas?'' The Bush White House, Mr. Black said, has a formal arrangement for informal advice.</p>
        <p>''It's easy to get caught up in the job over there, and John wants to talk to people who are traveling around the country, talking to grass-roots Republicans, folks out there,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The list includes the President's five children as well as senior campaign aides like Lee Atwater, the chairman of the Republican National Committee, Craig Fuller and Roger Ailes as well as Washington political consultants like Richard Bond, Frank J. Donatelli, Peter Teeley and James Lake.</p>
        <p>These people are also on the list:  Robert Teeter, the campaign's poll taker, who is now a political consultant.  Mitchell E. Daniels Jr., a former White House political director who is now president of the Hudson Institute, a policy research group.  Linda DiVall, a Republican pollster.  Kenneth M. Duberstein, a White House chief of staff under Ronald Reagan.  Frederic V. Malek, a longtime friend of Mr. Bush's who worked in the Nixon White House and is now a Washington banker.  Frank J. Fahrenkopf Jr., former chairman of the Republican National Committee.</p>
        <p>''When I get a speech or message,'' said Mr. Malek, ''most of the time I read through it, think about it and send in a written response. I have been fairly candid with Sununu. I think that's what he wants.''</p>
        <p>Although most members of the group decline to disclose their advice to the chief of staff, several made it plain that they had sought to ring alarm bells after the Alaskan oil spill and had been disappointed at what they saw as a slow response by the White House. Others have suggested that Mr. Bush's proposal to rewrite the Clean Air Act is perhaps too costly and that with some lawmakers seeking tougher acid rain legislation, Mr. Bush will eventually have to ''pick his battles.''</p>
        <p>Although the list includes Washington power brokers, Mr. Sununu insists that his group is highly informed about what's going on ''in the hinterland,'' not just inside the Beltway.</p>
        <p>''I want to try and keep the communication going so that the President, the Presidency and the President's Administration doesn't become isolated,'' said Mr. Sununu. ''That's the worst thing that can happen: the only people you talk to are inside these four walls; we just echo-chamber on each other.''  WASHINGTON TALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
