<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Czechoslovakia's Opulent Spas</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="304186"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CZECHOSLOVAKIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FURIO, JOANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDA103DF935A15752C1A96F948260" item-length="2272" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Czechoslovakia's Opulent Spas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE FURIO; Joanne Furio is a writer who lives in Brooklyn.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FURIO, JOANNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: For centuries, Carlsbad and Marienbad - the German names for Czechoslovakia's most famous spa towns, Karlovy Vary and Marianske Lazne - drew Europe's most prominent political and artistic figures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: For centuries, Carlsbad and Marienbad - the German names for Czechoslovakia's most famous spa towns, Karlovy Vary and Marianske Lazne - drew Europe's most prominent political and artistic figures.</p>
        <p>For centuries, Carlsbad and Marienbad - the German names for Czechoslovakia's most famous spa towns, Karlovy Vary and Marianske Lazne - drew Europe's most prominent political and artistic figures.</p>
        <p>Both were blessed with a wealth of mineral springs, which lured patients seeking cures as well as the healthy, and both evolved into luxurious retreats and important cultural and economic centers.</p>
        <p>Situated in the northern, Bohemia, region, both towns are closer to today's East and West Germany than to the capital city of Prague, and throughout history have attracted a large German-speaking clientele.</p>
        <p>Elaborate spa buildings and colonnades sprung up to surround the privileged visitor with an atmosphere of architectural splendor. Merchants set up fancy shops, hotels and restaurants. And, to keep such a group entertained, music and theater festivals were established, attracting some of the most respected performers.</p>
        <p>Karlovy Vary and Marianske Lazne no longer attract royalty or the wealthy, but average citizens of the Eastern Bloc.</p>
        <p>Recognizing the towns' importance as tourist centers, the government has made an effort to maintain their historic significance by restoring many of the rich 18th- and 19th-century buildings. As a result, both towns offer some of the most luxurious accommodations for the money in Czechoslovakia. And, trying to keep up their cultural traditions, the spa towns continue to offer some of the country's best classical music performers, as well as those from other Eastern Bloc countries.</p>
        <p>The only things a Westerner might miss on visits to these towns are foreign newspapers and magazines and a varied selection of vegetables. Although both towns have fine restaurants with an abundance of meat-based dishes, a lettuce salad is somewhat of a luxury. How the recent tumult in Eastern Europe will affect Western tourism is, at this point, anybody's guess.</p>
        <p>Although completely different in scale and atmosphere, Karlovy Vary and Marianske Lazne have much in common.</p>
        <p>Each is set in a valley, framed by hills of pines with a complex of walking trails and views, and an abundance of natural springs, which are thermal in Karlovy Vary.</p>
        <p>Today, almost 90 percent of the visitors are from the Eastern Bloc, mostly from Czechoslovakia itself, whose numerous trade unions have provided its members with their own facilities, as well as East Germany and the Soviet Union. Only a handful come from England and the United States, although that, like so much else in Eastern Europe, may change.</p>
        <p>Impressive colonnades built during the 18th or 19th centuries adorn both town centers, where visitors line up at fountains to fill porcelain mugs with the mineral waters, which they sip almost hypnotically while strolling or basking in the sun.</p>
        <p>The mugs, designed with unusual hollow handles that act as straws, are purchased by patients before they begin their therapies.</p>
        <p>Although the middle-aged people who visit these towns do so for curative purposes, staying an average of three weeks at the sanitariums, or spa houses, the towns do welcome those who come only as tourists, usually staying for two or three days, as well as a large number of day-trippers, who visit the towns on excursions from Prague.</p>
        <p>But since many do come for a medical pilgrimage, the spas offer a feeling of quiet solemnity, even if their sidewalks are lined with pedestrians. For those who long for the fast-paced action of a city, these towns are not for them.</p>
        <p>Karlovy Vary is the largest spa in the country - almost a city. (On a pocket-sized map printed by the country's official tourist office, Cedok, Marianske Lazne is not even delineated.) Karlovy Vary is said to have been discovered by Emperor Charles IV, who, in 1347, stumbled into the waters while on a hunting expedition. Later, the town achieved even greater notoriety by attracting such prominent personalities as Peter the Great, the Austrian Emperor Josef II, Beethoven, Chopin, Paganini, Richard Wagner, Freud, Tolstoy, Goethe and Gogol.</p>
        <p>Surrounded by steep slopes that make the already majestic 19th-century buildings seem even more imposing, the spa district of Karlovy Vary conveys a comforting sense of envelopment that separates it from the gloomy urban areas surrounding it.</p>
        <p>Karlovy Vary is centered on the River Tepla, which meanders through the town. Shops selling leather, crystal, the country's renowned folk ceramics and spa porcelain mugs line the streets on both sides of the river.</p>
        <p>The river itself is a bit of a disappointment when not at its height. At times it resembles a stagnant pool shallow enough to allow ducks to bathe standing up, while on cool days its thermal waters at least provide an impressive display of evaporating steam.</p>
        <p>Besides its high temperatures, ranging from 86 to 162 degrees, the waters of Karlovy Vary are known for their high levels of sulfate of soda and carbonate of soda. Because of these properties, the spas specialize in treating disorders of the gastrointestinal tract and liver.</p>
        <p>Karlovy Vary appears to have attracted more American, West German and Arab tourists than Marianske Lazne, perhaps because it is larger, better known and older.</p>
        <p>From the outside, those who don't stay in the spa houses might assume that they are elegant old hotels, well-maintained in their original Beaux Arts or Greek Revival style. Most of their interiors reflect such old-time opulence, as well as a kind of squeaky-clean, hospital atmosphere. This is where the doctors have their offices to diagnose and prescribe the appropriate water dosages for the patients (up to one liter a day), as well as regimens that include exercise, bathing in the waters and special diets.</p>
        <p>Tourists can enjoy some of the perks offered by the spa houses, without making a three-week commitment. The 19th-century Grand Hotel Moskva, the most elegant complex in town, offers a sauna, massage, tanning room and small work-out room for those who seek some pampering.</p>
        <p>Even if one doesn't seek such indulgences, the Grand Hotel is worth a visit. Completed in 1893, the hotel boasts several restaurants, stained-glass ceilings and other turn-of-the-century finery, as well as a white-and-gold rococo concert hall, where both Dvorak and Smetana, native sons, played.</p>
        <p>Another important landmark is the casino, built in the late 19th century by the renowned Austrian design team of Helmer and Feller. Renovated in June 1988, the building houses spa facilities as well as a small casino operated by an Austrian firm.</p>
        <p>The casino, portrayed in advertisements as a Czech Monte Carlo, is usually almost empty, with only a few West German and Arab visitors playing at the three blackjack and roulette tables on a Friday night. But it is worth seeing its elaborate period architec-ture and furnishings, including a spectacular marble staircase, 100-foot-high glass-paneled ceiling, murals depicting ancient Greeks at play and golden wood-paneled walls.</p>
        <p>While the casino captures the feeling of Karlovy Vary past, the mood of the town today is best witnessed at its colonnades.</p>
        <p>The Greek revival Colonnade of Czechoslovak-Soviet Friendship, conspicuously renamed after the Russian invasion of 1968, is the most traditional, allowing patrons to stroll in the shadow of Corinthian columns and potted palms or sit on white wrought-iron benches along a parklike promenade.</p>
        <p>In contrast, the Colonnade Yuri Gagarin is a modern steel-and-glass structure with a glass-domed room containing the Vridlo spring, which shoots hot waters 50 feet into the air, and an enclosed promenade where patients line up to get their water from modern brass fountains.</p>
        <p>Karlovy Vary is the site of an international film festival every other year, most recently last summer, which does include some lesser-known Western productions, though none that would be considered controversial, and has its own orchestra, which regularly performs works by Smetana and Dvorak in the elegant yet badly deteriorated 19th-century theater.</p>
        <p>The town museum displays antique folk ceramics and old spa mugs, along with a roster of its famous visitors. Not far is the Museum Karl Marx, which provides a lesson in propaganda for the uninitiated.</p>
        <p>Also worth visiting is the sedate Dvorak Park, with its Victorian gazebo, and, on the outskirts of the city, the Russian Orthodox Church of the Chief Apostles Peter and Paul, the cathedral church of Russian Orthodoxy in Czechoslovakia, which was built in 1897 and has an impressive display of antique iconography.</p>
        <p>The town's famous Becherova, a minty herb liqueur created by the German-born Jan Becher, is worth a taste.</p>
        <p>Farther south and west of Karlovy Vary is Marianzke Lazne, a much cozier town whose amenities can easily be absorbed in a few days.</p>
        <p>Its parks are integrated into the town center, thanks to early 19th-century planners. The main street, the Trida Obdoraru, is lined with the principal hotels and shops, pastel-colored Beaux-Arts buildings with impressive gargoyles and classical reliefs. Across the street is a stream and a series of winding parks that work their way, like the rest of the town, up toward the main square, named after Klement Gottwald, a former head of state.</p>
        <p>On the square, whose center is a park and fountain, is the Kavkaz Spa, once the Hotel Weimer, where the spa's most famous visitor, King Edward VII, stayed during his many visits. Since the facility serves spa patients only, visitors can just glimpse the former King's favorite resort by walking into the marble lobby, framed by a double staircase and potted palms.</p>
        <p>Edward was also responsible for one of the town's proudest assets, its 18-hole golf course, which was opened in 1905 by the king himself. Situated just outside town, the course is the largest in the country. Adjacent to the Kavkaz Spa is the museum, which has been connected to the former vacation residence of another noted visitor, Goethe. The rooms where the poet lived have been meticulously maintained, and the building is the only one in town that hasn't been renovated. Goethe memorabilia and some of his writings decorate the rooms, as does shiny wooden furniture inlaid in the style of the period. In the modern half of the museum, the town's famous drinking mugs and images of prominent doctors and visitors, including Czar Nicholas II, Ibsen, Kipling, Mark Twain and Thomas Edison are displayed. An audio-visual museum program is available in English.</p>
        <p>Across from the museum is the 19th-century Ascension of Mary Catholic Church, somber on the outside, with an elaborate wood-and-marble altar trimmed in gold leaf inside.</p>
        <p>Not far from Gottwald Square is the aquatic center of town for spa patients, the Gorki Colonnade, with an elaborate glass-paned archway and Corinthian columns. At one end of the colonnade is a plain modern fountain that plays classical music at intervals.</p>
        <p>Like Karlovy Vary, Marianske Lazne has developed a healthy agenda of entertainment to keep patients occupied. There are two movie theaters, but even if they show Western films they are usually dubbed in Czech. Its well-preserved theater and casino are better bets, offering classical music programs performed by the town's own orchestra, visiting pop performers like the Czech singer Heidi, theater and dancing to native brass bands.</p>
        <p>Marianske Lazne has 39 mineral springs, famous for their carbon dioxide content, as well as iron, magnesium and calcium. Drinking cures are used here in conjunction with carbon-monoxide gas injections, diet and exercise regimens, to treat urinary tract and respiratory problems.</p>
        <p>The Polyclinic treats nonspa visitors, offering drinking cures, peat applications, massage and other therapies, after a medical consultation, ''Everything,'' according to the town's slogan, ''for the health of the working people.''  FINDING THE WAY TO THE SPA TOWNS  KARLOVY VAR</p>
        <p>The town is about 74 miles from Prague, a one-and-a-half-hour drive. Car rental is about $100 a day. Take highway 6 west.</p>
        <p>A two-and-a-half-hour bus ride, about $4, is preferable to the train, which, at $4.50, takes four-and-a-half hours. Plane service is also available from Prague International Airport for $12.  Sights  The Casino, in the Spa House (1 Vysina Imperial; 6 P.M. to 1 A.M.).</p>
        <p>Museum of Karlovy Vary (Dukelskych Hrdinu; Wednesday to Sunday 9 A.M. to noon and 2 to 5 P.M.). Admission 40 cents.</p>
        <p>Museum Karl Marx (Dukelskych Hrdinu; daily from 9 A.M. to noon). Free.</p>
        <p>Church of the Chief Apostles Peter and Paul (26 Petra Velikehom; April to September 9 A.M. to 6 P.M.). Free.  MARIANSKE LAZNE</p>
        <p>A 135-mile trip from Prague, reachable by following the route to Karlovy Vary, then heading south to highway 20, which turns into 24 and leads directly into the town.</p>
        <p>Both the train and the bus cost the same ($4.50) and take the same amount of time, about three hours. Trolleys or taxis must be taken to the center of town, at the cost of about 10 cents for the former and about 25 cents for the latter, after telephoning from the station, a difficulty for those who don't speak Czech or German.  Sights</p>
        <p>Museum Marianske Lazne (Gottwald Square; daily 9 A.M. to noon and 2 to 5 P.M.). Admission 40 cents.</p>
        <p>Casino (between Trida Rude Armady and Dusikova; gambling from 6 P.M. to 1 A.M.).</p>
        <p>Theater Marianske Lazne (Trebizskeho; evening and weekend performances).</p>
        <p>Dining</p>
        <p>Most of the hotels have their own restaurants. Neither spa town has many independent restaurants.</p>
        <p>Foreign wines are more than double the price of fine wines from the southern, Slovak republic. Prices range from $10 to $25 for dinner for two with Slovak wine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
