<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Washington Talk: Congressional Budget Office; At Helm, a Centrist Respected by His Foes</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="231225"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONGRESSIONAL BUDGET OFFICE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENBAUM, DAVID E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REISCHAUER, ROBERT D (DIR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REISCHAUER, ROBERT D (BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON TALK PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890313T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DA133AF930A25750C0A96F948260" item-length="1026" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Washington Talk: Congressional Budget Office; At Helm, a Centrist Respected by His Foes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. ROSENBAUM, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENBAUM, DAVID E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Economists tend to be a quarrelsome lot, dogmatic in their own opinions and disdainful of colleagues who disagree.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Economists tend to be a quarrelsome lot, dogmatic in their own opinions and disdainful of colleagues who disagree.</p>
        <p>Economists tend to be a quarrelsome lot, dogmatic in their own opinions and disdainful of colleagues who disagree.</p>
        <p>That is why it is so remarkable that economists across this city, liberals and conservatives, those who work for business and those in labor unions, express such regard for Robert D. Reischauer, the new director of the Congressional Budget Office.</p>
        <p>''His political persuasion is to the moderate wing from mine,'' said Stuart M. Butler, the director of domestic policy studies at the Heritage Foundation, where many of Ronald Reagan's economic policies were developed. ''But I admire his professional objectivity. He is the kind of person who is highly respected by people like me who disagree with him.''</p>
        <p>''He will give a fair hearing to any point of view,'' said Robert Greenstein, a Carter Administration official who formed the Center on Budget and Policy Priorities eight years ago to fight the Reagan policies. Mr. Greenstein credits Mr. Reischauer with persuading him that the budget deficit could not be eliminated merely by raising taxes and reducing military spending and that some domestic programs had to be cut as well.</p>
        <p>''Bob has had more influence on my thinking than anyone else in Washington in the last three years,'' Mr. Greenstein added. Squarely in the Middle</p>
        <p>One reason Mr. Reischauer is able to operate so smoothly across the political spectrum is that his own views as an economist are so squarely in the middle. Mr. Greenstein calls him ''the pre-eminent centrist.'' Mr. Reischauer himself classifies his economic beliefs as ''eclectic, neither Keynesian nor monetarist nor neoclassicist but a touch of all of the above.''</p>
        <p>''I'm a believer in the efficacy of fiscal policy and the importance of monetary policy, although both have their limitations at different points in the business cycle,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In his new job, he said he hoped ''to present a mainstream view of how the economy is doing and where it's going.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reischauer, who is 48 years old, seems to have been in training most of his professional life to be director of the Congressional Budget Office, one of the most influential staff positions in Congress. Matching Executive Expertise</p>
        <p>Congress created the office in the mid-1970's to provide the legislative branch with economic expertise equivalent to that available to the executive branch. The director is Congress's chief economist and administers a staff of about 200 professionals.</p>
        <p>The first step that Alice M. Rivlin took after she was sworn in as the first director of the new agency in 1975 was to sign up Mr. Reischauer to be her special assistant. So Mr. Reischauer was, in his words, ''present at the creation,'' and with Mrs. Rivlin he was instrumental in turning the office into a respected, nonpartisan assayer and forecaster of economic statistics and trends.</p>
        <p>In economic circles, he is known more as a solid analyst than as an innovative thinker. ''I don't know of anyone who has a better grasp of the numbers in the budget,'' said Stanley E. Collender, a budget specialist at Price Waterhouse, the accounting firm.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reischauer stayed at the agency six years, rising to be assistant director and, for his last two years, deputy director. In 1981 he left to become senior vice president at the Urban Institute, a research organization, where he was especially admired for his administrative abilities. In 1986 he moved to the Brookings Institution as a senior fellow to continue work on his academic specialty, social welfare policy. Role in Dukakis Campaign</p>
        <p>Last year, he was a part-time adviser in Gov. Michael S. Dukakis's Presidential campaign and helped develop the proposal by the Massachusetts Governor for student loans that would be paid back through small deductions from the borrowers' pay for many years after graduation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reischauer has been under consideration for the directorship of the budget office ever since Rudolph G. Penner resigned two years ago. The job remained vacant because because of political differences between Senate and House leaders.</p>
        <p>Those disagreements were set aside this year. The new Democratic chairmen of the House and Senate Budget committees, Representative Leon E. Panetta of California and Senator Jim Sasser of Tennessee, quickly settled on Mr. Reischauer, and the announcement was made earlier this month.</p>
        <p>The most pressing budget issue to many is the Federal deficit, and Mr. Reischauer rejects any notion that the deficit is not a serious problem. ''I can't say it's dangerous over the next 12 or 24 months,'' he said. ''But if you run big deficits year after year, you're going to have a lower standard of living 5 or 10 or 15 years out.'' Ways Around the Problem</p>
        <p>In an academic paper he prepared for a symposium last fall, Mr. Reischauer said that year-to-year changes in spending and tax policies might not be enough to eliminate the deficit and that fundamental structural changes might be required.</p>
        <p>One possible change, he suggested, was to raise specific taxes for which the revenue would be earmarked to expand politically popular programs, freeing the revenue now spent on those programs to reduce the deficit.</p>
        <p>A gasoline or energy tax might be used to support environmental programs and expanded measures for curbing acid rain. A national sales tax might pay for Medicare, Medicaid and medical insurance for those not now covered.</p>
        <p>''Clearly, it would take a number of years to develop a consensus around any such major policy shift,'' Mr. Reischauer wrote. But ''structural reforms hold out some promise'' for producing ''a budget surplus in the late 1990's.''</p>
        <p>When he was tapped for his new position, Mr. Reischauer was two-thirds finished writing a book about poverty and the underclass. At first, he said, he thought he would be able to complete the book by writing nights and weekends, but after a week on the job he is not sure he will have time.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, he is delighted to be back in the Congressional Budget Office. ''The topics you deal with,'' he said, ''are the most interesting in town for people interested in policy analysis and applied economics.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
