<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Earth to NASA</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="278692"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREEN, BILL (REPR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">OP-ED</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFDB1E3FF934A1575BC0A96F948260" item-length="705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Earth to NASA</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bill Green; Bill Green, Republican of New York, serves on the House appropriations subcommittee, which funds NASA.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREEN, BILL (REPR)</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Voyager 2 is heading for the stars after transmitting to Earth a vast treasure of scientific information about the distant planets of our solar system. Simultaneously, another space probe is on its way to Venus to learn why a planet so near and similar in size to Earth suffers 900 degree temperatures underneath its veil of sulfur rain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Voyager 2 is heading for the stars after transmitting to Earth a vast treasure of scientific information about the distant planets of our solar system. Simultaneously, another space probe is on its way to Venus to learn why a planet so near and similar in size to Earth suffers 900 degree temperatures underneath its veil of sulfur rain.</p>
        <p>Voyager 2 is heading for the stars after transmitting to Earth a vast treasure of scientific information about the distant planets of our solar system. Simultaneously, another space probe is on its way to Venus to learn why a planet so near and similar in size to Earth suffers 900 degree temperatures underneath its veil of sulfur rain. No one is aboard either craft; no one is needed.</p>
        <p>During the Apollo moon shots two decades ago, the idea of a man on the moon was deliriously exciting. Today, such ''go-man-go'' gestures as placing men on the Moon (again) and on Mars should be set aside for more valuable and less costly earth and planetary sciences.</p>
        <p>We can't afford manned missions. The National Aeronautic and Space Administration's planned manned space station will cost $30 billion. Manned missions to the Moon and Mars would triple the agency's annual budget, now at $10.6 billion.</p>
        <p>When NASA pushes manned space operations, more valuable scientific work tends to take a back door. Emotionally, the Apollo moon mission may have been a giant step for mankind, but it was not a scientific stepping stone for the space program. Subsequently, the manned shuttle has eaten most of NASA's budget every year since its inception.</p>
        <p>NASA claims that, to insure funding, men in space are needed to excite the public. Really? The Hubble telescope planned for launch in 1990 will see light emitted from stars 15 billion years ago - near the time of the surmised birth of our universe. It will be followed by a series of satellites, including the Cosmic Background Explorer, seeking radiation left from the theorized ''Big Bang'' creation of the universe. Not too shabby.</p>
        <p>Within our galaxy, pictures sent by Voyager 2 have enthralled laymen and scientists. Magellan, heading toward Venus, and the future probe, Galileo, will also teach us without the expense of taking fragile humans along for the ride. Within Earth's immediate orbit, most scientific work planned for the space station could be done on a less expensive platform, only occasionally tended by humans.</p>
        <p>And on our planet, there is extremely valuable work for NASA to do in its program, ''Mission to Planet Earth.'' ''Mission'' is to be an Earth observation system in space performing integrated, long-term measurements of such processes as wind movement and ocean temperatures. We already know we have an endangered environment; what we need to know now is how the air, water and land function and what the technical problems are. Ground-level studies must be coordinated with long-term space surveillance.</p>
        <p>In fact, the NASA Advisory Council's Earth Systems Science Committee proposed such a holistic approach ''to obtain a scientific understanding of the entire Earth system.'' It said we need to ''develop the capability to predict those changes that will occur, in the next decade to the next century, both naturally and in response to human activity.''</p>
        <p>A major Earth science satellite is slated for launching in late 1995. It was paired with the space station as a package of funding, but the consensus of House subcommittee members is to fund the environmental platform even if the budget squeeze restricts the space station's development.</p>
        <p>In addition, NASA's latest budget proposal contains some funding for small, specialized missions to study the complex chemistry of the stratosphere and mesosphere, helping us learn about the causes of ozone depletion. The subcommittee will propose a tropical rain measuring mission, an important element to understanding global weather systems and assessing the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>These Earth missions and others projected for the future depend on the support of the full Congress and the White House, and restraint on manned projects. Currently, Congress is split between advocates of science and ''go-man-go.'' I hope the White House does not expect funding for manned flights to other heavenly bodies in the near future and that NASA scales down its $30 billion manned space station until needed science projects are secured.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, with Magellan on its way to Venus to study sulfur rain and great heat, the space agency can help prevent Earth from turning into that sultry planet's environmental twin.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
