<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="298798"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7DA1239F93BA35752C1A96F948260" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-15  The East German Cabinet resigned in testimony to the scale of the crisis that has seized the state under the pressure of mass demonstrations and mass flight. A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-15  The East German Cabinet resigned in testimony to the scale of the crisis that has seized the state under the pressure of mass demonstrations and mass flight. A1</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-15  The East German Cabinet resigned in testimony to the scale of the crisis that has seized the state under the pressure of mass demonstrations and mass flight. A1</p>
        <p>Flow to West continues A12</p>
        <p>With German ferment, Prague is increasingly isolated A12</p>
        <p>U.S. scholars assess German situation A13</p>
        <p>In Moscow, an alternative parade was staged by thousands of political dissenters on the 72d anniversary of the Bolshevik Revolution, a holiday that has traditionally been a celebration of Soviet rule. A1</p>
        <p>Washington Talk: The summit between Presidents Bush and Gorbachev next month should mostly focus on Eastern Europe's political maelstrom, but both leaders will also have other agendas to satisfy. A20</p>
        <p>Accord to limit carbon dioxide is prevented A8</p>
        <p>Long-range arms pact for next year is called unlikely A11</p>
        <p>Namibia had a large turnout in its election of delegates who will draft a constitution that will come into force when independence is declared, probably next year. A3</p>
        <p>In Benazir Bhutto's 11-month tenure as Pakistan's Prime Minister, many people have become disappointed with her Government and its lack of success in combating poverty and other problems. A10</p>
        <p>Indian leftists hope to gain a bigger role A9</p>
        <p>China has imposed a crackdown on non-state enterprises, closing more than a million rural industrial collectives and forcing the demise of 2.2 million private enterprises. A3</p>
        <p>Consumers pay dearly in Japan D6</p>
        <p>U.S.-Iran financial disputes should be settled to begin improving relations and possibly pave the way for the release of American hostages in Lebanon, U.S. officials said. A14</p>
        <p>Lebanon Cabinet talks open A6</p>
        <p>Israel requests police trials in killing on West Bank A7</p>
        <p>Honduras shifts; will attend Nicaragua talks A15</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A18-28, B10-11  L. Douglas Wilder appeared to have eked out a narrow victory for the governorship of Virginia, on the basis of almost complete but unofficial returns. A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: Black candidates showed in yesterday's elections that a deliberate style, experience in office and a knack for turning minority status into an asset could constitute a formula for victory. A1</p>
        <p>Four Senators tried to stop a rule that would have prevented certain risky investments by Lincoln Savings, an ex-Federal regulator said. The Senators had received campaign funds from the head of the institution. D1</p>
        <p>Agreement on raising debt ceiling D1</p>
        <p>Capital unruffled by latest uproar over Mayor A20</p>
        <p>Conferees strive for accord on Medicare plan A28</p>
        <p>Senate debates independent C.I.A. inspector A22</p>
        <p>F.B.I. chief defends acts on librarians A21</p>
        <p>Catholics cannot support the idea of ''choice'' to defend legal access to abortion, Roman Catholic bishops warned in a message apparently aimed at Catholic politicians who do not want to restrict the choice of others. A18</p>
        <p>Illinois prosecutor asks role in abortion case A18</p>
        <p>A child-abuse case was presented to the Supreme Court in which the Justices must weigh a parent's right against compelled self-incrimination against the Government's ability to investigate suspected abuse. A18</p>
        <p>Brockton journal: city reflects on police chief's arrest A18</p>
        <p>Two Israeli soldiers are killed testing Howitzer in Arizona A26</p>
        <p>Bonds rise on sign of Fed easing D1</p>
        <p>Braniff puts itself on auction block D1</p>
        <p>REGIONAL B1-10  David Dinkins won the mayoralty of New York City, building on near-unanimous support from black New Yorkers and the votes of one out of three whites. He becomes the city's first black mayor. A1</p>
        <p>Man in the news: David Dinkins B7</p>
        <p>Win by Dinkins prompts dancing and skepticism B8</p>
        <p>Excerpts from speech by Dinkins: a new link B8</p>
        <p>James Florio won election as Governor of New Jersey in a lopsided victory as voters rejected his opponent's promises to fight crime, taxes and big government. A1</p>
        <p>Man in the news: James Florio B9</p>
        <p>Democrats win the Assembly in New Jersey B9</p>
        <p>The New York City charter proposal was approved by voters. The plan represents the largest overhaul of the city's government since its formation in 1898. B1</p>
        <p>A new generation of leaders has gained seats on the Board of Estimate. They include a group of liberals who have been allied in criticizing many of the Koch administration's programs. B1</p>
        <p>Rules against AIDS-related bias have been expanded to protect people who are mistakenly believed to carry the virus that causes the disease and carriers of the virus who are not yet ill, advocacy groups say. B3</p>
        <p>Six D.M.V. clerks convicted for racketeering scheme B2</p>
        <p>The New York Times announced plans to close its northern New Jersey printing plant. D1</p>
        <p>Housing foe elected Mayor in Yonkers B1</p>
        <p>New Haven picks first black Mayor B10</p>
        <p>Gulotta defeats Korn for Nassau Executive B10</p>
        <p>Finding a home for New Jersey's dead leaves B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
