<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INSIDE</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="273587"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D91330F93BA3575BC0A96F948260" item-length="190" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INSIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  Polish Political Skirmish Citing a ''crisis of confidence,'' Lech Walesa urged two small parties aligned with the ruling Communists to defect and help form a Solidarity-led coalition Government. Page A3.  Acid Rain and Maya Ruins  Archeologists say pollution from Mexican refineries is damaging Maya sites, and they fear the peril will spread to rain forests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  Polish Political Skirmish Citing a ''crisis of confidence,'' Lech Walesa urged two small parties aligned with the ruling Communists to defect and help form a Solidarity-led coalition Government. Page A3.  Acid Rain and Maya Ruins  Archeologists say pollution from Mexican refineries is damaging Maya sites, and they fear the peril will spread to rain forests.</p>
        <p>Polish Political Skirmish Citing a ''crisis of confidence,'' Lech Walesa urged two small parties aligned with the ruling Communists to defect and help form a Solidarity-led coalition Government. Page A3.  Acid Rain and Maya Ruins  Archeologists say pollution from Mexican refineries is damaging Maya sites, and they fear the peril will spread to rain forests. Page C1.  Bailout and the Consumer  The costly savings-industry rescue will eventually affect millions of Americans, but the most immediate impact may be lower interest rates in the most distressed areas. Page D1.  Voting Rights, Part 2  Whites in Birmingham, Ala., and two Mississippi towns have used the Voting Rights Act of 1965 to challenge at-large voting systems. Page A10.  Giant Instrument, Tiny Goal  The largest scientific instrument yet built, the European Large Electron-Positron Collider, has come to life and started its search for tiny particles. Page C1.  Japan Party Elects Leader  Japan's ruling party selected Toshiki Kaifu to become the next Prime Minister. He has the task of rescuing the party from Scandal. Page A9.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
