<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hands Across the Water</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="63" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="238644"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="EX MACHINA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPECIAL SECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMMUNICATIONS SATELLITES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CULTURAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PETER H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cultural Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D6113CF93AA35757C0A96F948260" item-length="1168" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hands Across the Water</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter H. Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PETER H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Students from kindergarten to graduate school are beginning to use computers and communications satellites to break down cultural and geographical barriers while fostering greater awareness of the interdependent world and their own roles in it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Students from kindergarten to graduate school are beginning to use computers and communications satellites to break down cultural and geographical barriers while fostering greater awareness of the interdependent world and their own roles in it.</p>
        <p>Students from kindergarten to graduate school are beginning to use computers and communications satellites to break down cultural and geographical barriers while fostering greater awareness of the interdependent world and their own roles in it.</p>
        <p>For example, several hundred students and faculty from Tufts University in Massachusetts and Moscow State University will get together in class April 22 to discuss environmental problems shared by the superpowers, including global warming, acid rain and ozone depletion. Two-way television signals beamed via a satellite nearly 23,000 miles in space, along with simultaneous translation, will enable the students to discuss issues as if they were in the same lecture hall.</p>
        <p>''By exposing students in the United States directly to the viewpoints of students in other countries, and vice versa, the traditional cultural filtration of information is minimized,'' said Dr. Martin J. Sherwin, director of Tufts University's Nuclear Age History and Humanities Center. The effect, he said, is to truly internationalize the teaching of international relations.</p>
        <p>In the last year, Soviet and American students have met ''face to face'' via satellite at Tufts seven times to discuss issues such as the 1962 Cuban missile crisis, the effects of the nuclear threat on art, literature and culture, and the limited nuclear test ban treaty of 1963. Future classes will address North-South relations (between industrialized and developing nations) and the global economy.</p>
        <p>As a measure of the importance the Soviet Union places on the exchanges, the Moscow State classes are instructed by Evgeny P. Velikhov, vice president of the Soviet Academy of Sciences and one of Mikhail Gorbachev's principal scientific advisers.</p>
        <p>Such international dialogues are not limited to higher education. In another example of multinational cooperation, Apple Computer Inc. is designing a network that will enable elementary and secondary students and teachers in dozens of countries to exchange information and conduct joint research projects using personal computers.</p>
        <p>Once connected to the Apple Global Education network, schools equipped with a Macintosh computer, a modem and an Applelink electronic-mail address will be able to share pen-pal letters, scientific data, computer graphics, video images and even musical compositions with any other school on the network, all at the touch of a keyboard. A class in Guam might compare weather data with an Inuit school in Canada. A school in Puerto Rico might study heritage issues with a school in Spain.</p>
        <p>Among the proposals made to Apple so far are projects that would initiate regular dialogues on current world events or conflict resolution, the establishment of a mock United Nations, a chess tournament, an attempt to measure the speed of light and, from Lyons, France, an international culinary project that would gather favorite recipes from participants' hometowns. One American high school, Croton-Harmon in Westchester County, applying to join the Apple network has already proposed an international project ''to reanalyze and re-prove the Erastosthenes earth-circumference experiment, using the angles of the sun's rays on a particular date and at a particular time to provide trigonometric data from various paired sites'' at the opposite ends of the earth. Using computers and telecommunications, students can get hands-on experience with geophysical studies that until recently were merely abstract ideas, or that were logistically impossible for a single school.</p>
        <p>Although the Tufts and Apple efforts involve a relatively small number of schools, they show the potential of technology in global education. Hundreds of American campuses already have their own satellite facilities, and hundreds more have access to satellite technology through local television stations. As satellite technology becomes cheaper, more miniaturized and more reliable, it is conceivable that universities, high schools and even elementary schools will someday participate in global video networks.</p>
        <p>Currently, Tufts must lease time on a commercial communications satellite, which is costly. Jean Mayer, president of Tufts, has proposed that three communications satellites, enough to cover all parts of the globe from geosynchronous orbit, be launched and devoted strictly to academics.</p>
        <p>On the ground, the development of ''flyaway'' or portable satellite-transmitting dishes for sending signals from remote locations hold the promise of breaking down classroom walls. An agricultural-science professor might broadcast a lesson from a pest-infested field in Africa to a class at Iowa State University, for example. Conversely, agriculture students in Zaire might someday sit in on classes on pest management at Iowa State. Up to now, truckloads of unwieldy equipment have been required to send signals via satellite.</p>
        <p>Dissemination of expertise in virtually any academic discipline is possible. Medical schools in the United States could record broadcasts on new Soviet techniques in eye surgery. Master classes in music might be beamed to several schools from the home of an American virtuoso unable to travel. Economics students might be able to interview directly the finance officials of third-world nations for their perspective on debt.</p>
        <p>Apple's ambitious plan to link at least one school in every nation seems limited more by politics and cost than by technology. There are technical difficulties to overcome, to be sure. Telephone service is erratic in many countries, and many villages have never seen a Macintosh computer. But in this age, when an American business executive driving down Highway 101 in California can use a cellular car telephone to call his computer at the office in Chicago and order it by remote control to send a document to a fax machine on a yacht sailing in the Caribbean, technology seems to be a minor hurdle.</p>
        <p>''We expect to have 50 to 60 sites up and running with Applelink addresses by fall,'' said Dr. Martin Engel, education manager with an advanced technology group at Apple Computer Inc., who has traveled extensively in recent months to coordinate the project. ''I envision 1,000 schools by 1992.'' Dr. Engel said that connecting Moscow and Beijing to the network was another goal.</p>
        <p>Dr. Engel said his travels had made him aware that English is becoming the international language of science and technology. In addition, he said, ''English will be the common language'' for communicating on the Apple Global Education network. One major application of the network is expected to be language instruction.</p>
        <p>Schools interested in applying to join the network must make a proposal to their local Apple dealers, who in turn will relay the application to Apple headquarters. The school must obtain a Macintosh computer, a modem and communications software and have access to a telephone line. Dr. Engel said many schools might be able to get the equipment through donations from dealers or private sources.</p>
        <p>EX MACHINA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
