<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CRIME/MYSTERY</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="290810"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PARETSKY, SARA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HALL, JAMES W</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">TROPICAL FREEZE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D61639F936A25753C1A96F948260" item-length="788" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CRIME/MYSTERY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAPARETSKY; Sara Paretsky is the author of ''Blood Shot,'' a mystery.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PARETSKY, SARA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  TROPICAL FREEZE  By James W. Hall.  319 pp. New York:  W. W. Norton &amp; Company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  TROPICAL FREEZE  By James W. Hall.  319 pp. New York:  W. W. Norton &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>TROPICAL FREEZE  By James W. Hall.  319 pp. New York:  W. W. Norton &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Americans romanticize the loner. Our fictional heroes are self-sufficient men, close to nature, who turn to nature for help instead of other people. James Fenimore Cooper's Natty Bumppo provided the model; his descendants include Huck Finn, the Virginian and Shane. These men understand the spirit of justice - in contrast to a corrupt civilization obsessed with the letter of the law.</p>
        <p>Joining this stalwart crew is Thorn, who made his debut in 1987 in James W. Hall's ''Under Cover of Daylight'' and returns now in ''Tropical Freeze.'' Thorn lives the quiet, spare life of his fictional predecessors. He has never carried a driver's license, never registered for Social Security; he's rebuilding his Key Largo house from found wood, so that no trees will be destroyed to create his home. Near the end of the book, hallucinating from loss of blood, he conjures up wolves and moose for emotional strength.</p>
        <p>Thorn is reluctantly drawn from his seclusion into the problems of his childhood friend Gaeton Richards. Like Thorn, Gaeton is a true conch - the local name for a native - but he went off to Miami to become an F.B.I. agent. Now he works for the millionaire security consultant Benny Cousins.</p>
        <p>We first meet Benny when, as he smuggles a man named Claude into Florida, he casually shoots a couple of teen-age drug dealers using his chosen secluded port. Who Claude is and what becomes of him are part of a tortuous triple-cross between Benny and the F.B.I. To say more would spoil the ending.</p>
        <p>Benny is short, plump and ungainly; he desperately wants to be a conch himself. Benny thinks he can buy his way into the hearts of the natives. Unfortunately, many of them prove him right. Benny's goal is to be a latter-day Hemingway, tough enough to stand up to danger of any kind.</p>
        <p>Benny isn't the only person in ''Tropical Freeze'' haunted by Hemingway's ghost. A major subplot of the novel involves Papa John, a Hemingway buff and owner of the derelict Bomb Bay Bar, who tries to groom a cheap punk named Ozzie to become the son and heir he never had.</p>
        <p>Poor Ozzie, confused by Papa John into thinking he should be killing people, and almost dying of longing for a television weatherwoman in Miami named Darcy Richards, gets himself hired by Benny as a hit man. And that's when the action really heats up.</p>
        <p>Darcy grew up in Key Largo, tagging along behind Thorn and her big brother, Gaeton. Despite the Miami job, Darcy is also a true conch, and like Thorn is an elemental, natural person. She can tell a winter storm is coming because of ''something like the tartness of green apples in the back of the throat, a quiet burn in the sinuses.''</p>
        <p>When Gaeton is murdered, Darcy knows it from some sense of disturbance in the order of nature. She gets Thorn to help her find his body, but sets out alone to avenge his death. Hampered by Ozzie, who wants to kill him because of his affair with Darcy, Thorn works out his own separate path of vengeance; he meets up with Darcy at the end of the road, where they achieve a small measure of justice.</p>
        <p>Because ''Tropical Freeze'' comes out of the American heroic tradition, characters and events are idealized. Sometimes they tax the reader's credulity. Gaeton's dead body, left overnight in a Florida canal, doesn't rot. Thorn, although wounded, performs heroic deeds. Darcy shows no scars from her breast-reduction surgery, and when her jaw is badly broken she still discourses at length on her philosophy of life.</p>
        <p>There is, too, an unsettling difference between Thorn and the giants of yore. When the Virginian or Shane finished with Trampas or with Wilson and Fletcher, we knew a wind had swept the mountains clean, that Justice with a large ''J'' was restored.</p>
        <p>James Hall is too aware of the bitter realities of our day to allow Thorn and Darcy so happy an ending. ''Though Thorn knew the carbon dioxide fumes and the methane and the ozone and all the rest of it had not been blown very far away, and though he was certain the pollution was already beginning to mount up again, still, for a while, the sky would be fresh. And for those few days he and Darcy . . . would be able to feast on that good rich air, breathing again the way they were always meant to breathe.'' Thorn gets a respite, but no lasting peace.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall wrote poetry before turning to thrillers; passages like these reflect his poetic voice and set ''Tropical Freeze'' apart from the usual sex-and-violence fare. If the action is sometimes unbelievable, it really doesn't matter: Mr. Hall's lyrical passion for the Florida Keys, his spare language and unusual images haunt us long after the story has faded.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
