<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Delhi Journal; Shiny Tomorrow Meets Ragged, Hungry Today</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19890713T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="263306"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RURAL AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOLAR ENERGY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DAYAL, MAHESHWAR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CROSSETTE, BARBARA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rural Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFDE1E3EF930A35754C0A96F948260" item-length="1103" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Delhi Journal; Shiny Tomorrow Meets Ragged, Hungry Today</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CROSSETTE, BARBARA</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, July 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A haunting video documentary making the unofficial rounds here chronicles a community's psychological progression from bewilderment through awakening to defiance as it realizes it is about to be displaced by a missile site.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A haunting video documentary making the unofficial rounds here chronicles a community's psychological progression from bewilderment through awakening to defiance as it realizes it is about to be displaced by a missile site.</p>
        <p>A haunting video documentary making the unofficial rounds here chronicles a community's psychological progression from bewilderment through awakening to defiance as it realizes it is about to be displaced by a missile site.</p>
        <p>For the un-self-conscious participants in the film, ''Voices From Baliapore,'' the missile has become their introduction to high technology, and it threatens everything familiar. Baliapore is a city on India's east coast.</p>
        <p>India produces rockets, cars, computers, television sets and refrigerators in half a dozen colors. But as recent statistics from the Asian Development Bank show, India also harbors a larger and larger proportion of the world's poorest people, the majority of them illiterate, vulnerable to epidemic diseases and forced to live without lighting, clean water or rudimentary communication links to other Indians.</p>
        <p>Bridging the gap is not merely a material problem any more, say some experts in government and the private think tanks. Alienation grows as technology expands, and the singularly Indian model of austerity and unashamed simplicity exemplified by Mohandas K. Gandhi fades from public life. Unorthodox Approaches</p>
        <p>At the same time, the flow of information is often restricted by bureaucrats who have learned to wield it, and their literacy, as tools of power against the disadvantaged.</p>
        <p>Among the Indian philosopher-technocrats looking for ways to bring an understanding of science along with its benefits down to village level are two influential civil servants with unorthodox approaches.</p>
        <p>Maheshwar Dayal, a pioneer in nuclear technology who built India's first atomic reactor at Tarapur, now works full time promoting solar power and other simpler technologies as head of the Department of Nonconventional Energy Sources.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dayal, who in the last five years has brought solar-powered electricity to at least 5,000 poor villages - as well as solar water heaters to the hotels and hospitals of New Delhi - thinks new development strategies and economic policies to buttress them at local levels are required.</p>
        <p>''Development needs a change in focus, with not so much of it coming from the top,'' said Mr. Dayal, a former chairman of Unesco's science commission. He added that when development costs are calculated, some not-so-obvious factors need to be considered - for instance, how much environmental damage will be prevented by a project or how much time women will save for pursuits more useful, health-enhancing or lucrative for them than simple daily chores. These add real value to modest projects, or, viewed another way, reduce the costs.</p>
        <p>People at local level will be less fearful of technology if it works for them, perhaps with their involvement through small investments, he said. He described a village in Rajasthan where he introduced solar-powered lighting. 'Light Into Our World'</p>
        <p>''They never had any lights in their history,'' he said. ''They were so delighted. They told me: 'You have literally brought light into our world.' ''</p>
        <p>''Their days are longer,'' he said. ''They can read and study after work. They can have a farmers' literacy program at the end of the day. Doctors can treat the sick at night.'</p>
        <p>''Solar systems can also be used for cooking, crop-drying, stills and kilns,'' Mr. Dayal said in an interview in his office, where the electrical equipment runs on photovoltaic cells outside his windows.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dayal's department, which encourages industrial production of appliances run on renewable energy sources, is experimenting with solar-powered batteries for city buses. They can also run on electricity generated from city garbage.</p>
        <p>''Energy plantations'' of fast-growing trees are being sowed to mitigate the annual loss of 3.7 million acres of forest. In addition, 1.2 million rural families have been switched to bio-gas cooking, using wood and animal wastes.</p>
        <p>Satyen Gangaram Pitroda, a technology adviser to Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi and the chairman of a new telecommunications commission charged with improving the flow of information in the world's second most populous country, believes that too many Indians are unnecessarily afraid of technology. Technology and Tension</p>
        <p>''In a traditional society like ours, whenever you talk of technology, you create tension,'' said Mr. Pitroda, who worked as a businessman in Chicago for more than two decades. Indian-born, he recently renounced his American citizenship and resumed his Indian nationality.</p>
        <p>''The message of technology has not has not been understood properly,'' he said, ''Technology is always seen as something elite, urban, modern, exotic, fancy - foreign.''</p>
        <p>''Technology doesn't have to be that,'' he went on. ''Technology could be down to earth, rural, very docile, user-friendly.''</p>
        <p>''Take, for example, satellite imagery,'' he said. ''We use satellite imagery for finding water sources. We can tell village people that's the highest technology used for a mundane thing like water.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pitroda recently annoyed officials and business leaders by vetoing plans to import mobile telephone systems.</p>
        <p>''For every three car phones, I can provide communication to one village,'' he said. ''Shouldn't we do that first?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pitroda is fascinated by how information is handled in India. Which 100,000 Villages?  ''I'll give you a classic example,'' he said. ''We were told that we had to provide water to 100,000 villages. But no one would tell us which 100,000. You could never pin anybody down. It took us one year to get a list of names of waterless villages from the system. Nobody wants to give you names because information is power, and information also brings about accountability. As soon as you share information you pinpoint accountability.''</p>
        <p>He recalls how he had to turn to Unicef during a drought to find out how many well-drilling rigs India had. Tradition, local politics and social status all get in the way of information-sharing. The underprivileged suffer.</p>
        <p>''If today you and I had to go and get a land record for a piece of property that my father or grandfather owned in this country, it would be a hell of a problem,'' he said, ''It would take a year, and you've got to hassle with 10 fellows. All the records are manually documented. They could be modernized, computerized through technology.''</p>
        <p>''But as soon as you computerize,'' he said, ''you break the power of the village patwaris, who are a strong vested interest. They write the documents so that no one else can read them. They have power over the village because they own all the documents. One day, our computers will open that whole system.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 13, 1989, Thursday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>Because of a transmission error, an article on July 3 about technology in India misidentified a documentary about a community's realization that it is about to be replaced by a missile site. The title is ''Voices From Baliapal,'' not Baliapore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 13, 1989, Thursday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>Because of a transmission error, an article on July 3 about technology in India misidentified a documentary about a community's realization that it is about to be replaced by a missile site. The title is ''Voices From Baliapal,'' not Baliapore.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
