<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bottom-Line Thinking Won't Save Our Climate; Solar Thermal Machines</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="305180"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFDE1539F933A05752C1A96F948260" item-length="356" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bottom-Line Thinking Won't Save Our Climate; Solar Thermal Machines</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Governments Start Preparing for Global Warming Disasters'' (Science Times, Nov. 14) echoes the common sentiment that since the world economy runs on fossil fuels, we may as well give up on the idea of reducing carbon dioxide, the greenhouse gas, and prepare for survival on a hot planet. But there are lots of things we can do to reduce the generation of carbon dioxide and other bad things like chlorofluorocarbons, if we could muster the collective guts.</p>
        <p>One of the most accessible of these alternatives is solar thermal power, generated not by exotic silicon wafers, but by prosaic but efficient piston or turbine machines. Unlike the much better known silicon cells, solar thermal machines are simple, old-style technology, about as complicated as auto or aircraft engines. And so little effort has yet been put into them that they are susceptible to rapid improvements in their good performance and to reduction in their reasonable cost. An achievable near-term target is $1,000 per installed kilowatt, about the same as power from local or nuclear plants, but without their huge external costs.</p>
        <p>If we could gather the collective will, we could supply, carbon-dioxide free, all of the energy this country needs for transport, industry, domestic heating - everything from an area of our Southwestern desert about 170 miles on a side. That's a conservative estimate. The cost, even neglecting the saving from not doing more expensive energy alternatives, would amount to about 15 years of our military budget. A lot of money, but compare the cost-effectiveness of a 5,000-mile-long sea wall and all the things that would have to go with it.</p>
        <p>I am associated with a bunch of engineers who make solar thermal machines. But we remain, so far, uncorrupted by profit; our motives are more allied to fanaticism.</p>
        <p>By the way, if any readers still think that they can solve the problem of global warming by resorting to more air-conditioning, as is suggested in your article, they had better sign up for a refresher course in thermodynamics. WILLIAM BEALE  President, Sunpower Inc.  Athens, Ohio, Nov. 15, 1989</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
