<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Fights Perception That He Is Adrift</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="231308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CABINETS AND SUB-CABINETS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINORITIES (ETHNIC, RACIAL, RELIGIOUS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTS AND PRESIDENCY (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEINRAUB, BERNARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Diversity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890313T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DF133DF930A25750C0A96F948260" item-length="1362" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Fights Perception That He Is Adrift</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD WEINRAUB, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEINRAUB, BERNARD</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: After seven weeks in office, President Bush is still seeking a sense of definition for his Administration, or at least a widespread acceptance that he has defined its priorities in domestic and foreign policy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: After seven weeks in office, President Bush is still seeking a sense of definition for his Administration, or at least a widespread acceptance that he has defined its priorities in domestic and foreign policy.</p>
        <p>After seven weeks in office, President Bush is still seeking a sense of definition for his Administration, or at least a widespread acceptance that he has defined its priorities in domestic and foreign policy.</p>
        <p>The charge that he has failed to define his course comes more from Democrats than Republicans. But it is heard in his own party, too.</p>
        <p>Some Republicans worry that the perception the Administration is off to a crawl is more the problem than the reality, and is based on exaggeration in the press of what Representative Dick Cheney, the Wyoming Republican who is newly designated to be Defense Secretary, termed ''the usual start-up problems.'' Looking for Act I</p>
        <p>But among an array of political experts, some lawmakers and even Administration aides, the consensus is that while stories of drifting may be overstated, especially with the Bush Presidency in its infancy, the White House is largely without a pronounced program that could mobilize Congress and the nation. ''People keep saying, 'When is the overture going to end and the curtain go up?' '' one Administration official noted.</p>
        <p>Part of the problem - whether perception or reality - is that in several key departments, like State and Justice, many high-level positions are vacant. Besides dealing with the job vacancies, Mr. Bush has focused on a three-year, $50 billion savings and loan bailout and a purposely vague $1.16 trillion budget that seeks to trim the deficit and leave the task of cutting popular social programs at least partly in the hands of Congress.</p>
        <p>Whether this amounts to a defined program, the interplay between the reality and the image of Mr. Bush's first 50 days provides a striking example of the circular process by which Presidential authority and public perception interact.</p>
        <p>''What's taking place now is more perception than reality because it's based on models of activist Presidential influence, like F.D.R. and Ronald Reagan, who are not relevant to the Bush Administration in 1989 both in terms of what's desirable and what's politically possible,'' said Thomas E. Mann, director of governmental studies at the Brookings Institution, the Washington policy research group. ''This is a very constrained Presidency with limited opportunities.''</p>
        <p>This view is mirrored, in bluntly political terms, by a conservative Republican supporter of Mr. Bush, Representative Newt Gingrich of Georgia. ''In Washington,'' he said, ''the press tests a new President against what a liberal welfare state President would do. If he doesn't do it, like Bush, they say he's drifting. He's not doing it, but he's not drifting.'' Perceptions Rooted in Past</p>
        <p>Others say the notion that a President must turn his first 100 days into a swirl of activity and programs is based on historical models that don't apply and were fashioned into cliches by journalists. Franklin D. Roosevelt's first 100 days achieved major social change because the nation was stricken with financial despair. Ronald Reagan's fast-paced first 100 days -including 83 major program changes, proposals for the biggest military buildup since the Vietnam war and a large shift of resources from Government to private hands - followed a period of inflation, high interest rates and an ebbing of the nation's confidence in itself and in the future.</p>
        <p>The most striking part of the impression of an Administration adrift was the ordeal over the nomination of John G. Tower to be Defense Secretary, a battle that increasingly consumed the attention of the White House and Mr. Bush. The Senate killed Mr. Tower's nomination Thursday by a vote of 53 to 47. ''The supernova of John Tower whited out the rest of our agenda,'' one White House aide said.</p>
        <p>Regardless of the Tower proceedings, White House aides and advisers said it was unrealistic and unfair to expect an active agenda in the White House now. ''For one thing, President Bush came in as the third consecutive term of the same party, he was a key member of the outgoing Administration and there was absolutely no need to demonstrate you'll change everything since an element to Bush's election was continuity,'' said Robert Teeter, Mr. Bush's campaign pollster and a close adviser. No Long List of Goals</p>
        <p>On Thursday, before his selection to be Defense Secretary, Mr. Cheney said: ''The notion of drift is overdone just like the euphoria of the first couple of weeks was overdone. Obviously there were start-up problems. But the budget negotiations are going pretty well, as they get their act together they'll produce acid rain legislation, the savings and loan package is a big plus.''</p>
        <p>''Bush didn't come to town with long list of 45 things to do in his first 45 days,'' said Mr. Cheney. ''The last person to do that was Jimmy Carter.''</p>
        <p>So far, the lag in appointing officials to major jobs across the Administration, the hammerlock of a budget that must meet deficit reduction targets without a tax increase, and even what aides acknowledge to be the absence of conservative ideological fervor within the White House have contributed to the sense that the Bush Administration was stalled.</p>
        <p>As of Friday, White House officials said, Mr. Bush had nominated or announced intention to nominate people to fill 90 jobs. The officials said that in the same period of Mr. Reagan's first term, he named 59.</p>
        <p>The Carter Administration also faced difficulties filling jobs in its first two months.</p>
        <p>But because Mr. Carter and Mr. Reagan launched domestic and foreign initiatives in their first months, the lack of high-level appointments in their early months as President did not get as much attention as it has under Mr. Bush. Official Explains Lag</p>
        <p>Charles G. Untermeyer, the chief of White House personnel, said the lag in hiring was caused by ''the screening that the President and the public expects,'' as well as several other factors including a search for minorities and women and the desire for ''political soulmates'' in key jobs.</p>
        <p>One Republican analyst concedes there is drifting, but complains about the talk of it. ''The perception of drift, the discussion and dissection of drift is worsening the drift that exists,'' said Kevin Phillips. ''It's focusing attention to it. It's helped turn the transition from the happy-talk view of the new President to a cold-blooded assessment that they don't have an agenda.''</p>
        <p>White House aides say the focus on drugs, education, and deficit reduction will prove a cornerstone of Bush Presidency. But the financial constraints are enormous, they say, making it impossible to shape a substantial agenda. Even some Democrats sympathize with the White House.</p>
        <p>''We have a progressive Republican Administration that very specifically excludes all that anti-Government rhetoric of the last eight years, which was an aberration,'' said Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan, Democrat of New York. ''The new Government came in, and the officers sat down and said let's see what we can do about such critical matters as drugs and education. And a voice undoubtedly said, 'But we're broke, we have no money.' And that's the problem. They're broke. They have lower appropriations but higher priority.'' Foreign Policy</p>
        <p>Compounding the overall difficulties for Mr. Bush are the Administration's vagueness and uncertainties in foreign policy. Critics point to the failure so far to name high-level State Department officials, including the Assistant Secretary for European Affairs, who would deal directly with the Soviets, as well as a prolonged review of strategic relations as delaying any decision-making.</p>
        <p>While the focus of attention has been on Mr. Bush's domestic agenda, Mr. Cheney believes the final assessment of the Administration will center on foreign policy. ''This is an area where you'll remake the world in fundamental ways,'' he said. ''Economic policy has become fundamentally important. The NATO alliance. What's going on in the Soviet Union and China. Changes are taking place massive in scope that will require a good deal of the President's time. The Administration's foreign policy challenge will be greater and more sweeping than anything that will happen on the domestic side.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
