<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush's Shell Game</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="213447"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERIOR, DEPARTMENT OF THE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">OAKES, JOHN B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LUJAN, MANUEL JR (REPR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">OP-ED</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DF123FF931A25752C0A96F948260" item-length="703" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush's Shell Game</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John B. Oakes; John B. Oakes is former Editorial Page Editor of The New York Times.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">OAKES, JOHN B</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President-elect Bush has earned extra brownie points as an ''environmentalist'' for naming a well-regarded professional to head the badly crippled Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President-elect Bush has earned extra brownie points as an ''environmentalist'' for naming a well-regarded professional to head the badly crippled Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>President-elect Bush has earned extra brownie points as an ''environmentalist'' for naming a well-regarded professional to head the badly crippled Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>But in a balancing act that throws into question his seriousness of purpose, Mr. Bush simultaneously appointed to the nation's top-ranking environmental position - Secretary of the Interior - an amiable politician who has one of the worst environmental voting records in Congress.</p>
        <p>This is a time when environmental deterioration across the board -from ozone depletion and acid rain to deforestation and extinction of species - is at last becoming recognized as an even greater threat to life on this planet than the nuclear threat that it encompasses. This is a time when the National Academy of Sciences says environmental changes are putting ''the future welfare of human society'' at risk.</p>
        <p>This is no time for George Bush, self-styled ''environmentalist,'' to be still playing politics with the environment. This is no time for Mr. Bush to be making such a thoroughly political move as naming former Representative Manuel Lujan Jr. of New Mexico to the prestigious and powerful Cabinet level post at Interior.</p>
        <p>With his selection of Mr. Lujan, the President-elect is paying off political debts to his Hispanic supporters and right-wing G.O.P. moguls from the Rocky Mountain states. In doing so, Mr. Bush risks delivering the half billion acres of public domain under Interior Department stewardship into the hands of the same grazing, mining, oil and timber interests responsible for the nomination of Ronald Reagan's first Interior Secretary, the infamous James G. Watt.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lujan is no Watt - at least in manner. In the ''kinder, gentler'' mode that Mr. Bush has favored since his election, the New Mexico Congressman is personally popular; but he has no lasting commitment to environmental protection, no reputation for environmental leadership and two decades of Congressional service, almost always on the anti-environmental side. Of 16 ballots on major environmental issues in the last Congress, Mr. Lujan voted the wrong way on all but two, giving him a ''pro-environment'' vote of 12.5 percent against a House average of 54 percent.</p>
        <p>He voted for the sale of mining claims at giveaway prices (a process going on right now under Interior Secretary Hodel); he voted to cut funds for energy-conservation programs; he voted for wasteful water project boondoggles; he voted against protection of certain endangered species; he voted against moves to lessen ocean pollution and to encourage survival of sea birds and mammals; he failed to support strong acid-rain controls; he favors opening the Arctic wildlife preserve to oil and gas exploration.</p>
        <p>The nonpartisan League of Conservation voters gives him a 16 percent score on environmental votes in 1985-86; for the previous four years, he averaged 19 percent.</p>
        <p>''I remain committed to a strong Federal role in leadership for wildlife and public land protection programs,'' said Mr. Bush during the campaign. Where is that leadership?</p>
        <p>William K. Reilly, whom Mr. Bush named to head the E.P.A., is long-time president of the research-oriented Conservation Foundation. He is an expert who believes in moderation and mediation rather than confrontation on environmental disputes. Up to a point, that's all to the good. But a tough fighter is needed for the post, and the question is whether Mr. Reilly can and will be tough enough.</p>
        <p>The agency that he will now lead was decimated and degraded during the early years of the Reagan Administration. Neither the E.P.A. nor Mr. Reilly can conceivably cope with its immense regulatory responsibilities without a massive infusion of new blood, new spirit and new money -which there is doubt that Mr. Bush with his deficit and tax problems will be able or willing to supply.</p>
        <p>The appointment of even so admirable an environmentalist as Mr. Reilly to this administrative quagmire will be meaningless without an intensity and sincerity of Presidential leadership - and the naming of highly qualified, non-political personnel to the top echelons of both Interior and E.P.A. This is a war too important to be left to the politicians.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
