<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Danger of a Firefighting Wonder</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="273707"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HALONS (CHEMICALS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRADSHER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFDA1338F93AA3575BC0A96F948260" item-length="1471" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Danger of a Firefighting Wonder</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRADSHER, KEITH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Responding to growing pressure from the Environmental Protection Agency and environmental groups, a wide range of businesses, military installations and cultural institutions are struggling to curb their use of halons, a highly effective family of firefighting chemicals believed by scientists to be even more destructive to the world's ozone layer than their better-known chemical cousins, the chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Responding to growing pressure from the Environmental Protection Agency and environmental groups, a wide range of businesses, military installations and cultural institutions are struggling to curb their use of halons, a highly effective family of firefighting chemicals believed by scientists to be even more destructive to the world's ozone layer than their better-known chemical cousins, the chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>Responding to growing pressure from the Environmental Protection Agency and environmental groups, a wide range of businesses, military installations and cultural institutions are struggling to curb their use of halons, a highly effective family of firefighting chemicals believed by scientists to be even more destructive to the world's ozone layer than their better-known chemical cousins, the chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>Molecule for molecule, halon compounds are three to ten times as destructive to high-altitude ozone as chlorofluorocarbon 11 and 12, said Stephen O. Andersen, chief of the technology and economics branch in the E.P.A.'s division of global change.</p>
        <p>Although halons are produced in smaller quantities than chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, which are used in air-conditioning and refrigeration, experts estimate that they could account for up to a sixth of the eventual ozone depletion from current industrial gas production. The Technology of Choice</p>
        <p>Halons were little known in 1978 when the United States first moved to cut back on CFC's by banning their use in aerosol cans. Today, though, the halons' unique firefighting characteristics have made them the technology of choice for protecting everything from rare documents, like the Declaration of Independence, to aircraft and computer installations.</p>
        <p>''There is absolutely nothing on the market that comes close to being able to do the job,'' said Robert F. Rabroker, who designs and installs halon systems for the Koetter Fire Protection Service Company in Dallas. ''It is going to be tough to replace it.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, given the importance of protecting the ozone layer, which shields the earth from the sun's ultraviolet radiation, halon producers are searching for substitutes. The United States and 38 other countries are committed to reducing consumption to 1986 levels by 1992. E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company, which estimates it has about half of the $75 million domestic market, says its goal is to phase out halon production along with CFC's by the end of the century.</p>
        <p>Halons stop combustion in enclosed areas within seconds, usually without requiring the evacuation of people near the flames. Most approaches to suppressing fires involve smothering them (as with carbon dioxide gas, which is heavier than air and displaces the oxygen that a fire needs to burn) or cooling the fuel below its burning point (for example, by pouring on water).</p>
        <p>Halons disrupt a fire's chemistry, although the exact process is not well understood. As many as 40 chemical reactions may be involved, said Robert E. Tapscott, a professor of chemistry at the University of New Mexico and a specialist in combustion research. The most important are known to involve combinations of a halon's bromine atom with free hydrogen atoms that are produced by and then feed a fire.</p>
        <p>Bromine atoms bind hydrogen atoms together into less reactive hydrogen molecules, which consist of two hydrogen atoms, Mr. Tapscott said. The hydrogen molecules disperse in the air or combine with oxygen atoms at the top of flames to form water vapor. This process prevents the hydrogen atoms from participating in volatile combustion reactions with the substance on fire.</p>
        <p>''What you've done is tie them up,'' he said. Over all, halon leaves far fewer residues than water or carbon dioxide firefighting technology and is less likely to harm electrical and electronic equipment in the burning area.</p>
        <p>The same bromine atoms that fight fires so effectively also break up ozone molecules in the stratosphere, the E.P.A. says. Experts say several reactions might occur. But all of them involve bromine atoms turning ozone molecules, which consist of three oxygen atoms, into oxygen molecules of two oxygen atoms apiece, and end up leaving the bromine atom free to attack other ozone molecules.</p>
        <p>The ratification of the Montreal Protocol on ozone depletion in September 1987 by the United States and most other industrial nations is already putting pressure on consumers.</p>
        <p>The National Fire Protection Association, which three years ago considered advising municipalities to require the testing of halon systems on installation, now opposes all halon emissions except for fires. In addition, insurers have dropped their requirements that tests be conducted. Many users have already cut back on training in firefighting that involves the release of halon.</p>
        <p>Halon distributors are buying equipment to recycle halon reservoirs in buildings being demolished to prevent the unnecessary release of the chemicals in the air. About half of recoverable halons were recycled two years ago, said Gary M. Taylor, a Toronto fire-control expert who has been chairman of the Halon Technical Options Committee, an international group studying alternatives. Today, about 75 percent are recycled and that figure may reach 95 percent by the end of next year, Mr. Taylor said.</p>
        <p>Less than half of worldwide emissions are related to putting out fires, according to a survey of 1986 usage by the Halon-Technical Options Committee, an international body that reports to the United Nations Environment Program.</p>
        <p>Du Pont said that sales of its most common halon compound fell 11 percent last year and are expected to decline 20 percent this year, in large part because of conservation measures.</p>
        <p>A complete phase-out will eventually be necessary, a study scheduled for release on Friday by the options committee has found. The committee has called for the immediate elimination of halon use except when required to save lives or produce broad benefits to society.</p>
        <p>But the committee concluded that to protect the ozone, countries should be prepared to spend more on other fire prevention systems and to risk more costly property losses in cases where halon could be eliminated without endangering lives, Mr. Taylor said.</p>
        <p>Du Pont sold about three million pounds of halons in the United States last year, said Robert P. Gallucci, the company's account manager for halon products. The company hopes to have a substitute product on the market in the middle or late 1990's, he added.</p>
        <p>The other four companies selling halons in the United States - Kali-Chemie A.G. of West Germany, ICI P.L.C. of Britain, Atochem S.A. of France and the Great Lakes Chemical Corporation - have not set timetables for phasing out production. Indeed, Great Lakes officials question the common scientific view that industrial gases, and particularly halons, deplete the ozone layer, and argue that halon's benefits outweigh the perceived environmental cost.</p>
        <p>Unlike CFC's, halons are so expensive that they are used mostly when considered indispensable. A typical halon system is likely to be more than twice as expensive as automatic sprinklers. Halon systems cost upwards of $14 per square foot of floor area protected.</p>
        <p>Federal Aviation Administration regulations require automatic halon fire extinguishers in all engine housings, large cargo compartments and lavatory wastebaskets on commercial jetliners. Planes with a capacity of more than 60 passengers must also carry at least two portable halon fire extinguishers in the cabin.</p>
        <p>Halon is ideal for use in planes, said Gus Sarkos, manager of the fire safety branch at the F.A.A. Technical Center near Atlantic City. Gaseous halon 1301 (the digits describe the number of carbon, fluorine, chlorine, and bromine atoms, respectively, in the compound) spreads in seconds through an engine housing or cargo compartment, can be inhaled with minimum risk, and can be compressed and stored as a very compact and lightweight liquid, he said.</p>
        <p>''These unique properties of 1301 may make it difficult to come up with a substitute,'' Mr. Sarkos said in discussing the planned cutbacks. ''Perhaps there can be some exemptions made.''  A Reaction That Disrupts Fires  1. Halon 1301 is a gas made up of a carbon atom, flourine atoms and a bromine atom.  2. Free hydrogen atoms are both produced by and intensify fire.  3. The halon reacts with the hydrogen to form a trifluoromethyl radical* and hydrogen bromide.  4. The hydrogen bromide captures another free hydrogen atom, then breaks into a hydrogen molecule and a bromine atom. The hydrogen molecule disperses in the air or burns, forming water.  5. The bromine atom joins with another bromine atome to from a bromine molecule.  6. The bromine molecule combines with a free hydrogen atom to make hydrogen bromide and a bromine atom.  7. The hydrogen bromide and the bromine atom can then continue the reactions in steps 4 and 5. Quickly, enough free hydrogen atoms are combined into hydrogen molecules to deprive the fire of fuel.  * The trifluoromethyl radical is burned up, leaving carbon dioxide and a small amount of hydrogen fluoride (not shown).  Source: Robert E. Tapscott, University of New Mexico. (NYT)  BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
