<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deaths of Dolphins Are Linked by U.S. To Natural Causes</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="219595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALGAE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RED TIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOLPHINS AND PORPOISES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEACHES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POISONING AND POISONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ATLANTIC OCEAN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL OCEANIC AND ATMOSPHERIC ADMINISTRATION</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poisoning and Poisons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D71139F931A35751C0A96F948260" item-length="489" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deaths of Dolphins Are Linked by U.S. To Natural Causes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Hundreds of bottlenose dolphins found dead on East Coast shores two summers ago were poisoned after eating fish contaminated with a toxin from an algae rarely found in those waters, a National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration study has concluded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Hundreds of bottlenose dolphins found dead on East Coast shores two summers ago were poisoned after eating fish contaminated with a toxin from an algae rarely found in those waters, a National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration study has concluded.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of bottlenose dolphins found dead on East Coast shores two summers ago were poisoned after eating fish contaminated with a toxin from an algae rarely found in those waters, a National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration study has concluded.</p>
        <p>Gerald Scott, an official of the agency, said that as many as a thousand dolphins, half of the coastal migratory population, were lost. It could take up to a century to regain their former population level, he said. The ''red tide'' algae was found in the liver and other viscera of menhaden and Spanish mackerel and other fish eaten by the dolphins.</p>
        <p>Officials of the oceanic administration said the toxin was not found in the flesh of the fish and thus posed no threat to humans eating fish fillets.</p>
        <p>The officials said the algae occurred naturally and not because of any man-made pollutant. The deaths had puzzled scientists for 18 months and caused concern among the public about the health of the nation's waters, some of which are threatened by industrial discharges, sewage, air pollution and acid rain. Hundreds of Scientists</p>
        <p>The dolphins' death from such a cause ''is a first,'' said Joseph Geraci, professor of veterinary medicine in the pathology department at the University of Guelph near Toronto. Dr. Geraci headed an 18-month investigation that involved hundreds of scientists at dozens of Federal, university and private agencies and laboratories.</p>
        <p>The agency's findings were disputed by Greenpeace, a worldwide environmental group, which said brevetoxin and red tide blooms are common in the Gulf of Mexico, which is inhabited by thousands of bottlenose dolphins. ''There have never been any recorded cases of dolphins in the Gulf being affected by brevetoxin,'' said Bruce McKay, Greenpeace spokesman.</p>
        <p>Mr. McKay said the agency supplied no documented evidence for its theory. Officials said a final report would be available in three weeks.</p>
        <p>When asked why dolphins survive in the Gulf of Mexico with the red tide algae, Brian E. Gorman, an agency spokesman, said the red tide blooms there tend to be denser and more discrete than that found along the Atlantic coast. ''The red tide algae we are talking about in the dolphin episode was more widely dispersed and more easily taken up by the fish,'' he said. Some Pollutants Found</p>
        <p>Agency officials did, however, find elevated levels of some pollutants, mainly PCB's, in the internal organs of the dolphins, Mr. Gorman said. But, he said, ''We are convinced that it wasn't the high pollution level that lead to their death.''</p>
        <p>Today's explanation for the dolphins' death is consistent with Dr. Geraci's earlier findings in August 1987 that the dolphins died from common bacteria normally found in coastal waters. Dr. Geraci said today that, while some of the dolphins died immediately from the brevetoxin, others were weakened by it and became more susceptible to bacterial and viral infections.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
