<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="249504"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D81F31F930A25756C0A96F948260" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International 3-7  President Bush's Soviet policy was outlined in a long-awaited speech. He cautioned that Moscow still had to earn warmer ties with the West and resurrected a proposal for East-West aerial surveillance. Page 1  Moscow's latest nuclear arms cut was welcomed by the Western allies, but diplomats said the move only aggravates the divisions within NATO over negotiations on curbing short-range missiles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International 3-7  President Bush's Soviet policy was outlined in a long-awaited speech. He cautioned that Moscow still had to earn warmer ties with the West and resurrected a proposal for East-West aerial surveillance. Page 1  Moscow's latest nuclear arms cut was welcomed by the Western allies, but diplomats said the move only aggravates the divisions within NATO over negotiations on curbing short-range missiles.</p>
        <p>International 3-7  President Bush's Soviet policy was outlined in a long-awaited speech. He cautioned that Moscow still had to earn warmer ties with the West and resurrected a proposal for East-West aerial surveillance. Page 1  Moscow's latest nuclear arms cut was welcomed by the Western allies, but diplomats said the move only aggravates the divisions within NATO over negotiations on curbing short-range missiles.  1  News analysis: Moscow's plan to withdraw 500 nuclear weapons and President Bush's proposal for aerial surveillance marked a week of diplomacy intended to sway Western European opinion. 7  Panama's Roman Catholic Church issued a blistering attack on the Government of General Noriega, questioning its moral authority to govern and inviting the military to disobey repressive orders. 1  Washington steps up its drive against Noriega  5  Survey finds support for Panama Canal treaties 5  A world treaty on global warming is supported by President Bush, who wants to begin negotiations on a ''framework'' for a treaty on global warming but is not ready to endorse specifics, the E.P.A. said. 9  A diplomatic nominee was opposed as he tried to convince Democratic senators that neither he nor George Bush knew about the Reagan Administration's secret effort to arm the contras until late 1986. 5  Eighty percent of top posts under Bush still unfilled 9  An embarrassing setback in Japan occurred when Masayoshi Ito rejected appeals of the Liberal Democratic Party to serve as Prime Minister, saying it blocked his anti-corruption proposals. 3  Muslims march in Beijing 3  A Palestinian move to join the W.H.O. as a member state was set aside. The application to join the World Health Organization had been opposed by Israel and the United States. 3  Greek court backs extraditing Palestinian to the U.S. 4  Solidarity is learning to campaign for approaching elections, attracting political workers and media advisers from across the country to a race that essentially pits the union against the Communist Party. 4  Probable successor to Botha calls for black political role 7  Canada screens fuel imports 4  National 8-9, 26, 48  Producer prices rose moderately in April, by four-tenths of 1 percent, the Government said. It was the second straight moderate increase, following two months of soaring prices at the beginning of the year. 1  Reacting to the inflation report, the Dow Jones industrial average soared 56.82 points, and the Treasury securities market had its biggest one-day gain since September. 33, 36  Airline reservations were disrupted when the nation's largest reservation system shut down for almost 12 hours, leaving travel agencies and a large part of American Airlines without flight information. 1  Delay in the start of a new ethics law, which erects new barriers to employment for Government officials, was approved by the Senate. The law has prompted the resignaitons of at least 36 high-level officials. 1  Speaker Wright's $100,000 loan to finance his investment in a nursing home business has received the attention of the House ethics committee. A Texas bank said the panel has requested records from it. 8  Under new anti-discrimination laws in the Fair Housing Act, a Federal district court awarded a black woman from New Jersey a $40,000 consent judgment against a Florida mobile home company. 1  Sixty-nine general hospitals closed in 1987, eliminating 4,233 beds, while 13 new hospitals opened, a Government study has found. Reasons for the closings include shortages of doctors and patients. 26  Gene linked to breast cancer is found in ovarian tumors 8  Powerful chemicals for the oil spill off Valdez, Alaska, have been suggested by a top Coast Guard officer because other methods have proved ineffective. The suggestion is likely to be opposed by environmentalists. 8  A California freight train derailed in San Bernardino, demolishing a row of houses, killing one crew member and two children and shaking the area like an earthquake, officials and residents said. 8  WPP Group appears close to a deal to buy the Ogilvy Group, creating the world's second-largest advertising and marketing company. 33  63% of semifinalists for scholarship are men, a study finds 9  Changes urged in job training 9  Regional 27-30  Richard Green's memorial service at the Cathedral of St. John the Divine included 5,000 New Yorkers, from schoolchildren to leaders of the city and state. 27  Ambulance response to Green's attack is disputed 30  A would-be great in basketball, Lloyd Daniels lay in critical condition after being shot three times in a dispute over drugs. He never overcame the pitfalls that snare many less-gifted youths. 27  16 are charged in $100-million-a-year money-laundering 29  New York has agreed to settle suit by family of slain youth 29 New York City's welfare chief challenged New York State to take over the city's beleaguered social-service system after the state released a scathing review of the agency. 27  News analysis: Charter revision in New York City faces a vote this November, and while some say change is coming too fast, others say postponement may mean surrendering power to the courts or special elections. 29  Judge says Bronx Senate seat is vacant but fight goes on  29  Delaware panel lifts drought warning  29  Housing for elderly homeless people provides 19 men and women in Port Jervis, N.Y., with private bedrooms for $229 a month. In the experimental program, the tenants share a kitchen, living room and bathroom. 27  Rutgers protest on tuition rise ends in arrests 28  PATH motormen approve contract 29  Awash in copies, O'Neill's aides denounce fax attacks 28</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
