<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ANSWERS TO QUIZ</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="249392"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DA103EF930A25756C0A96F948260" item-length="460" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ANSWERS TO QUIZ</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Questions appear on page 11.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Questions appear on page 11.</p>
        <p>Questions appear on page 11.</p>
        <p>1. Guillermo Endara, Panama's opposition presidential candidate, needed stitches for a head wound inflicted by paramilitary squads who assaulted him and his running mates after the election in Panama.</p>
        <p>2. Dr. James E. Hansen, director of the Goddard Institute for Space Studies, said the White House tried to make his conclusions about global warming seem less serious and less certain than he had meant them to be.</p>
        <p>3. All subway cars are graffiti-free, according to transit officials.</p>
        <p>4. Mr. Gorbachev's plan for small cuts in Soviet nuclear arms is likely to widen the rift between two groups of NATO members: those who agree with West Germany's call for Washington to negotiate with Moscow on short-range nuclear arms, and Britain and the United States, which oppose such a move.</p>
        <p>5. The house was the first piece of real estate ever sold by Sotheby's and the first ever offered at a New York art auction.</p>
        <p>6. They were Soviet Government officials invited to testify before the House Armed Services Committee about arms control, East-West relations and Mikhail S. Gorbachev's policies.</p>
        <p>7. Mr. Schultz, the city's Environmental Protection Commissioner, said news that the drought emergency might be over because of the rain made him feel ''like Gene Kelly, singing in the rain.''</p>
        <p>8. Mogilny, a Soviet hockey star, has defected and asked political asylum in the United States after signing with the Buffalo Sabres.</p>
        <p>9. Ms. McCorvey was ''Jane Roe'' in the 1973 Supreme Court case, Roe v. Wade, that created a constitutional right to abortion.</p>
        <p>10. Arab students in the occupied West Bank attend clandestine classes because the Israelis have kept schools and universities closed more than 16 months, saying they were breeding grounds for unrest.</p>
        <p>11. Because the books and scores of both shows are old material, they were not eligible for best book and best original score. The Tony committee eliminated those categories.</p>
        <p>12. Mr. Koch wants a successor named by the time school starts in September. Some challengers in the primary want the choice made after the mayoral election so that whoever wins may take part in the selection.</p>
        <p>The kitchen is run by a charity in Leningrad and is the Soviet Union's first free food program for the impoverished. Officials were reluctant to admit that the Government could not provide minimal sustenance for the people.</p>
        <p>14. Easy Goer, who had been given a strong chance to win thoroughbred racing's Triple Crown, finished second to Sunday Silence in the Kentucky Derby.</p>
        <p>15. How to finance that expansion.</p>
        <p>16. Tennessee Meiji Gakuin (Academy) is the country's first Japanese high school that is fully accredited to both American and Japanese standards.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
