<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Outdoors; Bay's Striped Bass Stage a Comeback</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="278772"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISHING, SPORT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STRIPED BASS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISHING, COMMERCIAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MARYLAND</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHESAPEAKE BAY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRYANT, NELSON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6DC1631F934A1575BC0A96F948260" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Outdoors; Bay's Striped Bass Stage a Comeback</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nelson Bryant</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRYANT, NELSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: After nearly a decade of poor spawning years, the Chesapeake Bay's striped bass have produced a host of offspring.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: After nearly a decade of poor spawning years, the Chesapeake Bay's striped bass have produced a host of offspring.</p>
        <p>After nearly a decade of poor spawning years, the Chesapeake Bay's striped bass have produced a host of offspring.</p>
        <p>The news is so good that Maryland has already announced that its four-year ban on recreational and commercial fishing for the species will be lifted next year. And the Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission will probably propose easing restrictions on commercial and recreational harvesting of the species all along the coast in 1990. This could include allowing sport fishermen two bass a day, 28 or more inches long. The current regulation permits a coastal angler one bass, 36 or more inches long.</p>
        <p>Historically, striped bass spawned in the rivers entering Chesapeake Bay have accounted for about 90 percent of the East Coast's migratory stock of the species. By the late 1970's, landings of the species were swiftly declining, and in 1979, Congress approved an emergency striped bass study. In 1981, the fisheries commission put together an interstate fisheries management plan for the striper. In 1984, Congress gave that plan teeth by passing the Atlantic Striped Bass Conservation Act, which empowered the Federal Government to close fishing for stripers in states that did not comply with the plan.</p>
        <p>The reasons for the stripers' decline are not fully understood, but the factors involved include overfishing by sport and commercial interests, pollution, acid rain and unusual climatic conditions. Those laboring on the striper's behalf followed the one remedial course immediately available and proposed drastic harvesting restrictions. There was some heel-dragging among the states, but the Striped Bass Conservation Act and Maryland's bold move in placing a total ban on catching the species got the plan rolling.</p>
        <p>In 1982, the Chesapeake's stripers had a fairly successful spawning season, and a key element in the plan has been to protect the females of that year by a minimum-length limit, which increased each year until they spawned at least once. Nearly all female stripers accomplish that by their eighth year, when they are about 33 inches long and weigh about 19 pounds. Males mature by age 4. Stripers are a long-lived species, with a few reaching age 30.</p>
        <p>For more than 30 years, Maryland has been taking seining samples in July, August and September to measure the reproductive success of each year class of the Chesapeake's stripers. A measure of the relative abundance of yearling fish, it is called a young-of-the-year index. The average over the entire index period is about 8. The highest index was 30 in 1970, and in the 1980's, until this year, it fell below 5 except for 1982 when it was 8.4.</p>
        <p>The striper management plan in effect calls for continuing the harvesting restrictions until a production trigger (a three-year running average of 8) is reached. Two of the three samplings have been completed this year, and even if no fish at all show up in the September hauls, the 1989 index would be 17, more than enough to meet the trigger goal.</p>
        <p>In anticipation of the striper's comeback, the fisheries commission has been developing an interim plan that would allow increased but limited exploitation of the species by sport and commercial interests. The new plan also calls for continuous monitoring of coastal stripers throughout their range, relaxing or tightening harvesting regulations as bass populations rise or fall.</p>
        <p>Howard King of the fisheries division of Maryland's Tidewater Administration said the state planned an extremely limited sport and commercial fishery within the Chesapeake Bay for stripers next year with separate seasons for each that would last for only a few weeks. The commission would have to approve that plan, of course.</p>
        <p>The Roanoke River in North Carolina and the Hudson River are the other two major producers of stripers along the middle Atlantic coast. The Hudson's stripers have been thriving throughout the 1980's, and there have been suggestions that the A.S.M.F.C. should take this into account when developing management plans for coastal stocks of bass.</p>
        <p>The problem with this has always been determining the relative abundance of Chesapeake and Hudson stocks in New York's waters. Last year, the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation began a sophisticated study of this, and preliminary results suggest that Hudson fish predominate.</p>
        <p>Even if this proves to be so, the state faces a dilemma. Stripers of Hudson origin are contaminated by PCB's. Because of this, New York State closed all commercial fishing for the species more than a decade ago. Over the years, analyses of stripers caught in the state's waters have indicated varying levels, sometimes acceptable, sometimes not, of PCB's, according to where they were caught. There is also evidence to suggest that contamination increases as the fish grow older and larger. The state might be successful in persuading the A.S.M.F.C. to allow New York to have striper regulations more liberal than those elsewhere along the coast. That would enhance sport fishing, but the PCB's still stand in the way of the commercial endeavor.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
