<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. Not Story It Once Was to the U.S. Press</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="293707"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D91E3DF931A15753C1A96F948260" item-length="698" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. Not Story It Once Was to the U.S. Press</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In the newsroom at the United Nations, there are 34 manual typewriters facing 34 empty chairs. They usually sit untouched in neat rows, a monument to the days when reporters banged out breaking news with a click and a zing instead of rushing to electronic terminals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In the newsroom at the United Nations, there are 34 manual typewriters facing 34 empty chairs. They usually sit untouched in neat rows, a monument to the days when reporters banged out breaking news with a click and a zing instead of rushing to electronic terminals.</p>
        <p>In the newsroom at the United Nations, there are 34 manual typewriters facing 34 empty chairs. They usually sit untouched in neat rows, a monument to the days when reporters banged out breaking news with a click and a zing instead of rushing to electronic terminals.</p>
        <p>The United Nations is still making news, but American reporters are not taking note of much of it, officials and journalists here say. Over the last 20 years, coverage has steadily declined.</p>
        <p>''For every one or two stories on the U.N. that get in the paper, there are probably another 10 out there that won't,'' said Peter Spotts, national editor of The Christian Science Monitor. ''How many of their activities directly address readers concerns?''</p>
        <p>With the decline in coverage, there has been a decline in American correspondents. There were about 50 American reporters stationed at the United Nations when it was founded in 1945; today there are about half that many. The New York Times has a full-time correspondent and a bureau here.</p>
        <p>''The American media has been lost and neglected,'' said Joe Mehan, a consultant to the information department at the United Nations Educational and Scientific Cultural Organization. ''Now the United Nations has to aggressively sell and tell its story.''</p>
        <p>Richard C. Hottelet, the last full-time reporter to cover the United Nations for CBS News, remembers when every major newspaper and network had a permanent correspondent here.</p>
        <p>Now most American reporters at the United Nations are stringers or assigned to multiple beats. ''If I hadn't had Canada on the side,'' said Donald Shannon of The Los Angeles Times, ''it would have been a waste of time.''</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, just when there has been decreasing coverage, there seems to be increasingly more to cover there. Recent milestones like the cease-fire between Iran and Iraq, the Soviet withdrawal from Afghanistan and the winning of the Nobel Peace Prize for its peacekeeping operations have moved the United Nations into the limelight.</p>
        <p>News organizations in other countries still consider the United Nations a big story. Walid A. Mourani, president of the United Nations Correspondents Association, who covers the United Nations for news agencies in Iraq and Qatar, said membership among foreign journalists continues to grow. There are currently more than 250 member correspondents.</p>
        <p>Recently at Columbia University, journalists tried to explain why the United Nations story goes largely untold.</p>
        <p>''The U.N. is not a visual story,'' said Tom Ross, the senior vice president of NBC News. ''It was when Khrushchev was pounding on the desk, but on the current scene, it really is not a dramatic and visual story. The truth be told, the United Nations is very low on our list of priorities.''</p>
        <p>''It's not the sexy news. It's not the bite,'' said John Tessitore, the director of communications for the United Nations Association of the United States. ''But at the same time, much of what goes on in committees has a direct effect on the citizens of the United States and the citizens of the world.''</p>
        <p>As an example, Mr. Tessitore cited the Montreal Protocol, a treaty engineered by the United Nations Environment Program in 1987 that called for the reduction of chemicals known as chlorofluorocarbons, which damage the earth's ozone layer. Mr. Tessitore said the United Nations role was barely mentioned in news coverage. What does grab headlines at the United Nations are visits by prominent figures like President Bush and Foreign Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze of the Soviet Union and major questions like those raised by Yasir Arafat, chairman of the Palestine Liberation Organization, and by the United States decision to withhold part of its dues.</p>
        <p>Others argue that the problem is the United Nations bureaucracy - countless committees conducting endless debates producing limitless releases.</p>
        <p>Another theory is that the United Nations is a casualty of increasingly advanced communications technology. With sophisticated satellite equipment and more correspondents overseas, there is less need to cover a report on world famine when pictures of emaciated children can be beamed back from African countries in seconds.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
