<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic's Notebook; Avant-Garde Films in a Struggle to Stay Avant</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="262229"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WHITNEY MUSEUM OF AMERICAN ART (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JAMES, CARYN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D91E3EF93AA15755C0A96F948260" item-length="1217" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic's Notebook; Avant-Garde Films in a Struggle to Stay Avant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JAMES, CARYN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As he drives a vintage Thunderbird cross-country to California, where he will deliver it to a Japanese car collector, the narrator of Chip Lord's video ''Motorist'' keeps up a droll monologue on American consumer culture. He drives over the London Bridge, transported to Arizona. He passes through San Bernardino, which a gas station attendant proudly tells him is the birthplace of McDonald's, and enters Hollywood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As he drives a vintage Thunderbird cross-country to California, where he will deliver it to a Japanese car collector, the narrator of Chip Lord's video ''Motorist'' keeps up a droll monologue on American consumer culture. He drives over the London Bridge, transported to Arizona. He passes through San Bernardino, which a gas station attendant proudly tells him is the birthplace of McDonald's, and enters Hollywood.</p>
        <p>As he drives a vintage Thunderbird cross-country to California, where he will deliver it to a Japanese car collector, the narrator of Chip Lord's video ''Motorist'' keeps up a droll monologue on American consumer culture. He drives over the London Bridge, transported to Arizona. He passes through San Bernardino, which a gas station attendant proudly tells him is the birthplace of McDonald's, and enters Hollywood. Sounding like Sam Spade reincarnated as a post-modern guru, he snarls, ''This is where our memories get sold back to us, milked for the essential icon and dropped onto us like acid rain.''</p>
        <p>Hollywood is not the only place raining acidic icons. An obsession with the symbols of pop culture characterizes many of the 32 independently made films and videos included in the Whitney Museum of American Art's Biennial Exhibition, through Wednesday. The works, as John G. Hanhardt, the museum's curator of film and video, wrote in the exhibition catalogue, are ''neither driven by the art marketplace nor the commercial television and motion picture industries.'' The selections range from socially minded documentaries to films resembling abstract paintings, but overall they have a remarkable focus, borrowing images as familiar as Mickey Mouse and Mars candy bars in order to attack pop culture and consumerism.</p>
        <p>Too often, though, their comments are easy and self-congratulatory. They attempt to lob grenades at the establishment, but their proximity is so close that it suggests a crucial question: How can avant-garde film-making survive in a consumer culture so pervasive that it seems to absorb its own critics?</p>
        <p>''Motorist,'' one of the most accessible and successful works in the Biennial, is filled with the narrator's wry comments on the 50's of his boyhood. Mr. Lord includes found images that shaped this character, like the scene from a howlingly funny promotional film in which men in black tie and women in evening gowns glide around cars and sing ''A Wonderful New World of Fords.''</p>
        <p>While the narrator clings to his dream of shiny cars and a carefree boyhood, the Japanese go about buying the American dream. ''Motorist'' ends with the Thunderbird's new owner driving it through Tokyo. But the nondramatic form and sardonic theme of the piece are only unconventional compared with a network mini-series. It is easy to imagine this charming, hourlong work on a public television schedule.</p>
        <p>Jason Simon's video, ''Production Notes: Fast Food for Thought,'' is a more direct attack on consumer culture, and a simplistic failure. Here several actual television commercials are shown. Two students in a new school are reassured by an afternoon visit to McDonald's, and Mars bars are pitched at adults with happy scenes of men and women chomping away. Afterward, each commercial is run in slow motion, this time with a narrator reading the advertising agency's production notes for the commercial. They do not reveal strategies or concepts so much as the most mundane details of production - the cost, the locations, the types of actors needed.</p>
        <p>But such descriptions do not begin to reveal how commercials manipulate viewers. It is as if Mr. Simon were reciting instructions for assembling an atomic bomb, when what he really means to do is attack the idea of nuclear war. He reveals the obvious truth that commercials want to sell us something.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Simon lacks is an avant-garde perspective, one that plays off viewers' awareness of consumer images without being co-opted by their power.</p>
        <p>But other Biennial artists prove that an avant-garde critique of popular culture can succeed because they have discovered and maintained a tenuous interplay between the viewer and the work. Tony Oursler and Constance DeJong's ''JoyrideTM,'' uses corporate images familiar to us and creates a hellish landscape that is totally their own. The surreal narrative in this 17-minute video is framed by the idea that our culture is like a Disneyland exhibit, which people patiently stand in line to enter. A live-action Big Brother-ish mouth is superimposed on a loudspeaker, urging people in a soothing but zombielike voice to be patient and orderly. Advertising logos of Coke and Kodak float in and out of this colorful playland, made up of computer graphics, live action, painted backdrops and small-scale objects. When a sun and a smoke alarm seem to merge with each other at the end, nature and commerce blend and go up in smoke.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Sandy Moore's ''Reverse Transcriptase'' challenges viewers to enter its cartoonish world and decipher its message of destruction by recreating in a 10-minute animated film the molecular composition of the virus believed to cause AIDS. Elements appropriated from an old cartoon, including a mop and a flagpole, represent certain molecules of the virus, and they are presented in a blindingly quick series of images. Among the fragmented cartoon images is a glimpse of what looks like Mickey Mouse's white gloved hand. ''Reverse Transcriptase'' depends on the audience's awareness of the AIDS crisis, as well as viewers' ability to recognize the innocent, cartoon elements. The result is strangely effective, evoking menace by using the most innocuous images.</p>
        <p>Next to these avant-garde suggestions of apocalypse, Rea Tajiri's 15-minute video, ''Hitchcock Trilogy: Vertigo, Psycho, Torn Curtain,'' seems genial. Ms. Tajiri succeeds by subtly evoking her viewers' awareness of familiar Hitchcock films. With Bernard Herrmann's music from each film in the background, she presents images that are related to the Hitchcock films in a skewed manner. A 16th-century painting of the biblical Judith holding a severed head, a film of an Asian man in 1927, and the image of a jewel box represent the eerie triangle of ''Vertigo,'' with James Stewart duped by the dead Kim Novak's lookalike. Ms. Tajiri's ''Torn Curtain'' is a series of curtains parting, interspersed with film images of Gene Kelly dancing and Maya Deren in ''Meshes of the Afternoon,'' a film sacred to the American avant-garde.</p>
        <p>By prying so deeply and subtly into our memories, ''Hitchcock Trilogy'' eludes the trap fallen into by so many self-declared avant-garde works. In his 117-minute film, ''Plain Talk and Common Sense (Uncommon Senses)'' Jon Jost, whose avant-garde credentials go back more than 15 years, uses innumerable images to tackle the subject of America itself. He interviews tourists, gives census figures, shows maps and reads bits of the Constitution. We are all searching, he says, for answers in ''the elusive out there,'' and ''Plain Talk'' turns into a test of endurance proving it cannot be found.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jost characterizes this work as ''notes from the margin.'' But however non-narrative and imagistic the film, Mr. Jost's perspective is not outside the mainstream. He condescends to the tourists he interviews, catching them in silly poses in front of their families' Polaroids. He attacks the Internal Revenue Service. These are hostile and bitter views, but hardly avant-garde.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Jost has, however inadvertently, helped to answer the Biennial's most valuable question. His film is evidence that ''the margins'' are increasingly hard to find and that film and video artists who want to work outside popular culture must find new means of escape.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
