<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>White House Admits Censoring Testimony</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="248413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DB143CF93AA35756C0A96F948260" item-length="782" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>White House Admits Censoring Testimony</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The White House confirmed today that it had censored Congressional testimony on the effects of global warming by a top Government scientist, but it insisted that the changes reflected policy decisions, not scientific conclusions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The White House confirmed today that it had censored Congressional testimony on the effects of global warming by a top Government scientist, but it insisted that the changes reflected policy decisions, not scientific conclusions.</p>
        <p>The White House confirmed today that it had censored Congressional testimony on the effects of global warming by a top Government scientist, but it insisted that the changes reflected policy decisions, not scientific conclusions.</p>
        <p>Marlin Fitzwater, the White House press secretary, said the Office of Management and Budget had changed conclusions about global warming data contained in the testimony of Dr. James T. Hansen, director of the space agency's Goddard Institute for Space Studies. He said the action was taken because the ideas presented were ''not necessarily those of all scientists who have considered this matter.''</p>
        <p>In his original text, before it was changed, Dr. Hansen asserted that computer projections showed that global warming caused by pollution from human activity would cause upheavals in the earth's climate. He warned of substantial increases in temperature, drought in mid-latitudes, severe storms and other stresses.</p>
        <p>But his testimony was changed to make his conclusions seem less certain.</p>
        <p>In response to questions at the regular White House briefing this morning, Mr. Fitzwater said that an official of the Office of Management and Budget ''five levels down from the top'' had changed Dr. Hansen's testimony to reflect that ''there are many points of view on the global warming issue and many of them conflict with those stated by Dr. Hansen.''</p>
        <p>But Dr. Hansen, appearing today before the Senate Subcommittee on Science, Technology and Space, said that the testimony he had submitted specifically stated that the conclusions represented his own scientific opinion, not Government policy or a scientific consensus.</p>
        <p>He said he had been forced by the budget office to make changes that raised questions about the reliability of scientific evidence on expected climate changes. Another change imposed by the budget office made it seem as if there was some doubt that human activity was chiefly responsible for the pollution that, it is now widely agreed, will cause a global warming trend. This would occur as carbon dioxide and other manmade pollutants trap and retain heat from the sun in a process similar to what happens in a greenhouse.</p>
        <p>''I don't think the science should be altered,'' he said in response to a question by Senator Albert Gore, the Tennessee Democrat who is chairman of the subcommmittee. ''As a Government employee, I can and certainly do support Government policy. My only objection is changing the science.'' Similar Complaint Reported</p>
        <p>Another Government scientist testified at today's hearing that the budget office had tried to change his testimony on scientific issues earlier this year.</p>
        <p>The scientist, Dr. Jerry D. Mahlman, director of the Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, said that the changes proposed for his testimony on issues related to global warming were ''objectionable and unscientific'' and that the testimony would have been ''embarrassing.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Mahlman said that he had refused to accept the changes in his testimony. ''We in the scientific community demand the right to be wrong,'' he said. Dr. Mahlman said he prevailed in his effort to prevent the budget office from changing his testimony. Dr. Hansen said, however, that the budget office insisted on editing his testimony despite his strong objections. Gore Assails Administration</p>
        <p>Senator Gore said Dr. Hansen's testimony was changed because the Bush Administration did not want to take action to cope with the expected global warming trend.</p>
        <p>He said United States officials now meeting in Geneva with delegations from other countries were arguing that more study was needed before beginning work on an international treaty aimed at reducing the impact and mitigating the effects of climate change.</p>
        <p>''President Bush, only months ago, told us he was an environmentalist,'' Mr. Gore said. ''Yet, in the past few days alone, we've seen his Administration back away from a critical diplomatic initiative on global warming.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fitzwater said President Bush's ''personal view is that this is a serious problem that America needs to show and take leadership.'' Sorting Out Conclusions</p>
        <p>''But the science is something that still has to be sorted out,'' he said. ''Obviously, the President hasn't made a judgment about scientific assessments.''</p>
        <p>The White House spokesman said that Dr. Hansen had a right to voice his opinion and that no punitive action would be taken against him for objecting to the changing of his testimony.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said that if there was any retribution against Dr. Hansen, the Bush Administration would face ''the equivalent of World War III'' with Congress.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
