<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nuclear Power Is No Solution</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="224407"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="LETTER: ON GLOBAL WARMING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PUBLIC INTEREST RESEARCH GROUP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAGAVERN, BILL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DC113DF93BA25751C0A96F948260" item-length="354" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nuclear Power Is No Solution</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''The Greenhouse Effect Is for Real'' (editorial, Jan. 27) asserts that a plan to help postpone the greenhouse effect should include development of ''a new generation of safer, cheaper nuclear power plants.'' However, nuclear power has proved to be an unsafe, unreliable, uneconomical energy source, and we would be better off pursuing the other anti-greenhouse steps you recommend: phasing out chlorofluorocarbons, developing solar power, conserving energy and preserving forests.</p>
        <p>Future reactors may prove to be less susceptible to meltdown than current plants. Or they may not; the technologies are still untested. We do know that they will not be safe: any process that produces radioactive material is inherently unsafe. Even low doses of radiation can cause genetic damage, and nuclear waste remains radioactive for 250,000 years.</p>
        <p>Construction of nuclear plants is so expensive that it has led utilities into bankruptcy and exorbitant rate increases in many regions, as Long Island Lighting Company ratepayers are painfully aware. For all that money, consumers received an unreliable source of power: nuclear utilities have operated at less than 60 percent of capacity over the last 15 years.</p>
        <p>Cheaper, safer energy is available. As Peter Passell's Jan. 18 Economic Scene column pointed out, meeting higher efficiency standards for refrigerators would alone eliminate the need to build 14 Shoreham-size power plants. Furthermore, renewable energy sources already supply 9 percent of America's total energy (more than nuclear does), and their contribution is expected to double by the year 2000. While new renewable technologies like solar photovoltaic cells are developing, efficient natural gas plants offer a low-carbon alternative at one-third the cost and one-fifth the construction time of nuclear reactors.</p>
        <p>Yes, the greenhouse effect is for real, and it calls for a rapid, effective, environmentally sound response that should not include nuclear power. BILL MAGAVERN  Washington, Jan. 31, 1989  The writer is a staff attorney for the U.S. Public Interest Research Group.</p>
        <p>LETTER: ON GLOBAL WARMING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
