<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST: FRIDAY, AUGUST 18, 1989</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="276424"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3D6143FF93BA2575BC0A96F948260" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST: FRIDAY, AUGUST 18, 1989</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  The Economy</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  The Economy</p>
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>The U.S. trade deficit narrowed sharply in June to $8.2 billion, the lowest level in four and a half years. American exports reached a record $30.9 billion, a gain of 1.5 percent, and accounted for about three-quarters of the improvement. Analysts and economists were cheered by the Commerce Department report.  [ Page A1. ]</p>
        <p>The nation's largest user of coal criticized President Bush's acid rain proposal, saying it could wreck the economy.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>The indictment of a former Boeing official is part of a broader investigation into how military contractors obtained secret Pentagon documents, Federal officials said.  [ D15. ] Markets</p>
        <p>A Goldman, Sachs partner pleaded guilty to a felony charge of insider trading. In announcing the plea by Robert A. Freeman, the Government also said it was ending its investigation of two other Wall Street traders, Richard B. Wigton and Timothy L. Tabor.  [ Page A1. ]  A former salesman with the company that prints Business Week settled insider trading charges.  [ D6. ]</p>
        <p>Treasury securities prices tumbled despite a morning rise after the Government reported a smaller-than-expected June trade deficit. The rally was halted by a Government report that the number of jobless claims fell to 317,000 in the week ended Aug. 5, from 330,000 in the preceding week.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Stock prices fell widely in the wake of a broadly lower bond market. The Dow Jones industrial average dropped 13.66 points, to 2,679.63, after being down 25 points in the early afternoon.  [ D6. ]</p>
        <p>The dollar rose sharply worldwide on news that the U.S. trade deficit narrowed in June. The rise brought the dollar near the highs it reached two months ago, but profit taking capped gains.  [ D13. ]</p>
        <p>Copper futures prices soared on New York's Commodity Exchange, extending the rally to a seventh day.  [ D13. ] Companies</p>
        <p>UAL's stock jumped 6 percent, climbing $14.625 to $266.375, on the news that Marvin Davis was willing to raise his offer for the parent of United Airlines. UAL's board met last night and said it was continuing to review its options.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Bell Atlantic reached an agreement with one striking union, the Communications Workers, although local issues remain to be settled. The company is continuing talks with the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers.  [ A10. ]</p>
        <p>Lands' End reported a big drop in second-quarter earnings that sent its stock price skidding.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Navistar said it would cut truck output by 15 percent at its plant in Springfield, Ohio, because of declining demand. It also said some assembly-line workers would be laid off.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Hewlett-Packard's earnings fell, and for the second consecutive quarter by more than analysts' had expected.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>Northwest Airlines ordered 26 more jetliners from Airbus and took options on 4 others in a deal valued at $2.7 billion.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>I.B.M. and Siemens ratified a previously announced deal for Siemens to take over part of I.B.M.'s Rolm subsidiary.  [ D4. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>No Federal Reserve chairman is a hero at the White House. Leonard Silk: Economic Scene.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>The requirement that corporate insiders report their purchases and sales of company securities on a timely basis is being studied by the S.E.C. Floyd Norris: Market Place.  [ D6. ]</p>
        <p>Liz Claiborne is introducing a men's fragrance, with a campaign seeking men who might like to take an introspective and vulnerable approach. Randall Rothenberg: Advertising.  [ D5. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
