<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Capital, Jersey Rivals Behave Like Statesmen</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="294693"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNORS (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAY, CLIFFORD D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FLORIO, JAMES J (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COURTER, JIM (REPR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DF153DF935A15753C1A96F948260" item-length="1310" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Capital, Jersey Rivals Behave Like Statesmen</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD D. MAY, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MAY, CLIFFORD D</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: During the months they have been vying for New Jersey's top office, James J. Florio and Jim Courter have appeared as likely adversaries if not natural enemies. But here in Washington, where both candidates for governor are members of the House of Representatives, they do not seem to be cut from very different cloths.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: During the months they have been vying for New Jersey's top office, James J. Florio and Jim Courter have appeared as likely adversaries if not natural enemies. But here in Washington, where both candidates for governor are members of the House of Representatives, they do not seem to be cut from very different cloths.</p>
        <p>During the months they have been vying for New Jersey's top office, James J. Florio and Jim Courter have appeared as likely adversaries if not natural enemies. But here in Washington, where both candidates for governor are members of the House of Representatives, they do not seem to be cut from very different cloths.</p>
        <p>Both are lawyers raised in New Jersey and New York. Both project images as bright, dynamic, youthful Congressmen, though Mr. Florio comes off as rough-hewn and rather earthy, in contrast to Mr. Courter who appears polished and a bit aloof.</p>
        <p>Each was elected to Congress just after his 37th birthday. Mr. Florio, at 52 years old, is four years older than Mr. Courter and preceded him on Capitol Hill by two terms. Both have been concerned about the crime, illicit drugs and soaring automobile-insurance premiums. Similar Political Traits</p>
        <p>Mr. Courter serves on the Armed Services Committee, a fitting assignment for a no-nonsense, mainstream Republican. Mr. Florio serves on Energy and Commerce, equally appropriate to a no-nonsense, mainstream Democrat. Both sit on the Select Aging Committee. (Mr. Florio has a third seat on Veterans Affairs.) ''They have very similar political characteristics,'' said Ross K. Baker, a political scientist at Rutgers University and the author of ''House and Senate,'' just published by by W. W. Norton. ''Both are serious legislators. Neither is viewed as a lightweight. I've seen both debate on the House floor and they're both good at it.''</p>
        <p>One more thing they have in common: Despite their statesmanlike demeanor on Capitol Hill, both have been willing to wage an unusually mean-spirited campaign against one another in New Jersey, one that has included sharp and sometimes loosely substantiated attacks on the honesty and integrity of the other.</p>
        <p>''It's interesting and disturbing to me,'' said Richard V. Sinding, president of the Center for Analysis of Public Issues in Princeton. ''Florio and Courter have clearly worked hard to carve out reputations in Washington as gentlemen of some substance. And yet in this race they have gone at each other like a couple of party hacks.''</p>
        <p>As members of Congress, the differences between Mr. Florio and Mr. Courter stem largely from divergent interests and priorities. In recent months, the pressures of the campaign have caused both to miss many debates and votes in the Capital.</p>
        <p>But today, Mr. Florio - who has been endorsed by abortion-rights groups - did make a brief appearance in Washington to vote for an override of President Bush's veto of a bill expanding Federal payments for abortion in cases of rape and incest. The override effort fell short of the two-thirds majority needed. Mr. Courter, who has said he opposes abortion in most cases but would not ''impose my views on the people of the state,'' decided not to interrupt his campaign schedule to participate in the vote.</p>
        <p>Mr. Florio's voting record wins the support of liberals and unions. He is widely regarded as a leading expert on the environment; most significantly, he receives primary credit for championing the establishment in 1980 of a Federal Superfund to pay for toxic-waste cleanups.</p>
        <p>His ''community right to know'' law has for the first time required corporations to tell local residents and authorities precisely what potentially hazardous substances they are producing. Three years ago, Florio legislation established a system for removing asbestos from the nation's schools.</p>
        <p>Transportation and consumer affairs have been other areas of concentration. Mr. Florio fought against cutbacks for Amtrak and for the upgrading of the passenger and freight rail system along the Eastern corridor.</p>
        <p>He has also stood out as one of only a few Democratic Congressmen to push for legislation to reduce the influence that special interest groups wield through political action committees. But such bills have not passed.  An articulate proponent of limited government, low taxes and free-market economics, Mr. Courter is also considered an expert on defense policy.</p>
        <p>But unlike most Republicans who focus on the Pentagon, he has held the generals' feet to the fire on wasteful spending. In particular, legislation he wrote has sought to increase the percentage of military contracts awarded through competitive bidding.</p>
        <p>Mr. Courter has also favored more money for military projects he considers worthwhile, like the Strategic Defense Initiative - also known as Star Wars - and he has argued for military aid to the contra rebels battling the Nicaraguan Government. Some Failures by Both</p>
        <p>''He's a smart guy and he's been a serious player on the Armed Services Committee,'' said Representative Les Aspin, the Wisconsin Democrat who is chairman of that committee. ''He's been a chief water carrier for the Administration on all the defense bills we've come out with in recent years.'</p>
        <p>Occasionally, each man has made forays into the other's sphere. Last summer, for example, Mr. Courter pushed for a bill to ban oil exploration off the New Jersey coast for the next decade, and he has advocated stricter measures for controlling acid rain.</p>
        <p>Mr. Florio was a co-author last year of an amendment to the Omnibus Trade bill authorizing the President to block any acquisition of a military supplier by a foreign company if it would jeopardize national security.</p>
        <p>Both Congressmen have also suffered what might be interpreted as failures. For example, over the 14 years that Mr. Florio has represented Camden - where he is also the leading local political power - it has continued to decline and decay. 'They've Both Done Well'</p>
        <p>Mr. Florio does not deny the deterioration, but he suggests that the onus belongs more with the Republican Administrations in Washington than with him, Congress or local officials.</p>
        <p>''The cities of our state and nation have not fared well over the last eight years,'' he said. ''At a time when cities are in a state of disrepair, the Federal Government has bailed out on making efforts to rehabilitate them.''</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Courter, even though he serves on the Military Installations and Facilities subcomittee, he failed to prevent Fort Dix, the nation's second-largest military training base, from being included among bases scheduled for scaling-down or closing.</p>
        <p>''Overall, I think they've both done well in Washington,'' said Richard Roper, director of the Program for New Jersey Affairs at Princeton. But one important difference, he added, is that ''Florio's concerns have been much more home-based, and that's got to be an advantange for somebody running for governor.</p>
        <p>Another factor working to Mr. Florio's benefit and Mr. Courter's detriment is that the Democrats have been the majority party in Congress throughout their tenure.</p>
        <p>Neither Congressman maintains a presence in Washington as they do in New Jersey. Mr. Florio generally stays in the capital only three nights a week, he said. When he is in Washington, he lives in a one-room efficiency apartment above the International Liquor Store, a few blocks from his Capitol Hill office. Mr. Courter rents a one-bedroom apartment in a renovated town house in Arlington, Va.</p>
        <p>Mr. Courter generally stays in Washington from Tuesday till Thursday, the days that the House is actually in session.</p>
        <p>Both politicians explained their desire for wanting to exchange the House of Representatives for the State House by saying that they had experienced larger than anticipated frustrations trying to translate their ideas and arguments into policies and practice in Washington.</p>
        <p>''As governor I think you could accomplish things in a way that's very difficult to do as a legislator, particularly one from the minority party,'' Mr. Courter said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Florio echoed that thought: ''In Washington you're one among many, many Congressmen. As Governor, I think I could really make an impact.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
