<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; Saving the Forest In Costa Rica</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="221407"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">COSTA RICA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Costa Rica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DA143FF93BA35751C0A96F948260" item-length="802" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; Saving the Forest In Costa Rica</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
      <dateline>QUEPOS, Costa Rica</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: FORTY years ago, 75 percent of this Vermont-sized democracy sandwiched between Nicaragua and Panama was covered by forests. Half the wilderness has since been cleared to harvest hardwoods and to open thin, easily eroded soils to subsistence farming. If deforestation continues at the current pace, Costa</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: FORTY years ago, 75 percent of this Vermont-sized democracy sandwiched between Nicaragua and Panama was covered by forests. Half the wilderness has since been cleared to harvest hardwoods and to open thin, easily eroded soils to subsistence farming. If deforestation continues at the current pace, Costa</p>
        <p>FORTY years ago, 75 percent of this Vermont-sized democracy sandwiched between Nicaragua and Panama was covered by forests. Half the wilderness has since been cleared to harvest hardwoods and to open thin, easily eroded soils to subsistence farming. If deforestation continues at the current pace, Costa Rica will run out of trees by the year 2015, with much of this fragile land ending up as low-quality pasture or scrub too poor to cultivate.</p>
        <p>But that is not likely to happen. Government officials - notably the ebullient Minister of Natural Resoures, Alvaro Umana, a physicist-turned-ecologist - have awakened to the prospect of economic disaster. They have locked up a third of the remaining forest and restricted development on another third. And they are encouraging ''debt for nature'' swaps, a form of economic alchemy in which chunks of Costa Rica's foreign debt are converted to a conservation endowment.</p>
        <p>The swaps could certainly help slow deforestation throughout the tropics, where land is being cleared at the startling rate of 100 acres a minute. But few countries are in a position to exploit such deals as skillfully as Costa Rica. And even in Costa Rica there are limits to what swaps can accomplish. The challenge is to find a way, once and for all, to link write-offs of third world debt to environmental planning on a grand scale.</p>
        <p>Costa Rica's latest initiative, announced last month, follows a now-familiar pattern. American Express Bank, a large creditor to Costa Rica (but far from its largest), sold $5.6 million in Costa Rican i.o.u.'s to the Nature Conservancy for $784,000. The Washington-based environmental group then traded the paper back to the Costa Rican central bank for $1.7 million in local-currency bonds, with the interest to be paid to a local conservation group to manage nine projects.</p>
        <p>American Express got a tax deduction - as it would with any bad debt once realized. The Costa Rican central bank retired a bit of its $1.5 billion debt to foreign banks and the Nature Conservancy doubled the purchasing power of its cash donation.</p>
        <p>If everyone benefited from a $5.6 million swap, why not think big? Why not 100 times $5.6 million? For one thing, banks holding Costa Rican debt may not be ready to dump so much of it at the current market rate of just 14 cents on the dollar. For another, conservation groups could not possibly raise 14 percent of $560 million from private donors.</p>
        <p>Then there is the problem of diverting scarce local resources to conservation. Costa Rica would be reluctant to raise taxes sufficiently to cover the interest on $170 million worth of local-currency bonds. If the central bank simply printed the money, it would have to cope with the resulting increase in purchasing power. Mr. Umana believes that no more than $15 million in foreign debt can be reabsorbed annually without unacceptable inflationary pressures.</p>
        <p>Similar constraints limit the scale of such deals elsewhere. Bolivia, Ecuador and the Philippines have exchanged debt for local currency plus commitment to preservation. But these and future swaps are too small to dent the global problem.</p>
        <p>Indeed, it is not clear that the swaps will be used at all in places where they are needed most. In Brazil, the country with by far the most forest to lose, developers call debt-for-nature deals the work of foreign devils. President Jose Sarney, engulfed in an economic crisis that threatens to topple his constitutional Government, denounced the swaps as an affront to Brazilian sovereignty.</p>
        <p>How then to protect the vanishing jungle? One approach is to create preservation plans that serve the interests of developers. In Costa Rica that will not be difficult. Tourism is a rapidly growing source of income and employment, and Mr. Umana said one tourist in three chooses Costa Rica for its natural diversity and beauty. The Ministry of Natural Resources is also pressing ''sustainable cultivation'' techniques for hardwood forests, cycles of harvesting that permit regrowth and retard erosion.</p>
        <p>But most of the world's tropical forests will be long gone before the desperately poor nations that control their destiny focus their attention on the problem. If the forests are to be saved, it will take a lot of help from the developed world.</p>
        <p>There are reasons beyond altruism and respect for nature for investing in a crash effort: tropical forests serve as both the primary source of cultivable plant species and as collectors of carbon dioxide. There is even a convenient mechanism for the investment. Forgiveness of much of the third world's $1.2 trillion hard-currency debt through officially sponsored settlements is now widely viewed as inevitable. If such settlements are linked to enforceable preservation commitments, the great forests may yet be granted a reprieve.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
