<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Fighting Global Warming Could Be Painless and Profitable</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="280356"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIFE STYLES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">REINHOLD, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Life Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DA103CF930A3575AC0A96F948260" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Fighting Global Warming Could Be Painless and Profitable</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT REINHOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REINHOLD, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: UNWELCOME as it is, the prevailing view of energy and climate experts who fear a catastrophic warming of the globe is that Americans must make drastic sacrifices in their comfortable way of life. Already, Angelenos are on the cutting edge of this brave new world without leaf blowers and drive-through burger stands, facing new controls on everyday life just to clean up the breathing air, never mind the stratosphere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: UNWELCOME as it is, the prevailing view of energy and climate experts who fear a catastrophic warming of the globe is that Americans must make drastic sacrifices in their comfortable way of life. Already, Angelenos are on the cutting edge of this brave new world without leaf blowers and drive-through burger stands, facing new controls on everyday life just to clean up the breathing air, never mind the stratosphere.</p>
        <p>UNWELCOME as it is, the prevailing view of energy and climate experts who fear a catastrophic warming of the globe is that Americans must make drastic sacrifices in their comfortable way of life. Already, Angelenos are on the cutting edge of this brave new world without leaf blowers and drive-through burger stands, facing new controls on everyday life just to clean up the breathing air, never mind the stratosphere.</p>
        <p>But a few experts believe that in warding off climatic doom, painful sacrifices can be avoided by adopting the newest in energy-saving technology, like prototype cars that get up to 138 miles per gallon and superefficient light bulbs. A leading proponent of this theory, Amory B. Lovins of the Rocky Mountain Institute, a nonprofit research group in Snowmass, Colo., says that conserving energy can actually be profitable. ''The opportunity to profit from selling efficiency is real, pervasive, and arrestingly large,'' he maintains.</p>
        <p>No one doubts that more efficient use of energy can make a big difference. But skepticism about whether this alone can head off global warming is also real, pervasive and large, as was clear at a Soviet-American conference on the greenhouse effect late last month in Sundance, Utah. Michael Deland, chairman of President Bush's Council on Environmental Quality, said Americans and Russians must cleanse their own hands and make ''fundamental changes in life style'' before preaching to the rest of the world about using too much energy.</p>
        <p>But less wrenching solutions were not entirely dismissed. Georgi S. Golitsyn of the Soviet Academy of Sciences said that energy for lighting, heating and refrigeration could be cut by a factor of 4 to 10 ''without diminishing the quality of life.'' But he admitted that the impediments are high. Soviet engineers have designed a turbine that uses heat produced during production of electricity, but manufacture is stalled while different ministries argue over who is to make them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lovins argues that about half of global warming, which is caused by the emission of carbon dioxide, chlorofluorocarbons and other industrial gases, is attributed to energy use and that three-fourths of that amount could be profitably abated by energy efficiency. For example, equipping American factories and buildings with the latest in motors and lighting fixtures would save three-quarters of all electricity used, he said, and commercially available lighting reflectors and controls could save 92 percent of lighting energy. Mr. Lovins envisions a day when saved electricity becomes a commodity itself, called ''negawatts,'' that could be traded among companies, utilities and even nations. Selling Efficiency</p>
        <p>Skeptics call such ideas brilliant in theory, but difficult in practice. Howard P. Allen, chairman of Southern California Edison, says that efficiency does not sell. Most people, he maintains, prefer to pay 49 cents for a conventional light bulb rather than $20 each for new ones that would save $4 to $5 a year in power, though commercial customers are trying such measures. Mr. Lovins says government should make efficiency more attractive, for example by taxing cars on the basis of fuel consumption to stimulate production of the new more efficient prototypes.</p>
        <p>But efficiency faces a tough political and social battle. ''Power corrupts and horsepower corrupts absolutely,'' said Stephen H. Schneider, a climatologist at the National Center for Atmospheric Research and the author of a new book, ''Global Warming.'' Owning a big car or pickup truck, even if a few bags of groceries is the heaviest load, is a symbol of affluence, he said.</p>
        <p>Analysts like Irving Mintzer of the World Resources Institute, a private research group in Washington, agree that there is room for much improvement without sacrifice in American living standards. He noted, for example, that West German industries use far less energy to make cement than American ones. But avoiding world climate change, he maintains, will also require compromises, like ride sharing and more use of mass transit. He argues for a gradual increase of the gasoline excise tax to $1 a gallon, combined with a penalty against owners of gas guzzlers paid to drivers of new efficient cars. But he said these measures would be politically impossible now.</p>
        <p>If solutions to protecting the atmosphere are difficult in developed countries they are all the more intractable in the rapidly developing third world, where the issue is often survival, not luxuries. Energy use in industrialized countries is growing by only 1 percent a year compared with 5 percent in the third world. Mr. Lovins argues that industrialized countries must stop selling obsolete technology to the third world and help them leap directly into energy-efficient industries. ''This may take considerable infusions of Western technology and currency to make this work,'' he says. ''But they'll get more barrels out of buying Western insulation, windows and light bulbs than oil-drilling equipment.''</p>
        <p>The price of this climate insurance will be high. Mr. Schneider calls for a ''global survival bargain'' between the world's have-nots and haves: The have-nots agree to reduce population growth and concede their standard of living will never equal that of the haves; the haves help the have-nots develop with low-polluting technology and reduce their own standard of living somewhat.</p>
        <p>THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
