<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="246304"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DC1239F930A35756C0A96F948260" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International A3-15  Government subsidies on wheat sales to the Soviet Union were approved by President Bush, the first time his Administration has authorized such export subsidies. Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International A3-15  Government subsidies on wheat sales to the Soviet Union were approved by President Bush, the first time his Administration has authorized such export subsidies. Page A1</p>
        <p>International A3-15  Government subsidies on wheat sales to the Soviet Union were approved by President Bush, the first time his Administration has authorized such export subsidies. Page A1</p>
        <p>The call for Afghan peace talks by the Soviet Union should be resisted by Secretary of State Baker when he visits Moscow next week, a security panel has urged. A1</p>
        <p>In refusing to open talks on weapons, President Bush is making a serious mistake, Paul H. Nitze, the Reagan Administration's top arms control adviser, said. A1</p>
        <p>Bonn's call for talks on missiles with Moscow was pressed by the Foreign Minister. The proposal was the product of his ardent conviction that a new era has dawned. A10</p>
        <p>France formally receives Arafat A3</p>
        <p>Out of concern about the ozone layer, 80 nations have indicated that they would favor banning production of certain harmful substances by the end of the century. A13</p>
        <p>Students marched through Shanghai in the first indication that China's pro-democracy movement had spread to the nation's largest city and economic capital. A8</p>
        <p>China's search for an identity was discussed at a conference in Bolinas, Calif., attended by leading advocates of further democratic change in the country. A8</p>
        <p>President Bush has warned Panama that the United States will not recognize the presidential election on Sunday if the results are rigged by Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega. A3</p>
        <p>In talks on the future of Cambodia, Prince Norodom Sihanouk requested further constitutional changes before he will return, the Cambodian Prime Minister said. A14</p>
        <p>National A16-24,B5</p>
        <p>Hopes that a new nuclear fusion might give the world an unlimited source of cheap energy appear to have been dealt a devastating blow by scientific evidence. A1</p>
        <p>The biggest drug raid in Washington has provided its own rush and letdown for law-enforcement officers who are struggling against the nation's worst cocaine epidemic. A1</p>
        <p>Little League baseball is turning 50 this year, and all across the nation, thousands of leagues in towns like Palos Hills, Ill. are renewing their seasonal bond. A16</p>
        <p>A national boycott of Exxon products was called for by consumer and environmental groups, describing the Corporation as a ''polluter without equal.'' A17</p>
        <p>Federal job training programs should be redesigned to focus on high school dropouts, welfare recipients and others with low incomes and poor skills, a study says. A16</p>
        <p>Jim Wright is still House Speaker, still in command and still conducting legislative business. That is the simple political message he is trying to convey. A24</p>
        <p>ABC dropped a crime program from its prime-time schedule last Saturday after it failed to attract any paid advertising, a problem attributed to the concerns of corporate sponsors about growing public opposition. D1</p>
        <p>Texas Air reported worsened losses for the first quarter, but analysts found hope in Continental's earnings despite a continuing strike at East D1  Navy undecided on repair of battleship turret A20</p>
        <p>Denver abolishes zoning barring outlawing unmarried couples A24</p>
        <p>Washington Talk B5</p>
        <p>Maneuvers on the Medicare surtax, delivered by Senator Lloyd Bentsen, provides the latest example of manipulative skills by the old pols on Capitol Hill.  In the capital, protection takes precedence over compromise  Regional B1-6</p>
        <p>An increase in tuition was blocked by Gov. Mario M. Cuomo an hour before a legal deadline would have allowed for a $200-a-year rise for students of New York's State University and City University systems. A1</p>
        <p>A cut in state aid has forced CUNY to offer fewer courses, increase class sizes, reduce the purchase of supplies and cut back on maintenance at many of the university's 20 colleges. B6</p>
        <p>Columbia Law Review adopts affirmative-action plan B1</p>
        <p>With the Roosevelt Raceway closed, the grandstand is crumbling, its owners are being investigated and critics say they may reap more than $100 million in profits. A1</p>
        <p>Expanding the City Council to 60, including the five borough presidents, was considered by the panel that is writing a new charter for New York City. B1  Jersey City's revaluation of property has created anger, despair and bitterness. The Jersey City Coalition for Fair Taxation argues that the appraisal was flawed. B1</p>
        <p>To improve New Jersey schools by making them compete for students, Gov. Thomas H. Kean proposed a program that would allow parents to choose the schools for their children. B2</p>
        <p>Plans for a new port on Staten Island may proceed now that a Federal judge in Brooklyn has removed the last major obstacle. Critics say it will be a nuclear base. B1</p>
        <p>Ladies' Mile was designated historic by the New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission. The commission's unanimous vote ended a three-year campaign. B3</p>
        <p>Early turnout is light in school board voting B3</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
