<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Acid Rain and Fertilization Linked to Greenhouse Effect</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="288028"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FERTILIZER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NITROGEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHANE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MARINE BIOLOGICAL LABORATORY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fertilizer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEED6173DF930A35753C1A96F948260" item-length="703" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Acid Rain and Fertilization Linked to Greenhouse Effect</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: NITROGEN deposited in the soil by acid rain and as agricultural fertilizer may be promoting an atmospheric buildup of methane gas, a major contributor to the greenhouse effect, a new study suggests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: NITROGEN deposited in the soil by acid rain and as agricultural fertilizer may be promoting an atmospheric buildup of methane gas, a major contributor to the greenhouse effect, a new study suggests.</p>
        <p>NITROGEN deposited in the soil by acid rain and as agricultural fertilizer may be promoting an atmospheric buildup of methane gas, a major contributor to the greenhouse effect, a new study suggests.</p>
        <p>Methane is produced in garbage dumps, landfills, rice paddies, bogs, marshes and the guts of cows and termites. Like carbon dioxide released by the burning of fossil fuels and the destruction of trees, it traps heat in the atmosphere and, in fact, is 20 to 30 times as efficient as carbon dioxide in doing so.</p>
        <p>The worldwide growth of both agriculture and industrial societies has caused the atmospheric concentration of methane to double since 1800, scientists estimate. Some say the gas could be responsible for as much as 20 percent of global warming caused by human activity in the next century, during which the planet's average temperature is expected to rise by 3 to 8 degrees Fahrenheit.</p>
        <p>Certain microorganisms in the soil slow the buildup of atmospheric methane by consuming it as an energy source. But the microbes prefer to use nitrogen sources when they are available. And now an experiment by scientists in Massachusetts, reported in the current issue of the British journal Nature, shows that over the short term, adding nitrogen to soil reduced the microbial intake of atmospheric methane by 33 percent.</p>
        <p>While it is too early to assess the global effect of this on levels of atmospheric methane, the results are ''certainly provocative at this point,'' said Paul A. Steudler of the Marine Biological Laboratory at Woods Hole, Mass., one of four scientists who conducted the experiment.</p>
        <p>The others were R. D. Bowden and J. M. Melillo, also of the Woods Hole laboratory, and J. D. Aber of the University of New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>Nitrogen is being deposited on soil in increasing amounts through agricultural fertilizer, whose use is increasing worldwide, and through acid rain, which is a growing problem both in Europe and North America.</p>
        <p>The Massachusetts experiment was intended primarily to assess the effect on forests of nitrogen compounds found in acid rain, which are similar to those in fertilizer. Surprised by Absorption Rate</p>
        <p>The New England experiment took place on two stands of trees in the Harvard Forest in central Massachusetts, one of hardwoods and one of pine, from May through October 1988. Nine experimental plots, each roughly 80 feet square, were delineated in each stand of trees. Three of the plots in each stand were designated as controls. A total of 82 pounds of ammonium nitrate, the basic compound in most fertilizers, was applied to another three of the plots. The investigators believe that nitrogen compounds from acid rain have the same effect as the fertilizer on microbial action and the consumption of methane. The 82-pound dose represented four times the amount of nitrogen the forests normally receive from rain. It was about equal to or a little less than the amount of nitrogen deposited by acid rain on the most polluted forests of Europe. The remaining three plots in each stand of trees received a combined dose of 265 pounds of ammonium nitrate. In all cases, the fertilizer was deposited in six equal applications over the six-month period.</p>
        <p>Methane was measured periodically inside a special five-sided plastic chamber installed on each plot.</p>
        <p>To their surprise, the researchers found that much more methane was absorbed by microbes in the soil of the unfertilized plots than previous investigators had reported. This, the scientists said, suggests that forests in temperate zones and colder latitudes may play a much larger role than tropical forests in removing methane from the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>After six months, the experimenters found, methane consumption in the plots that had been most highly fertilized declined by 33 percent compared with the control plots, Whether this rate would hold over a longer term is uncertain and can be determined only by future experiments. Nevertheless, the scientists said, the findings suggest that methane consumption may be suppressed in agricultural areas and forests affected by acid rain. Further measurements are necessary before any conclusions can be drawn about these effects on a global basis, they said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
