<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shaping a Summit Agenda: Mitterrand and Bush Goals</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="265128"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOODS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">POLAND</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BANGLADESH</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITTERRAND, FRANCOIS (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Bangladesh</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DF1E3EF932A25754C0A96F948260" item-length="1192" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shaping a Summit Agenda: Mitterrand and Bush Goals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, July 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As the leaders of the seven leading industrialized democracies prepare to meet here on Friday, President Francois Mitterrand of France is pushing for the annual Group of Seven summit conference to focus on helping the world's poor nations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As the leaders of the seven leading industrialized democracies prepare to meet here on Friday, President Francois Mitterrand of France is pushing for the annual Group of Seven summit conference to focus on helping the world's poor nations.</p>
        <p>As the leaders of the seven leading industrialized democracies prepare to meet here on Friday, President Francois Mitterrand of France is pushing for the annual Group of Seven summit conference to focus on helping the world's poor nations.</p>
        <p>With France celebrating the 200th anniversary of its Revolution, Mr. Mitterrand wants the talks to help lighten the third world's $1.3 trillion debt burden and to underwrite a $5 billion project to fight flooding in Bangladesh.</p>
        <p>But President Bush, attending his first summit meeting as President, already appears to be undercutting, or at least sidetracking, Mr. Mitterrand's agenda by pushing for the talks to focus more on Eastern Europe. Mr. Bush, who will have just visited Poland and Hungary, will press the leaders to make a strong statement supporting the moves toward democracy in those countries.</p>
        <p>Officials planning the three-day talks say Mr. Bush, who today announced a six-part program of American aid to Poland, will call on his partners to provide more aid to Poland. But there is already some dispute among the meeting nations about how much of the aid should come from deficit-ridden Washington and how much from Eastern Europe's neighbors in Western Europe. The Group of Seven nations that will be meeting in Paris - the United States, France, Britain, West Germany, Italy, Canada and Japan - are expected to back President Bush's call for debt relief for Poland, including rescheduling its $39 billion in debt. 5,000 Journalists With 5,000 journalists converging on Paris, the summit conference could become, like some of the 14 previous meetings, a klieg-light-filled stage. With the world watching, the leaders seize the occasion to try to carve out the image they want.</p>
        <p>While some French politicians and newspapers have accused President Mitterrand of trying to turn the ''bicentennial'' summit meeting into a coronation, Mr. Mitterrand's aides say he his goal for the talks is to carry on the ideals of the French Revolution.</p>
        <p>For his part, President Bush, some French commentators say, wants to show that he is leader of the West and that Mikhail S. Gorbachev, the Soviet leader, has nothing on him in setting the world's agenda.</p>
        <p>With the rise of the Green movement in many countries, the leaders are also jockeying to show they are friends of the earth. Thus the environment will be high on the agenda, with agreements in sight on protecting the ozone layer and oceans. There is a dispute, however, on the best approach to take on the problem of global warming.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, one senior official working on preparations for the talks said, ''The fact that this will be the first time the environment is looked at fully at a summit shows that this is a turning point.''</p>
        <p>With the dollar sliding in recent days back into a range that finance ministers find comfortable, several officials said the dollar would not be a big issue. They said the Group of Seven would repeat past statements about the benefits of currency stability, fighting inflation and international economic cooperation. Often a Maverick</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitterrand, often an unpredictable maverick at international gatherings, is under intense criticism at home for making the celebration of the French Revolution an event dominated by the rich - or at least the rich nations. Thus, Mr. Mitterrand's aides say, he will use the summit conference itself to show his critics he is the best friend the poor nations have in the industrial world.</p>
        <p>To make sure the bicentennial celebrations are not an exclusive preserve of the rich nations, the French Government also plans to entertain leaders from two dozen developing nations, including India, Pakistan, Mexico, Brazil, the Philippines, Senegal and Zaire.</p>
        <p>The visiting leaders from poor and rich nations alike will be treated by the French to dinner at the new Glass Pyramid at the Louvre, the opening of the new Bastille Opera House and good seats for the Bicentennial Parade on the Champs-Elysees on Friday. There will be 30,000 soldiers and police officers for security. Extending Hand to Poor</p>
        <p>The summit conference itself will extend a hand to poor nations in several ways.</p>
        <p>First, the industrial world's leaders will seek to give some impetus to the four-month-old debt plan proposed by Treasury Secretary Nicholas F. Brady. This plan calls for commercial banks to reduce the annual debt service of middle-income countries.</p>
        <p>Several officials from several countries said they wanted to continue putting pressure on commercial banks to make concessions to the middle-income debtor nations like Brazil and Mexico. They said it was not yet time for the industrial nations to adopt a more generous debt strategy because that could reduce the pressure on the commercial banks.</p>
        <p>Several months ago French officials said they would push for a plan in which the International Monetary Fund would use $10 billion in special drawing rights to guarantee interest payments owed by debtor nations. This would give banks an incentive to forgive some debts or lend new money. Time Is Not Right</p>
        <p>French officials now say that the time is not right for a new plan and that the Brady plan should be given a chance to work. However, since President Mitterrand is under such pressure to show he is a friend of the poor, some officials believe he might begin arguing that the Brady plan is inadequate and a new plan is needed.</p>
        <p>In another measure to help the poor, the seven leaders are expected to agree to pursue a $5 billion, 20-year program to protect Bangladesh against flooding. President Mitterrand is pushing for a program to build embankments and take other flood-prevention measures. In September, more than 2,000 people died in Bangladesh from flooding that left millions homeless.</p>
        <p>''This will prove to the world that we can provide concrete help to people in need,'' one aide said.</p>
        <p>France also hopes to win backing for a plan that would combine scientific studies and land-management programs to fight the expansion of the Sahara. Some 20 million acres are lost each year to desert, and the plan aims to help reverse the loss of grazing land.</p>
        <p>On the issue of global warming, France is seeking an agreement to cut carbon dioxide emissions contingent upon scientific findings that global warming is, in fact, taking place. Many scientists say heat is trapped as carbon dioxide builds up in the atmosphere. Approach Called Hasty</p>
        <p>But some officials say the French approach is too hasty because so many scientists are not convinced that global warming is occurring. ''The idea of reducing carbon dioxide emissions will hurt because it involves cars, power plants and factories,'' one aide said.</p>
        <p>Several officials foresee a compromise in which the leaders call for an international conference on global warming.</p>
        <p>''Environmental protection has to be based on sound science, but we also need to say on sound economics as well,'' one senior British official said.</p>
        <p>Several aides said the seven nations would affirm in strong language May's Helsinki agreement, in which 81 nations declared their intent to phase out the use of chlorofluorocarbons by 2000.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
