<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Up From Reagan</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="220062"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WICKER, TOM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REILLY, WILLIAM K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BAKER, JAMES A 3D (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">OP-ED</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6D6133DF930A35751C0A96F948260" item-length="788" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Up From Reagan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Tom Wicker</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WICKER, TOM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Forget all that family hoopla, the pork rinds nonsense and the good-old-boy image-making. Reserve judgment on the savings account ''fee'' fiasco. All that's par for the course for any new President. On two major fronts, however, the Bush Administration really has asserted itself as an improvement on its predecessor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Forget all that family hoopla, the pork rinds nonsense and the good-old-boy image-making. Reserve judgment on the savings account ''fee'' fiasco. All that's par for the course for any new President. On two major fronts, however, the Bush Administration really has asserted itself as an improvement on its predecessor.</p>
        <p>Forget all that family hoopla, the pork rinds nonsense and the good-old-boy image-making. Reserve judgment on the savings account ''fee'' fiasco. All that's par for the course for any new President. On two major fronts, however, the Bush Administration really has asserted itself as an improvement on its predecessor.</p>
        <p>What postwar Secretary of State before James A. Baker ever chose to make his first significant pronouncement not on Soviet-American relations, or arms control, or NATO, but on the global environment? As if that were not enough to prove the Administration's environmental intentions, William K. Reilly, the new head of the E.P.A., followed with a promise of legislation to curb acid rain.</p>
        <p>These developments may prove more significant, though they gained lesser headlines, than the retreat by John Tower, the Secretary of Defense-designate, from the overblown Reagan conception of Star Wars, or space-based defense against nuclear missiles. It's true that only former President Reagan and his most sycophantic followers any longer believed in his original pipe dream of making missiles ''impotent and obsolete''; too many technical obstacles, some seeming insurmountable, had been shown to stand in the way of such an impenetrable missile shield.</p>
        <p>These obstacles had not persuaded Mr. Reagan or his relentless Secretary of Defense, Caspar Weinberger, to compromise on their demands for funds for the so-called Strategic Defense Initiative, or to modify their insistence on it in arms control negotiations with the Soviet Union -though it was clear that, in practice, S.D.I. research was moving more toward point defense for U.S. nuclear installations than toward the overall shield Mr. Reagan had envisioned.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tower, once an ardent supporter of S.D.I., conceded in his confirmation hearings that such a shield was not a practical prospect, thus signaling a far more restrained missile defense policy for the Bush Administration. This should make possible substantial reductions in the Pentagon budget, and may signal greater emphasis on more practical measures to improve nuclear deterrence - mobile missiles, for example.</p>
        <p>Just as important, a more restrained defense research program makes likely a more flexible U.S. bargaining position in arms control talks with the Soviet Union. The prospect of a full-scale U.S. effort to develop a space-based defense, which the Soviets regard not only as destabilizing to mutual deterrence but as a potential offensive threat, has been perhaps the greatest obstacle to an arms reduction treaty. It also led to the Reagan Administration's one-sided effort to reinterpret the ABM treaty to permit Star Wars testing and development.</p>
        <p>Restraint on Star Wars had been more or less expected to follow Mr. Reagan's departure. During his Presidential campaign, moreover, Mr. Bush proclaimed himself an environmentalist, improved his prospects in California by promising to curtail offshore oil drilling, and blasted his opponent for Boston Harbor pollution.</p>
        <p>Still, the immediacy with which two of Mr. Bush's principal appointees moved to associate the new Administration with both global and domestic environmental concerns was unexpected but welcome. The Reagan Administration had given no sign of any interest whatever in the ''greenhouse effect'' - the threat of rising temperatures worldwide because of excessive discharges of carbon dioxide and other gases into the atmosphere, which could cause rising sea levels and disastrous changes in climate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baker told an international conference that the world could not defer action until all uncertainties about the greenhouse effect were cleared up. ''Time will not make the problem go away,'' he asserted. Indeed not, and here again, effective action will involve steps useful for more than controlling climate change - a reduction, for example, in fossil fuel consumption.</p>
        <p>As for acid rain, the Reagan Administration finally conceded the problem but avoided doing anything about it by calling for more study. In contrast, Mr. Reilly said the Bush Administration already was developing legislation to reduce acid precipitation caused by coal-burning power plants and other industrial sources. This is a complicated political problem, because the emissions arise in some states while the pollution falls in others; and the remedy in many cases will be costly.</p>
        <p>What action will follow these bold promises remains to be seen, and first indications were that the U.S. had no strong proposals ready to follow up Secretary Baker's greenhouse speech. Nevertheless, he and Mr. Reilly have committed the new Administration -as did Mr. Tower on strategic defense - and those are long steps up from the Reagan years.</p>
        <p>IN THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
