<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FASHION: Gone Fishing; If the Fin Fits, Someone Is Wearing It</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="52" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="270591"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOCHSWENDER, WOODY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1D6103CF933A05754C0A96F948260" item-length="725" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FASHION: Gone Fishing; If the Fin Fits, Someone Is Wearing It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WOODY HOCHSWENDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOCHSWENDER, WOODY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: August is the time of year when it would be nice to live the life of a fish. What could be better than being constantly underwater, borne by cool currents, feasting on colorful algae and, of course, smaller fish?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: August is the time of year when it would be nice to live the life of a fish. What could be better than being constantly underwater, borne by cool currents, feasting on colorful algae and, of course, smaller fish?</p>
        <p>August is the time of year when it would be nice to live the life of a fish. What could be better than being constantly underwater, borne by cool currents, feasting on colorful algae and, of course, smaller fish?</p>
        <p>For reasons unfathomable, fish seem to be in fashion. When the air seems the density of water, fish styles are seen more and more on the street. But they also seem to be in fashion in the wider sense, showing up as motifs in architecture, home furnishings, jewelry and other designed objects. In clothing, they show up on everything from T-shirts to scarves to designer dresses.</p>
        <p>Sybilla, the acclaimed Spanish designer, incorporated fish forms in her collection two season ago in Milan, Italy. The French designer Thierry Mugler built his entire spring-summer 1989 collection around the fish theme: slinky evening sheaths with fish-gill detailing along the hips, fin bracelets and earrings, and shark-jaw trims on jackets. At his fashion show in Paris last year, models in seaweed dresses wrestled in tangled messes on the runway.</p>
        <p>On these shores, Marc Jacobs, the new designer at Perry Ellis, showed long, shimmery mermaid gowns in his first fall collection for the company. The shiny sequins, in bands of tropical colors, resemble fish scales. The dresses are currently in the windows of Bergdorf Goodman.</p>
        <p>In the book ''Scenes From the Fashionable World'' by Kennedy Fraser (Knopf, 1987), society is likened to a lobster, crawling along the ocean bottom of life, with fashion the antennae telling what's ahead. Does fish wear suggest an unconscious awareness of something like the greenhouse effect, for instance, which could lead to major population centers being underwater? Or is it subliminal sympathy for oil-doused ocean life? It could be a lot simpler than that. ''Fish are cool and have a nice shape,'' said David Hudnut, encountered at Broadway and 79th Street in Manhattan wearing a fish-print shirt. ''This is a holy mackerel shirt.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hudnut, a student at the Columbia University School of International and Public Affairs, could think of no underlying causes. ''I'm just a slimy guy, I guess,'' he said.  A Fish Skyscraper?</p>
        <p>Frank Gehry, the architect, is somewhat obsessed with fish. Mr. Gehry has constructed fish sculptures, a carp lamp and a fish room for an exhibition at the Whitney Museum of American Art. He once designed a New York skyscraper in the shape of a fish (it was never built) and uses fish forms in his building designs.</p>
        <p>''I started using fish forms when post-modernism began,'' Mr. Gehry said. ''Everybody seemed to be looking backward. So I said why not look further back - to 300 million years before man.''</p>
        <p>The fish motif turns up in chi-chi interiors everywhere, from the designer Katharine Hamnett's shop in London, which has a tank of tropical fish, to the jewelry department of Barneys New York, with its beautiful wall of aquariums, to Teddy's, the TriBeCa restaurant, with its colorful collection of aquatic chordates. There's no wriggling out of it. Undersea horror films are now the rage in Hollywood, with James Cameron's ''Abyss'' due to open in theaters later this month. Scuba trips are the hot vacation getaway.</p>
        <p>The American Museum of Natural History has opened a cocktail lounge called the Whale's Lair in the middle of its Hall of Ocean Life, where fashionable people can sip deep blue drinks beneath the dorsaling splendors of a full-scale model of the colossal blue whale. The museum also sells a wide variety of fish prints and objects in its gift shop: lacquer fish boxes from the Soviet Union, Thai jewelry and carved African stones.</p>
        <p>''There's always been an interest in fish,'' said Martin Tekulsky, manager of the shop. ''But the single hottest category remains the dinosaur.''</p>
        <p>Unlike dinosaurs, fish have always been fashionable. Consider the Art Deco sunfish, or even the lowly flounder. A flounder, through a biological fluke, so to speak, is able to adjust its coloring to mimic the ocean floor where it resides. This is a bit like the downtown crowd who wear black clothes studded with metal pieces, camouflage for downtown's dank, industrial cityscape.</p>
        <p>''Man is more closely related to the salmon than is the salmon to the shark,'' says the text for an exhibit at the Museum of Natural History. Words to contemplate while eating poached salmon.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
