<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is It Thatcher's Britain?</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="233956"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="AT HOME ABROAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC WORKS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, ANTHONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">THATCHER, MARGARET H (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">OP-ED</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Works</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D91539F930A15750C0A96F948260" item-length="749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is It Thatcher's Britain?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anthony Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, ANTHONY</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In the London subway system, much of it deep underground, nearly a third of the escalators are not working. Two recent commuter train crashes killed more than 40 people. Many of the country's hospitals are in a Dickensian state.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In the London subway system, much of it deep underground, nearly a third of the escalators are not working. Two recent commuter train crashes killed more than 40 people. Many of the country's hospitals are in a Dickensian state.</p>
        <p>In the London subway system, much of it deep underground, nearly a third of the escalators are not working. Two recent commuter train crashes killed more than 40 people. Many of the country's hospitals are in a Dickensian state.</p>
        <p>Those are examples of a condition that is nagging at Britain's political consciousness. Public goods are in decay. People are increasingly aware of it, and they do not like it.</p>
        <p>After 10 years of the gospel according to Margaret Thatcher, people are discovering that market economics and individual acquisitiveness have their limits. A good life also requires healthy public institutions. It requires services that only the community -the Government - can provide.</p>
        <p>None of this indicates that Mrs. Thatcher is going to lose the next election. She still has many advantages over a divided opposition. But in the politics of ideas that she has dominated for so long, her ideas are fading. Government intervention is once again discussed as a necessity of modern society, not as an evil. And she knows it.</p>
        <p>One of Mrs. Thatcher's most amazing performances has been her sudden emergence as a Green - a politician devoted to saving the environment. Nothing in the last 10 years suggested that she would favor tight Government controls to prevent destruction of the earth, but that is now her posture.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago she presided over an international conference on saving the ozone layer. Then her Chancellor of the Exchequer, Nigel Lawson, introduced tax measures to discourage the use of leaded gasoline - which is still scandalously dominant in sales here, with dangerous effects on the air.</p>
        <p>Pollution is a subject of real public concern. People talk about the devastation of their beaches and their air as the British never used to. Mrs. Thatcher has responded, and won the praise of environmentalists.</p>
        <p>The most sensitive subject, politically, is probably health. The Conservative Government has proposed a reform of the National Health Service to make it more efficient. The reform does not follow Thatcher ideological lines. But polls show a hostile public reaction, apparently indicating fear that Mrs. Thatcher is basically antagonistic to the idea of the Health Service.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Thatcher is giving her opponents an advantage at the moment by taking an extreme ideological line on one front. She is pushing a pet scheme to privatize water supply in the country. Since the result would only be to exchange public for private monopolies - not for a free market - even some of her friends consider this political folly.</p>
        <p>The broader opposition argument is that Britain desperately needs more public investment: in schools and roads and hospitals and the like. It is increasingly, in Prof. J. K. Galbraith's phrase, a land of private affluence and public squalor.</p>
        <p>The Thatcher Government has squeezed Britain's universities so hard that dozens of leading academics have moved to America. Much-praised artistic institutions are under pressure from cutbacks in government support. Mrs. Thatcher is trying to upset the broadcasting system that is generally regarded as the best in the world.</p>
        <p>In short, there are plenty of reasons for political discontent. To them can be added the simple fact that Mrs. Thatcher has been in office for so long. Lately she has seemed to take almost a regal view of her position, using the royal we. On a television program after the birth of her first grandchild she said, ''We have become a grandmother.'' The sentence did not go down well in a country that cherishes its real Queen.</p>
        <p>The leader of the Labor Party, Neil Kinnock, has improved his position. He is slowly but surely shedding the policies of the extreme left that did the party so much damage, moving it back toward the center. He has performed well in the House of Commons. Current polls show Labor drawing almost even with the Tories.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kinnock still has tough problems. One is the pro-Thatcher tilt of the press. Rupert Murdoch owns newspapers with 34 percent of the national circulation, including The Sun and the News of the World, the largest-selling daily and Sunday papers. Mr. Murdoch admires Mrs. Thatcher and is not shy about that.</p>
        <p>The formidable fact is the division of the opposition. In addition to Labor, there are now two small center parties. In Britain's electoral system, the party with the most votes in each parliamentary constituency wins, so the Tories may take many a seat as the largest minority, as long as the opponents are split.</p>
        <p>AT HOME ABROAD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
