<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S.-Soviet Citizen Forum: Fewer Rifts Now</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="296274"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">US-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-USSR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CHAUTAUQUA INSTITUTION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ARGUMENTY I FAKTY (SOVIET NEWSPAPER)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEAR, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STARKOV, VLADISLAV A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORBACHEV, MIKHAIL S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">POZNER, VLADIMIR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DD153EF932A05753C1A96F948260" item-length="818" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S.-Soviet Citizen Forum: Fewer Rifts Now</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PEAR, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>PITTSBURGH, Oct. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Soviet and American citizens celebrated the improvement in relations between their two nations today as they met here for their fifth annual exercise in people-to-people diplomacy. But the occasion was marred by American concern about a Soviet editor who was not allowed to attend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Soviet and American citizens celebrated the improvement in relations between their two nations today as they met here for their fifth annual exercise in people-to-people diplomacy. But the occasion was marred by American concern about a Soviet editor who was not allowed to attend.</p>
        <p>Soviet and American citizens celebrated the improvement in relations between their two nations today as they met here for their fifth annual exercise in people-to-people diplomacy. But the occasion was marred by American concern about a Soviet editor who was not allowed to attend.</p>
        <p>Officials from the two countries, speaking at the conference sponsored by the University of Pittsburgh and the Chautauqua Institution, said they hoped that they could reach significant agreements to reduce both conventional and nuclear weapons before the summit meeting tentatively planned for late spring or early summer of 1990.</p>
        <p>Vladimir F. Petrovsky, a Soviet Deputy Foreign Minister, said such agreements, including one to reduce strategic offensive arms by 50 percent, were possible if ''both sides make vigorous efforts.'' Such a timetable is highly optimistic and would require spectacularly rapid progress by arms negotiators.</p>
        <p>The Chautauqua conferences, which began a few months after Mikhail S. Gorbachev took power in 1985, have become a barometer of Soviet-American relations, marked in the past by fierce debates and ideological fireworks. But there are fewer points of contention this year, and the conference has become a forum for charting cooperation on economic matters. Pittsburgh's Perestroika</p>
        <p>Senator John Heinz, Republican of Pennsylvania, and Wesley W. Posvar, president of the University of Pittsburgh, said the Soviets could learn many lessons about perestroika from Pittsburgh, which has restructured its economy in the last decade, with the demise of big steel plants and the rise of high-technology industries.</p>
        <p>Vladislav A. Starkov, chief editor of the weekly tabloid Argumenty i Fakty, had been scheduled to attend the conference, but he is not here. A senior member of the staff of the Central Committee of the Soviet Communist Party, Leonid N. Dobrokhotov, said Mr. Starkov had been ''advised'' to remain in Moscow.</p>
        <p>''It was not punishment,'' the party official said. ''He is a Communist. We have the right to advise members of the party to do something or not to do something. He agreed with it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Starkov published a reader survey that cast doubt on President Gorbachev's popularity and glorified his more radical critics.</p>
        <p>Vladimir V. Pozner, the Soviet television commentator who is serving as a moderator for some of the sessions here, expressed ''sympathy and support'' for his journalistic colleague. He deplored the effort to remove Mr. Starkov, who he said was ''fighting back.''</p>
        <p>American delegates said the exclusion of Mr. Starkov was inconsistent with the spirit of Chautauqua, an intellectual, ecumenical retreat in western New York that promotes cultural exchanges and uncensored debate on political issues. Wide Range of Topics</p>
        <p>Among the topics to be discussed by Soviet and American experts in open sessions at the six-day conference this week are trade and economics, arms control, human rights, the role of ''women in contemporary society,'' regional conflicts, drug abuse, the exploration of outer space and environmental issues like acid rain and global warming.</p>
        <p>At the insistence of Soviet officials, the program also includes discussions of ''religious pluralism'' and ethnic diversity in the Soviet Union and the United States.</p>
        <p>Seventy-nine families in the Pittsburgh area have opened their homes to members of the Soviet delegation, who are sampling American supermarkets, pizza parlors, and sports events.</p>
        <p>The United States Government strongly supports this type of citizen diplomacy, and the United States Information Agency helps with the arrangements.</p>
        <p>Surveying Soviet-American relations, Curtis W. Kamman, a Deputy Assistant Secretary of State, said the two nations were no longer just adversaries, but ''cooperative partners in certain respects.''</p>
        <p>''A key difference is the fact that the ideological component of U.S.-Soviet relations has diminished,'' he said. ''This has allowed both countries to move away from an ideological prism and thus find a more realistic and pragmatic way of tackling problems.'' Nicaragua Issue Raised</p>
        <p>Mr. Kamman called on the Soviet Union to make sure that the Government of Nicaragua did not resume combat operations against guerrilla forces backed by the United States. President Daniel Ortega Saavedra of Nicaragua has threatened to break the 19-month truce because of renewed attacks by the contras. Mr. Kamman complained that the continued shipment of arms to Nicaragua from Soviet bloc countries ''makes it much more difficult'' to have free elections of the type promised for February 1990.</p>
        <p>Mr. Petrovsky said the Soviet Union had agreed to ''desist from shipping arms to Nicaragua'' as part of an effort to promote a political settlement there.</p>
        <p>More generally, Mr. Petrovsky said that Moscow wanted to ''become an equal and predictable member of the civilized community of nations.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
