<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bay Area Brewpubs: Beer at the Source</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="247747"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="FARE OF THE COUNTRY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SAN FRANCISCO (CALIF)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FUSSELL, BETTY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/San Francisco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DE1438F934A35756C0A96F948260" item-length="1786" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bay Area Brewpubs: Beer at the Source</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BETTY FUSSELL; BETTY FUSSELL, the author of ''Food in Good Season'' (Knopf), lives in New York.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FUSSELL, BETTY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: CALIFORNIA still has the jump on the rest of the country when it comes to pioneering America's revolution in food and drink. Lately the state has turned its attention to beer; the repeal in 1976 of a Prohibition-era law against homebrewing has allowed a new generation of homebrewers and microbreweries to flourish.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: CALIFORNIA still has the jump on the rest of the country when it comes to pioneering America's revolution in food and drink. Lately the state has turned its attention to beer; the repeal in 1976 of a Prohibition-era law against homebrewing has allowed a new generation of homebrewers and microbreweries to flourish.</p>
        <p>CALIFORNIA still has the jump on the rest of the country when it comes to pioneering America's revolution in food and drink. Lately the state has turned its attention to beer; the repeal in 1976 of a Prohibition-era law against homebrewing has allowed a new generation of homebrewers and microbreweries to flourish. The revolution skyrocketed, however, in 1983, when California became the first state to repeal laws forbidding the sale of beer in breweries.</p>
        <p>Within the year, the nation's first post-Prohibition brewpub opened, in Hopland, appropriately, where the Mendocino Brewing Company restored the century-old remnants of the Hopvine Saloon. Now, of the 100 brewpubs nationwide, 29 are in California, with more opening every month. Most are in the San Francisco Bay Area, running north to Mendocino, south to Santa Cruz and east to Sacramento. Pubcrawlers who venture from San Francisco to Berkeley, Oakland and Walnut Creek (the Bay Area Rapid Transit system, or BART, will take you there) can sample, compare and discuss the beers of a dozen brewpubs.</p>
        <p>The beauty of brewpubs, according to Michael Lewis, known locally as the ''brewru'' who heads the School of Fermentation Sciences at the University of California in Davis, is the intimacy between brewer and drinker, brought together over a frothing glass. Just as the brew travels but a few feet from vat to tap instead of thousands of bottled miles, so the brewer has but to step from behind the glass wall that separates his copper tanks from the bar to chat up the customers for reactions to his latest work. Since many customers are themselves homebrewers, palates are as informed as the talk is heady with terms like ''peachy aromas'' and ''rich coffee and chocolate overtones.''</p>
        <p>Most brewpubs regularly make three kinds of beer - usually a light ale, a medium ale and a dark porter or stout - with seasonal specialties where the brewer can flaunt his creative potential. Most of the Bay Area brewpubs brew ale, rather than lager, and good ale means beer that is fresh, natural and redolent of flavor, as opposed to standardized commercial beers designated for quantity consumption and eternal shelf life. Fresh means the beer is on tap as soon as the fermenting process is completed. Natural means no fillers like rice, corn and sugar and no chemical preservatives. Brewpubs boast that their beers contain only the elements prescribed by Duke Wilhelm of Bavaria in the 16th century when he enacted a purity of beer law, known in the trade as Reinheitsgebot - malted grains such as barley as well as water and hops - plus yeast. Flavor depends on the recipe and skill of the brewmaster in combining different roastings and dryings of malted grains with different temperatures and fermentation periods.</p>
        <p>Since 94 percent of the beer consumed in America (and produced by the six giants) is light lager, more distinguishable by brand name than by taste, the brewpub offers not only variety and quality in its handcrafted brews, but also flavors and names as fanciful and quirky as the whim of its brewers - Deep Ender Dark, Hooker Oak Amber, Pelican Ale, Grail Ale, Earthquake Pale, Seismic Ale, Blue Whale Ale.</p>
        <p>Legally what matters in a brewpub - and what distinguishes it from a microbrewery - is that food must be served along with drink. Just as California developed a food style to go with its native wines, now it's developing a style of beer cuisine. Most brewpubs began with simple hearty fare but stellar chefs like Alice Waters of Berkeley's Chez Panisse and Narsai David, a restaurateur and radio commentator, are now designing menus for local pubs. Wolfgang Puck of Spago in Los Angeles has promised to open his own brewpub later this year in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>GOOD beer and good atmosphere tend to go together in the Bay Area because of its abundance of old saloons. Barbary Coast atmosphere is what draws the crowds to San Francisco's first brewpub, the San Francisco Brewing Company, founded in 1985 by Allan Paul, and situated on Columbus and Pacific Avenues near North Beach and the Financial District. For his brewpub, Mr. Paul converted a classic turn-of-the-century saloon, the Albatross, with stained glass windows, brass ceiling fans and carved mahogany bar. The San Francisco Brewing Company is rare in these parts in that it offers lagers, or bottom-fermented brews, as well as top-fermented ales. The basic house brews are Albatross Lager and the light amber Emperor Norton Lager, in addition to specialties like Year of the Dragon Ale, a pale ale of medium body, with a malty, fairly assertive hop flavor. Food is mostly sandwiches and snacks, among the best of which is a broiled hot Louisiana sausage sandwich with peppers and onions.</p>
        <p>Oldtime corner-saloon comfort is what draws students and others to Berkeley's major brewpub, Triple Rock Brewery and Alehouse, founded by John and Reid Martin in 1986 on Shattuck Avenue, heart of what's called the gourmet ghetto that encompasses Chez Panisse and the Acme Bakery. The alehouse is a neighborhood joint of pine and old brick, with chalkboard menu and walls of beer memorabilia to contemplate - posters, trays, bottles, ads - while sampling the house trio of the light and fruity Pinnacle Pale Ale, hearty Red Rock Ale and a dark, nutty Black Rock Porter. Specialty ales may include their Ollalaberry Wheat Beer, a light summer brew with a pinkish-red hue from the berries, which resemble blueberries, or Bug Juice Ale, which has a strong malt flavor, nicely balanced with hops. When you've had your fill of watching the brewmasters work at the front of the alehouse, you can climb to the beer garden on Top of the Rock to eat your bowl of black bean chicken chili or a sandwich of roast beef and Swiss cheese, slavered with blue cheese dressing, on a Semifreddi Bakery baguette flavored with anise and poppy seeds. Not exactly standard beer fare.</p>
        <p>At Devil Mountain Brewery in Walnut Creek, founded in 1987, Greg Jones has gone all out for atmosphere in converting an 1891 Southern Pacific train station into a brewhouse and bar, and a 1919 Pullman observation car into a dining room. Appropriately, his regular beers include smooth and creamy Railroad Ale, full-bodied Iron Horse Ale, and a dark, rich, full-bodied stout called the Devil's Brew. Each of these was a winner at the Great American Beer Festival held in Denver last summer with 168 beers competing to satisfy the tastes of 6,000 drinkers. With live blues on tap on the weekends and a new chef from the Union Hotel, Lev Dagan, in the galley, Devil Mountain's menu is more extensive than most, featuring sausage, pasta and mushroom dishes according to the season.</p>
        <p>One of the most recent brewpubs is the Pacific Coast Brewing Company, founded in 1988 in downtown Oakland by a trio of college roommates, Barry Lazarus, Steve Wolff and Don Gortemiller. They've restored the Victorian interior of the old Cox Saloon on Washington Street, refurbishing its stained glass windows and carved mahogany bar, adding a dartboard in the back and a rhythm-and-blues band on occasion. Their regular brews are a hearty, robust pale Gray Whale Ale, a hefty Orca Porter and rotating specialties like Yellow Jacket Ale, which has honey added. Menus suggest English pub fare with a plowman's platter of fruit, sausage and cheese, a daily specialty sausage and a Cornish pastie served with a salad. An outdoor beer garden is in the works.</p>
        <p>At least five new brewpubs are supposed to be opening shortly; if you want to know where they are, ask any brewpub brewer as you sample his ale and discuss its peachy, raspberry or chocolate aroma.  BREWING AND SAMPLING  The Process</p>
        <p>Brewing begins with malted barley grains, which have been partly germinated and then dried. If they are then lightly toasted, they produce pale beers; if heavily toasted, they produce dark beers such as stout. Unmalted barley is sometimes darkly roasted to produce nutty, dark beers. If the barley is soaked and dried a second time, it produces a red toffee-tasting beer.</p>
        <p>The first step in brewing is mashing, where the malted grain is crushed and mixed with 170-degree water in the ''mash tun.'' Enzymes in the grain separate out the starch from a sweet liquid extract, now rich in maltose, called ''wort.''</p>
        <p>The wort is then strained into the boil kettle for heating. Once the wort is boiled, hops are added for flavor and preserving. Hops are the dried green buds of a plant related to marijuana that contribute to a beer's distinctive aroma and somewhat bitter taste.</p>
        <p>The wort is clarified at a boiling point called ''the hot break,'' where the brewer stirs the liquid with a wooden canoe paddle in order to create a whirlpool, with the debris collecting at the center and the liquor can be drawn off from the side. The wort is then cooled to around 70 degrees before yeast is added for fermentation in a stainless steel tank in the ''clean room.''</p>
        <p>When the primary fermenting is completed (which takes from two to seven days), the tank of ''green beer'' is sealed to trap the natural carbon dioxide and then cooled to allow longer fermentation (about two weeks for ales). From here the brew is pumped straight from serving tank to bar to drinker's glass.  Pubs to Visit</p>
        <p>San Francisco Brewing Company, 155 Columbus Avenue, San Francisco; 415-434-3344. Open Sundays and weekdays from 11:30 A.M. to 12:30 A.M.; Thursdays, Fridays and Saturdays to 2 P.M. Lagers at $2 a glass, $2.75 a pint. Sandwiches from $4.50 to $6.95, snacks $2.95 to $4.95.</p>
        <p>Triple Rock Brewery and Ale House, 1920 Shattuck Avenue, Berkeley; 415-843-2739. Open daily 11:30 A.M. to after midnight. All house beers at $1.75 a pint, specialty beers sometimes higher. All sandwiches and chili under $4.</p>
        <p>Devil Mountain Brewery, 850 South Broadway, Walnut Creek; 415-935-2337. Open Sundays through Thursdays, 11 A.M. to 11 P.M.; Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays to 1 A.M. House ales at $2.50 a pint, specialties at $2.75. Appetizers from $5 to $7, main dishes from $8.50 to $15.</p>
        <p>Pacific Coast Brewing Company, 906 Washington Street, Oakland; 415-836-2739. Open 11:30 A.M. to 11 P.M. weeknights, to midnight on Fridays and Saturdays and to 8 P.M. on Sundays. House ales at $1.50 a glass, $2.25 a pint, specialty beers slightly more. Sausage of the day $5.95, sandwiches from $3.95 to $7.95, salads from $5.95 to $7.95.</p>
        <p>Other brewpubs of note: Buffalo Bill's Brewpub, 1082 B Street, Hayward; 415-886-9823. The Tied House Cafe 7 Brewery, 954 Villa Street, Mountain View; 415-965-2739. Santa Cruz Brewing Company and Front Street Pub, 516 Front Street, Santa Cruz; 408-429-8838. Winchester Brewing Company, 820 South Winchester Boulevard, San Jose; 408-243-7561.</p>
        <p>FARE OF THE COUNTRY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
