<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Insects Endangering Sugar Maples</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="216559"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAPLE SYRUP AND SUGAR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PEAR THRIPS (INSECT)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">RUSS, DARREL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DB1531F931A15752C0A96F948260" item-length="523" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Insects Endangering Sugar Maples</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: FOR years, maple sugar producers in Connecticut thought pollution was harming their sugar maples. But this year, their concern is centered on another enemy - tiny insects that growers say have clearly weakened their already stressed trees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: FOR years, maple sugar producers in Connecticut thought pollution was harming their sugar maples. But this year, their concern is centered on another enemy - tiny insects that growers say have clearly weakened their already stressed trees.</p>
        <p>FOR years, maple sugar producers in Connecticut thought pollution was harming their sugar maples. But this year, their concern is centered on another enemy - tiny insects that growers say have clearly weakened their already stressed trees.</p>
        <p>''Pollution has got to be considered at all times,'' said Richard Norman of Woodstock, president of the 160-member Maple Syrup Producers Association of Connecticut. ''This year the primary thing is insects.''</p>
        <p>Last spring, insects known as pear thrips infested maple trees, laying eggs in the buds and hatching as leaves began forming, sugar producers said.</p>
        <p>Depending on the number of insects, the trees produced withered, malformed leaves, and some failed to develop many leaves at all, according to Darrell Russ, a maple sugar producer in the western part of the state, where damage was particularly heavy.</p>
        <p>Many trees tried to form new buds, a process that takes energy and can cause additional stress, Mr. Russ said.</p>
        <p>Connecticut has about 425 maple producers who last year turned out about 12,000 gallons of syrup, a drop from the 20,000 gallons recorded five years ago, Mr. Norman said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Russ, who has been sugaring at Great Mountain Forest in Norfolk since 1950, said he has seen a slow but steady decline of the sugar maple at the 2,400-acre property.</p>
        <p>Mr. Russ and Mr. Norman said that they are unable to explain the decline, but that several factors contribute to the stress.</p>
        <p>''Once a tree is put under stress from a number of different things, every little thing adds to it,'' Mr. Russ said. ''It might be that without acid rain and without the dieback, the maple tree might throw off the pear thrip. A weak insect might kill a weak tree.''</p>
        <p>Hubert Vogelmann, chairman of the botany department at the University of Vermont, said the pear thrip damage was probably related to the pollution.</p>
        <p>''The pear thrips have been around for a long time,'' Mr. Vogelmann said. ''The big question is why do they suddenly begin to attack the maples? We know healthy trees cannot be damaged by disease.''</p>
        <p>''It's like AIDS,'' he said. ''You lose that immune system and something kills the tree.''</p>
        <p>Acid rain, which weakens the protective layer of leaves and damages roots, has been blamed for the devastation of trees in Vermont, New York and Canada. Connecticut has been less affected by acid rain, Mr. Norman and Mr. Russ said.</p>
        <p>As maple growers look forward to the start of the sugaring season next month, they are making adjustments to deal with the damage caused by pear thrips. Members of the producers association planned to meet yesterday in Burlington for a workshop on sugar maple care.</p>
        <p>''There are certain trees that shouldn't be tapped this year,'' Mr. Norman said. ''The producers should have noted which trees got affected and which didn't.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Russ said he was looking for trees that had never been tapped to use this year.</p>
        <p>''They're not stressed from previous tapping,'' he said. ''Then, depending on what we find out from testing our maples, we may go to the point where, instead of putting three or four taps on the tree we might put one. It's a serious problem.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
