<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="259852"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1D71E3BF93AA25755C0A96F948260" item-length="958" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International A2-11</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International A2-11</p>
        <p>International A2-11</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Papandreou lost in Greek elections yesterday, relinquishing control of Parliament. But it was unclear whether his conservative opponents would win a majority to form a government. Page A1</p>
        <p>Socialists and environmentalists gained in all 12 countries of the European Community, according to initial results of voting for seats in the European Parliament. A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: West German economic success in spotlight</p>
        <p>D2</p>
        <p>Ozone and acid rain in Central Africa has been discovered in high levels in the region's rain forests for the first time, creating new concerns about the forests' tenuous future. A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: Which China is real? The nation of free markets or the one of iron-handed totalitarianism? That is a question before foreigners and Chinese alike. A1</p>
        <p>Military analysis: China's army put loyalty and stability above all else when it fired on unarmed civilians, but it may nevertheless have created problems for itself that will take a long time to solve. A10</p>
        <p>Foley calls for U.S. to consider more sanctions against China</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Strategic arms are not top priority with Washington's arms control officials for the first time since they began talks 20 years ago. As Geneva talks resume today, conventional forces are most important. A11</p>
        <p>Polish voters rebuffed Communists once again in runoff elections for the new national Parliament. They ignored both Government and Solidarity appeals for them to vote. A3</p>
        <p>Israel banned three militant groups in an intensified crackdown on Palestinians associated with the 18-month-old uprising in the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip. A3</p>
        <p>Nicaragua to require Americans to get visas A3</p>
        <p>Rushdie denies giving interview since threat A2</p>
        <p>National A12-13, B8-11</p>
        <p>The startling rise of the dollar over the last six weeks is beginning to be felt from the boardrooms of businesses to the pocketbooks of Americans traveling abroad. A1</p>
        <p>Gasoline stations are going on sale across the country as small owners find the cost too high of complying with new regulations aimed at protecting underground water from storage tank leaks. A1</p>
        <p>Death penalties have bogged down in a costly legal and emotional morass that has overloaded the courts, divided citizens and left death row convicts in legal limbo. B10</p>
        <p>New ways to teach young students during early adolescence, when, despite a ''desperate sense of isolation,'' they are thrust into big schools, has been called for by the Carnegie Corporation of New York. A12</p>
        <p>An $838 million cleanup of chemicals and radioactive waste in Oak Ridge, Tenn., is providing evidence of the cost of restoring the environment at nuclear weapons plants. A12</p>
        <p>Management failings at nuclear plants cited A12</p>
        <p>Catches of cod, flounder and haddock in the rich fishing grounds off New England are half of what they were 10 years ago and less than a quarter of the levels in the 1960's. Overfishing is the major culprit, experts say. A13</p>
        <p>The Time-Warner-Paramount tangle has featured shifting rumors and wild swings in sentiment about who will win. Now traders are looking to the Delaware courts for answers. D1</p>
        <p>Auto workers chief gives warning on work rules A13</p>
        <p>The shape of the White House staff after five months in office reflects President Bush's relaxed, unpredictable style and centers on a John Sununu-Richard Darman alliance. B8</p>
        <p>Washington Talk B8</p>
        <p>Barbara bush is taking a dim view of Lee Atwater because of the Republican chairman's rock-and-roll impersonations and other pursuits. Like many First Ladies, she is concerned with the image of the Presidency.  Cuba's Washington mission has a new chief.  Regional B1-6</p>
        <p>The strike at Tavern on the Green, in its eighth week, has deepened into an angry urban battle involving a flamboyant restaurateur, a powerful union local with underworld ties and a grand jury investigation. B1</p>
        <p>New York City's standing may erode as the preeminent world financial center, and it could lose tens of thousands of jobs, unless business and government take action, says a report by a business task force. B1</p>
        <p>A long-delayed strip of Interstate 78, crossing the Delaware River, is to open this fall, tightening the bonds between exurban western New Jersey and rural Pennsylvania and creating a new migration route. B1</p>
        <p>New York's use of eminent domain in the Adirondacks, in which it buys land at a price set by a judge, will be tested this fall in a lawsuit by a dermatologist who is trying to hold on to his 1,000 acres. B1  To extend its drug-dealer crackdown to more professional criminals, the New York City Police Department plans to set up a new investigating unit and a computerized data base on 50,000 hard-core drug offenders. B3</p>
        <p>With a vote on the death penalty in New York State expected soon, Governor Cuomo has mounted a campaign to press lawmakers to create a sentence of life without parole, instead of overriding his veto. B10</p>
        <p>Responding to outrage over rape, law-enforcement and medical experts called for more effective rehabilitation programs and tougher penalties at a New York State Senate hearing. B2</p>
        <p>Yachts to glide into new Battery Park City berths B3</p>
        <p>Train derailment delays riders in Brooklyn and Manhattan</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Kristallnacht savior looks back</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
