<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Office Pool, 1990</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="312549"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="ESSAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NINETEEN HUNDRED NINETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">OP-ED</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DC153BF93BA15751C1A96F948260" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Office Pool, 1990</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The originator of annual prognostication was Jonathan Swift, whose ''Predictions for the Year 1708'' confidently named ''the great actions and events of next year particularly related, as they will come to pass. Written to prevent the people of England from being further impos'd on by vulgar almanack-makers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The originator of annual prognostication was Jonathan Swift, whose ''Predictions for the Year 1708'' confidently named ''the great actions and events of next year particularly related, as they will come to pass. Written to prevent the people of England from being further impos'd on by vulgar almanack-makers.</p>
        <p>The originator of annual prognostication was Jonathan Swift, whose ''Predictions for the Year 1708'' confidently named ''the great actions and events of next year particularly related, as they will come to pass. Written to prevent the people of England from being further impos'd on by vulgar almanack-makers.''</p>
        <p>The great satirist quit after the first year; not me. Guesswork in this space has become one of the hoariest journalistic traditions extant - 16 years of error, never a day of doubt -and events foretold here last year included the fall of the Berlin wall. (Forget the rest.) To the crystal ball: 1. First Bush insider to find himself on the outside will be (a) John Sununu after his campaign to oust C.I.A. chief William Webster backfires; (b) Agriculture Secretary Clayton Yeutter after scandals rock his Commodity Credit Corporation; (c) cuff-shooting Joseph Verner Reed after some protocol gaffe; (d) James Baker, after repeatedly slamming into the everlasting Gates. 2. Major White House problem will be (a) major shootout at credibility gap; (b) plunge in Bush popularity at alarming economic prospects; (c) Sununu's press ambush of the Fed's Greenspan for worrying more about inflation than recession; (d) revelation of a secret deal at Malta; (e) Poindexter's threatened tell-all book. 3. Democratic front-runner in the 1992 sweepstakes will be (a) Mario Cuomo, who will not run again for Governor of New York; (b) the new Mayor of Washington, Jesse Jackson; (c) Senator Bill Bradley, after abandoning the snore-inducing third world debt; (d) ever-aging Senator Al Gore, heated by global warming; (e) Sam Nunn, already beating Wall Street bushes for financing. 4. Nonfiction stunner of the year will be (a) ''What I Saw at the Revolution,'' by Peggy Noonan; (b) Helmut Schmidt's ''Men in Power''; (c) ''One by One by One: Facing the Holocaust,'' by Judith Miller; (d) ''The Bible and Us,'' by Andrew Greeley and Jacob Neusner; (e) ''My C.I.A. Years,'' by Manuel Noriega. 5. Surprise best-selling novel will be (a) ''Mayday Man,'' by William Beecher; (b) ''When They Took Away the Man in the Moon,'' by Kate Lehrer; (c) ''Gordon Liddy Is My Muse,'' far-out fiction by John Calvin Batchelor; (d) ''Protect and Defend,'' by Jack Valenti. 6. Diplomatists concerned with the German Question will be muttering about (a) another Rapallo; (b) another Locarno; (c) another Tauroggen; (d) another Brest-Litovsk; (e) another Peace of Tilsit. (This is a hard one.) 7. The U.S. economy (a) will boom at over 4 percent real growth, helped by a capital gains tax reduction; (b) will bust into recession by year-end, increasing the deficit; (c) will continue its rolling re-adjustment with regional recessions; (d) will be shaken by a stock market crash in Japan. 8. As superpower dominion lessens, (a) Poles and Germans will argue about the Oder-Neisse line; (b) Hungarians will demand a return of Transylvania from Rumania; (c) anti-Communist Rumanians and Bessarabians will demand Moldavia back from the Soviets; (d) Finns will agitate for the Soviets to return Karelia; (e) The New York Times will grimly continue to spell Romania with a ''u.'' 9. The source of Mikhail Gorbachev's most job-threatening trouble will be (a) dissident Yuri Afanasyev; (b) Prime Minister Nikolai Ryzhkov; (c) populist Boris Yeltsin; (d) the K.G.B.'s Vladim Kryuchkov; (e) the Red Army's Ogarkov faction. 10. Best news of the year will be (a) the repeal of Article 6 of the Soviet Constitution; (b) the emergence of moderate Palestinian leaders; (c) the reality of the peace dividend; (d) the winning of independence by the Baltic republics; (e) the quieting of legalizers by progress in the drug war. 11. Worst news of the year will be (a) the sobering realization that many superpower interests are still in conflict; (b) multibillion losses in Federal credit and insurance programs beyond the S &amp; L's; (c) the Islamic bomb; (d) big Democratic gains in the Senate. 12. The big geopolitical headache will be (a) quick German reunification; (b) the rush to a Start treaty to save a Gorbachev who may not be there; (c) suddenly expansionist Japan; (d) the Sino-Soviet conflict. 13. Conservatives will be sore at Mr. Bush for (a) new taxes; (b) selling out Jonas Savimbi; (c) sticking them with the abortion issue; (d) dithering with Sandinistas; (e) abandoning S.D.I.; (f) being so popular with his suffocating centrism.</p>
        <p>If you don't play, you can't win; no sideline snickering allowed. My own picks are: 1-b, 2-b, 3-a, 4-c, 5-b, 6-a, 7-b, 8-e, 9-b, 10-d, 11-b, 12-a, 13-f. I do this only to prevent you from being further impos'd on by vulgar almanack-makers.  Anthony Lewis is on leave.</p>
        <p>ESSAY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
