<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business Digest</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="273814"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DE103BF93AA3575BC0A96F948260" item-length="581" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business Digest</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  Companies</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  Companies</p>
        <p>Companies</p>
        <p>Frederick A. Wang resigned as president of beleaguered Wang Laboratories, returning control of the company to his ailing father. Wall Street continued to speculate that the family is searching for a way to sell the office computer manufacturer.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>UAL's shares jumped $8.50, to $219.25, on the heels of Monday's increase of $46.25. Traders continued to bid up the stock in advance of a UAL board meeting today that will consider a takeover offer from Marvin Davis.  [ D1. ]  An Ampco-Pittsburgh investment arm has acquired a 6.6 percent stake in Midway Airlines.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>Sun Microsystems and Hewlett-Packard stepped up their battle by announcing licensing agreements for their chip designs. Sun will license its Sparc microprocessor to Philips; Hewlett-Packard is licensing its design to Samsung.  [ D5. ]</p>
        <p>Sir James Goldsmith offered to place B.A.T.'s American insurance operations under the control of an independent trust if his group succeeds in its $21 billion bid for B.A.T.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>CS First Boston told its employees that it had sold an 18.25 percent stake in the firm to a group of international investors.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>Las Vegas's Sun and Review-Journal are applying for permission to enter a joint operating agreement.  [ D18. ]</p>
        <p>Financiere de Suez said it was making a bid for full control of Compagnie Industrielle, the largest shareholder of Groupe Victoire, a large French insurance company.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>Prudential Insurance has acquired Cartersville Federal Savings Bank of Georgia.  [ D4. ] Markets</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average traded above the 2,700 level for the first time since August 1987, before ending the day at 2,699.17, up 4.18. The Dow Transportation average set another high, rising 11.74 points, to 1,355.80.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Three brokers pleaded guilty to charges including commodity fraud, wire fraud, and mail fraud. Theirs were the first pleas entered since the Government announced the indictment last week of 46 commodity brokers and traders.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>Prices of Treasury notes and bonds were narrowly mixed in light trading, as credit market participants bid on $10 billion worth of new three-year notes, the first leg of the Treasury's quarterly refunding auctions.  [ D15. ]  Yields fell sharply on C.D.'s and money market accounts.  [ D15. ]</p>
        <p>Cotton futures prices made an abrupt turnabout, surging to the upper reaches of the daily trading limit.  [ D14. ]  The dollar drifted lower against all major currencies.  [ D14. ] The Economy</p>
        <p>I.R.A.'s could be disrupted by a recent opinion from the Labor Department that interest on I.R.A. deposits could lose its tax-deferred status if the deposits are counted toward minimum balances needed to receive free checking accounts.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Consumer credit rose at a 5.1 percent annual rate in June, down from a 7.3 percent pace in May.  [ D5. ] Technology</p>
        <p>Attempts are being made to curb the use of halon, an effective firefighting chemical that is harmful to the ozone layer.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Semiconductors are being sugarcoated to find out what it takes to make living cells adhere to each other.  [ D6. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>Mikhail S. Gorbachev is trying to swap guns for butter. Peter Passell: Economic Scene.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>Buying stocks that have low price/earnings ratios has been found to be a profitable strategy. Floyd Norris: Market Place.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>Media trade publishing companies might do well to consider making movies. Randall Rothenberg: Advertising.  [ D17. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
