<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fill It Up, Please, With Clean, Economical Ethanol; Bus Rule Backfires</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="260580"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHANOL</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6DC1730F931A15755C0A96F948260" item-length="358" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fill It Up, Please, With Clean, Economical Ethanol; Bus Rule Backfires</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your articles ''Weaning the U.S. From Fossil Fuels'' and ''When Methanol Is in the Tank'' (Business Day, May 17) raise valid points about the need for and use of alternative fuels. But transit riders should be concerned that a Federal rule designed to encourage clean-burning-fuel technology in buses is about to backfire.</p>
        <p>Diesel buses, which for years have been the workhorses of transit service, are unlikely to be purchased for 1991 and later model years, as of July. The reason? Available and expected diesel engine technology will not meet a new Federal tailpipe emission standard for soot particles. Transit operators will face the dilemma of buying desperately needed new buses with alternative-fueled engines that have yet to be proved in day-to-day service or of halting bus purchases altogether until the technologies are ready.</p>
        <p>The latter option appears to be the choice of more than 70 percent of the 165 U.S. systems that participated in our recent survey. The inevitable result will be dirtier emissions and worsened air in the trail of old buses that otherwise would be retired.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency has in hand our petition to review this rule and to set a 1991 interim standard for buses that is within reach and consistent with one facing diesel-powered trucks. Under our proposed standard, transit buses as a group would emit two and a half times less soot than if the current rule is permitted to stand.</p>
        <p>Operators of transit systems strongly believe in a stringent but workable national emissions standard. They are carefully watching demonstrations of the promise of alternative fuels. After all, transit is a significant part of the solution to air quality problems in cities and suburbs across America.</p>
        <p>But for Washington to require buses to meet an early emission standard - without available diesel engine technology and in the face of the unproven reliability and dependability of alternative fuels - is counterproductive to our shared national goal of cleaner air. JACK R. GILSTRAP  Executive Vice President  American Public Transit Association  Washington, June 1, 1989</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
