<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Panel Is Urged to Bar Drilling</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="262560"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OFFSHORE EXPLORATION AND INSTALLATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reserves (Natural Resources)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6D7163BF933A05755C0A96F948260" item-length="350" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Panel Is Urged to Bar Drilling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>ARCATA, Calif., June 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Lawmakers, businessmen and citizens urged a Presidential study group today to recommend banning proposed oil drilling off the rugged Northern California coast.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Lawmakers, businessmen and citizens urged a Presidential study group today to recommend banning proposed oil drilling off the rugged Northern California coast.</p>
        <p>Lawmakers, businessmen and citizens urged a Presidential study group today to recommend banning proposed oil drilling off the rugged Northern California coast.</p>
        <p>Senator Pete Wilson, Republican of California, told the panel, ''The north coast simply can't afford the risks of an economic shutdown that are associated with spills from offshore oil and gas development.''</p>
        <p>Recent oil spills off Alaska, Rhode Island and elsewhere demonstrate that there are ''some risks that are not worth taking,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilson's comments to the five-member panel came in the second and last day of hearings to evaluate the environmental effects of proposed drilling off parts of Northern and Southern California and the west coast of Florida. The panel is scheduled to make its recommendations to President Bush in January. Local Opposition Voiced</p>
        <p>Numerous local politicians opposed any drilling off the scenic coast.</p>
        <p>''We cannot allow Northern California to be leased and our valuable ocean resources blown out the tailpipe of a gas guzzler when there is no national energy policy,'' said Wesley Chesbro, chairman of the Humboldt County Board of Supervisors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chesbro and others called for increased conservation efforts and a policy based on renewable energy sources like wind and solar power. Opponents of the offshore drilling fear spills could devastate the local tourism and fishing industries.</p>
        <p>The study group is made up of members of the Departments of the Interior, Energy, Commerce and the Environmental Protection Agency and the Office of Management and Budget. The first sales in the area under review were scheduled for February, but Mr. Bush postponed them for additional review.</p>
        <p>In a minority view, a Eureka City Councilman, James Worthen, testified that his Council had voted unanimously to support ''orderly and environmentally safe exploration of oil and gas preserves.''</p>
        <p>Stressing the importance of safety, Mr. Worthen said that he believed most transportation problems could be overcome with technology and that pipelines to shore could avoid many tanker transport risks.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
