<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Weary Buenos Aires Family Wonders How to Keep Afloat</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="259416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARGENTINA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKE, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DC1738F93BA25755C0A96F948260" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Weary Buenos Aires Family Wonders How to Keep Afloat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKE, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>BUENOS AIRES, June 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: With his 2-year-old son squirming on his lap, Guillermo Dietrich pondered how to keep his family afloat in Argentina's rising sea of inflation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: With his 2-year-old son squirming on his lap, Guillermo Dietrich pondered how to keep his family afloat in Argentina's rising sea of inflation.</p>
        <p>With his 2-year-old son squirming on his lap, Guillermo Dietrich pondered how to keep his family afloat in Argentina's rising sea of inflation.</p>
        <p>''My wife, my mother and my aunt are the antibodies of hyperinflation,'' the drawn father of two said, cracking a rare smile. ''Every morning, they pool price information and try to save before prices are marked up again.''</p>
        <p>Last month, food prices jumped 78 percent, a record here. Argentina's working class neighborhoods erupted in the worst riots in a decade. 'We Live Day to Day'</p>
        <p>This month, prices are expected to jump 100 percent. With businessmen projecting this year's inflation to be 12,000 percent, Argentina's middle class feel pushed to the edge.</p>
        <p>''We live day to day,'' Mr. Dietrich said. ''We only pay bills when the money comes in.''</p>
        <p>The descendants of immigrants from Europe, the Dietrichs grew up to think of themselves as middle class. Guillermo was a construction foreman. Elida, his wife, is a lawyer. But in May, inflation, devaluation and underemployment depressed their joint income to $77 a month. Measured in black market exchange rates, their income was $38.</p>
        <p>For decades, Argentina boasted Latin America's largest middle class. Today, in this nation of 32 million people, the sudden impoverishment of millions of people like the Dietrichs has sparked angry debate.</p>
        <p>''It can now be said that with the events of last month, the minimum salary in our country is below that of a miserable oxcart driver of India,'' the newspaper Clarin said last week.</p>
        <p>In the last five years the number of poor Argentines increased to nine million from three million, Argentina's President-elect, Carlos Saul Menem, said on Sunday.</p>
        <p>''I never thought that a worker could make barely $20, one of the lowest salaries in the world,'' Mr. Menem, a Peronist, said. ''This fills us with rage.''</p>
        <p>On Monday, the Governor of Buenos Aires announced that emergency social programs are feeding 750,000 people in this province, Argentina's richest.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to see Argentina converted into one big soup kitchen,'' said the Governor, Antonio Cafiero.</p>
        <p>One recent evening, as the chill of a Southern Hemisphere autumn settled over the streets of this city's Caballito neighborhood, Guillermo and Elida Dietrich sat at the dining room table of their rowhouse apartment and discussed how they try to cope with jumping rents, prices and bills.</p>
        <p>''We grew up with inflation of 7 to 15 percent a month,'' Mr. Dietrich, 31 years old, said. ''But now, prices don't mean anything any more.''</p>
        <p>''I bought this last week at 37 australes,'' he said, toying with a pack of cigarettes. ''Now it is selling for 55 australes. Next week, it will be 78 australes. What is the price?''</p>
        <p>Elida Dietrich juggled her 4-year-old daughter, Valeria, and said: ''It makes you feel very insecure.''</p>
        <p>''This morning, I went into one store, looking for detergent,'' she continued. ''In one place, it was 140. The next place, 100. Finally, I bought it at a third store at 80. But tomorrow all the prices will change.''</p>
        <p>On all sides, the Dietriches say, they feel hemmed in by walls of rising prices - health insurance almost doubled last month to $18, rent for their four-room apartment is to go up 65 percent this month to $40, and the car stays in the garage because a tank of gasoline has risen to about $8.</p>
        <p>''We are down to the bare essentials,'' Mr. Dietrich said, visibly fatigued as he removed his glasses and rubbed the bridge of his nose.</p>
        <p>Consumer prices for the basics are expected to rise in coming weeks. In the first two weeks of June, the wholesale price of Argentine beef rose 49 percent, to 100 australes a kilo.</p>
        <p>Months have passed since the family bought clothes, went to the movies, or had dinner at a restaurant. Last month, they dropped table wine. This month, it may be cigarettes and disposable diapers.</p>
        <p>''Disposable diapers are something that middle-class women have achieved in recent years - it is hard to think that we now have to go backward,'' said Mrs. Dietrich, who reduced her law work to part time to care for her two small children.</p>
        <p>Monthly pay raises partly shield many against inflation. To further reduce the bite, wages will soon be paid weekly instead of monthly, said Jorge Triaca, designated Minister of Labor for the Government that is to take office next month.</p>
        <p>But in the last six months, prices increased 565 percent, while the minimum salary increased just 205 percent. Stagnant Investment, Odd Jobs</p>
        <p>With investment here stagnant for years, millions of Argentines are like Mr. Dietrich - underemployed.</p>
        <p>Trained to work overseeing metal construction on building sites, he has worked at odd jobs for the last few years, chiefly repairing cars.</p>
        <p>With unemployment spreading, many customers cannot afford to pay inflation-adjusted repair costs. In what may be a sign of things to come, Mr. Dietrich recently fixed a friend's car in return for four gallons of milk.</p>
        <p>In late May, sudden rises of food prices triggered the sacking of hundreds of food shops across Argentina. Fifteen people were killed, dozens were injured and hundreds were arrested.</p>
        <p>Like many Argentines today, the Dietriches sometimes admit with bitterness that they wish their European ancestors had boarded boats destined for North America instead of South America.</p>
        <p>Without any real hope of emigrating, Elida Dietrich looked at her 2-year-old son, German, and said: ''The generation of our fathers thought things would be better for us. Now, it looks like another generation will be lost.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
