<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>7 AGENCIES JOINING IN CLIMATE WATCH</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="279808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HILTS, PHILIP J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DE1738F932A3575AC0A96F948260" item-length="574" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>7 AGENCIES JOINING IN CLIMATE WATCH</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP J. HILTS, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HILTS, PHILIP J</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Bush Administration set priorities today for all Federal research on global warming, ozone depletion and other potential environmental disasters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Bush Administration set priorities today for all Federal research on global warming, ozone depletion and other potential environmental disasters.</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration set priorities today for all Federal research on global warming, ozone depletion and other potential environmental disasters.</p>
        <p>The Administration has asked for a 43 percent increase, to $191 million from $134 million, in funds for the research next year. And today the chairman of the group that listed the priorities, Dallas Peck of the United States Geological Survey, said that while future requests were confidential, ''substantial increases'' could also be expected for the following year.</p>
        <p>At a news conference in Washington, officials of seven Federal agencies announced a plan to coordinate Federal climate research and listed what research projects would be undertaken and in what order. Robert Corell of the National Science Foundation said the agencies were cooperating to set the priorities in a manner ''virtually unprecedented.'' The Clouds Get High Priority</p>
        <p>Given the top priority was research on clouds, the ''ultimate greenhouse gas,'' in the words of J. Michael Hall of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</p>
        <p>Clouds act as a blanket to trap heat near the earth and also as a shield against the sun's rays to keep the planet cool. The balance between the two is crucial to understanding the climate.</p>
        <p>The next priorities are the measurement of ocean currents and temperatures, and the measurement of gases like carbon dioxide, carbon monoxide and ozone.</p>
        <p>The three chief aims of the research plan are to monitor the climate around the world, or to ''monitor how this planet really works,'' as Mr. Corell of the science foundation put it; to learn how the chemical and physical systems work, and to build computer models that will predict changes in the climate caused naturally and by mankind's acts. An Administration First</p>
        <p>The report is the first time the Bush Administration has laid out detailed plans on what research it will conduct to monitor the planet and to make predictions.</p>
        <p>In a statement, the President's science adviser, Dr. D. Allen Bromley, said of the report: ''It represents my own personal commitment as well as that of the President to deal with some of the nation's pressing environmental challenges.'' Dr. Bromley was absent from the briefing.</p>
        <p>Senator Al Gore, Democrat of Tennessee, who has criticized the Administration's policy toward the environment, said the report ''is a welcome blueprint,'' adding, ''Our research into the causes and consequences of the world's environmental crisis must be well-coordinated.''</p>
        <p>But he said the plan was ''only a beginning in what must be a broader, more comprehensive effort not only to study global changes but to prevent them.'' Appeals for More Money</p>
        <p>Daniel Lashof, a senior scientist at the Natural Resources Defense Council, said: ''In an attempt to show that the Government is responding to the threat, it has renamed a lot of programs 'global climate.' There is not a lot of new money here. They could very usefully do a lot more.''</p>
        <p>John S. Perry, who heads the global climate study for the National Academy of Sciences, said he believed the priorities listed were good ones, although ''everyone would like to see more money put into this.''</p>
        <p>The Committee on the Earth Sciences, under the President's Office of Science and Technology Policy, produced the report. Its chairman, Mr. Peck, said the group would not make policy recommendations but would gather the facts needed to make them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
