<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="226797"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">SUMMARY</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DF133CF935A15751C0A96F948260" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL/3-19</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL/3-19</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL/3-19</p>
        <p>President Bush said better ties between Moscow and Beijing could enhance the prospects for peace in Cambodia. He also expressed strong approval for Mikhail Gorbachev planned visit to China. 1</p>
        <p>At Bush's Beijing villa, Marxists pursue profit  12</p>
        <p>Major changes in Eastern Europe could ultimately undermine the Soviet Union's hold on several nations and recast the continent's balance of power, Western European policy makers and academic specialists say. 1</p>
        <p>Poland cracked down on meetings and demonstrations over the weekend by small independent groups that support Solidarity but reject its negotiations with the Government. 1</p>
        <p>A proposal for a mutual withdrawal of naval shipping in the Persian Gulf by the Soviet Union and the United States was renewed by the Soviet Foreign Minister, Eduard Shevardnadze. 17</p>
        <p>Britain has asked the Soviets to raise the issue of the death sentence against Salman Rushdie, when the Soviet Foreign Minister meets with the Ayatollah Khomeini. 16</p>
        <p>Many clergymen quiet in Rushdie case  16</p>
        <p>U.S. military aid to Afghan rebels will continue to go through Pakistan's intelligence services, rather than going directly to the newly formed rebel government-in-exile, senior officials said. 15</p>
        <p>The Beirut authorities in Christian and Muslim areas are moving to close ports operated by private militias, in the first measure of its kind since the Lebanese civil war broke out nearly 14 years ago. 11</p>
        <p>A conference on global warming has recommended a gasoline tax to curb consumption and provide money for reforestation. Both steps would be aimed at reducing carbon dioxide, a major cause of warming.  6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL/22-31</p>
        <p>What soured the Tower nomination? Bad tactics and bad judgment played a major part in alienating Democrats on the Senate Armed Services Committee, White House and Congressional officials say. 1</p>
        <p>President Bush and John Tower began a public relations effort to salvage Mr. Tower's nomination. Meanwhile, the White House staff moved to show that allegations against Mr. Tower are unfounded. 26</p>
        <p>President Bush's approval rating -the number of Americans who like the way he is doing his job - is at 61 percent for his first month in office, a poll says. Only 9 percent polled disapprove.  1</p>
        <p>Private security forces have spread across the country as off-duty police officers protect businesses and neighborhoods, raising concerns over whether security is now going only to those who can afford it. 1</p>
        <p>The plane accident over the Pacific on Friday turned the routine into the extraordinary. There was bang, a whoosh and suddenly the cabin was filled flying debris and terror. 1</p>
        <p>A Federal inquiry into the incident has examined the damaged Boeing 747's cargo door latch, which may have allowed the door to open in flight. The F.A.A. last year ordered modifications for similar doors. 28  Americans' ignorance of languages and the cultures of other nations endangers the economic well-being of the United States, a panel representing the nation's Governors said. 22</p>
        <p>People with life-threatening diseases will by allowed by the Canadian Government to obtain any drugs that companies are willing to sell, even if no country has approved them for marketing. 28</p>
        <p>Elderly people needlessly pay for duplicative health insurance by mistakenly believing they are adding to private coverage that supplements Medicare. 30</p>
        <p>Democrats found to be top spenders in Congress races  27</p>
        <p>REGIONAL/32-38</p>
        <p>Long Island residents are organizing grass-roots campaigns to roll back assessments and cut government spending, as angry voices rise over property-tax increases of almost 20 percent in most communities this year. 34</p>
        <p>Gov. Cuomo's proposed Medicaid cut of $350 million for New York State is being opposed by an unlikely coalition of hospital industry representatives, labor unions and health-policy experts. 38</p>
        <p>Growth of jobs in the private sector in New York City virtually stagnated in 1988 after years of steady growth, Federal labor statisticians have concluded. At the same time, government employment rose by 15,000, to a new record. 37</p>
        <p>To provide the elderly with services at home, a ''Living-At-Homes'' program in New York City sends medical teams out to older Chinese people. It is part of a wider national effort. 38</p>
        <p>Electrician held in fatal fire  33</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
