<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Finding a Burial Place For Nuclear Wastes Grows More Difficult</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="306785"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NUCLEAR WASTES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DC163AF936A35751C1A96F948260" item-length="2168" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Finding a Burial Place For Nuclear Wastes Grows More Difficult</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: WHEN the Department of Energy said last week that it had lost confidence in its latest effort to find a safe place to bury nuclear waste, a gnawing question resurfaced: is the task possible?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: WHEN the Department of Energy said last week that it had lost confidence in its latest effort to find a safe place to bury nuclear waste, a gnawing question resurfaced: is the task possible?</p>
        <p>WHEN the Department of Energy said last week that it had lost confidence in its latest effort to find a safe place to bury nuclear waste, a gnawing question resurfaced: is the task possible?</p>
        <p>Some of those closest to the issue say that even now, 30 years into the nuclear age, the answer is not clear.</p>
        <p>The problem is formidable because some radioactive materials created in nuclear reactors will last so long that from the human standpoint, they might as well last forever. And these long-lived elements, especially plutonium, can be poisonous in minute quantities. They must be isolated from contact not only with people, but also with anything that might come into contact with people, like water supplies or the food chain. Since the nuclear age began, engineers have considered everything from shooting the wastes into outer space to putting them under the polar ice caps. For now, most of the wastes are sitting in pools of filtered, cooled water next to the reactors that created them, awaiting more permanent disposal. To that end, scientists and engineers have adopted three major overlapping strategies.</p>
        <p>Official policy in the United States is that the safest method is burial in a ''deep geologic repository,'' someplace dry, stable and desolate. But finding the spot is proving tough.</p>
        <p>A second approach, used mainly in France but also in West Germany and Japan, is chemical treatment of the waste to remove the plutonium for use in a reactor. There its atoms are split, giving off heat to make electricity and turning the plutonium into elements whose radioactivity is shorter-lived.</p>
        <p>But civilian reprocessing has been rejected in this country on two grounds: high cost and the danger that commerce in plutonium could lead to the spread of nuclear weapons. Moreover, the operation can cause nuclear pollution, and finding a place for the reprocessed wastes is still a problem. Most military wastes have been reprocessed, however.</p>
        <p>A third option, chosen by many smaller nations, is to store the wastes above ground, in steel or concrete casks thick enough to block the radiation or in thinner containers housed in solid, earthquake-resistant buildings. Unlike storage in pools next to reactors, this does not require pumps and filters, which can break down. The casks and buildings will not last forever, but the expectation is that they will keep well into the next century, when scientists will presumably have found a solution to the problems of underground disposal.</p>
        <p>But in this country, progress on geologic disposal has been slow, and today even the definition of the job is sketchy. Since its old performance standards for underground repositories were thrown out by a Federal judge in 1987, the Environmental Protection Agency has been drafting new ones, specifying the maximum permissible leaks after 1,000 and 10,000 years.</p>
        <p>The success in containing the wastes will depend on the integrity of the packaging materials and the chemistry of the surrounding soil. Government scientists say that the soil at their leading site, Yucca Mountain, on the edge of the Nevada Test Site 100 miles northwest of Las Vegas, is favorable, tending to bind up radioactive material rather than allow it to travel with underground water. The are still developing the packaging, but say that it should be possible to build a container that will hold the waste in for many centuries. But predicting leaks for 10,000 years is a new challenge.  Though plutonium remains dangerous much longer than that, for 240,000 years, the E.P.A. believes that so much geological change will take place over 10,000 years that it is pointless to try to plan for longer.</p>
        <p>''I don't know of any estimation model on the face of the earth that could even talk about a 1,000-year projection,'' said Dennis O'Connor, a special assistant in the E.P.A.'s Office of Radiation Programs who is working on the project. ''It's darn difficult to talk about a health risk 10,000 years in the future.''</p>
        <p>Others are far more optimistic, saying that with adequate skill and resources, a place can be found to bury the wastes that will keep them isolated until they are harmless.</p>
        <p>''Geologic processes are very slow,'' said J. Carl Stepp, a seismologist at the Electric Power Research Institute, a utility group in Palo Alto, Calif. ''It's quite within the state of our scientific ability to understand those processes and predict their rates, with some uncertainty, of course.''</p>
        <p>Carl P. Gertz, the manager of the Department of Energy's waste project, pointed out that many natural features, from caves to rats nests, have endured more than 10,000 years. Salt and Granite</p>
        <p>So government scientists and engineers have set out to find a suitable geologic structure. Early in the process, they focused on salt formations, because they are stable, their existence indicates that very little water has been present to dissolve them, and over time they tend to seal up all openings dug in them.</p>
        <p>But salt presented two problems. First, although many salt formations are low in moisture, critics said a hot object in salt would attract water. The wastes generate heat as they give off radiation, and some scientists say water concentrating around them could form a highly corrosive brine, eating through the waste containers. Second, the salt formations are in Texas, Louisiana and Mississippi, which had enough political muscle to frustrate the plans for a repository.</p>
        <p>Another geologic structure that raised the hopes of planners was granite, because it is solid. Much of the granite is found in wet areas, however, and water could disperse the wastes. But the investigation of granite was halted for a different reason: the political storm that greeted the Energy Department in potential locations like Michigan, New Hampshire and Maine.</p>
        <p>The current candidate for the wastes, Yucca Mountain, a volcanic ash structure, was promoted to front-runner by Congress in a 1987 amendment to the Nuclear Waste Policy Act. The amendment instructed the Energy Department, which is to build the repository to meet the E.P.A. specifications, to evaluate Yucca's suitability and then build there unless an insurmountable problem is found. Long-Dormant Volcano</p>
        <p>Volcanism may be such a problem. A volcanic cone about five miles away was once believed to be more than 300,000 years old, and thus probably dormant. But it is now believed to result from an eruption less than 20,000 years ago, raising the possibility of another eruption, which might breach the repository. The chief official in Nevada's effort to block the repository, stresses this possibility, but the head of the project suggests that not only is an eruption nearby unlikely, but it would not necessarily affect the repository.</p>
        <p>At the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, which is to use the standards developed by the E.P.A. to evaluate the Energy Department's license application for the repository, John Trapp, the senior geologist, told his superiors in a memorandum this year, ''Yucca Mountain site would have a very hard time passing a licensing hearing, strictly on the volcanics issue.'' He suggested that the site be dropped.</p>
        <p>The initial attraction at Yucca was its climate: desert. With very little rainfall, the area has no surface water and a very low water table.</p>
        <p>But the water table, 800 to 1,200 feet below the the proposed site, is another scientific question mark. Curiously, it rises in one corner. Scientists do not know why, or whether the water level could rise further.</p>
        <p>Nor is it certain that the area will always be a desert. Historically, rates of rainfall change very slowly, but there is growing consensus that the earth is entering a period of climatic change induced by human activity, in which the past may not be a good guide to the future.</p>
        <p>Scientists are also discussing how to mark the repository and its lethal contents for future generations, who may not speak any language now spoken. For guidance, the Government in 1982 commissioned an archeological survey of the oldest man-made objects to determine which were still comprehensible and why. Among other complications, the survey noted that acid rain is fast obliterating many ancient monuments, and that any monument made of a useful material, from metal marker to stone block, might end up being recycled in some future generation. Among the long-term possibilities for marking a site: creating a magnetic anomaly, presumably by burying large magnets, or changing the local vegetation.</p>
        <p>The alternative to burial is above-ground storage, either in a central location or at the reactors where the material is produced, an idea that few people like but that some dislike less than burial.</p>
        <p>''The best way to handle that material is to require it to be stored where it is generated,'' said Hugh J. Kaufman, assistant to the director of the Hazardous Site Control Division at the Environmental Protection Agency. He emphasized that this was his own opinion, which runs counter to the path the Government is now pursuing.</p>
        <p>The grounds around a nuclear power plant are a better place to store highly radioactive waste than a nuclear dump would be, he said, adding: ''The people who work at nuclear power plants have Ph.D.'s in chemistry and physics. They know how to handle it. And handling it is much easier than running the plant.'' In contrast, he said, the people who operate a repository are likely to be much less well trained.</p>
        <p>Another alternative is a above-ground buildings that would hold the wastes well into the 21st century, although finding the host for such a complex would be difficult if it appeared permanent. 'I'd Let It Sit There'</p>
        <p>Lawrence T. Lakey, a nuclear consultant who formerly managed the International Programs Support office of Pacific Northwest Laboratories, which tracks disposal efforts around the world, said he once favored underground disposal. Now, he said, there is so much public anxiety that ''I don't see how they're going to get the O.K.'s to do it.''</p>
        <p>''If I had my druthers,'' he said, ''I'd let it sit there and let the whole hullabaloo die down. That's what's happening in other countries.''</p>
        <p>But some environmentalists disagree. Dan W. Reicher, the lawyer at the Natural Resources Defense Council who successfully argued the case against the Environmental Protection Agency's original standards, believes that a geologic repository is the only solution.</p>
        <p>''It's almost philosophical,'' he said. ''We simply can't rely on distant generations to have the same sort of institutional controls over this very dangerous material that current society does. We need to isolate this from the environment to the greatest extent possible, so we don't have to rely on distant generations to make sure that it's kept safely.''  Legacy of the Nuclear Age</p>
        <p>MOST of the ''high level'' waste that the Government hopes to bury in the Nevada desert is the spent fuel of nuclear reactors.</p>
        <p>Reactors run on uranium, which is only slightly radioactive. But the reactors create radiation. To make heat, they split the uranium atoms, leaving fragments that are inherently unstable. After their creation, these fragments regain their stability by throwing off sub-atomic particles or energy waves called radiation.</p>
        <p>The rate at which the fragments give off their radiation and return to stability varies from seconds to millennia, depending on the material involved. Iodine 136, for example, has a half-life of 83 seconds, meaning that its radiation level falls by half in that amount of time. Cesium 137 has a half life of 30 years.</p>
        <p>The rule of thumb is that after 10 half-lives, the material has reached the background radiation level, meaning the level that exists in nature. For most fission products, 10 half-lives is a period measured in hundreds of years.</p>
        <p>But reactors create a second category of radioactive materials, many of which are longer lived. These ''activation products'' have become unstable by absorbing a sub-atomic particle called a neutron. The most important of these is plutonium 239, with a half life of 24,390 years. Plutonium is not found in nature. Making Plutonium</p>
        <p>Plutonium can itself be used to run reactors or to fuel bombs. The Energy Department and its predecessor agencies have run reactors simply to make plutonium, processing the spent fuel by chemical and mechanical means to recover that material for weapons. France, Great Britain and Japan do the same, to varying extents, to gain plutonium for reactor fuel. France has an active program to commercialize breeder reactors, which make more plutonium than they consume.</p>
        <p>Those reprocessed wastes are in liquid form, but France solidifies them in glass. The Energy Department is building plants to do the same with its liquids in preparation for burial. The reprocessing and solidification increases the volume of wastes, however, and even after reprocessing, some very long-lived material remains. Iodine 129, for example, has a half-life of 17 million years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
