<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shoreham's Lesson: We Need a Qualified Nuclear Administrator</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="232287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SHOREHAM NUCLEAR POWER PLANT</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND LIGHTING CO (LILCO)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NUCLEAR REGULATORY COMMISSION</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDA123DF934A25750C0A96F948260" item-length="441" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shoreham's Lesson: We Need a Qualified Nuclear Administrator</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Fear of Shoreham'' (editorial, March 2) is, in my view, an inaccurate treatment of the disgraceful outcome of a program that is vitally important to the future of Long Island and to our nation. It completely misses the point and fails to identify the crux of the problem.</p>
        <p>There is only one sentence in it that is accurate, where you state that the ''Shoreham plant was doomed long ago because of public fear of a nuclear mishap.''</p>
        <p>There is actually only one real villain in this whole disgraceful episode and that is the Nuclear Regulatory Commission. The other players are all engaged in a series of political charades, motivated by selfish political interests with no regard to the consequences of their thoughtless action. They include Gov. Mario M. Cuomo, the New York State Legislature, the Suffolk County officials and legislators, the Long Island Lighting Company and the so-called Long Island Power Authority, not to mention the N.R.C.</p>
        <p>As to the N.R.C., its total inability to regulate a hazardous industry is truly tragic and is just another example of the fact that a committee-type body cannot effectively regulate such an industry. We found that out in 1958 when we took the rule-making authority away from the Civil Aeronautics Board and gave it to the administrator of the Federal Aviation Agency -he didn't have to get a vote on a vital regulation to insure the safety of aviation operations in the national airspace.</p>
        <p>A commission can never carry out such a mission for the simple reason that a regulation vital to the public safety must reflect the approval of a majority of the members. Inevitably, the need to reach agreement results in a compromise, and ends up with a watered-down version.</p>
        <p>Until we recognize this basic fact of life, and establish a Federal nuclear power authority (or agency), headed by a technically qualified administrator, we will continue to flounder in the political arena while the world's supply of fossil fuels dwindles and carbon dioxide and other pollutants overwhelm us. In addition we face the real possibility of other incidents like Three Mile Island, Seabrook and Shoreham; so far we have avoided a Chernobyl in this country, but the potential is always there.</p>
        <p>Our nations's future, and the lives of our children and grandchildren, demand that we have a safe, viable nuclear power industry that is regulated by a tough, nonpolitical agency, one staffed with capable technically qualified personnel; it's that simple.  JAMES T. PYLE  Oyster Bay, L.I., March 4, 1989</p>
        <p>The writer was formerly deputy administrator of the Federal Aviation Agency, 1959-61.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
