<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bitter Cold Giving Way to a 'Veritable Heat Wave'</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="311780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HEVESI, DENNIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0D7143DF937A15751C1A96F948260" item-length="962" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bitter Cold Giving Way to a 'Veritable Heat Wave'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNIS HEVESI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HEVESI, DENNIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The cold snap that has fastened onto the New York area since Thursday loosened its clutch just a bit yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The cold snap that has fastened onto the New York area since Thursday loosened its clutch just a bit yesterday.</p>
        <p>The cold snap that has fastened onto the New York area since Thursday loosened its clutch just a bit yesterday.</p>
        <p>Pedestrians in Manhattan were actually walking upright during the afternoon, disdaining the hunched-over protectionist stance they had assumed the two previous days.</p>
        <p>Children even paused with their parents outside Macy's when offered a chance by one sidewalk Santa to toll the bell for his charitable appeal.</p>
        <p>Still, it was no paradisiacal stroll along some Caribbean beach.</p>
        <p>A necklace of ice, strung from the drippings of a faulty fire hydrant, remained wrapped around the curb at Seventh Avenue and 36th Street.</p>
        <p>Bins in front of some sidewalk fruit stands were bare, the produce taken inside because the God-given refrigeration was still turned up too high.</p>
        <p>And in upstate New York, believe it or not, it was too frigid for some of the nation's best bobsledders. Afternoon High of 20</p>
        <p>But given the bone-brittle cold of Friday, when even daytime readings were in the single digits, yesterday afternoon's high of 20 degrees offered welcome respite, and the prospect of a warmer yuletide.</p>
        <p>Gene Salerno, a meteorologist at the National Weather Service in Rockefeller Center, said it would be sunny today, ''with temperatures climbing all the way into the mid-20's - a veritable heat wave.'' Christmas Day, Mr. Salerno said, should be cloudy with the high almost nearing 30 - but no snow.</p>
        <p>If, however, yesterday afternoon could be considered a portent of relief, conditions Friday night and before dawn yesterday were nothing less than harsh. Between 4 and 5 A.M., the temperature in Central Park was 6 - two degrees colder than the low of 8 on Friday, but still not a record for the day. That is minus 1, set on Dec. 23, 1883.  Similar readings were recorded throughout the metropolitan area. And with all too familiar results.</p>
        <p>City shelters for the homeless were crammed and private shelters at churches and synagogues provided an additional 1,300 beds, said George McDonald, director of the Doe Fund, a support group for the homeless. The rest of the city's huddled masses ''suffer through the best they can in subways, terminals, in A.T.M. machines and on heating grates,'' he said. Huddled Over Fires</p>
        <p>A police spokesman, Sergeant Nick Vreeland, said there were no reports of deaths from the cold overnight Friday. One homeless person in Central Park was moved to shelter in the Harlem Armory, he said. Last weekend four people seeking shelter from the cold died in the subway system.</p>
        <p>On the Lower East Side yesterday, clusters of homeless people hovered over fires in garbage cans. At First Street and the Bowery, hundreds of shabbily dressed men and women waited in line for a free pre-Christmas dinner being served by employees of a restaurant supply company and a nearby delicatessen.</p>
        <p>''I immigrated from Russia 10 years ago, and America gave me a lot,'' said Alex Oberfeld, co-owner of the supply company, A &amp; A Restaurant Supply. ''This is my chance to pay America back.''</p>
        <p>The switchboard at the Automobile Club of New York was flooded with distress calls yesterday morning. ''We're getting thousands upon thousands of calls,'' said Dexter Brown, a phone operator for the club. ''We set up a couple of extra rooms with computers to accommodate all the calls.'' On a Mountaintop, 18 Below</p>
        <p>In Connecticut, too, towing companies were hard put to come to the rescue. ''We've got nine trucks and they're running steady,'' said Jim Russo, owner of Whitey's Towing in Hartford. ''We're flat out.'' And in upstate New York, near Plattsburg, residents of a trailer park were evacuated Friday night when a buildup of ice caused the Saranac River to flood and sent water rushing through the complex. Residents of the Underwood Avenue trailer park were being housed in a school gymnasium, said Police Officer Scott Beebie, while volunteer firefighters sandbagged the riverbanks.</p>
        <p>Bitter cold also forced cancellation of the final two heats of the United States Bobsled Federation's national two-man bobsled championships. Temperatures at the top of Mount Van Hoevenberg in Lake Placid, where the competition was being held, were recorded at 18 below zero.</p>
        <p>Back in Brooklyn, it was even too cold for the sea lions. As a few bravura joggers bounced along the Coney Island boardwalk and dozens of sea gulls huddled on the beach, a loudspeaker at the nearby New York Aquarium crackled out the announcement that the 2 P.M. sea lion show had been called on account of cold. ''We are sorry for the inconvenience,'' the voice echoed over the nearly empty boardwalk.</p>
        <p>Polly DuJany sat beneath a palm tree, reading a newspaper, in lower Manhattan yesterday. ''Not a bad way to stay out of the cold,'' said Ms. DuJany, gazing about the sparsely populated Winter Garden restaurant in the World Financial Center. ''The whole atmosphere here is so lovely - and it's warm.'' To Ward Off Cold, Borscht</p>
        <p>Despite brisk winds at Battery Park, where an ice-speckled harbor shimmered under a midday sun, hundreds of tourists still flocked to see the Statue of Liberty. A deckhand on the ferry set to leave for Liberty Island said 500 people an hour were making the trip.</p>
        <p>For David Cohn, hot borscht was an antidote to cold. En route to the Brooklyn Museum from his home in the Riverdale section of the Bronx, he and his wife detoured to Brighton Beach for a bite at a Russian cafe. ''Everyone's talking about global warming, but we think there's a new ice age beginning,'' Mr. Cohn said. ''It's brutal.'' Not for everyone.</p>
        <p>At a Haagen-Dazs ice cream store on the Upper West Side, one of the scoopers, 18-year-old Princesa Valez, said the cold had not hurt sales. ''People are crazy,'' she said, ''they still buy cones like it's summer.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
