<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sunglasses, Either Hot Or Cool</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="58" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="245302"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="FASHION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUNGLASSES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOCKSWENDER, WOODY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Eyes and Eyesight</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DE1238F933A05757C0A96F948260" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sunglasses, Either Hot Or Cool</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WOODY HOCHSWENDER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Sunglasses have their fashions like anything else. What looked dowdy or ridiculous a few years after it was in style begins to seem amusing and smart again 10 or 20 years later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Sunglasses have their fashions like anything else. What looked dowdy or ridiculous a few years after it was in style begins to seem amusing and smart again 10 or 20 years later.</p>
        <p>Sunglasses have their fashions like anything else. What looked dowdy or ridiculous a few years after it was in style begins to seem amusing and smart again 10 or 20 years later.</p>
        <p>For example, a modified John Lennon look is the newest old thing. Alain Mikli, the French designer eyewear store at Fifth Avenue and 15th Street, sells big 60's versions, with thick round rims, almost like Pop Art. Smaller models resemble goggles, and make you look as if you're about to swim the English Channel.</p>
        <p>Once upon a time, many women, especially those working in offices, had a imperious cat look. That 50's feline shape is back, with or without rhinestones, as worn by Daryl Hannah and Marlee Matlin, impersonating Eve Arden, at the Academy Awards. Lunettes, a line of fashion glasses sold at Macy's, has a very attractive version in blue plastic with metal trim that makes you feel like chewing gum and snapping, ''Can I get you a cuppa coffee or something?''  Serious Uses for Dark Lenses</p>
        <p>Shade has a serious side. Last summer, for instance, you really needed sunglasses. It was like walking around in a greenhouse. Who knows how thick sunglasses will be in the future?</p>
        <p>''The destruction of the ozone layer does bring in more ultraviolet light,'' said Dr. William McCarty, the president of the New York State Society of Ophthalmologists. ''Theoretically it can cause damage to the eyes, making it more important to wear sunglasses.'' To determine the shapes of shades in the future, Dr. McCarty said, ''they will have to do a lot more studies.''</p>
        <p>Futuristic designs tend to subvert the basic purpose of sunglasses, which is to provide something to hide behind, and add useless appurtenances. A pair of strange metallic folding glasses from Marithe Francois Girbaud - something Robocop might wear - fit into a little zippered suede pouch with a belt hook. Others are so odd you cannot wear them most places, except around the house when you want to scare your parents.</p>
        <p>Sunglasses are more like furniture for the face. Function is more closely related to form than in other kinds of fashion. Sporty, athletic sunglasses remain popular, although for most people, sun safety is less important than making a statement.</p>
        <p>Revo and Serengeti are two sunglass brands that emphasize both anti-glare lenses and fashion shapes. Revos, with their colorful reflecting surfaces, have made a splash on the cover of Elle magazine. Body Glove, the surfer supply company turned fashion house, makes a neoprene sunglass in neon colors that you can sit on without breaking, for $24.  Designers Make Their Marks</p>
        <p>Many clothing designers, from Ralph Lauren and Donna Karan to Giorgio Armani and Jean-Paul Gaultier, have licensed eyewear collections with designs that reflect their image. Mr. Gaultier's sunglasses, like his clothes, use odd industrial-design elements to bind the parts, for example, a copper coil to bridge the nose in his modified granny glasses, $195.</p>
        <p>For people who can't handle daylight, Ms. Karan's glasses are big and dark enough to blot out the world. They make you look like a star even if you aren't. Unfortunately, they weigh a ton, another burden of stardom.</p>
        <p>Some people seem so brilliant, other people need sunglasses just to be around them.</p>
        <p>Anna Wintour, the editor in chief of Vogue, wears sunglasses indoors at fashion shows, perhaps as protection from photographers' flashes. She is usually surrounded by a coterie of Vogue editors, also in sunglasses.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wintour buys hers from Better Vision Optical, for 41 years at Spring Street in SoHo, recently relocated at 439 Canal Street near Varick Street. ''I don't handle designer sunglasses, outside of Ray-Bans,'' said Bernard Winter, the store's owner.</p>
        <p>Some people wear sunglasses to survive. ''See behind'' sunglasses have become a very popular item among young people in New York. These have lenses mirrored on the inside corners, so one can see what's happening in back, including who's following you. They sell for $8 at newsstand vendors in Times Square, an area where they can come in handy.</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
