<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Can Sand, Even A Mountain of It, Stop the Tides?</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="240603"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEACHES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAST EROSION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SAND AND GRAVEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EROSION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">OCEAN CITY (MD)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ARMY CORPS OF ENGINEERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PILKEY, ORRIN H JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAY, CLIFFORD D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland/Ocean City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coast Erosion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sand and Gravel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DF153DF935A25757C0A96F948260" item-length="971" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Can Sand, Even A Mountain of It, Stop the Tides?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD D. MAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MAY, CLIFFORD D</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IT is an enterprise of epic proportions, yet little evidence exists that it has even taken place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IT is an enterprise of epic proportions, yet little evidence exists that it has even taken place.</p>
        <p>IT is an enterprise of epic proportions, yet little evidence exists that it has even taken place.</p>
        <p>Over the last quarter century, the Army Corps of Engineers has spread 1.7 billion cubic yards of sand over more than 400 miles of American beaches at a cost roughly estimated at $8 billion.</p>
        <p>The goal has been to save those beaches from the threat of erosion. But some scientists and environmental advocates have begun to see this and related government efforts to stabilize shorelines as fundamentally misguided and, in some cases, environmentally destructive.</p>
        <p>The most recent attack comes from a longtime critic of attempts to hold back the sea, Orrin J. Pilkey Jr., a Duke University geologist.</p>
        <p>Dr. Pilkey has long argued that sea walls, groins and other barriers used to preserve beaches have sacrificed them instead. In a new study, Dr. Pilkey goes further, criticizing the Corps' efforts to replenish beaches by adding sand. Restored beaches, he says, are much more costly and much less durable than the Corps of Engineers leads the public to believe and the benefits are often not as advertised.</p>
        <p>''Ocean City, Md. is a great example,'' Dr. Pilkey said. ''The beach there was replenished just last fall by the Corps at a cost of $12 million. Fifty percent of that has already washed away. So now the Corps is proposing a second phase of replenishment that will cost $60 million.''</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for the Corps of Engineers say that Dr. Pilkey's views are too simplistic. ''You have to be very site-specific,'' said John Housely, one of the Corps' senior coastal engineers. ''Sure, any time you stop sand from moving where the waves would like it to go, that's going to have an effect. You may save one beach while starving another. But we do research to determine that and we've learned a lot from what's been done in the past.''</p>
        <p>At Ocean City, the Corps maintains that the sacrifice of sand protected valuable land and buildings just beyond the beach. Mr. Housely said that the beach could also be expected to rebuild itself in the months ahead if the weather remains calm. Debating the Benefits</p>
        <p>Dr. Pilkey counters that if the purpose of replenishing beaches is to save private waterfront houses rather than public beaches, that fact should be acknowledged, with ensuing debates about who benefits and who should pay the cost.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, as at Ocean City, a case can be made that the beach is the center of a tourist industry vital to the local community. In other places a case can be made that preserving the beach may be most beneficial to wealthy owners of summer retreats. Federal funds cover about 65 percent of the average replenishment project, although not all Federal taxpayers live near the water. The remainder is usually paid out of state and local budgets.</p>
        <p>Dr. Pilkey also disagrees with the Corps' contention that replenished beaches usually rebuild themselves. ''Artificial beaches don't come back the way natural beaches do,'' he said. ''They disappear between one-and-a-half and 12 times faster than natural beaches.''</p>
        <p>Stephen P. Leatherman, the director of the Laboratory for Coastal Research at the University of Maryland, says no one can say definitively where the sand of Ocean City has gone or whether it will return. The most likely explanation, he said, is that much of it ends up as part of the beach's underwater profile. ''For 5 percent of the cost of a replenishment project you could have excellent monitoring studies that would determine that,'' he said. ''But that's not being done now. The state isn't funding it and neither is the Corps.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Pilkey's study concludes that along the Atlantic Coast from Long Island to Florida, where 90 beaches have been restored since 1962, 26 percent substantially washed away within a year. The worst statistics come from New Jersey, Dr. Pilkey said, with replenishments at places like Long Beach Island, Atlantic City and Ocean City, N.J., substantially disappearing within two years. Few restored beaches on any coast lasted more than five years, he said. Crowding the Coasts</p>
        <p>If the scientists, engineers and environmentalists agree on anything, it is that the debate will affect a large portion of the nation's population. Roughly half of all Americans now live within 50 miles of a coast, and that number is expected to rise substantially by the end of the century.</p>
        <p>As people migrate toward the water, the water is also migrating toward them. James G. Titus, project manager for sea level rise at the Environmental Protection Agency, believes that global warming associated with the greenhouse effect, together with land subsidence, will lead to a rise of one foot in sea level within the next 40 years and two to seven feet in the next 100 years. Left alone, many scientists agree, most shorelines would recede but sandy beaches, dunes, barrier islands and lagoons would migrate, too, as they have been since the last Ice Age. Efforts to keep the shore at a particular moment in its natural history -the ultimate aim of all beach stabilization projects - inevitably carry risks and consequences.</p>
        <p>Protecting property by constructing sea walls, Dr. Titus said, does indeed result in beaches being lost. By contrast, groins - structures perpendicular to the shore - preserve sand in one spot at the expense of another place farther along the coast. ''Groins are like lawyers,'' he said. ''It would be better if nobody had one. But once somebody has one, everybody's got to have one.''</p>
        <p>Said Dr. Leatherman, ''Ideally, the best thing would be to just build or move everything a few hundred yards back from the ocean. Then you wouldn't have to worry about shoreline retreat for years. But it's not going to happen that way. People are on a collision course with the ocean. It's the folly of follies but that's the way it is.''  THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
