<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SHUTTLE PREPARES FOR EARLY LANDING</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="293626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE SHUTTLE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATLANTIS (SPACE SHUTTLE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WIND</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DA163DF931A15753C1A96F948260" item-length="529" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SHUTTLE PREPARES FOR EARLY LANDING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla., Oct. 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Flight controllers prepared today to end the flight of the space shuttle Atlantis one or two orbits ahead of schedule on Monday to avoid high winds predicted for later in the day at the desert landing base in California.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Flight controllers prepared today to end the flight of the space shuttle Atlantis one or two orbits ahead of schedule on Monday to avoid high winds predicted for later in the day at the desert landing base in California.</p>
        <p>Flight controllers prepared today to end the flight of the space shuttle Atlantis one or two orbits ahead of schedule on Monday to avoid high winds predicted for later in the day at the desert landing base in California.</p>
        <p>Mission officials radioed the astronauts to complete their experiments and photography earlier Sunday and get ready for a landing at least one orbit, or about an hour and a half, earlier than had been scheduled. The possibility of a landing three hours earlier was being considered.</p>
        <p>The five-day mission had been scheduled to end at 3:38 P.M. Eastern time with a landing on the dry lake bed at Edwards Air Force Base in the Mojave Desert.</p>
        <p>But meteorologists are predicting winds of 39 miles an hour at the scheduled landing time Monday. Mission rules forbid a landing attempt into headwinds of 27 miles per hour or crosswinds of 15 m.p.h. Alternative: Wait It Out</p>
        <p>Flight controllers at the Johnson Space Center in Houston continued to study an alternative plan - having the astronauts wait out the weather by extending the mission an extra day or two. The shuttle has a normal capability for two additional days of operation, and in anticipation of possibly using that time, the crew has been ordered to conserve oxygen and other life-support resources.</p>
        <p>But that option is unlikely because weather forecasters say winds at the primary landing site are expected to be worse Tuesday.</p>
        <p>A third, but least desirable, option would be to redirect the shuttle to a landing at either the Army Missile Test Range at White Sands, N.M., or here at the Kennedy Space Center. White Sands has ample room for a landing on the hard gypsum basin, but little equipment for servicing the shuttle. The Kennedy base has only one usable runway.</p>
        <p>National Aeronautics and Space Administration officials said the decision on landing changes could be made as late as Monday morning. Most of the discussions between flight controllers and the astronauts today, however, dealt with preparations for an early return. Experiments Go On</p>
        <p>Unfazed by the uncertainty of their landing plans, the five astronauts spent a quiet day in space - their third full day - making more measurements of the ozone layer in Earth's upper atmosphere and concluding experiments to determine how molecules of different plastic materials form in the weightlessness of orbit. They also took pictures of lightning storms over the Indian Ocean and western Australia.</p>
        <p>The Atlantis astronauts are Capt. Donald E. Williams and Comdr. Michael J. McCulley of the Navy, Dr. Shannon W. Lucid, Dr. Franklin R. Chang-Diaz and Dr. Ellen S. Baker.</p>
        <p>At the Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena, Calif., Neil Ausman, the director of the Galileo mission to Jupiter, reported that that spacecraft, which was launched from the Atlantis's cargo hold Wednesday, succeeded in measuring a surge of radiation coming from an eruption on the Sun. The spacecraft survived the radiation unscathed.</p>
        <p>''Everything went great,'' Mr. Ausman said this afternoon. The Galileo craft's detecting device was switched on Friday night, he said, and was ''immediately able to detect some of the solar flare activity.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
