<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Few Bills Passed or Ready for Action, Congress Seems Sluggish</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="249569"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">RASKY, SUSAN F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDE1439F937A25756C0A96F948260" item-length="920" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Few Bills Passed or Ready for Action, Congress Seems Sluggish</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN F. RASKY, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RASKY, SUSAN F</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: More than four months into the legislative session, the 101st Congress has passed few major bills and does not have many ready for floor action.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: More than four months into the legislative session, the 101st Congress has passed few major bills and does not have many ready for floor action.</p>
        <p>More than four months into the legislative session, the 101st Congress has passed few major bills and does not have many ready for floor action.</p>
        <p>But its pace may seem slower than it really is. In fact, the output of this Congress is not appreciably less than the output in the same period of the first year of the Carter Administration or the first year of the Reagan Administration.</p>
        <p>But at the beginning of those sessions, the new Administration was proposing legislation, or promising to, and that created an air of impending action on Capitol Hill. No Initiatives or Confrontations</p>
        <p>In contrast, the legislative landscape for 1989 has been shaped by an Administration that seeks neither bold initiatives nor confrontation. And since Congress, for all its claims to a shared mandate to govern, is basically a reactive body, its modest legislative work this year has been overshadowed by more dramatic institutional battles over a raise, John Tower's nomination to be Secretary of Defense and the ethics troubles of the House Speaker Jim Wright.</p>
        <p>But at the committee level, where most legislation is actually shaped, activity is so brisk that chairmen say they are having trouble finding vacant hearing rooms to discuss a revamping of housing policy, the problem of global warming or improvement of security at the nation's airports.</p>
        <p>So far, however, severe budget constraints have left lawmakers producing testimony, not legislation. In Shadow of 100th Congress</p>
        <p>To a great extent, the 101st Congress suffers from comparison to its most recent predecessor, the energetic 1988 session of the 100th Congress, when Democrats and Republicans seized the initiative from a flagging Reagan Administration and joined forces to produce major legislative achievements in areas as diverse as trade policy, welfare reform, civil rights and drug control.</p>
        <p>In this Congress, the Senate minority leader, Bob Dole of Kansas, has taken to opening the policy planning luncheon for Senate Republicans with the same refrain: ''We've done two things this year,'' he tells them. ''We've killed the pay raise, and we've killed John Tower. This week we have some nominations and some resolutions. Next week we have nothing scheduled, and after that we'll be so exhausted that we'll take another recess.''</p>
        <p>Senator Tom Daschle, the South Dakota Democrat who is co-chairman of the Senate Democratic Policy Committee, agreed that there has been a void on the Senate floor. But he said it was partly the result of changes in the way the Senate does business made by the new Senate majority leader, George J. Mitchell of Maine.</p>
        <p>''We aren't bringing things to the floor unless we have an agreement,'' Mr. Daschle said. ''We could bring child-care legislation to the floor right now, but that would mean two months of fighting. We want to maximize productive time by trying to work out as much as we can in advance.'' Bills Moving in House</p>
        <p>In the House, Mr. Wright's troubles and mounting anxiety among members about news media attention to ethics issues in general have made for gloom but not necessarily institutional paralysis. Ten of the 13 annual appropriations bills are now ready to come to the floor, right on schedule, and legislative committees are grinding away at the edges of problems they would like to tackle if only the Federal Government had the money to pay for the solutions.</p>
        <p>In looking back on the 100th Congress, Representative Barney Frank, a Massachusetts Democrat, noted that the accomplishments of 1988 were the result of crucial spadework by committees in 1987.</p>
        <p>Representative Thomas S. Foley of Washington, the House majority leader, said: ''The very size of the agenda last year exhausted the consensus. Now you're dealing with the tougher problems, the more persistent and difficult ones that are left.''</p>
        <p>So this year, lawmakers in both parties are taking consensus where they can get it, compromising with the White House on issues like the budget, aid for the Nicaraguan rebels and the bailout of the savings and loan industry.</p>
        <p>''It is progress,'' said William Schneider, a political analyst at the American Enterprise Institute. ''But it's progress that leads to a compromise, not a bold agenda. The press is frustrated, Washington insiders are frustrated, and the only people who are not frustrated are the public. They didn't vote for any bold agenda.''</p>
        <p>There have been a few steps toward implementing the much promised Democratic agenda, including the housing, health care, environmental, public works and child-care measures that were to stand as the majority party's program.</p>
        <p>Bills requiring companies to give leave to workers who must care for newborn infants or seriously ill children or parents have made their way through committees in the House and Senate and await floor action. But other items on the agenda are still at the negotiating stage, and some like reauthorization of the Clean Air Act or long-term health-care legislation are unlikely to make it through Congress at all this year.</p>
        <p>So far the only major item on the Democratic agenda that has been approved in the House and Senate is legislation increasing the minimum wage. The final version of the bill is awaiting action in the Senate before it heads to the White House for a virtually certain veto by President Bush and an uncertain fate afterward since Democrats lack the votes in either chamber to override that veto, although they could decide to compromise with Mr. Bush and scale back the increase.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
