<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Limestone Dispenser Fights Acid Rain in Stream</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="258205"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIMESTONE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MASSACHUSETTS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WHETSTONE BROOK (MASS)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FISH AND WILDLIFE SERVICE</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFD9173FF930A25755C0A96F948260" item-length="411" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Limestone Dispenser Fights Acid Rain in Stream</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>SPRINGFIELD, Mass., June 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A modified water wheel that automatically dispenses powdered limestone has been installed on a trout stream to combat acid rain pollution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A modified water wheel that automatically dispenses powdered limestone has been installed on a trout stream to combat acid rain pollution.</p>
        <p>A modified water wheel that automatically dispenses powdered limestone has been installed on a trout stream to combat acid rain pollution.</p>
        <p>''The powdered calcium carbonate we use is the same stuff that's in the antacid tablets that you eat and it does the same thing,'' said Ken Simmons of the Cooperative Fisheries Research Unit at the University of Massachusetts. Limestone is composed primarily of calcium carbonate.</p>
        <p>The water-powered device was installed at Whetstone Brook in Wendell, Mass., by the Federal Fish and Wildlife Service. It provides a steady dribble of the chemical to buffer the stream's acidity.</p>
        <p>The device is the first of its type to go into operation. It is part of a $2.5 million state and Federal research project.</p>
        <p>A similar machine is being placed on a stream in Tennessee and a slightly different machine that grinds up limestone before dumping the residue in the water has been treating a West Virginia stream since December, said Kent Schreiber, who heads the program.</p>
        <p>The Federal agency is also working with Minnesota officials to treat a lake there with lime and with New York on treating a wild watershed in the Adirondacks by using aircraft to dump powdered lime on the forest floor, he said. Adjusting the Dosage</p>
        <p>Trout and other stream life are particularily vulnerable because heavy rains or runoff from melting snow can raise a stream's acidity sharply within a few hours, Mr. Schreiber said.</p>
        <p>The water wheels on the devices are geared to automatically increase the dosages of calcium carbonate required as the stream flow rises. ''One of the pleasant side effects we've found is some of the limestone settles into the sediment where it can have a longer-lasting effect,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Treating the 30-foot wide, one-foot deep Whetstone Brook will require about 60 tons of powdered limestone a year, Mr. Simmons said. About 24 tons of the chemicals are stored in two 15-foot silos built along the stream with the help of volunteers from the local chapter of Trout Unlimited.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, because of the amount of limestone involved, this isn't the sort of thing that can be done to every stream,'' Mr. Schreiber said. ''But the aim of our project is to see what can be done and the effects on the water and the fish and invertebrates in a variety of situations.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Simmon said the device has worked surprisingly well, but he noted that the powdered limestone ''is one of the most difficult things to work with.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
