<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Atop the Great Smokies</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="252192"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKS AND OTHER RECREATION AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT SMOKY MOUNTAINS NATIONAL PARK</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FURGUSON, ERNEST B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee/Great Smoky Mountains National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0D61131F932A15756C0A96F948260" item-length="1922" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Atop the Great Smokies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERNEST B. FURGURSON; ERNEST B. FURGURSON, Washington columnist for The Baltimore Sun, also writes outdoor essays.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: NOW in midspring, the blackpoll and Cape May warblers have flitted north through the high tops of the tulip and sweetgum trees around Cades Cove.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: NOW in midspring, the blackpoll and Cape May warblers have flitted north through the high tops of the tulip and sweetgum trees around Cades Cove.</p>
        <p>NOW in midspring, the blackpoll and Cape May warblers have flitted north through the high tops of the tulip and sweetgum trees around Cades Cove.</p>
        <p>The wild iris is in bloom along the trail up Trillium Gap. The bright shades of mountain laurel and flame azalea streak the lower slopes of Clingman's Dome. Catawba rhododendron overhanging the Little Pigeon River reaches out of the thickets for sun to warm open its blossoms.</p>
        <p>The bloom of forest flowers works its way upward with the advancing season. By the time the last laurel opens in late June along the 6,000-foot spine of Great Smoky Mountains National Park, the weather up there will match that in the lower Laurentians north of Montreal.</p>
        <p>Then, in fall, the reds of maple and dogwood in late September are followed by the yellows of poplar, birch, beech and buckeye, and the rich cider and burgundy shades of oak. When that show is done, some 10 million Americans will have come to the Smokies this year alone. That makes it the most popular national park of all, with as many visitors annually as Yosemite, Yellowstone, Grand Teton and Rocky Mountain parks together.</p>
        <p>These are our oldest mountains, the highest in the East. Sixteen peaks within the park reach above 6,000 feet. The Smokies' southerly latitude and heavy rainfall (close to 100 inches a year on loftier slopes) make them a vast botanical museum.</p>
        <p>Plant life here is more varied than anywhere else in the world's temperate zone. More vigorous, too: wild grapevines fingering far upward into the forest canopy get as thick as five feet in circumference, and laurel shrubs reach 40 feet high. The country's biggest virgin hardwood and red spruce stands are most conspicuous, but there are nearly 2,000 plant species, some 150 different trees - half again as many as in the continent of Europe.</p>
        <p>This green plenty created the haze of moisture and particles that gave the Smokies their name. Even today, these mountains are unspoiled compared to all else in their region, and so the park was picked as a reserve for the United Nations' Man in the Biosphere program. It will provide baseline data to measure man's further impact on the earth - and already that impact is measurable here. The haze over the Smokies today is partly acid rain, mostly from coal-fired power plants to westward. The high ridges comb that pollution from the clouds and it sickens the evergreens that rim the horizon.</p>
        <p>Among the millions who come are scientists who study these phenomena, who use the Smokies as a laboratory. But most visitors are not here for the microscopic view.</p>
        <p>They climb the tower atop 6,642-foot Clingman's Dome, highest point in the park, from which the rounded ridges seem to stretch forever. From Newfound Gap, where the main road (U.S. 441) crosses east to west, it is an unlikely treat to look down on high-flying ravens, soaring on the breezes that curve up the slope. Hikers dig hard for their second wind as they trudge up up Mounts Guyot (6,621 feet) and Le Conte (6,593).</p>
        <p>Still more come to get close to the attraction they have seen on postcards: the photogenic black bears of the Smokies, so common they are a problem along roadsides, at campsites and picnic areas. Visitors may assume all the park's bears are bad-mannered panhandlers and camera hogs, but biologists estimate that only 5 percent of them show up near humans; the rest are shy, and stick to the deep woods. A few are caught outside the park and caged as roadside attractions in the tourist towns of Gatlinburg and Cherokee. Most will seldom see or be seen by man.</p>
        <p>Just as most bears are not in the tourist business, the most interesting visitors are not tourists from afar. They are mountain families whose roots run deep in those coves and hollows, dispossessed when the park was created in the 30's. Some resettled just beyond the park boundaries, and cross in and out daily, as if this were an urban neighborhood park. Others come back each spring, from Detroit or Atlanta or Baltimore, to hug and picnic and renew old ties.</p>
        <p>This is reunion season in the mountains. Settlements uprooted half a century ago become communities again as four and even five generations come together for a weekend. Those who lived in Greenbrier Cove, on the way up Mount Le Conte, unite at a picnic shelter along the Little Pigeon.</p>
        <p>Tidying up overgrown family cemeteries while teaching the children the legends and interweavings of ancestral history is an annual rite of bonding. Gravestones inscribed with poems and flowers, put down long ago in hard-won clearings, are shaded now by walnut and tulip trees that have sprung up almost 100 feet since the land was turned back to nature. Periwinkle - cemetery vine - covers the loamy forest floor. Crisscrossing through it are trenches plowed by wild hogs, which root with their snouts for nuts, grubs, tubers, anything edible.</p>
        <p>The hogs are the progeny of European stock that escaped, multiplied and became a menace to the native ecology. Their rooting destroys delicate plants. They eat rare salamanders and tons of mast, the nuts and acorns needed by bears and other wildlife. Thus local trappers are encouraged to take hogs from the park to adjacent Nantahala National Forest, where hunting them is permitted. Beyond the fringes of the 800-square-mile park are more mountains, rugged as those under federal jurisdiction. But there are necessary salients of civilization, and their commercialism makes the next-door wilderness seem wilder. Gatlinburg is biggest, a milelong motel-and-souvenir strip that is the main entry point from the Tennessee side. Across in Carolina, the town of Cherokee has a more poignant history.</p>
        <p>The Indians there are the eastern survivors of the Cherokee tribe; the government drove their ancestors along the ''trail of tears'' to Oklahoma territory 150 years ago. The mountain Cherokees hid in the forest from soldiers, and now make their living in bead and moccasin shops, some posing in war bonnets for tourist photographers. The tribe also is partner in a huge bingo-parlor enterprise that draws busloads of players from half the nation.</p>
        <p>Modern convenience and the need to make a living thus prevail along the park's edges. But within the park, the effort is to take visitors back in time.</p>
        <p>At lower elevations, that means to the days of early white settlement. At Oconaluftee, on the Carolina side, a pioneer farmstead demonstrates what could be done by sweat and ingenuity in place of electricity and the internal combustion engine. In the isolated valley of Cades Cove, on the western slope, descendants of the original farm families run a blacksmith shop, grist mill and other exhibits of how life was after 1818, when the cove was settled.</p>
        <p>But as the mountains rise these signs of early civilization drop away. Except for about 170 miles of paved roads, the high Smokies are maintained as nearly as possible the way they were before white men came. Visiting is at a peak in midsummer, but the park is open all year, with only its highest and most remote roads closed by winter snow. There are summer nature camps, field schools, campgrounds, self-guiding motor nature trails and wildflower walks to encourage visitors to see the mountains the way they were made.</p>
        <p>Hiking and horseback trails run up to overlooks never seen by the road-bound tourist. Trout streams and waterfalls bubble in the cool of the towering woods. Indigo buntings trill along the edge of high balds, the unexplained forest openings thick with intertwined laurel and rhododendron. Along the Appalachian Trail between Newfound Gap and Indian Gap are soft splashes of fringed phacelia, yellow adder's tongue and spring beauties that blossom in late May and early June.</p>
        <p>But most memorable of all to me, what comes back from moments of catching my breath, my heart pounding as I looked out from Clingman's Dome or Mount Le Conte, is the absence of foreign sound. A raven crawks, the breeze sifts through the ridgeline spruce, but that is all - a quality of quiet that is worth the longest journey.  A VISITOR'S GUIDE TO THE PARK  Campgrounds</p>
        <p>All campgrounds in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park offer cold running water, barbecue grills, picnic tables and flush toilets, but no electrical or water hookups or showers.</p>
        <p>The three most central, and therefore popular, campgrounds - Cades Cove, Elkmont and Smokemont - require reservations, which must be made at Ticketron (804-456-2267). Sites at each of these cost $10 a night.</p>
        <p>The seven other campgrounds are available on a first-come, first-served basis. At Balsam Mountain, Cosby, Deep Creek and Lookrock campgrounds, sites cost $7 a night; at Abrams Creek, Big Creek and Cataloochee campgrounds, they cost $5.  Activities</p>
        <p>Five stables offer guided horse rides for $10 an hour. Cades Cove, a restored pioneer farmstead, also offers buggy rides for $5 and hay rides for $4. One of the loveliest bicycle rides - along the Cades Cove loop - is closed to cars Saturdays until 10 A.M. so that cyclists can enjoy the view. Mountain biking is allowed on roads and dirt roads, but not on hiking or horse trails. Bicycles can be rented for $2 an hour at the Cades Cove Store (615-448-9311 or 615-448-9316; these are pay phones, so let them ring).</p>
        <p>Fishing is allowed year-round. Regulations available at park headquarters. The park offers 11 self-guided walks and three self-guided drives, each of which comes complete with an informative leaflet. (A 25-cent contribution is requested for each leaflet.) The hikes range from a third of a mile to five miles and explore such subjects as abandoned farmsteads and the park's botanical diversity.</p>
        <p>Just off the park's main roads are a handful of half- to one-mile quiet walks. The entrances contain parking spaces for only two or three cars, so the walks remain relatively idyllic.</p>
        <p>The Great Smoky Mountains Natural History Association sells a detailed road guide called ''Mountain Roads and Quiet Places,'' available at park headquarters for $5.95.  Courses</p>
        <p>The University of Tennessee offers one- and two-day courses through the Smoky Mountain Field School. These cost $25 to $45 and may be general introductions to park wildlife or focus on a single specialization, such as ferns or mushrooms. Information: Smoky Mountain Field School, Non-Credit Programs, 2016 Lake Avenue, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, Tenn. 37996; 615-974-6688.</p>
        <p>The Great Smoky Mountains Natural History Association runs an institute that offers hiking and camping retreats. These last from a weekend to eight days. Among them are the Discovery Camps, $140 for six days for children aged 9 to 12; the Wilderness Adventure Camps, $175 for eight days for children aged 13 to 16; the Family Camps, a weekend costing $45 for adults, $35 for children, for families and their children under 12, and Elderhostels, $215 for seven days for people over 60. All prices include meals and lodging. Information: Great Smoky Mountains Institute, Great Smoky Mountains National Park, Route 1, Box 81, Townsend, Tenn. 37882; 615-448-6709.</p>
        <p>General information is available from the Great Smoky Mountains National Park, Gatlinburg, Tenn. 37738; 615-436-5615.  Lodging</p>
        <p>Le Conte Lodge, secluded retreat atop Mount Le Conte, accessible only by foot or horse trail. 615-436-4473.</p>
        <p>Wonderland Club Hotel, rustic, from early 1900's. Accessible by car from Gatlinburg. 615-436-5490.</p>
        <p>For accommodations and restaurants in surrounding towns, contact their chambers of commerce. - E. B. F.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
