<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Energy Glut in the Ground Imperils Ecological Hopes</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="291100"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHORTAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESERVES (NATURAL RESOURCES)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reserves (Natural Resources)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7DF113DF936A25753C1A96F948260" item-length="1102" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Energy Glut in the Ground Imperils Ecological Hopes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: FOSSIL fuel reserves, almost always discussed with the modifier ''dwindling'' attached, are now growing rapidly. The conventional wisdom of the 1970's was that the world was running out of oil, coal and natural gas. But in the last three years governments and the companies that do the drilling and mining have found far more than has been extracted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: FOSSIL fuel reserves, almost always discussed with the modifier ''dwindling'' attached, are now growing rapidly. The conventional wisdom of the 1970's was that the world was running out of oil, coal and natural gas. But in the last three years governments and the companies that do the drilling and mining have found far more than has been extracted.</p>
        <p>FOSSIL fuel reserves, almost always discussed with the modifier ''dwindling'' attached, are now growing rapidly. The conventional wisdom of the 1970's was that the world was running out of oil, coal and natural gas. But in the last three years governments and the companies that do the drilling and mining have found far more than has been extracted.</p>
        <p>This is not unalloyed good news. Combustion of fuel is the main source of carbon dioxide and other gases believed responsible for global warming, and with current price and supply trends, carbon dioxide emissions could rise by 70 percent between 1985 and 2020, according to a study released by the World Energy Conference, a London-based association of energy engineers, at its convention last month in Montreal.</p>
        <p>Scarcity and high price, once in everyone's forecast, now seem less likely to limit consumption. It looks now as though any incentives to reduce fuel use, thus slowing the greenhouse effect or cutting air pollution, will have to come from governments, not the marketplace. Political Factors</p>
        <p>Prices are likely to rise, especially as more of the oil supply is concentrated in OPEC countries. But short-term price increases work against long-term price increases; they quickly dampen demand and increase the incentive to find more oil, gas and coal, which tends to bring prices back down.</p>
        <p>In addition, oil is equated with political power in locations as diverse as Texas and Teheran, and governments in both places will look for more oil for reasons other than economic.</p>
        <p>According to a survey by the energy conference, the quantity of ''proved recoverable'' oil reserves -the amount of oil in the ground estimated to be recoverable under existing price levels and technology - is up by 30 percent over the last three years to about 890 billion barrels. Even more striking is the reversal in the years of supply remaining, up from 28.2 in 1979 to more than 45, according to Cambridge Energy Research Associates, a consulting company in Cambridge, Mass.</p>
        <p>The increase in the number of years of supply represented by the reserves is only partly the product of growing reserves; the other factor is a slowing in demand caused by higher prices and conservation efforts. When prices peaked in 1983, demand dropped to 19.2 billion barrels from 22.9 billion barrels in 1979, a decrease of 16 percent.</p>
        <p>Consumption will be back up near the 1979 peak this year because of stable prices and strong economic growth, especially in Asia, according to the Cambridge group. But the fact that consumption has ceased galloping ahead at ever-higher levels has increased the number of years existing supplies will last.</p>
        <p>All this ''new'' oil in the ground is of little consolation to the United States. Last year, according to a study by Arthur Andersen &amp; Company, oil companies in this country found only a bit more than half as much oil as they pumped out of the ground. Over the long term they obviously must find as much oil as they produce, or eventually they will have nothing left to drill for.</p>
        <p>Production in the continental United States and Alaska is falling by about 7 percent a year. Imports in some months have exceeded domestic production, something that hasn't happened in nearly a decade. The bulk of the additions to reserves, meanwhile, were in Iran, Iraq, the United Arab Emirates and Venezuela, all members of OPEC, and three of them in the Persian Gulf.</p>
        <p>The growing OPEC reserves are not a reflection of geology but of politics. Cash-hungry OPEC members are forever arguing over the quota of oil they are allowed to pump each year, and one negotiating card the member countries bring to the table is the ratio of their production to their reserves. The bigger their known supplies underground, the stronger the argument they can make that they deserve to be allowed to produce more.</p>
        <p>Iran and Iraq, until recently rivals on the battlefield and now competitors in OPEC, would each like more income to rebuild their economies. So Iran added 48 billion barrels to its estimate, and Iraq, 56 billion. The United Arab Emirates, which habitually produces more than its assigned quota, added 66 billion. These countries have always known that if they spent more money on exploration, they could increase proven reserves, but with decades or centuries of future supply in the ground, there was not much need to look.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, reserves of natural gas, once thought to be even more limited than oil, are doubling every 10 years, according to the World Energy Conference. Gas requires greater capital investment to transport, and is hard to move at all by sea unless prices rise above a certain level. Thus it is not as widely traded as oil, though that seems likely to change. Low-Profile Fuels</p>
        <p>But as with oil the news does not favor the United States. The Soviet Union's reserves are estimated at 1.5 million billion cubic feet, followed by Iran with about one-third as much, and then the United Arab Emirates and the United States, each with about one-seventh as much as the Soviets, or about 200,000 billion cubic feet.</p>
        <p>Coal, like natural gas, is a lower-profile fuel because it can be used in fewer applications and is not traded as widely. But reserves of coal are up an astounding 80 percent in the last three years, according to the World Energy Conference, to nearly 1.1 trillion tons. The study traced most of the increase to China, which is planning a large industrialization drive. China says it has 610 billion tons; the United States, 113 billion, and the Soviet Union, 104 billion.</p>
        <p>With growing concern about the greenhouse effect, word that supplies of fossil fuels are ample is a bit like telling a person who is dangerously overweight that the refrigerator is fully stocked. At the end of the 1970's and early 1980's, when oil was $40 a barrel and some analysts said it would reach $100 by the end of the century, the energy problem looked as though it might be self-correcting; as the price rose, oil use would be replaced by nuclear or solar power or conservation. In recent years, however, oil prices have been so low that even natural gas has had trouble competing; nuclear power has largely priced itself out of the market, and solar power, down in cost by a factor of 10, is still too expensive for most uses.</p>
        <p>More exotic technologies, like hydrogen, wind or ocean thermal energy, have been driven into the background. When the idea of scarcity allowed the price of fossil fuels to rise, those alternatives were aiming for targets that were getting closer. When prices fell, the targets got farther away.</p>
        <p>THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
