<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Galileo Deployed, Shuttle Crew Conducts Space Experiments</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="292812"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE SHUTTLE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATLANTIS (SPACE SHUTTLE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TESTS AND TESTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GALILEO PROJECT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JUPITER</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DD1531F933A15753C1A96F948260" item-length="589" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Galileo Deployed, Shuttle Crew Conducts Space Experiments</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla., Oct. 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Having completed their primary task, deploying the Jupiter-bound Galileo spacecraft, astronauts of the space shuttle Atlantis settled down today to a planned four more days of orbiting Earth and conducting an assortment of scientific experiments.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Having completed their primary task, deploying the Jupiter-bound Galileo spacecraft, astronauts of the space shuttle Atlantis settled down today to a planned four more days of orbiting Earth and conducting an assortment of scientific experiments.</p>
        <p>Having completed their primary task, deploying the Jupiter-bound Galileo spacecraft, astronauts of the space shuttle Atlantis settled down today to a planned four more days of orbiting Earth and conducting an assortment of scientific experiments.</p>
        <p>All systems on Atlantis were reported to be functioning normally. The shuttle, with five astronauts aboard, was launched here Wednesday afternoon. The 2.5-ton Galileo, the main cargo, was then released and sent rocketing on its interplanetary course.</p>
        <p>At the Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena, Calif., Galileo flight controllers said the spacecraft was cruising at a speed of 9,340 miles an hour away from Earth. A day after its planned six-year journey began, Galileo was already 250,700 miles from Earth. The shuttle remained in its orbit, ranging from 185 miles to 205 miles out.</p>
        <p>Neil Ausman, the Galileo mission director, said the timing and power of the spacecraft's launching ''was as good as you could possibly have hoped for.'' Adjustments in Flight Path</p>
        <p>Alan Wood, a spokesman at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory, said the Galileo's steering thrusters would be fired Saturday in the first of many maneuvers planned to adjust the craft's flight path and its orientation to the Sun. A minor correction in the spacecraft's velocity is scheduled to be made in three weeks.</p>
        <p>On the first leg of its journey, the Galileo is traveling in toward the Sun, aiming for Venus. It is to loop around Venus next February, getting a boost in velocity from the planet's gravity, and then make two swings by Earth, in December 1990 and 1992, for additional gravity ''assists'' before finally heading toward Jupiter. Efforts will be made for Galileo to fly close to the asteroid Gaspara in October 1991.</p>
        <p>Arrival at Jupiter is scheduled for December 1995, when Galileo is to dispatch an instrument probe into the Jovian astmosphere and then go into orbit of the giant planet for months of photography and scientific observations. This will be the first time a spacecraft has orbited one of the outer giant planets.</p>
        <p>Since the spacecraft was designed originally for a direct mission to Jupiter, always moving away from the Sun, controllers must carefully maintain the Galileo craft's orientation to the Sun, keeping vital components in the shade to prevent overheating. Two Unexplained Anomalies</p>
        <p>Mr. Wood said two unexplained anomalies had been observed in the spacecraft's operations immediately after it was deployed. A low voltage reading on a radio receiver corrected itself and has not recurred, he said. Another unusual voltage measurement was detected in the spacecraft's main power system, which Mr. Wood said is ''still being looked at.''</p>
        <p>''Everything else about Galileo is normal and working fine,'' Mr. Wood said.</p>
        <p>On board the Atlantis, the astronauts were reported in good health as they began a half dozen experiments. These involved measuring Earth's protective ozone layer to calibrate instruments for meteorological satellites, observing nighttime lightning strikes on Earth, recording how molecules and ice crystals form in the absence of Earth's gravity, and determining the effects of weightlessness on plant growth hormones.</p>
        <p>The Atlantis astronauts are Capt. Donald E. Williams and Comdr. Michael J. McCulley of the Navy; Dr. Shannon W. Lucid, a biochemist; Dr. Franklin R. Chang-Diaz, a physicist, and Dr. Ellen S. Baker, a physician.</p>
        <p>The mission is scheduled to end at Edwards Air Force Base in California on Monday at 3:38 P.M., Eastern daylight time.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
