<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="282403"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DE1F3CF932A2575AC0A96F948260" item-length="1017" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International A3-12  East Germans can leave Hungary for West Germany, Budapest said. The announcement was a final chapter in a summerlong exodus through the new Hungarian gap in the Communist frontier. Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International A3-12  East Germans can leave Hungary for West Germany, Budapest said. The announcement was a final chapter in a summerlong exodus through the new Hungarian gap in the Communist frontier. Page A1</p>
        <p>International A3-12  East Germans can leave Hungary for West Germany, Budapest said. The announcement was a final chapter in a summerlong exodus through the new Hungarian gap in the Communist frontier. Page A1</p>
        <p>U.S. advisers in Latin America have been authorized to move outside base camps, opening the way for a potentially expanded role for American troops in the anti-drug effort, Administration officials said. A1</p>
        <p>Colombian-Americans attend Mass for victims A6</p>
        <p>Boris Yeltsin arrived in New York over the weekend and spent his first day in the United States embracing the American way of life. He also warned of problems back home. A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: Soviet groups pursue conflicting visions</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>A Rumanian passenger ship sank after colliding with a Bulgarian tugboat on the Danube. The ship had been carrying 179 people, and the toll appeared to be high. A11</p>
        <p>Prague journal A4</p>
        <p>Many of South Asia's problems are rooted in high population growth, as reflected in the Indian state of Rajasthan, where land and vegetation are visibly running out. A8</p>
        <p>Salvadoran Government-rebel talks that begin Tuesday are more of a twirl in a political minuet than a breakthrough toward ending the war, Western diplomats said. A12  Latin America increased its exports and managed for the first time since 1982 to cut its outstanding foreign debt, the Inter-American Development Bank said. D6</p>
        <p>At least 10 Palestinians were killed over the weekend, some by fellow Arabs and others by Israelis. Those slain by Arabs are accused of cooperating with Israeli officials. A3</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Merbah of Algeria agreed to give up his job after an unusual act of defiance on Sunday when he refused to step down after his dismissal by President Benjedid. A3</p>
        <p>World Bank policy on global warming has not been aggresive enough, environmentalists and politicians are complaining. A9</p>
        <p>What will 1992 do to border towns? Border police officers, customs agents and freight forwarders across Europe fear that the elimination of internal borders in 1992 will rob the towns of their raison d'etre. D1</p>
        <p>National A14-19, A22, B8, B10</p>
        <p>Development of a nuclear reactor for use in outer space is too expensive for the Energy Department under the current Federal budget pressure, Federal officials said. A1</p>
        <p>A proposal to shift agriculture away from practices dependent on synthetic chemicals would take decades and require major policy changes, farmers and experts say. A1</p>
        <p>A clot removed from Ronald Reagan on Friday was the second clot he has suffered since his July riding accident, his neurosurgeon said. A14</p>
        <p>The homeless are creating tent cities within many cities. With the police under pressure to dismantle such settlements, they are fast becoming the front lines in political battles. A14</p>
        <p>Detroit's mayoral primary Tuesday will almost surely advance Coleman Young to the general election; the question is, Who will be the other top vote-getter that advances? A14</p>
        <p>Samuel Pierce overruled an official in the housing department on a $23 million Chicago housing deal, court files show. The event shows Mr. Pierce's management style was not always hands off. A16  The misconduct of two drug makers appears to have been more serious and widespread than the companies led Government investigators to believe, two lawmakers said. A17</p>
        <p>The Campeau Corporation's decision to sell Bloomingdale's signals that its plans have gone awry, partly because it appears to have taken on too much debt, analysts said. D1</p>
        <p>A race to invent a better button is heating up the men's dress-shirt industry. It is a response to an apparently growing number of complaints about broken buttons. D1</p>
        <p>The prison population increased by a record 46,004 inmates in the first six months of this year to a total of 673,565 people, the Bureau of Justice Statistics said. A18</p>
        <p>Judges debated bioethical issues and whether courts were the place to resolve them at the first national judiciary conference on the issue. A19</p>
        <p>Federal workers leave their jobs at about the same rate as workers in private companies, a report shows. But some agencies say it is the best workers who most often leave. A18</p>
        <p>W. Virginia rejects amendments</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>Regional B1-6</p>
        <p>Campaigns worked on voter turnout as the New York City mayoral primary neared. Volunteers dialed thousands of phone numbers in an effort to get supporters to the polls. A1</p>
        <p>The mayoral candidates campaigned through steaming heat. David Dinkins led the African-American Day parade; Mayor Koch spoke to a black congregation. B1</p>
        <p>Board of Elections is taking extra steps against vote fraud B4</p>
        <p>Flood of campaign mail precedes mayoral primary B4</p>
        <p>A city gets excited as the primary nears B4</p>
        <p>A man who died in police custody Saturday received no injuries that could have caused his death, only minor cuts and bruises, the New York City Medical Examiner's office said. A1  Governor Cuomo backed pro-choice after years of ambiguity on the issue of abortion. He stated firmly that abortion ''must be a matter of the woman's conscience.'' B1</p>
        <p>Robert Garcia's trial opens today with jury selection. The Congressman's trial on bribery and extortion charges is likely to be the last major one from the Wedtech scandal. B3</p>
        <p>Yonkers's decision on complying with a housing desegregation order is likely to be a central issue in the city's primary elections on Tuesday. Officials will discover how their positions sit with voters. B3</p>
        <p>The ''talking date'' is popular. Men and women, fearful of AIDS and put off by the high cost of fun, are seeking romance in hours of talk. B1</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
