<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Searching for Incentives To Entice Polluters</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="289099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATURAL RESOURCES DEFENSE COUNCIL</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN PETROLEUM INSTITUTE (API)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAWKINS, DAVID G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DIBONA, CHARLES J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">INTERVIEW</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFD61E3CF93BA35753C1A96F948260" item-length="1726" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Searching for Incentives To Entice Polluters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As Congress last week discussed the renewal of the Clean Air Act, it wrestled with expanded use of an unusual concept in pollution control: letting industries buy and sell the right to emit pollutants, with companies deciding among themselves how to share the work that the Government wants done. Under President Bush's proposal, this flexibility would extend to automobiles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As Congress last week discussed the renewal of the Clean Air Act, it wrestled with expanded use of an unusual concept in pollution control: letting industries buy and sell the right to emit pollutants, with companies deciding among themselves how to share the work that the Government wants done. Under President Bush's proposal, this flexibility would extend to automobiles.</p>
        <p>As Congress last week discussed the renewal of the Clean Air Act, it wrestled with expanded use of an unusual concept in pollution control: letting industries buy and sell the right to emit pollutants, with companies deciding among themselves how to share the work that the Government wants done. Under President Bush's proposal, this flexibility would extend to automobiles. The law would specify the number of ''alternative fuel'' cars but would not say what fuel or precisely which companies would make them or the fuels.</p>
        <p>Industry generally favors these trading programs, saying they lead to greater economic efficiency. But environmentalists warn of pitfalls that will make the cleanup program less effective.</p>
        <p>Last week Charles J. DiBona, the president of the American Petroleum Institute and an economist, and David G. Hawkins, senior attorney at the Natural Resources Defense Council, who was the Environmental Protection Agency's Assistant Administrator for Air, Noise and Radiation from 1977 to 1981, met to debate the merits of pollution trading. Matthew L. Wald of The New York Times moderated.</p>
        <p>Mr. DiBona: We now spend on the order of $100 million per year, or about 2 percent of G.N.P, on environmental controls. In the future the cost will undoubtedly rise, perhaps quickly. If the Europeans and Asians should utilize incentive approaches to protect their environments while we do not, our industries will be at a competitive disadvantage. While there is not much experience with incentive systems, they have in some cases provided substantial economies, and many academic studies show large potential economies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hawkins: In some circumstances the environmental community feels comfortable with incentive systems based on trading the right to pollute. An example is the President's proposal on the trading of sulfur dioxide emission allowances for acid rain control. A reduction somewhere in the market is fungible with a reduction elsewhere. It does not involve trading one individual's right to a clean environment against another's right to a clean environment. And the pollutants, particularly sulfur dioxide, can be accurately monitored.</p>
        <p>But we are not as confident in the President's bill to allow market alternatives with respect to automotive air pollution, particularly ozone and smog. It violates fundamental principles of environmental protection.  Question: In what way?</p>
        <p>Mr. Hawkins: The so-called alternate fuels proposal would obligate vehicle makers starting in 1995 to sell 500,000 vehicles a year, going up to 1 million, that can use alternate fuels like methanol. The proposal would allow auto makers to market cleaner vehicles in one metropolitan area and dirtier vehicles in another. It would permit fuel refiners to market cleaner fuels in one metropolitan area, dirtier fuels in another.</p>
        <p>This approach is different from acid rain in that these reductions are not fungible. Why should New Yorkers be subjected to dirtier cars because auto makers found it convenient to sell cleaner cars in L.A.?  Mr. DiBona: There is a provision in the bill that permits fuel manufacturers and auto manufacturers to trade or share the responsibility of delivering these fixed numbers of autos or volumes of fuel, so I don't think that it runs into the problems you suggest. I agree that it would not make much sense to reduce the quality of air in Chicago to improve it in some other area. What we ought to insure is that the trades are commensurate.</p>
        <p>Now, we can debate a trade between areas. You can imagine that part of a given region might meet the ambient air standard and part of it might not. A trade between these two areas that reduced costs, brought the area not in compliance into compliance, raised the level of pollutants in the other, but not enough to put it over the standard, in some instances would be a sensible step.</p>
        <p>You'll get the most bang for your buck in environmental reduction if the next increment of pollution reduction comes from the emitter who can do it cheapest. And you will do that until his costs rise to the point where there's someone else who can now start doing it even more cheaply.  Q. Why is that better than just ordering pollution reductions?</p>
        <p>Mr. DiBona: The problem of the command and control system, in which the government sets pollution levels and everyone must comply, is that you set a set standard for everybody. Some people are going to be able to do better, but they don't have to. In fact, they have every incentive not to let you know they can do it better.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hawkins: The system often does lack the incentive to do better. However, our fix is different.</p>
        <p>The fix that's typically proposed is that you start with a base line. The government, with all its inability to spot developing pollution control trends, determines the amount of opportunity for further progress. A trading system is set up where people who have successfully withheld from the government information showing that they can do better will be able to turn that into allowances to pollute more elsewhere.  Q. In other words, this is a system that rewards those who have hidden their capabilities thus far?</p>
        <p>Mr. Hawkins: It certainly does. For example, in the Clean Air Act, there is a term - reasonably available control technology. A lot of proposals want to allow trading of pollution allowances if you do anything beyond what's reasonably available. Politically, how could you be opposed to giving credit for going beyond what's reasonable? Our remedy would be to impose a charge on emissions, to create an incentive for reductions.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, if you introduce trading of allowances into a system that is in the process of defining regulatory requirements, you have introduced a new incentive. You introduce an incentive to define the pre-existing regulatory requirements as leniently as possible. Because the more lenient the base line, the more opportunity there is for trade.  Q. Are we arguing over what level should be reached, or how to reach it?</p>
        <p>Mr. Hawkins: We are not arguing what levels should be reached. And, indeed, in Congress the petroleum industry is not arguing that the ambient air quality standard should be changed for smog. They are arguing about how many years these cities should be allowed to violate these health standards. It's not acceptable to have a 21-year period where these standards can be violated.</p>
        <p>Mr. DiBona: We are not arguing about the standards. We have argued that we and the government should spend a little more time getting information about alternative fuels. Companies might implement it faster once they have that information. They do not have the information on methanol because there have not been enough tests.</p>
        <p>The advantage of even using a lousy system of trading rights is that you don't have to set them for eternity. Then you watch how the system works. You'll get a lot of information on how to clean up that you would never get otherwise. And then you can re-set the system.  Q. We're still left with this issue of how to pick a starting point, of what is reasonably available control technology.</p>
        <p>Mr. DiBona: Let's say you use the current system of standards for pollution levels. And it was very bad because some people had succeeded in duping the authorities, and therefore had lots of trading rights. You will quickly learn whether or not they have the capability of going further at low cost because someone else will buy their rights. And you will discover those are the guys who can do it better, and you will learn about the technology they are using.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hawkins: If you try to change it at that point, as a regulator you will be accused of disrupting the market and eliminating the incentives.</p>
        <p>Mr. DiBona: You have to leave it in place, but not indefinitely. You have to say, this is something we're going to let run for 5 years, or 10 years to foster innovations. Because now I've got something I can sell. Not only can I use it myself to reduce my costs, but I can provide it to others. And I think that there's some evidence that the current system doesn't provide much innovation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hawkins: We're in favor of innovation. But the air pollution control area demonstrates just as many examples of scams, if not more, than of innovation.</p>
        <p>I'll give you an example I worked on personally. A steel company persuaded the state of Michigan that reasonable control for dust from its plant was to water the dirt road. That was the regulatory benchmark. Then the company went out and did something truly innovative - it paved the road. That's the innovation for which they claimed all sorts of credit so they could take off controls on a steel-making furnace.</p>
        <p>Everything that Charlie says about innovation using the regulatory benchmark approach is far truer about the approach that I am advocating, charging a fee for being permitted to pollute. If we want to try an incentive system, let's use what our economic system is based on: dollars.</p>
        <p>Mr. DiBona, couldn't your arguments be used to suggest a system where there was no benchmark, there was just a charge for pollution?</p>
        <p>Mr. DiBona: We have been advocates of fees in some areas. But fees can generate an immense revenue and that raises questions about whether you want the revenue effects or you want to use something like a marketable permit instead. Most fees are probably highly regressive and would tend to increase consumer costs in a particular industry. To the extent that the industry is in international competition, fees raise the cost of your goods relative to foreign produced goods.</p>
        <p>The marketable permit system permits you to specify the amount of reduction because you've just issued that many permits to emit pollutants. Then let people trade them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hawkins: There are hybrid systems being considered that would auction allowances. One of the issuesabout the marketable permits system - in fact it's being raised about the acid rain proposal now - is who receives these allowances, and whether there are barriers to entry created because the allowances are initially allocated free of cost to existing polluters.</p>
        <p>Mr. DiBona: You can structure them so it's not a problem. Auctions are a way of establishing value. But they're a problem because they may generate very large revenues.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
