<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Earth Comes First</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="270735"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="FOREIGN AFFAIRS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTICS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, FLORA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D9153FF933A05754C0A96F948260" item-length="793" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Earth Comes First</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Flora Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, FLORA</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Some criticized President Bush's pledge to establish a Moon colony and a manned flight to Mars for lacking specifics about dates and money. But the real trouble is the idea itself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Some criticized President Bush's pledge to establish a Moon colony and a manned flight to Mars for lacking specifics about dates and money. But the real trouble is the idea itself.</p>
        <p>Some criticized President Bush's pledge to establish a Moon colony and a manned flight to Mars for lacking specifics about dates and money. But the real trouble is the idea itself.</p>
        <p>Nostalgia for the proud glow that suffused the nation, and much of the world, when Neil Armstrong made his ''giant step for mankind'' 20 years ago isn't much reason for an extravagant new commitment. Have people forgotten how quickly it faded and left us with our real problems?</p>
        <p>Space exploration is useful as well as satisfying to our innate, healthy desire to know more about the universe surrounding us. But it can be done at least as efficiently and at vastly less expense without shooting people off the home planet for a long time to come.</p>
        <p>There are some quirky, narrow-based arguments for manned missions. One is NASA's eagerness for grandiose projects to keep it in business. Another is the wish of a few to be the ones to provide a vicarious great adventure to the rest of us. The former astronaut Rusty Schweikert advances the odd thesis that mankind's genetic pool is wearing thin and can be refreshed by extraterrestrial exposure.</p>
        <p>The real appeal, though, is an underlying sense of need for a ''vision,'' an enterprise to give wings to the imagination and a feeling of grand purpose as we go about mundane affairs. Looking to the Moon and Mars is looking in the wrong direction. The time has come to find that vision on Earth. We have seen it in the photographs from space, the luminous blue ball swathed in lacy mists, sailing serenely through the emptiness. You could put a tiny ''x'' on the picture and mail it to friends with the message ''That's where I live.'' But it doesn't look like that down here, and the way things are going we don't know how much longer it will look like that from out there.</p>
        <p>The warnings come in a barrage now: sick seas awash with suffocating algae, ultraviolet radiation due to ozone depletion, global warming, loss of topsoil (24 billion tons a year) as the population swells (by 86 million a year), loss of air-purifying forests.</p>
        <p>And they are beginning to be heard. At the Paris summit meeting, the Group of Seven put major emphasis on the need for far-reaching environmental initiatives. For the first time, there was top-level recognition that development, debt reduction and environment are linked problems that must be addressed in a common context.</p>
        <p>President Francois Mitterrand of France, who supports the idea of a European environmental agency, has pointed out that there is no ''political authority capable of taking decisions on a global scale'' and that ''the level of decision is not equal to the risk.''</p>
        <p>This is true, but environment has become a mainstream political issue in many countries, including Communist-run states. ''Green'' parties are sprouting in most democracies. People are ready to pay attention when clear, specific programs are offered.</p>
        <p>The American Forestry Association launched a campaign to plant 100 million trees in U.S. cities by 1992, which would take only a drop out of the carbon dioxide bucket. But experts have concluded that planting lots more trees and protecting existing forests could make a significant difference in this menace to the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The U.S. General Accounting Office estimates that there are 130,000 to 425,000 hazardous waste sites in the U.S. The Environmental Protection Agency has started cleanups of 257 and completed 48 since 1980, according to World Watch Institute.</p>
        <p>Public concern and availability of information have come a long way since Ronald Reagan assured everybody that ''acid rain comes from trees'' and is nothing to worry about.</p>
        <p>But the explosion of awareness has a drawback. There are so many aspects to the degradation we are imposing on our planet, so many kinds of problems, scientific, industrial and agricultural, local, national and global, that it's hard to know where to start. Mind-boggling disasters are predicted. Proposals come pouring out at a bewildering rate, without priorities or clear focus.</p>
        <p>This is the subject to pull together in a grand vision, to offer the goal of a sustainable earth, to provoke hope through action in which all can participate, and not just arouse dread.</p>
        <p>It will take the coordinated expertise of a great many people, just as man-on-the-Moon did. It will take a lot of our money, in the same way. It will take explanation, exhortation, provision of a unifying understanding that saving the earth is a noble, exhilarating endeavor in which all can take pride.</p>
        <p>We do need to look forward to something exciting. Return to the Moon? Maybe some day. Anyway, it won't be the same the second time. For the poetry of leadership he seeks, let Mr. Bush proclaim: Meanwhile, back on the earth . . .</p>
        <p>FOREIGN AFFAIRS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
