<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tougher Fuel Economy Rules Planned, in Shift From Reagan</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="240286"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY EFFICIENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0D91F3BF936A25757C0A96F948260" item-length="980" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tougher Fuel Economy Rules Planned, in Shift From Reagan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr., Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Taking an opportunity to embrace oil conservation and clean air, the Bush Administration will soon announce a tightening of fuel efficiency rules for 1990 model automobiles, Government and auto industry officials say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Taking an opportunity to embrace oil conservation and clean air, the Bush Administration will soon announce a tightening of fuel efficiency rules for 1990 model automobiles, Government and auto industry officials say.</p>
        <p>Taking an opportunity to embrace oil conservation and clean air, the Bush Administration will soon announce a tightening of fuel efficiency rules for 1990 model automobiles, Government and auto industry officials say.</p>
        <p>The decision, denying requests by General Motors and others to relax standards set by law in 1975, would reverse the practice of the Reagan Administration.</p>
        <p>Transportation Secretary Samuel K. Skinner has decided that auto makers should be required to attain an average fuel consumption of 27.5 miles per gallon in all the cars they sell, Government officials said. The current standard is 26.5 miles per gallon.</p>
        <p>The officials expect President Bush to endorse the decision, which has been under intense scrutiny at the White House for about two weeks.</p>
        <p>The ruling will not have drastic repercussions in Detroit, although the automobile industry will hardly welcome it. It is too late to change the designs of automobiles in the 1990 model year.</p>
        <p>Because the standards apply to the average mileage of all vehicles made by a particular company in a given year, the companies will use sales techniques to meet the standards. Using incentives to encourage purchase of small cars and setting higher prices on larger ones would prod buyers away from increasingly popular big automobiles toward more fuel-efficient models.  'We Can't Force People'</p>
        <p>On being informed of the plan, Gerald Stofflet, a General Motors official, said: ''We can't force people into more fuel-efficient cars.'' He said that recent gas price increases did not appear to have driven buyers to smaller cars. Officials at other auto companies declined to comment on the development until a decision is announced.</p>
        <p>Companies can fall short of the standard in one year without incurring penalties if they exceed the standards in other years.</p>
        <p>More notable are the political ramifications of the decision. The Reagan Administration had proposed repealing the requirements, which are set out in the Government's corporate automotive fuel economy standards, or CAFE. Instead, Congress is now considering proposals that would substantially increase the standards, which were first set in the oil crisis of 1974.</p>
        <p>''If it indicates a first step in raising the standards as we move out into the 1990's, then I think it is significant,'' Charles K. Ebinger, an energy expert at the International Resources Group, a consulting concern in Washington, said of the prospective tighter standard.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said the decision to tighten standards for 1990 did not imply a forceful push for even more efficient automobiles in later years. Administration officials say that especially after the Exxon Valdez oil spill in Alaska, the ruling will help the Administration portray itself as being environmentalist.</p>
        <p>One consideration in tightening the standards, say officials involved in the rule making, was the need to reduce oil consumption to counter what scientists say is a global warming trend that they attribute in part to pollution from burning of fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>Officials said Secretary Skinner was especially mindful of energy production and import trends as he reached his decision. Because automobiles burn about 30 percent of all the oil consumed in the United States, fuel-efficient cars have long been seen as a primary tool for conservation. Imports of Foreign Autos</p>
        <p>Cars imported by foreign manufacturers must also meet the standards. Small imports have no trouble doing so, but foreign companies that make primarily large or powerful cars have had trouble. Manufacturers of cars like the Jaguar, Porsche and Mercedes have paid civil penalties for falling short of the standards. The penalties per car come to $50 for every mile per gallon below the standard. For these luxury cars, the importers' profits make up for the cost of the penalties.</p>
        <p>At a time when oil imports have just caught up with domestic production and demand for gasoline is growing, the fuel efficiency of autos has reached a plateau. It had roughly doubled since 1974, although experts disagree whether this resulted from Federal regulations or higher gasoline prices.</p>
        <p>A recent study by the Congressional Office of Technology Assessment found that while fuel efficiency would continue to increase as old, inefficient cars were gradually replaced, the rate of increase would ''drastically slow.'' A major factor, it said, is consumer demand for relatively inefficient large cars, small trucks and four-wheel drive vehicles.</p>
        <p>Jim Burnley, who as Transportation Secretary in the Reagan Administration relaxed the standards, said this week that in his view ''the whole CAFE scheme is in terms of public policy ridiculous, and has the practical effects of driving U.S. jobs abroad.'' Maneuvers to Meet Standards</p>
        <p>Under the law, the standard rose to 27.5 miles per gallon in 1985. Beginning in 1986 the Reagan Administration granted industry requests for lower standards each year: to 26 miles per gallon from 1986 through 1988, and to 26.5 miles per gallon in the current year. As a result, some auto makers have been able to meet and even exceed the standards, earning credits with which to offset lapses in other years.</p>
        <p>But the companies argue that this was done partly by shifting the production of large cars overseas. The fuel-efficiency standards are applied separately to cars produced domestically and those that are imported or made largely of imported parts.</p>
        <p>The automobile manufacturers say that to compete with small cars built at low cost overseas, they must make many of their smallest, most efficient models abroad.</p>
        <p>But domestic automobile lines, weighted toward large car production, have a hard time attaining the standards. One way to tilt this balance back is to shift the production of large cars and components abroad, making the big cars count in the import column.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
