<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ODE ON AN OED</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="240830"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DICTIONARIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KENNER, HUGH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMPSON, J A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEINER, E S C</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">OXFORD ENGLISH DICTIONARY, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D81630F935A25757C0A96F948260" item-length="2507" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ODE ON AN OED</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HUGH KENNER; Hugh Kenner, a professor of English at Johns Hopkins University, through the years has reviewed myriads, more or less, of reference books.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KENNER, HUGH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  THE OXFORD ENGLISH DICTIONARY  Second Edition.  Prepared by J. A. Simpson and E. S. C. Weiner.  20 volumes. 21,728 pp. New York:  Clarendon Press/Oxford University Press. $2,500.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  THE OXFORD ENGLISH DICTIONARY  Second Edition.  Prepared by J. A. Simpson and E. S. C. Weiner.  20 volumes. 21,728 pp. New York:  Clarendon Press/Oxford University Press. $2,500.</p>
        <p>THE OXFORD ENGLISH DICTIONARY  Second Edition.  Prepared by J. A. Simpson and E. S. C. Weiner.  20 volumes. 21,728 pp. New York:  Clarendon Press/Oxford University Press. $2,500.</p>
        <p>So here it is at last, the distinguished thing, and at 11.5 cents a page not really overpriced. For these pages average 2,300 words. Thus Stephen King's hard-cover publisher charges more per word for phrasing far less meticulously thought out. ''Meticulously''? That contains the Latin ''metus,'' fear, and it used to connote timid fussing such as you'd smirk at. But the Oxford English Dictionary's dated citations permit you to watch as in the 20th-century meticulousness slides toward the admirable: ''careful, punctilious, scrupulous, precise.''</p>
        <p>All four of those words apply to any OED entry. Take ''adamant,'' which my favorite one-volume dictionary, Webster's Ninth New Collegiate, disposes of in six lines. In the Oxford they accord it half a page, from which we learn that its Greek root means ''untamable''; that Greeks and then Romans applied it to the hardest substances they knew of (ultimately the diamond); then that ''early med.L. writers'' got hung up on ''adamare,'' Latin for ''to love deeply,'' and took to using ''Lapidem Adamantem,'' the Attracting Stone, for the new-fangled magnet. ''With this confusion the word passed into the modern languages''; that's why you can hardly feel sure what Shakespeare, for one, means by it:</p>
        <p>You draw me, you hard-hearted Adamant,</p>
        <p>But yet you draw not Iron, for my heart</p>
        <p>Is true as steele.  That is ''A Midsummer Night's Dream,'' and virtual nonsense. But the sense of unyieldingness somehow prevailed, and by 1936 we find adamant meaning just plain stubborn (though the point at which it slid from noun to adjective is ''not determinable''). The OED's final citation is from a 1961 London Sunday Times: '' 'When it's a girl her mother should be the one interviewed,' he stated adamantly.'' We've drifted far, far from diamonds. It is by such means, entry after patient entry, that the huge work offers us keys to the kingdom of English.</p>
        <p>In the first edition, the citations for ''adamant'' stop at 1878, well before anyone was stating adamantly. That was because Oxford published the first part of ''A'' as long ago as 1884, and kept it locked in type. From then clear to 1928 the work emerged piecemeal, in units of (normally) 64 pages, collected by thrifty folk for future binding. By the time the whole dictionary was available in a 12-volume set (1933), so much new material had flooded in that the earlier portions were already obsolete. So the same year saw a supplementary volume; and when a second (four-volume) Supplement got added (1972-86), meticulous users found themselves consulting three alphabets. It was time, they decided at Oxford, to consolidate.</p>
        <p>Briefly: with generous help from I.B.M.-United Kingdom Ltd., the whole huge bank of knowledge got computerized, the supplementary entries now made integral with what they'd once supplemented. Henceforward, no more of tacking new stuff on at the end. A novelty inserted in its proper place now nudges everything to its right further rightward. In the process some 5,000 new words (and new uses of old words) got added: ''acid rain,'' ''daisy-wheel,'' ''Amex,''</p>
        <p>''Visa,'' ''CAT,'' ''brain-dead,'' ''dingbat''; the computerist's sense of ''Pascal,'' the mathematician's of ''set.'' (And hang on, we'll be getting back to ''set.'' No review may slight so eccentric a tour de force.) I've made that all sound easier than it was. The keyboarding, subcontracted to a firm outside Philadelphia in Fort Washington, Pa., took 180 people 18 months. Custom software nicknamed Oedipus Lex (OED Integration, Proofing and Updating System) got written in England, while at the University of Waterloo, in Ontario, people devised the data base code to keep track of structural ''tags,'' more or less the elements typography sorts out on the page: pronunciations, etymologies, subdivisions of senses, instances ordered by date. At one stage the eyeglasses of fully five dozen proofreaders were being wiped with unreckonable Kleenexes. (Kleenex, 1925: ''the proprietary name of an absorbent disposable cleansing paper tissue'' - and 10 citations from such sources as Trade Marks Journal, Noel Coward, Gypsy Rose Lee, Graham Greene.) The result is so up-to-now it's even captured ''fax'' (v.t., 1979, with examples down to 1986).</p>
        <p>So a certain Victorian aroma has evaporated from the OED. (Those four-letter words, even; yes, they're now treated in full. That began as long ago as the Supplements.) It is still, though, recognizably the work Sir James Murray shaped and guided for 38 years, with no more resources than pen, paper and pigeonholes. Murray, whose granddaughter Elisabeth's life of him, ''Caught in the Web of Words,'' ranks with the most entrancing of biographies, had been exactly the man (stern, Scottish, fanatical) to organize the fumblings of the Philological Society, a loose gathering of zealots who thought it a national disgrace that there was no decent English dictionary.</p>
        <p>The society had been aroused by Richard Chenevix Trench, Dean of Westminster, later Anglican Archbishop of Dublin, who wrote in 1851 that ''Many a single word . . . is itself a concentrated poem, having stores of poetical thought and imagery laid up in it.'' Trench had read in ''The Poet'' by Ralph Waldo Emerson (1844) about all language being ''fossil poetry.'' The job of a dictionary should be not to legislate usage but to display a tongue's slow unfolding word by word from its stubborn roots. To capture that process, for the whole of the documented language, was the project Murray was rash enough to undertake and stubborn enough to bring as far as the letter T - in the midst of which, ''Trink to Turndown'' just issued, he died in 1915 at the age of 78.</p>
        <p>Even 50 years earlier the enterprise would not have been thinkable. For one thing, ''the great consonant shift'' (formulated by Jakob Grimm in 1822) was then undreamed of. Now it could explain countless perplexing matters, such as how English ''fish'' was connected not only with Saxon ''fisc'' but with Latin ''piscis.'' That made usable Sir William Jones's conception of an Indo-European language family, to which English belongs and to which Sanskrit is a main clue. (Sanskrit! Samuel Johnson had made do with Latin, Greek, Hebrew.) Also, printed books had been growing plentiful. Steel pens (1831) had superseded goose quills. And a decent postal service was in place, steam-driven, to bring the penned findings of countless readers to Oxford. For the vast project depended on many hundreds of readers combing through book after book for each word that struck them, filling out a slip with word, book, page, quotation. Slips by the hundreds of thousands rained in on Murray. As 11 little Murrays one by one grew literate, they earned pocket money alphabetizing.</p>
        <p>The great task, though, was organizing what the alphabet could bring together; which leads us to ''set.'' ''The language,'' Murray wrote in 1881, ''seems not to contain a more perplexing word.'' By then an assistant had spent 40 hours organizing it. Thirty-some years later - time to confront the S's in earnest - ''set'' 's final ordering would consume 40 days.</p>
        <p>Part of the trouble inheres in the Teutonic structure of the earliest English roots. But what a German dictionary can regard as ''separable prefixes'' - ''absetzen,'' ''aufsetzen,''</p>
        <p>''vorsetzen'' - and banish to different alphabetical places, an English lexicon must treat as instances of plain ''set'' - ''set up,''</p>
        <p>''set to,'' ''set forth,'' ''set out'' (verb plus preposition) - to be managed all in one entry. That seems to entail pretending that ''set'' has a core meaning for every preposition in the language to somehow modify, and assigning such a core meaning is nigh impossible.</p>
        <p>The final arrangement of ''set,'' achieved under the by then septuagenarian Murray, is perhaps lexicography's Eroica Symphony. The noun occasions two movements, one related to ''seat'' (as, ''where the sun sets''), the other to ''sect'' (as, ''a sett of avaricious Hucksters''). In both movements the orchestra grows agitated; the first ''set'' is soon evoking (I.10.d) ''Of a woman: A determined attempt to gain a man's affections'' and (I.19.b) ''The slight lateral deflexion in opposite directions of the alternate teeth of a saw,'' while the second divagates into such areas as (I.4) ''The number of persons required to perform a country dance,'' or (II.9.b) ''The complement of teeth (natural or artificial) with which a person (or animal) is furnished.''</p>
        <p>It is ''set'' the verb, though, that really runs amok. Its categories include sitting, then descending. But soon they start a frantic revel, till we're getting ''Of a rabbit: To be resting,'' or ''Of a soft-nosed bullet: To expand on impact.'' While the conductor Murray keeps on staunchly beating time, his measures visit the timpani, flutter in the strings, exhaust and even re-exhaust the alphabet con brio - in one instance from ''a'' to ''z'' and from ''aa'' clear to ''rr'' - while the look of barely comprehensible order, imposed here and there by recourse even to Greek-lettered sequences, contends with utter semantic wildness: ''to arrange the pleats of a gown''; ''to prepare woad for dyeing''; ''to flow in the reverse direction''; ''to soil the next leaf or sheet.'' Anything in the universe seems ready to turn up under ''set.'' A lifetime feels insufficient for grasping the grand design of those 60,000 words, a fettered anarchy fully four-fifths the length of Milton's ''Paradise Lost.'' And hadn't Milton undertaken the easier task, relying as he could on a plot? If the OED is the Victorian epic poem, is its ''set'' not perhaps the Georgian ''Finnegans Wake''? (In the first edition, the ratio between ''set'' and ''Paradise Lost'' was closer to 2 to 3; that gives an idea of what the language has been up to in seven decades while the OED waited and watched.) We next confront the vexing fact that the words that cause the most trouble - words like ''set'' and ''black'' and ''water'' - are just the ones least likely to be looked up. You might turn to a dictionary to learn what ''borborygmus'' means (bowel rumble) and find a definition some clerk wrote in five minutes. What turned a James Murray's hair white you're unlikely to scan at all. The earliest dictionaries were merely lists of hard words; it was only when the quest for completeness started reaching for the common words too that lexicography became a calling for saints.</p>
        <p>Another rule of the intricate game the editors have agreed on is that they'll use no pictures, not a one. My Webster's has a fine striped aardwolf on its very first page. The OED, which doesn't reach the aards (-vark, -wolf) till as late as page seven - though Lord! its dealings with plain A! - makes do with ''A South-African carnivorous quadruped (Proteles Lalandii St. Hil.), of the size of a fox, occupying an intermediate position between the dogs, hyenas, and civets'' (citations from 1833, 1847). Webster's wording, even, is more visual than that: ''A maned striped mammal (Proteles cristata) of southern and eastern Africa that resembles the related hyena and feeds chiefly on carrion and insects.'' Clearly, the OED assumes a client who's far from asking what an aardwolf looks like - no, one athirst for such taxonomic insight as it's austerely willing to provide.</p>
        <p>But Lalandii vs. Webster's cristata: that discrepancy does fuel one's suspicion that the science in some older entries remains a mite old-fashioned. A need for resident scientists on the staff wasn't felt till as late as 1967, when the editor paid an eye-opening visit to the Merriam-Webster offices. Earlier, Webster's Third of 1961 had documented an explosive development of English outside of England. That disturbed a good deal of complacency, and the reach of the Second Edition of the OED extends everywhere you can think of.</p>
        <p>You'll find ''Faulknerian,'' for instance, and ''blue grass'' (the latter documented from 1751, but missed by Murray's team completely). You'll find Ezra Pound cited as the first authority for ''persona'' (1909), the role played by a writer in his work. You'll find coinages like Eliot's ''polyphiloprogenitive'' (1919) and Joyce's ''riverrun'' (1939). On that theme, Frank Tompa of Waterloo University, who helped devise the retrieval software, needed about 10 seconds at his console to scan 350 million characters (the actual scan took only one second; it took Mr. Tompa nine seconds to type in the command) and advise me that the OED now sports an astonishing 184 citations from darkest ''Finnegans Wake.''</p>
        <p>One, of course, is under ''quark,'' with ''Three quarks for Muster Mark'' to illustrate the assertion of the physicist Murray Gell-Mann that he named those elusive particles with Joyce's aid. Where did Joyce, though, come upon the word? Speculation has ranged pointlessly far, as far even as the Swiss-German name for cottage cheese. But Joyce's ''quarks'' are emitted by sea-birds. And what's this, higher up on the same page? ''Quark: to croak,'' with an 1893 citation: ''The herons quarked harshly.'' That entry dates from Murray's time, and Joyce's.</p>
        <p>So the ''quark'' that helps certify scope and up-to-dateness for the OED's Second Edition got there via ''Finnegans Wake,'' the book of a tireless dictionary fan who in all likelihood had skimmed ''quark'' originally from the First Edition of the OED.  ALL OR NOTHING AT ALL</p>
        <p>Don't think of it as a dictionary; think of it as five cartons, each about 10 by 16 by 12 inches and weighing 30 pounds, piled up on your doorstep by United Parcel Service, all the way from a warehouse in Fairlawn, N.J., four to six weeks after you order the Second Edition of the Oxford English Dictionary. All you have to do to cause this to happen is dial (800) 451-7556 and give Oxford University Press a credit card number that's good for $2,500 - the price of the 20 volumes - plus $75 for shipping charges. As of early this month, Oxford had sold 841 sets in the United States, out of the total print run of 10,000 sets.</p>
        <p>The original 12 volumes of the First Edition, issued from 1884 to 1928, were sold by subscription in paperbound segments as they became available, and you can still have the First Edition in computer-readable form (on CD-ROM, I.B.M. compatible) from Oxford for $995. The First Edition is also still available photographically reduced into two large volumes of tiny type, magnifying glass included, for $27.95 through the Book-of-the-Month Club as a premium for joining, or from Oxford for $195.</p>
        <p>There are no other ways of purchasing the new Second Edition - for the time being at least, it's all or nothing at all.</p>
        <p>But it may be possible to find discounts at local booksellers. One neighborhood store in Brooklyn, for instance, Bookcourt at 163 Court Street, will order it for you at 15 percent off - $2,125.  TOM FERRELL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
