<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Outdoors: A Pond, An 'Old Man' And Philosophy</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="261638"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISHING, SPORT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAINES, HOWELL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DD1130F935A15755C0A96F948260" item-length="1094" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Outdoors: A Pond, An 'Old Man' And Philosophy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWELL RAINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAINES, HOWELL</byline>
      <dateline>BROAD RUN, Va.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IT looked to be an ordinary farm pond. But it was also an oasis in the vast Sahara of parenting: an opportunity to play ''the old man.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IT looked to be an ordinary farm pond. But it was also an oasis in the vast Sahara of parenting: an opportunity to play ''the old man.''</p>
        <p>IT looked to be an ordinary farm pond. But it was also an oasis in the vast Sahara of parenting: an opportunity to play ''the old man.''</p>
        <p>''I want you to remember this day,'' I told my 17-year-old son, Jeffrey. ''I've been fishing for 40 years, and I've never seen fish striking any more rapidly than they are right now.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, this was fishing good enough to stand up to a little philosophy. In a patch of water no larger than a bathtub, large bluegills offered manic strikes the instant our flies touched the water. So as not to spook the spawning fish, we took turns casting into this shaded spot over a drowned tree top.</p>
        <p>Only after one of us had hooked up and played his fish into open water near our canoe would the other make a cast. Spawning bluegills are not skittish, but too much surface activity will drive them off the ''beds.''</p>
        <p>These fish were thick, muscular males, wearing mating colors of pink and orange along their bellies. We were casting what I entered in my fishing journal as Smith Rigs - double-fly leaders named in honor of our hosts. (Smith is not their real name; they wanted to avoid a traffic jam on their splendid little lake.) Sometimes the fish came two at a time. In five hours, we must have landed over 150, releasing all except a score that we cleaned and shared with the owners.</p>
        <p>A nice thing about this day was that it was part of a spring in which I have caught more fish, killed fewer and stumbled onto more effective new flies than in any season since that fateful day in 1949 when my parents let me play hooky to catch my first limit of crappie.</p>
        <p>The trick has been to dodge the thunderstorms and the barbs of my trout-fishing friends who think I've reverted altogether to chasing the warm-water species I grew up with in Alabama.</p>
        <p>Trout still figure in my dreams, plans and tackle purchases, but the fact is that the fishing in the waters around Washington for largemouth and smallmouth bass and the various sunfish species has been so good since late April as to be irresistible.</p>
        <p>It was guilt, I suppose, that led to my reliance on the Smith rig. I always feel lousy about killing a brook trout. So this spring I stopped by the Smith's pond on my way to meet my two sons and Tennant McWilliams, a lifelong fishing companion, for our annual brook-trout trip to the Shenandoah National Park near Sperryville, Va.</p>
        <p>A low, gray sky and fitful rain did not bode well for my plan to catch enough bluegills and bass for a big fish fry, so as to prevent our being tempted to murder any of the precious native trout in Jeremy's Run.</p>
        <p>I had in my vest a style of Orvis leaders used most often in early season trout fishing. It has a dropper tied in about 18 inches from the end, so that a cast of two wet flies can be presented at once. Since I was hoping to feed four people, I decided to double my chances. My only claim to inventiveness was that I tied a floating bug, a cork-bodied chartreuse Sneaky Pete, on the bitter end and a small white streamer called the Wooly Bugger on the dropper. Soon I found that while both bass and large bluegills occasionally took the surface bug, bluegills found the streamer dangling a few inches under the surface absolutely irresistible. And they hit with such vigor that the floating fly, acting as a bobber, would zoom out of sight in a most stimulating way.</p>
        <p>In the course of the spring, I've tried other combinations. On the Rappahannock River, a fast-running smallmouth stream in central Virginia, I had success with a new streamer that Lefty Kreh, a great fly caster and fishing authority, regards as one of the best smallmouth flies ever made. It is called the Clouser's Deep Minnow and is the invention of Bob Clouser, proprietor of Clouser's Fly Shop in Middletown, Pa. One morning, when Jeff and his four teen-age friends refused to rouse from their tents for the early fishing, I took over 40 fish before breakfast.</p>
        <p>Actually, I should have known things would work out well when I called Clouser to order eight Deep Minnows in various colors. ''I'm not one to brag,'' he said over the telephone, ''but you better hold on to your fly rod when you throw one of these things in.''</p>
        <p>Clouser, a renowned guide on his Susquehanna home waters, also put me on to another fly that has become a favorite. It is Clouser's Swimming Nymph, a furry, impressionistic wet fly based on the aquatic insect larvae that abounds in many trout and smallmouth streams. The reddish-brown version was murderous on the Rappahannock, and to my surprise, I have found the tan version to be extremely effective when fished on the Smith rig in still-water ponds. Bass are particularly fond of it, and the Swimming Nymph was the star of the great day Jeffrey and I had.</p>
        <p>But fishing loses its appeal if it becomes too free of frustration. The estimable Orvis Company provided some in the form of unreliable knots. Now that I am addicted to their two-fly leaders, I am haunted by the fact that I have had three failures in the factory-tied knots in these otherwise fine products. Orvis, consider this a public appeal to hold a refresher course on the blood knot in your leader department in Manchester, Vt. I am so adept at losing big fish through sloppy tactics that I do not need any help from my tackle.</p>
        <p>In fact, I lost the best fish of the season on that fine day on the Smith's pond. For several years, I have been carrying a big swimming fly called the Dahlberg Diver, just waiting for its moment to arrive. About an hour before dark, I tied it on my seven-weight fly rod and hurled it into the shoreline growth among a bunch of willows. Following a heavy strike, a bass of two pounds or more burst from the water - once, then twice -as sleek and businesslike as a torpedo. I stripped line furiously as the fish moved toward the canoe. Then on third leap, the hook, which was flopping from its lower lip like a dentist's siphon, pulled free.</p>
        <p>''Dad, you horsed him,'' said Jeffrey in a quiet voice.</p>
        <p>I responded with a blizzard of excuses. The hook was dull. This big rod was too stiff - I needed my whippy little five-weight. Or maybe it was the wind. Or the stock market. Global warming. The Federal deficit.</p>
        <p>''I think you just put too much pressure on him,'' Jeffrey said in a maddeningly regretful tone. What is worse at such moments than the true sympathy of a loved one?</p>
        <p>My shoulders sagged. The kid was right. Well, if I couldn't have my fish, at least he could have the pleasure of correcting my technique. When the fishing is good enough, everyone gets a chance to play the old man.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
