<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senators' Goal: Make New Ideas Pay Their Own Way</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="233227"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SENATE (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">APPLE, R W JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WIRTH, TIMOTHY E (SEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DB123BF933A15750C0A96F948260" item-length="1035" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senators' Goal: Make New Ideas Pay Their Own Way</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R. W. APPLE Jr., Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">APPLE, R W JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A generation ago, political conversations here were routinely punctuated, if not interrupted, by the question, ''But what about the Vietnam War?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A generation ago, political conversations here were routinely punctuated, if not interrupted, by the question, ''But what about the Vietnam War?''</p>
        <p>A generation ago, political conversations here were routinely punctuated, if not interrupted, by the question, ''But what about the Vietnam War?''</p>
        <p>The present-day equivalent is, ''But what about the budget deficit?'' That question (and, of course, the reality of straitened Federal finances that lies behind it) has become a major impediment for activist politicians.</p>
        <p>From President Bush to Senator Edward M. Kennedy, Republicans and Democrats and conservatives and liberals who have new ideas for government find them blocked; there is an almost universal conviction in the Capital that scarce resources must be concentrated on a major effort to bring the deficit under control.</p>
        <p>Gradually, under the goad of these limitations, younger senators are beginning to search for new approaches to old problems. Among the Democrats engaged in the process are Tim Wirth of Colorado, Al Gore of Tennessee, Bill Bradley of New Jersey, Bob Graham of Florida and Tom Daschle of South Dakota. Among the Republicans are John Heinz of Pennsylvania, Trent Lott of Mississippi and John McCain of Arizona. A Fruitful Marriage Is Seen</p>
        <p>Consider one of Mr. Wirth's ideas.</p>
        <p>The Senator, an advocate of increased spending on education and of energy conservation, says the two could be fruitfully linked, especially in the military, without costing the Government money. Indeed, he says, money could be saved if 65 or 75 cents of every dollar saved on military bases through reduced electrical consumption and gasoline usage was allocated to base schools.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wirth, who serves on the board of the United States Air Force Academy at Colorado Springs, says he hopes the academy will try the idea.</p>
        <p>''We have a choice,'' he said in a conversation the other day. ''We can have four years of stasis, with no real government action on our pressing problems, Democrats blaming Republicans and vice versa, the public increasingly disgusted with all of us. Or we can face up to reality, let that drive our thinking and try to come up with smarter, more practical solutions.''</p>
        <p>All these Senators are between 40 and 52 years of age, young by Senate standards, and all are in their first terms except Mr. Bradley and Mr. Heinz, who are in their second and third terms respectively. The budgetary question they are groping with, each in a different way, is preoccupying official Washington. 'More Will Than Wallet'</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's pledge not to impose new taxes, at least in his first year in office, taken together with the Democrats' belief that they would commit political hara-kiri if they sponsored new taxes without his agreement, means that for some time to come the nation is likely to have much ''more will than wallet,'' as the President said in his Inaugural Address.</p>
        <p>In that speech, making a virtue of necessity, he called for ''a new activism,'' by which he meant a redoubling of the country's already prodigious volunteer social and charitable activity. Democrats don't think that will suffice. But many of them are not persuaded, either, by those of their brethren, like Gov. Michael S. Dukakis of Massachusetts, who argue that the needed funds should be created by deep cuts in military spending. Too deep, the skeptics think, and the old image of Democratic ''softness'' will recur.</p>
        <p>One solution, of course, is to try to substitute exhortation for programatic spending. Mr. Bush has confessed he will have to do some of that in the campaign against drugs. A second solution is symbolic acts that don't cost much money, if any; an example is the ban on imports of semiautomatic assault rifles. A third is cuts in some domestic programs to spend more on others. That is favored by the President as a way of aiding the homeless, but strongly opposed and therefore blocked by the Democratic majorities in Congress. Making the New Pay Its Way</p>
        <p>The approach of Mr. Wirth to several problems, and that of others to other issues, is completely different. What they seek to do, broadly speaking, is find ways to make new programs pay for themselves wholly or in part.</p>
        <p>''If you can use the energy and the language of market economics, you can win,'' the Colorado lawmaker said. ''That's what liberals and social activists have never understood and what they have never been able to do. Now some of us are trying, and we are finding new friends across the aisle.''</p>
        <p>In an hour's talk, Mr. Wirth mentioned a number of notions that he is tinkering with, including financing more and better national parks by ''charging a fee, yes, but putting the receipts in a trust fund like that used for highway construction, not putting it in the Treasury to build weapons.'' Another idea is somehow using a debt swap with such Latin countries as Argentina to pay for more vigorous efforts to impede the flow of illegal drugs.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most thoroughly considered of his schemes is Project 88, a plan to ''harness market forces to protect the environment,'' which Mr. Wirth and Mr. Heinz co-sponsored. Convinced that major issues like waste disposal, acid rain, radon and ozone shortages in the stratosphere, dramatized by the problems of last summer, will require more governmental action, they also believe it is impractical to use the old methods. Business vs. Government</p>
        <p>Recommending an array of tradable credits and permits, taxes, swaps, refunds and deposits to tackle 16 major economic problems, the two Senators urge that Congress set the environmental standards as before but leave the doing to the private sector ''by providing incentives for business and individuals to go beyond what regulators can require.''</p>
        <p>For example, they propose to attack sulfur dioxide from aging electricity-generating plants, which contributes heavily to acid rain, not by requiring business to install scrubbers, but by setting overall limits for such emissions, then letting companies with low-pollution plants trade or sell credits to companies with high-pollution plants or use them to offset their own installations with high emissions.</p>
        <p>The ideas have split the environmental lobby, with the Environmental Defense Fund, for example, backing them but the larger Natural Resources Defense Council bitterly opposing them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
