<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Audubon Group Finds Its Interests Extend Far to South</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="265011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIRDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CENTRAL AMERICA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH AMERICA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BELIZE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">AUDUBON SOCIETY, MASSACHUSSETTS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">COCA-COLA CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Belize</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Belize</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DA1F3CF932A25754C0A96F948260" item-length="913" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Audubon Group Finds Its Interests Extend Far to South</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ASIDE from the fact that they are former British colonies and about the same size, Massachusetts and Belize would seem to have little in common. But they do share the wood thrush, the hooded warbler, the American redstart, the Northern waterthrush and the crested flycatcher.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ASIDE from the fact that they are former British colonies and about the same size, Massachusetts and Belize would seem to have little in common. But they do share the wood thrush, the hooded warbler, the American redstart, the Northern waterthrush and the crested flycatcher.</p>
        <p>ASIDE from the fact that they are former British colonies and about the same size, Massachusetts and Belize would seem to have little in common. But they do share the wood thrush, the hooded warbler, the American redstart, the Northern waterthrush and the crested flycatcher.</p>
        <p>These songbirds nest in New England and spend the winter in Belize and other Central American countries. This migratory connection has prompted the Massachusetts Audubon Society to help start a multimillion-dollar conservation effort in Belize that is intended in part to protect the birds.</p>
        <p>The forests and other areas used by the songbirds as wintering grounds are rapidly being developed or degraded under the pressure of population growth, poverty, war and exploitation of land to raise beef and other products for export.</p>
        <p>The heart of the $7 million effort, called Program for Belize, will be the purchase of 110,000 acres of forest rich in wildlife along the Rio Bravo in the western part of the country. The Coca-Cola Company, which owns land in the area, will donate an additional 42,000 acres of forest, savanna and wetlands. Another 100,000 acres will be retained by a private owner and managed as part of the program. Development to Be Permitted</p>
        <p>In cooperation with the Belize Government, the land will be managed as the Rio Bravo Conservation Area for preserving wildlife and the ecological system in ways that will also permit economic development.</p>
        <p>''The Massachusetts Audubon Society has a budget of $6 million a year, 200 people on its staff, 44,000 members and maintains sanctuaries totaling 8,500 acres,'' said James Baird, vice president of the society. ''But it will do us no good whatsoever to protect the areas in Massachusetts where wood thrushes nest if when the wood thrushes leave here they have no place to go.</p>
        <p>''It may seem like a selfish interest,'' he continued, ''but Massachusetts Audubon has always been interested in assisting other countries and views the world as one big ecosystem.''</p>
        <p>The environmental group gave $200,000 to the Belize program, lent it $300,000 and is helping to raise more money to complete the purchase of the land for the conservation area. But the program itself is an independent project with both Americans and Belizeans on its board and staff. It operates by agreement with the Belize Government.</p>
        <p>F. William Burley, director of planning for the program, said that while the conservation of wildlife, including the songbirds, the jaguar and other animals and plants, is an important goal, it is not the only one.</p>
        <p>''What separates this from other environmental projects is that we are trying to make conservation work along with development,'' Mr. Burley said in a telephone interview from Belize City. By permitting appropriate development, he said, ''we make this project attractive not only to developers but to people at large in Belize.'' Mayan Ruins Open to Tourists</p>
        <p>While some areas of the conservation project would be set aside for wildlife, sustainable logging for mahogany and cedar would be permitted in other areas. Sapodilla trees will be tapped for the chicle used in chewing gum, Mr. Burley said. The area is rich in Mayan ruins, which will be opened to tourism.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burley said conditions for conservation in Belize were better than in most other areas of Central America because population density was relatively low, pressures on the land were not as great and the natural resource base ''has not been raped and destroyed.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, there are strong development pressures building. One of the problems Mr. Burley faces is the theft of timber from the conservation area. With mature mahogany logs worth as much as $1,000 each, poor people are tempted to cut trees illegally. ''That's as much as some of these guys earn in a year, so you can understand why they do it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Belize program is one of a number of environmental projects in Central and South America run or supported by United States environmentalists. Environmental groups are increasingly concerned that the destruction of forests and the deterioration of natural systems in Latin America contribute to such problems as the loss of species and the threat of global warming.</p>
        <p>Recently, for example, the World Wildife Fund, along with the Nature Conservancy, bought $10 million worth of Ecuador's foreign debt. The i.o.u.'s were traded to the Ecuadorean Government for local-currency bonds, which were turned over to Fundacion Natura, a nonprofit Ecuadorean group. It will use the interest on the bonds for conservation projects in the Galapagos Islands, the Amazon forests and elsewhere. Money Stays in Ecuador</p>
        <p>The benefit to the Ecuadorean Government is that it is relieved of part of its foreign debt, increasing its credit worthiness. Moreover, money that would have been paid as interest to foreign banks is now being spent in the domestic economy, generating income for the country.</p>
        <p>United States groups have participated in a number of these debt-for-nature transactions in Latin America as a means of relieving countries of part of their debt and encouraging the conservation of land and resources.</p>
        <p>Conservation International, a group that pioneered the debt-for-nature concept, recently began to carry out a new ''ecosystem conservation strategy'' in Bolivia, Costa Rica and Mexico. The strategy combines economic development with resource conservation similar to the approach being taken in Belize.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
