<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clues to Ice Age's End</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="259945"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="SCIENCE WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE AGE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Age</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D8163DF933A15755C0A96F948260" item-length="375" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clues to Ice Age's End</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Scientists have known for some time that the last ice age came to a rather sudden halt about 10,700 years ago. Now a newly published study indicates that this shift occurred extremely quickly, and at least one expert says the finding may help cope with climatic changes expected as a result of a buildup of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Scientists have known for some time that the last ice age came to a rather sudden halt about 10,700 years ago. Now a newly published study indicates that this shift occurred extremely quickly, and at least one expert says the finding may help cope with climatic changes expected as a result of a buildup of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Scientists have known for some time that the last ice age came to a rather sudden halt about 10,700 years ago. Now a newly published study indicates that this shift occurred extremely quickly, and at least one expert says the finding may help cope with climatic changes expected as a result of a buildup of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>A separate study has also concluded that most, if not all, the Greenland ice disappeared between the last two ice ages, more than 100,000 years ago. It is known, from coral reefs, that sea levels then rose 20 feet. If most of the ice on Greenland and the Canadian islands melted, it is proposed that the west Antarctic ice could not have slid into the sea, as some have theorized, or the ocean would have risen much more.</p>
        <p>The new timetable for the end of the last ice age was based on carbon dating of ice layers containing deuterium and oxygen isotopes in holes dug nearly 2,100 yards into Greenland's polar cap. The isotopes indicate temperatures when the ice was deposited as snow. A research team led by Willi Dansgaard of the Geophysical Institute of the University of Copenhagen established that a rise in temperature of about 14 degrees Fahrenheit occurred in 50 years.</p>
        <p>In addition, examination of diminishing concentrations of wind-blown continental dust in the cores led the scientists to conclude that a dramatic climate change occurred throughout sub-arctic Europe in slightly less than two decades, accompanied by milder and less turbulent weather.</p>
        <p>The study is reported in the current issue of the journal Nature.</p>
        <p>In an editorial accompanying it, David A. Peel of the British Antarctic Survey said analyzing evidence gathered from ice cores may be the best method of identifying the external factors that bring about such shifts, in turn helping researchers predict and perhaps modify future changes associated with a carbon dioxide buildup, or the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>In the May 26 issue of Science R. M. Koerner of the Geological Survey of Canada proposed that ice in Greenland may have vanished entirely, or retreated to a northern cap, during the last interglacial period. He based his conclusions on analysis of ice at the bottom of drill holes in Greenland and the Canadian islands.</p>
        <p>SCIENCE WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
