<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Market for Trading 'Pollution Rights'</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="258411"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDD1239F937A25755C0A96F948260" item-length="764" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Market for Trading 'Pollution Rights'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr., Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Bush Administration's ambitious plan to harness market forces on behalf of clean air will lead to a trading system in which ''pollution rights'' would be bought and sold like securities, with brokers matching the parties, Government and environmental sources said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Bush Administration's ambitious plan to harness market forces on behalf of clean air will lead to a trading system in which ''pollution rights'' would be bought and sold like securities, with brokers matching the parties, Government and environmental sources said today.</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration's ambitious plan to harness market forces on behalf of clean air will lead to a trading system in which ''pollution rights'' would be bought and sold like securities, with brokers matching the parties, Government and environmental sources said today.</p>
        <p>The public may be allowed to participate, a senior official of the Environmental Protection Agency said, and the development of futures markets is almost certain.</p>
        <p>Under the plan announced by President Bush on Monday, a company would have the right to keep a particular plant above the legal limit for emissions if it agreed to offset those emissions by a requisite reduction in emissions from a plant already meeting the standard. In the next phase, these ''rights to pollute''could be bought and sold among companies, and perhaps even to the general public, thus letting the marketplace, rather than the Government, decide the cheapest way to contain smokestack emissions.</p>
        <p>The day may be in sight when an environmental group, for example, could buy utility-pollution rights and then retire them, making the air cleaner through its direct financial action instead of through the political process. Environmental Defense Fund</p>
        <p>Although some elements of the market plan remain undetermined, officials at the E.P.A. and the Environmental Defense Fund, a private group that contributed heavily to the Administration's proposal, today described its workings in some detail.</p>
        <p>During the first five years - the last half of the 1990's - the owners of 107 of the nation's most offensive utility plants would be required to bring their emission levels for sulfur dioxide down to 2.5 pounds per million B.T.U.'s of electricity generated. Sulfur dioxide combines with moisture in the air to produce acid rain.</p>
        <p>The utilities, not the Government, will decide how this should be done. The options include installing scrubbers on coal-fired units and switching fuels.</p>
        <p>Under Phase 1, however, such flexibility would be limited to individual utility systems or states and, while the E.P.A. is studying whether to set up a market in emissions credits at this stage, it would be limited. Governors' Prerogatives</p>
        <p>Another feature of Phase 1 is that a governor would be allowed to override the utility executives in a state by imposing a mechanism for curbing air pollution. This is especially likely, one source said, in states like West Virginia and Ohio where large amounts of coal are both produced and burned. That creates direct conflict in choosing between preservation of mining jobs and higher electric bills for consumers.</p>
        <p>When Phase 2 begins at the turn of the century, the standard would tighten to 1.2 pounds per million B.T.U.'s. Also, 200 to 300 plants would enter the arena, and ''utilities can begin to sell credits to one another'' with little restriction, said Rob Brenner, director of air policy at the E.P.A. ''It's wide open.''</p>
        <p>Transactions would, however, probably be kept within one of two geographic areas - a 31-state region covering the Eastern states and the ones just west of the Mississippi, and a Western region of the rest of the contiguous states. This distinction is based partly on the prevalence of low-sulfur coal in the West and high-sulfur coal in the East. More than half the nation's electricity is generated from coal. The bulk of the rest comes from nuclear reactors, natural gas and oil.</p>
        <p>The Government, meanwhile, would act not as a stock exchange but as supervisor of an over-the-counter market that would spring up in the private sector. The Government's role would be limited mainly to monitoring the pollution levels and making sure the utilities had acquired sufficient rights for their emissions. It might also print the equivalent of a stock certificate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brenner said it had not yet been decided whether to give companies credit for plants that initially had better performance than the standard, or what the base would be for measuring improvement. Most likely, however, the base would include 1985, the year for which much information exists.</p>
        <p>Whether outsiders will be allowed to participate is also to be decided, probably within the next few weeks, but the planners seemed to favor the idea. If permitted, environmentalists could buy pollution credits for the purpose of retiring them, forcing down the level of legally permissible air pollution.</p>
        <p>In economic theory, the initial price of pollution rights would be the marginal cost of pollution reduction, or somewhere between $1,000 and $2,000 a ton at current prices, one official estimated.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
