<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Antarctic Accord Must Protect Environment; Support Gore Plan</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="294019"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINES AND MINING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METALS AND MINERALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL DEFENSE FUND (ORGN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, ALBERT JR (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MANHEIM, BRUCE S JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DE153EF937A15753C1A96F948260" item-length="447" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Antarctic Accord Must Protect Environment; Support Gore Plan</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Deborah Shapley's ''Polar Thinking on the Antarctic'' (Op-Ed, Oct. 17) is as thin in logic as the ozone layer over Antarctica was last month. By contending that research into global warming is threatened by those who seek a ban on development of oil and gas in Antarctica, Ms. Shapley constructs a specious argument that should be iced.</p>
        <p>Ms. Shapley extols a pending international minerals agreement that could open the continent to commercial mining as a ''victory for pragmatic diplomacy.'' Yet, if the 22 voting parties approve it, it would be a stunning defeat for the Antarctic environment and its vital role as a global monitoring laboratory. Indeed, if commercial mining ever begins in Antarctica, tanker accidents similar to the Exxon Valdez oil spill disaster in Alaska will be inevitable.</p>
        <p>What is most distressing about Ms. Shapley's views is that they are shared by officials within the Bush Administration. The State Department has consistently argued that the United States should ratify the minerals agreement rather than pursue an outright ban. These officials adamantly oppose the efforts of Australia and France to set aside Antarctica as a wilderness reserve where commercial mining is prohibited.</p>
        <p>The State Department asserts that the minerals accord would permit any party to veto plans to exploit Antarctica if the environmental risks are too high. The record of other Antarctic agreements, however, indicates that the nations responsible for managing Antarctica have in the past not raised environmental concerns for fear of upsetting delicate political relationships. The same timidity is likely to control decisions about commercial mining.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, members of Congress have recognized the fallacies of the Administration's approach. In late September, Senator Albert Gore introduced a resolution that calls upon the United States to negotiate a new agreement to protect Antarctica as a scientific preserve. Until that agreement enters into force, the resolution directs the President not to submit the minerals accord to the Senate for its consent to ratification.</p>
        <p>If Ms. Shapley is truly concerned about global warming, she should support the Gore resolution, rather than adoption of the minerals agreement. The fundamental lesson to be learned from global climate change is that we must draw the line on burning of fossil fuels at some point. Given Antarctica's vital role in understanding global warming patterns, the last untouched wilderness is a good place to start. BRUCE S. MANHEIM JR.  Washington, Oct. 18, 1989</p>
        <p>The writer is a lawyer and scientist with the Environmental Defense Fund's wildlife program.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
