<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Natural Gas May Hold Key in Global-Warming Era</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="218766"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DD173BF933A05752C0A96F948260" item-length="676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Natural Gas May Hold Key in Global-Warming Era</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Concern about the global effects of the addition of carbon dioxide to the atmosphere and the resulting global warming has become widespread. What needs to be discussed further are the contributions that various possible energy sources would make.</p>
        <p>In the same units, for a given amount of energy made available as heat (for heating houses, fueling automobiles, electricity generation or industrial processing) the different fuels make the following carbon dioxide contributions to the atmosphere:</p>
        <p>Taking natural gas (methane) as one unit, light oil and gasoline (average) will contribute 1.4 units, heavy fuel oil 1.5 units, coal (average) 1.8 units. (Preparation and use of synthetic fuels would average 2 or above.) Nuclear and hydropower contribute no carbon dioxide (although in construction and fuel preparation there may be processes that do).</p>
        <p>Of the two fuels that are available in abundance - natural gas and coal - gas is superior in delivering almost twice the energy for a given carbon dioxide burden, and in many applications where a higher burning efficiency can be used, the advantage is ever greater.</p>
        <p>The case on environmental grounds for using gas in preference to other fuels is clearly strong, stronger still if one includes the environmental advantages of absence of other noxious effluents, and little environmental damage in production and transportation. From a strategic and economic viewpoint, one might add that domestically available gas can greatly diminish the dependence on imported oil.</p>
        <p>In recent times, it has been widely recognized that natural gas exists in many locations and in much larger quantities than had been thought. For example, the Shell Briefing Service of November 1988 includes the following statements: ''as unconventional reserves one regards gas-containing oil sands, coal-seam methane, shale gas, ultradeep occurrences, gas hydrates (ices of water and methane) as well as gas of nonbiological origin . . . even the less optimistic estimates suggest that the unconventional quantities are substantially larger than the presently known reserves of conventional natural gas.''</p>
        <p>The opening up of new large reserves of fuels, even one as environmentally benign as natural gas, may be thought to risk further and pro-longed damage to the atmosphere. ''If we find more, we will use more'' - that would be the seemingly unavoidable conclusion. But in a world that has plenty of natural gas, there are new possibilities. Methane can readily be dissociated into very pure carbon and hydrogen, and one may then decide to use only the hydrogen for burning.</p>
        <p>Hydrogen is the ideal fuel, producing only water as its combustion product (and in quantities that are trivial in the water budget of the earth). So long as natural gas is in short supply, this possibility would not be economically feasible, but the opening up of new large reserves would change that. Furthermore, the pure carbon so obtained may itself become an industrially valuable resource, as the technology of carbon fibers for structural purposes advances, and carbon-fiber compounds replace steel for many applications.</p>
        <p>Combined hydrogen-burning, carbon-fiber-producing plants may be the solution of the future. But even if the carbon were not used, but only deposited, it is stable on geologic time scales, and most of it would not re-enter the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>It is also possible that the search for natural gas, especially at the deeper levels where it seems to be plentiful, will show that hydrogen itself can be obtained directly in some locations. The deep drilling efforts in the Soviet Union and in Sweden give strong suggestions that this is a possibility, and the Soviet Union is reported to be pursuing a program toward this end.</p>
        <p>It is clear that every effort should be made to find out what we have underground before any decision is made on industrial-environmental policy. THOMAS GOLD  Ithaca, N.Y., Jan. 9, 1989</p>
        <p>The writer is the former John L. Wetherill Professor of Astronomy at Cornell University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
