<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>JAPAN TO PROPOSE A PACKAGE OF AID WORTH $43 BILLION</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="265243"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BALANCE OF PAYMENTS AND TRADE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AFRICA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">UNO, SOUSUKE (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BAKER, JAMES A 3D (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEISMAN, STEVEN R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D61239F931A25754C0A96F948260" item-length="1259" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>JAPAN TO PROPOSE A PACKAGE OF AID WORTH $43 BILLION</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN R. WEISMAN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEISMAN, STEVEN R</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, July 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Japanese officials said tonight that Prime Minister Sousuke Uno would announce to leaders of the major industrialized democracies this week a $43 billion package of grants and loans to improve the global environment and to spur economic growth in countries crushed by poverty and indebtedness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Japanese officials said tonight that Prime Minister Sousuke Uno would announce to leaders of the major industrialized democracies this week a $43 billion package of grants and loans to improve the global environment and to spur economic growth in countries crushed by poverty and indebtedness.</p>
        <p>Japanese officials said tonight that Prime Minister Sousuke Uno would announce to leaders of the major industrialized democracies this week a $43 billion package of grants and loans to improve the global environment and to spur economic growth in countries crushed by poverty and indebtedness.</p>
        <p>The package includes important new support for the third world debt reduction plan of Nicholas F. Brady, the United States Secretary of the Treasury. Mr. Uno is calling specifically for a $5.5 billion increase above the $4.5 billion pledged last April for a ''parallel lending facility'' for poor nations, bringing it to $10 billion, including $2.05 billion that Japan recently pledged to help Mexico. Guaranteed Source of Funds</p>
        <p>The new loans are intended to help Mexico negotiate a reduction in debt to its commercial creditors by providing a guaranteed source of funds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Uno's $43 billion package, disclosed before the start of the Paris summit meeting of the industrialized democracies on Friday, recalled previous sizable Japanese initiatives announced before gatherings of chiefs of state or finance ministers.</p>
        <p>The Japanese, sensitive to foreign criticisms of their huge trade surpluses, like to refer to their foreign aid initiatives as ''recycling'' those surpluses. Indeed, the recent Japanese aid surpasses that of the United States or any other Western nation. Key Elements of Package</p>
        <p>In addition to the $10 billion to bolster the Brady plan, these are the other key elements of Mr. Uno's package:</p>
        <p>* A $35 billion expansion of the $30 billion program Japan announced in 1987 to ''recycle'' the country's trade surpluses to assist poor countries in spurring growth, controlling inflation and replacing lost private capital. Of the $35 billion disclosed today, $13.5 billion would be loans from the Export-Import Bank of Japan, $7 billion would be used for low-interest loans by the Government's Overseas Economic Cooperation Fund, and $14.5 billion would be aid from the Government's Capital Recycling Program.</p>
        <p>* A new commitment of $600 million in grants for more than a dozen countries in sub-Saharan Africa, on top of a previous $500 million commitment announced in 1987.</p>
        <p>* A new three-year, $2.25 billion program of grants and credits for environmental needs, including tree planting and helping poor people find alternatives to cutting down trees for fuel and fodder, which experts say is a major cost of deforestation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brady's plan envisions new loans, backed by guarantees from the World Bank or the International Monetary Fund, to permit Mexico and other debtor nations to restructure and lengthen their old loan payment schedules, thereby reducing each country's debt payments.</p>
        <p>Only a year ago, when Japan proposed that the I.M.F. and the World Bank play a greater role in helping third world countries reduce their debt burdens, Treasury Secretary Brady rejected the idea. He even asked Tokyo not to present it at the summit meeting then getting under way in Toronto. Course Reversed by Brady</p>
        <p>But the following March, Mr. Brady reversed course and announced acceptance of major parts of the Japanese proposals. What became known as the Brady plan received enthusiastic support from Tokyo, although some European industrial countries have had mixed views about involving international lending agencies in third world debt problems because of the risk involved.</p>
        <p>Officials said the new program was also significant because it reflected Mr. Uno's determination to assert Japan's leadership and to defuse what many agree is a widespread impression that his Government had been weakened by recent crises.</p>
        <p>Until last week, a few political experts here even questioned whether recent electoral setbacks might prevent Mr. Uno from going to Paris at all. But aides say the Prime Minister has been working hard to show the Western leaders that Japan's policies will endure, even if the Government may not. Budget Announcements Made</p>
        <p>In other steps aimed at demonstrating the continuity of its policies, Japan has made various budget announcements in the last week, including smaller increases in foreign aid programs and a rise in military spending for the next fiscal year.</p>
        <p>In the past, Japan's big aid initiatives followed pressure from the United States and European countries, but lately Japan, the world's largest creditor and aid donor, has shown increasing willingness to take the initiative.</p>
        <p>''One can be cynical about it,'' a Western diplomat said. ''But Japan has been using its resources generously and effectively. In spite of all of Uno's political problems, they're going to the summit in pretty good shape. No other leader in Paris can put up this kind of money.''</p>
        <p>The Japanese plan was the third multiyear, multibillion-dollar program from Tokyo in as many years. Last year, Prime Minister Noboru Takeshita announced a five-year $50 billion program of direct development assistance to poor countries, and the year before Japan announced a three-year $30 billion program of loans and grants.</p>
        <p>In other summit issues, Japan is expected to caution other leaders not to impose further economic sanctions on China or to denounce Beijing in a way that might ''isolate'' it from the West and push it into the arms of the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>To defuse highly contentious trade issues, Japan and the United States have reportedly agreed to set aside their disputes and to assure the other summit countries that they are trying to resolve their differences through negotiations.</p>
        <p>Officials emphasized tonight that Japan's new aid would not be tied to any commitments by recipient countries to import Japanese products or even to maintain economic relations with Japan. Accusations on Motives</p>
        <p>In recent years, some countries have accused Tokyo of cynically forcing some recipients to use Japanese contractors. Thus, Japan has become especially sensitive to the view that its aid program has been a program to help Japanese businesses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Uno is also expected to announce tax relief for Japanese commercial banks to give them an incentive to ease the debt burdens of poor countries. Japanese banks have a significant portion of the $1.3 trillion debt that is strangling third world countries, especially in Latin America, but the Finance Ministry said it did not have total figures.</p>
        <p>Other leaders are expected to welcome this step, too, and possibly to seek to emulate it.</p>
        <p>In another attempt to try to defuse foreign ciriticism, Japan will try to seize some initiative on the environmental issue that is expected to be a dominant theme of the summit meeting, officials said. Trying to Defuse Criticism</p>
        <p>Many environmental groups have charged that Japan, as one of the world's largest timber-importing countries, has contributed to the deforestation that has helped cause the global warming phenomenon. But Japan contends that the loss of forests has probably been caused mostly by poor peasants chopping down trees for their own needs, and not by the big timber importers.</p>
        <p>In any case, Japan is expected to call for greatly stepped-up research and technological assistance on the problem of environmental degradation and the depletion of the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Tokyo has recently announced that it would unilaterally cut down on consumption of chlorofluorocarbons, which scientists say are causing depletion of the ozone layer. But Japan, like the Bush Adminsitration, is also expected to oppose any call for strict international regulations to cut back on these or other emissions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
