<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="258422"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0D71239F937A25755C0A96F948260" item-length="877" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-17  Britain demanded that boat people from Vietnam who have found temporary asylum elsewhere in Southeast Asia be forcibly returned to Vietnam, beginning by October. Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-17  Britain demanded that boat people from Vietnam who have found temporary asylum elsewhere in Southeast Asia be forcibly returned to Vietnam, beginning by October. Page A1</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-17  Britain demanded that boat people from Vietnam who have found temporary asylum elsewhere in Southeast Asia be forcibly returned to Vietnam, beginning by October. Page A1</p>
        <p>Several Chinese officials resurfaced in public on national television, amid signs that the Communist purge might not be so sweeping as had been feared. Attacks on a dissident and the United States Embassy cooled. A1</p>
        <p>Trying to revive China's economy after the military crackdown shook the confidence of Chinese and foreigners alike is the critical task before the nation's leaders. A16</p>
        <p>U.S. suggests way out of dispute on dissidents A17</p>
        <p>Closer Moscow-Bonn economic ties were called for by President Gorbachev. He said the current level of trade between the two nations is ''ridiculously low.'' A1</p>
        <p>In a Soviet Asian republic, cause of the strife is elusive A12</p>
        <p>Soviets find organized crime gaining hold A14</p>
        <p>The Afghan President rejected calls for the removal of his Soviet-backed Government as a first step toward a political settlement of the war in Afghanistan. A1</p>
        <p>Argentina's President-elect agreed to take office on June 30, the day Presi-dent Raul Alfonsin has said he will resign, four months early. A3</p>
        <p>Quayle meets Salvador leader and urges respect for rights A3</p>
        <p>Ronald Reagan returned to Britain this week and was welcomed almost as visiting nobility. In a lecture to the English Speaking Union, he assailed the Chinese crackdown. A6</p>
        <p>An easing of U.S. trade restrictions against the Soviet Union was called for by American Jewish organizations in response to recent increases in Soviet Jewish emigration. A13</p>
        <p>Arms chiefs in Congress urge new U.S. position on missiles A10</p>
        <p>Poland bars eight key Communists from runoff vote A11</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A18-24, B6  President Bush vetoed a bill to raise the minimum wage to $4.55 an hour, setting the stage for a partisan political battle and test of wills with Democrats in Congress. A1</p>
        <p>The chief aide to Samuel Pierce, the former Housing Secretary, refused to answer questions from lawmakers about allegations of political abuse, citing her Fifth Amendment right against self-incrimination. A1</p>
        <p>The losses at savings associations totaled $3.4 billion in the first quarter of the year, the Federal Home Loan Bank Board reported. A1</p>
        <p>The race for House majority whip between William Gray and David Bonior is building tensions, with Democrats preparing to caucus today and reconstruct their leadership. B6</p>
        <p>Head of ethics panel says wife got no favoritism on business B6</p>
        <p>Toxic waste has contaminated lakes, rivers, estuaries and coastal areas by the hundreds, at levels that make them dangerous for aquatic life, the E.P.A. reported. A24</p>
        <p>Businesses concerned by Bush clean-air plan D1</p>
        <p>Reaction to a Supreme Court ruling on Monday that permits whites to challenge an affirmative action settlement was mixed at the place where the case orginated, the Birmingham Fire Department. A18</p>
        <p>Lawmakers plan legislation to reverse Court decisions A18</p>
        <p>University research is for sale to foreign and domestic companies willing to pay for advance word on results of federally financed studies, a lawmaker said at a hearing. A22</p>
        <p>Effort to verify 'cold' fusion experiment collapses A20</p>
        <p>Strong evidence of salmon pirating by foreign boats on the West Coast may have found the Coast Guard aboard a detained Taiwanese fishing vessel, officials say. A18</p>
        <p>Baptists re-elect conservative A19</p>
        <p>Time stock rises $5 above bid D1</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON TALK A23  The Democratic Party's Greens are the latest politcal fashion. They see issues like clean air and global warming as the key to future victories.  REGIONAL B1-5  An increase in cocaine deaths, in which the police subdue an apparently deranged man who later dies, is provoking outcries of police brutality and adding to racial tensions in New York and other cities. B1</p>
        <p>To make drug treatment available to all New Yorkers who seek it, the Coalition for the Homeless filed a lawsuit against New York State and New York City in State Supreme Court. B1</p>
        <p>Nomads in the foster-care system of New York City, the ''overnighters'' bounce around between short-term placements. Advocates call the practice another troubled aspect of the system. B1</p>
        <p>Agreement on smoking restrictions for many of New York State's public places has been reached in Albany, legislators said. B1</p>
        <p>New York State education officials are being lobbied to allow Whittle Communications to bring sponsored newscasts to classrooms. B3</p>
        <p>Changes in West Point's honor code were called for by a special panel appointed by the Army. If adopted, the recommendations would simplify the way judgments are made and expand the range of penalties. B3</p>
        <p>Man cleared in bond case and look-alike is charged B5</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
