<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pollution Shrouding National Parks</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="306099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKS AND OTHER RECREATION AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NATIONAL PARKS, MONUMENTS AND SEASHORES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SEQUOIA NATIONAL PARK (CALIF)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KINGS CANYON NATIONAL PARK (CALIF)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ACADIA NATIONAL PARK (MAINE)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROBBINS, JIM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/National Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maine/Acadia National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DE113FF930A35751C1A96F948260" item-length="2139" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pollution Shrouding National Parks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM ROBBINS; JIM ROBBINS contributes to The Times from Helena, Mont.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROBBINS, JIM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: SOME of America's most cherished scenic vistas are gradually disappearing behind a curtain of air pollution. A growing number of the country's national parks, from Sequoia and Kings Canyon in California to Acadia in Maine, are at times so afflicted with air pollution that views are often obscured and health is sometimes threatened.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: SOME of America's most cherished scenic vistas are gradually disappearing behind a curtain of air pollution. A growing number of the country's national parks, from Sequoia and Kings Canyon in California to Acadia in Maine, are at times so afflicted with air pollution that views are often obscured and health is sometimes threatened.</p>
        <p>SOME of America's most cherished scenic vistas are gradually disappearing behind a curtain of air pollution. A growing number of the country's national parks, from Sequoia and Kings Canyon in California to Acadia in Maine, are at times so afflicted with air pollution that views are often obscured and health is sometimes threatened.</p>
        <p>In addition, the biological diversity that the national parks shelter is at risk. Scientists have begun to see ill effects on plants within the parks, which serve as vital grounds for species that are vanishing elsewhere. The damage is primarily from ozone and acid rain. ''Every place we've monitored we've seen degradation of visibility from man-made sources,'' said Christine L. Shaver, chief of the Policy, Planning and Permit Review Branch of the National Park Service's Air Quality Division in Denver. ''No place is immune.''</p>
        <p>The Park Service says that more than 90 percent of the time, scenic vistas in all of the parks are affected by man-made pollution. The conclusion, based on nationwide monitoring stations within the parks and data collected over eight years, is contained in a comprehensive report on air quality originally issued in July 1988, titled ''Air Quality in the National Parks.''</p>
        <p>Because pollution usually comes from several sources rather than one or two, and because of legal obstacles that industry raises before refitting its plants, effective enforcement by the Environmental Protection Agency has been hamstrung, environmentalists and the park service say. Responsibility for overseeing air quality in the parks rests with the E.P.A.; the Park Service has no jurisdiction over pollution originating from outside of park boundaries.</p>
        <p>Acadia National Park in Maine, and Sequoia and Kings Canyon National Parks in the mountains of east-central California provide good examples of the range of pollution sources that make it difficult for the E.P.A. to enforce standards. At Acadia, multiple sources of pollution - chiefly ozone - is the problem. Pollution drifts from Boston, New York and other cities to the south and is perhaps the most common air pollutant, according to the park service. The gas, formed when nitrogen (chiefly from automobile exhaust) is chemically changed in the atmosphere, stings the eyes and mouths of healthy people and worsens the health problems of children, the elderly and those with serious health problems. White pines have also been damaged by ozone. (While ozone in the upper atmosphere, whose depletion is of concern because of global warming, is necessary to filter out harmful ultraviolet rays from the sun, it is poisonous at ground level.) At Sequoia and Kings Canyon, the sources of pollution include oil refineries and plumes of dust from agriculture and coal-fired power stations. Tiny airborne particles spewed out by automobiles, farming, trucking, oil refining and other development, as well as the 2.5 million people who live in California's booming San Joaquin Valley, which is due west of the parks, creates what officials call regional haze. The air shed over the valley is the country's dirtiest after Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>''The San Joaquin is like a big bathtub and we form the east wall of the bathtub,'' said Tom Nichols, an environmental specialist with Sequoia National Park. ''Every day the haze fills up the valley and the canyons and we look into the gray, murky soup.''</p>
        <p>Haze virtually smothers the park most of the time, so that only a dim, indigo silhouette of mountains that are very close to the viewer is visible. Taking scenic photographs is almost impossible. On the rare clear day in Sequoia, a visitor can stand on Moro Rock, a popular viewing spot, and see 100 miles away and 11 mountain ranges, including California's coastal mountains. An air pollution specialist at Sequoia estimates there are about 8 or 10 days a year in which the sky is clear; the visibility is usually less than 10 miles, with 2 of 11 ranges barely visible. Ozone also poses a serious problem here.</p>
        <p>Regional haze is worsening throughout the park system and, indeed, throughout the country. Since 1948 observers at airports in the eastern United States have measured visibility, and in the past 40 years the average distance that people can see has dropped from a range of 18 to 30 miles to exactly half that. At the Great Smoky Mountains National Park in Tennessee the average summertime visibility is just over seven miles; the viewing distance without smog is estimated to be 35 to 40 miles.</p>
        <p>''At one time you could see the Capitol Building and the Washington Monument from the Blue Ridge Mountains,'' said Mark Scruggs, a chief of the research branch with the Park Service Air Quality Bureau. ''No one has seen them in a long time.'' The natural haze from rotting vegetation that gave the Blue Ridge Mountains their name has been so polluted by man-made sources that the haze is turning white.</p>
        <p>But it is the shrouding of the West crystalline skies that has drawn the most attention. Haze from Los Angeles, as well as from coal-fired power plants throughout the Southwest, settles into the Grand Canyon, especially in winter. The lingering haze washes out the famous vista of striking reds, purple, browns and grays, and obscures the canyon's varied textures. On average, visitors cannot see the other side of the roughly 10-mile-wide canyon one day out of 10.</p>
        <p>The fight to clean the air in the Grand Canyon has gone on for years. In 1982 the Environmental Defense Fund, a lobbying organization that has been active in taking on industrial polluters, sued the E.P.A. to force the agency to uphold a portion of the 1977 Clean Air Act that mandates enforcement of visibility standards in the national parks. The E.P.A. director, Anne Gorsuch Burford, stayed the program. The defense fund sued in 1982 to gain enforcement of the standards. In 1984 the defense fund won in Federal District Court and, as part of the court order, the E.P.A. undertook a study, which is continuing, of air pollution at the canyon. In August the E.P.A. issued a report stating that a primary cause of pollution was the Navajo Generating Station at Page, Ariz., a mammoth coal-fired power plant 80 miles from the center of the Grand Canyon. The plant is owned by a consortium that includes the City of Los Angeles and the Federal Bureau of Reclamation.</p>
        <p>THE utility industry contradicts the findings, arguing that Navajo is responsible for only a small percentage of the pollution at the Grand Canyon. However, the assistant chief of the National Park Service Air Quality Division, Molly Ross, says the industry argument looks at the Navajo pollution as a percentage of all gases that make up the atmosphere. The Park Service, however, is looking at it as a percentage of man-made pollutants.</p>
        <p>''They're using a misleading definition of haze,'' she said. ''We're very confident of this data. This is 10 years of study with state of the art technology.''</p>
        <p>By February the Environmental Protection Agency is scheduled to determine by how much the plant must reduce its emissions. If Navajo's owners contest the findings, as appears likely, the ensuing court case could drag on for years. Sorting out responsibility for pollution at other parks, where sources are multiple, could take far longer. In the meantime new plants are being built, adding to further pollution sources. Ten coal-fired plants are planned for northeast Nevada, and many others are on the drawing board. Moreover, the present coal-fired plants are operating only at about 60 percent of capacity, according to Bob Yuhnke, senior attorney with the Environmental Defense Fund in Boulder, Colo.</p>
        <p>To compound the situation, the E.P.A. has not written regulations to deal with regional haze, even though the agency is ordered to do so under provisions of the 1977 Clean Air Act. Some legislators are hoping to include a new regional haze section to the Clean Air Act amendments now before Congress. Congress recessed late last month without resolving the issue; it will resume deliberation in January. Senator George J. Mitchell, Democrat of Maine, the Senate Majority leader, said it would be a priority when the Congress returned.</p>
        <p>''Are things going to get worse before they get better?'' asked Dave Stonefield, Chief of the Visibility Program for the E.P.A. in Durham, N.C. ''That's a fair statement.''</p>
        <p>However poor the air quality has become in many parks, to inhabitants of polluted American cities the air still seems good by comparison. People simply don't notice the deteriorating air quality, in part because they are coming from more polluted places. ''We get a lot of people from L.A.,'' said Dawn Vernon, a Park Service interpreter who has set up a program at Sequoia to explain park air pollution to visitors. ''They get here and think the air is wonderful. When we tell them it's not they're shocked.</p>
        <p>''It's an aerial sewer,'' she said. ''If it was water you wouldn't swim in it and you certainly wouldn't drink it.''</p>
        <p>To record how dramatically visibility can be impaired, the Park Service has begun taking photos over long periods of time with automatic cameras in many parks with air-pollution problems, such as Sequoia and Grand Canyon. Comparisons are often striking. One recent photo in this series taken of the Grand Canyon during serious air pollution and intended for research shows only several rock formations in the foreground; the far rim is obscured by haze and almost no colors are apparent.</p>
        <p>Air quality in much of the West is expected to worsen. The E.P.A. estimates that sulfur and nitrogen oxides from coal-fired power plants may double by the year 2010. ''There are projected increases in sulfur dioxide of less than 10 percent in California, 40 to 50 percent in the Rocky Mountains and 70 percent in Texas,'' said Ms. Shaver of the Park Service. Based on these figures, Ms. Shaver said, air quality at some parks will deteriorate. Discussing another national park, she said, ''At a place like Big Bend in Texas, an average day will become a good day and a bad day will become the average.''</p>
        <p>Sulfur dioxide emissions also damage the parks in the form of acid rain. Both ozone and acid precipitation show up in high levels in Sequoia and Kings Canyon. Ozone has contributed to the death of Jeffery pine trees in Sequoia and caused visible damage to ponderosa pine; how it will affect the giant sequoias is not yet known. Studies by the Park Service in which branches of the sequoia trees are encased in plastic and fumigated with high levels of ozone are just getting underway, but preliminary results indicate that ozone does adversely affects the root and shoot growth of sequoia seedlings. In some parks, including the Santa Monica Recreation Area and Indiana Dunes National Monument, high levels of ozone have wiped out many species of lichen.</p>
        <p>Ozone damage to plants and trees has shown up in 50 national park units, including Acadia, Joshua Tree National Monument and the Santa Monica National Recreation Area in California, the Great Smoky Mountains and Shenandoah National Parks.</p>
        <p>THE effects on human health of ozone and respirable particles that pollute the air in the parks are the same as they would be elsewhere. However, people who visit the parks often exert themselves by running or hiking, which can exacerbate health problems, though the park service keeps no records of such problems. In 1988 in Acadia officials were forced to warn visitors not to exert themselves when ozone levels shot up well above the Federal air quality standard, and stayed that way for several days. ''If those levels had been in a factory it would have violated Occupational Safety and Health Administration standards and been illegal,'' said Elizabeth Fayad, Park Threats Coordinator for the National Parks and Conservation Association, a lobbying organization for the parks.</p>
        <p>As air quality in the parks worsens, the Air Quality Division of the Park Service is working out a policy to warn visitors of health threats in parks from air pollution, although there is no timetable for implementation. One aspect of the pollution issue that remains to be addressed is whether the Park Service will continue allowing natural fires in parks to burn, which worsens air quality. The policy, in effect since the 1970's, was suspended this year because of the fires that devoured Yellowstone in the summer of 1988.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists hope revisions to the Clean Air Act now under consideration in Congress will address some of these problems. ''Ninety percent of the pollution in the parks is from regional haze and that's what the E.P.A. has abandoned,'' said Mr. Yuhnke of the Environmental Defense Fund.</p>
        <p>''Unless the Clean Air Act requires the E.P.A. to do something, nothing will happen.'' The result of inaction, he said, is ''a graying of the West.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
