<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Outdoors; Easing Limits on Striped Bass</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="291173"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISHING, COMMERCIAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISHING, SPORT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASS (FISH)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MARINE FISHERIES COMMISSION, ATLANTIC STATES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRYANT, NELSON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2D7173CF936A25753C1A96F948260" item-length="941" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Outdoors; Easing Limits on Striped Bass</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nelson Bryant</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRYANT, NELSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission has voted to relax restrictions on recreational and commercial fishing for striped bass next year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission has voted to relax restrictions on recreational and commercial fishing for striped bass next year.</p>
        <p>The Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission has voted to relax restrictions on recreational and commercial fishing for striped bass next year.</p>
        <p>Phil Coates, chairman of the commission's striped bass board, calls it the start of a conservative transition period during which stocks of the fish, which became seriously depleted about a decade ago, will be carefully monitored.</p>
        <p>In the season now ending, sport fishermen are limited to one bass a day, 36 or more inches long. Next year, the daily bag limit will remain at one fish, but the minimum length will be 28 inches. An exception to this will exist in those states that produce significant numbers of stripers, where the length limit, in inland waters, will be 18 inches.</p>
        <p>Currently, the states that so qualify are Maryland, New York, Virginia and North Carolina. Delaware would presumably be included as a producer state when restoration of spawning stocks of Delaware Bay stripers has been accomplished, as well as the portion of New Jersey that borders on Delaware Bay.</p>
        <p>Those states that so desire will also be permitted to have commercial fisheries for the species that would take no more than 20 percent of the stripers harvested in an average year during 1972-1979.</p>
        <p>The proposal is an amendment to the existing striped bass management plan. The amendment approach - rather than a new plan - was chosen in order to insure that the new regulations would be subject to the controls of the Atlantic Striped Bass Conservation Act. Passed by Congress in 1984, the Act empowered the Federal Government to close fishing for the species in states that do not comply with the commission's desires.</p>
        <p>Over the years, the Chesapeake Bay has produced perhaps 90 percent of the striped bass that migrate up and down the coast. The Hudson's stripers, which do not wander as far afield, account for most of the remainder of the migratory stocks. The Hudson's bass have been thriving in recent years.</p>
        <p>Faced with the decline of the Chesapeake's striped bass, the commission put forth a management plan for the species in 1981. It involved severe curtailment of commercial and recreational fishing. Some states balked at this, but fell into line after the passage of the Striped Bass Conservation Act. Another factor in creating acceptance of the plan was Maryland's decision - made four years ago - to shut down all fishing, both sport and commercial, for the species.</p>
        <p>The causes of the striper's decline in the Chesapeake were never fully understood, but pollution, including acid rain, and over-fishing by both sport and commercial interests were factors. Stripers are an anadromous species, spawning in rivers with the young remaining in the stream or its estuary for varying periods of time before venturing to sea. During the years of the striper's decline, enough females for adequate production often showed up in the rivers entering Chesapeake Bay, but few of their progeny survived.</p>
        <p>To measure spawning success, Maryland fisheries biologists have, for more than 30 years, been sampling, with seines, the relative abundance of yearling stripers in that state's portion of the Chesapeake system, establishing what is called a young-of-the-year index.</p>
        <p>The average index over the entire period is about 8. The highest index was 30 in 1970. In this decade, and until this year, it went below 5 except for 1982, when it was 8.4. (The current 36-inch limit - which had been creeping upward year after year - had been aimed at allowing the females of the 1982 year class to spawn at least once.) This year, the Maryland index is 25.2. Even before all the results were in, Maryland authorities announced jubilantly that they were making plans for an extremely limited sport and commercial fishery for stripers next year. At the time of the announcement - with September seine samplings still to be made - it was known that the index would be at least 17. (The commission's management plan had called for no relaxation of harvesting limitations until -over a three-year period - an average index figure of 8 was reached.) Some of the striper's champions, including Joe Boone, a Maryland fisheries biologist, have questioned the validity of this year's index figure. Boone, who, until his retirement in 1986 ran Maryland's striper index survey for 27 years, believes that the 1989 index was skewed by two abnormally successful seine hauls in the Choptank River. Boone believes that 1989 was a good striper production year, but not as good as some would have it, and he is fearful that relaxation of existing regulations will take too high a toll of the spawning fish that produced the 1989 yearling bass.</p>
        <p>The doubts of Boone and others were aired at a recent meeting by the commission, says Coates, who adds that the Maryland scientists present assured all hands that their figures were sound.</p>
        <p>The amended plan leaves room for the producer states to further relax their striper regulations if they can demonstrate that only a few of the wide-ranging Chesapeake fish would be affected.</p>
        <p>New York, for example, is engaged in a sophisticated study to determine if the stripers caught in its coastal waters are mainly of Hudson origin. If this can be proved, the commission might allow more intensive harvesting of those stocks. There's a fly in the ointment, however. Stripers of Hudson origin are contaminated by PCB's. Because of this, the state closed commercial fishing for them more than 10 years ago. In stripers caught in the state's waters, PCB levels - sometimes above the concentrations deemed safe for human consumption, sometimes not - vary with catch location and size of the fish.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
