<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>California Alliance Proposes Vote On Broad Environmental Measure</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="289954"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFERENDUMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAZARDOUS AND TOXIC SUBSTANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PESTICIDES AND PESTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">REINHOLD, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFD7173DF932A25753C1A96F948260" item-length="1453" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>California Alliance Proposes Vote On Broad Environmental Measure</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT REINHOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REINHOLD, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Oct. 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In a move that has as much to do with California politics as the environment, an alliance of politicians and environmentalists today offered a ballot measure that they called the broadest effort ever mounted to protect air, food and water against chemical contamination.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In a move that has as much to do with California politics as the environment, an alliance of politicians and environmentalists today offered a ballot measure that they called the broadest effort ever mounted to protect air, food and water against chemical contamination.</p>
        <p>In a move that has as much to do with California politics as the environment, an alliance of politicians and environmentalists today offered a ballot measure that they called the broadest effort ever mounted to protect air, food and water against chemical contamination.</p>
        <p>If passed, the measure would phase out all agricultural pesticides that cause cancer or birth defects, ban new oil drilling off the coast and set up a $500 million state cleanup fund for oil spills, cut by 40 percent carbon dioxide emissions believed to contribute to global warming, prohibit the clearing of ancient redwood stands and create an elected environmental advocate with the power to sue to enforce the law. Given Strong Chance for Passage</p>
        <p>The measure would have profound consequences well beyond the state's borders for the chemical and agricultural industries and is expected to draw bitter opposition from them.</p>
        <p>It has also received a cool reception from some environmentalists who say it tries to do too much and may not withstand legal challenge. But the measure is given a strong chance for passage amid a rising tide of public concern about the environment.</p>
        <p>Drafters of the proposal were unable to say today what the measures would ultimately cost.</p>
        <p>The complex measure is the latest move by states and localities to take the lead in environmental legislation and proceed with more dispatch than the Federal Government. Tom Hayden, a Democratic State Assemblyman who was chairman of the panel that drafted the initiative, called it ''the most significant proposal for protecting the environment ever placed before the voters in this country.''</p>
        <p>Drafters hope to put the proposal on the ballot next year, on the same date that Californians will vote for governor. The measure is already emerging as a major factor in the gubernatorial race. Candidates in the state have increasingly taken to linking their names to popular ballot measures to bring out sympathetic voters. But critics charge that the candidates are using the measures to skirt strict limits on campaign contributions, since there are no limits on contributions to ballot drives.</p>
        <p>Even before the measure was written, Attorney General John Van de Kamp, a Democratic candidate for governor, endorsed it. His action put off balance two potential opponents, Dianne Feinstein, a Democrat who is a former Mayor of San Francisco, and Senator Pete Wilson, a Republican. Both have been asked to endorse the initiative and are considering it. But Senator Wilson, who has made elaborate gestures toward the environmental vote, wrote the drafters today that he would join only if certain ''defects'' in the measure, like transferring environmental enforcement authority from the governor to an environmental advocate, were corrected. 'Greater Concern' on Pollution</p>
        <p>Environmentalists say they detect a rising tide of opinion against pollution in California and elsewhere that made the time ripe for today's move. ''There is greater concern than ever before,'' said Al Meyerhoff of the Natural Resources Defense Council, a nonprofit environmental advocacy group. ''This measure recognizes these issues cannot be dealt with piecemeal. California is going to set the stage for the battle over the environment.''</p>
        <p>A ballot measure is needed, environmentalists say, because the Legislature has failed to act. ''A lot of these proposals have been discussed ad nauseum in the Legislature,'' said Lucy Blake, executive director of the 25,000-member League of Conservation Voters, a political action committee. ''As the environmental challenge becomes more staggering, we must circumvent many competing forces in the Legislature and get a clear expression from the voters.''</p>
        <p>The measure was drawn up by representatives of the Sierra Club, the League of Conservation Voters, the Natural Resources Defense Council, the National Toxics Campaign, Citizens for a Better Environment, Lieut. Gov. Leo McCarthy and Attorney General Van de Kamp. Three Major Concerns</p>
        <p>The measure is aimed mainly at three concerns: the food supply, global warming and protection of coastal waters. The main elements are these:</p>
        <p>* All pesticides and herbicides known to cause cancer or reproductive harm would have to be phased out by 1996. This would affect 24 chemicals in use in California, including Alachlor, Captan, 1,3-Dichloropropene and Aldicarb. If no alternatives could be found and ''severe economic hardship'' to the state's agriculture industry would result, a three-year extension could be obtained.</p>
        <p>* The allowable levels of pesticide residues on foods would be reduced to levels safe for children. Produce imported from other states and countries would have to meet the same standard.</p>
        <p>* Exposure of farm workers to dangerous pesticides would be reduced by lengthening quarantine periods before workers are allowed into a treated field. The workers would also be allowed access to pesticide use records.</p>
        <p>* The state would develop a plan to reduce emissions of any gases that contribute to global warming when they rise into the stratosphere. The focus is on carbon dioxide, a major product of combustion, which would have to be reduced by 40 percent by the year 2010, less an adjustment for population growth. The measure does not specify how that would be done.</p>
        <p>* The use or manufacture of all chlorofluorocarbons must be phased out by 1997, except for medical uses. CFC's are used in hundreds of ways in making electronic products and have been found to destroy the protective layer of ozone in the upper atmosphere.</p>
        <p>* A $200 million state fund would be established to purchase stands of ancient redwood trees if threatened by logging. A one-year moratorium on the clearing of such strands would be imposed on the day of the vote, Nov. 7, 1990. Trees consume carbon dioxide and are thought to be needed to counter global warming.</p>
        <p>* New offshore oil drilling would be permitted within the three-mile state limit only in a national emergency and the state would draw up a oil spill prevention plan. Oil producers would be assessed a fee of 25 cents a barrel to establish a $500 million oil spill prevention and cleanup fund.</p>
        <p>The measure does not address other concerns like smog, drinking water quality and solid waste disposal. The drafters said these matters were already being addressed by other legislation.</p>
        <p>Unlike in New York, voters in California can make law directly through the voter initiative under the State Constitution. And in the last 12 years Californians have used the ballot to try to roll back insurance rates, cut property taxes, limit state and local government spending and put new curbs on campaign contributions. An initiative becomes law if it gets more than half the votes cast. Not Taking Sides</p>
        <p>The environmentalists said today that in putting aside past differences and working with the Attorney General they were not taking the Democrat's side in the gubernatorial race. ''We have not any evaluation on the race yet,'' said Ms. Blake of the League of Conservation Voters.</p>
        <p>But Otto Bos, Senator Wilson's campaign manager, said the Republican was invited to join the initiative process only at the last minute, and he suggested that Mr. Van de Kamp was using it to get around state campaign contribution limits. Backers of the proposal believe Mr. Wilson may remain neutral on it next year.</p>
        <p>At a news conference this morning, Mr. Van de Kamp vigorously disputed suggestions that he was using the measure to get around contribution limits. ''Utter nonsense,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Conspicuously absent from the measure is the Environmental Defense Fund, the major backer of a measure three years ago that requires warnings on products that cause cancer or birth defects. David Roe, a lawyer with the group in Oakland said he supported the initiative ''in principle'' but had reservations about the way the measure was drawn. It is almost certain to be challenged on the ground that it violates a California constitutional provision that ballot measures address only a single topic.</p>
        <p>Clark Biggs, a spokesman for the California Farm Bureau Federation, representing the state's agricultural industry, said his organization had not seen the full proposal and was unable to comment in detail. ''We certainly aren't opposed to pesticide regulation if it's reasonable and protects agriculture and farm workers,'' he said. Mr. Meyerhoff said substitutes were available for most of the affected pesticides.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hayden said the group would start next month to gather the 500,000 signatures needed to qualify the measure for the ballot, adding that $700,000 had already been raised for gathering the signatures and promoting the measure.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
