<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Communist Economics Fell Short</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="309913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE, EAST</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D9103CF934A25751C1A96F948260" item-length="1164" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Communist Economics Fell Short</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER PASSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IT'S not over 'til it's over, Yogi admonished. But with Muscovites salivating over the arrival of McDonald's and Hungary celebrating the embrace of General Electric, it is hard to deny that the long ideological war between capitalism and socialism has ended in a decisive win for the home team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IT'S not over 'til it's over, Yogi admonished. But with Muscovites salivating over the arrival of McDonald's and Hungary celebrating the embrace of General Electric, it is hard to deny that the long ideological war between capitalism and socialism has ended in a decisive win for the home team.</p>
        <p>IT'S not over 'til it's over, Yogi admonished. But with Muscovites salivating over the arrival of McDonald's and Hungary celebrating the embrace of General Electric, it is hard to deny that the long ideological war between capitalism and socialism has ended in a decisive win for the home team.</p>
        <p>Economists across the political spectrum agree that central planning has proved a bust in recent decades. Most would also agree that decentralized economic decision-making offers Communist countries the best hope for catching up with the affluent West. But the dramatic collapse of the economic system that allowed both the Soviet Union and China to transform bitterly poor rural societies into world powers in a single lifetime has yet to be explained to the satisfaction of all.</p>
        <p>The issue is more than academic. The Soviet leadership, for example, is agonizing over how much it is prepared to risk to get the moribund economy moving again. Last week, to the disgust of radicals who favor a clean break with the past, Prime Minister Nikolai Ryzhkov backed away from earlier proposals to liberalize restrictions on private property and abolish subsidies and price controls on consumer goods.</p>
        <p>Even in Eastern Europe, where central planning was imposed on reluctant peoples by the Russian invader, non-Communist leaders still talk of finding a third way - an economic system that combines the efficiency of free markets with the paternalist ethic of socialism. Capitalism's weaknesses, after all, were what inspired socialist theorists in the 19th century and generated support for the great experiments in central planning in the 20th.</p>
        <p>When capitalism works just right it is a miraculous engine of productivity, yielding a growth dividend that can be used to ease poverty and increase social mobility. But the system does not always work just right. Free-market prices, which should automatically equate costs to value, are distorted by monopoly power, as corporations and unions conspire to increase their shares of the economic pie. Dickensian Extremes</p>
        <p>Much worse, the invisible hand that coordinates the workings of thousands of different markets is prone to breakdown. Sometimes the prices of goods fail to go down in response to falling demand, forcing factories to close and leaving millions out of work. Sometimes, the demand for goods and services exceeds the capacity to produce them, leading to spiraling increases in prices. And as the experiences of such capitalist countries as Brazil and Chile suggest, even well-functioning markets can lead to Dickensian extremes in income.</p>
        <p>Under the purest versions of centralized planning, administrators decide what goods will be produced and what economic resources will be used to make them. Unemployment is, in effect, abolished by decree. And inflation is suppressed, with excess demand showing up as shortages rather than as rising prices.</p>
        <p>But in practice, the performance of planned economies is mixed. Their inherent strength, the ability to mobilize resources for a few national goals, is familiar to anyone who remembers the way the American economy rallied to support the Allied armies in World War II. By organizing what amounts to a permanent war economy, Stalin was able to transform a backward land into a great military power with an impressively large industrial base. And by forcing Soviet citizens to invest a high percentage of income, planners could maintain very high growth rates through the 1960's. Drowning in Detail</p>
        <p>Soviet economists once thought they could use computer models to simulate the decentralized workings of markets, but that idea has proved far beyond the capacities of the speediest supercomputer. And as the Soviet economy grew more complex, the lack of accurate signals of cost and value began to cut more deeply.</p>
        <p>Production goals set in tons, for example, have led Soviet pipe manufacturers to use far more steel than necessary. Consumer prices held far below cost have led to colossal waste: it often pays farmers to sell their grain to the state, and then buy back the subsidized bread made from the grain, to use as animal feed.</p>
        <p>Correcting such obvious misincentives is not easy. Planners, with thousands of interdependent production sectors to coordinate, drown in detail. Even the Soviet Congress, convened last week to debate momentous issues of policy, was reduced to quarreling over the poor quality of washing machines and the scarcity of school desks. Scale and complexity seem to magnify another weakness of planned economies - the lack of financial incentives for personal initiative. In Stalin's day it might have been sufficient to set quotas for numbers of tractors assembled or tons of coal dug, rewarding overachievers with New Years' vodka and punishing shirkers with holidays in the gulag.</p>
        <p>But in a modern economy whose long-term prospects critically depend on the creation and rapid diffusion of technology, such crude incentives cannot work. While Soviet science is often first rate, engineers have little incentive to address the needs of consumer goods makers. And when they do, factory managers have little incentive to bet on unproven techniques.</p>
        <p>Moreover, as Soviet growth lost momentum it became obvious that the planners had been unable to deliver on promises of economic justice or macroeconomic stability. Housing and health care are dirt cheap. But outside a few cities, their quality is little better than in the third world. Corruption, a special temptation where everything from central heating to penicillin is rationed by bureaucrats rather than by price, has bred cynicism and disrespect for law. And the Soviet cure for inflation - shortages of everything - has become as painful as the disease.</p>
        <p>To Mr. Gorbachev's radical critics at home, the lesson is simple. No gradual transition to some hybrid of fixed and free markets can cure what ails the Soviet economy. They may be right. But a little humility, at least on the part of Western economists, is in order. For the current successes of capitalism are no guarantee of future ones. And not every augury is positive.</p>
        <p>One fundamental weakness of the free market system is so obvious it is often ignored: It is usually cheaper to buy government protection against rivals than to match the price or quality of the competition. And as the stakes get higher, interest groups get better at beating the system.</p>
        <p>And as economic interactions grow more complicated and publicly used resources grow more scarce, the potential for damage increases. It is hard to be optimistic, for example, that the decentralized market economies will make rational choices about controlling the greenhouse gases that are warming the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Could the worm turn? Could free market economies decline in the face of some potent hybrid system - say, the highly adaptable corporatism of South Korea or Japan? In these heady days of perestroika, such a fate seems a long way off. Perhaps it is. Perhaps.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
