<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Of Course We Worry About What's in Our Food</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="239315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD CONTAMINATION AND POISONING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PROTECTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD ADDITIVES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHESSON, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6D61330F932A25757C0A96F948260" item-length="571" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Of Course We Worry About What's in Our Food</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>It is William Safire's contention (''Madness of Crowds,'' column, March 23) that the concern the American people have expressed over carcinogenic apples and tainted grapes is being manipulated into a panic-stricken frenzy by the organic food ''lobby.'' He asserts that the ''apple scare'' and ''similarly dramatic scenarios of impending environmental doom'' are fabrications of the ''clean-living industry.'' He concludes with a bizarre parallel linking a rejection of unhealthy food with lack of national will and courage in the event of some future ''nuclear blackmail.''</p>
        <p>Does Mr. Safire truly believe that global environmental degeneration is some fantasy manufactured by the ''Greens,'' apparently his term for anyone awake enough to care about what went into or was processed out of the food he or she is eating? One need only skim your pages casually to gain insight into the terrible problems ahead - rapid extinction of species and a corresponding erosion of ecosystems, ozone depletion of the atmosphere, deforestation, acid rain, global warming, famine, oceanic and marine pollution, and human overpopulation. The planet is on the verge of losing the ability to regenerate itself. Perhaps Mr. Safire believes this is an invention of the National Press Club?</p>
        <p>Mr. Safire maintains that America's '' 'Greens' will continue to undermine the trust laymen have had in the scientists at the F.D.A.'' What trust? The Food and Drug Administration clearly knew for years that alar was a carcinogen, and did nothing to ban it immediately, citing legal constraints for its inability. Mr. Safire states that ''In the apple scare, minimal risks were inflated into imminent threats with no thought of unintended consequences.'' Minimal to whom?  Mr. Safire severely underestimates the psychological trauma the news of possibly poisoned apples caused in the American consciousness. It is not important what percentage of the fruit is suspect. It is irrelevant for him to quote dreary statistics meant to allay our fears regarding the danger. What is beginning to pierce all our hearts is the realization that we are slowly poisoning ourselves and that this cannot be attributed to the organic food ''lobby.''</p>
        <p>In the market where I shop there is organic produce available, and not surprisingly, people are choosing to buy it. These people do not look like the victims of panic psychology; they are just ordinary people taking responsibility for their own health. It is one area where we have some control in our lives.</p>
        <p>Mr. Safire wonders what will happen when some future ''dictator'' threatens us with an atomic weapon. He surmises that a populace that will stop eating apples ''overnight'' is not a public that will back its Government in resisting nuclear blackmail. It is unclear what Mr. Safire expects from us in such an event. Start eating the bad apples at once?</p>
        <p>It is curious that we no longer have to fear the Soviet Union in Mr. Safire's scenario, since it too has become bankrupt in the endless arms race. The fear is switched to another locale, but it is an old game, and a dangerous one. As a final irony to Mr. Safire's paranoid logic, the same day your front page reported that toxic chemicals poured into the air by American industry are a growing threat to public health. Mr. Safire tells us to enjoy our apple pie. We will - and our poison sky. JAMES CHESSON  New York, March 24, 1989</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
