<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tough Guys in Black and White</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="216443"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CABLE TELEVISION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ESPN (CABLE TV NETWORK)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL FOOTBALL LEAGUE (NFL)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ST ONGE, HENRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cable Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DA143AF931A15752C0A96F948260" item-length="697" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tough Guys in Black and White</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Sports Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Sports Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Sports Editor:</p>
        <p>Institutional racism is a term frequently used to characterize the variety of indecencies, insults and inequities practiced on members of minorities. All reasonable people agree that it exists, along with other evils like the greenhouse effect, acid rain, the trade deficit and the national debt. And like the other evils, we have become so accustomed to its existence that we often pay scant attention to its particular manifestations. Every so often, however, it becomes too explicit to be ignored.</p>
        <p>During the extended football mania of the holiday season, ESPN broadcast a program on the National Football League's ''tough guys,'' an hourlong account of six of the toughest players in the history of the National Football League. The film was produced by NFL Films complete with the reverential tone it ordinarily employs (the sacred incantations one would expect during a funeral service for a world leader or the canonization of a saint).</p>
        <p>The tough guys profiled were Howie Long of the Raiders, Mike Curtis of the old Colts, Pat Fischer of the less old Cardinals, Larry Csonka in his Dolphin days, Danny White of the Cowboys, and, of course, Dick Butkus, who seems by consensus to be the toughest, meanest, most violent, barbaric and animal-like to ever wear a helmet.</p>
        <p>Now, no reasonable person would question the toughness of these players. They all share the delight in causing pain common to a practitioner of the amusements of the Marquis de Sade. But the ability to cause or accept pain in the N.F.L. is not considered antisocial, criminal or aberrant. Indeed, it is prized and respected. And given the N.F.L. framework, Butkus and the others share the qualities associated with toughness in the tough world where they gained fame and honor. They also share the same skin color.</p>
        <p>One could infer, I suppose, that N.F.L. public-relations folk did not wish to tag blacks with the attributes of barbarism and brutality, that by selecting whites only as tough the N.F.L. meant to imply that blacks were mild, peaceable and Quaker-like in their football behavior.</p>
        <p>Perhaps NFL Films did not intend to slight black players. Perhaps it did not occur to the executives of ESPN that they were ignoring blacks. It likely never occurred to the narrators and announcers of the program.</p>
        <p>But it is precisely this lack of conscious intent to slight or ignore the black athletes that defines and characterizes ''institutional'' racism in sports. The N.F.L.-ESPN essay on toughness reflects the white world values, or more probably the wishes and unconscious self-delusion of the white world.</p>
        <p>In a word, the acceptance of white leadership or black subordinance, whichever you prefer, is institutionalized. It matters little which institution: the government, the military, the academy, the corporation, the church. Of course, one would not expect to find many black names in a list of six great generals, Presidents, Popes or Archbishops of Canterbury, even of giant conglomerates or corporations. These institutions have not yet found room at the top for the so-called people of color. Neither has room been found in the boardrooms, front offices or head-coaching ranks in the N.F.L. But on the playing field?</p>
        <p>Csonka was a marvelous football player, but did he knock over any more people than Jim Brown? Was Walter Payton effete to survive the pounding he received over the years and to endure the way he did? Is Lawrence Taylor incapable of ferocity on the field or did Joe Theismann, an announcer on the program, forget what happened to his career? Was Big Daddy Lipscomb a flower child? Was Mean Joe Greene's nickname ironic? Is Howie Long any tougher than his ex-teammate Jack Tatum or just whiter?</p>
        <p>Again, the argument is not that the six white players weren't tough. They are all formidable men. But there were and are plenty of black N.F.L. players who can match them. Every fan knows it and the athletes themselves know it. But the white men who run the N.F.L. myth machine seem psychologically unable to accept it. They have institutionalized their beliefs, or are themselves the captives of the institution.  HENRY ST. ONGE  New Paltz, N.Y.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
