<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hugo Is the Latest Episode of Weather In the Extreme</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="285595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="IDEAS &amp; TRENDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHANE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HURRICANES AND TROPICAL STORMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">HURRICANE HUGO</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DD1F38F937A1575AC0A96F948260" item-length="663" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hugo Is the Latest Episode of Weather In the Extreme</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: FROM the great drought and heat wave of 1988 to the monster hurricane that smashed Charleston, S.C., on Thursday and Friday, the last 16 months have brought a startling sequence of out-of-the-ordinary weather to the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: FROM the great drought and heat wave of 1988 to the monster hurricane that smashed Charleston, S.C., on Thursday and Friday, the last 16 months have brought a startling sequence of out-of-the-ordinary weather to the United States.</p>
        <p>FROM the great drought and heat wave of 1988 to the monster hurricane that smashed Charleston, S.C., on Thursday and Friday, the last 16 months have brought a startling sequence of out-of-the-ordinary weather to the United States.</p>
        <p>Last year's disastrous three-month dry spell in the nation's midsection was followed by an unusually mild and snowless winter in the Northeast. Then, just as New Yorkers feared they might run short of water this summer, one of the rainiest summer seasons in modern history burst over the Northeast starting in May. Assuming normal rainfall for the rest of the year, 1989 will be one of the three or four wettest years in New York City since measurements of precipitation began in Central Park in 1869.</p>
        <p>And now Hurricane Hugo. Beginning as one of the worst tropical cyclones in years, it devastated the Caribbean islands of Guadeloupe, Montserrat, St. Croix, St. Thomas and Puerto Rico early in the week. That passage weakened it some, and forecasters thought that tropical storm Iris, following in Hugo's wake, would draw enough moisture and energy from the hurricane to keep it relatively weak.</p>
        <p>But in the end, Hugo destroyed Iris, the big hurricane's more powerful winds literally shearing the smaller storm in two, separating its thunderstorms from its center and causing it to fall apart. By the time Hugo slammed into the South Carolina coast, it had nearly regained the 140 mile-an-hour winds that made it so destructive in the islands. Hugo turned out to be the 10th most intense hurricane of the 137 that have made direct hits on the United States coastline since the turn of the century. As measured by the atmospheric pressure near its center, it ranks a hair behind Hurricane Carla, which hit the Texas Gulf Coast in 1961 and is remembered as one of the most fearsome of cyclones.</p>
        <p>Are such scenes likely to be played out more often in the future? Does the last 16 months' train of atmospheric happenings mean that the climate is changing for the worse, moving toward more frequent extremes?</p>
        <p>As unusual as they are, all of these events are well within the range of experience. The great drought of the 1930's was far worse than that of 1988. There have been years as wet or wetter than 1989 in the Northeast. And in this century, 13 hurricanes about as powerful as Hugo have hit the United States. Two others were in a class by themselves. A 1935 storm that killed more than 400 people in Florida and Hurricane Camille, whose 200 m.p.h. winds ravaged the Mississippi Gulf Coast and killed 256 people in 1969, were Category 5 cyclones, the most powerful.</p>
        <p>Hugo was a Category 4 when it struck Charleston. But only a handful of deaths resulted. Improvements in predictions brought about largely by satellites and computers, along with television and other means of getting the word out, seem to have relegated to history the days when a hurricane can kill thousands in the United States, as happened in Galveston in 1900.</p>
        <p>Some climate experts like to say that all weather is abnormal, that one abnormality simply gives way to another in a seamless web of interacting atmospheric events.</p>
        <p>But many scientists believe that humans are changing the game by pouring into the air increasing amounts of carbon dioxide, methane and chlorofluorocarbons. These gases combine with water vapor to trap heat in the earth's atmosphere - the greenhouse effect. Most climatologists believe that the effects of human-induced global warming cannot yet be distinguished from natural climatic variations. But they also think that some warming of the global climate is inevitable.</p>
        <p>And while no responsible climatologist will say that any weather event of the last 16 months was directly caused by global warming, some say that ultimately the greenhouse effect almost certainly will increase the odds that droughts and hurricanes will occur, and that they will be more intense.</p>
        <p>Humans, they say, are painting more warm spots on the climatic dice.</p>
        <p>IDEAS &amp; TRENDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
