<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Despite Uncertainty, a Family Makes Maple Syrup</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="231107"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAPLE SYRUP</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PESTICIDES AND PESTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PEAR THRIPS (INSECT)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LAMOTHE'S SUGARHOUSE (BURLINGTON, CONN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LIBOV, CHARLOTTE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAMOTHE, ROB</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890312T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEED81F3EF931A25750C0A96F948260" item-length="1120" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Despite Uncertainty, a Family Makes Maple Syrup</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLOTTE LIBOV</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LIBOV, CHARLOTTE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ROB LAMOTHE does not consider himself to be a gambler, but this year he is taking a chance. At the same time that many of his fellow maple syrup producers are cutting back, Mr. Lamothe, who operates Lamothe's Sugarhouse in Burlington, is doubling the size of his operation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ROB LAMOTHE does not consider himself to be a gambler, but this year he is taking a chance. At the same time that many of his fellow maple syrup producers are cutting back, Mr. Lamothe, who operates Lamothe's Sugarhouse in Burlington, is doubling the size of his operation.</p>
        <p>ROB LAMOTHE does not consider himself to be a gambler, but this year he is taking a chance. At the same time that many of his fellow maple syrup producers are cutting back, Mr. Lamothe, who operates Lamothe's Sugarhouse in Burlington, is doubling the size of his operation.</p>
        <p>''If you look at history, there have been problems as early as the 1900's about insects, defoliation, drought,'' he said one recent Saturday, while watching gallons of maple sap being boiled into jugs of pure syrup in his sugarhouse. ''These are recurring problems. You have to be aware of them, but we still decided to take a chance, and to this point, we're not sorry.''</p>
        <p>Even when maple trees are robust, making maple syrup is chancy because of the weather, with warm days and cold nights needed to cause the flow of the sap. It is also a demanding process; about 40 gallons of sap must be boiled down to yield 1 gallon of syrup.</p>
        <p>In past years, maple syrup producers have contended with a series of environmental threats ranging from pests to the effects of acid rain on the trees. This year, their main threat is another insect, the pear thrip. A small insect, the pear thrip sucks the sap from sugar maples, as well as from many fruit trees.</p>
        <p>Although experts have not yet determined whether the pear thrips pose a significant problem in Connecticut, ''many of our members are not producing syrup or have cut back as much as 50 percent,'' said Richard Norman, who is president of the 150-member Maple Sugar Producers of Connecticut.</p>
        <p>There is no way of telling how significant the problem is because the thrips will not be visible until after the maple syrup season is over, said Dr. Louis Magnarelli, an entomologist at the Connecticut Agriculture Experiment Station in New Haven. The sugaring season runs until the end of June, but a meaningful survey cannot be taken until later in the spring, he said.</p>
        <p>A survey, though, will yield valuable results for the future, he said. ''We have to figure out how extensive the thrip problem is in Connecticut,'' he said. ''We have to get a handle on it. In the northern part of the state, I suspect they probably are found, but I'm not sure about the southern part.''  Cutting Back on Tapping</p>
        <p>Still, many producers are cutting back on the number of trees they tap this season to try to spare the trees any additional stress, said Mr. Norman. Of his own operation, in Woodstock, he said: ''We had 1,000 taps last year, but we're putting in 500 or 600 this year. A couple of others who were producing on the substantial side are not tapping at all. They're concerned about the stress on the tree, so if they have other businesses to keep them busy, it makes a good reason not to tap.''</p>
        <p>This latest threat from the pear thrip is also fueling fears about the future of maple sugaring, he said.</p>
        <p>''I don't think its going to finish off the sugar maples, like Dutch elm disease did to the elms, but it makes them more vulnerable if something else came along,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Most maple syrup producers in Connecticut do so as a hobby or as a side business, Mr. Norman said, noting that the state produced about 1,500 gallons of syrup last year, making it a small part of the state's agricultural industry. Nearly half of his association's members make 10 gallons or less per season.</p>
        <p>But even though some producers are cutting back, maple syrup production is under way, said Gabe Moquin, an assistant to State Agricultural Commissioner Kenneth Andersen. If a tree appears to be in good health, tapping it should not be a problem, Mr. Moquin said, and the quality of the syrup produced should not be affected.</p>
        <p>''This is always a fun time of the year to go out and visit a maple syrup sugarhouse and watch them boiling sap,'' he said. ''A lot of them encourage people to come and visit and see how the syrup is produced. Most of the major producers will be making syrup this year. It may be at a reduced level, but it will be happening. Once you start doing it, it's difficult to stop. It's almost like a rite of spring.''</p>
        <p>Producing maple syrup began as a hobby for Mr. Lamothe, who is a machinist. He got interested in maple syrup eight years ago, when he bought some taps for his brother, Leonard, as a birthday present.</p>
        <p>''We're very much into self-sufficiency,'' Mr. Lamothe said. ''Leonard and my wife started tapping the trees, and we started boiling down the sap, and everyone decided this was a good thing. We moved the operation into an old tool shed and made some nice syrup. Eventually, a lot of people started wanting to buy a half-pint, a pint or a quart, and the business started taking off. Nowadays, we can get 40 people out here on a Saturday during the season.''</p>
        <p>For the Lamothes, maple sugaring is very much a family affair, and it includes their son, Andrew, 13 years old, and daughter, Jessica, 11, who is partial to wearing jewelry in the shape of maple leaves.  A French-Canadian Link</p>
        <p>It also helps them preserve their ties to Mr. Lamothe's French-Canadian heritage, he said. Maple sugaring is popular in Canada. He advertises his business on a local French-Canadian radio program, and he particularly enjoys having French-Canadians visit his operation. ''The syrup brings them back to their roots,'' he said. ''You can see them smiling as they come up the driveway and they smell that sweet aroma. We always have traditional music playing in the background, and they like our hospitality.''</p>
        <p>Still, deciding to expand was a difficult decision. Although they did the construction themselves, the Lamothes' new 60-foot-long, fully equipped sugarhouse represents an investment of about $65,000.</p>
        <p>''I've had some sleepless nights,'' Mr. Lamothe said. ''We've always paid everything as we've gone along, and this was a big decision. But we were very, very convinced that what we were doing is right.''</p>
        <p>By bringing people out to the sugarhouse, Mr. Lamothe also hopes to raise their awareness about the environmental problems faced by the industry. ''We feel if we can get out there and educate youngsters and some adults about how the environment is being depleted, we can serve a worthwhile social duty,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Youngsters are very much aware that our sugar maples are sick. They know there are certain things that could be done if political leaders so desire. The Canadians have done quite a bit, and it's time for the United States to do so.</p>
        <p>''It has always been the farmer in New England that's had hard sledding because conditions in New England are never favorable to small farming. But our close friends and relatives were willing to work with us, so we thought, 'This is it; we're just going to take a chance.' To this point, I'm not sorry I did it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
