<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Population Bomb Keeps Ticking</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="290632"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POPULATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FORNOS, WERNER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDC1E38F937A25753C1A96F948260" item-length="362" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Population Bomb Keeps Ticking</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Sixteen years ago, when George Bush was United States delegate to the United Nations, he wrote: ''Success in the population field, under United Nations leadership, may . . . determine whether we can resolve successfully the other great questions of peace, prosperity and individual rights that face the world.''</p>
        <p>Six years ago, when George Bush was Vice President, the Reagan Administration announced a new United States policy on international population assistance, wherein our Government would no longer consider population growth as a factor in development. Two years later, the United States withdrew its funding for the United Nations Population Fund, the largest multilateral provider of family planning assistance to the third world. Ironically, the United States had been instrumental in establishing the Population Fund and was its leading donor.</p>
        <p>When President Bush spoke Sept. 25 to the opening session of the General Assembly, he had an opportunity to reverse the regressive policy this country has pursued in recent years on international population assistance. But he did not.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Bush was the delegate to the United Nations, the population of the world had not quite reached four billion. Today global population stands at 5.2 billion, and if Mr. Bush is elected to a second term, he will be President when our human numbers reach six billion. Virtually all of this growth will occur in the developing world, regions and countries that can least afford it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush professes concern for the global environment, for the possibility that the earth's temperatures are dropping permanently, for the damage that has been done to the ozone layer. He says that he is concerned about pollution of the earth's atmosphere and its waters. A true reflection of his professed concern would be a reversal of the United States international population policy.</p>
        <p>Although President Bush missed a tremendous opportunity in his address before the General Assembly, there is still time for him to reverse our policy. But the population meter is running. WERNER FORNOS  President, The Population Institute  Washington, Sept. 26, 1989</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
