<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CONSUMER'S WORLD: Coping; With Leaking Auto Air-Conditioners</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="52" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="245005"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR CONDITIONING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CONSUMER'S WORLD PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D8153AF93AA15757C0A96F948260" item-length="803" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CONSUMER'S WORLD: Coping; With Leaking Auto Air-Conditioners</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: If you drive your air-conditioned car to the beach this summer but fear lying in the sun because of the depletion of the ozone, you may be the cause of your own problem. Environmental experts point out that automobile air-conditioners are a major source of the chemicals that are destroying Earth's ozone layer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: If you drive your air-conditioned car to the beach this summer but fear lying in the sun because of the depletion of the ozone, you may be the cause of your own problem. Environmental experts point out that automobile air-conditioners are a major source of the chemicals that are destroying Earth's ozone layer.</p>
        <p>If you drive your air-conditioned car to the beach this summer but fear lying in the sun because of the depletion of the ozone, you may be the cause of your own problem. Environmental experts point out that automobile air-conditioners are a major source of the chemicals that are destroying Earth's ozone layer.</p>
        <p>But there are steps that drivers can take to minimize the damage until substitutes for the damaging chemicals are developed.</p>
        <p>Ozone is an oxygen compound prevalent in the atmosphere 10 to 35 miles up that blocks rays from the sun that can cause skin cancer. But scientists say that when synthetic chemicals called chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, rise and are broken up by the rays of the sun they chemically destroy the ozone.</p>
        <p>CFC's come in dozens of different chemical configurations, but one of the most dangerous to the ozone is the one in auto air-conditioners, r-12 (r is for ''refrigerant''). It gets into the atmosphere because the design of auto air-conditioners requires a seal around the shaft that drives the compressor, and that seal is almost certain to leak after a few years.</p>
        <p>Kevin J. Fay, director of the Alliance for Responsible CFC Policy, an industry group, said this country produces about 700 million pounds of r-12 a year, and the 100 million cars with air-conditioners leak about a pound each, on average. That 100 million pounds acocounts for a not insignificant 4.5 percent of the world's output of CFC's, 2.2 billion pounds.</p>
        <p>R-12 ''is on the hit list,'' said Jim Norman, a spokesman for the American Society of Heating, Refrigeration and Air Conditioning Engineers. He was referring to a list of CFC's whose production will be sharply cut beginning this summer under an agreement that 24 nations, including the United States, reached in Montreal in September 1987. Spot shortages of these CFC's may result. Auto makers are redisigning air-conditioners to use different refrigerants, but no substitute is likely for units that use r-12. Substitutes are being sought for home refrigerators and freezers, but while they also use r-12, they are not so prone to leaks. (Home air-conditioners use a less harmful substance, r-22.) In the meantime, what can a consumer do to limit environmental damage from a car air-conditioner?</p>
        <p>For one thing, experts say, stop using the recharging cans of r-12 sold in discount and auto parts stores. If your system has a leak, better to pay the money to have it fixed than to keep recharging the system yourself and bleeding more CFC's into the air. If your system shows signs of starting to fail, have it serviced sooner rather than later.</p>
        <p>To check for a leak yourself, turn off the car engine and look for oil on the lower edges of air-conditioning components. The oil is a sign of a refrigerant leak. A light film at the compressor seal is normal, though.</p>
        <p>Choose a repair shop carefully. Paul M. Allen, executive director of the International Mobile Air Condition Association, an industry trade group based in Dallas, said ''probably half'' of the shops offering auto air-conditioner service would treat a leak simply by adding r-12.</p>
        <p>''You'd be happy because you're going to get through the summer,'' he said. ''They'd be happy because they made $15 on the job, and the environmental and refrigerants problem would be compounded.''</p>
        <p>But even well-intentioned technicians can cause damage, by pumping up a system with r-12 to look for leaks, and letting the refrigerant leak out when they open the system. Mr. Allen's group is promoting the use of equipment that recycles the refrigerant drained from air-conditioners, but only about 1,000 shops in the country, fewer than 1 percent, have such equipment, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Allen's group, fearful of strict government regulation if the industry does not act on its own, is urging service stations to use a vacuum system for finding leaks, to keep careful inventories of supplies and to look for more than one leak before repressurizing a system. Many more stations will have recycling equipment by 1990 and 1991, he predicted, in part because prices for r-12 are going to rise rapidly and the equipment will pay for itself. California is already drafting legislation for mandatory recycling.</p>
        <p>Mr. Allen's association maintains a list of shops that comply with its recommendations. The association's address is 3003 LBJ Freeway, Suite 219, Dallas, Tex. 75234. The phone number is 214-484-5750.</p>
        <p>Consumers can help save the ozone by buying the most energy-efficient refrigerators, said Dr. Jan Beyea, a scientist with the Audubon Society. Even if a refrigerator does not leak while it is used, its CFC's are likely to find their way into the environment after it is discarded, he said, and the most energy-efficient model is likely to have as little as half as much r-12 as the least efficient.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
