<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="245700"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PROTESTANT EPISCOPAL CHURCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ST JOHN'S EPISCOPAL CHURCH (OAKDALE, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KETCHAM, DIANE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MOONEY, NOREEN O'CONNOR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Episcopal Church</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDF1331F933A05757C0A96F948260" item-length="1336" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANE KETCHAM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KETCHAM, DIANE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  Ms. Priest?  DECIDING what to call the new priest is the first problem facing the small congregation of St. John's Episcopal Church in Oakdale. What do you call a female priest? ''I don't know,'' said Betty Voehl, whose family has attended St. John's since 1946. ''Father won't do,'' said her husband,</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  Ms. Priest?  DECIDING what to call the new priest is the first problem facing the small congregation of St. John's Episcopal Church in Oakdale. What do you call a female priest? ''I don't know,'' said Betty Voehl, whose family has attended St. John's since 1946. ''Father won't do,'' said her husband,</p>
        <p>Ms. Priest?  DECIDING what to call the new priest is the first problem facing the small congregation of St. John's Episcopal Church in Oakdale. What do you call a female priest? ''I don't know,'' said Betty Voehl, whose family has attended St. John's since 1946. ''Father won't do,'' said her husband, William.</p>
        <p>''Mother Mooney doesn't make it either,'' said the priest in question, Noreen O'Connor Mooney. ''I've asked them to call me Noreen,'' she said. ''The more formal can call me Mrs. Mooney.''</p>
        <p>In an unusual blending of old and new, the first female Episcopal priest to oversee a congregation on Long Island is performing that duty in one of the oldest churches on the Island.</p>
        <p>St John's, a one-room church with upstairs slave gallery and ramrod straight-back pews, complete with accordion doors to lock in the worshippers, opened its door in 1765. The first Episcopal bishop in America administered there; American Revolution and Civil War veterans are buried in its churchyard. It is a church rich in history. And now it is making more.</p>
        <p>The bubbly and full-of-life Mrs. Mooney, the divorced mother of a 16-year-old, David, is one of three Long Island women ordained as Episcopal priests earlier this year. She is the first female priest to have her own church, even if only temporarily. ''I'm the supply priest here,'' she said. ''The priest in charge retired to Florida after Easter. The diocese is deciding what to do, but I would love to stay.''</p>
        <p>The Episcopal Diocese of Long Island is not certain what the future of St. John's, with its dwindling congregation, will be, but the future for women as priests on Long Island ''is bright,'' said Tony Miller, a diocese official. ''The reaction has been generally positive. You'll be seeing more women priests on the Island.''</p>
        <p>''I think that's wonderful,'' said Christine Giles of Oakdale, who attends St. John's with her 11-year-old daughter, Jennifer. ''Women are just as capable,'' she said. In place of an organist, Ms. Giles plays her guitar and sings in a pure Judy Collins-like voice at the 10 A.M. service. She said that a female priest ''may put some people off, the narrow-minded ones, ''but I don't think God's going to differentiate between a man or a woman as long as they're doing God's work.''</p>
        <p>There are now only five or six people regularly attending the one Sunday service at St. John's. Mrs. Mooney is hopeful that more will come and she can remain there. ''Celebrating the Eucharist in the same church as our first bishop did; well, it's awesome,'' she said.  Whatever It Is, It's Big</p>
        <p>The Long Island zoological question for the spring: What is an emu, and where does it come from?</p>
        <p>The emu (pronounced EE-myoo) is ''not little and furry.'' Nor is it ''like an antelope,'' as two Long Islanders guessed. An emu is a bird, a big bird. At 5 feet tall, it's second in size only to the ostrich, the world's biggest bird.</p>
        <p>Where do emus come from? Copiague. Well, at least three do. Although the emu is the national bird of Australia, three of the giant birds have wound up in the backyard of Steve Weinkselbaum of Copiague.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weinkselbaum keeps emus as pets. ''They're quiet, they don't make much noise, just a little bellow now and then, and you don't have to worry about them flying away,'' he said. Emus can't fly, and after visiting Mr. Weinkselbaum's emus, which each weigh about 100 pounds, you're glad they don't. Having one of those overhead could be a bit disconcerting.</p>
        <p>Although the Copiague emus are the most popular sightseeing attraction for children getting off the local school bus, a few years ago the Town of Babylon challenged Mr. Weinkselbaum's right to keep emus in his backyard. He won in court, however, with his emus being classified exotic birds rather than livestock.</p>
        <p>And like other birds, exotic or otherwise, come spring, the emu's thoughts turn to love nests for two, or in the case of Mr. Weinkselbaum's emus, three. His two females and one male are expecting. The male has been sitting dutifully on the one big green emu egg, in the ground-level nest, for the last two months, Mr. Weinkselbaum said. ''The problem with emus is that since they're from Australia their winters are our summers,'' he said. ''They've sat on the nest in the snow.''  Promoting Methanol</p>
        <p>On the outside, the dark gray Chevrolet Corsica looks like any other automobile on the Long Island Expressway. Of course there are the decals, promoting New York Institute of Technology, General Motors and the Department of Energy, but turning the outside of your car into a driving billboard is nothing new on Long Island.</p>
        <p>It's the inside of this car that sets it apart. Like the television show ''Nightrider,'' the dashboard is strictly high tech. ''It looks really fancy with all the computer gadgets,'' said Prof. Bernard Gleimer, the assistant dean of engineering at New York Tech. The computer instruments are necessary because the car now runs on methanol. New York Tech's student chapter of the Society of Automotive Engineers have spent the last five months modifying the car's engine, fuel tank, and fuel injectors so it can run on 85 percent methanol and 15 percent gasoline.</p>
        <p>This weekend the students and their methanol car joined a methanol marathon rally. Ten students from New York Tech are traveling through Michigan, Canada and New York City (they'll be in Central Park on Tuesday) and on to Washington, competing against 15 other university teams that also converted Chevrolet Corsicas to run on methanol. The cars will be judged on cold starts, fuel economy and rally times.</p>
        <p>''Our car has good manners,'' said Christopher Blyseth, a senior at Tech and president of the automotive club. ''It handles well.'' Winning the marathon, however, is a long shot, he said.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists are pushing for methanol cars because ''if alcohol is burned properly, it only emits carbon dioxide, none of the hydrocarbons,'' Professor Gleimer said. ''It's a big step toward clean air and you don't have to depend on foreign countries for the fuel product.''</p>
        <p>He predicts that by the 1990's, 10 percent of the cars in this country will run on methanol. Right now, however, having a methanol-running car is a challenge. ''There are no methanol fuel pumps to pull up to, and say, 'Fill 'er up,' Mr. Blyseth said. ''We had to use little cans.''  Clean-a-Thon</p>
        <p>Isabel Cutler of Stony Brook has a dream. She would like to see the streets and shopping center near her Strathmore development home free of litter. But unlike most dreamers Mrs. Cutler is willing to do something to make her dream come true.</p>
        <p>She is trying to organize a garbage-thon. ''We have so many walk-a-thons and swim-a-thons and run-a-thons, why not a clean-a-thon?'' she asks. ''Why not do something for the environment while you're raising money?''</p>
        <p>She has commandeered the meeting room at the Emma Clark Library in Setauket the night of May 24 for her first clean-a-thon meeting. Anyone who lives in the Three Village area and would like to help clean up the streets and shopping centers or help organize a garbage-thon is urged to attend, she said. ''If neighbors and families would band together we could clean everything up and raise money for some charity at the same time,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''I spent a year in California because my husband was transferred out there on business,'' she said, explaining what motivates one homeowner to take on the garbage of Stony Brook. ''When I came back to Long Island I went into visual pollution shock. It's so depressing how much garbage is strewn about.'' She's already asked the environmental club at Ward Melville High School to get involved. Now she's looking for other concerned Long Islanders. The idea of a garbage-thon is sound, she said; she just needs the bodies to make it work.</p>
        <p>''If a kid came to my door and said how much would you pledge for every bag of garbage I collected, you better believe I'd give him money,'' she said, ''and a lot more than for someone swimming laps.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
