<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="223145"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DF1F3CF937A25751C0A96F948260" item-length="969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-15  President Bush has rewarded major financial contributors and longtime supporters by naming them to prestigious ambassadorships, senior officials say. Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-15  President Bush has rewarded major financial contributors and longtime supporters by naming them to prestigious ambassadorships, senior officials say. Page A1</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-15  President Bush has rewarded major financial contributors and longtime supporters by naming them to prestigious ambassadorships, senior officials say. Page A1</p>
        <p>A man going on trial for terrorism in Washington, Fawaz Yunis, is the first accused terrorist to be spirited out of Lebanon and brought to trial in an American court. A1</p>
        <p>An attack on an American center in Pakistan has created a crisis for Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto. The attack and its causes are testing the bonds of friendship between the United States and Pakistan. A1</p>
        <p>Mikhail Gorbachev is so popular in Western Europe that Secretary of State James Baker is worried. Mr. Baker is concerned that the Soviet leader's charm may hinder NATO's room for political maneuver. A8</p>
        <p>The last Soviet military garrisons in Afghanistan were reported to be packing for home, less than 48 hours before tomorrow's deadline agreed to by the Kremlin for its final troop withdrawal. A8</p>
        <p>In Yugoslavia, two opposition groups have been founded since December in the republic of Slovenia to contest the ruling Communist Party's monopoly on political power. Party leaders are uneasy, but have not interfered. A5</p>
        <p>Hopes are fading for better relations between the United States and Mexico. Recently, the relations have been irritated by an outcry over President Bush's choice as the new United States Ambassador to Mexico. A15</p>
        <p>The search for Olof Palme's killer has narrowed down to a ''lone, mad Swede.'' After nearly a three-year hunt, Swedish officials say they may have found the man who killed the country's Prime Minister. A3</p>
        <p>Winnie Mandela seems to be isolated among South African blacks after weekend press reports that she took part in the beatings of four black youths, one of whom is presumed dead, at her home in Soweto on Dec. 29. A3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A16-22  Debate on President Bush's budget intensified over the question of whether the $1.16 trillion budget is a realistic effort to cut the deficit or a ploy to force the Democrats to trim popular social programs. A1</p>
        <p>A Bush savings and loan proposal that the industry double its capital cushion in two and a half years has upset many savings executives. They warn that the requirement could push 1,000 institutions out of business. A1</p>
        <p>A ''Baby Bell'' won approval, for the first time since 1984, to invest in a major foreign telecommunications operation. A Federal judge has permitted the Pacific Telesis Group to become part-owner of a consortium in Japan. A1</p>
        <p>Oliver North's lawyers said former President Ronald Reagan and other senior officials made ''direct, personal'' deals to help provide secret military aid to rebels inside Nicaragua despite a Congressional ban. A19</p>
        <p>In Antarctica, biologists are worried about the threats posed by increased commercial fishing, drastic depletion of the protective ozone layer in the atmosphere and rising pollution of a once pristine habitat. C1</p>
        <p>A proposed ''safe sex kit'' ordinance in Berkeley, Calif., requires that every hotel room in the city contain condoms and educational literature about AIDS. A16</p>
        <p>The long debate over John Tower as a nominee for Secretary of Defense has delayed Pentagon policy decisions, especially budget-cutting ones. The Defense Department is in its fourth week without a civilian leader. A20</p>
        <p>Soviet Jews are flocking to Boston, straining the resources of social service agencies and adding new life to a small but growing community of Jews who have settled in the city's neighborhoods and suburbs. A16</p>
        <p>New England's economy has slowed. For the first time in the 1980's, the growth of employment in the six-state region, the envy of the nation for nearly a decade, is much lower than in the United States as a whole. A18</p>
        <p>F.B.I. faulted on plan to use computer to track suspects A17</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON TALK A20</p>
        <p>REGIONAL B1-5  Lilco reportedly reached an accord with its customers on a racketeering case that could have bankrupted the utility. The accord requires Lilco to reduce planned increases in electric rates. A1</p>
        <p>A fax machine is a matchmaker for single people using a service called SinglesFax. Members of the service fill out a questionnaire, then wait by their home or office machines, hoping for a perfect match. A1</p>
        <p>Atlantic City casino workers face problems associated with the intense round-the-clock style of the gambling industry. Along with the economic rebirth in the New Jersey city, social problems like alcohol and drug abuse have mushroomed. B1</p>
        <p>A reef will be made from concrete from Manhattan's West Side Highway, two New York State agencies say. The concrete will be sunk to the bottom of the Atlantic off Long Island to benefit fish and fishermen. B1</p>
        <p>Making English the official language is the aim of a proposal in Suffolk County. Critics say the proposal is racist. Backers say it will curb a growing number of bilingual programs in county government. B3</p>
        <p>News analysis: Governor Cuomo, by insisting that the State Legislature approve any settlement to shut the Shoreham nuclear power plant, has raised questions over the sharing of the burden for such a decision. B4</p>
        <p>A nationwide alert has been issued for a 19-year-old Sussex County, New Jersey, man suspected of stabbing to death a high school student and forcing a girl to go with him as he fled in a Jeep on Sunday. B1</p>
        <p>Black officers defend Ward against critics B3</p>
        <p>NEEDIEST CASES B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
