<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Logging in Lush Alaskan Forest Profits Companies and Costs U.S.</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19890605T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="254520"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOOD AND WOOD PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC PROPERTY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALASKA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">TONGASS NATIONAL FOREST (ALASKA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FOREST SERVICE, US</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">EGAN, TIMOTHY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wood and Wood Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D91530F93AA15756C0A96F948260" item-length="1336" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Logging in Lush Alaskan Forest Profits Companies and Costs U.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY EGAN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">EGAN, TIMOTHY</byline>
      <dateline>SITKA, Alaska</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Here in the emerald panhandle of southeastern Alaska, where rain is measured in feet and the legacy of Russian America can still be seen in onion-domed churches, the Forest Service sells 500-year-old trees for the price of a cheeseburger.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Here in the emerald panhandle of southeastern Alaska, where rain is measured in feet and the legacy of Russian America can still be seen in onion-domed churches, the Forest Service sells 500-year-old trees for the price of a cheeseburger.</p>
        <p>Here in the emerald panhandle of southeastern Alaska, where rain is measured in feet and the legacy of Russian America can still be seen in onion-domed churches, the Forest Service sells 500-year-old trees for the price of a cheeseburger.</p>
        <p>If sold on the open market, those same $2 Sitka spruce trees would cost up to $300 a log. The wood is bought by two pulp mills, one of them owned by a Japanese investment consortium. The mills say they are turning a handsome profit on America's biggest and, to the American taxpayer, costliest national forest. #98 Cents Lost on Each Dollar In some years, the Forest Service has lost 98 cents for every dollar it spent on the logging program in the Tongass National Forest, a network of evergreen-covered islands and lush valleys encompassing most of the 500-mile long Alaskan panhandle.</p>
        <p>Critics say the timber management of the Tongass demonstrates that the Forest Service spends most of its money serving industry to the detriment of the environment and taxpayers. They say that the agency has lost sight of its mission, to manage and protect the public forests for the benefit of all, and that the failure is nowhere more evident than here.</p>
        <p>Proponents of the Tongass program, including both of Alaska's Senators and its lone member of Congress, say losing money on timber sales is no different from spending money to buy wilderness. They say small towns in sparsely populated Southeast Alaska would be hit hard if the Government did not keep them alive with the income generated from the below-cost timber sales.</p>
        <p>Now, with bills pending in Congress that would cut the timber subsidy, the outcome of the fight could shape the future direction of the Forest Service, which has been criticized for its management of the 156 national forests, one-third of which lose money selling their trees to industry.</p>
        <p>The Tongass controversy, like nearly everything in Alaska, is full of extremes.</p>
        <p>At 16.5 million acres, the national forest is roughly the size of West Virginia. Only about a third of it is prime timber land. The rest is scrub trees, ice, rock and glacial moraine where nothing grows but lichen.</p>
        <p>For years, the Forest Service has been trying to develop a timber industry here, home of rich salmon spawning streams and the highest concentration of bald eagles and brown bears in the nation.</p>
        <p>But the remote and roadless country, far from big markets, has been unattractive to business. In the 1950's, the service succeeded in luring two pulp mills to the region by offering them 50-year, low-cost timber contracts. The mills, one in Ketchikan and one in Sitka, grind Tongass timber into pulp, most of which is then sold to Asian countries where it is processed into synthentic fabric for clothing.</p>
        <p>Whether there should be any Government-sponsored logging at all here is hotly debated. Environmentalists say the Tongass, as one of the world's last temperate rain forests, is more valuable as a climate-cooling canopy.</p>
        <p>Timber industry leaders say the logging program, if properly managed to protect streams and wildlife habitat, does not cause significant long-term environmental damage. Dispute on Effects</p>
        <p>In a Congressional hearing this year, Senator Tim Wirth, a Democrat from Colorado who is the prime sponsor of a bill to alter the Tongass management, said cutting the Alaskan rain forest was contributing in a small way to global warming. Senator Frank H. Murkowski, a Republican from Alaska, replied that cutting old trees was actually beneficial to the atmosphere because the young trees that would grow back in place of the aging giants would give off more oxygen.</p>
        <p>What draws the most criticism is the $400 million the Forest Service has spent running the logging program in the last eight years.</p>
        <p>When Congress was considering the creation of 5.4 million acres of Tongass wilderness in 1980, Senator Ted Stevens, Republican of Alaska, added provisions that set a goal for the Forest Service to cut roughly 170,000 acres of the forest every 10 years and to spend at least $40 million doing it. The spending is not subject to annual Congressional review.</p>
        <p>Shortly after the 1980 bill passed, the timber market collapsed. Jobs in the two Tongass pulp mills fell 40 percent. Yet the Forest Service kept building roads and preparing timber sales for wood that nobody wanted to buy.</p>
        <p>A report on the Tongass forest by the General Accounting Office, an investigative arm of Congress, said the Forest Service spent $131 million for five years of road building and surveying in old-growth forests that the mills did not want to buy.</p>
        <p>The price of timber remained relatively low until 1986, but today is at its highest level in more than a decade. Loss of Jobs Threatened</p>
        <p>Under terms of their contracts, the mills are entitled to buy up to 15,000 acres of Tongass timber a year at $2.19 per 1,000 board feet, less than 1 percent of the market price, which is $100 to $400 per 1,000 board feet, depending on the grade of wood. Without the agreements, the mill owners say, they might close their operations and eliminate 1,800 jobs.</p>
        <p>''What they're saying is that they need a monopoly, they need the very best timber and they need $40 million a year in taxpayer money to keep them going,'' said Joe Mehrkens, a 17-year Forest Service employee who now works for the Wilderness Society in Alaska.</p>
        <p>But Michael Barton, regional forester for the Tongass, the Forest Service's top official in the area, said his agency is keeping the economy of southeastern Alaskan alive.</p>
        <p>''Sure, we've lost a lot of money in the 1980's,'' Mr. Barton said, ''but I think it's the Forest Service's role to help provide an economic base.''</p>
        <p>Rollo Pool, a spokesman for the mill in Sitka, the Japanese-owned Alaskan Pulp Corporation, said the company is in the midst of record earnings for its Tongass products with sales of more than $120 million in 1988. But he said if Congress were to break the 50-year contract promising below-cost prices, the mill might have to close down and leave Sitka.</p>
        <p>The other company is Ketchikan Pulp Company, a subsidiary of Louisiana-Pacific Corporation.</p>
        <p>Besides the threat to eliminate jobs, the companies also hint at legal action. ''Regardless of whether these contracts are good or bad, the mills have said if they are canceled today they would seek up to $700 million in compensation,'' Mr. Pool said. Conflicting Interests in Town</p>
        <p>The town here is divided. The mill provides about 25 percent of the jobs but is also the chief source of air and water pollution in the region. Fishing and tourism, the other main sources of income here, have been at odds with the Government's timber program.</p>
        <p>The Sealaska Corporation, a native American group with 16,000 shareholders in southeastern Alaska, runs a timber business on its own land, but says it is put at a competitive disadvantage because of the Tongass contracts.</p>
        <p>''We think the timber industry in Alaska should be market driven,'' said Byron Mallott, chairman of Sealaska, which cuts about 10,000 acres of timber a year. ''If they can't operate without a Federal subsidy, then maybe they should just shut down.''</p>
        <p>Besides Senator Wirth's bill, there also is legislation in the House, sponsored by Representative Robert J. Mrazek, Democrat of Long Island. The measure, approved last week by the House Interior Committee, would end the 50-year contracts, make the $40 million yearly appropriation subject to annual review, set up additional protected wilderness areas and, perhaps most significantly, direct the Forest Service to devote more money and attention to on recreational uses and wildlife enhancements instead of economic concerns.</p>
        <p>In Sitka, there are bumper stickers that say, ''Bob Mrazek is my Congressman.'' But he is also cursed as a meddler from the East.</p>
        <p>''In general, Alaskans tend to be very leery of environmentalists,'' said Mr. Mehrkens of the Wilderness Society. ''But this whole Tongass program is just so absurd that it's broken down all the labels.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 5, 1989, Monday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>A map last Monday misidentified the area of the Tongass National Forest in Alaska, which encompasses most of the 500-mile Alaskan Panhandle. A corrected map appears today on page B6.</p>
        <p>A map last Monday misidentified the area of the Tongass National Forest, which encompasses most of the 500-mile Alaskan Panhandle. The story was about the debate over Government-sponsored logging in the region.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 5, 1989, Monday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>A map last Monday misidentified the area of the Tongass National Forest in Alaska, which encompasses most of the 500-mile Alaskan Panhandle. A corrected map appears today on page B6.</p>
        <p>A map last Monday misidentified the area of the Tongass National Forest, which encompasses most of the 500-mile Alaskan Panhandle. The story was about the debate over Government-sponsored logging in the region.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
