<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush, in Ottawa, Now Vows To Pursue Acid Rain Pact</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="222326"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MULRONEY, BRIAN (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOWD, MAUREEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (MRS)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MULRONEY, MILA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DC1E3FF932A25751C0A96F948260" item-length="616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush, in Ottawa, Now Vows To Pursue Acid Rain Pact</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DOWD, MAUREEN</byline>
      <dateline>OTTAWA, Feb. 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush met with Prime Minister Brian Mulroney today and agreed to pursue an international accord with Canada to reduce the acid rain that falls on both sides of the border.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush met with Prime Minister Brian Mulroney today and agreed to pursue an international accord with Canada to reduce the acid rain that falls on both sides of the border.</p>
        <p>President Bush met with Prime Minister Brian Mulroney today and agreed to pursue an international accord with Canada to reduce the acid rain that falls on both sides of the border.</p>
        <p>Although the meeting between the two leaders, Mr. Bush's first foreign trip as President, was billed as a symbolic encounter to reaffirm the neighbors' harmonious relationship, it produced an American commitment that Canada eagerly desired.</p>
        <p>Ottawa had long sought an agreement on acid rain from Washington, but the Reagan Administration had resisted such a costly move and insisted that the pollution problem required greater study.</p>
        <p>Acid rain is produced largely by sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxides when fossil fuels are burned. It has been found to destroy freshwater plants and wildlife and is suspected of damaging crops and threatening human health. 'Quite Substantial Progress'</p>
        <p>The Prime Minister said he was delighted with what Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d called an American change of attitude that would result in an accord by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>''I think that this represents quite substantial progress,'' Mr. Mulroney said. ''You know it wasn't so long ago that Canada was sort of going it alone in many ways in this area.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush was accompanied by his wife, Barbara; Mr. Baker; Brent Scowcroft, the national security adviser; Carla Anderson Hills, the special trade representative, and his chief of staff, John H. Sununu.</p>
        <p>After their four-hour meeting, the two men stood in their overcoats in 13-degree-below-zero weather outside the Prime Minister's gray stone residence above the frozen Ottawa River. Canadian mounties in red jackets stood stoically behind. Asked whether he and the Prime Minister were in accord on East-West relations, Mr. Bush replied in an insouciant if imperfect French accent, ''Certainement.'' 'As Fast as Possible'</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said he had set no timetables or targets for emission reductions of the sulfur dioxide that is spewed into the atmosphere from industrial smokestacks. ''I have in mind as fast as possible,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But he reiterated the pledge that he made in his budget address on Thursday night to move swiftly in presenting legislation strengthening the Clean Air Act and setting a timetable to limit emissions that cause acid rain.</p>
        <p>''What has to be decided primarily is how much, what is the target for reduction and who's going to pay the price?'' said Secretary Baker, adding that the decision ''could affect different regions different ways.''</p>
        <p>American action on this issue, which Canadians felt was stalled during the Reagan years, has been the major irritant between the two countries. In 1985, Canada adopted a stringent program to cut back on the use of fuels high in sulfur and to force utilities and smelters to install expensive ''scrubbers'' to clean their exhausts.</p>
        <p>Saying that the mood of the meeting was ''upbeat,'' President Bush said he chose Canada for his first trip outside the United States ''to see that this strong relationship becomes even stronger.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush clearly wanted to help Mr. Mulroney soothe any anti-American sentiments that had been stirred up in the recent Canadian election.</p>
        <p>The Prime Minister won in November on the Progressive Conservative ticket after a bitter fight with the opposition Liberal and New Democratic parties, who had charged that his support of a free-trade agreement with the United States was a ''sell-out'' to America.</p>
        <p>The race spurred anxiety here that the trade bill would make an already insecure Canada hopelessly dependent on its powerful neighbor. Mr. Mulroney fought that notion and promised to ''refurbish'' the relationship between the two countries.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
