<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Atlanta's Gold (Forsythia) Battles Its Purple (Smog)</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="236799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOG</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREES AND SHRUBS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ATLANTA (GA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">APPLEBOME, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia/Atlanta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D6103EF931A35757C0A96F948260" item-length="841" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Atlanta's Gold (Forsythia) Battles Its Purple (Smog)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">APPLEBOME, PETER</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, April 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To outsiders Atlanta is a booming, spit-and-polish haven for middle managers and regional salesmen - the heart, if not the soul, of the bustling New South.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To outsiders Atlanta is a booming, spit-and-polish haven for middle managers and regional salesmen - the heart, if not the soul, of the bustling New South.</p>
        <p>To outsiders Atlanta is a booming, spit-and-polish haven for middle managers and regional salesmen - the heart, if not the soul, of the bustling New South.</p>
        <p>But there is another animating force that pervades life here much as it did 50 years ago. It exists in the dogwood and crab apple, oak and hickory, tulip poplar, magnolia and maple trees of this densely wooded city. The United States Forest Service says Atlanta has the most densely wooded metropolitan area in the country.</p>
        <p>As spring envelops a city that awaits the flowering of the dogwoods as most places await Christmas, it is difficult to avoid two conflicting thoughts - how beautiful spring is here and how fragile even so powerful a certitude as spring can seem. In a year in which environmental issues have suddenly become inescapable, even spring in Atlanta brings a faint undercurrent of sorrow.</p>
        <p>''The first time I saw the azaleas and dogwoods in the spring here, it was like a religious experience; I was awestruck,'' said Ed Macie, senior arborist of Fulton County. ''But today, for example, I was driving on one of the freeways, and all you could see was the purple haze of the smog. For the people on the road, it wasn't springtime at all. I thought that was a pretty telltale sign.'' Defined by Its Greenery</p>
        <p>Atlanta began as a railhead in the middle of a Piedmont hardwood forest. If man has hacked and slashed through the woods with a relentless determination, the area is still largely defined by the luxurious greenery in which it is enveloped.</p>
        <p>The basic unit of human interaction here often seems to be the garden clubs. The advent of spring, from the first blooms of forsythia and Bradford pear to the incandescent pink and red flowering of the dogwoods in mid-April, is so intense that motorists have to be careful not to run off the road as they gawk at the greenery.</p>
        <p>A highlight of the Dogwood Festival April 8-16 is a tour of lighted trees, in which residents spotlight their grandest trees much as people display Christmas lights elsewhere.</p>
        <p>People flock like pilgrims to view the most extravagant flowerings and fashionable homes on Lullwater Road in Druid Hills or Habersham Road in Buckhead. Atlanta politicians can speak of trees the way Presidential candidates pay homage to the flag. What Does Atlanta Mean? ''The word that I think best describes Atlanta is trees,'' said Maynard Jackson, who was Mayor from 1974 to 1982 and is running for the office again.</p>
        <p>A more common word tied to Atlanta is growth. From 1980 to 1987 alone, the population of the metropolitan area increased 25 percent. It was great for business and terrible for the trees.</p>
        <p>According to Trees Atlanta, a nonprofit organization, the seven-county Atlanta area loses 50 acres of trees every day as against 27 acres a day five years ago. There was a 16 percent decrease in forest cover between 1975 and 1985. In booming Gwinnett County alone, more than 4 million trees were lost, the organization said.</p>
        <p>Usually, the fate of the trees is no more than an afterthought. After engineers prepared a 1986 study for a proposed extension of Georgia Highway 400, which is scheduled to cut a six-mile, 400-foot swath through a densely wooded residential area of north Atlanta, an environmental impact assessment was made. It did not even consider loss of trees. Instead, it briefly noted the role in providing a wildlife habitat that is played by the 13 ''natural area remnants'' of 10 acres or more in the highway's path. 'We Live in a Forest'</p>
        <p>''Trees are what makes this city livable,'' said Edward Daugherty, an Atlanta landscape architect. ''As soon as you lose that encompassing gown or fabric, you've lost what this city has to offer. If you live by the seashore, you don't promote a plan to dry up the ocean. We live in a forest, and we need to learn to evaluate what the forest does for us.''</p>
        <p>Just as the greenhouse effect has evolved from an esoteric scientific theory linking pollution to a global warming into a household word, trees here have become a mainstream concern. Trees Atlanta, founded in 1985, talks about the importance of trees for cooling off the torrid Atlanta summer, filtering pollutants from the air and preventing soil erosion as often as it mentions the esthetic advantages of a city of trees versus a sea of concrete.</p>
        <p>Several municipalities have developed ordinances that attempt to limit tree loss. Trees Atlanta is working toward replanting and preservation, but the losses still far outweigh the gains. Combined with a lingering drought and an eerily warm winter, the situation has left many people who have no firm ties to environmental causes wondering what the future will hold.</p>
        <p>''People talk about the rain forests of Brazil, but the first place we have to educate people is right here,'' said Jackie Fitts, an Atlanta interior designer whose garden club is trying to form a group that would encourage developers to save and replant trees. ''We have been blessed with a wonderful environment that we are destroying very quickly.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
