<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City of Freeways Plants An Idea to Help Nature</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="213555"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREES AND SHRUBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES (CALIF)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">REINHOLD, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRADLEY, TOM (MAYOR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DF103EF931A25752C0A96F948260" item-length="880" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City of Freeways Plants An Idea to Help Nature</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT REINHOLD, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REINHOLD, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Jan. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: If any city has a moral obligation to do something about global warming, this is it. And so today the city of angels and internal combustion took action.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: If any city has a moral obligation to do something about global warming, this is it. And so today the city of angels and internal combustion took action.</p>
        <p>If any city has a moral obligation to do something about global warming, this is it. And so today the city of angels and internal combustion took action.</p>
        <p>Mayor Tom Bradley announced a program to encourage the planting of two million to five million trees in the city in the next five years, trees that would serve to cool buildings and absorb the carbon dioxide that experts say is a major culprit in the worldwide warming trend.</p>
        <p>Many scientists fear that the general increase in temperatures around the world, caused by gases absorbing solar heat, could bring environmental catastrophe in the next century.</p>
        <p>Mayor Bradley said that although the Los Angeles tree program could have only a small effect on the warming trend, he hoped that major cities around the world would emulate his city.</p>
        <p>He said he would write the mayors of Los Angeles's 14 ''sister cities'' abroad.</p>
        <p>''We are trying to raise the level of consciousness, to spread information,'' Mr. Bradley said, just two hours after launching his campaign for a record fifth term as Mayor of the second-largest American city.</p>
        <p>The Mayor said the city would work with a local private group, Tree People, to plant the trees in parking lots, along streets and in other unshaded places. He said the project would not cost the city any money beyond that for maintaining trees on city property, but he had no estimate of that expense. 'Environmental Crisis'</p>
        <p>Joining Mayor Bradley for the announcement was Jeremy Rifkin, president of the Foundation on Economic Trends, a Washington-based public affairs group that has been sounding the alarm on the environmental hazards of genetic engineering and global warming. Mr. Rifkin spoke as a member of the recently formed Global Greenhouse Network, a group of organizations and lawmakers in 35 countries whose goal is to halve global carbon dioxide emissions by the year 2030.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rifkin said he hoped that the tree program would be the first step in a worldwide effort to use local solutions to stem global warming without waiting for national and international bodies to act. He called such warming the ''first truly global environmental crisis.''</p>
        <p>The warming is caused by various gases, particularly carbon dioxide produced by combustion of fossil fuels, chlorofluorcarbons and halons from industry, methane from agriculture and waste dumps and nitrous oxides from motor vehicles and fertilizers. These gases absorb radiation from the sun that would normally be reflected back into the outer atmosphere, and thus they cause a gradual warming of the earth's surface. This effect is compounded by widespread deforestation for development and farming, which has reduced the number of green plants that absorb carbon dioxide. Consensus for Action</p>
        <p>Experts have debated how urgent the problem is and whether the warming has caused recent droughts and heat waves. There is a growing consensus, however, that concerted worldwide action is needed.</p>
        <p>Last week, the National Academy of Sciences urged President-elect George Bush to put the issue high on his agenda. ''Global environmental change may well be the most pressing international issue of the next century,'' it said.</p>
        <p>Climatologists have predicted that the warming could melt the polar ice caps and thereby raise sea levels by several feet and inundate major cities. They also said the warming could drastically reduce the planet's capacity to produce food.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rifkin said his organization approached Los Angeles first to tackle the problem locally because of its history of air pollution. California as a whole, he said, ranks with the top 10 industrial countries of the world in contributing to global warming. With 23.5 million registered vehicles, California has about 13 percent of all vehicles in the United States; Los Angeles alone has about five million vehicles. Trees for the Olympics</p>
        <p>The tree planting program is not the first in Los Angeles. A similar effort was made for esthetic reasons before the Summer Olympic Games here in 1984, but many of the one million or so trees planted have since died for lack of proper care and planning.</p>
        <p>John W. Stodder Jr., the Mayor's environmental aide, said a better effort would be made to save the trees this time and that $25,000 had been raised privately for Tree People to study how to do that. A portion of that money would be used to study which species of trees can best survive with little water. Two other local environmental groups, Campaign California and the Coalition for Clean Air, are also involved in the project.</p>
        <p>Mayor Bradley, who has long been associated with the economic growth that has contributed to the city's air pollution, asked the City Council last week to adopt more than 60 measures to reduce air pollution. For example, he would eliminate most free parking in the city, even at shopping malls, use cleaner fuels at city utility plants, upgrade city vehicles to make them more fuel efficient, and create stronger incentives for van pooling and discouraging single-occupancy vehicles.</p>
        <p>But the question remains whether Los Angeles residents, wedded to an easy ''car culture'' more than any other Americans, were willing to make the compromises in their style and standard of life that may be necessary to clean the air.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
