<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Natural Resources</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="267523"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="WASHINGTON TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON TALK PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2D71330F933A15754C0A96F948260" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Natural Resources</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Philip Shabecoff, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Looking backward decades from now, will the summit meeting of the summer of '89 seem meaningless, or will it be a watershed in the history of the health of planet Earth?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Looking backward decades from now, will the summit meeting of the summer of '89 seem meaningless, or will it be a watershed in the history of the health of planet Earth?</p>
        <p>Looking backward decades from now, will the summit meeting of the summer of '89 seem meaningless, or will it be a watershed in the history of the health of planet Earth?</p>
        <p>''All words and no action,'' was the first assessment by Senator Albert Gore Jr., Democrat of Tennessee, summing up the environmental efforts of the meeting of seven industrial democracies in Paris last week.</p>
        <p>''There were strong policy statements but not a lot of real commitment,'' said James Tripp, a lawyer for the Environmental Defense Fund, who was in Paris as an observer.</p>
        <p>''The communique contained an unprecedented expression of urgency and concern about the environment,'' said William K. Reilly, Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency. The meeting moved environmental concerns ''a long way from the periphery to the center of policy making,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In any case, it is a long way from the last Administration, when Ronald Reagan complained that environmentalists wanted to turn the White House into a bird's nest. President Bush not only joined the leaders of the industrial democracies in a meeting he knew would endorse strong measures to protect the global environment. In a step the optimists think is more than just symbolic, he also asked Mr. Reilly to come along.</p>
        <p>So now what? Advocates for vigorous action to protect the environment plan to keep up the momentum. About a third of the final communique from Paris was devoted to international environmental concerns. It spoke of the need to take decisive action, including an international treaty to deal with the global warming that many have said will result from the trapping of industrial gases like carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>James Gustave Speth, president of the World Resources Institute, a research and policy group in Washington, said the United States and other industrial countries, having made strong promises to save the environment, must ''breathe life'' into those promises with concrete actions.</p>
        <p>But he warned, ''If we wait until we have 150 countries in agreement or even a large part of them, these problems will get genuinely intractable.'' The answer must start with unilateral action, Mr. Speth said, especially by the United States, which he called one of the world's great polluters and consumers of natural resources.</p>
        <p>He and others said the place to begin is with a national energy policy -one that reduces the reliance on coal and oil, which release carbon dioxide when burned, and emphasizes energy conservation and the use of renewable sources of energy like sun, wind and water power.</p>
        <p>The grave problems that threaten the global environment, the advocates said, must be faced not just by national governments but by industry, agriculture and the public. People all over the world, especially in countries like the United States that consume a great deal of energy and natural resources, must learn to live more lightly upon the earth - to be less wasteful in their use of energy and goods and services, and to reduce the pollutants they pour into the land, air and water.</p>
        <p>In many areas, people and communities are ahead of their national leaders. On Tuesday, for example, the City Council of Irvine, Calif., voted to ban the use of most chlorofluorocarbons, chemicals that have been implicated in the destruction of atmospheric ozone. Around the country, a number of other communities and even some industries have been taking actions to meet threats to the global environment.</p>
        <p>But many still insist that the Government in Washington must lead the way.</p>
        <p>''There is no way that the United States can exercise moral authority in leading the world on these issues,'' Senator Gore said, ''without taking action ourselves to reduce greenhouse gas emissions.''  WASHINGTON TALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
