<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ACID RAIN MEASURE WOULD DIVIDE COST</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="297281"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SULFUR DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FACTORIES AND INDUSTRIAL PLANTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DINGELL, JOHN D (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DD123EF930A35752C1A96F948260" item-length="465" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ACID RAIN MEASURE WOULD DIVIDE COST</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To break a deadlock that has stalled action on the Bush Administration's clean air bill, the chairman of the House Energy Committee today proposed a new way to finance the multibillion-dollar cleanup of the pollution that causes acid rain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To break a deadlock that has stalled action on the Bush Administration's clean air bill, the chairman of the House Energy Committee today proposed a new way to finance the multibillion-dollar cleanup of the pollution that causes acid rain.</p>
        <p>To break a deadlock that has stalled action on the Bush Administration's clean air bill, the chairman of the House Energy Committee today proposed a new way to finance the multibillion-dollar cleanup of the pollution that causes acid rain.</p>
        <p>The proposal, by John D. Dingell, Democrat of Michigan, would impose a fee on utilities and other industries that produce more than 100 tons of sulfur dioxide a year. The emissions fee would go toward the cleanup costs of the heaviest polluters, which are concentrated in the Midwest.</p>
        <p>Lawmakers from the Midwest have threatened to block further consideration of President Bush's clean air bill unless utilities in their region are given some relief from the cleanup costs. They want the rest of the country to share the burden, which would probably result in higher electricity charges for customers.</p>
        <p>The Administration, which has pledged not to impose any new taxes, has firmly resisted such proposals, saying that they would be a tax in disguise and that the polluters should pay the costs themselves. 'Good-Faith Effort'</p>
        <p>Sulfur dioxide, which is the chief component of acid rain, is now emitted at the rate of 20 million tons a year. By the year 2000, the President's proposal would require utilities to cut their emissions a total of 10 million tons of a year. Mr. Dingell said his proposal would retain that requirement.</p>
        <p>There was no immediate comment from the Administration on the proposal. A spokesman for Representative Philip R. Sharp, the Indiana Democrat who is chairman of the Energy and Power Subcommittee of Mr. Dingell's panel, said Mr. Sharp was studying the proposal and added that it was a ''good-faith effort to bring the two sides together.''</p>
        <p>In a letter to committee members, Mr. Dingell said he had offered the proposal because he was concerned about the increasing acrimony on the panel over acid rain, an issue that has divided Congress and the nation for years. He added that he hoped to avoid ''public bloodletting'' that ''has the potential to turn close friends into lasting enemies and divide this committee on many issues for years to come.''</p>
        <p>But Henry A. Waxman, a California Democrat who is an influential committee member, called the proposal a ''non-starter.'' Disputing Congressman Dingell, he said some provisions would allow far more pollution than the President's bill would. And he said the cost-sharing arrangement means that utilities that are relatively clean would have to pay for the cleanup of their dirtier Middle Western counterparts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Waxman, who has fought with Mr. Dingell over air pollution issues for many years, said it was curious that Mr. Dingell, a leading sponsor of the President's clean air bill, would propose a measure so different from the Administration's position.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
