<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Rabbit's Tale: Bugs's 50 Years in Show Business</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="270937"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMATED FILMS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WARNER BROTHERS INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">COLLINS, GLENN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JONES, CHUCK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Studios</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Studios/Warner Brothers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animated Films</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D61E3EF932A05754C0A96F948260" item-length="1058" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Rabbit's Tale: Bugs's 50 Years in Show Business</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GLENN COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COLLINS, GLENN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: His regrets? None, save for the carrots of yesteryear. His health? Superb (''supoib'' was what he actually said). His attitude toward that harebrained upstart, Roger Rabbit? Paternal (''patoinal,'' as he put it). In fact, for a show-business legend preparing for his 50th-birthday celebration, that wascally wabbit Bugs</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: His regrets? None, save for the carrots of yesteryear. His health? Superb (''supoib'' was what he actually said). His attitude toward that harebrained upstart, Roger Rabbit? Paternal (''patoinal,'' as he put it). In fact, for a show-business legend preparing for his 50th-birthday celebration, that wascally wabbit Bugs</p>
        <p>His regrets? None, save for the carrots of yesteryear. His health? Superb (''supoib'' was what he actually said). His attitude toward that harebrained upstart, Roger Rabbit? Paternal (''patoinal,'' as he put it). In fact, for a show-business legend preparing for his 50th-birthday celebration, that wascally wabbit Bugs Bunny is surprisingly sanguine about his life in the summer of 1989.</p>
        <p>''Kiddo, Cary Grant said it foist an' said it best: 'I don't look young, I look good for my age!' '' Mr. Bunny recently said to his lifelong friend and mentor, Chuck Jones. The 76-year-old animator directed more than 50 Bugs Bunny cartoons among the 300 he made during the glory years of Warner Brothers animation.</p>
        <p>Following custom, Mr. Bunny declined to speak directly for publication. But the star of more than 160 cartoons agreed to answer questions through Mr. Jones, who also created the first features starring Road Runner, Wile E. Coyote and Pepe LePew. And Now They're in Museums</p>
        <p>A pall was cast over the planning sessions at Warner Brothers for this fall's 50th-birthday celebrations when word came of the death of Mel Blanc, the vocal artist who worked on all of Bugs Bunny's films. Mr. Bunny had planned to work quite closely with Mr. Blanc during the festivities. ''It just ain't fair that Mel will miss my 50th,'' a saddened Mr. Bunny told Mr. Jones. ''It hoits not just because I loved the guy. It's that I feel I've lost a part 'a myself.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jones said that ''Bugs never anticipated such a fuss in the first place'' over the birthday plans. ''Bugs had no concept that people would celebrate his 50th, because he never thought his pictures would last,'' he added. ''I didn't. Mel didn't. Bugs didn't. All of us thought they'd just go into a vault. But now they're even shown in museums.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the Bugs Bunny screenings were sold out when the Museum of Modern Art honored the art of Warner Brothers animation in 1985. So popular is the wise-cracking rabbit that he has not been absent from television for one day in more than 30 years; the Bugs Bunny cartoon half-hour is the longest consecutively running and highest rated network animated series in television history, the A. C. Nielsen Company has said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jones, who lives in Corona del Mar, Calif., and speaks of Bugs Bunny with great affection, offered a revealing portrait of the celebrity cottontail as he approaches the half-century mark. ''Bugs said that aside from Harvey and the Easter Bunny, there aren't all that many distinguished rabbits, so he's gratified by all the birthday noise,'' Mr. Jones said. What a Schedule!  Noise indeed: Warner Brothers plans to stage several black-tie Bugs Bunny birthday parties; a prime-time network television special is in the works, and movie, television-syndication and book tie-ins are planned.</p>
        <p>Ushering in the season of festivities is to be the unveiling of a Bugs Bunny balloon at the Macy's Thanksgiving Day parade. ''Bugs has never been the type to be full of hot air,'' Mr. Jones said, ''but he likes the balloon idea well enough. It's just hard for him to hold still very long for the modeling sessions.''</p>
        <p>In addition, there are to be millions of items bearing the buck-toothed bunny's 50th anniversary logo, among them T-shirts, watches, plush toys, mugs and music boxes. What does he think of the logo, an update of his famed rabbit-in-the-bull's-eye trademark?</p>
        <p>''Ya can quote me: It's woise than askin' Miss Liberty whedda she likes the Statue a' Liberty,'' Mr. Bunny told Mr. Jones.</p>
        <p>The legendary long ear's off-screen life is low in profile but far from reclusive. ''Bugs is often seen in Malibu and Beverly Hills,'' Mr. Jones said, ''but he's a peripatetic kind of guy who feels at home wherever he is.''</p>
        <p>His health is so good ''that he still does all his own stunt work,'' Mr. Jones said of the rabbit's continuing employment in television and feature films. ''He does it because it's fun, and, like Burt Lancaster, he doesn't want his public to think that he's faking it,'' he explained. Acid Rain and a Favorite Crop</p>
        <p>Like many in Hollywood, Mr. Bunny works tirelessly for the cause of animal rights, ''and is especially concerned about the effect of acid rain on carrots,'' Mr. Jones said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bunny has long since forgiven Daffy Duck for taking a role in ''Who Framed Roger Rabbit?'' but feels his longtime co-star was badly miscast. Mr. Jones, who also directed Mr. Duck in dozens of cartoons, sums it up this way: ''Bugs feels they forced Daffy into the role, and Daffy got short shrift in the movie. But Daffy deserves long shrift.''</p>
        <p>Clearly, Mr. Bunny and Daffy Duck are still friends, ''though they still do battle over whether it's rabbit season or duck season,'' Mr. Jones said. ''I think they're as close to being friends as an intellectual and a dunce can be,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Often the two movie veterans work out lines, gags and stunts together, and - utterly informally - the duo recently collaborated on a 50th-birthday vaudeville sketch. Though neither superstar has ever posed for pictures, both agreed to hold still long enough for Mr. Jones to sketch them during a recent impromptu rehearsal at the Warner Brothers studio. (The drawings accompany this piece.) When Bugs Became Bugs Mr. Jones has been sketching the carrot-munching hare for half a century. ''I've known Bugs since 1939,'' continued Mr. Jones, who directed the rabbit that year in two of his earliest cartoons. This was only a year after Mr. Bunny's 1938 appearance as a bit player in ''Porky's Hare Hunt,'' which some cite as his cartoon debut.</p>
        <p>Why, then, will Bugs Bunny's 50th birthday be celebrated in 1990?</p>
        <p>''Bugs feels he wasn't really himself, and those of us who worked with him agree,'' Mr. Jones said of the primitive rabbit character that appeared in the early cartoons. ''He was truly Bugs for the first time in 'A Wild Hare' in 1940,'' Mr. Jones said, ''when he had the true Bugs Bunny insouciance.</p>
        <p>''That was directed by Tex Avery, who first got Bugs to say 'Eeee-ya, what's up, doc?' '' The phrase's variants, in assorted cartoons, have included ''What's up, Duke?'' ''What's up, duck?'' and ''What's up, Zsa Zsa?''</p>
        <p>Did Mr. Bunny say anything else of interest? ''Bugs,'' answered Mr. Jones, ''had a statement for the end of the interview. You can quote him as saying, 'That's all folks!' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
