<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bottom-Line Thinking Won't Save Our Climate</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="305240"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDF123EF933A05752C1A96F948260" item-length="446" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bottom-Line Thinking Won't Save Our Climate</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your Economic Watch article on the costs of limiting the emissions of carbon dioxide (front page, Nov. 19) raises troublesome issues. The extent to which society chooses to spend money slowing greenhouse gas emissions or adapting to inevitable climatic impacts does depend partly on the costs and benefits of the different actions. But traditional cost-benefit studies, such as the ones you cite, are an unsatisfactory basis for guiding such decisions.</p>
        <p>The true costs to society of global climatic changes are unknown, and they are unlikely ever to be accurately determined. We are not likely to know the full range of global consequences until climatic changes are upon us because of the difficulties of accurately modeling the climate. More important, many of the probable effects, such as the extinction of species, the loss of natural ecosystems and long-term human health effects, simply cannot be put into classic economic terms. Even calculating the costs to society of the more obvious effects, such as a rise in sea level, is fraught with computational pitfalls, methodological complications and controversial assumptions. Economic analysis simply ignores these issues, leading to the fallacy that what can be most easily counted is what really counts.</p>
        <p>Equally disturbing, however, the costs of climatic impacts and the costs of reducing emissions will be unequally distributed. Many of the worst impacts of climatic change are likely to fall on poorer, developing countries without the resources to adapt to the changes. But the costs of prevention will fall on the industrialized countries responsible for the vast majority of the emissions. Thus the richer countries responsible for the problem may prefer to delay action on limiting emissions, while poor countries that cannot build sea walls or develop irrigation systems to save their agricultural production will be forced to suffer the consequences.</p>
        <p>Finally, many studies suggest that some actions to slow the rate of climate change are economical and could be taken today, such as improving our energy efficiency to the level of Japan's, or eliminating chlorofluorocarbons that contribute to the destruction of the ozone layer and to the greenhouse effect. Such actions should be considered prudent and inexpensive, preferable to taking no action and suffering the consequences. Waiting until imperfect traditional cost-benefit studies are done means waiting until climatic changes are upon us. PETER H. GLEICK  Berkeley, Calif., Nov. 19, 1989  The writer directs the global environment program of the Pacific Institute for Studies in Development, Environment and Security.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
