<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. and Japan Executives Exchange Barbs on Trade</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="284331"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLUSHA, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DE103FF93AA2575AC0A96F948260" item-length="565" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. and Japan Executives Exchange Barbs on Trade</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN HOLUSHA, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLUSHA, JOHN</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Sept. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Tensions over the trade imbalance between the United States and Japan today produced some unusually blunt exchanges between chief executives gathered here for a conference on the outlook for manufacturing industries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Tensions over the trade imbalance between the United States and Japan today produced some unusually blunt exchanges between chief executives gathered here for a conference on the outlook for manufacturing industries.</p>
        <p>Tensions over the trade imbalance between the United States and Japan today produced some unusually blunt exchanges between chief executives gathered here for a conference on the outlook for manufacturing industries.</p>
        <p>Akio Morita, the co-founder and chairman of the Sony Corporation, said 50 percent of American imports from Japan were now high-technology machinery and devices like microchips. ''The fact that the United States is losing its competitiveness in so many areas of high-tech manufacturing suggests that something is fundamentally amiss in American industry,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Mr. Morita said that because of the emphasis by Americans on short-term financial results, American manufacturers had not made investments that would pay off in the long term. But a top American executive chastised Japanese industry, and Mr. Morita directly, for what he said was Japan's resistance to imports.</p>
        <p>''The fact is that Japan remains a virtually impenetrable market for many foreign businesses,'' said Edward L. Hennessy Jr., the chairman of Allied-Signal Inc. Referring to a new book, ''The Japan That Can Say No,'' by Mr. Morita and Shintaro Ishihara, a Liberal Democratic Party politician who was a candidate for Prime Minister in August, Mr. Hennessy added, ''Instead of a Japan that can say 'no,' all of us need a Japan that can say 'yes' to open markets.''</p>
        <p>In the book, the authors suggested that Japan could use the United States' dependence on it for high-technology components as leverage in trade disputes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Morita and Mr. Hennessy spoke at the International Industrial Conference, a meeting held every four years to assess the outlook for manufacturing industries. It is sponsored by the Conference Board, a business research group, and SRI International, a research and consulting organization.</p>
        <p>According to the organizers, it is being attended by executives and Government officials from 31 countries, including the Soviet Union and Hungary.</p>
        <p>Judging from questions posed to a panel of experts, the major concerns of executives here appear to be: increasingly stringent environmental standards, the development of trade blocs and changing social patterns.</p>
        <p>''Burdens on companies will change in the 1990's,'' said Tore Browaldh, a Swedish banker who is the honorary chairman of Svenska Handelsbanken. ''There will be a shift from economic growth to care of the environment, health and safety for workers and women's rights.''</p>
        <p>The participants agreed that environmental issues would become an increasingly contentious issue between industrialized countries and those just beginning their economic development. Saburo Okita, a former Japanese Foreign Minister, said, ''Developing countries are not signing the Montreal Protocol,'' which seeks to reduce the use of chemicals known as chlorofluorocarbons, which damage the earth's ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Newly developing countries, he added, felt industrialized nations could afford to use less efficient substances, while they could not until they were economically advanced.</p>
        <p>Mr. Okita also said Asian nations were increasing their cooperative efforts in response to the United States-Canadian trade treaty and the European Community's plans for economic integration after 1992. But he added that he doubted that a unified trade bloc would emerge in Asia, where countries were less alike socially and economically than in Europe.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
