<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Global Warming Means New Global Politics</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="300168"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="IDEAS &amp; TRENDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NETHERLANDS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE, WEST</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D91438F931A25752C1A96F948260" item-length="815" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Global Warming Means New Global Politics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: UNTIL recently, politicians who wanted to avoid the issue of global warming could duck behind the scientific uncertainties. Now, with soaring public concern for the environment and wide scientific agreement about the nature if not the timing of the problem, the debate has shifted. The question is no longer whether the threat is real, but rather how fast it needs to be countered and at what expense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: UNTIL recently, politicians who wanted to avoid the issue of global warming could duck behind the scientific uncertainties. Now, with soaring public concern for the environment and wide scientific agreement about the nature if not the timing of the problem, the debate has shifted. The question is no longer whether the threat is real, but rather how fast it needs to be countered and at what expense.</p>
        <p>UNTIL recently, politicians who wanted to avoid the issue of global warming could duck behind the scientific uncertainties. Now, with soaring public concern for the environment and wide scientific agreement about the nature if not the timing of the problem, the debate has shifted. The question is no longer whether the threat is real, but rather how fast it needs to be countered and at what expense.</p>
        <p>As discussion moves from the scientific to the political, the world has split into several factions. Some nations like the United States and Japan are also fighting internal political battles.</p>
        <p>Last week environmental ministers from 68 countries met in the Netherlands and agreed in principle to stabilize emissions of carbon dioxide, the main contributor to the so-called greenhouse effect. But bowing to pressure from the United States, the conference avoided any specific timetable.</p>
        <p>Much of the carbon dioxide buildup is caused by the burning of coal and oil in power plants and gasoline in automobiles. Other sources include the burning of tropical rain forests. Cutting back carbon dioxide emissions could require big advances in energy conservation, large investment in renewable fuel sources like solar energy and greatly increased automobile fuel economy.</p>
        <p>Deciding to pay the price of prevention is doubly painful because no one can prove just when pollution-induced warming and weather disruptions will begin, if they have not already. Experts warn that if the world waits for incontrovertible evidence of major climate change, it will be far too late to do much about it.</p>
        <p>The debate has split the world into three camps. Several industrialized European nations support strong measures to stabilize or reduce the emissions. Third world countries like China and India argue that since they are not responsible for much of the problem they should get financial aid in return for cooperating in measures that could hamper desperately needed economic growth. Three major industrial powers, the United States, Japan and the Soviet Union, advocate more cautious approaches.</p>
        <p>In October, the United States led a United Nations-sponsored working group in Geneva to discuss an agreement on global warming. American representatives said they came away from the sessions surprised by the extent of support for faster action to stabilize carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>The tone of the Geneva meeting anticipated what would occur in the Netherlands. In the conference declaration, the participants agreed that stabilization of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases should be achieved ''as soon as possible.'' Several European nations, led by the Netherlands, had pressed for a commitment to stabilize the emissions by the year 2000 at 1988 levels, and for a 20 percent reduction by 2005.</p>
        <p>The Administration favors more study of the impact of carbon dioxide emissions on the climate and wants to pursue the issue more slowly through the United Nations. That approach received support this week from Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher of Britain, who called on the United Nations to complete a global warming treaty by 1992.</p>
        <p>Not everyone in the Administration supports the deliberate approach. William K. Reilly, the head of the Environmental Protection Agency, is known to have favored a more aggressive posture at the Netherlands conference, but was rebuffed by other Administration officials. A similar internal struggle is apparently under way in Japan, said Richard Mott, a representative of the Environmental Law Institute, a Washington group that closely monitors climate change issues. As in the United States, the forces in Japan that backed a slower approach won the day at the Netherlands conference.</p>
        <p>The White House would prefer a general accord at first, followed later by specific commitments. But William Nitze, the State Department official responsible for coordinating Government policy on global warming, suggested at a conference last month that the United States may be unable to resist a commitment to stabilize carbon dioxide emissions if a world agreement is negotiated in the next few years.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, the President has been sharply criticized by environmental groups and members of Congress from both parties for resisting more aggressive action. The critics warned of dire environmental consequences if the United States, which contributes a fifth of the world's emissions of carbon dioxide, failed to take the lead in dealing with the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>''It may be logical to say that we need more information about the consequences of accepting a plan to freeze emissions of carbon dioxide at current levels,'' said Senator John Heinz, Republican of Pennsylvania. But on the other hand, he said, ''It is illogical not to weigh the consequences of indecision and inaction on the global environment and our own well-being here in the United States.''  IDEAS &amp; TRENDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
