<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.P.A. Acts to Stimulate Recycling</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="303791"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCINERATORS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DC133AF937A15752C1A96F948260" item-length="888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.P.A. Acts to Stimulate Recycling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In a far-reaching effort to stimulate recycling, the Environmental Protection Agency is proposing that incinerator operators around the country be required to reduce the amount of garbage they burn by 25 percent by recycling it instead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In a far-reaching effort to stimulate recycling, the Environmental Protection Agency is proposing that incinerator operators around the country be required to reduce the amount of garbage they burn by 25 percent by recycling it instead.</p>
        <p>In a far-reaching effort to stimulate recycling, the Environmental Protection Agency is proposing that incinerator operators around the country be required to reduce the amount of garbage they burn by 25 percent by recycling it instead.</p>
        <p>The agency views the plan as a way to cut emissions of toxic substances, lower the amount of ash that has to be put in landfills and promote its goal of reducing the nation's garbage by 25 percent by 1992.</p>
        <p>But the agency is under pressure to drop or modify the plan from the incinerator industry, which has a multibillion-dollar investment at stake, from municipal governments and from the Federal Office of Management and Budget.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists see the issue as a test of the Bush Administration's credibility on the environment and are hoping President Bush sides with the Environmental Protection Agency. Many Are Publicly Owned</p>
        <p>The country now has 50 incinerators and 122 plants that burn waste and produce electricity as a byproduct, according to the National Solid Wastes Management Association, a Washington-based trade group. About two-thirds of the waste-to-energy plants and incinerators are publicly owned.</p>
        <p>The association said 31 waste-to-energy plants are under construction and 74 are under contract to be built.</p>
        <p>Under the E.P.A. plan, incinerator operators would have to separate recyclable material like glass, metal, paper and plastic from refuse, either at the plant or through a community sorting program. The standard would also prohibit the burning of car batteries, which under combustion emit lead and sulfuric acid. The agency says sorting out these materials will result in fewer emissions of toxic substances like lead, cadmium and mercury and gases that contribute to acid rain.</p>
        <p>Opponents of the E.P.A. plan assert that such a rule would discourage investment in new incinerators because operators would not want to be responsible for a function they think should be directed by municipalities. If the incinerators are not built, the critics say, more waste will end up in landfills even as capacity is shrinking and the nation is trying to lessen its reliance on them. Looking to Local Government</p>
        <p>''The logical party that ought to be held responsible for recycling is the local government,'' said Allen Moore, a spokesman for the National Solid Wastes Management Association.</p>
        <p>The opponents also say that they support increased recycling but that such a major initiative should be undertaken through Federal legislation, not regulation.</p>
        <p>The agency's recycling plan is part of a broader regulation on incinerator emissions that must be made public by Nov. 30 and would be made final a year later.</p>
        <p>The date is set by court order, as a result of legal action brought in the Federal court several years ago by the State of New York and the Natural Resources Defense Council. The action forced the E.P.A. to regulate incinerator emissions like sulfur dioxide and dioxin.</p>
        <p>The proposed regulation was made public in early October, when it was sent for review to the Office of Management and Budget. Neither the budget office nor the E.P.A. will comment about the split over recycling. Their differences were disclosed by representatives of the New York State Attorney General's office and the Natural Resources Defense Council, which strongly back the recyling provisions. Seeking an Extension</p>
        <p>The environmental agency is pressing to delay the deadline for release of the regulation for several months so it can address the criticism from the budget office and industry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moore says the group is working with the E.P.A. to draw up a recycling provision that would be less burdensome. The industry says not all communities can achieve a 25 percent recycling level in the near future.</p>
        <p>But David R. Wooley, an Assistant Attorney General for New York, says New York and the Natural Resorces Defense Council will not yield on the deadline. This is apparently a strategy aimed at forcing the environmental agency to go forward with the recycling plan or risk embarrassment at having backed down.</p>
        <p>A major concern in the industry is that the Government would shut down an incinerator if it failed to carry out the 25 percent mandate. This has caused anxiety among potential investors, who see added financial risk in such a situation. No Room at the Landfills</p>
        <p>The incinerators are one way to deal with diminished landfill capacity. The E.P.A. estimates that 80 percent of existing landfills will close in 20 years. Still, many communities have fought incinerators because of their emissions.</p>
        <p>The budget office supports more recycling, said an Administration official who spoke on condition of anonymity. But this official asserted that the environmental agency's proposal is misguided and will force more garbage into landfills.</p>
        <p>New York State and the Natural Resources Defense Council view the clash between the E.P.A. and the budget office as a test of the Administration's environmental credibility, and more specifically, whether the Office of Management and Budget will continue to block E.P.A. regulations, as it regularly did during the Reagan Administration.</p>
        <p>''If the President is to be taken at his word,'' said Robert Abrams, the New York Attorney General, ''then in this situation he has to overrule O.M.B.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
