<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Everybody Loves Solar Energy, But...</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business World Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="64" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Business; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="285681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOLAR ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">LUZ INTERNATIONAL LTD</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA EDISON CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEISS, MICHAEL J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DD1F3DF937A1575AC0A96F948260" item-length="3718" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Everybody Loves Solar Energy, But...</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michael J. Weiss; Michael J. Weiss, a writer based in Washington, is the author of ''The Clustering of America.''</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEISS, MICHAEL J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ON A SUMMER MORNING, just before dawn, the sky turns a coppery gold above the Mojave Desert, a 15,000-square-mile expanse of sand and sagebrush in southern California. In the handful of communities clinging to the two-lane highways crisscrossing the desert, nothing breaks the quiet except for the occasional trucker pulling over at a dusty drive-in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ON A SUMMER MORNING, just before dawn, the sky turns a coppery gold above the Mojave Desert, a 15,000-square-mile expanse of sand and sagebrush in southern California. In the handful of communities clinging to the two-lane highways crisscrossing the desert, nothing breaks the quiet except for the occasional trucker pulling over at a dusty drive-in.</p>
        <p>ON A SUMMER MORNING, just before dawn, the sky turns a coppery gold above the Mojave Desert, a 15,000-square-mile expanse of sand and sagebrush in southern California. In the handful of communities clinging to the two-lane highways crisscrossing the desert, nothing breaks the quiet except for the occasional trucker pulling over at a dusty drive-in.</p>
        <p>But at Kramer Junction, 150 miles from Los Angeles, the landscape awakens abruptly. As the first rays of light stretch across the arid plain, 600,000 curved glass mirrors flip over to face the sun. Within moments, the synthetic oil flowing through tubes suspended over the shimmering mirrors reaches 735 degrees Fahrenheit, the heat transforms water to steam and generators are producing 194 megawatts of electricity for Southern California (SoCal) Edison - enough power to serve 270,000 residential customers. So begins another day for Luz International Ltd., whose solar fields generate an estimated 90 percent of the world's solar power.</p>
        <p>Luz (rhymes with ''fuse'') has built seven solar electric-generating systems, known as SEGS. While Luz's plants generate only 1 percent of SoCal Edison's power, they provide that electricity when it is most needed: during the hottest part of the day, when air-conditioning demand reaches its peak.</p>
        <p>Since its first SEGS went on line in 1984, Luz's cost for producing a kilowatt hour of electricity has dropped from 24 cents to 12 cents - less than the cost of energy from the newest nuclear plants now in operation. Last April, the company broke ground on a $1.2 billion expansion that is expected to triple Luz's electricity output while dropping the cost to about 8 cents per kilowatt hour, nearly competitive with conventional coal- and oil-fueled plants.</p>
        <p>More than a decade after the Arab oil embargo convinced Americans of the need for alternative sources of energy, cost-competitive solar power is finally reaching the marketplace. And not a moment too soon. Acid rain, global warming and this year's plague of oil spills emphasize the dangers of relying on coal- and oil-fueled power plants. In the South Coast Basin, which includes Los Angeles, the ground-level cloud of ozone has become so hazardous that state officials have passed a plan to restrict everything from chemical factories to gas-powered lawn mowers to charcoal lighter fluid.</p>
        <p>Yet a cloud also hangs over the future of Luz. The growth of the company -which had revenues of $153 million last year, mostly from the construction and sale of solar plants - has been made possible in large part by an array of Federal and state tax incentives and favorable government regulations. Now the last of the tax breaks is scheduled to run out in December. Given the current, relatively low prices of oil and natural gas, which together in 1988 generated 44 percent of California's electricity, it remains to be seen whether utilities and investors will continue to smile upon Luz.</p>
        <p>In 1977, announcing his determination to break the nation's dependence on imported oil, President Carter called for a 20 percent reliance on renewable energy resources by the year 2000. He called it ''the moral equivalent of war.'' His Administration initiated a 40 percent residential energy conservation tax credit and a 15 percent commercial tax credit for renewable energy projects. In a symbolic gesture, Carter even installed solar hot-water panels atop the White House.</p>
        <p>The following year, Congress passed the landmark Public Utility Regulatory Policies Act (PURPA), which required utilities to provide a market for qualifying independent producers of electricity. The measure dictated that utilities must buy energy from these producers at a reasonable rate based on ''avoided costs'' - the amount of money the utility would otherwise pay to increase production using fuels such as natural gas or oil and building traditional plants. Independent solar producers were to be exempt from local public utility commission rate regulations as long as they met certain qualifications; plants, for example, could be no more than 30 megawatts in size.</p>
        <p>The result of these benevolent policies was a market free-for-all. Solar panels were manufactured for the small-scale heating of water in homes and factories. Companies began producing photovoltaic cells - which convert sunlight directly into electricity by means of silicon wafers - for everything from hand-held calculators to wristwatches. And solar-thermal plants were designed to produce electricity for businesses and utilities.</p>
        <p>But the fledgling industry also produced its share of lemons. Large corporations, taking advantage of new Government research funds, produced demonstration pro-jects that ultimately proved unsuccessful. ''A lot of Fortune 500 companies built dishes and windmills that were 10 times larger than the market could bear,'' says Scott Sklar, the executive director of the Solar Energy Industries Association. ''All over the country, they left these idols, these statues of great ideas, that wasted a lot of money.'' IN MORE WAYS THAN one, Luz was an exception. Founded by Arnold Goldman, a 46-year-old, bearded and cerebral electrical engineer, it began life without Government research and development funds, and its research base was in Israel. Raised in Providence, R.I., and the recipient of a master's degree from the University of Southern California, Goldman went to work at Litton Industries in 1967. Two years later, he left to help form Lexitron, which eventually produced one of the first word processors.</p>
        <p>In 1977, Raytheon acquired Lexitron, and Goldman dropped out to write a book with a modest topic: the meaning of life. For years, he had been filling notebooks with his thoughts on ''holism,'' which he defines as ''the quest to make everyday life holy.'' With more than a million dollars in proceeds from the sale of his company and Los Angeles home, Goldman moved his family to Israel to finish his work in progress.</p>
        <p>Goldman titled his book ''A Working Paper on Project Luz,'' taking the name Luz from the site in the Bible where Jacob dreamed that angels traveled between heaven and earth. In 1979, Goldman founded a company he called Independent Household Products. ''I envisioned the company starting cities which would be energized by solar projects,'' he explains by telephone from his home in Jerusalem. But he soon dropped the idea for lack of converts. ''It was too bold and too broad to explain to people,'' he says. Scaling down his ambitions, he changed his company's name to Luz International, and set about formulating a business plan for the manufacture of solar-power plants.</p>
        <p>Then Goldman met Patrick Francois, a soft-spoken Frenchman, now 46, with a remarkable resemblance to the actor Robert Vaughn. Francois, who had operated a textile-manufacturing company in Paris, had moved to Israel in 1970 and launched an apparel-manufacturing company, Magoo Ltd. He eventually built it into a $3 million enterprise, employing up to 150 workers. In 1979, he sold out to become a consultant, advising foreigners on investments in Israel.</p>
        <p>Francois at first regarded Goldman as ''a kind of mad scientist,'' he says. ''He started telling me about these hundreds of millions of dollars that we could make selling solar electricity, and my first reaction was, 'Is this guy crazy?' '' But, after reviewing Goldman's business plan, Francois asked to join the company.</p>
        <p>Goldman and Francois each put up $100,000, and they raised $950,000 for the first round of equity in the company, much of it from people who had backed Lexitron. Although both founders held Israeli citizenship, and their manufacturing and research operations were based in Jerusalem, in 1979 they incorporated Luz in California, partly because of the receptive regulatory environment but also because of their concern about possible anti-Israeli sentiment. ''Some investors are worried about tax issues and currency flow,'' Goldman explains. ''Others are just sensitive to the Arab boycott.''</p>
        <p>At first, Goldman and Francois targeted small American companies such as textile mills that required steam for manufacturing. But most potential customers didn't want to take the risk. ''The market just wasn't there,'' Goldman says. ''We had some very tough times.'' Between 1979 and 1983, Luz racked up losses of $13.5 million, a skid that took a serious toll on Goldman. At age 39, he suffered a heart attack.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the price of domestic oil had jumped from almost $13 a barrel to over $26, making solar power far more attractive to utilities. Goldman and Francois decided to shift gears. In 1983, they landed Southern California Edison.</p>
        <p>Luz received a 30-year contract, under which the price paid for power from its SEGS I was guaranteed for a decade. SoCal Edison also granted the company a long-term lease on property in Daggett, Calif. Luz would manufacture most of the necessary equipment in Israel, find limited partners to invest in building the plant and handle construction. In return for operating the finished facility, the company would receive 1 percent of revenues.</p>
        <p>Goldman and Francois were soon splitting their time between Israel, where they were manufacturing Luz's solar designs, and California, where they were looking for potential investors. Luz would hold less than 1 percent equity. They needed $62 million to build SEGS I. Since the plant would be producing power at a cost of 24 cents a kilowatt, and SoCal Edison was obligated to buy it for considerably less (payments for the first five years have averaged 13.9 cents a kilowatt hour), they could hardly ballyhoo profitability. What they had to sell were tax breaks.</p>
        <p>In 1983, the Federal Government was offering SEGS backers 25 percent investment and energy tax credits. The state of California allowed a 13.5 percent energy tax credit. Francois explained that because of these credits, which could be written off against income in the first year, and because of accelerated depreciation that could be spread over five years, SEGS I investors could expect a 15 percent annual return on every dollar invested. ''Investors had potential risks if the system did not perform reasonably well,'' says Paul Salvodelli, Luz's assistant general counsel. ''Which is the difference between having a valid tax shelter as opposed to a nonvalid tax shelter.''</p>
        <p>But Francois faced skeptical audiences. ''We had a hell of a time convincing people that, in spite of being solar, it was legitimate,'' he says. To reduce the investors' risk, Luz guaranteed the output of the plant for 10 years.</p>
        <p>Francois also emphasized the simplicity of the technology chosen for the Luz plant. Basically, the system used a conventional steam turbine attached to solar reflectors whose reliability had been demonstrated at the Sandia National Laboratories in Albuquerque, N.M. Luz's technological twist was its design of the synthetic-oil-filled heat-collection pipes and the computer controls that tilted the mirrors according to the sun's east-west arc. To ensure power at night and on cloudy days, Luz included a natural-gas-fueled heater that, under Federal regulations, could provide up to 25 percent of the plant's daily output. ''It wasn't the fanciest technology,'' says Goldman, ''but it was the quickest and cheapest that would bring solar power to market.''</p>
        <p>In 1984, Luz opened SEGS I, a 13.8-megawatt facility. When the second plant started up a year later, it turned out 30 megawatts at 17 cents a kilowatt hour, which SoCal Edison bought for an average of 7 cents a kilowatt hour. The utility tracts for another five plants. ''Unlike some other producers, they were savvy in the business environment,'' says Pamela Easterwood, the utility's qualifying-facility development manager. ''They succeeded because they were small, innovative and aggressive.''</p>
        <p>WITH EACH NEW PROJECT, Luz managed to pare down its costs. Improved technology helped. The reflectors have been increased in size, and Goldman has designed new ceramic coatings for the pipes and more accurate computer-control systems. Two years ago, to realize economies of scale, Luz lobbied successfully for a change in the 30-megawatt limit under the Public Utility Regulatory Policies Act. SEGS VIII, scheduled for completion by December, is an 80-megawatt solar plant.</p>
        <p>The improved efficiency of the Luz plants has helped Francois raise $750 million from investors. To date, backers have included insurance companies such as Prudential and Metropolitan Life as well as utilities like Baltimore Gas and Electric and Iowa-Illinois Gas and Electric. Lured by Luz's track record and the tax breaks, Potomac Capital Investment, a venture-capital subsidiary of Potomac Electric, organized a consortium of utilities to invest in five SEGS projects in 1986. P.C.I. put in $63 million of its own money. ''Those investment credits had a big impact on our economic analysis,'' says a vice president at P.C.I., John McConomy.</p>
        <p>But the credits have been under siege. California's tax incentives ended in 1988. The Federal investment tax credit ended the same year. The Federal energy tax credit, scheduled to end in 1988, has been extended, but not without opposition. In another sign of the times, the solar panels on top of the White House vanished during the Reagan Administration. ''The Reagan ideologues viewed solar as a granola experience for a lot of crazy liberals,'' says Scott Sklar, the industry lobbyist. ''They seemed to lump together communism and solar energy.''</p>
        <p>Today, says Ross Ain, a Luz lobbyist who is a former associate general counsel with the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, ''The budget is tighter and tighter and most legislators have other priorities.''</p>
        <p>The remaining 10 percent Federal energy tax credit is due to expire on Dec. 31, but Congress is considering a bill that would extend it for five years. Many legislators, however, see the measure as an unnecessary tax break for Luz's power-plant investors. ''I don't know why we have to be loading up a lot of tax benefits for otherwise profitable operations,'' says Rep. Pete Stark (D-Calif.). To the argument that Luz produces clean, nonpolluting energy, Stark responds: ''So do squirrels running a treadmill. It's a question of how much you want to subsidize the squirrel-breeding industry.''</p>
        <p>The House has failed to extend the credit, but in the past the Senate has succeeded in keeping it. Senate supporters are once again hopeful. ''All in all, the chances for extension look good,'' says Senator Spark Matsunaga (D-Hawaii), the author of the bill. ''There is increasing support for solar energy because of environmental concerns.''</p>
        <p>In fact, President Bush has often expressed his devotion to nonpolluting renewable energy resources, but his position on the extension has yet to be disclosed. ''The jury is still out,'' says Matsunaga.</p>
        <p>On the other side of the continent, SoCal Edison has begun to look less lovingly at any new alternate energy producers like Luz. In the beginning, the utility had planned to sign on for 2,000 megawatts of power from renewables, but was forced by PURPA to contract for 6,000 megawatts of costly power. SoCal Edison today must pay about 8 cents per kilowatt hour for solar energy when it can purchase hydroelectric power for about 4 cents. ''Under PURPA, we can't say no,'' says SoCal Edison's Easterwood. ''We have to take the power, which is now more than we need, and for much more than we want to pay.'' In the utility's 1988 annual report, PURPA is described as a ''well-meaning public policy that turned out to be wrong.''</p>
        <p>As it now stands, 26 percent of the utility's power is produced from oil and natural gas, 21 percent from nuclear plants, 15 percent from coal and 16 percent from other utilities. The remainder comes from water (4 percent) and from other renewable sources (18 percent).</p>
        <p>SoCal Edison has offered Luz a different kind of contract to cover SEGS VIII and succeeding plants. Betting that the price of oil and natural gas will remain stable, or dip, the utility wants to peg what it pays Luz to current traditional fuel prices. That has discouraged some of Luz's backers, including P.C.I., which has shied away from investing in SEGS VIII.</p>
        <p>These days Goldman and Francois are selling SEGS plants as a hedge against a rise in oil prices. When he meets venture capitalists, Francois lays out several scenarios: With oil at the August price of $17.50 a barrel, investors in SEGS VIII could expect a return of about 13 percent; at $20, it would be in the 16 percent range. In fact, with oil at $20 or more, Francois insists, Luz's plants would be profitable with or without tax breaks. O N THE TOP FLOOR OF a glass and concrete office tower near the main campus of the University of California at Los Angeles, the scuffed walls at Luz's headquarters are bare but for the occasional SEGS photograph or surveyor's map of the Mojave Desert. In Francois's office, two Israeli trade awards hang; Luz's manufacturing plant is one of Israel's top 10 exporters.</p>
        <p>Luz International, the parent company, is directed by what staffers call ''the triumvirate,'' three leaders who are rarely together at any one time. Goldman spends much of the year with Luz's 400 employees in Jerusalem. Francois spends his days with 60 employees at the Los Angeles office, whose main occupation is raising money for future Luz plants.</p>
        <p>Last April, Luz named James Bazor as its chief operating officer and the man in charge of the construction division. The crusty, 55-year-old Bazor had been building SEGS projects for Montgomery, Ala.-based Blount Inc. He now labors in the Mojave Desert, overseeing a work force of 1,000 - including 250 technicians who operate the plants and another 60 permanent construction managers. Over the next few months, 200 more employees will be signed on as Luz rushes to complete primary construction on SEGS VIII to qualify for the remaining Federal tax credit.</p>
        <p>Luz International has recently benefited from an infusion of cash from C. P. National, a telecommunications company based in Walnut Creek, Calif. ''We knew utilities weren't going to build huge generating plants anymore because of the financial risks,'' says Michael Holmstrom, the company's president. ''And Luz was a perfect match because of its small modular plants that offered peak power when it was needed.'' C. P. National has put up $11 million to become a limited partner in SEGS projects, but it has also invested directly in Luz International. Last year, the firm added $11 million to its $6 million stake in Luz International, becoming the largest shareholder, with 38 percent of the outstanding stock.</p>
        <p>Luz International's profit picture has only recently begun to brighten. As opposed to the limited partners who bought into SEGS plants, shareholders in the parent company have watched it consistently lose money between 1979 and 1985. Last year the company reported a $5 million profit on $153 million in revenues; this year Luz expects to make about $5 million to $6 million on revenues of $250 million, mainly from the sale of the SEGS VIII plant. But the profit is to be plowed back into the company.</p>
        <p>Its prospects continue to be tied, in large measure, to the public concern about the environment. In California, those concerns have led to a dramatic reduction in the use of oil and natural gas for electricity from 81 percent in 1977 to less than half this year. ''We had a heroin-like dependence on fossil fuels,'' says Charles Imbrecht, the chairman of the California Energy Commission, ''and we've spent the last 10 years trying to kick the habit.''</p>
        <p>In fact, a new California Energy Commission rule, which will go into effect in 1990, adds an environmental price tag to the cost of power: among other things, the cost of pollution controls, of rehabilitating strip mines and of decommissioning nuclear facilities. ''Some energy resources have looked artificially better than solar,'' says Imbrecht. The commission is committed to fulfilling 10 percent of the state's needs with solar power by the year 2000. With an optimism born of experience, Luz is plunging ahead. The company recently broke ground on the first of five large-scale SEGS plants in Harper Lake, Calif., about 20 miles from Kramer Junction. Over the next five years, the company plans to spend $60 million on research and development projects, including a storage battery that will save daytime energy for use at night or on cloudy days and double-access tracking devices that will tilt the mirrors not only east and west, but also north and south, to follow the sun through the seasons.</p>
        <p>AT THE MOMENT, LUZ faces little competition.</p>
        <p>There are no other large-scale solar thermal plants anywhere. Photovoltaics are widely viewed as a promising form of solar energy, but photovoltaic power still costs about 30 cents per kilowatt hour and the largest photovoltaic plant is only 6.5 megawatts. Chronar Corp., of Princeton, N.J., has announced its intention to build a 50-megawatt photovoltaic plant north of Los Angeles, but no contract has yet been signed; it will produce power in the 10-to-12 cents per kilowatt hour range.</p>
        <p>Arnold Goldman says that the company's SEGS could one day produce hundreds of thousands of megawatts of solar power for the nation's utilities. He envisions much larger plants owned by utilities and thus not limited by PURPA's 80-megawatt restriction on independent producers. Nevada, Arizona and other Sunbelt states are his natural market in the United States since they possess the cloud-free days, dry air and low-cost land he needs. Solar plants still require four or five acres of land for every megawatt of power produced.</p>
        <p>Ironically, Luz has had difficulty selling its wares in Israel, whose climate and terrain appear ideal. ''The engineers at Israel Electric are like those at a lot of American utilities,'' says Goldman. ''They tend to be very conservative.''</p>
        <p>Patrick Francois sums up Luz's prospects in these terms: ''We'll have a nice business in the future if you believe that oil and gas are finite resources, if you believe that oil prices will return to $20 a barrel and if you believe that society still cares about getting the cleanest power possible.''</p>
        <p>But that's a lot of if's -even for a business built on sunshine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
