<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WASHINGTON TALK: ENVIRONMENT</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="246163"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REILLY, WILLIAM K (ADMR)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON TALK PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DB103EF931A35756C0A96F948260" item-length="652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WASHINGTON TALK: ENVIRONMENT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Philip Shabecoff, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush and his Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, William K. Reilly, have repeatedly proclaimed American readiness to assert leadership in cleaning up the world environmental mess. And many say the Administration has played the issues cannily, demonstrating a keen sense of damage control in its first major test, Alaska, where Mr.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush and his Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, William K. Reilly, have repeatedly proclaimed American readiness to assert leadership in cleaning up the world environmental mess. And many say the Administration has played the issues cannily, demonstrating a keen sense of damage control in its first major test, Alaska, where Mr.</p>
        <p>President Bush and his Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, William K. Reilly, have repeatedly proclaimed American readiness to assert leadership in cleaning up the world environmental mess. And many say the Administration has played the issues cannily, demonstrating a keen sense of damage control in its first major test, Alaska, where Mr. Bush abandoned his early defense of Exxon. But the United States call to lead a global march for environmental reform has led to challenges from Congress and other world leaders to clean its own house first.</p>
        <p>For instance, at a symposium on global warming conducted by the National Academy of Sciences last week, Dr. Peter Raven, the director of the Missouri Botanical Gardens, noted that the United States continues to cut the trees from its own temperate rain forest in southeast Alaska at a rapid rate while urging Brazil and other countries to slow the destruction of their tropical rain forests.</p>
        <p>It is not easy to be a leader in the solution when one is a leader in the problem. A few more specifics show the magnitude of the chore:</p>
        <p>* The United States each year produces five tons of carbon dioxide for every man, woman and child in the country. Carbon dioxide is the most significant of the gases building up in the atmosphere and accumulating heat from the sun to produce global warming. The next largest producer is the Soviet Union, with annual per capita emissions of three and a half tons. The world average is under one ton.</p>
        <p>* The United States continues to permit the export of agricultural chemicals banned in this country as dangerous to human health or the environment.</p>
        <p>* The United States continues to lead all industrial nations except Canada in the amount of energy used per unit of production of goods and services. Fuel consumption is the principal cause of air pollution and global warming.</p>
        <p>* The United States has the highest automobile density among large countries. Moreover, its auto fleets -one car for every 1.8 people - burn more gasoline per mile on average than those of other industrialized nations.</p>
        <p>* The United States accounts for nearly a third of all use of chlorofluorocarbons, the most important of the chemicals depleting the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>* The United States has not entered into an agreement sought by Canada to reduce the pollution that sends acid rain north of the border.</p>
        <p>* The United States has not ratified the Law of the Sea treaty governing use of the marine environment.</p>
        <p>* The United States is spending little to protect Hawaii's plants and animals. The 50th state has the highest number of endangered species for its size of any area in the world.</p>
        <p>* The United States, which gets most of its crude oil by tanker, did not develop the advanced technology needed to clean up marine oil spills, like the one that has devastated Alaska's coastline. The Soviet Union did. And so forth. ''It is time for the United States to reduce carbon dioxide emissions,'' 24 senators, nine of them Republicans, said in a letter to President Bush last month. ''Without a policy to reduce our own emissions our ability to convince others to act on the the greenhouse effect will be constrained.''</p>
        <p>The Soviet leader, Mikhail S. Gorbachev, has made repeated pronouncements about the need to act on issues like global warming. Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher of Britain has also been giving such issues repeated attention of late.</p>
        <p>But President Jose Sarney of Brazil has another view. In an angry reaction to American criticisms of development in the Amazon Basin earlier this year, he declared that industralized countries like the United States do the most harm to the global environment.</p>
        <p>''They discharge their wastes into the atmosphere damaging the ozone layer, and they still stockpile nuclear arms which can destroy humanity two or three times over,'' he said. ''They are the worst plunderers.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
