<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="219151"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7DC1F3CF932A05752C0A96F948260" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A2-12  A severe Nicaraguan austerity plan that cuts the national budget by almost half, was announced by President Ortega in an dramatic move to shore up the nation's rapidly deteriorating economy. Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A2-12  A severe Nicaraguan austerity plan that cuts the national budget by almost half, was announced by President Ortega in an dramatic move to shore up the nation's rapidly deteriorating economy. Page A1</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A2-12  A severe Nicaraguan austerity plan that cuts the national budget by almost half, was announced by President Ortega in an dramatic move to shore up the nation's rapidly deteriorating economy. Page A1</p>
        <p>A call to combat global warming through international political action was made by Secretary of State Baker as he spoke to a 17-nation ''working group'' formed to prepare environmental policy responses. C7</p>
        <p>Rival groups of Afghan guerrillas in a provincial capital have installed themselves as separate authorities. The contest that could damage a rebel alliance group's plans to set up national administration. A1</p>
        <p>U.S. closes Kabul offices but a storm prevents exit A12</p>
        <p>Details of Warsaw Pact troops and weapons in Europe were published for the first time in an effort to show that the East and West are about evenly matched in overall military strength. A6</p>
        <p>Gorbachev plans a visit to Bonn A6</p>
        <p>Large amounts of poison chemicals were shipped to Jordan by American and foreign businessmen, Federal officials said, broadening an inquiry into illegal shipments to the Middle East. A3</p>
        <p>A far-right gain in West Berlin sent shock waves across West Germany. About 10,000 protesters demonstrated against the unexpected success, in which the rightists captured 11 seats in the city's parliament. A3</p>
        <p>The Yugoslav military warned the nation's leaders against ''pushing our Yugoslav ship toward the rocks.'' The statement marked a break with the military's traditional distance from political affairs. A3</p>
        <p>Lebanon's rival Shiite militias signed a peace agreement that they said would end their power struggle and year of bitter fighting and would protect the staff of international organizations. A10</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A14-20  Federal deposit insurance premiums paid by lending institutions would be increased under a plan that Administration officials said they would urge the President to accept. A1</p>
        <p>Nursing homes that care for patients on Medicare and Medicaid must inform them of their rights, including rights to refuse treatment, manage personal funds and be free of restraints, Federal rules say. A1</p>
        <p>U.S. would limit doctor 'kickbacks' A16</p>
        <p>Private panel backs health care for all A16</p>
        <p>Calling blacks African-Americans, a proposal by the Rev. Jesse Jackson, has met with approval by some blacks and with skepticism by others, who have seen earlier name changes and do not identify with Africa. A1</p>
        <p>Congress's views on a pay increase for members are being collected by the Speaker of the House. He distributed a 12-question survey about the controversial issue. A19</p>
        <p>President Bush will not testify at the criminal trial of Oliver North, set to begin today, but former President Ronald Reagan may be asked to appear, a Federal judge ruled. A20</p>
        <p>A lower capital gains tax rate and other tax incentives backed by President Bush during the election campaign will almost certainly be proposed to Congress next week, Bush aides said. A17</p>
        <p>The U.S. Attorney in Massachusetts, Frank McNamara, resigned. He has been pressed to step down since November, when the Government said he had falsely accused his predecessor of smoking marijuana. A15</p>
        <p>Corruption by Indian governments and among Federal programs intended to assist American Indians is rampant, a prominent Indian leader told a Senate hearing. A14</p>
        <p>Brown is the only candidate left for the top Democratic post A17</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON TALK A20  Congress purrs under Bush's strokes  REGIONAL B1-5  Joel Steinberg was convicted of first degree manslaughter after eight days of often stormy jury deliberation in Manhattan's State Supreme Court. He faces from eight and one third to 25 years in prison. A1</p>
        <p>The charge against Mr. Steinberg of second-degree murder was rejected because several jurors had doubts about a critical element of the count: that he acted with ''depraved indifference'' by failing to get medical help. A1</p>
        <p>The city payroll needs to be reduced in New York City by 12,000 employees if Governor Cuomo's proposed state budget is not changed, Mayor Koch said, pursuing a strategy to shift fiscal blame to Albany. A1</p>
        <p>&gt;Officials oppose staff cuts by Koch B4</p>
        <p>People who know an accused sniper, charged Sunday in five sniper attacks in two Long Island towns, describe him as a quiet, playful and devout man. To police in the Middle West, he was known as a one-man crime wave. B1</p>
        <p>Major New York City zoning changes were proposed to preserve the shape, size and nature of housing in that half of the city dominated by one- and two-family homes, two or three stories high. B1</p>
        <p>Plans for a new hotel on East 57th Street in Manhattan that would vie for an internationally elite clientele, charging more than $400 a night, are being drawn by developers backed by $300 million from Japan. B1</p>
        <p>A comatose woman in Connecticut may legally be put to death by her family, the state's highest court ruled, in the first major challenge to the state's right-to-die law. B3</p>
        <p>NEEDIEST CASES B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
