<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Tools Aid Oil Hunt in U.S.</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="275851"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOFTWARE PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESERVES (NATURAL RESOURCES)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRODUCTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXPLORATION OF RESOURCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAYES, THOMAS C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reserves (Natural Resources)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exploration of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DD1530F935A2575BC0A96F948260" item-length="1510" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Tools Aid Oil Hunt in U.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS C. HAYES, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAYES, THOMAS C</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS, Aug. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Experts on energy thought for years that oil production in the United States would shrink to insignificant levels by the middle of the next century, making imports the nation's only meaningful supply. Now they are finding that steady advances in the technology for finding oil from large but hard-to-reach reserves discovered years ago seem likely to stretch the nation's era of oil production, possibly well beyond the year 2100.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Experts on energy thought for years that oil production in the United States would shrink to insignificant levels by the middle of the next century, making imports the nation's only meaningful supply. Now they are finding that steady advances in the technology for finding oil from large but hard-to-reach reserves discovered years ago seem likely to stretch the nation's era of oil production, possibly well beyond the year 2100.</p>
        <p>Experts on energy thought for years that oil production in the United States would shrink to insignificant levels by the middle of the next century, making imports the nation's only meaningful supply. Now they are finding that steady advances in the technology for finding oil from large but hard-to-reach reserves discovered years ago seem likely to stretch the nation's era of oil production, possibly well beyond the year 2100.</p>
        <p>The tools include software, run on high-speed computers, that help simulate underground rock formations to identify where oil is likely to lie and provide clues for the best ways to get at it. They also include seismic gauges that record sound waves used to probe the intricate structures of underground rock formations. And there are extraction techniques that involve pumping water, carbon dioxide, natural gas and a variety of chemicals under high pressure to flush out more oil. Removing the Guesswork</p>
        <p>''This is the future of the drilling business in the United States,'' said James L. Carroll, an analyst who follows the oilfield service industry for Paine Webber Inc., in New York. ''The industry is trying to locate these reservoirs in the greatest amount of detail. It is no longer a hit-or-miss process.''</p>
        <p>The major oilfield service companies, including Schlumberger Ltd., the Halliburton Company and Dresser Industries, are straining to develop or acquire advanced oilfield-simulation software.</p>
        <p>In addition to its own oilfield-simulation systems, Schlumberger owns 75 percent of the Geophysical Company of Norway, which makes seismic gauges. Halliburton has acquired the Gearhart Corporation, Geophysical Services Inc. and Sierra Geophysics Inc., all of which make gauges, software or other equipment for oilfield simulation. A joint venture of Litton Industries and Dresser Industries, Western Atlas, also makes seismic equipment. Landmark Graphics of Houston is an independent, publicly traded maker of oilfield imaging systems.</p>
        <p>Because of the improving ability to identify and extract oil, the amount of recoverable reserves has barely slipped during the 1980's, according to Government figures. The number has remained fairly steady even though the United States is pumping about three billion barrels of oil a year and even though the amount discovered annually in previously unexplored areas has dropped 30 percent from peaks in the early 1980's to well below one billion barrels a year.</p>
        <p>The decline in new discoveries has come partly because of budget slashing in domestic exploration activities after prices collapsed early in 1986 and partly because most areas in the United States likely to contain oil have been thoroughly explored.</p>
        <p>But even with the technological advances, the nation is using more oil than it finds and the oil industry is not optimistic that this will be changed through further gains in technology or another surge in oil prices that encourages exploration. There has not been a major oil discovery since Alaska's giant Prudhoe Bay field was found in 1968. With drilling activity at the lowest point since records were started in World War II, the nation's use of foreign oil climbed to 45 percent of demand in the first half of the year.</p>
        <p>With the gains in technology, some experts say the recovery rate for proven reserves can rise to one of every two discovered barrels -enough to more than double the supplies once expected to run out within 60 years or so. The industry has recovered an average of one of every three barrels from domestic reserves in recent years.</p>
        <p>The Government estimated that the nation had 27.3 billion barrels of recoverable oil at the end of 1987. The Government reported that United States oil production between 1976 and 1987 exceeded the amount of new recoverable reserves - an amount that includes oil found in both old and new fields - by an average of about 600 million barrels a year. Energy Department officials estimated that without any changes, there would be little oil left to pump in the country within 50 or 60 years.</p>
        <p>But now, ''a lot of companies are going back to old, mature fields,'' said Marcus E. Milling, a professor at the University of Texas at Austin and director of the Geoscience Institute for Oil and Gas Recovery Research.</p>
        <p>With effective application of today's technology, an additional 20 billion barrels could be recovered from existing reservoirs in the next 20 to 30 years, assuming the price of oil rises to an average of $25 a barrel from less than $20 now in current dollars, he said. That would almost double the current volume of recoverable reserves.</p>
        <p>Dr. Milling, a geologist, said that if the industry and Government spent more on research to improve techniques to free oil now trapped and unable to flow to wells, another 60 billion barrels could be recovered from known fields.</p>
        <p>Natural-gas producers, using the same advanced equipment, have also reported rising recovery estimates.</p>
        <p>Typical of the computer programs being adopted by the oil industry is one developed by Sierra Geophysics. The program enables geophysicists to simulate an explosion or other burst of energy used to propel sound waves through layers of rock where pockets of oil are known to exist. The computer shows how the sound waves might be reflected by the rock layers back to gauges placed in previously drilled wells. The rock formations drawn by the computer are based on information acquired during what is often several years of drilling and production in the area.</p>
        <p>The speed and direction of the waves traced by the computer program provide clues to the contours of the rock layers within a producing field. For instance, in a case where geologists have already discovered oil in sandstone at a depth of 4,000 feet in one location, they can use the program to sketch how the sandstone layer is likely to change in direction and depth across that producing field.</p>
        <p>These simulated tests are done frequently by geophysicists to help production engineers determine where to set up actual seismic tests conducted before additional lease rights are purchased near producing fields.</p>
        <p>Many companies have reported improved drilling results in fields where they have been pumping oil for years. Amoco Inc., the nation's fifth-largest oil company, recently raised its estimate of the amount of crude oil it can extract from its West Texas fields by as much as 15 percent.</p>
        <p>Production experts changed drilling locations and other recovery practices at those sites in 1987 after two- and three-dimensional computer simulations of the fields detected previously unknown rock patterns.</p>
        <p>David S. Gutleber, a senior engineer at Amoco's research center in Tulsa, Okla., said the company expected to post higher reserve estimates and recovery rates for most of its production fields as the new techniques spread through Amoco's operations.</p>
        <p>''We haven't had enough performance, but 15 percent seems like a representative number'' of how much additional oil Amoco can pump from its proven reserves, he said.</p>
        <p>In a similar case, the Louisiana Land and Exploration Company raised estimates of recoverable reserves at its Canadian operations by 50 percent. The increases were made after production workers drilled again in areas where company managers had thought the most attractive pockets of oil had already been found. Computer-generated maps of the reservoirs' geology changed their minds.</p>
        <p>Louisiana Land's prospects in the Gulf of Mexico and the North Sea also improved after new seismic studies and computer models created a different picture of probable sites for untapped reserves.</p>
        <p>One of the biggest problems still to be overcome in simulating underground reservoirs is getting a clear view of what lies beneath subterranean salt layers, which absorb sound waves. That leaves geologists in the dark about what lies below, which often turns out to be large oil pockets.</p>
        <p>''We're probably two or three years away'' from developing seismic-recording techniques to sketch beyond salt caps, said Orville Gaither, president of the Africa and Middle East region of the Amoco Production Company, an Amoco subsidiary. ''When that comes, we will have made a major milestone.''</p>
        <p>Most of the nation's 20,000 independent producers, which collectively pump 40 percent of the nation's oil, spend little on research. And the costs to drill a new well, which range from $500,000 to $75 million or more, discourage many of them from exploring existing fields.</p>
        <p>For many of these smaller companies, investments of $2 million or more in reservoir simulation equipment make sense if they think the payoff will be a higher rate of drilling success. To reduce the amount of initial investment required, the Energy Department recently made some oilfield simulation software developed by its researchers available to producers at no cost.</p>
        <p>''Geologists and geophysicists are risk managers, like stockbrokers,'' said Bob Hart, Sierra's president. ''The more information we can get them, and the more precise it is, the better their judgment will be.''</p>
        <p>BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
