<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="293913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D9133FF930A15753C1A96F948260" item-length="597" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL  Military contractors are turning abroad for parts to build weapons systems, as the Pentagon puts pressure on companies to reduce costs and as foreign suppliers become more adept. The trend is raising fears on dependence, jobs and profits.  [ Page A1. ] A plan to phase out many American farm programs if other countries agree to similar cutbacks will be put forward this week by the Bush Administration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL  Military contractors are turning abroad for parts to build weapons systems, as the Pentagon puts pressure on companies to reduce costs and as foreign suppliers become more adept. The trend is raising fears on dependence, jobs and profits.  [ Page A1. ] A plan to phase out many American farm programs if other countries agree to similar cutbacks will be put forward this week by the Bush Administration.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL  Military contractors are turning abroad for parts to build weapons systems, as the Pentagon puts pressure on companies to reduce costs and as foreign suppliers become more adept. The trend is raising fears on dependence, jobs and profits.  [ Page A1. ] A plan to phase out many American farm programs if other countries agree to similar cutbacks will be put forward this week by the Bush Administration. But there is much skepticism about the prospects for the plan.  [ D9. ] El Salvador's Government has begun an audacious program intended to rebuild a battered economy and alleviate the social injustice, unemployment and stagnation from which leftist insurgents have historically drawn their strength.  [ D14. ] Chile is creating an autonomous central bank that the Government says will help preserve the nation's hard-won economic stability, growth and modernization.  [ D14. ] THE ECONOMY  Steel shipments are falling, reflecting a slowdown in the automobile and construction industries. Several analysts predict that total shipments in the second half of the year will be as much as 15 percent below 1988 levels.  [ D1. ] Saving the world from global warming may require sharp reductions in burning fuel, but there was no consensus at a two-day meeting of 40 nuclear industry executives, government officials, energy experts and environmentalists on whether new nuclear reactors are needed.  [ D1. ] COMPANIES  I.B.M.'s control of the mainframe market is being threatened by far-reaching changes in the industry. Digital Equipment and Tandem are both planning to challenge I.B.M. in its most successful computer market.  [ D1. ] UAL's board is to meet today to consider its options, under pressure to respond to the plunge in the company's stock.  [ D1. ] R. H. Macy has agreed to make all of its private-label merchandise available to Kintetsu Department Stores of Japan. The one-year contract gives Macy an additional outlet for its large production capacity in East Asia.  [ D2. ] Campeau is again facing cutbacks in merchandise shipments as some suppliers to its Federated and Allied department stores have found their trade credit curtailed or canceled.  [ D2. ] THE MEDIA BUSINESS  McGraw-Hill is willing to customize college textbooks to suit the needs of individual professors, or even individual students, and it says it can make the changes in 48 hours.  [ D1. ] Eveready has turned to a marauding rabbit in an advertising campaign intended to startle viewers into paying attention.  [ D11. ] China Books and Periodicals has closed its bookstores in New York and San Francisco and will close its Chicago store on Dec. 1, but it is expanding its other book businesses.  [ D11. ] Magazine publishers are turning away from premiums as part of their campaigns to build circulation. Magazines.  [ D11. ] Holly Farms has dropped Dinah Shore as a spokeswoman and turned to a fast-paced television campaign that puts the focus on health concerns. Advertising.  [ D12. ] TODAY'S COLUMNS  Maryland has an innovative plan to try to resolve the thousands of asbestos cases that have swamped court dockets in the state. Stephen Labaton: Business and the Law.  [ D2. ] What did not happen in the stock market last week may be more important than what did. Floyd Norris: Market Place.  [ D8. ] Credit market participants are expected to return to their study of economic data and put the stock market's plunge behind them. Credit Markets.  [ D9. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
