<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rome Journal; How Is Marcus Aurelius? As Right as Acid Rain</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="211225"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HISTORIC BUILDINGS AND SITES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MONUMENTS AND MEMORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ROME (ITALY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HABERMAN, CLYDE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">TREVI FOUNTAIN (ROME)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Rome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D9123BF930A35752C0A96F948260" item-length="1047" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rome Journal; How Is Marcus Aurelius? As Right as Acid Rain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HABERMAN, CLYDE</byline>
      <dateline>ROME, Jan. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: They have made it more difficult to toss even one coin into the Trevi Fountain, let alone the Hollywood allotment of three.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: They have made it more difficult to toss even one coin into the Trevi Fountain, let alone the Hollywood allotment of three.</p>
        <p>They have made it more difficult to toss even one coin into the Trevi Fountain, let alone the Hollywood allotment of three.</p>
        <p>The problem is that the 18th-century Baroque vision of gods and tritons and dashing horses, as famous a symbol of this city as any, is undergoing serious restoration, and has been fully wrapped for the last month in a long glass screen that stands more than six feet tall. In places, even Orel Hershiser, the Dodger pitcher, would have a hard time clearing the barrier.</p>
        <p>A Japanese tourist discovered that for herself the other day when she bowed to legend, which dictates that a coin thrown over one's shoulder and into the fountain guarantees a return visit to Rome.</p>
        <p>Her first coin clinked ineffectually against the screen, clattering to the pavement like a dream deferred. Gamely, she tried again. Another clink.</p>
        <p>Finally, with a heave, she landed her third coin where she wanted it. But her embarrassment was evident. ''Difficult, isn't it?'' she said to her traveling companions. Overhaul to Last a Year</p>
        <p>Rome officials argue that her troubles are a small price to pay to keep the fountain in public view while workmen give it a badly needed overhaul that is expected to take until the end of the year.</p>
        <p>Normally when the city's monuments undergo restoration, they disappear for years behind tarpaulins and green netting. But Trevi, built between 1732 and 1762 against the back wall of a palace, is such a popular attraction that the municipal government decided that it had to remain on display, if under glass.</p>
        <p>''It's our version of perestroika,'' said Italo Ceccarelli, an architect supervising the restoration for the city.</p>
        <p>By any standard, the fountain is a mess.</p>
        <p>The marble statues of Ocean, Abundance and Salubrity are blackened by smog that has saturated the stone. Ocean's left knee is so worn away that some experts fear it may be beyond repair. Condensation, lime buildup, rust and algae have all taken their toll of travertine and stucco.</p>
        <p>No significant restoration work has been done since the late 1950's. For many the fountain became synonymous with the 1961 Fellini film ''La Dolce Vita.'' Countless starlets - a word still in vogue - hoped to make names for themselves by imitating Anita Ekberg's movie romp through Trevi's waters. Mostly, they just got wet. La Vita Is Less Dolce</p>
        <p>The vita is a bit less dolce today. It certainly is tamer. Most visitors to the fountain, which was commissioned by Pope Clement XII and designed by the architect Nicola Salvi, settle for quiet strolls through the small plaza that it dominates.</p>
        <p>Many are young men traveling in packs and carrying car radios wherever they go. It is not that they intend to listen to the radios. Rather, they are protecting themselves against car thieves. Some evenings, there are so many many Roman men walking around with car radios in hand that the practice looks like a fashion statement.</p>
        <p>Repairing the fountain is estimated to cost $1 million, which will be paid by an insurance company and not the hard-pressed city government. The municipality, however, has millions of dollars worth of restoration projects of its own, for the most part involving lesser-known monuments and public buildings.</p>
        <p>But no matter how much work is done, keeping Rome in shape remains a Sisyphean task. Even a casual stroll through the city reveals the impossibility of restoring the countless marble columns that have been turned to plaster by acid rain, or of scrubbing centuries-old cathedrals and palaces that are sickly gray after decades of foul air, chaotic traffic and public indifference. What to Do With Marcus</p>
        <p>So grave is the situation that it has produced a verbal fistfight over what to do with an equestrian statue of the Emperor Marcus Aurelius.</p>
        <p>After seven years of back-room restoration, the second-century statue is ready again for public diplay. Municipal leaders want to return it to the Piazza Campidoglio, the majestic square on the Capitoline Hill where Michelangelo put it 450 years ago. ''It is a symbol of the people of Rome,'' said Gianfranco Redavid, the city's culture commissioner.</p>
        <p>But others say it makes little sense to put Marcus Aurelius out in the open when Rome's pollution will only cause him to wither again. Alessandra Melucco Vaccaro, who directed the restoration project, outraged some Romans recently by suggesting that a copy of the statue be put in the Campidoglio and that the original be stored safely in a museum.</p>
        <p>This idea goes to the broader question of whether Rome is worthy of its treasures, an argument as eternal as the city itself. It was given new life this month by a historian and member of Parliament, Luigi Firpo, who told an Italian magazine that Rome was ''rotten to the core,'' and that it was therefore pointless to give it public funds for restoration projects.</p>
        <p>''Nobody is as arrogant as the Romans,'' said Mr. Firpo, who is from Turin. ''Nobody is as violent. They are vulgar.'' Taking Attila's Place Naturally, this did not sit well in the capital. While the novelist Alberto Moravia took the attack calmly enough, writing in a newspaper that people have always said such things about his city, others were offended. A newspaper commentator named Livio Zanetti wrote a few days ago, ''As a symbol of Rome's enemies, Firpo has taken Attila's place at the top of the ladder.''</p>
        <p>Thus far, the Trevi Fountain project has been spared such grand disputes. Small irritations arise nonetheless.</p>
        <p>With the water shut off, except for a brief return this holiday week, the number of tourists is down, and souvenir salesmen and nearby shop owners complain that so is business. Street people who roam Trevi's periphery looking for coins that did not make it into the fountain find that pickings are slimmer now.</p>
        <p>Still, the fountain's appeal endures, as does its stately calm in a city of turbulence.</p>
        <p>That was true one recent night for three sweepers assigned to the three streets - tre vie, in Italian - that lead to the fountain and give it its name. At about 1:30 A.M., they decided it was time for a break. With almost no one around to watch, they lay down their brooms and sat on a stone bench, smoking cigarettes and looking straight at Ocean as they discussed that afternoon's soccer match.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
