<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Second Chance for Vision</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="309892"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DB133CF934A25751C1A96F948260" item-length="818" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Second Chance for Vision</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: America had a fair idea of what it was getting in George Bush: a competent, cautious steward with a slim agenda and no taste for what he called ''the vision thing.'' He would make changes at the margins of the Reagan Revolution without disturbing its core. The nation would be kinder and gentler. Taxes would stay low, defenses strong.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: America had a fair idea of what it was getting in George Bush: a competent, cautious steward with a slim agenda and no taste for what he called ''the vision thing.'' He would make changes at the margins of the Reagan Revolution without disturbing its core. The nation would be kinder and gentler. Taxes would stay low, defenses strong.</p>
        <p>America had a fair idea of what it was getting in George Bush: a competent, cautious steward with a slim agenda and no taste for what he called ''the vision thing.'' He would make changes at the margins of the Reagan Revolution without disturbing its core. The nation would be kinder and gentler. Taxes would stay low, defenses strong. He would be a prudent leader in placid times. Uncharismatic, for sure, but the voters found that preferable to the uncertain candidacy of Michael Dukakis.</p>
        <p>Now, thanks largely to Mikhail Gorbachev and the long-stifled emotions of millions of Eastern Europeans, the world George Bush inherited has changed dramatically. The end of the cold war does more than challenge old assumptions. It inspires high hopes that America will shift resources from receding foreign threats to neglected domestic needs.</p>
        <p>A few months ago, Mr. Bush seemed well matched to his times - in The Economist's words, ''a President without a vision when visions are out of fashion.'' Yet a visionary named Gorbachev now invites more than stewardship from the President in Washington. Is Mr. Bush up to the task? His first year in office offers grounds for hope - and worry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's inaugural provided no grand plan, just a sensible approach to governance. The country, he said, had grown weary of ideological combat and was eager for bipartisanship. So he moved quickly to defuse controversy. On Central America, for example, he cut a deal with Congress to send humanitarian but not military aid to the Nicaraguan contras, removing at one stroke an issue that had paralyzed Mr. Reagan's relations with Congress.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush kept the Reagan faith by opposing abortion, though his views increasingly antagonized Republican women - and dismayed Republican officeholders. He shamelessly exploited the flag burning issue. Yet he broke cleanly with Mr. Reagan on important environmental questions like acid rain, faced up to the savings and loan crisis and offered an original approach to third world debt. And unlike his predecessor, who had ears only for good news, Mr. Bush acknowledged that America suffered from drugs, poor housing and poor schooling.</p>
        <p>He brought a new style, too. Jimmy Carter cared little for Congress, Ronald Reagan even less for the press. George Bush held 24 formal news conferences in his first nine months. He pitched horseshoes with reporters, herded Congressmen on tours through the White House living quarters, composed handwritten notes by the bushel. There was no escaping his relentless bonhomie. These have been welcome adjustments to the Reagan legacy. Other aspects of Mr. Bush's first year give pause.</p>
        <p>For a man who personifies openness and prudence, the President has sometimes displayed a disturbing penchant for secretive, even impulsive behavior. He arranged the Malta summit meeting without telling his Defense Secretary, Dick Cheney, who was himself involved in sensitive discussions with Soviet officials.</p>
        <p>Just a week ago, Mr. Bush dispatched two aides on the furtive mission to Beijing. A patient explanation of his strategy might have allayed the sense of betrayal felt by Americans sickened by the slaughter of Chinese students last spring. The two episodes were unhappy reminders of how Mr. Bush startled the public, and even some of his closest aides, by choosing Dan Quayle as his running mate.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Bush has sometimes seemed oddly impetuous, he has often been surprisingly insubstantial. The sound emanating from Washington is the sound of wind machines. The whirr is intended to make people think America is moving.</p>
        <p>The education summit meeting conducted by the self-styled Education President was all wind. The housing plan, ditto. The famous War on Drugs, mostly ditto. There's little new money, and no will to find any. The deficit - and Mr. Bush's stubborn refusal to budge from his no-new-taxes pledge - have paralyzed Congress. Mr. Bush doesn't shout charge! He whispers it.</p>
        <p>That defines the central worry about Mr. Bush in the Gorbachev era. The President is right to approach enormous matters like the reshaping of Europe with prudence. He is right when he says there can be no instant peace dividend; reductions in defense will have to be made gradually.</p>
        <p>But if Mr. Gorbachev can sustain his vision of a more peaceable Soviet Union, he invites Americans, and their President, to imagine, too. George Bush can be more than what he thought he would be, a capable shepherd of the status quo. He can, over the next three years, begin a transformation of American priorities.</p>
        <p>That means doing all he can to help Mr. Gorbachev survive. It means honoring his pledge at Malta to push the bureaucracy ''as fast as I possibly can'' toward agreement on strategic nuclear weapons and conventional forces. And it means seizing this moment to plan for peace - a precious and unexpected opportunity that asks the unexpected of George Bush.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
