<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEW MARS FINDINGS FROM SOVIET CRAFT</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="292381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MARS (PLANET)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PHOBOS (MARTIAN MOON)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFDF133CF93AA25753C1A96F948260" item-length="877" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEW MARS FINDINGS FROM SOVIET CRAFT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla., Oct. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Observations by a Soviet spacecraft reveal that magnetic forces surrounding Mars are controlled by ''winds'' of electrified gases from the Sun, not from magnetism generated by the planet. The finding could explain why Mars has lost most of its atmosphere over the last billion years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Observations by a Soviet spacecraft reveal that magnetic forces surrounding Mars are controlled by ''winds'' of electrified gases from the Sun, not from magnetism generated by the planet. The finding could explain why Mars has lost most of its atmosphere over the last billion years.</p>
        <p>Observations by a Soviet spacecraft reveal that magnetic forces surrounding Mars are controlled by ''winds'' of electrified gases from the Sun, not from magnetism generated by the planet. The finding could explain why Mars has lost most of its atmosphere over the last billion years.</p>
        <p>The spacecraft also returned data supporting the hypothesis that the tiny, dark Martian moon Phobos is an asteroid captured by the planet's gravity. Phobos's structure and composition were found to be strikingly irregular -as irregular as its lumpy shape. Its surface is extremely dry, but beneath could well be an icy interior, which could be a vital source of oxygen, hydrogen and water for future explorers or settlers of Mars.</p>
        <p>These were among the most intriguing results reported today by Soviet and Western scientists after a preliminary analysis of observations by the Phobos 2 spacecraft. Phobos 2 orbited Mars for almost two months this year, making several passes within 500 miles of the little moon, before a computer failure caused it to spin out of control on March 27. New and Important Findings</p>
        <p>Phobos 2 was the first spacecraft to visit Mars since the two Vikings, launched by the United States, landed on the planet in 1976 in a vain search for life there. A companion craft, Phobos 1, failed on the way to Mars. Phobos 2's premature end deprived scientists of information from what was to have been the mission's primary objective, the landing of instruments on the moon itself.</p>
        <p>Despite these disappointments, scientists said the mission did return new and important data. The results were reported in the issue of the journal Nature published today.</p>
        <p>European scientists with instruments on Phobos 2 confirmed the prevailing assumption that Mars has little or no magnetic field of its own. But the spacecraft did not get close enough to make a definitive determination about Martian magnetism.</p>
        <p>Commenting on the results in an accompanying article in the journal, Dr. Mark Saunders, a planetary scientist at the Imperial College of Science in London, said the ''initial data analyses suggest that the character of Martian space is controlled by the solar wind and its embedded interplanetary magnetic field.'' Tail Like the Wake of a Ship</p>
        <p>The Phobos scientists reported measurements of the turbulent interactions between solar magnetic forces and the Martian ionosphere. Solar wind, a supersonic flow of electrified gases, carries with it the interplanetary magnetic field. The Martian ionosphere, consisting of rarefied and electrified atmospheric atoms extending out several thousand miles, acts as an obstacle to the solar wind.</p>
        <p>Slamming into the ionosphere, the solar wind is diverted and flows around either side of the planet. The flowing magnetized gases, or plasma, form a magnetic tail like the wake of a ship knifing through water. Similar interactions create magnetic tails at Venus, at the comets and at Titan, the largest moon of Saturn.</p>
        <p>Earth has a strong magnetic field of its own that serves to bottle in the planet's atmosphere, preventing its leakage into space. At Mars, carbon dioxide from its thin atmosphere is observed escaping out the opening in the magnetic tail.</p>
        <p>The rate of leakage may seem small, Dr. Saunders said, but ''if maintained, it would result in Mars's thin atmosphere being lost within one billion years, which is less than the age of the solar system.'' Eons Ago, Water on Mars</p>
        <p>Many theorists believe Mars had a much denser atmosphere in its early history. This presumably created conditions allowing for the presence of liquid water on the planet. Photography by American spacecraft reveal seemingly clear evidence of widespread water erosion on Mars. With water and a thicker atmosphere, scientists argue, some forms of life might have evolved on Mars, only to vanish as its water and air dissipated.</p>
        <p>Scientists of the Space Research Institute in Moscow reported that the craft's imaging spectrometer showed Phobos to have a dark surface and irregular structure.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview, Dr. William B. McKinnon, a planetary geologist at Washington University in St. Louis, said the structure ''means Phobos probably has been broken up and reassembled in orbit.''</p>
        <p>Dr. McKinnon agrees with the Soviet scientists in saying the evidence supports the assumption that Phobos is an asteroid that was captured by Martian gravity. Presumably the other small moon, Deimos, is also an asteroid.</p>
        <p>Although Soviet scientists reported that the surface of Phobos was especially dry, Dr. McKinnon noted in comments published in Nature that most asteroids of its type have dry surfaces over icy interiors.</p>
        <p>''The prospect of icy moons circling a desert below,'' Dr. McKinnon wrote, ''is only one of the many Martian mysteries to be explored by further analysis of Phobos 2 data.''</p>
        <p>Dr. McKinnon added in the interview that the findings, if confirmed by further investigations, were encouraging for long-range planners of space colonization. Settlements on the Moon, which is extremely dry, could extract water and hydrogen for fuel and rocket propellant from asteroids. Many scenarios for Mars colonization include the use of Phobos and Deimos as fueling stops for oxygen and hydrogen extraction.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
