<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>European Luxury Cars Fade</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="227082"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER BEHAVIOR</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEVIN, DORON P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFD9153EF934A15751C0A96F948260" item-length="1524" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>European Luxury Cars Fade</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DORON P. LEVIN, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEVIN, DORON P</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Feb. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Some auto industry executives are worried that a fundamental shift in the psychology of luxury-car buyers has reduced the number of people willing to pay from $20,000 to more than $75,000 for what a Saab official describes as ''really only four-wheeled personal transportation boxes with a lot of image.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Some auto industry executives are worried that a fundamental shift in the psychology of luxury-car buyers has reduced the number of people willing to pay from $20,000 to more than $75,000 for what a Saab official describes as ''really only four-wheeled personal transportation boxes with a lot of image.</p>
        <p>Some auto industry executives are worried that a fundamental shift in the psychology of luxury-car buyers has reduced the number of people willing to pay from $20,000 to more than $75,000 for what a Saab official describes as ''really only four-wheeled personal transportation boxes with a lot of image.''</p>
        <p>Sales of Mercedes-Benz, Porsche, BMW, Saab, Volvo, Jaguar and Audi automobiles, once the icons of the go-go 1980's, have sharply fallen in the last two years. Sales have been hurt by higher prices, as well as by changes in the tax laws and increased competition from American and Japanese luxury cars.</p>
        <p>But sales of European luxury cars seem to be suffering from something more subtle than their steep pricing. An Emotional Decision</p>
        <p>''Buying a car for more than $10,000 or $15,000 is a decision that has a certain amount of emotion in it,'' a spokesman for BMW said. ''Have our cars ceased to be status symbols? It's a serious question.''</p>
        <p>Robert Sinclair, president of Saab's import arm in the United States, said many Americans have come to regard ostentatious displays of wealth and lavish spending as socially irresponsible.</p>
        <p>''It's the change from the me-too yuppie era,'' he said. ''People are seeking more traditional values.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sinclair delivered this appraisal to Saab directors in October; they had come to New York to discuss why American sales of the Swedish luxury car had dropped to 38,490 cars in 1988, from 48,086 in 1986. During that period, the price of Saab's least expensive car rose to $17,000, from $12,300, while the most expensive model soared to $32,100, from $23,700.</p>
        <p>Making generalizations about buyer psychology is a tricky business. But market researchers have found evidence of a shift in attitude. ''Luxury cars are still a symbol of success, but the consumer is becoming much more pragmatic,'' said Sandy Hoffman, senior vice president of the Roper Group. ''The focus on self, while still there, is muted.''</p>
        <p>The Daniel Yankelovich Group, which surveys public opinion, found last year that ''the crash of 1987 was a psychological watershed for affluent buyers, as well as a group we call the young aspirers,'' said David Meer, senior vice president.</p>
        <p>Among households with annual incomes of $100,000 or more, ''a sense of caution and limits has entered their thinking,'' Mr. Meer said. Concern with the environment, Government budget deficits and social issues like homelessness was also more evident than in the previous two years.</p>
        <p>''I don't think people are backing away from buying Jaguars because they're concerned about the ozone layer,'' he said. ''It's not cause and effect. But I think both things - the worry and the decision not to buy -spring from the same underlying feeling, that we can't have everything.'' Style and Substance</p>
        <p>Until 1987, European makers of luxury cars had consistently been able to charge premium prices and increase sales for two reasons: substance and style. European cars had a quality and performance advantage over most American-made vehicles.</p>
        <p>The European auto makers also attempted to reinforce their sophisticated, high-class image by advertising and promotion that often focused on status. Aston Martin of Britain, for example, ran an advertisement that read ''Demoralize Thy Neighbor.''</p>
        <p>''That ad epitomized the 1980's, Wall Street, go-for-it mentality,'' Mr. Meer said.</p>
        <p>''Getting wealth and flaunting it doesn't feel quite as good as the society changes,'' he said. ''Obviously, George Bush's people do research as well, and that's why they talk about a kinder, gentler nation. Those words struck a responsive chord because that's what is on people's minds.'' Narrowing the Quality Gap</p>
        <p>A crucial aspect of European luxury-car marketing has been the message that it is intelligent and acceptable behavior to reward oneself by spending an enormous sum on a car. Such behavior made sense, in the logic of the marketers, because the buyer was getting a superior-quality vehicle.</p>
        <p>Throughout the 1980's, however, domestic auto makers have narrowed the gap in quality and performance, eroding the extra value that luxury buyers perceived they were getting for the premium prices.</p>
        <p>''We've had three to four years of pretty good news from the U.S. car makers, and the public is starting to find out,'' said David E. Davis, publisher of Automobile magazine. ''We're seeing the convergence of two important trend lines: rising import prices and growing improvement by the domestics. There had to be a point where they crossed.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, the 1986 overhaul in the Federal income tax laws increased the cost of owning a luxury car. The deductibility of most interest payments was phased out and the use of investment tax credits was curtailed. That meant lawyers, doctors and brokers who once deducted their cars as a business expense were forced to make more practical choices.</p>
        <p>The decline of the dollar's value against the West German mark, the Swedish krona and other European currencies has only accelerated the price increases that luxury-car makers had begun about two years ago. Many executives in the luxury-car import business are now convinced that prices have risen so high - and competing American vehicles have so markedly improved - that buyers no longer believe the extra value in a European luxury car justifies the premium price.</p>
        <p>''You don't really know where the price versus value threshold is until you've crossed it,'' said Brian Bowler, president of Porsche Cars of North America. ''And we crossed it.'' While the price of some Porsche models has jumped sharply, the number of cars brought into this country has dropped by half since 1986, to 15,737, from 30,471. 'That's Crazy'</p>
        <p>One Porsche dealer, who asked not to be identified, quoted a customer as saying: ''I'm willing to pay $40,000 for a Porsche 911, but $55,000? That's crazy.''</p>
        <p>Joseph Herman, who is a partner in 22 auto dealerships, most of them selling European luxury cars, said a buyer who agrees to buy a car that others think is too highly priced fails to achieve the image for which he or she is searching.</p>
        <p>''The problem is that a person who spends too much money on a car that doesn't have sufficient value is perceived by his friends to be a fool,'' Mr. Herman said.</p>
        <p>The fool was once considered by many to be the buyer of an American car, but not any longer. ''The bottom line is you can show up now driving one of the better American cars and not suffer any social stigma,'' Mr. Davis said.</p>
        <p>As demand for European luxury cars has declined, widespread dealer discounting has ensued, enabling some buyers to buy luxury cars for thousands of dollars less than the sticker price. This discounting has upset manufacturers, who think it cuts into their carefully cultivated luxury images.</p>
        <p>In response to this sales erosion, most European auto companies are freezing or reducing prices, offering rebates disguised as free optional equipment or, in the case of Mercedes, providing a free flight to Europe to pick up the car. Competing With Second Homes</p>
        <p>A. B. Shuman, a spokesman for Mercedes-Benz, disputed the notion that affluent consumers are backing away from expensive European cars. But he said the most expensive Mercedes, which costs about $80,000, may now be vying with ''non-automotive competitors,'' like boats and second homes.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, to make Mercedes more affordable and more enticing, the company has lowered the price of its entry-level 190 series and put a bigger engine in those cars.</p>
        <p>Sales of Audi cars have been hurt by complaints that some of its models had an unintended acceleration problem. Audi has rebutted the complaints, which have not been substantiated, and the company said it was about to start a major television advertising campaign billing itself as ''technological leader of the European luxury imports.''</p>
        <p>At Jaguar, Michael Dale, senior vice president of sales and marketing, said the company realized in 1987 that it had overpriced its cars when its sales fell.</p>
        <p>''It's quite easy to see that customers will pay $20,000 for the difference between a Jaguar and a Cadillac, but we were charging $30,000'' more than Cadillac, he said.</p>
        <p>Jaguar has reduced some prices, and it has also limited the number of cars sent to the United States to maintain an air of exclusivity. Porsche's Moves</p>
        <p>Porsche has frozen prices for the rest of the year, dropped the lower-priced 924 model and, to improve the value-to-price relationship, added a more powerful engine in the 944 and a new suspension in the 911.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sinclair is convinced that Saab is poised to take advantage of ''instability'' in the European luxury segment by positioning its cars as ''solid, dependable, safe transportation.''</p>
        <p>For good measure, Saab will also criticize German and Japanese competitors in a series of ads that will appear next month.</p>
        <p>All of these moves might be too little, too late: Toyota, Nissan and Honda have been moving into the luxury field with cars that have won praise from critics. The Japanese luxury cars offer styling and power similar to the European models but generally at lower prices.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
