<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tiny Fish Help Solve Cancer Riddle</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="312247"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CANCER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BROOKHAVEN NATIONAL LABORATORY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMITT, ERIC</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DC1231F935A15751C1A96F948260" item-length="849" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tiny Fish Help Solve Cancer Riddle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMITT, ERIC</byline>
      <dateline>UPTON, L.I.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: RESEARCHERS at the Brookhaven National Laboratory are employing a novel model to study skin cancer in humans: they are exposing tiny tropical fish to ultraviolet radiation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: RESEARCHERS at the Brookhaven National Laboratory are employing a novel model to study skin cancer in humans: they are exposing tiny tropical fish to ultraviolet radiation.</p>
        <p>RESEARCHERS at the Brookhaven National Laboratory are employing a novel model to study skin cancer in humans: they are exposing tiny tropical fish to ultraviolet radiation.</p>
        <p>The intent is to measure how the earth's thinning ozone layer promotes cancer. Atmospheric ozone plays an important role in absorbing ultraviolet light from the sun. But scientists believe that chlorofluorocarbons produced in the making of refrigerants and foam insulation are destroying that crucial buffer. Scientists generally agree that increased ultraviolet radiation will bring a sharp rise in skin cancers, primarily among fair-skinned people.</p>
        <p>The fish were chosen because the usual test animals, mice and rats, are less useful in skin cancer studies, the scientists said. Their fur blocks some radiation and also hinders tumor growth, so researchers are required to shave each animal daily, a laborious and inexact chore. Studying Wavelengths</p>
        <p>By inducing tumors in the fish, scientists hope to pinpoint the precise ultraviolet wavelengths that may cause or promote melanomas, the life-threatening skin cancers. That knowledge is important to health experts to help them determine how ozone depletion contributes to skin cancer. Ozone absorbs the shorter ultraviolet wavelengths better than it blocks longer wavelengths.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency has calculated that in the United States alone there will be more than 155 million additional cases of skin cancer and 3.2 million additional cancer deaths over the next century if the ozone destruction continues at its current pace.</p>
        <p>The ultraviolet radiation breaks and damages the DNA in cells, altering the genetic blueprint so that the cells begin uncontrolled growth.</p>
        <p>For their research, the scientists are using a cross between two iridescent tropical fish, a platyfish and a swordtail, both of which are only an inch long. The hybrid's thin, hairless skin is extremely sensitive to ultraviolet exposure and thus ideal for studying the effects of various wavelengths. The parent fish also reproduce rapidly and in large enough broods for laboratory samples.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the reaction of the DNA in the fish cells in some ways mimics the reaction of human DNA, said Dr. Richard Setlow, a senior biophysicist at the laboratory. 400 Fish Tanks ''Only fish yield good results for melanomas,'' said Dr. Setlow, who last year received the Enrico Fermi award from the Federal Energy Department for his work in molecular biology and radiation biophysics.</p>
        <p>In an old greenhouse at the laboratory, Dr. Setlow and a team of researchers have assembled 400 10-gallon and 25-gallon fish tanks in which to conduct their experiments. In the initial stage, female platyfish, which carry incipient melanoma genes as well as genes that repress the cancer, are mated with male swordtails, which have neither gene.</p>
        <p>The hybrid offspring are then crossed again with a swordtail. This produces a pale green or orange hybrid, whose melanoma gene remains but whose cancer-repressor gene is suppressed, making the inducement of cancers more likely. Each breeding period takes about three months.</p>
        <p>When the specimens are five days old and about the size of a pea, researchers place them in groups of about 20 in 10-gallon tanks. The tanks, however, are filled with two inches of water. If the water is too deep, the ultraviolet wavelengths are distorted, altering the radiation's effects. Filters Screen Out Light</p>
        <p>The tops of the tanks are covered with a filter that screens out all but the wavelength to be tested. Several tanks are set on a wooden shelf. Lamps hang directly above each aquarium. The fish are irradiated once, for a total of 1 to 10 minutes. The rack of shelves is covered in black cloth to block out external light.</p>
        <p>Researchers are careful to limit exposure. The ultraviolet light most damaging to living organisms has a wavelength ranging from 280 to 320 nanometers. (A nanometer is a billionth of a meter.) ''We want to give them a tan, not a sunburn,'' said Dr. Avril Woodhead, an associate biologist working on the project. Indeed, in these fish a sunburn is fatal.</p>
        <p>After the radiation exposure and a 24-hour waiting period, researchers transfer the fish to 25-gallon holding tanks and wait for tumors to appear, which takes about four weeks. Scientists Count Tumors</p>
        <p>Even on the naturally speckled hybrid fish, the black blotchy tumors on the sides and dorsal fins are evident to an untrained eye. Within six months to a year, the tumors eventually kill the fish.  By the time the experiment is completed next year, scientists will have exposed hundreds of fish. Five or six different ultraviolet wavelengths will be tested for varying lengths of time. The scientists count the number of fish that contract tumors and the number of tumors on each fish.</p>
        <p>The experiment, now in its third year, has not yielded conclusive results about which ultraviolet wavelengths promote cancers, Dr. Setlow said. But he said there are some indications that longer wavelengths may help reverse certain damage caused by the shorter wavelengths.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
