<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>M.I.T. Chief Reflects on His Tenure</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="250848"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="EDUCATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRAY, PAUL E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DA123EF934A25756C0A96F948260" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>M.I.T. Chief Reflects on His Tenure</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
      <dateline>CAMBRIDGE, Mass., May 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: For the last nine years, Paul E. Gray has been president of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, a school that is synonymous with pioneering research in the sciences and a pressure-cooker academic environment. Mr. Gray announced in March that he would quit the university's top job in July 1990 and become chairman of the M.I.T.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: For the last nine years, Paul E. Gray has been president of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, a school that is synonymous with pioneering research in the sciences and a pressure-cooker academic environment. Mr. Gray announced in March that he would quit the university's top job in July 1990 and become chairman of the M.I.T.</p>
        <p>For the last nine years, Paul E. Gray has been president of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, a school that is synonymous with pioneering research in the sciences and a pressure-cooker academic environment. Mr. Gray announced in March that he would quit the university's top job in July 1990 and become chairman of the M.I.T. Corporation, the school's governing board.</p>
        <p>In a recent interview, Mr. Gray reflected on his years at M.I.T.'s helm.</p>
        <p>Q. How has M.I.T. changed since 1980?</p>
        <p>Let me mention two kinds of changes that I think are important. One is that the gender and the racial composition of the student body has changed. In 1980, I don't know what the figure was for women in the student body. It couldn't have been more than 15 or 20 percent. But it's now, at the undergraduate level, in the neighborhood of 35 percent and at the graduate level in the neighborhood of 20 percent.</p>
        <p>Over that same period, the number of what we would call underrepresented minorities, which means principally blacks, Hispanics and native Americans, has increased quite a lot. I suppose about 10 years ago it was in the neighborhood of 7 or 8 percent and now it's more than twice that - 17 percent of this year's freshman class.</p>
        <p>The second element of change relates to the way engineers and engineering educators perceive themselves and their role. I think there is much more recognition now than there was 10 years ago that engineering is a socially derived activity. It is an activity that influences and is influenced by the society, the attitudes and priorities that have been expressed.</p>
        <p>Some of this is because of greater public consciousness about the environmental, the health and safety, broadly social effects of the engineering activity. And some of that is presently underscored for us by things like Three Mile Island or I suppose Prince William Sound or the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>Q. One thing you say that hasn't changed in 40 years is the M.I.T. style. What does that mean?  This is a place which attracts and retains high achievers, people who enjoy competition, particularly in its intellectual dimensions, and who thrive on intensity of effort. Those are aspects of what I mean by ''style.'' That is mirrored in the faculty. The faculty are folks of similar intensity and interest.</p>
        <p>I said 10 years ago, when I was inaugurated, that I thought that this would be a more educational institution. The phrase that I used then was, if you could turn the throttle back just a little, not much, 10 or 20 percent -have a little more time for reflection, feel a little less driven by the set of things that were on our plates individually. And looking back on it now, 10 years later, I have to say that I haven't made any impression at all on that aspect of M.I.T. None at all. It is a place in which sloth is the cardinal sin, and anything that gives the impression of sloth is almost as bad.</p>
        <p>Q. What issues will your successor face in the next 10 years?</p>
        <p>I described how this place had grown in the 15 years after World War II. The people who accomplished that big growth, of tripling in size in a 15-year period, are coming up to retirement age in this next decade, at a time when the higher education system as a whole is not producing enough Ph.D.-level folks to meet ordinary replacement needs in science and in engineering, let alone the sort of extraordinary needs that come along when you are trying to replace a lot of people retiring. So I think we are going to go through a period of time in which it is going to be very hard to maintain faculty size and faculty quality, and trying to maintain it is going to put extraordinary strains on budgets.</p>
        <p>I think that the changing demographics of the nation are going to put pressure on universities with respect to enrollments, the gender and racial characteristics of their enrollments and the composition of the whole work force in these organizations. Something like two-thirds coming into the work force between now and the end of the century will be either minority or women. I think it is a particular challenge for this place, because of our science-based focus.</p>
        <p>Q. You note that M.I.T.'s growth in enrollment and faculty has slowed in the last 10 or 20 years. Is there any pressure to change?</p>
        <p>I am pressed constantly by -particularly by the high-tech industry in Massachusetts - to grow and to expand, to do more, particularly in graduate education. Because those folks see the need for trained people. And they see Massachusetts educational institutions not quite meeting that need, and they worry about what the future will bring.</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
