<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Industry's Race With Summer</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="225822"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR CONDITIONING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRODUCTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDUSTRY PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHORTAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLUSHA, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DC1E3FF930A15751C0A96F948260" item-length="1204" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Industry's Race With Summer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN HOLUSHA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLUSHA, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Manufacturers of room air-conditioners are running their production lines at full speed to refill a distribution pipeline that dried up last August after two successive steamy summers. But because of a worldwide scarcity of compressors, a key component, another long, hot summer this year could find some people left out in the heat again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Manufacturers of room air-conditioners are running their production lines at full speed to refill a distribution pipeline that dried up last August after two successive steamy summers. But because of a worldwide scarcity of compressors, a key component, another long, hot summer this year could find some people left out in the heat again.</p>
        <p>Manufacturers of room air-conditioners are running their production lines at full speed to refill a distribution pipeline that dried up last August after two successive steamy summers. But because of a worldwide scarcity of compressors, a key component, another long, hot summer this year could find some people left out in the heat again.</p>
        <p>Last year was a bonanza for air-conditioner manufacturers, who shipped 4.6 million units. That was well above the 3.6 million shipped in 1987 but far below the record of 5.9 million set in 1970. Dollar sales for 1988 have not yet been tablulated, but should well exceed the $1.03 billion level of 1987.</p>
        <p>Despite the robust output last year, many wilting customers discovered that the industry was sold out all the way back to the factory floor as the tropical temperatures persisted. The problem was particularly acute in the Northeast, where housing tends to be older and central air-conditioning far less common than in the South and Southwest. Sales Depend on Weather</p>
        <p>There are about a dozen domestic producers of room air-conditioners, with the Fedders Corporation, the Whirlpool Corporation - which makes them for Sears, Roebuck -and White Consolidated Industries among the leaders. Imports, mostly from Japan, have been gradually increasing but remain a relatively minor factor, accounting for about 16 percent of total sales in 1987.</p>
        <p>Unlike most other appliances, room air-conditioners are heavily dependent on weather for sales. That makes decisions on production schedules tough calls for the manufacturers.</p>
        <p>If a company increases output and the summer is warmer than usual, it stands to increase sales and market share. But if the summer is cool, it may be stuck with expensive, unsold machines.</p>
        <p>''You have to plan for an average year,'' said Robert C. Dixon, director of merchandising for Whirlpool's appliance group. ''If not, you are likely to go broke carrying over excessive inventory.''</p>
        <p>But even boom years are not without their problems, Mr. Dixon added. 'When you sell out to the walls you make people unhappy because you can't supply what they want.''</p>
        <p>Industry executives are divided over the retail sales outlook for the next few summers. ''The problem is that for the last 10 or 15 years we've had benchmark demand of about 3.2 million units a year,'' said John Monaco, assistant general manager for appliances at the Quasar Company. ''Now we've had two hot summers in a row. There is no reason to believe that this new level of demand will continue.'' 'It's Getting Warmer'</p>
        <p>But Jerry Rudinsky, vice president for light residential products at the Carrier Corporation, thinks the pattern has changed. ''I personally believe in the greenhouse effect,'' he said, referring to the theory that the earth's climate is becoming warmer. ''It's getting warmer all over; the flowers are blooming in England right now.''</p>
        <p>Trying to forecast the weather in any detail is futile, most industry executives say. ''We subscribed to a professional weather forecasting service for a while,'' said Larry D. Cain, a vice president at a White Consolidated plant in Dublin, Ohio. ''We found, though, that it was not much better than the Farmer's Almanac.''</p>
        <p>The official industry forecast, issued by the Association of Home Appliance Manufacturers, is for factory sales of 3,750,000 units in the 1989 calendar year. Since dealer stocks are said to be almost nonexistent, sales will be limited by factory capacity if demand is strong.</p>
        <p>To insure that it will have an adequate supply of rotary compressors, a critical and hard to obtain component, Carrier has invested in a joint venture factory in Korea to produce them, Mr. Rudinsky said. How the Compressor Works</p>
        <p>The compressor is the heart of an air-conditioner, refrigerator or other cooling device. It compresses the refrigeration fluid, an action that heats it. The fluid is then allowed to cool to room temperature, after which it expands from its compressed state, which lowers its temperature further.</p>
        <p>Older units had reciprocating compressors, which used pistons to compress the fluid. But they tended to be noisy and prone to vibration. ''Window shakers,'' Mr. Rudinsky called them. Newer models have rotary compressors, which eliminate the pistons and are generally quieter, more energy-efficient and vibrate less.</p>
        <p>But it takes two years and about $50 million to build and de-bug a rotary compressor factory. And such factories can be technically difficult. The General Electric Company discovered that last year when a new line of rotary compressors for refrigerators proved to be defective. The cost was estimated at several hundred million dollars.</p>
        <p>As a result, many air-conditioner manufacturers in this country have stopped making compressors and are relying instead on manufacturers in the Far East. Demand in Asia Grows</p>
        <p>''Compressors are in tight supply,'' said Charles Marino, vice president for marketing at the Friedrich Corporation in San Antonio. ''China has put big demands on Asian producers, and the Japanese domestic market for air-conditioners has been growing.''</p>
        <p>Many executives fear that if demand for air-conditioners remains strong through August, as it did last year, the shortage of compressors may again keep manufacturers from filling all orders. Others are more optimistic. Sal Giordano Jr., chief executive of Fedders, said inventories and production levels should be sufficient to avoid shortages.</p>
        <p>The last two hot summers have disrupted normal production and distribution patterns and may have changed customer buying habits as well. In the past, air-conditioner factories began production in the fall and shipped most products in the spring. Because last year's sales stripped shelves bare, distributors and retailers are placing orders much earlier.</p>
        <p>''We've found that some retailers wanted delivery in the fourth quarter of last year, rather than in the first or second quarters of this year, which would be typical,'' said Barbara Van Blarcum, director of investor relations at Fedders. The 'Fear Factor'</p>
        <p>Such early stocking of what is usually a seasonal product has led to speculation that customers who wilted last summer will buy an air-conditioner early this year. ''There is a fear factor still out there,'' said Mr. Marino of Friedrich. ''Customers remember what it was like.''</p>
        <p>In more normal times, it was an industry axiom that it took at least three straight days of temperatures in the 90's to set off a wave of buying.</p>
        <p>An early blast of heat could accelerate a trend of pre-emptive buying at a time when retailers are still restocking. ''If we have an early period of sustained heat while the dealers only have a little inventory, there could be a problem,'' said Mr. Cain of White Consolidated.</p>
        <p>Even if temperatures this summer are more normal, some air-conditioner makers say, the underlying level of demand may increase because machines sold in the late 1960's and early 70's are wearing out.</p>
        <p>'We're not totally weather dependent,'' Mr. Rudinsky said. ''We could have a swing of 400,000 or 500,000 units in a peak year, but there is a base of about 3.5 million a year there as long as the economy stays in good order.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
