<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PRESIDENT URGES STEPS TO TIGHTEN LAW ON CLEAN AIR</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="258284"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SULFUR DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NITROUS OXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FACTORIES AND INDUSTRIAL PLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">URBAN AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON MONOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAZARDOUS AND TOXIC SUBSTANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service"></org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REILLY, WILLIAM K (ADMR)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CLEAN AIR ACT OF 1970</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7DE143EF930A25755C0A96F948260" item-length="1721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PRESIDENT URGES STEPS TO TIGHTEN LAW ON CLEAN AIR</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Saying ''we will make the 1990's the era for clean air,'' President Bush today proposed an array of costly measures to strengthen the nation's law for fighting air pollution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Saying ''we will make the 1990's the era for clean air,'' President Bush today proposed an array of costly measures to strengthen the nation's law for fighting air pollution.</p>
        <p>Saying ''we will make the 1990's the era for clean air,'' President Bush today proposed an array of costly measures to strengthen the nation's law for fighting air pollution.</p>
        <p>In a speech at the White House, the President asked that the Clean Air Law of 1970 be amended to cut almost in half sulfur dioxide emissions from coal-burning power plants. Sulfur dioxide is a leading component of acid rain.Mr. Bush also recommended other efforts to combat urban smog and reduce emissions of toxic chemicals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's proposal marked a break with the Reagan Administration, which for eight years essentially opposed all efforts to impose antipollution requirements on industry. With Mr. Bush's support, the initiative is expected to break the deadlock in Congress that has blocked any change in the Clean Air Act since 1977. Economists' Argument Prevails</p>
        <p>For the first time, the arguments of economists have apparently found a receptive audience at the White House. Mr. Bush's proposals would allow companies to buy and sell the right to pollute and thus let the market decide the cheapest way to contain smokestack emissions. The adoption of such a market-oriented approach would alter the thrust of antipollution efforts for decades to come.</p>
        <p>If enacted as described by the President, the proposals could significantly lower threats to health and the environment now posed by air pollution.</p>
        <p>They could also require heavy investments by industry, including electric utilities and the automotive and oil businesses. William K. Reilly, Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, estimated that the costs to industry of complying with the President's clean air program could reach $14 billion to $18 billion a year when it is in full effect.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly, who urged the President to propose far-reaching measures, appears to have prevailed largely, although not entirely. His views were opposed by many Presidential advisers who cautioned that the costs would burden the economy.</p>
        <p>''It won't be easy; some hard choices will have to be made,'' Mr. Reilly said at a briefing for reporters. But he added: ''Today is a historic moment for the environment. I believe we can look forward to the fulfilling the promise of the Clean Air Act.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush outlined his proposals to members of Congress, state officials and environmentalists, who generally endorsed the President's goals as representing an important change from the previous Administration. Some, however, expressed doubt that the means proposed by the President were adequate to reach the goals.</p>
        <p>While industry groups also spoke favorably of the President's initiative, there were some complaints, particularly from electric utilities and the oil industry, which said certain requirements were excessive or unnecessary. President's Proposals</p>
        <p>Among the specific proposals offered by the President for cleaning the nation's air was a 10-million-ton reduction in emissions of sulfur dioxide from coal-burning electric power plants by the year 2000, somewhat less than half the amount currently emitted, and cutting emissions of nitrogen oxides by two million tons a year, or about a one-tenth reduction.</p>
        <p>The oxides of sulfur and nitrogen change chemically as they move through the atmosphere and fall to earth as acidic rain, snow, fog or dust. Such pollution, much of which originates in the Midwest, harms life in lakes and streams and is suspected of damaging forests and injuring human health, particularly in the northeastern United States and in Canada.</p>
        <p>Half the reductions would have to be accomplished by 1995 and the rest by 2000, under the proposal. Companies would be free to decide how to reach the goal. They could use scrubbers, special equipment on smokestacks that removes sulfur by a chemical reaction; they could burn coal with lower sulfur content; they could encourage their customers to conserve electricity, thus reducing the amount of coal they burn, or they could adopt new technology that allows them to burn coal in ways that do not emit pollution. Those who choose the new technology would have until 2003 to meet the final deadline to allow time for the equipment to be developed. Selling Pollution Rights</p>
        <p>The first phase of required cuts would affect some 107 power plants in 18 states. As an incentive to reaching the goals, plants within the same state would be allowed to trade pollution rights; that is, if they exceeded the required reductions, they could sell rights to emit extra pollution to other companies or transfer rights to other plants within the same company.</p>
        <p>Senator Robert C. Byrd, Democrat of West Virginia, said the President's proposal would ''decimate'' the companies that mine high-sulfur coal, which are largely in Eastern states like his, because power plants would take the easiest route to achieving the reductions and switch to low-sulfur coal, which comes mainly from mines in the West.</p>
        <p>When he was Senate majority leader, Senator Byrd effectively opposed acid rain legislation for many years and he remains a powerful voice on issues that affect the coal industry. Urban Air Quality</p>
        <p>The President proposed an extensive list of measures to deal with urban smog and carbon monoxide that threaten the health of more than 100 million Americans in some 100 cities.</p>
        <p>Chemicals from motor vehicles, factories and businesses like bakeries and dry cleaners react with sunlight to form ozone, a main component of smog. Ozone has been found to cause serious respiratory problems, especially in asthmatics, children and the elderly.</p>
        <p>Carbon monoxide from vehicle tailpipes has been shown to contribute to heart disease.</p>
        <p>Although the deadline under current law for reducing smog to relatively harmless levels has long since passed, many cities have been unable to achieve the goal. The President's plan calls for all but a few cities to reach the ozone standard by 2000. The three cities where that would be most difficult, Los Angeles, New York and Houston, would be given until 2010, but would have to show progress each year.</p>
        <p>The President called for these measures to improve urban air quality:</p>
        <p>* Controls would be stricter on tailpipes of motor vehicles to reduce hydrocarbon and nitrogen oxide emissions.</p>
        <p>* Cleaner-burning alternatives like natural gas and alcohol would be used instead of gasoline in the most seriously polluted areas.</p>
        <p>* Gasoline refiners would be required to reduce the volatility of gasoline refinery products to prevent fumes from escaping from engines and service stations would be required to install equipment to capture gasoline vapors during refueling.</p>
        <p>* New controls would be placed on emissions of volatile organic chemicals from small sources like dry cleaners and from sites where hazardous wastes are disposed.</p>
        <p>* The 20 cities with the worst ozone problems would have to reduce such pollution by 3 percent a year.</p>
        <p>* Cities with carbon monoxide problems would be required to use some alternative fuels that produce less of that pollutant.</p>
        <p>The President has also directed the Environmental Protection Agency to devise a plan under which automobile makers could reach antipollution goals using market incentives, trading pollution rights the way utilities could. Toxic Air Pollution</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. has estimated that industry each year emits 2.7 billion pounds of toxic chemicals into the air. Many of those chemicals can cause cancer and others pose the threat of neurological disease, respiratory illness or birth defects.</p>
        <p>The President's program would require polluters to employ ''maximum available control technology'' to reduce such pollution by 75 percent in 10 years. A second phase would require the E.P.A. to determine to what extent dangerous chemicals are still being emitted after controls are installed and to take additional steps if the risks are still too high.</p>
        <p>S. William Becker, executive director of the State and Territorial Air Pollution Program Administrators, an association of state officials, said the provisions regulating air pollution were the weakest among the proposals. He said the plan gives too much discretion to the environmental agency to determine acceptable risks.</p>
        <p>Joseph Goffman, a lawyer for the Environmental Defense fund, a nonprofit group, said that even though there were loopholes in the President's program, it was important because it signaled his commitment to clean air. ''All bills now will be measured by his commitment,'' Mr. Goffman said.</p>
        <p>The Senate majority leader, George J. Mitchell of Maine, said ''the President deserves credit for his willingness to propose clean air legislation,'' although he called the acid rain provisions and some other specifics inadequate.</p>
        <p>Several industry statements, while commending the President's goals, expressed disappointment about specific means. The American Petroleum Institute objected to a requirement for alternative fuels, urging instead only a pilot program to test them. The Edison Electric Institute, the trade group of the electric utility industry, said the acid rain program should wait for clean coal technology to be developed.</p>
        <p>But the American Gas Association praised the President's effort to ''break the stalemate'' on clean air, particularly the flexibility it would allow for the use of such fuels as natural gas.  Three Steps Toward Clean Air  1. Reduce sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide emissions  Sulfur dioxide emissions would be reduced by 10 million tons, or 50 percent, through restrictions on coal-burning power plants. Nitrous oxide emissions would be cut by 2 million tons, or about 1 percent. These two kinds of emissions are a chief cause of acid rain.  2. Reduce ozone and carbon monoxide  Market incentives would encourage the production of cars powered by alcohol to limit ozone-causing emissions. Restirctions on auto emissions would be tightened. Cities would be expected to meet health standards for ozone and carbon monoxide by the year 2000.  3. Reduce industrial pollution  Industry would be required to use the newest technology to curb the release of cancer-causing and other toxic chemicals. Plan anticipates reductions in airborne toxic chemicals between 75 percent and 90 percent, and the elimination of three-fourths of the annual cancer deaths attributed to them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
