<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Forests Are Still Vanishing</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="234301"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRAZIL</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WICKER, TOM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890324T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D9123AF937A15750C0A96F948260" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Forests Are Still Vanishing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Tom Wicker</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WICKER, TOM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Eastern region of the United States once was covered with dense forests. Westward to about the 95th meridian, beyond the Mississippi River, mighty trees covered the land, save in what are now Illinois and Iowa.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Eastern region of the United States once was covered with dense forests. Westward to about the 95th meridian, beyond the Mississippi River, mighty trees covered the land, save in what are now Illinois and Iowa.</p>
        <p>The Eastern region of the United States once was covered with dense forests. Westward to about the 95th meridian, beyond the Mississippi River, mighty trees covered the land, save in what are now Illinois and Iowa.</p>
        <p>Not until the mid-19th century did settlers moving west, ''which they had for generations seen at sunset through traceries of the twigs and leafage of the primal forests,'' reach the Great Plains and stand ''at last with the forests behind them.''</p>
        <p>That was the end of ''Book One of our history,'' wrote Herbert Quick, an Iowa editor and novelist, in his autobiography. Even by then the great forests through which the pioneers had pushed with ax and rifle were pocked and spotted with farm clearings and primitive roads; as the nation developed into an agricultural-industrial colossus, the destruction of the Eastern forests rapidly proceeded.</p>
        <p>Now there's little left of the vast tree cover that once stretched from the Atlantic to the Mississippi and beyond; and only on the Pacific Slope are ancient or ''old-growth'' forests in sizable tracts still to be found in this country. Even they may be gone within 20 or 30 years.</p>
        <p>Thus has the United States done throughout its history what a righteous world denounces Brazil for doing today; no wonder Brazilian leaders point to the United States as their role model in deforestation. And even without Brazil's development needs, the U.S. continues to clear away its most valuable forests.</p>
        <p>The United States Forest Service regulates most of the nation's remaining old-growth timber, almost all of it in the Pacific Northwest and Alaska, including the important temperate rain forests of the Olympic Peninsula in Washington. But that doesn't mean these forests are protected from cutting.</p>
        <p>The Forest Service is charged not with preserving forests but with their utilization - timber productivity as well as recreation and the protection of wildlife habitat and ecosystems. So it regularly permits private lumber companies, as they deplete their own forests, to cut Forest Service timber.</p>
        <p>Old-growth trees, 300 or more years old, make particularly valuable timber for their huge size and tight grain. Critics charge that the Forest Service does not sufficiently protect these irreplaceable trees or the remarkable ecosystems that surround them, and that it contends twice as much old-growth remains on its lands as is actually the case.</p>
        <p>Wilderness Society officials believe, for example, that within two or three years no ''ecologically significant'' old-growth will remain in the Gifford Pinchot National Forest in Washington. West Coast conifer forests unique to the United States are being cut, too; sometimes mixed stands of spruce, hemlock and cedar are inadequately replaced with Douglas fir alone, making for a very different forest. In old-growth areas, of course, saplings planted today hardly replace trees that took hundreds of years to grow.</p>
        <p>For the loggers to get at the trees, roads must be cut, increasing forest destruction and preventing affected areas from ever being declared protected ''wilderness.'' In six Southern Appalachian national forests encompassing 3.5 million acres, the Forest Service plans to open more than two million acres to logging in the next decade, doubling the timber harvest. The plans call for more than 3,000 miles of new roads in the six areas.</p>
        <p>An active Federal tree-planting program was established in the 1985 farm bill, but the need is enormous and growing with every slash of the saw. The Wilderness Society estimates that up to 3.1 million Forest Service acres need to be reforested. The American Forestry Association has identified 20 million open acres in the Southeast alone that should be planted to trees.</p>
        <p>In cities, towns and suburbs, which the Forestry Association calls ''heat islands,'' it urges the need by 1992 for 100 million more trees to be planted in yards around houses and businesses, and 60 million more along streets - not just for scenery but to achieve huge savings in energy use.</p>
        <p>Deforestation anywhere - in Montana or Brazil - means soil erosion, fouled streams, increased vulnerability to flood and wind, vanished habitat, extinct species, a heritage discarded. The disappearance of trees, moreover, with their capacity for absorbing carbons from the atmosphere, is a major cause of global warming, with all its dangers. In these circumstances, the United States needs to plant more and cut less; until it does, the finger it points at others will not be clean.</p>
        <p>IN THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
