<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The American Sense of Peril: A Stifling Cost of Modern Life</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="FIRST OF TWO ARTICLES ON RISK AND PUBLIC POLICY" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="248220"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="ECONOMIC WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DB113AF93BA35756C0A96F948260" item-length="1786" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The American Sense of Peril: A Stifling Cost of Modern Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER PASSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Is the slight risk of contracting cancer from Alar too high a price to pay for crisper apples? Is the dramatic increase in milk production available through genetically engineered growth hormones worth the unknown risk to children's health? If a few aging aircraft suffer explosive decompressions, should all old airliners be grounded?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Is the slight risk of contracting cancer from Alar too high a price to pay for crisper apples? Is the dramatic increase in milk production available through genetically engineered growth hormones worth the unknown risk to children's health? If a few aging aircraft suffer explosive decompressions, should all old airliners be grounded?</p>
        <p>Is the slight risk of contracting cancer from Alar too high a price to pay for crisper apples? Is the dramatic increase in milk production available through genetically engineered growth hormones worth the unknown risk to children's health? If a few aging aircraft suffer explosive decompressions, should all old airliners be grounded?</p>
        <p>Risks to health and safety and the complex questions of public policy they create are seemingly everywhere these days. And while there is little statistical evidence that the hazards of daily life are on the rise, a wide range of academic and business experts believe that Americans' perception of increased peril is stifling technology, wasting billions of dollars and, ironically, making it more difficult to contain the most serious risks.</p>
        <p>One way to restore a sense of balance between risk and reward, psychologists say, is to package information about risk in ways that people can more easily grasp. But economists and legal scholars argue that equilibrium will not be possible until there is wider understanding that unfamiliar and often unmeasurable risk is the price of prosperity and societal achievement. Serious Hazards Exposed</p>
        <p>Not every newly discovered peril is trivial. Without the selfless and often unappreciated efforts of health and safety activists, serious hazards ranging from asbestos to radon to lead would have gone unnoticed and underregulated for years longer. Any change in government institutions or public attitudes that tended to silence such gadflies would hardly serve the public interest.</p>
        <p>But by broad statistical measures, Americans have never been safer. Life expectancy at birth in 1986 was 74.8 years, up a full four years since 1970, largely because of a dramatic drop in deaths from heart disease and strokes.</p>
        <p>Cancer deaths, adjusted for age, are up slightly in the last two decades, but not, apparently, due to man-made hazards in the air, water, workplace and food supply.</p>
        <p>A landmark study, published in the Journal of the National Cancer Institute in 1981, linked just 2 percent of all deaths from malignancies to such environmental exposure. Michael Gough, a senior fellow at Resources for the Future, confirmed this striking conclusion last year by extrapolating deaths from Environmental Protection Agency estimates of the number of cancer cases that are due to involuntary exposure to man-made hazards. Statistically Safer to Fly</p>
        <p>Even the high-profile threats have not changed the risks of untimely death or injury. The skies may be crowded, the planes aging and the pilots inexperienced, but the trend in aircraft fatalities is downward. From 1982 through 1986, Americans were 70 times as likely to die in an automobile trip as they were traveling the same route on a scheduled airline.</p>
        <p>Indeed, in a technological catastrophe of singularly grand scale, the Chernobyl accident, the toll in human life and suffering is barely visible against the canvas of natural hazards. An assessment published last December in the journal Science said 237 people received massive doses of radiation from the explosion and fire at the Soviet nuclear reactor and 31 people died soon thereafter. Another 4,000, exposed to relatively high doses in an 18-mile radius of the plant, are about two and a half times times as likely to die from leukemia as the general population, raising the ultimate death toll by fewer than 20.</p>
        <p>But outside the immediate area, the report argues, the long-term impact will be widely diffused and barely discernible. Of the people in the northern hemisphere who lived in the path of Chernobyl fallout, 513 million will eventually die of cancer. At most, the report estimates, 17,400 of those cancer deaths - one in 29,000 - will be linked to the reactor disaster. Major Risks Are the Same</p>
        <p>The primary environmental causes of premature death and disease, say most scientists, are the same as they were decades ago: smoking, diets rich in fat and lean in fiber, lack of exercise, alcohol abuse. Many Americans, however, apparently do not understand the relative risks, or do not find the numbers reassuring.</p>
        <p>The clearest examples are in health care. Bendectin, a drug still recognized by the Food and Drug Administration as safe and effective for the treatment of nausea in pregnancy, was taken off the market by the Dow Chemical Company's Merrell Dow Pharmaceuticals Inc. because some juries decided it caused birth defects. All intrauterine birth control devices were permanently withdrawn by their manufacturers after one defective brand, the Dalkon Shield, was found to cause pelvic inflammatory disease. And according to George Zeidenstein, the president of the Population Council, private industry's development of contraceptives has been retarded because the ''ratio of potential profit to risk is way down.''</p>
        <p>Life-saving medicines have been less dramatically affected, but even here, the measures to compensate for risk can radically change the economics of distribution. The cost of a common childhood vaccination, for diptheria, pertussis and tetanus, rose from 50 cents in 1982 to $11.40 in 1986, as its manufacturer, the Lederle Laboratories, a division of American Cyanamid Company, amassed cash to pay legal claims for rare but predictable side effects.</p>
        <p>Peter W. Huber, an engineer, lawyer and author of ''The Legal Revolution and its Consequences'' notes that similar ''safety taxes'' are added to the price of thousands of other goods and services, distorting production and reducing living standards. By Mr. Huber's reckoning, the safety tax represents 30 percent of the cost of a step ladder, one-third the cost of a ride on a Long Island tour bus and $300 of the cost of giving birth in New York City.</p>
        <p>Sometimes the implicit safety tax is so high that it even inhibits the introduction of substitutes for dangerous products. Richard J. Mahoney, the chief executive of the Monsanto Company, said the company developed a safer alternative to cancer-causing asbestos in brake linings. But the company chose not to take the chance of marketing the new product because juries might decide it was not safe enough. Environmental Threats</p>
        <p>A parallel cost is the distortion in priorities created by coping with environmental threats. Frank Young, Commissioner of the Food and Drug Administration, notes that while the risks from pesticides in food are ''low and decreasing,'' there has been an ''explosion'' of disease caused by contamination from microbes. A result, the agency says, are some 33 million cases of gastrointestinal illness, with serious consequences for the very young and very old. But there is little public pressure to toughen safety standards for the major offenders: meat, eggs, fish and poultry.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency also regards itself as handicapped by Congressional and public misperception of relative risks.</p>
        <p>In 1987, the agency published ''Unfinished Business,'' a staff ranking of 31 environmental problems. Items high on the scientists' list included indoor radon exposure, global warming from the greenhouse effect and chemical discharges into estuaries and coastal waters. But much of the agency's money and effort is devoted to managing lower-level risks like toxic waste dumps, underground storage tanks and non-hazardous muncipal waste sites.</p>
        <p>''E.P.A.'s priorities,'' the report drily concluded, ''appear more closely aligned with public opinion than with our estimated risks.''</p>
        <p>Another area where perceived risks may have distorted environmental and economic priorities is in energy production. Reports issued last month, one by Salomon Brothers and one by Arthur Anderson and Cambridge Energy Research Associates, warn of impending shortages in electricity generating capacity, notably in the Northeast. But under pressure from local and state governments, responding to public fears about nuclear energy, the Long Island Lighting Company is giving up the battle to operate its completed, 800-megawatt nuclear plant at Shoreham. Costs Will Spread Widely</p>
        <p>The $5.5 billion loss on the plant will be apportioned among customers and stockholders. plus the United States Treasury in the form of $850 million in lost corporate income taxes. Lost power will in part be replaced with fossil fuel plants that will inevitably produce local air pollution and add greenhouse effect gases to the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>What explains the public's decreasing tolerance of some risks and apparent indifference to others? Paul Slovic of the Decision Research Corporation in Eugene, Oregon and Baruch Fischhoff of Carnegie Mellon University, point out that perceived risk is not always related to the probability of injury.</p>
        <p>Easily tolerated risks include ones that people can choose to avoid (chain saws, skiing), that are familiar to those exposed (smoking), or that have been around a long time (fireworks). Poorly tolerated risks are involuntary (exposure to nuclear waste), have long delayed effects (pesticides) or unknown effects (genetic engineering).</p>
        <p>As Dr. Slovic notes, nuclear and chemical technologies fare especially badly in such subjective rankings. Indeed, the general acceleration of technical change and integration of new technology in products helps to explain the increase in public anxiety about risk.</p>
        <p>Paul R. Portney, an economist at Resources For the Future, believes there is another reason Americans worry more and trust government less: the casual approach toward regulation flaunted by the Reagan Administration. Legacy of Watt, Gorsuch</p>
        <p>Senior Reagan appointees, including James G. Watt, the first Reagan era Secretary of the Interior, and Anne Gorsuch, the E.P.A. Administrator, reduced public confidence in the Government's will to put the broad social interests in the environment ahead of parochial business concerns. That, in turn, invited tighter oversight by Congress, leaving the current generation of regulators with far less discretion to balance economic and environmental needs.</p>
        <p>Yet another ingredient in the anti-risk brew, Peter Huber asserts, is the legal doctrine of strict liability, which has made producers far more vulnerable to lawsuits. By effectively prohibiting buyers from bearing personal responsibility for injuries, the courts have inadvertantly lowered society's tolerance for risk.</p>
        <p>Thirty years ago most people who fell off ladders assumed it was their own fault. Today, Mr. Huber suggests, they would be inclined to question the design of the rungs or - more insidiously - assume that manufacturers have an obligation to make ladders accident-free, no matter what the cost.</p>
        <p>Next: What experts say could be done to balance safety against other economic and social goals.</p>
        <p>ECONOMIC WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
