<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boston Journal; Waiting for the Snow to Fall and Wondering Why</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="217601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DD123BF935A15752C0A96F948260" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boston Journal; Waiting for the Snow to Fall and Wondering Why</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Jan. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: What would Henry James have had to write about this winter? What would John Singer Sargent have had to paint? The artists who captured this city's temperament using scenes of the snow-touched Boston Common might have been frustrated this January, the first in recent memory with no real snowfall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: What would Henry James have had to write about this winter? What would John Singer Sargent have had to paint? The artists who captured this city's temperament using scenes of the snow-touched Boston Common might have been frustrated this January, the first in recent memory with no real snowfall.</p>
        <p>What would Henry James have had to write about this winter? What would John Singer Sargent have had to paint? The artists who captured this city's temperament using scenes of the snow-touched Boston Common might have been frustrated this January, the first in recent memory with no real snowfall.</p>
        <p>January is normally the city's snowiest month, a time when the whir of car tires mired in slush interrupts the serenity of dazzling snowflakes. While the average January snowfall is 12.5 inches, only seven-tenths of an inch of snow has fallen this year. A light snow is forecast for Thursday but even that is expected to turn to rain.</p>
        <p>Much of the Northeast has experienced similarly dry weather this winter, but the phenomenon has been particularly striking in the Boston area, where major winter storms are the stuff of legend and where Gov. Michael S. Dukakis made his antique snow blower a symbol of his Presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>Weather forecasters stress that anything could happen, and Bostonians are not putting their sleds into storage yet. ''Two big storms and we could be back to normal,'' said Jeff Waldsteicher, a meteorologist with the National Weather Service bureau here.</p>
        <p>Among the people who have their fingers crossed for big storms are the managers of the city's water supply, now at its lowest level in 15 years. The Quabbin Reservoir in central Massachusetts, which feeds water to Boston and much of eastern Massachusetts, is now only 69 percent full, as against the usual 80 percent.</p>
        <p>''If we don't get above-normal precipitation soon, I think the outcome is going to be a very serious water supply problem in the summer months,'' said Ilyas Bhatti, director of the division of watershed management for the region.</p>
        <p>Threats of a summer drought, daily temperatures in the 50's, and memories of August's heat wave have made popular dinner conversation of a global trend to higher temperatures as pollutants in the earth's upper atmosphere trap heat like a greenhouse. One prevailing joke is that property values will soon rise as warmer temperatures cause Southerners to flee north.</p>
        <p>Although climatologists disagree on the origins of this winter's dry spell, they rule out the greenhouse effect as a cause. ''I do not believe the greenhouse effect has anything to do with a mild January or a hot summer,'' said Harvey Leonard, station meteorologist for WNEV-TV, Boston's CBS affiliate. ''Even if the greenhouse effect were at work, all it could do would be to elevate temperatures by a half a degree.''</p>
        <p>Louis A. Scuderi, an assistant professor of geography at Boston University, believes the dry weather here could be a result of ''El Nino,'' a Pacific current of abnormally warm water near South America that has been linked to climate changes around the globe. But Mr. Leonard said he believed the culprit was an opposing force that some scientists have called ''La Nina,'' an especially cold strip of Pacific water.</p>
        <p>Mr. Waldsteicher of the National Weather Service, disagreeing with them both, attributed the weather to random shifts in the jet stream.</p>
        <p>As pleasant as the weather may be for cyclists and traffic officers, a lot of people who live here really like snow and are very disappointed. Mr. Leonard said that the 100 local ''weather watchers'' who report temperatures in their towns for his evening report are ''kind of depressed'' over the period of clemency.</p>
        <p>''Weather freaks enjoy the exciting weather,'' he said, ''To be perfectly honest, they'd like to see some action coming out of the atmosphere.''</p>
        <p>Ski enthusiasts are also in a bad mood, although not so bad as the operators of ski resorts, who have been running hopeful advertisements about the efficiency of their snow-making machines.</p>
        <p>The good news is that many towns have saved money that would normally be spend on snow removal and rock salt for icy roads. At this time last year, the city of Boston had spent almost $2.25 million to remove ice and snow from roads. This year, only $700,000 has been spent, much of it on equipment upkeep, according to Joseph Casazza, Boston's Commissioner of Public Works.</p>
        <p>Bostonians like to collect trivia about the Blizzard of 1888, and reminisce about the storm of 1978, when rapidly mounting snowdrifts stranded motorists along highways. But strange things can happen here in warmer winters, too. On Jan. 15, 1919, unseasonably mild weather was partly to blame for the explosion of a 90-foot-tall molasses tank in the city's North End. Molten molasses, 2.3 million gallons of it, flooded the city, killing 21 people and bogging hundreds of horses in streets of mire.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
