<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Bush Budget: Alive on Arrival</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="222405"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DD1E3EF932A25751C0A96F948260" item-length="671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Bush Budget: Alive on Arrival</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush has given new life to the ''dead-on-arrival'' budget that Ronald Reagan submitted only four weeks ago. Mr. Bush mainly repeats the Reagan program, re-flavoring it with small alterations. More important than his details, he avoids confrontation and invites negotiation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush has given new life to the ''dead-on-arrival'' budget that Ronald Reagan submitted only four weeks ago. Mr. Bush mainly repeats the Reagan program, re-flavoring it with small alterations. More important than his details, he avoids confrontation and invites negotiation.</p>
        <p>President Bush has given new life to the ''dead-on-arrival'' budget that Ronald Reagan submitted only four weeks ago. Mr. Bush mainly repeats the Reagan program, re-flavoring it with small alterations. More important than his details, he avoids confrontation and invites negotiation.</p>
        <p>Two fundamental conditions govern the Bush budget: a new President has little leverage on spending in his first year, and Mr. Bush's predecessor left precious little room for new initiatives. Reducing the huge and stubborn deficit comes first; deficit reduction plus ''no new taxes'' equals not-much-new-spending.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush declares candidly that his positions are not fixed in concrete. Indeed, he doesn't even take a position on some deeply divisive issues, and conceals some proposed cuts that would be unpopular. While his failure to spell out everything clearly frustrates criticism, his evident effort to seek compromise with the Democratic-controlled Congress is a welcome relief from the frequent contention and paralysis of the Reagan years.</p>
        <p>To develop credibility before the world, the Government must be seen to be making a substantial dent in the annual deficits. Mr. Bush proffers a way to get deficit reduction back on track without an immediate tax increase and without outrageously distorting the facts.</p>
        <p>Indeed, budget experts agree that it shouldn't be too difficult to cut the deficit to $100 billion next year from more than $160 billion this year, as required by law. Converging trends in spending and revenue will help. But after next year, deficit reduction will be much harder, and Mr. Bush still offers no credible way to achieve it without raising taxes.</p>
        <p>The Bush budget offers plenty to shoot at. The President asserts that lowering the tax on capital gains will increase revenue by $5 billion; it's a fantastic assertion. At a minimum, honest men disagree on whether lowering capital gains rates will increase or decrease revenues. Mr. Bush can't expect Congress to buy his extravagant claim, especially not when the Democrats don't like the idea anyway; its benefits are sharply focused on the very rich.</p>
        <p>Nor is Congress likely to buy his proposal to curb cost-of-living adjustments for Federal pensions. The proposal makes sense, but Mr. Bush told Congress in his budget speech that ''we have a moral contract with our senior citizens'' to maintain Social Security benefits and full COLA's. Why does he feel free to breach that contract when it comes to older Americans who worked for the Government or served in the military?</p>
        <p>The proposed reduction in the Reagan defense spending plan looks like a cutback; it's actually an increase, with strings attached. Mr. Reagan wanted defense spending to go up by 2 percent more than the rate of inflation. Mr. Bush proposes an increase simply to keep pace with inflation. But Congress has voted less than this ''zero'' increase for four years now. That means Mr. Bush is really asking for more than recent Congresses would provide - plus still more in later years. Moreover, he insists that Congress commit next year's defense savings for other Bush proposals. Fat chance.</p>
        <p>Most of Mr. Bush's refinements on the Reagan plan fit his ''kinder, gentler'' theme - among others, canceling the Reagan proposal to cut back on Medicaid, and offering more money for Head Start, the homeless, national parks and acid rain. The funds he would add for AIDS research are listed as a ''priority initiative,'' but represent no initiative at all; Mr. Reagan proposed the same. And the cuts he has in mind for some social programs are so well shrouded in rhetoric and misty numbers that they went unnoticed at first.</p>
        <p>After eight years of Reagan budgets, some programs need more than token increases, and Congress may want to go further than Mr. Bush. Congress will also challenge his cuts, especially deep in Medicare and agriculture. The key word in President Bush's message is ''negotiation.'' With his Inaugural and first budget now behind him, the bargaining has just begun.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
