<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If Radiation Were the Color and Texture of Oil; A Birth on L.I.</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="248250"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SHOREHAM NUCLEAR POWER PLANT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TOSHER, DAVID</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0D71F3AF93BA35756C0A96F948260" item-length="318" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If Radiation Were the Color and Texture of Oil; A Birth on L.I.</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Through the years I have read with frustration and incomprehension your editorial stance on the issue of the Shoreham, L.I., nuclear plant. ''The Energy Vandals'' (editorial, April 20) has moved me to raging anger. You fail to understand that the conscientious citizens you speak of fret not only about America's rising dependence on foreign oil, but also about nuclear energy and its threatening pollution.</p>
        <p>Against the pristine backdrop of white mountains in Valdez, Alaska, the sight of the sludge-fouled shoreline and oil-slicked baby seals strike revulsion in everyone. For a long time Exxon will be inextricably linked with the image of oozing black sludge being carefully removed from our beloved wildlife.</p>
        <p>We are amazed when the chief executive officer of Exxon estimates the cleanup of Valdez will be complete in the autumn of 1989. Had this tragedy been nuclear, the cleanup would take 10,000 years, not 10 months, and we would be revolted by the need for bone-marrow transplants for children rather than the cleansing of oil-covered baby seals.</p>
        <p>If there is a lesson to be learned from Valdez, it is that one should be skeptical when a major industry tells you its operations are safe and that in the event of crisis it will respond promptly. Another lesson is that there are no safeguards against human error of the type demonstrated by the captain of the Valdez.</p>
        <p>I am a Long Islander, one of those involved in the ''folly'' of scrapping Shoreham. In a few days I will experience the birth of my first child. This child inherits the consequences of acid rain, exhaust emissions, antique septic systems, industrial waste, seeping poisonous landfills, fertilizer runoffs, all on a strip of land 4 miles wide and 100 miles long. We of Long Island have stood up to stop one more peril on that long list. No Shoreham ever. DAVID TOSHER  Hampton, L.I., April 21, 1989</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
