<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scientists Link '88 Drought to Natural Cycle in Tropical Pacific</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="211210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WIND</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DROUGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOODS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PACIFIC OCEAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FAR EAST, SOUTH AND SOUTHEAST ASIA AND PACIFIC AREAS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BANGLADESH</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bangladesh</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Bangladesh</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DE153BF930A35752C0A96F948260" item-length="2121" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scientists Link '88 Drought to Natural Cycle in Tropical Pacific</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: LAST year's killing drought in the United States was caused by massive, naturally occurring climatic forces in the tropical Pacific Ocean and had little to do with global warming caused by the greenhouse effect, according to new evidence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: LAST year's killing drought in the United States was caused by massive, naturally occurring climatic forces in the tropical Pacific Ocean and had little to do with global warming caused by the greenhouse effect, according to new evidence.</p>
        <p>LAST year's killing drought in the United States was caused by massive, naturally occurring climatic forces in the tropical Pacific Ocean and had little to do with global warming caused by the greenhouse effect, according to new evidence.</p>
        <p>The same complex forces, involving large-scale shifts in ocean temperatures and winds in the equatorial Pacific, affected not only North America. They also made themselves felt on the other side of the world, scientists say, causing the unusually heavy monsoon rains that in 1988 brought record floods, death and misery to Bangladesh.</p>
        <p>These broad, intricately interconnected relationships between the ocean and the atmosphere have been only dimly understood in the past. But now climatologists are making major strides in understanding the ways in which such relationships in one part of the world drastically affect weather conditions, lives and fortunes in another.</p>
        <p>While most climate experts believe that the greenhouse effect, a global warming caused by pollutants in the atmosphere, will have a major impact in the decades ahead, even those who argue most strongly for that point of view agree that last year's drought was overwhelmingly a product of natural forces. Even if a warming trend is already under way, as some experts believe, on a year-to-year basis events such as last year's changes in the Pacific exert a far stronger influence on the weather, scientists say.</p>
        <p>The tropical Pacific is emerging in some scientists' minds as perhaps the planet's most important source of short-term climatic changes.</p>
        <p>This is the territory of El Nino, the massive strip of abnormally warm water that from time to time stretches westward along the Equator from South America and that sometimes plays havoc with the weather in various parts of the world. But El Nino is only part of the story.</p>
        <p>Climatologists now recognize that it is not just a random phenomenon. It appears periodically, alternating with what has only recently been identified as its opposite twin: an abnormally cold stretch of equatorial water.</p>
        <p>Scientists disagree on what to call the cold cycle. It was first dubbed La Nina, Spanish for ''the girl,'' to distinguish it from El Nino, which means ''the boy,'' or Christ Child, so named because the warm cycle appears near Christmas. Some scientists objected to La Nina as sexist, however, and substituted El Viejo, ''the old man,'' as in Old Man Winter. Still others prefer to avoid all this by simply calling the cycles warm events and cold events.</p>
        <p>It was this cold cycle in the eastern Pacific, some scientists now say, that played a major role in creating the great North American drought of 1988 and the devastating floods that indundated Bangladesh.</p>
        <p>El Nino and its opposite are the two poles of a continuous back-and-forth action in which the surface waters around the Equator in the eastern Pacific go from one temperature extreme to another every 3 to 6 years. Scientists have named the grand atmospheric changes that accompany these swings, and that are tightly interwoven with them, the ''southern oscillation,'' and it is an object of intense study. More Disruption Predicted</p>
        <p>The cold phase that affected last year's climate still persists. And if it continues to dominate that part of the Pacific into this spring (in the Northern Hemisphere), as some forecasters predict, scientists say it could disrupt the worldwide weather picture again. But at this point no one can say exactly what its impact would be.</p>
        <p>Still, the fact that scientists now know as much as they do about these mechanisms is a measure of how far they have come in the last decade in understanding short-term, global climatic change. Improved data collection and more advanced computer models of climatic processes have enabled climatologists to develop at least a rudimentary picture of these processes. Until recently, such a picture hardly existed.</p>
        <p>''What's exciting about it is that three years ago, none of us recognized the cold side of this southern oscillation,'' said Dr. James O'Brien, a meteorologist and oceanographer at Florida State University who this year will head the National Academy of Science's committee on the ocean's role in global climatic change.</p>
        <p>Precisely what triggers a warm or cold phase is not yet perfectly understood, but scientists believe they know much about the general processes at work. A cold phase, such as now exists, develops when strong trade winds, blowing from the east, drive warm surface water to the western Pacific. At the same time, there is an increased upwelling of cold water from the ocean depths off South America.</p>
        <p>Across the Pacific, the warm water driven westward by the trade winds literally piles up in the western Pacific. This warm water intensifies rainstorm activity in that region, producing unusually strong monsoon rains in South and Southeast Asia. This is a major reason why Bangladesh suffered so in 1988. 'Spring Is Transition Time'</p>
        <p>At such a time, skies are relatively clear on the other side of the Pacific, near South America, and the sun begins re-heating the water there. The cycle starts to reverse. The reverse trend accelerates when trade winds are at their weakest, usually in the spring. ''Spring is transition time,'' says Mark A. Cane of Columbia University's Lamont-Doherty Geological Observatory. ''You have the sense that nature rolls its dice in April every year and once it does, the pattern is set for the next year.''</p>
        <p>As the trade winds weaken, warm water from the western Pacific flows back toward the east, and with it, an area of atmospheric instability that generates thunderstorms and rain. This weakens the trade winds further, and the warm water reaches all the way back to South America.</p>
        <p>At the same time, less cold water wells up from the ocean depths. The result of all this is an El Nino. The most severe El Nino of the 1980's, in 1982-83, brought heavy rains and flooding to the west coast of South America and severe drought to Australia and the Philippines.</p>
        <p>On average, each warm and cold phase takes about two years to develop and play out, though some are longer or shorter. Each warm and cold phase also has its own profile -some are major and some are minor. The latest El Nino in 1986-87, for example, was mild, producing sea-surface temperatures of 4 degrees Fahrenheit above average; by contrast, the disastrous 1982-83 event was about 7 degress above average.</p>
        <p>The present phase represents ''an unusually cold side of the coin,'' says Dr. Kevin Trenberth, who heads the Climate Analysis Section at the National Center for Atmospheric Research in Boulder, Colo. Sea-surface temperatures along the Equator dropped 10 degrees from their 1986-87 El Nino high, to about 6 degrees below average. A more usual ''cold event'' brings temperatures of about 3 degrees below average. History of a Drought</p>
        <p>Enter the 1988 United States drought. According to a study by Dr. Trenberth and colleagues that appeared in a recent issue of the journal Science, it happened this way:</p>
        <p>The cold water along the Equator caused a zone of unstable air just to the north, called the intertropical convergence zone, to move farther north. The convergence zone, where trade winds from the Northern and Southern Hemispheres collide, is a major area in which thunderstorms and rain develop. It tends to occupy the warmest water in the region.</p>
        <p>This year, for unexplained reasons, a large, abnormally warm patch of water developed southeast of Hawaii, in effect pulling the convergence zone northward even as the cold water along the Equator pushed it. Eventually, the convergence zone overlapped somewhat with the warm patch to the north. The result was thunderstorm activity in an area where it normally does not occur.</p>
        <p>This area impinged on the southern edge of the eastward-flowing river of air that includes the North American jet stream, which carries the low-pressure areas that bring spring and summer rain to America.</p>
        <p>In this case, the intense thunderstorm activity disturbed the westerlies, like a rock in the middle of a stream, setting up ripples and swirls in the atmosphere. These developed into high- and low-pressure systems that moved the jet stream far to the north. This made way for a large, rainless high-pressure system, which moved into the gap from the south. It dominated the Midwest for weeks, bringing on the drought.</p>
        <p>Once the drought began, Dr. Trenberth said, it fed on itself as evaporation at the Earth's surface decreased and surface temperatures thereby increased, ''so that even if a cloud wanted to form, it doesn't have enough moisture to produce rain.'' 'We Don't Understand'</p>
        <p>For now, other climatologists are treating the Trenberth theory on the drought as they do any new scientific report: as something that must be subjected to further testing. ''It's a sound, useful idea, but it would be stretching it to take it as conclusive at this point,'' said Dr. Cane of Lamont-Doherty. There are probably a number of contributing factors to the drought that have not been identified, he said, adding: ''I don't think we have an understanding of how these droughts come about and why they persist. Which is not to say that we don't understand anything.'' Models of Forecasting</p>
        <p>Dr. Cane and colleagues have developed the most ambitious of a number of models that predict the fluctuations of warm and cold cycles in the tropical Pacific. Based on the latest data, for November, Dr. Cane said that the present cold phase should ''bottom out'' about now and that it should start to ease in the summer.</p>
        <p>A forecast by Dr. O'Brien's group at Florida State, also based on November data, says that the cold phase will last another three or four months. ''That's about as far in the future as we tend to look at those things.''</p>
        <p>A third forecast by a group led by Dr. Tim Barnett at the Scripps Institution of Oceanography at La Jolla, Calif., calls for the cold phase to persist into spring. ''We're looking for next summer and fall to be more or less normal,'' he said. After that, if scientists are right about the new pattern, another swing toward El Nino, the warm phase, should begin.</p>
        <p>Dr. Trenberth said that while global warming from the greenhouse effect may have made the 1988 drought worse, it ''almost certainly'' was not the fundamental cause. Over a long span of time, he said, global warming might make droughts more likely in some parts of the world, and worse wherever they occur. But year-to-year variations in climate are affected more powerfully by ''natural'' climatic forces he said, pointing out that the short-term temperature swings in the southern oscillation are far larger than the short-term differences produced by global warming.</p>
        <p>Dr. James E. Hansen of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, whose testimony on the greenhouse effect at the height of the 1988 drought focused attention on the problem, said in an interview that he agreed with this analysis. Dr. Hansen, on the basis of a mathematical model, holds that as the greenhouse effect gets stronger, the frequency of drought will increase significantly. But this change will not start to be noticed until the 1990's, he said.</p>
        <p>Some scientists believe that the warm and cold swings in the eastern Pacific, because they cover such vast stretches, have more effect on global atmospheric temperatures than the greenhouse effect. One, Dr. O'Brien, is predicting that the present cold phase will bring about a sharp drop in average global temperatures, reducing them to 1950's levels and slowing down planetary warming by 30 to 35 years. Others, while conceding the effect, say that estimate is too high.</p>
        <p>What long-term effect the greenhouse effect may have, in turn, on El Nino and its sibling is a matter for speculation at this point, one of a many unanswered questions that still challenge climatologists.  Global Weather Connections  New findings link last year's drought in the United States and floods in Asia to periodic shifts in winds and ocean temperatures in the tropical Pacific.  THE SOURCE: According to the theory, the drought originated with unusually cold water along the Equator (1), which pushed the intertropical convergence zone (2), where trade winds collide, farther north than usual. Abnormally warm water southeast of Hawaii also pulled the zone northward. The zone overlapped the warm patch (3), resulting in unusual thunderstorm activity (4). The storms disturbed the atmosphere, (5) setting up ripples and swirls that became high- and low-pressure systems. These pushed the jet stream far north (6), making way for a large, rainless high-pressure system (7), which brought weeks of drought.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
