<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic's Notebook; A Film Festival With the Spirit of Margaret Mead</title>
    <meta content="623589SGM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="306383"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E4DF153AF937A35751C1A96F948260" item-length="1297" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic's Notebook; A Film Festival With the Spirit of Margaret Mead</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gods, shamans, peasants and chorus girls populate the works at the Margaret Mead Film Festival, which begins today and runs through Thursday at the American Museum of Natural History. The annual festival, named for the influential anthropologist, may suggest endless accounts of Samoan initiation rites. But the 48 nonfiction films to be shown are eclectic enough to include Hindu pilgrims, rangers at Yosemite National Park and a Chinese-American bubble dancer.</p>
        <p>A sampling of the films (most of which run about an hour) suggests that several are models of innovative documentary film making, while in many others flabbergasting images fight with the sort of droning voice-overs that give documentaries a bad name.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gods, shamans, peasants and chorus girls populate the works at the Margaret Mead Film Festival, which begins today and runs through Thursday at the American Museum of Natural History. The annual festival, named for the influential anthropologist, may suggest endless accounts of Samoan initiation rites. But the 48 nonfiction films to be shown are eclectic enough to include Hindu pilgrims, rangers at Yosemite National Park and a Chinese-American bubble dancer.</p>
        <p>A sampling of the films (most of which run about an hour) suggests that several are models of innovative documentary film making, while in many others flabbergasting images fight with the sort of droning voice-overs that give documentaries a bad name.</p>
        <p>But in most of these works, voices and images of incomparable strangeness float off the screen. These are some examples:</p>
        <p>* ''I would like to visit you and receive a cow,'' Al Hajji, a colorfully robed and stately Muslim, tells a neighbor in Cameroon. ''Al Hajji and His Four Wives'' captures the daily life of this religious teacher, who explains that it helps to keep the peace if you don't reveal one wife's secrets to another.</p>
        <p>* ''I'm Howard Finster, and a stranger from another world,'' says a preacher and high-priced folk artist. ''Howard Finster: Man of Visions'' depicts the curious phenomenon of American folk art as a valuable commodity.</p>
        <p>* An elderly naturalist in ''Yosemite: The Fate of Heaven'' kneels on the snow-covered ground as if in prayer and picks up a barely visible insect called the snow flea. He wonders if places like Yosemite can give its visitors ''a comprehension of what America was like in its primitive, primeval condition.''</p>
        <p>His concern is also that of the Margaret Mead Festival, which strives to make bits of primitive and sophisticated cultures comprehensible. Perhaps the most entertaining and cinematically successful film is Arthur Dong's ''Forbidden City, U.S.A.,'' an affectionate memoir of a once-famous nightclub in San Francisco where Chinese-Americans performed for predominantly Caucasian audiences.</p>
        <p>Blending historical film from the 1930's and 40's with contemporary interviews in which performers recall their Forbidden City days, Mr. Dong recaptures and explodes the image of Chinese-American entertainers. We see singers and dancers - including Larry Ching, billed as ''the Chinese Sinatra,'' and Paul Wing, ''the Chinese Astaire'' - who imitated mainstream popular culture for the amusement of audiences who regarded them as curiosities. The chorus girls, known as ''the Devilettes'' when they wore their brief devil costumes, were especially scandalous to their tradition-minded parents.</p>
        <p>The performers say they played along with the stereotypes, and were grateful that Forbidden City gave them a chance to work when the mainstream entertainment industry did not.</p>
        <p>Toy Yat Mar, a woman who was billed as ''the Chinese Sophie Tucker,'' recalls that she never liked singing ''Some of These Days'' but that her gimmick was commercial. In a poignant and painful memory, she tells of touring the segregated South with other Forbidden City performers and wondering if she should sit in the front or the back of a bus. ''I sat in the middle,'' she says, ''but nobody sat next to me.''</p>
        <p>''Forbidden City, U.S.A.'' will also be shown on public television early next year, with three short sexual allusions deleted. An equally artistic but far more somber and suddenly topical film is the Czechoslovak director Dusan Hanak's ''Pictures of the Old World.'' Made in 1972, it is a beautiful, elegiac work about poor, elderly peasants, but until 1988 it was banned in Czechoslovakia and not allowed to be shown outside the country. The film is never overtly political or critical of the Government - its images could apply to Appalachia or any other desperately poor region - but its depiction of extraordinary neglect was apparently considered dangerous.</p>
        <p>With no narration, Mr. Hanak simply presents, in subtle black and white, images the peasants' haggard, lined faces and the cramped hovels in which they live. As they describe the barren conditions and simple beliefs of their existence, the film unfolds with the smooth regularity of their daily lives.</p>
        <p>''I've lived in the shed for 50 years,'' one woman says. A man carries a few eggs to the village to sell; in such circumstances, a cracked egg becomes heartbreaking. A woman walks in daylight through a cemetery where dozens of candles burn on graves. She stops at one headstone and says, ''I met this one after he'd been dead a year.''</p>
        <p>And in the most extraordinary section, an old man talks with great fascination and lucidity about space travel, recalling how two astronauts walked on the moon and collected rocks while a third circled in their spaceship. Tacked to the wall of his crumbling shack is a small photograph of men walking on the moon. ''Pictures of the Old World'' and ''Forbidden City, U.S.A.'' have remarkable immediacy partly because no narration distances the audience from the subjects. ''Dust and Ashes,'' the major opening-night film, suffers from a lulling narrative, which assumes a clicheed ''objective'' tone (as if every documentary does not have some point of view). Yet this extraordinary photography brings us to the center of an almost surreal event. Fifteen million Hindu pilgrims gather where the Ganges and Yamuna Rivers meet, in a purification ritual that takes place every 12 years. A gigantic procession includes painted elephants, saffron-robed holy men and naked holy men covered in dust and ashes. One pilgrim, his face painted white with a large red marking on his forehead, leans on a makeshift swing because he has sworn not to sit or lie down for 12 years.</p>
        <p>The dilemma documentary film makers face, of course, is that some context is necesary, as ''Al Hajji'' makes clear. Without any voiceover, only occasional title cards like ''The Sheep Feast'' to set up events, we're left on our own to puzzle out the ritual significance of a sheep's throat being slit.</p>
        <p>''Yosemite'' succeeds because it uses narration in a fresher way. Robert Redford reads from the 1851 journal of a doctor who accompanied soldiers into the Indian land that eventually became Yosemite National Park. The 19th-century account of discovering the area, naming it and forcing Indians off the land, even burning one of their villages, is heard over views of today's preserved canyons and waterfalls, as well as a traffic jam of tourists' campers and a meeting to discuss the problem of acid rain. The narrative adds a historical layer and complexity to what might have been another set of pretty photographs.</p>
        <p>Yet even when the films' subjects outstrip their artistry, the Margaret Mead Festival is rarely boring and never irrelevant.</p>
        <p>What's Showing And When</p>
        <p>Screenings at the Margaret Mead Film Festival are to take place today through Thursday from 6:30 to 10:30 P.M. in the four theaters of the American Museum of Natural History, Central Park West at 79th Street. Ticket sales begin at 5 P.M. daily, with no advance sales. Admission for the evening is $6, or $5 for museum members.</p>
        <p>Here is the schedule for the films mentioned:</p>
        <p>''Dust and Ashes,'' tonight at 6:30 in the auditorium.  ''Al Hajji and his Four Wives,'' tonight at 6:30 in the Kaufmann Theater.  ''Forbidden City, U.S.A.,'' Tuesday at 8:15, auditorium.  ''Yosemite: The Fate of Heaven,''</p>
        <p>Tuesday at 9:30, auditorium.  ''Howard Finster: Man of Visions,''</p>
        <p>Wednesday at 7:45, auditorium.  ''Pictures of the Old World,'' Thursday at 9:15, auditorium.</p>
        <p>For a complete schedule of films, call 769-5305.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
