<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Plans A Refuge Of 13 Isles In the Ohio</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="290701"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WILDLIFE SANCTUARIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">OHIO RIVER</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">OHIO RIVER ISLANDS NATIONAL WILDLIFE REFUGE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HINDS, MICHAEL DECOURCY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wildlife Sanctuaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3D91E3BF937A25753C1A96F948260" item-length="1107" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Plans A Refuge Of 13 Isles In the Ohio</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL deCOURCY HINDS, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HINDS, MICHAEL DECOURCY</byline>
      <dateline>MUSKINGUM ISLAND, W. Va.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: An osprey with a fish in its talons languidly flaps by, well above a stream of acrid smoke belching from a power plant - a juxtaposition of industry and nature that is common here where the Ohio River flows around a string of unspoiled islands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: An osprey with a fish in its talons languidly flaps by, well above a stream of acrid smoke belching from a power plant - a juxtaposition of industry and nature that is common here where the Ohio River flows around a string of unspoiled islands.</p>
        <p>An osprey with a fish in its talons languidly flaps by, well above a stream of acrid smoke belching from a power plant - a juxtaposition of industry and nature that is common here where the Ohio River flows around a string of unspoiled islands.</p>
        <p>To make sure that nature continues to hold its own, Congress has passed a bill that would preserve 13 of the islands, including this one, for wildlife and recreation.</p>
        <p>If President Bush signs the measure, as he is expected to, the legislation will create the Ohio River Islands National Wildlife Refuge, calling for spending up to $850,000 to buy 11 islands in West Virginia and 2 in Pennsylvania, with a total of 445 acres on them. The United States Fish and Wildlife Service, which oversees wildlife refuges, plans to develop a island management plan that would include compatible recreational uses like hunting, hiking, fishing, bird watching and swimming.</p>
        <p>The refuge was part of a package of more than 200 land parcels for which Congress authorized spending a total of $215 million. The goal is to conserve important lands by buying them on the open market, sometimes in competition with developers and manufacturers who say the Federal Government already owns a third of the country and should not acquire any more of it. Accessibility as a Factor</p>
        <p>On the face of it, purchase of the Ohio River islands would seem to support this criticism of the Government. Wildlife preserves are often thought to be inaccessible wetlands or forests, not islands smack in the middle of one of the nation's busiest freight-shipping channels.</p>
        <p>The Ohio River was formed 13,000 years ago as a kind of drainage ditch on the face of the Wisconsin Glacier. It has lost many of its natural characteristics over only the last 100 years. Its depth and its currents are now controlled by locks and dams to ease shipping along its 981 miles from Pittsburgh to Cairo, Ill., where it empties into the Mississippi. The Ohio's bottom and a dozen of its islands have been strip-mined for sand and gravel for decades.</p>
        <p>Its shores, particularly along the first 100 miles from Pittsburgh, are dotted with nuclear and coal-fired power plants for refining oil and making chemicals, steel and electricity. Its waters are plied by thousands of barges, pushed by towboats, that have carried away so many mountains of coal to the nation's power plants that the river has been dubbed the birth canal of acid rain.</p>
        <p>But the Ohio has survived. It has even regained its health as a result of a 20-year-old Federally mandated effort to clean up the water, and a concurrent decline in smokestack industries and their emissions, Federal officials said. A West Virginia Renaissance</p>
        <p>So many birds, fish, animals and people have returned to the remaining pristine sections of the river in West Virginia that conservationists have begun worrying about preserving the islands from careless development.</p>
        <p>In 1981 William A. Tolin, a biologist in the Elkins, W.Va., office of the Fish and Wildlife Service, began cataloging flora and fauna on the river to make a Federal case for preserving it. He is a 45-year-old outdoorsman who has hunted and fished on the Ohio almost all his life.</p>
        <p>''Look, there are some confusing fall warblers heading south,'' Mr. Tolin said, pausing on a recent tour of the river, pointing out flocks of birds that were dressed indistinguishably in their dull fall plumage. ''On these islands I've seen all the songbirds that damn near exist.''</p>
        <p>He completed an assessment of 38 environmentally important islands on a 362-mile stretch of the river after, as he put it, three long summers and a divorce. Among other things, his report listed 355 kinds of plants, 133 species of birds, 20 species of mammals, 55 kinds of fish and 30 types of mussels, including the pink mucket, which is on the Federal list of endangered species. The Cruel Lords of the Sky</p>
        <p>But the most dramatic and visible of the river's wildlife are the soaring osprey, the great blue herons, the bald eagles and the peregrine falcons. In spring and fall, the Ohio River becomes a flyway for hundreds of thousands of migrating raptors, songbirds, shorebirds and waterfowl that nest in the islands' forests and wetlands.</p>
        <p>''What Bill found was just about the best intact remnants of an ecosystem untouched by man in West Virginia,'' said Roger J. Stern, assistant director of the West Virginia office of the Nature Conservancy.</p>
        <p>The conservancy is a private not-for-profit organization based in Arlington, Va., that owns or oversees four million acres of land preserves. The organization had lobbied the Government to create a wildlife refuge on the Ohio River and, to get the plan started, bought seven of the islands last month for $250,000 and obtained options to buy the other six for $450,000 in the hope of reselling them to the Government at cost. The conservancy raised the money from individuals, corporations and philanthropies.</p>
        <p>The conservancy obtained the rights to these 13 islands from the Dravo Basic Materials Company, a Pittsburgh company that had held the islands as reserves for mining sand and gravel that would now sell for $5 to $8 a ton. ''I wish we could have dug up the islands, but the state told us we couldn't, so we sold them,'' said C. Daniel Smith Jr., a Dravo vice president. ''Every year that we reapply for permits to dredge sand and gravel, the rules become tougher.'' Barge Lines Feel the Pinch</p>
        <p>No one formally opposed the proposal for the refuge, but barge lineoperators also complained about ever-tightening restrictions on their business. They said they were wary of an increased Federal presence on the river.</p>
        <p>Congress, prompted by Senator Robert C. Byrd, Democrat of West Virginia, decided to buy the 13 islands to be used as a refuge, but it made no commitment to buy any of the other 25 islands that Mr. Tolin identified as natural treasures. Most of those other islands, on the Ohio between Shippingport, Pa., and Ashland, Ky., are privately held, but some are municipally owned. One, Blennerhassett, W. Va., is already a state park.</p>
        <p>The conservancy plans to continue fund-raising to buy - or obtain options to buy - as many islands as possible, or to secure preservation easements on them. The organization plans to hold the islands in trust until the Government buys them.</p>
        <p>There are 430 Federal wildlife refuges, but this archipelago of river islands would be the first in West Virginia. ''Because of our state's history of resource extraction, it hasn't been the first impulse to be leaders in conservation,'' said Mr. Stern of the conservancy, ''but that's changing.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
