<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kellogg Journal; Mining Town Given Lift In Effort to Be a Resort</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19890802T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="265514"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">KELLOGG (IDAHO)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">EGAN, TIMOTHY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Idaho</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Idaho</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DF103BF930A25754C0A96F948260" item-length="753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kellogg Journal; Mining Town Given Lift In Effort to Be a Resort</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY EGAN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">EGAN, TIMOTHY</byline>
      <dateline>KELLOGG, Idaho, July 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Slouching toward trendiness, this worn-out mining town is giving itself a makeover and earnestly striving to shed its scruffy past.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Slouching toward trendiness, this worn-out mining town is giving itself a makeover and earnestly striving to shed its scruffy past.</p>
        <p>Slouching toward trendiness, this worn-out mining town is giving itself a makeover and earnestly striving to shed its scruffy past.</p>
        <p>Bordellos that were once patronized by thousands of miners have adopted Bavarian motifs. Square-shouldered brick buildings, constructed in the days when more silver was mined in this area than any other place in the world, have been dusted off and given brass historical tags. Saloons that specialized in double shots at sunrise are offering espresso and croissants.</p>
        <p>With a federally financed ski lift as the centerpiece, Kellogg is trying to avoid a future as a ghost town by embracing the quaintness of Bavaria.</p>
        <p>''One day this area will rival Sun Valley,'' said Loulou Kneubuhler, a French-born ski consultant who is assisting Kellogg in its metamorphosis.</p>
        <p>Scorn and ridicule prevailed two years ago when it obtained a $6.5 million Federal grant to build a three-mile gondola lift to the ski slopes behind town. Critics had a field day lampooning what would be the only ski resort in the nation financed in large part by the American taxpayer.</p>
        <p>One month into construction, the cable tramway is rising above scarred land that gave up most of its silver and lead, and Kellogg's leading citizens predict a renaissance for a valley that saw its ghost when unemployment reached 70 percent. The gondola may be a unique form of welfare, they say, but few handouts have ever generated as much excitement.</p>
        <p>Few places were hit as hard by the recession of the early 1980's as the Silver Valley, as this necklace of mining towns from Smelterville to Wallace is called, when the two biggest mines closed in 1982.</p>
        <p>More than two-thirds of the 3,500 people of Kellogg, next to the Bunker Hill Mine, were out of work. Many went on welfare or moved away. Those who stayed behind dreamed of a new future based on tourism and a ski slope called Jackass.</p>
        <p>''You could have taken a nap in the middle of this street seven years ago and nobody would've disturbed you,'' said Pete Jasberg, a former engineer at the mine who now runs a gift shop on the main street.</p>
        <p>With one foot in the grave, Kellogg decided on a makeover. They considered a Western theme, but Idaho and Montana were already full of similar places. Many wanted to capitalize on the area's mining background, but Wallace, a few miles to the east, had already cornered that market.</p>
        <p>They settled on old Bavarian. An ordinance was passed dictating that all new construction be in Alpine style, with exposed beams, flower boxes and murals painted over blank walls. They changed the name of the ski hill from Jackass to Silverhorn and refurbished a couple of old chairlifts. But even with the promise of deep powder and a vertical drop of 2,000 feet, few skiers came.</p>
        <p>What was needed, the town leaders concluded, was a gondola, but they did not have an adequate tax base to support the project, nor could a private company be lured in to take it on.</p>
        <p>Finally, Senator James A. McClure, a Republican who is the state's senior Senator, succeeded in adding a $6.5 million grant for the project to the Forest Service's budget.</p>
        <p>The Congressionally Directed Special Project Grant - critics call it simply pork - will pay for half the project. The other half will come from the builder, Von Roll Transport Systems of Switzerland, which expects to be reimbursed once the gondola is operating next summer.</p>
        <p>Whether skiers and summer tourists will stop to sample the Alpine air is still very much in question. Large sections of the valley have been deforested by acid rain and pollution from a smelter that is no longer in use.</p>
        <p>New trees have been planted, but the scenery is hardly Alpine. The old Bunker Hill Mine, partly reopened with several hundred workers, clangs with activity a few hundred feet from the site of the tramway's base. And the smelter, though closed, looms over a small mountain of mining rubble at the edge of town.</p>
        <p>''You look at Aspen 25 years ago and it was the same thing, an old mining town,'' said Larry Love, a Von Roll executive, ''Once they get going, that gondola will be the best $6.5 million the Government ever spent.''</p>
        <p>Kellogg may yet make it as the next Sun Valley, but some residents believe the town will never completely shake the mining dust out of its hair.</p>
        <p>''I have some real reservations about going Bavarian,'' said Katie Lutz, who used to work in the mine and now runs a dress shop called Granny's Squares. ''We should never forget that we're mining people in a valley built on the mines.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 2, 1989, Wednesday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>A picture caption on July 13 about the transformation of Kellogg, Idaho, from an old mining town to a trendy resort misidentified the sculptor whose work was being installed. He was David R. Dose.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 2, 1989, Wednesday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>A picture caption on July 13 about the transformation of Kellogg, Idaho, from an old mining town to a trendy resort misidentified the sculptor whose work was being installed. He was David R. Dose.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
