<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plan's Value to Peabody Questioned</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="250119"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PEABODY HOLDING CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEWMONT MINING CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HICKS, JONATHAN P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DE173BF936A25756C0A96F948260" item-length="889" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plan's Value to Peabody Questioned</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HICKS, JONATHAN P</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A recapitalization of the Peabody Holding Company proposed last week would mean a significant financial gain for the Newmont Mining Corporation, which owns a 49.97 percent stake in Peabody. But analysts and executives of other coal companies say there appears to be no appreciable benefit for Peabody.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A recapitalization of the Peabody Holding Company proposed last week would mean a significant financial gain for the Newmont Mining Corporation, which owns a 49.97 percent stake in Peabody. But analysts and executives of other coal companies say there appears to be no appreciable benefit for Peabody.</p>
        <p>A recapitalization of the Peabody Holding Company proposed last week would mean a significant financial gain for the Newmont Mining Corporation, which owns a 49.97 percent stake in Peabody. But analysts and executives of other coal companies say there appears to be no appreciable benefit for Peabody.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the recapitalization will virtually double Peabody's long-term debt to more than $1 billion and place the company on tenuous footing, the analysts say.</p>
        <p>Under the plan announced Thursday by Newmont, Peabody, which operates the largest coal company in North America, would refinance its existing debt of about $560 million and take on more debt to buy out its four owners other than Newmont. It would then pay Newmont a dividend.</p>
        <p>''This transaction creates very bad credit for Peabody,'' said Marc D. Cohen, a coal analyst with Kidder, Peabody &amp; Company. ''As long as they don't have to borrow any more money for capital investments any time in the future, they are in good shape. If things change, they are likely to have trouble.''</p>
        <p>Executives at two leading competitors of Peabody, who asked not to be identified, also said they thought the recapitalization would put the company in a substantially weaker financial position. Question on Newmont Intentions</p>
        <p>Some analysts view the recapitalization as a move by Newmont to transfer some of its $1 billion in debt to Peabody. Newmont, the centerpiece in a takeover battle between Consolidated Gold Fields P.L.C. of Britain and Minorco S.A., the investment arm of South African mining interests, took on much of that debt as it struggled to avoid a 1987 takeover attempt by T. Boone Pickens. But Newmont's vice chairman, Richard B. Leather, said last week that there was ''absolutely no connection'' between the Peabody recapitalization and the struggle with Minorco.</p>
        <p>Minorco has offered $5.9 billion for Gold Fields, which owns 49 percent of Newmont. The takeover proposal, which has a deadline of Wednesday, has been blocked by a Federal court injunction. The Peabody recapitalization is expected to be completed by autumn.</p>
        <p>Although Peabody is the largest United States coal producer, it is hardly the most profitable. Because of older equipment and mining properties, Peabody has not benefited as much as other competitors from higher demand for coal, analysts say.</p>
        <p>Peabody is making a profit of about $2.25 a ton, analysts said. That compares with $4 to $5 a ton among Peabody competitors like E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company and Mapco Inc.</p>
        <p>The recapitalization also calls for Newmont to sell 50.03 percent of Peabody to Salomon Brothers Inc. and Shearson Lehman Hutton Inc., which would leave Newmont's stake at the same level. Optimism at Peabody</p>
        <p>Peabody executives were not available for interviews during the weekend. Gayla Hoffman, a spokeswoman for the company, said that during the last five years Peabody had ''established an excellent cash-flow record which has enabled us over the years to support a $1 billion capital program and to pay $300 million in cash dividends to our owners.</p>
        <p>''It's not inconceivable that the changes in the recapitalization would have some impact on cash flow,'' she said. ''But we're confident that we are in a sound financial position that will enable us to continue to operate as a strong company.''</p>
        <p>Peabody, a century-old company based in St. Louis, has gone through a number of ownership changes in recent years. It was bought by Kennecott in 1968, but the acquisition was challenged by the Justice Department. After a lengthy bidding process, it was then purchased by a group of companies. Stakes are now owned by Newmont, the Boeing Company, Bechtel Investments Inc., the Equitable Life Assurance Society and Eastern Enterprises.</p>
        <p>Robert H. Quenon, president and chief executive, has been running the company for the last decade. In that time, Peabody has grown through acquisitions, including the 1984 purchase of Armco Inc.'s coal mining operations, which brought large coal reserves in West Virginia. And two years ago, Peabody acquired Eastern's coal properties in exchange for 15.01 percent of Peabody stock. Good Positioning Seen</p>
        <p>Analysts said the two deals had put Peabody in a good strategic position, with a national presence and a mix of low- and high-sulfur coal.</p>
        <p>After suffering from lower consumption in the early 1980's, the coal industry has enjoyed a resurgence as demand from utility companies has increased.</p>
        <p>Last year, Peabody had an operating profit of $185 million on revenues of $1.73 billion, compared with operating earnings of $169 million on revenues of $1.78 billion in 1987.</p>
        <p>Thomas K. McCaughey, a managing director at Salomon Brothers, said the company's cash flow would continue to be solid because the bulk of Peabody's contracts are long term. ''They sell by far the bulk of their coal on contracts, some of which extend for 30 years or more,'' Mr. McCaughey said.</p>
        <p>Still, analysts said, the company could suffer if strict laws on acid rain are enacted, forcing some customers to abrogate their contracts.</p>
        <p>''A significant portion of their operations have historically been medium- to high-sulfur coal, which creates a problem under those circumstances,'' Mr. Cohen said. ''Of course, they could pull this recapitalization off, but with a lot of caveats.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
