<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>This Little Piggy Got None</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="287051"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="OBSERVER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CAPITAL GAINS TAX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BAKER, RUSSELL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Gains Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDA1E3FF933A0575AC0A96F948260" item-length="751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>This Little Piggy Got None</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Russell Baker</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BAKER, RUSSELL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: September, and the sun vanishes early. Chill comes with night, and furnace wants oil, gas, electricity, money, money, money.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: September, and the sun vanishes early. Chill comes with night, and furnace wants oil, gas, electricity, money, money, money.</p>
        <p>September, and the sun vanishes early. Chill comes with night, and furnace wants oil, gas, electricity, money, money, money.</p>
        <p>What? Furnace not working? September is calling the furnace man. Money, money. Sitting by kitchen television sadly eating summer's last garden lettuce while listening to a man repeatedly saying ''impact the educational process.''</p>
        <p>And he a teacher too. Why people talk like that? What in the name of unholy Moloch means ''impact the educational process''? And him a teacher. No wonder kids can't find America on a map.</p>
        <p>The President is at Charlottesville, University of Virginia, big P.R. photo op and chin-chin about sad state of education, kids getting dumber by the million, and so forth, round up the usual cliches.</p>
        <p>President doesn't say ''scourge'' this time out though. Noticeable omission, that ''scourge.'' Could have said ''educational-inadequacy scourge will impact the progress process.''</p>
        <p>Last of the lettuce is gone. Soon there will be only cement afternoons, brown landscape, darkness before ''Live at Five'' with melancholy sound bites of President saying ''scourge.''</p>
        <p>The papers say we're killing the Everglades, the oceans are dying, the rain forest is burning down, the great deciduous forest of North America being destroyed by acid rain. Chemicals leaching poison and death into streams, creeks, ponds, millraces, rivers. Farms coffined under asphalt.</p>
        <p>Whine, whine, eh, Mr. Melancholy? Can't take September's abrupt smashing of summer's happy delusions, we suppose. Well, don't whine at us just because OPEC is at your jugular again, and furnace fixers too.</p>
        <p>Smile and the world smiles with you. Speak of the laughter of little children, the joy of a newborn baby's cry upon sensing she has not become drug-addicted in utero. Remember the magic of Irving Berlin, those wonderful songs, ''Blue Skies,'' ''Always,'' ''God Bless America,'' ''Impactin' on the Educational Process at the Ritz,'' and hundreds more.</p>
        <p>September and a nice, sweet, juicy tax cut, but only for folks whose money comes from capital gains (''the C.G. words,'' as the President probably calls them). Yes, sweet and juicy that tax cut, but not for this house though it needs furnace fixing, needs shelter from rapacious OPEC, needs relief from sound bites.</p>
        <p>Oh yes, self-pity is the beginning of death, just as James Bond said to himself in that adventure where he's swimming in barracuda-infested waters. How sad, sad, sad looking back now to realize James Bond was wasting his time, it wasn't Communism that would finish us off, it was acid rain, poisoned rivers, dead oceans, burned rain forests and garbage.</p>
        <p>Robert Frost: a poet for September melancholy. Some say the world will die of ice and some of fire, he said. Not even Frost, a man as grim as his name, guessed it would die of garbage. This could not become obvious until the pitiless curse of progress brought us into - Doom! Shaboom! - the Age of Instant Plenty.</p>
        <p>Nice, sweet, juicy tax cut for capital-gains folks - aye, there's the rub that produces this swelling blister of self-pity. Democrats in on that one too. Not just Republicans doling it out as usual to the gold-plate set, but Demos struggling to shove big bankroller snouts into the trough.</p>
        <p>Demos, bah! Demos worthless now except to fat-cat political action committees paying to get them re-elected ad nauseam. You no-good Demos, not worth the powder and shot it would take to blow you up with, to quote dear dead mother.</p>
        <p>September's melancholy is deepened because the nice, sweet, juicy tax cut is only for capital's gainers. Of course, of course, of course, my friend, of course everybody knows they are the people who really need it, for the good of the country.</p>
        <p>Of course everybody knows they are not outrageously rich, knows in fact that they are actually lovely, poor, innocent little old ladies who have for years been discouraged from taking the cute little gain on their wretchedly skimpy chunks of capital because Government would have taxed it at a brutal 28 percent.</p>
        <p>Now that the tax will be less than 20 percent these dear little old female creatures will sell at last, investing their profits in the great engines of American industry, turning us once again into a giant so mighty that Japan will never again dare buy one of our great movie companies.</p>
        <p>Knowing this, why not give three cheers for blessings that President and worthless Democrats are bringing us? September melancholy is the answer, with its thoughts of death by garbage.</p>
        <p>OBSERVER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
