<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Companies to Phase Out Peril to Ozone</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="289911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HALONS (CHEMICAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDB103AF932A25753C1A96F948260" item-length="414" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Companies to Phase Out Peril to Ozone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Reuters</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: More large companies have agreed to eliminate ozone-destroying chlorofluorocarbons and halon in their worldwide operations, the Environmental Protection Agency said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: More large companies have agreed to eliminate ozone-destroying chlorofluorocarbons and halon in their worldwide operations, the Environmental Protection Agency said today.</p>
        <p>More large companies have agreed to eliminate ozone-destroying chlorofluorocarbons and halon in their worldwide operations, the Environmental Protection Agency said today.</p>
        <p>The companies are among the largest users of the chemicals, which have been found to deplete the ozone layer that shields the Earth from harmful ultraviolet radiation. Elevated levels of such radiation can cause skin cancer and eye cataracts in humans, as well as damage to wildlife and crops.</p>
        <p>The Boeing Company, the Digital Equipment Corporation, the Ford Motor Company, the General Electric Company, Honeywell Inc., Motorola Inc. and Texas Instruments Inc. announced their commitment today at an international conference on chlorofluorocarbons and halon substitutes.</p>
        <p>The companies have agreed to share technical information on new alternatives and work with their suppliers and others to curb the use of the chemicals.</p>
        <p>Three other companies, the American Telephone and Telegraph Company, Northern Telecom Inc. of Canada and Seiko Epson of Japan have already pledged to end the use of chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, in the near future.</p>
        <p>Forty-five countries have ratified a treaty that calls for a 50 percent reduction in the production and use of the chemicals by the year 2000. The E.P.A. has frozen American production and consumption of chlorofluorocarbons at 1986 levels and has ordered a 50 percent reduction in their use by mid-1998.</p>
        <p>Speakers at the conference here today discussed alternatives to the chemicals, which are used as refrigerants, as insulation, and for sterilizing medical instruments and cleaning delicate electrical and computer parts.</p>
        <p>Pamela Pope, a British Petroleum engineer in Alaska, warned that if production of halon was halted before a suitable alternative was found, oil production on Alaska's North Slope would be endangered. The North Slope accounts for about 25 percent of American oil production. Problems With Halon</p>
        <p>''Currently halon is the only fire protection product that can prevent an explosion in a flammable gas/air mixture,'' Ms. Pope said.</p>
        <p>While several alternatives to CFC's exist, scientists at the conference said, there are no chemicals with the same characteristics as halon.</p>
        <p>Unless substitutes are developed, a panel of experts from the United States and Europe said, halons will have to be limited to the most essential uses, aboard Navy ships, for example. And even this, they said, would still have an adverse affect on the environment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
