<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Environment Is Security</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="252948"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="FOREIGN AFFAIRS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NATIONAL SECURITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, ALBERT JR (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, FLORA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DA1E3CF937A15756C0A96F948260" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Environment Is Security</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Flora Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, FLORA</byline>
      <dateline>COPENHAGEN</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Students at Copenhagen University, like most young people across Western Europe, have written off the defense issue. They want to get on with talk about the future. Some put it as shifting from East-West to North-South problems. Others, more appropriately, see it as facing the longer-term global threat to the environment as the threat of nuclear war seems to have receded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Students at Copenhagen University, like most young people across Western Europe, have written off the defense issue. They want to get on with talk about the future. Some put it as shifting from East-West to North-South problems. Others, more appropriately, see it as facing the longer-term global threat to the environment as the threat of nuclear war seems to have receded.</p>
        <p>Students at Copenhagen University, like most young people across Western Europe, have written off the defense issue. They want to get on with talk about the future. Some put it as shifting from East-West to North-South problems. Others, more appropriately, see it as facing the longer-term global threat to the environment as the threat of nuclear war seems to have receded.</p>
        <p>They are premature in declaring the cold war over. The vast arsenals that can destroy human life in minutes rather than decimate it in decades are still in place. And the underlying issues of confrontation - freedom, individual rights, self-government -certainly remain. These students have only to ask their counterparts in Eastern Europe and China, for example, about the priority of their demands.</p>
        <p>But the issues of environment and third world are real, and much more complicated than the old ideological theories with a simple formula of defining the enemy and opposing him.</p>
        <p>They are coming into mainstream politics now, not only in established democracies but in countries like Hungary, Poland, even the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>The pattern has been to take up environmental questions, inevitably linked to third-world economic and population growth as well as to wanton habits of industrialized countries, in a fragmented way. The greenhouse effect, toxic waste, desertification, destruction of forests inevitably require confronting highly contentious trade-offs that politicians have only been facing at the margin of conflicting pressures.</p>
        <p>Bringing these issues, which once seemed exotic or futuristic, into the central debate for voter decision is the new task for responsible politicians. It won't be easy, but it is the only way to get effective action.</p>
        <p>I was struck by the approach of Senator Albert Gore, the Tennessee Democrat, in a recent speech to the National Academy of Sciences. He asked, ''Do we need a crisis before we can start?'' And he pointed out that it often takes a long time before a gradually mounting menace evokes response, as in the case of Hitler, for example. But drawing on his own large experience of strategic arms control, he said global environment should be seen as a national security issue.</p>
        <p>Allocating resources to ward off disaster, rather than waiting to repair or overcome what has already gone wrong, has been accepted in the field of defense to prevent war. It can also be understood in the field of protecting our natural heritage from surprise attack, if leaders are able to explain that surprise comes only from neglecting to prepare. Since he was speaking to scientists, Mr. Gore used an elegant simile to Einstein's theory of relativity. ''Time is relative in politics as in science,'' he said, shaped by the gravitational pull of massive catastrophe in the past or the identifiable future.</p>
        <p>''The problem in organizing our response'' to the environmental threat (for example, ''one Tennessee's worth of forest destroyed every year'') is that ''the worst effects seem far off in the future, and they are so unprece-dented that they defy common sense. While right now, in the present, millions of people are suffering in poverty and dying of starvation, warfare and preventable diseases.''</p>
        <p>The task is to make clear that the apocalypse, as with nuclear war, must be deterred with measures taken now or the warp of time will leave us defenseless, Mr. Gore argued.</p>
        <p>Nor, he said realistically, can the third world be cajoled or compelled to give up hope of economic development because advanced countries have already taxed the global environment beyond limits it can bear. ''Development is part of the problem as well as the solution.'' No one is prepared to abandon growth.</p>
        <p>It was a long speech, addressing the complexities and contradictions of devising ''dynamic new strategies'' that will require not only sacrifice of wealth but of custom and old assumptions of what constitutes self-interest. There was too much to summarize fairly.</p>
        <p>And it had specific, non-utopian recommendations, on how to seek better answers in the near, middle and long terms for the use of energy, the techniques of agriculture, industrial processes, transportation. Mr. Gore suggested a carbon dioxide tax to fund energy research, ''although that is not yet politically viable.''</p>
        <p>''My optimism,'' he said, ''is tempered by awareness of the power in the forces of greed and fear. But I do believe we have the capacity for what is needed - because the challenge can now be accurately described in terms of national security.''</p>
        <p>It is a good start for moving on from fashionable distress about the environment to generating a wide-gauge program. That's what politicians are supposed to be for.</p>
        <p>FOREIGN AFFAIRS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
