<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who Can Predict Our Life in the Greenhouse; A Net Saving</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="307568"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LASHOF, DANIEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDC153AF93BA35751C1A96F948260" item-length="549" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who Can Predict Our Life in the Greenhouse; A Net Saving</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>While some economists foresee staggering costs to curb the earth's warming (front page, Nov. 19), other analysts expect substantial economic and environmental benefits from actions that reduce the risk of catastrophic climate change. This dramatic difference in views results primarily from two key assumptions.</p>
        <p>First, economic models generally assume that market forces are currently yielding optimal economic results. By assumption, then, any policy that results in reduced CO#2 emissions will have direct economic costs rather than benefits.</p>
        <p>It is well documented, however, that energy consumers forgo investments in energy efficiency with real rates of return from 30 to 200 percent or more while they, and energy suppliers, simultaneously make investments yielding only 5 percent or less. This occurs because choices that determine energy efficiency are often made with inadequate information about upfront costs versus reduced energy bills, under extreme time pressure, and/or by builders or landlords who do not pay the energy bills. Furthermore, energy prices do not reflect the large environmental costs of obtaining and using energy (even excluding global warming).</p>
        <p>The second key failing of most economic models is that technology is treated statically. Not only are innovations continually emerging that reduce the energy needed to generate a dollar of gross national product even during periods of declining real energy prices, but also this progress can be accelerated through policies that make reducing greenhouse gas emissions an integral part of the research and development process.</p>
        <p>Recent experience with the development of chlorofluorocarbon substitutes demonstrates this point. A 1982 Rand study concluded that CFC use could not be cut by more than one-third without severe economic consequences. After the world committed itself to a 50 percent cut in production of these compounds, however, substitutes and process modifications rapidly emerged that could allow a complete phase-out of these compounds with net savings through increased energy efficiency.</p>
        <p>Curiously, while your story is pessimistic about our ability to reduce emissions, it is amazingly optimistic about our ability to adapt to global warming. Rich countries might be able to deal with gradually rising seas and a gradual drop in the productivity of a few crops if those were the only impacts of climatic change. The problem is that these gradual effects are likely to be punctuated by more powerful hurricanes, more frequent severe droughts, pest out-breaks, forest diebacks, millions of environmental refugees fleeing their floded homelands and other impacts we cnnot now imagine. In addition, natural ecosystems have no hope of adapting to climate change.</p>
        <p>We will never know the exact costs or benefits of preventing global warming without performing the experiment. The choice is to experiment by continuing to dump carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases into the atmosphere, or to experiment with designing policies to reduce energy bills, cut oil imports and improve the competitiveness of our economy while protecting the global atmosphere. DANIEL LASHOF  Washington, Dec. 1, 1989  The writer is a senior scientist at the Natural Resources Defense Council</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
