<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oil Parley Is Told of Political Cost of Valdez Spill</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="300858"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXXON VALDEZ (TANKER)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TANKERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TANKERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHIPS AND SHIPPING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALASKA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PRINCE WILLIAM SOUND (ALASKA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">EXXON CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAYES, THOMAS C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tankers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DF1E3CF937A25752C1A96F948260" item-length="788" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oil Parley Is Told of Political Cost of Valdez Spill</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS C. HAYES, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAYES, THOMAS C</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Nov. 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Industry consultants gave oil executives a bleak forecast today, outlining a wide range of long-term political damage related to environmental worries and public anger over the Exxon Valdez spill in March.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Industry consultants gave oil executives a bleak forecast today, outlining a wide range of long-term political damage related to environmental worries and public anger over the Exxon Valdez spill in March.</p>
        <p>Industry consultants gave oil executives a bleak forecast today, outlining a wide range of long-term political damage related to environmental worries and public anger over the Exxon Valdez spill in March.</p>
        <p>Those assessments, along with urgings to speed the transition to alternative fuels and support President Bush's proposed Clean Air Act, drew polite applause and no challenges from industry executives at a crowded morning session today at the annual convention of the American Petroleum Institute.</p>
        <p>Adam E. Sieminski, vice president of the Washington Analysis Corporation, a public-policy research firm, said growing political sentiment to curb the sources of water and air pollution and slow the global warming trend would exact a heavy toll on the industry in coming years. ''The public policy debate is pointing inexorably to higher costs and lower demand for products,'' he said. Stronger Enforcement</p>
        <p>William K. Reilly, administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, said the agency would take stronger enforcement steps to force reductions in toxic emissions from chemical plants and petroleum refineries.</p>
        <p>Many chemical producers have taken voluntary steps to reduce toxic emissions, and many reported that the effort was also paring costs at the plants. He said the oil industry should also take the same voluntary path to insure that it retains flexibility in meeting tighter emission control standards.</p>
        <p>''We believe in market incentives, but we want results,'' he said. ''The context for voluntary performance has to be the certainty of enforcement'' if pollution-control standards are not met.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly also said that although the oil industry was a world leader in oil production, the ''disaster'' of the Exxon Valdez proved how little the industry knew about cleaning oil spills.</p>
        <p>He said the industry must spend more than the $35 million it has proposed for the next five years in research on oil-spill cleanup technology. The equipment brought to the scene in Alaska's Prince William Sound in March and April proved ''grossly inadequate,'' he said. ''This research clearly should have been done years ago.'' History of Global Warming</p>
        <p>Irving Mintzer, director of policy research for the Center for Global Change, an environmental group, traced the history of global warming for more than 100 years. He said global temperatures were certain to rise further even if industrial nations and consumers immediately stopped burning the fossil fuels the energy industry produces.</p>
        <p>Of the 11 billion tons of waste produced in the United States each year, the oil industry generates 2.2 billion tons. The United States is responsible for 21 percent of the carbon dioxide being added each year to the earth's atmosphere. Rising levels of carbon dioxide are a major cause of rising global temperatures.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mintzer said 24 Senators asked President Bush recently to support legislation to force industry to reduce carbon dioxide levels by 20 percent in the year 2000. The President rejected the suggestion, but Dr. Mintzer said the episode illustrated that ''the political base of support to reduce emissions is strong - and growing.''</p>
        <p>Asked later how the nation could achieve a 20 percent drop in carbon dioxide emissions, Dr. Mintzer said conservation and improving the efficiencies of automobiles, light bulbs and thousands of other energy-dependent products were the best hopes. Cost of Resisting Change</p>
        <p>He and others on the panel, ''Energy and the Environment,'' said the industry's tendency to resist change and oppose environmental concerns had hurt it in Congress, as well as made it slow to see business opportunities in developing products and technology that lower pollution. One example, they said, would be speeding research to develop low-polluting, reformulated gasolines.</p>
        <p>In remarks later in the day, Charles J. DiBona, president of the institute, said the nation could not avoid a future oil shortage if it relied on conservation to ''save'' its way to sufficient energy supplies.</p>
        <p>Mr. DiBona repeated past calls to Congress to open the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge in northern Alaska. He said public opinion would support it when oil supplies ''eventually'' tighten. But many oil executives believe the hostile political fallout from the Exxon spill will keep the refuge closed to drilling for years. $400 Million in 5 Years The industry-led effort to create a coastal network to limit and clean up future offshore oil spills will cost more than $400 million in the next five years, Vice Adm. John D. Costello, the former Coast Guard commander who heads the new organization, told reporters. The amount is more than twice the initial estimate announced in June.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
