<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fill It Up, Please, With Clean, Economical Ethanol</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="260548"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHANOL</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethanol</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1D61338F931A15755C0A96F948260" item-length="468" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fill It Up, Please, With Clean, Economical Ethanol</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Contrary to recent news stories and analyses, it is now feasible both on a technical and economic basis to produce nonpolluting ethyl alcohol fuel for vehicles from renewable biomass - that is, plant - sources.</p>
        <p>I am a chemist who has been principally occupied for more than 40 years making new membrane and filter systems and evaluating their properties and uses. These are now state-of-the-art, with substantial industrial uses in place. More recently, I and others developed new microfilters that make fermentation more efficient, and also pervaporation membranes that afford a particularly energy-efficient means of separating alcohol-water mixtures.</p>
        <p>A key element of this conversion process is its acceptable cost. Feedstock at 2 cents a pound amounts to 28 cents a gallon. With conversion costs conservatively estimated at 15 cents, alcohol at 43 cents a gallon is competitive because ethanol has two-thirds the energy content of gasoline. Gasoline and diesel engines are readily adjusted to use ethyl alcohol fuel.</p>
        <p>The only practical American biomass source is starch from corn, because it can be produced at a low enough cost. Currently, 350 million bushels of corn per year are converted into 100 percent ethanol for blending with gasoline for gasohol. Extensive experience in Brazil shows that alcohol at about 97 percent (with water) serves alone as an excellent, nonpolluting vehicular fuel. Our annual production of 7.5 billion bushels could be expanded by 5 billion, making enough ethanol to satisfy about 13 percent of U.S. motor fuel needs.</p>
        <p>A larger-scale feedstock is cane sugar, now cultivated in the tropics and readily expanded manyfold.</p>
        <p>Conversion processes based on membranes will be closed-loop and nonpolluting because the feedstock biomass is entirely converted into alcohol fuel, animal feed, byproducts and virtually all needed fertilizer.</p>
        <p>We can now build a pilot plant based upon these state-of-the-art technologies while carrying out laboratory and bench-scale studies to select the best available membranes and then building and installing the additional pilot plant devices. The project can be completed within three years for about $5 million.</p>
        <p>All of the questions raised on the impracticality of biomass conversion are invalid when proper feedstocks and processes are employed. Methanol, methane and similar fuels are inferior, being derived from fossil fuels that contribute to the greenhouse effect, a step backward. A major fraction of our energy must continue to come from liquids which are readily stored, are transportable and suitable for vehicular propulsion; gasoline and now ethanol are the principal candidates. HARRY P. GREGOR  New York, June 7, 1989</p>
        <p>The writer is professor emeritus of chemical engineering, Columbia U.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
