<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mr. Bush Clears the Air</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="258489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CLEAN AIR ACT OF 1970</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DF1738F937A25755C0A96F948260" item-length="551" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mr. Bush Clears the Air</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: For years, the fight against dirty air has missed a crucial element: a President who thinks the nation deserves clean air. George Bush's proposals to overhaul the antiquated Clean Air Act of 1970 aren't perfect. But they represent a major departure from years of official indifference. They will force industry to think creatively about new technologies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: For years, the fight against dirty air has missed a crucial element: a President who thinks the nation deserves clean air. George Bush's proposals to overhaul the antiquated Clean Air Act of 1970 aren't perfect. But they represent a major departure from years of official indifference. They will force industry to think creatively about new technologies.</p>
        <p>For years, the fight against dirty air has missed a crucial element: a President who thinks the nation deserves clean air. George Bush's proposals to overhaul the antiquated Clean Air Act of 1970 aren't perfect. But they represent a major departure from years of official indifference. They will force industry to think creatively about new technologies. And they challenge Congress to end more than a decade of legislative paralysis.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's plan would tackle three major kinds of air pollution:</p>
        <p>Acid Rain. Acid rain is caused mainly by oxides of sulfur and nitrogen that change chemically as they move through the air and then fall to earth in rain, snow or fog - damaging lakes, streams and forests. For eight years the Reagan Administration engaged in endless studies and took no action. As environmentalists had hoped all along, the Bush plan would require that coal-burning power plants, most of which are concentrated in the Middle West, cut sulfur dioxide emissions in half by the end of the century. Companies would be free to decide how to meet that goal. They could invest in scrubbers to clean the emissions, switch to low-sulfur coal or use various market incentives.</p>
        <p>Smog. Eighty-one metropolitan areas exceed Federal health standards for ozone, the main component of urban smog. The President's plan would require all but three to meet the standards by the year 2000. The exceptions - Los Angeles, New York and Houston- would be given until 2010, but would have to show annual progress.</p>
        <p>The plan focuses heavily on motor vehicles, which are responsible for more than half of ozone's harmful ingredients. New and stricter tailpipe standards, for example, would require a 40 percent cutback in hydrocarbon emissions by 1993 and a 30 percent reduction in nitrogen dioxides. These targets fall well short of cutbacks proposed by aggressive environmentalists like Representative Henry Waxman, a California Democrat. But even Mr. Waxman has said the Bush proposal is something to build on.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's most dramatic idea would require the gradual phasing in of cars built to run on so-called ''clean fuels'' like methanol, natural gas or ethanol, which do not emit hydrocarbons. Detroit would be required to make 500,000 alternative-fuel cars by 1995, and one million a year by 1997.</p>
        <p>The alternative fuels plan brought howls from the oil companies; even environmentalists warn that some ''clean fuels'' may pose new hazards. Methanol, for example, emits carbon dioxide, a major contributor to the feared greenhouse effect. Yet there can be little harm in forcing the automobile and oil industries to think seriously about new technologies. And the gains could be immense.</p>
        <p>Industrial Toxics. The Environmental Protection Agency estimates that each year industry emits 2.7 billion pounds of toxic chemicals into the air. Mr. Bush's plan would require polluters to install the best available technology and cut these emissions by 75 percent in 10 years.</p>
        <p>These proposals are estimated to cost $14 billion to $18 billion a year. Industries, and inevitably consumers, will pay most of the cost. But poll after poll has shown that Americans are willing to pay for cleaner air. Mr. Bush is now asking for cleaner air. The question is whether Congress is prepared to legislate cleaner air.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
