<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. to Urge Joint Environmental Effort at Summit</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="263930"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DB143CF935A35754C0A96F948260" item-length="665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. to Urge Joint Environmental Effort at Summit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Seeking to take the lead on environmental issues, the United States will press for a broad agenda of international cooperation on combating pollution and preserving natural resources at a summit meeting next week in Paris, senior American officials said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Seeking to take the lead on environmental issues, the United States will press for a broad agenda of international cooperation on combating pollution and preserving natural resources at a summit meeting next week in Paris, senior American officials said today.</p>
        <p>Seeking to take the lead on environmental issues, the United States will press for a broad agenda of international cooperation on combating pollution and preserving natural resources at a summit meeting next week in Paris, senior American officials said today.</p>
        <p>As a result, the officials said, environmental concerns are expected to be more prominent this year than at any previous meeting of the seven leading industrialized democracies. William K. Reilly, head of the Environmental Protection Agency, said at a White House briefing that ''there is something of a race on by the summit leaders to see who can be greenest.''</p>
        <p>But he indicated that the United States would be wary of moves in Paris to adopt broad new spending programs or create new institutions for protecting the environment. ''Our posture will be that efforts to the restore the environment are not a sprinter's game,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A draft declaration for the summit meeting, prepared by Administration officials, shows that the United States will propose or support steps toward meeting international environmental problems in several areas. The draft, which was described as preliminary and not yet reviewed by President Bush, calls in particular for measures to help developing countries preserve resources and avoid deterioration of their ecological systems. Help for Developing Countries</p>
        <p>For example international development agencies like the World Bank would be asked to assess the environmental effects of all projects for which they provide funds.</p>
        <p>In addition, ''in special cases,'' the United States would support efforts to reduce the foreign debt of developing countries in return for efforts in those countries to protect the environment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly said today that President Bush thought that these ''debt-for-nature swaps'' were a good idea. But he stopped short of saying that the United States would back a full-scale program for forgiving debt in return for the protection of the environment.</p>
        <p>The debt-for-nature exchanges completed so far have chiefly been arranged by conservation groups and have been relatively modest in scale.</p>
        <p>The industrial nations are now discussing a major program of debt relief for the developing countries, and the subject of including environmental programs in that program has come up at least peripherally. But commercial banks who hold large amounts of the developing countries' debt generally oppose such a debt forgiveness program. Even if the industrialized countries and the international lending institutions do agree on a debt forgiveness plan, it might stress traditional conditions, like reducing domestic spending by the debtor countries.</p>
        <p>The draft also said that both industrial and developing countries had a duty to assure that tropical forests are used on a sustainable basis and called for carrying out a worldwide strategy to protect those forests.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly said today that the activities of developing countries as they industrialize, particularly countries like China and India, could have a major effect on such problems as the destruction of the ozone layer and climate change caused by pollution accumulating in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The draft stresses the need to reduce carbon monoxide produced by the burning of fossil fuels, the chief pollutant contributing to a global warming trend that scientists anticipate will occur in the next century.</p>
        <p>But the American draft would not commit the summit nations to any specific reduction of carbon dioxide emissions. Instead, it endorses the current process of analyzing the problem of global warming under the auspices of the United Nations Environment Program and says a United Nations conference on the environment, scheduled for 1992, is expected to be the ''turning point'' in dealing with this and other major questions.</p>
        <p>The Paris meeting will bring together the United States, France, West Germany, Britain, Italy, Canada and Japan, as well as a representative of the European Community.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
