<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Global-Warming Panel Urges Gas Tax in West</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="226845"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW DELHI (INDIA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAZARIKA, SANJOY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India/New Delhi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DA113CF935A15751C0A96F948260" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Global-Warming Panel Urges Gas Tax in West</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANJOY HAZARIKA, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAZARIKA, SANJOY</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, Feb. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Delegates at a conference on global warming have recommended steps to deal with the problem that emphasize the responsibilities of poor as well as rich nations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Delegates at a conference on global warming have recommended steps to deal with the problem that emphasize the responsibilities of poor as well as rich nations.</p>
        <p>Delegates at a conference on global warming have recommended steps to deal with the problem that emphasize the responsibilities of poor as well as rich nations.</p>
        <p>A major recommendation by more than 140 scientists, environmental experts and government officials at the three-day meeting ending Friday was a tax on gasoline and other fossil fuels in Western nations, which are the major users of nonrenewable sources of energy. Scientists say the burning of fossil fuels is a major contributor to global warming. The conference delegates said such taxes could assist reforestation programs in poor countries and could help finance alternatives to industries that produce chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>Many scientists are convinced that it would be prudent to reduce the emission of chlorofluorocarbons and other gases like carbon dioxide, methane and nitrous oxide that contribute to the greenhouse effect, in which the gases combine with water vapor to trap heat inside the earth's atmosphere. The loss of forests contributes to the greenhouse effect because trees absorb carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>A rise in global temperatures could produce vast climatic changes and hurt agricultural and other economic activities. Such changes could flood low-lying island communities or delta populations and ruin crops.</p>
        <p>The conference here marked what a top Indian scientist described as an end to ''finger pointing'' by third world countries against the industrialized world about global warming and about depletion of the protective ozone layer in the atmosphere, as well as recognition that poorer countries must play a more active role on the issues.</p>
        <p>''We cannot sit on the sidelines anymore,'' said M. S. Swaminathan, president of the International Union for Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources, a conference organizer.</p>
        <p>The conference, which was dominated by representatives of the third world but also attended by experts from the United States and Britain, called on developing countries to improve existing energy efficiency, pioneer renewable energy use such as solar energy, improve forest growth, stop deforestation, and curb the population explosion. It suggested that each country set up a national board to monitor the atmosphere. It also urged controlling animal populations and grazing and pressed for the development of natural gas.</p>
        <p>Adding significance to the conference was the fact that most of the participating underdeveloped countries were not members of the Montreal Convention of 1987, which froze production levels of chlorofluorocarbons in an attempt to retard the depletion of the ozone layer, and sought to reduce production by the end of the century.</p>
        <p>There were no sharp confrontations on the issue and ideological differences were apparently bridged when American scientists like George Woodwell, director of the Woods Hole Research Center at Woods Hole, Mass., acknowledged the failure of the United States ''to put its own house in order'' and the major contribution of the industrialized world to chlorofluorocarbon and carbon-dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>Indian officials indicated that the Government, which has opposed the convention as discriminating against developing countries that have neither alternative technologies nor financial flexibility, is considering joining it.</p>
        <p>A senior official said that such a decision may take some years, although India, which is a leader of the third world, no longer has ''reservations about the need for global cooperation on the issue.'' Rising Role of Third World</p>
        <p>Such a move would have worldwide implications, especially for the underdeveloped countries. With a population that is expected to exceed one billion by the end of the century, India is likely to increase its use of chlorofluorocarbons for refrigeration and insulation.</p>
        <p>The conference was organized by the Tata Energy Research Institute, which is run by Tatas, the country's leading industrial corporation, in association with the Woods Hole Research Center and the World Resources Institute in Washington.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
