<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Film; An Uncouth Uncle Against the Suburban Grain</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="275826"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CANBY, VINCENT</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">UNCLE BUCK (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D61630F935A2575BC0A96F948260" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Film; An Uncouth Uncle Against the Suburban Grain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT CANBY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CANBY, VINCENT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Uncle Buck (John Candy) is the sort of character that no American suburb should be without. Everything about him offends middle-class manners, fashions and aspirations. Though his ancient automobile needs a muffler and travels around in its own permanent cloud of exhaust smoke, Uncle Buck is a breath of fresh air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Uncle Buck (John Candy) is the sort of character that no American suburb should be without. Everything about him offends middle-class manners, fashions and aspirations. Though his ancient automobile needs a muffler and travels around in its own permanent cloud of exhaust smoke, Uncle Buck is a breath of fresh air.</p>
        <p>Uncle Buck (John Candy) is the sort of character that no American suburb should be without. Everything about him offends middle-class manners, fashions and aspirations. Though his ancient automobile needs a muffler and travels around in its own permanent cloud of exhaust smoke, Uncle Buck is a breath of fresh air.</p>
        <p>Aside from making a deal here and there, and going to the racetrack, Uncle Buck does not believe in work. He favors cigars that reek and wears clothes that don't match, either him or each other. He is the embodiment of all things uncouth that people in the suburbs hope they have left somewhere else.</p>
        <p>In ''Uncle Buck,'' which opens today at the Warner and other theaters, John Hughes has had the good sitcom idea of placing Uncle Buck in the middle of an ideal suburb (actually, Winnetka, Ill.), in the middle of Mr. Hughes's idea of an average American family. The results are sometimes funny and, in the way of small-screen entertainment, so perfectly predictable that one could mail in the laughs.</p>
        <p>When his brother and sister-in-law are called away to Indianapolis, Uncle Buck leaves his gloriously slobbish existence in Chicago to take care of his two nieces and nephew. The two younger children, Miles (Macauly Culkin) and Maizy (Gaby Hoffman) are at first shocked by his unconventional ways and then delighted.</p>
        <p>The older child, Tia (Jean Kelly), is a teen-age beauty alienated from her parents. She is alternately mortified by Uncle Buck's crude ways and furious at his meddling in her romance with a boy who's up to no good. You don't need a diagram to know how that will come out.</p>
        <p>As in ''War and Peace,'' it's not the plot that counts. In ''Uncle Buck'' it's watching Mr. Candy dealing with a clown who arrives for Miles's birthday party drunk and driving a Volkswagen equipped with large mouse ears. ''In the field of live home entertainment,'' says the clown, ''I am a god.'' Says Uncle Buck, ''Get in your mouse and leave.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Candy is at his best when he is being crafty and, at the beginning, downright nasty to the children. So is the film. When ''Uncle Buck'' goes sweet (complete with Chaplinesque music), fun flees. ''Uncle Buck'' is a movie in which saying ''I love you'' to Mom or Dad or Uncle Buck solves all problems except, perhaps, acid rain.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Hughes has had huge success with his theatrical movies about teen-agers (''Sixteen Candles,'' ''Ferris Buehler's Day Off,'' among others), he may be the first real auteur of television-style entertainment.</p>
        <p>He knows exactly what he's doing and does it with attention to obligatory detail. The exterior of a house in a Hughes film immediately establishes the sappy nature of the characters within as well as the kind of movie it is. He can write funny lines. He comes up with engagingly absurd situations. Yet there is something unnerving about the way he denatures real life.</p>
        <p>One doesn't notice this in the limited confines of the small screen. In a movie theater, too many Hughes images are simply big and empty. They are filler material. Dead. Though he likes to shoot on location, the world he records seems phony or, at best, consistently trivial.</p>
        <p>The cast is good, especially Miss Kelly, who not only looks great but who may also be an actress in the making. Amy Madigan does well in the fairly abbreviated role of Uncle Buck's steady if impatient female friend. It is Mr. Candy who gives the film what heft it has. He is an entertaining performer through thick and mostly thin.</p>
        <p>''Uncle Buck,'' which has been rated PG (''parental guidance suggested'') contains vulgar language.  If You're Feeling Blue, Just Say, 'I Love You'  UNCLE BUCK, written and directed by John Hughes; director of photography, Ralf Bode; edited by Lou Lombardo, Tony Lombardo and Peck Prior; music by Ira Newborn; production designer, John W. Corso; produced by Mr. Hughes and Tom Jacobson; released by Universal Studios. At the Warner, Broadway and 43d Street; the Manhattan Twin, 59th Street at Third Avenue; running time: 95 minutes. This film is rated PG.  Uncle BuckJohn Candy  Tia RussellJean Kelly Maizy RusselGaby Hoffman Miles RussellMacaulay Culkin  Chanice KobolowskiAmy Madigan MCAd(Universal Studios)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
