<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>1960's 'Hair' in Bridgeport Revival</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="238434"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DOWNTOWN CABARET THEATER (BRIDGEPORT, CONN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KLEIN, ALVIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HALLINAN, RICHARD C</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">HAIR (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFDE143BF93AA35757C0A96F948260" item-length="1091" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>1960's 'Hair' in Bridgeport Revival</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KLEIN, ALVIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IN the late 1960's, there was a musical about innocence, peace, love and harmony - and protest. With a bountiful rock score, a minimalist book and free-flowing staging, it signaled a radical new form for the Broadway musical. It also had a profusion of taboo words, scenes depicting drug use and lovemaking, and one scene displaying frontal nudity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IN the late 1960's, there was a musical about innocence, peace, love and harmony - and protest. With a bountiful rock score, a minimalist book and free-flowing staging, it signaled a radical new form for the Broadway musical. It also had a profusion of taboo words, scenes depicting drug use and lovemaking, and one scene displaying frontal nudity.</p>
        <p>IN the late 1960's, there was a musical about innocence, peace, love and harmony - and protest. With a bountiful rock score, a minimalist book and free-flowing staging, it signaled a radical new form for the Broadway musical. It also had a profusion of taboo words, scenes depicting drug use and lovemaking, and one scene displaying frontal nudity.</p>
        <p>One does not need to be a musical theater connoisseur to name the show. It was ''Hair.''</p>
        <p>But what is one to make of ''Hair'' today? Is it dated, yet another artifact of the 1960's? Or is it a quaint period piece to be wistfully recalled? Can it shock anew, and for new reasons?</p>
        <p>Richard C. Hallinan, the executive producer of the Downtown Cabaret Theater's production of ''Hair,'' which began a 10-week run in Bridgeport on Friday, said he cannot help wondering just how the revolutionary ''American Tribal Love-Rock Musical'' of 1967 will go over with modern audiences.  Chosen for Variety</p>
        <p>Even though he sensed that he might be stirring things up with ''Hair,'' the main reason Mr. Hallinan chose the musical was to put variety into the season. ''We used to do similar shows back to back, but now we're aiming for a broad contrast,'' he said, citing the Cabaret's last two offerings, ''Dreamgirls,'' a high-tech disco opera, and ''The Boy Friend,'' a 1950's version of a 20's musical, and the forthcoming ''Sugar,'' a conventional 1970's book show based on the film ''Some Like It Hot.''</p>
        <p>''Yes, 'Hair' is obviously dated,'' Mr. Hallinan said. ''The specter of AIDS and the pressing problem of drugs make it so. But we're trying to make a virtue of the period and keep to it. This is the way it was and this is the way it looked. But whereas we thought we were doing a musical the whole world knew, it's clear that's true only up to a certain age.</p>
        <p>''When we saw a production in Chicago three months ago, a couple at our table, in their early 20s, had never heard the songs. I've always loved the music, and its infectious enthusiasm. I know it's old, but right now it's all fresh and new to me. And this was the first time young people dared to get up and challenge the establishment.''  Caveat for the Audience</p>
        <p>As a safeguard, Mr. Hallinan said, ''we're giving it an 'R' rating.''</p>
        <p>''We have warned our audiences in a reasonable way,'' he said. ''If subscribers think it's offensive, they can get credit or a refund. And often ticket buyers are told there's a brief nude scene at the end of Act 1. Actually, our audiences might have a harder time with the show's structure than with songs like 'Sodomy' or 'Hashish.' 'Hair' can look like a happy shambles, without a discernible book, and with all those loose relationships and diversions. But, of course, it is tightly conceived.''</p>
        <p>''Hair'' lasted 1,750 performances on Broadway, still one of the longest-running shows. The number of ''Hair'' productions - amateur and professional, country and worldwide - since the 1968 Broadway opening (after a successful run at the Public Theater in 1967) may well be incalculable. But, it is clear that a renewed interest in ''Hair'' is in the air.</p>
        <p>Witness a spate of recent revivals, starting with a concert version performed at the United Nations last year for the benefit of an organization to combat AIDS. And Performance Studio in New Haven presented a six-weekend run of ''Hair'' in the round at the beginning of this year.</p>
        <p>Such revivals are perhaps prompted by the considerable media attention to the year 1968 - ''the year that shaped a generation,'' according to a special Time magazine issue published this year.  'A Healing Power'</p>
        <p>When reached in Fort Lauderdale, where he was attending a new production of the musical, James Rado, the co-author of ''Hair's'' book and lyrics with Gerome Ragni, said: ''The show has that emotional impact again, like a healing power. Even though it's about the past, what are our concerns now? The environment, the ozone layer, oil spills, nuclear arms, our food. The war that was going on then stirred us, but today we have a symbolic war.</p>
        <p>''I have a strong feeling the show will come to New York again. The time is right. Musical energy in the theater is needed now.''</p>
        <p>A full-scale Broadway revival of ''Hair'' in 1977, which Mr. Rado called premature and poorly conceived, ran only 43 performances after 79 previews.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rado is so confident of a new life for ''Hair'' that he, Mr. Ragni and the musical's composer, Galt MacDermot, who are collaborating upon a new musical, ''Sun,'' have been revising ''Hair.''</p>
        <p>''We've been working on the script for two years, altering the sequence of songs and adding new ones,'' Mr. Rado said. ''It's almost surreal, creating a new project which is not a rock musical - it has Latin rhythms and it's about the world today - and then realizing, 'My God, we're still writing 'Hair!' ''</p>
        <p>In a lower Manhattan rehearsal hall, before a recent run-through of the Bridgeport production, which will include one of the new songs and several script revisions, the director Stanley Ramsey commented on the recent Chicago production of ''Hair.''</p>
        <p>''It was a 1990's technological wonder, without the spirit,'' he said. ''They didn't do their research.'' Mr. Ramsey is a ''Hair'' veteran who was understudy for the role of Hud, a black militant, in the Broadway production in 1970.  Encounter Groups for the Cast</p>
        <p>The Bridgeport company has 21 actors between the ages of 18 and 30. The Broadway cast had 26 members. To get the Bridgeport cast into the spirit, Mr. Ramsey, re-created encounter groups and exercises on sensitivity and trust that the show's original director, Tom O'Horgan, conducted more than 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>At one point, the cast formed a circle, joined hands and chanted while breathing deeply. ''They send positive energy to each other and that enables them to work as an ensemble,'' Mr. Ramsey explained.</p>
        <p>As for research, each cast member was asked to fill out a 36-part questionnaire that asked such questions as ''Where is Woodstock?'' ''What was Kent State?'' ''Who was Janis Joplin?'' and ''How long was the U.S.-Vietnam involvement?''</p>
        <p>When questioned about the show's staying power, Mr. Ramsey said: ''Society has gone in the direction of greed. The 80's got rid of idealism and substituted cynical attitudes and fear. But some people still have it in their hearts and they're trying to survive. The issues of the show are about human and civil rights. It's not about dirty words or doing drugs. And 'Hair' is still naive enough to think we can change the world.''</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
