<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE EAST VILLAGE'S ART GALLERIES ARE ALIVE IN SOHO</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="217815"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RELOCATION OF BUSINESS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOHO (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EAST VILLAGE (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, ROBERTA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDD153DF934A15752C0A96F948260" item-length="1942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE EAST VILLAGE'S ART GALLERIES ARE ALIVE IN SOHO</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SMITH, ROBERTA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The East Village art scene may be defunct, but its legacy lives on deep in the complicated heart of SoHo, where art and money, glamour and real estate continue to mingle in evermore varied combinations. The move of galleries out of the East Village, which started in earnest last season, still continues and is in its second and probably final phase.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The East Village art scene may be defunct, but its legacy lives on deep in the complicated heart of SoHo, where art and money, glamour and real estate continue to mingle in evermore varied combinations. The move of galleries out of the East Village, which started in earnest last season, still continues and is in its second and probably final phase.</p>
        <p>The East Village art scene may be defunct, but its legacy lives on deep in the complicated heart of SoHo, where art and money, glamour and real estate continue to mingle in evermore varied combinations. The move of galleries out of the East Village, which started in earnest last season, still continues and is in its second and probably final phase.</p>
        <p>In a way SoHo has absorbed its opposition, and is somewhat the better for it. This year's crop of migrating East Village dealers has shifted SoHo's geographical balance toward its quieter southern corners, and a few have left their spaces a bit more raw than has lately been the norm. Consequently, visiting these new galleries one has an eerie sense of being in touch with both SoHo's emptier, less high-powered past and its expansive and increasingly sophisticated present - and sometimes this quality is reflected in the art on view.</p>
        <p>Inevitably, the how and where of these recent relocations send different signals and have different effects. Certain dealers have moved to bigger, more glamorously designed spaces. Their new addresses and interiors - as much as the art on view - seem intended to announce a kind of professional coming of age.</p>
        <p>This is true of the newly relocated 303 Gallery, briefly of East Sixth Street, although its name derives from its original Park Avenue South address. It is also true of the big new Broadway quarters that the P.P.O.W. Gallery, known for its shows of political art, moved into last September. Why Some Make the Move</p>
        <p>For other galleries, moving to SoHo has had more of a foot-in-the-door feeling, the keeping of a deliberately low profile, with dealers relocating to spaces that are either small, modestly refinished or somewhat off the beaten path. The latter is the case with the Fiction/Nonfiction Gallery, which has departed from its tiny Avenue B storefront for a large plain space on Mercer Street below Grand.</p>
        <p>It also applies to the American Fine Arts Company, the enterprise of the dealer Colin De Land, whose nominally rehabilitated space on Wooster Street below Broome Street may invoke memories of SoHo circa 1972 for some viewers. Whether it's a matter of style or necessity, it's refreshing that new SoHo galleries can at least look as if they're run on a shoestring.</p>
        <p>This season's new arrivals from the East Village and elsewhere have tended to avoid the three huge gallery buildings - or art malls - at Prince and Broadway. Their locations, as outlined below, plot a loose circular swing through SoHo's southern half, with emphasis on its sparsely occupied southwest corner. Of course, it's only relative. But, compared with the congested sidewalks of Prince and Broadway - where the new and enlarged Dean &amp; DeLuca store with its coffee bar and people-watching windows has put yet another spin on the action - Broome and Wooster can seem almost like no man's land.</p>
        <p>It is perhaps best to start this southwesterly swing through SoHo at P.P.O.W., with the group exhibition ''Broken Landscape, Discarded Object,'' where connoisseurship and a rather morose romanticism seem to have won out over politics. This show (on view through Feb. 8), whose curator was Christopher Sweet, offers a potpourri of images and objects that concentrate on fragmented terrains or pieced-together still lifes. Its best moments are many; some of the less predictable ones include Rudy Burckhardt's photographs, two drawings by Franz Kline, H. C. Westermann's 1955 lead sculpture titled ''Cross Section of a Man Buried Alive'' and Walter Murch's ''Doorbell,'' a watercolor from about 1950. Like the 70's</p>
        <p>If the relative quiet of some SoHo streets can momentarily bring back memories of calmer emptier days, the art in several of the new galleries often recalls aspects of the early 70's as well. One floor down from P.P.O.W. for example, one can view the subdued monochromes of Nancy Haynes, on view (through Feb. 4) at the John Good Gallery, which moved south from NoHo this fall. In previous efforts, Ms. Haynes has juxtaposed small panels of different materials - steel next to oil on wood, for example - as if using the early work of Brice Marden and Carl Andre as points of departure.</p>
        <p>This year, Ms. Haynes is taking a more exclusively painterly approach, using illusions of light and color to divide her panels. For the most part, the work seems to mark a transition for the artist and has too many echoes of Minimalist abstraction.</p>
        <p>Down the street from P.P.O.W. and John Good is an East Village arrival of last season: the Bruno Facchetti Gallery at 476 Broadway, below Broome Street. The current exhibition here (through Feb. 25) is Maura Sheehan's ''Surface-Tension,'' an installation involving two crisscrossing volleyball nets, a large white ball that emits strange sounds and parallel black lines on the floor, whose decreasing intervals distort the depth of the room. Suggesting aspects of both Surrealism and computerization, the work nonetheless has the effect of a one-line joke that never quite makes its point. Rational and Playful One block west at 21 Mercer Street below Grand is the Fiction/Nonfiction Gallery where Stanley Whitney's abstract paintings can be seen (through Feb. 4). Balancing the rational with the playful, Mr. Whitney's floating spheres suggest party balloons, but they also define a grid and are themselves gridded by loose brushwork. Often beautifully painted, these canvases become monotonous when viewed in a group; their marks are not as varied as those that have animated the artist's small prints over the years.</p>
        <p>Doubling back toward Grand Street, the visitor should take in the exhibition of Conrad Atkinson, a British Conceptualist, on view through Feb. 4 at the Ronald Feldman Gallery at 35 Mercer, a longtime outpost in southern SoHo. Mr. Atkinson's satiric paintings and posters (the latter designed for the London Underground) revise the front pages of various newspapers, especially The Wall Street Journal.</p>
        <p>Conflating art and news, past and present, the best evoke a time (virtually, but not quite nonexistent) when artists were among the world's movers, shakers and policy makers. With such headlines as ''Rodin to Sculpt Missile Silo'' and ''Fra Angelico Utterly Opposed to Star Wars; Defines the Plan as Unethical, Unworkable and Ungodly,'' they are good for several laughs.</p>
        <p>Back on Grand Street, one can visit Shelagh Keeley's exhibition of black-and-white drawings at Tomoko Ligouri Gallery (93 Grand Street, through Feb. 11) before continuing west two blocks to Wooster Street. There, at the American Fine Arts Company at 40 Wooster Street is a show by Peter Fend, another artist with strong Conceptual Art leanings, titled ''Completion of the War'' (through Feb. 11).</p>
        <p>At once grandiose and visually attenuated, Mr. Fend's work consists of big cutout aeronautical maps featuring some of the world's seas and coastlines that figured prominently in 20th-century military and economic struggles, especially the pursuit of fossil fuels. These works are intriguing for the way they tackle the interface of 20th-century history, economics and basically, the future of the planet, but they don't give the viewer much to go on, nor does the artist's long rambling explanatory text clarify matters. Of Contrasts</p>
        <p>Across the street is another recent arrival from the East Village, the Pat Hearn Gallery at 31 Wooster. The gallery's three-artist exhibition, on view through Feb. 4, evokes the early days of Process art and its European counterpart, Arte Povera, and a time when artists were strongly guided by the inherent properties of contrasting materials.</p>
        <p>In this show, Patty Martori fills a long glass case with a slope of pure white plaster, simultaneously evoking burial, human remains, the landscape and an artificial environment for a delicate unseen creature. Similarly, Thom Merrick rests half a dozen rusted steel pipes on a translucent vinyl mattress cover filled with ink. The ensemble suggests a disassembled raft floating on its own dark ocean while more immediately putting pressure on an unstable situation.</p>
        <p>Also on view at Hearn are two wall pieces by one J. St. Bernard. These consist of images from dog-food packages printed on paintinglike steel forms that come complete with their own canvas covers, a la Ashley Bickerton. The artist's name, the dearth of biographical data, the canine subject matter and general hipness of this work suggest a kinship to John Dogg, a fictional artist thought to be the creation of a number of artists and dealers, whose work was exhibited at 303 Gallery and the American Fine Arts Company in 1987. Seemingly on a Shoestring</p>
        <p>Another new presence in this corner of SoHo and an adherent to the shoestring mode is the Feature Gallery, squeezed into a tiny space at 484 Broome Street, just west of Wooster. Feature has relocated to SoHo from Chicago, but its style and scale are very East Village. Its current exhibition through Feb. 11 presents the work of an artist from Cincinnati, Peter Huttinger: small hard-surfaced monochromes whose organic bumps and craters suggest enlargements of the skin's surface or condensations of the moon's.</p>
        <p>One block north and east, on the corner of Spring and Greene Streets, is the just opened 303 Gallery at 89 Greene Street (with a temporary entrance at 127 Spring Street). Its inaugural exhibition presents the work of Larry Johnson, a young artist from California who is showing for the third time at this gallery. Mr. Johnson's work continues a tendency of Conceptual Art that gives the printed word pride of place. While the texts deployed by by such artists as Barbara Kruger and Jenny Holzer - to cite two well-known examples - frequently focus on feminist issues, Mr. Johnson's newest texts, which come in the form of framed color photographs, focus on homosexuality. Telling Stories</p>
        <p>Every one of Mr. Johnson's word pictures tells a story, both through its text and the artist's use of color. The suggestiveness of his subject matter is often veiled by visual devices -like printing the letters of each word in several colors so the eye stumbles over them or gets caught up in the purely formal aspects of their constrasting shades.</p>
        <p>In one piece, the letters are so pale that the text - some form of police interrogation - becomes unreadable at certain points, creating the sensation of listening in on a clandestine event that despite the official language is fraught with menace. The meanings or tone of one work can also affect our reading of the next. While one text quotes from ''The Joys of Hustling,'' the one next to it, parenthetically titled ''The Friends You Keep and the Books You Read,'' is simply an Amway testimonial, but it ends up sounding as seductive and perhaps even more cynical than its neighbor.</p>
        <p>The continual give and take between meaning and form in Mr. Johnson's work is its strongest quality. He forces us to compare the perceptual differences of seeing and reading and the distinctly different pleasures of looking and hearing. At the End</p>
        <p>Leaving 303 Gallery, the viewer has more or less come full circle through an area where new galleries are filling in some of the gaps between established galleries.</p>
        <p>Three more East Village venues poised for migration to SoHo are Gracie Mansion Gallery, which is to be relocating to the fourth floor of 532 Broadway (upstairs from P.P.O.W.) in March or April; Loughelton Gallery, to open in a small ground-level space at 67 Prince Street at Crosby, in March, and Postmasters Gallery, currently of 66 Avenue A, which is close to signing a lease on a gallery space near Spring and Greene in SoHo.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
