<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Greenhouse Effect Is for Real</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="217949"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DE1F3CF934A15752C0A96F948260" item-length="540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Greenhouse Effect Is for Real</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A team of Government scientists report no sign of a warming trend in the average temperatures in the United States over the last century. Does that mean the greenhouse effect, the feared heating of the earth's atmosphere by burning coal and oil, is just another false alarm? The answer, unfortunately, is an emphatic no.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A team of Government scientists report no sign of a warming trend in the average temperatures in the United States over the last century. Does that mean the greenhouse effect, the feared heating of the earth's atmosphere by burning coal and oil, is just another false alarm? The answer, unfortunately, is an emphatic no.</p>
        <p>A team of Government scientists report no sign of a warming trend in the average temperatures in the United States over the last century. Does that mean the greenhouse effect, the feared heating of the earth's atmosphere by burning coal and oil, is just another false alarm? The answer, unfortunately, is an emphatic no.</p>
        <p>Gases like carbon dioxide, spewed out in the burning of coal, wood and oil, let in the sun's light but trap the resulting heat as it tries to return to space. That's a matter of simple physics.</p>
        <p>Also undisputed is that the amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere has been steadily building up since the beginning of the Industrial Revolution. Unless there is something to counteract the growing volumes of carbon dioxide, the earth's atmosphere will eventually start to heat up.</p>
        <p>There is no certainty that it has done so. But that doesn't mean the theory is wrong. The expected amount of warming is very small compared with the natural variability in the earth's temperature. Thus any signal of a warming trend would be hard to spot.</p>
        <p>Last summer's dramatic drought helped focus attention on the greenhouse theory because drought in mid-latitudes is one of the warming effects predicted by computer simulations. Even then, many climatologists were rightly concerned not to cry wolf by declaring too early that the warming had begun. Most of them believe, however, that the greenhouse effect is to be taken seriously.</p>
        <p>Climatologists will argue for many years whether the greenhouse warming has started. But there's every reason to take action immediately, and not wait until that debate is concluded. Once warming begins, its momentum will continue - even if gas emissions could be stopped immediately - for the three decades or so that it takes to heat the oceans. At that point the planet will again be in equilibrium, but at a much higher temperature than that of the initial warming signal.</p>
        <p>It's far too early to recommend that countries stop burning coal. But there are several other steps that would help postpone the greenhouse effect, all well worth taking in their own right:</p>
        <p>* Phase out chlorofluorocarbons, the industrial gases used as refrigerants and solvents. They chew up the protective ozone layer in the stratosphere and also exert a strong greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>* Conserve energy by taxing gasoline and requiring Detroit to double the fuel efficiency of its cars.</p>
        <p>* Preserve tropical forests instead of letting them be burned by landless farmers. The wholesale burning of forests in Brazil contributed a tenth of the carbon dioxide injected into the world's atmosphere last year.</p>
        <p>* Press the development of smokeless forms of energy generation, like solar power and a new generation of safer, cheaper nuclear power plants.</p>
        <p>The earth's climate is far from being understood. Natural counteractions to the warming, like increased cloud cover, might come to the rescue by damping down any greenhouse effect. But why bet on it? The greenhouse warming may not arrive for several decades, or it may already have started and outrun the capacity of natural systems to adapt. Either way, the precautionary measures already at hand are cheap insurance against risks of such magnitude.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
