<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Palmy, Balmy Site for Breeders'</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="296360"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="ON HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HORSE RACING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THOROUGHBRED RACING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FLORIDA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CRIST, STEVEN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BREEDERS CUP</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DF1531F932A05753C1A96F948260" item-length="757" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Palmy, Balmy Site for Breeders'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Steven Crist</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CRIST, STEVEN</byline>
      <dateline>HALLANDALE, Fla.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The smell of suntan lotion sweetens the salt air in the ocean breezes. Hot and blinding sunlight bounces from the blue water to the shell-pink stucco of the beachfront hotels. The breaking waves muffle the rustle of swaying palm fronds. Just like the travel brochures promise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The smell of suntan lotion sweetens the salt air in the ocean breezes. Hot and blinding sunlight bounces from the blue water to the shell-pink stucco of the beachfront hotels. The breaking waves muffle the rustle of swaying palm fronds. Just like the travel brochures promise.</p>
        <p>The smell of suntan lotion sweetens the salt air in the ocean breezes. Hot and blinding sunlight bounces from the blue water to the shell-pink stucco of the beachfront hotels. The breaking waves muffle the rustle of swaying palm fronds. Just like the travel brochures promise.</p>
        <p>Welcome to the most unfamiliar sights and sounds ever to surround a fall championship season in American thoroughbred racing. Don't blame global warming: it's only that the Breeders' Cup, which will be run Saturday for the sixth time, has never been held in Florida before.</p>
        <p>In the pre-Cup era, the sport's titles were won and lost on chilly October afternoons at Belmont Park. Overcoats and hip flasks were the order of the day. Even at last year's Breeders' Cup, champions emerged from the cold rain and darkness of Churchill Downs.</p>
        <p>Three of the first five Cups were contested in California, but that is not the same, in either latitude or attitude. Californians seem to live at room temperature, but Miami is unmistakably tropical. This is the first Breeders' Cup where the locals have suntans and the visitors are rushing the beaches.</p>
        <p>Only the horses are taking it in stride. Most headed south before sprouting their winter coats, and the first hours after dawn are cool enough to gallop beneath the palms without getting hot and bothered.</p>
        <p>Even for Florida racing, the time is out of joint. The races of lasting significance here are run January through April, not this late in the calendar year or this early in the tourist season.</p>
        <p>The arrival of the Cup coincides with another jarring change. Two weeks from Saturday, Hialeah Park, the gorgeous track where the flamingos roam and great horses used to race, will open its longest and strangest meeting ever.</p>
        <p>Rock-bottom claimers from minor league tracks around the country will occupy the stalls where future Kentucky Derby winners once wintered. The track will try to scratch out an existence while competing on a daily basis with Calder and then, for almost four months beginning Jan. 15, with Gulfstream.</p>
        <p>It is a war that Hialeah seems doomed to lose, especially now that Bertram R. Firestone is a few formalities away from owning both Calder and Gulfstream. The Calder and Gulfstream horses will not be welcomed back if they van over to Hialeah, so Hialeah might as well be a jai-alai fronton on Key West, or Mars. The only question is whether Hialeah will fold, surrender or live on in obscurity.</p>
        <p>Even in season, Florida racing has a surreal quality beyond its exotic setting. The winter game is a nightmare to handicap. Horses are shipped in from dozens of northern tracks, local Calder runners try entirely new footing at Gulfstream, and stakes horses are prepped at less than full effort for the richer events of the spring.</p>
        <p>The degree of difficulty in picking winners may prove the most familiar aspect of Florida this week. On first, second and third glance, this year's Cup races look either challenging (if you're an optimist) or impossible (if you're a realist).</p>
        <p>''With most of these races,'' the trainer Shug McGaughey was saying yesterday, ''you might as well put the horses' names in a danged hat to pick your winners.''</p>
        <p>McGaughey was presumably not referring to the $3 million Classic, where his Easy Goer is the day's only solid favorite. The next-richest race, the $2 million Turf, is a lottery among the worst crop of American grass horses in years and a planeload of substandard Europeans.</p>
        <p>The Mile, usually the toughest race on the card, looks comparatively manageable this year, with Steinlen clearly the top American, and Zilzal towering over the Europeans. In the Distaff, Bayakoa may be odds-on in the betting, but it's tough to believe she will fight off all the pacesetters being thrown at her early and still survive.</p>
        <p>As for the Juvenile, Juvenile Fillies and Sprint, McGaughey's hat might be the answer.</p>
        <p>No one is complaining, though. The Breeders' Cup in just five years has fulfilled its planners' hopes, attracting virtually every top horse in training to determine the best of the best. So what if the races look tough? Showdowns among divisional leaders are not supposed to be mismatches. If you have an opinion, you'll get a square price.</p>
        <p>Those opinions will come into focus this week, as the horses have their final workouts and the horseplayers sharpen their figures - if they can keep their minds on the past performances. With beaches, racing greyhounds and stone crabs beckoning, this championship week is full of delightfully unseasonal distractions.</p>
        <p>ON HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
