<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Effort to Protect Ozone</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="285888"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR CONDITIONING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DB163AF936A1575AC0A96F948260" item-length="1480" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Effort to Protect Ozone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The battle to save the atmosphere's protective layer of ozone is moving to a new front: the corner auto-repair shop, where an ounce-by-ounce struggle is under way to limit the escape of the vast amounts of air-conditioning fluid handled daily.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The battle to save the atmosphere's protective layer of ozone is moving to a new front: the corner auto-repair shop, where an ounce-by-ounce struggle is under way to limit the escape of the vast amounts of air-conditioning fluid handled daily.</p>
        <p>The battle to save the atmosphere's protective layer of ozone is moving to a new front: the corner auto-repair shop, where an ounce-by-ounce struggle is under way to limit the escape of the vast amounts of air-conditioning fluid handled daily.</p>
        <p>All types of air-conditioners and refrigerators use the ozone-depleting chemicals called chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC-12. About 41 percent of the CFC-12 used for refrigeration in the United States is used by vehicle air-conditioners. But because vehicle air-conditioners are particularly prone to leaks and need frequent replacements of refrigerant, they use 75 percent of the country's replacement CFC-12. Large amounts of CFC-12 escape into the air during the replacement and also during regular operation of auto air-conditioners.</p>
        <p>''They're guaranteed to leak,'' said Arthur T. Anderson, a specialist in CFC's at the Energy Department.</p>
        <p>But this month, several new machines that will recycle the refrigerant were endorsed by Underwriters Laboratories, a consumer-products testing concern, for use on car air-conditioners under warranty. The result could be widespread changes in the way vehicle air-conditioners are serviced. Payback on Equipment</p>
        <p>The change would be expensive -costing an estimated 225,000 repair shops perhaps $750 million - and would be passed on to the owners of about 100 million cars that have air-conditioning. But the manufacturers of the machines, which cost from $2,500 to $7,000, argue that, with the cost of CFC-12 rising as production is slowed, the equipment will quickly pay for itself, in addition to helping the environment.</p>
        <p>The United States is the only large country in which auto air-conditioners are in wide use. ''Americans who want to sound like good guys sound like jerks, because so much of our use is auto air-conditioners,'' said David D. Doniger, the director of the ozone protection project at the Natural Resources Defense Council.</p>
        <p>Mr. Doniger's group, a nonprofit organization based in Washington that has been particularly active on the ozone issue, favors a faster phase-out, and recycling, of the refrigerant in all the places it is used.</p>
        <p>One reason car air-conditioners leak more than window air-conditioners or home refrigerators is the harsh environment under the hood. Another is the fact that the mechanical power to run car units comes from outside the system, requiring a spinning shaft attached to the car's engine that is hard to seal and that sooner or later springs leaks. In a building's window air-conditioner, the power comes from an electric motor that is located inside the sealed system. Supply Squeeze Ahead</p>
        <p>With CFC-12 production already cut to 1986 levels under an international environmental agreement signed in January, a shortage of the refrigerant is dveloping. Prices have already doubled in the last year and are widely expected to double again in coming months. Freon, the Du Pont brand, is the best-known CFC-12.</p>
        <p>What is more, production is scheduled to be cut by half by 1998, and many environmental officials would like to accelerate the cut. President Bush has endorsed a complete ban on production by 2000, if safe replacements can be found.</p>
        <p>One alternative for cars is a non-CFC-12 refrigerant, but the only chemical combinations discovered so far would require $1,000 or more in modifications to existing air-conditioners.</p>
        <p>The layer of ozone in the upper atmosphere helps screen the earth from ultraviolet rays and other harmful radiation from the sun. An increase in air pollutants produced by industrialization over the last century has caused a chemical reaction with ozone that scientists say has thinned or depleted the ozone layer in some spots. An increase in the amount of harmful rays reaching earth has been linked to increases in skin cancer and cataracts in humans, and a variety of problems in other animals and plants.</p>
        <p>Vermont, Oregon and Hawaii have already passed laws barring the sale of small cans of refrigerant, which are used by weekend mechanics and poorly equipped gas stations, and other states are expected to follow. The cans allow car air-conditioners to be refilled cheaply, but without repairing the leak, meaning that another refill will be required.</p>
        <p>From an environmental point of view, said Mr. Doniger, ''you're putting CFC's in your air-conditioner for a day, a month or even a season, and then into the atmosphere for 150 years.'' The cans, he said, are ''grenades.'' Leakage During Repair</p>
        <p>When an auto air-conditioner has stopped working because of a refrigerant leak, it may still have as much as 70 percent of its coolant. It is standard practice to vent the system before fixing. Even when a unit is fixed, mechanics often use a full load of refrigerant just to flush out a system or check for leaks.</p>
        <p>The alternative is a machine that will recycle the refrigerant by sucking it out of the air-conditioner and purifying it for re-use. One obstacle had been that auto manufacturers insisted on virgin coolant or they would not honor the warranty. Contaminated coolant could damage a system.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, however, Underwriters Laboratories certified several recycling units as able to filter coolant to a standard sufficient for use in units under warranty.</p>
        <p>Now that recovery machines are available, manufacturers expect brisk sales. ''You can't penalize a shop, saying they must have a machine, if they can't get one,'' said Jeffrey L. Sachs, president of Draf Industries Inc., a privately held manufacturing company in Bedford Hills, N.Y. The company makes a $2,995 recycling machine that was recently approved by Underwriters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sachs said that, as certified machines become available, ''within 18 months, almost every state's going to have a regulation'' requiring mechanics to buy one.</p>
        <p>Some manufacturers think adoption of the new machines will not even require state laws. ''Just the economics of using the equipment will drive the market,'' said John P. Hancock, vice president of White Industries of Indianapolis, which markets its $2,900 machine under the brand name K-Whit Tools. With refrigerant at its present price, he said, his machine would save enough to pay for itself after 300 cars. Commitment by General Motors</p>
        <p>''If the price of this stuff gets up high enough, even a junkyard will want to buy one,'' said John Tyson, vice president of the SPX Corporation, Muskegon, Mich. His company sells recycling equipment under the brand names of Robinair, Kent-Moore and Bear Automotive. The General Motors Corporation announced in August that it would make the Kent-Moore model available to its 10,000 dealers and that the dealers would have to have the equipment for 1991 cars.</p>
        <p>Others are not certain that the economics will induce thousands of small businesses to invest. But some service stations may do so and publicize the fact to capitalize on public concern about the ozone, experts predict.</p>
        <p>''I never hear people talk about toxic chemicals, old-growth forests or things like that,'' said Mr. Doniger, whose organization concerns itself with a varity of environmental problems. ''But people know about the hole in the ozone layer. They care about this stuff.''</p>
        <p>The idea appeals to some service mechanics.</p>
        <p>''I'm an environmental goof,'' said Richard A. De Silva, owner of De Silva's Auto Air Conditioning in East Detroit, Mich. ''I like to get things cleaned up. And we've got to protect the kids coming up.''</p>
        <p>Mr. De Silva, who has 11 service bays, has been using a recycler for eight months, cutting his refrigerant use drastically. It has already paid for itself, he said. Two Machines at Once</p>
        <p>Efforts to protect the ozone may give the manufacturers of recycling equipment a double boon: one now, when service stations rush to buy so they can continue servicing air- conditioners, and one when the next generation of air-conditioners comes along. Those air-conditioners will use a refrigerant that does not damage the ozone, but it is likely to be so expensive that recycling will be the norm. And the two refrigerants cannot be mixed, so two machines will be needed as long as both kinds of air-conditioners are on the road.</p>
        <p>Industry experts think a side-effect of widespread recycling will be a reduction in the number of service locations for air-conditioning work. The business may become similar to transmission work, with car owners either going to a specialist or to a local gas station that farms out the work to the specialist.</p>
        <p>If the price of environmental regulations drives some companies out of the air-conditioning repair business, say the manufacturers, so be it.</p>
        <p>''A man who cannot afford a $2,500 recovery system,'' said Thorne Gould, president of the Murray Corporation, a manufacturer of recycling equipment and other air-conditioning service parts, ''is really not in the air-conditioning business anyway.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
