<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PARIS GROUP URGES 'DECISIVE ACTION' FOR ENVIRONMENT</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="266577"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CURRENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITTERRAND, FRANCOIS (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORBACHEV, MIKHAIL S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARKHAM, JAMES M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0D8123BF934A25754C0A96F948260" item-length="1399" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PARIS GROUP URGES 'DECISIVE ACTION' FOR ENVIRONMENT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES M. MARKHAM, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARKHAM, JAMES M</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, July 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The leaders of the Group of Seven industrial democracies today signaled a shift to a new realm of concern by dedicating a third of their final communique to an appeal for ''decisive action'' to ''understand and protect the earth's ecological balance.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The leaders of the Group of Seven industrial democracies today signaled a shift to a new realm of concern by dedicating a third of their final communique to an appeal for ''decisive action'' to ''understand and protect the earth's ecological balance.''</p>
        <p>The leaders of the Group of Seven industrial democracies today signaled a shift to a new realm of concern by dedicating a third of their final communique to an appeal for ''decisive action'' to ''understand and protect the earth's ecological balance.''</p>
        <p>Concluding one of their most harmonious summit gatherings ever, the seven nations also endorsed Washington's strategy for encouraging banks and third world nations to negotiate the terms of debt reductions; expressed prudent confidence in the general state of the world economy, and agreed to set up a task force to combat the laundering of money earned through drug trafficking. United Nations Aid Sought</p>
        <p>Asserting that ''the drug problem has reached devastating proportions,'' the seven leaders called for enlisting the United Nations ''to counter drug production, to reduce demand and to carry forward the fight against drug trafficking itself and the laundering of its proceeds.''  [ Text, page A7. ]  While expressing concern, and at times alarm, about the environment, the leaders from Western Europe and North America fell short of making any firm commitments to remedy the situation.</p>
        <p>The shift toward a new global agenda was underscored, too, by the detailed attention given by the seven leaders over dinner last night to a letter from Mikhail S. Gorbachev, the Soviet President, offering to integrate the Soviet Union ''fully and completely into the world economy'' and to help resolve the issue of third world debt.</p>
        <p>Summarizing the summit's deliberations at a news conference at the gleaming Arche de la Defense on the western outskirts of Paris, President Francois Mitterrand said that the seven leaders did not consider it necessary to respond collectively to Mr. Gorbachev's missive but that they ''hoped for the success of the democratization under way in the Soviet Union.'' 'We Will Contribute'</p>
        <p>''We are not charged with assuring its success but, to the extent that we can do so, we will contribute,'' said Mr. Mitterrand, who was host to Mr. Gorbachev during an official visit to Paris this month.</p>
        <p>Chancellor Helmut Kohl of West Germany effusively welcomed the Gorbachev initiative, but President Bush echoed Mr. Mitterrand's caution, saying it would take greater ''manifestations of freedom'' before the Soviet Union could become a full-fledged economic interlocutor for the seven.''</p>
        <p>''I think it's very premature,'' President Bush told a news conference. ''There's an awful lot that has to transpire in the Soviet Union, it seems to me, before anything of that nature could be considered here. We're talking about free market economies here.''</p>
        <p>Speaking on the lawn of the American embassy residence, Mr. Bush said that he did not think the time was yet right for a summit encounter with Mr. Gorbachev and pronounced the Paris gathering ''a clear success'' that had been ''a watershed on the environment.''</p>
        <p>The exceptionally smooth three days of deliberations in Paris were helped by a moderately buoyant world economy and the sharp reduction of East-West tensions that has flowed from Mr. Gorbachev's reforming efforts at home. President Bush also facilitated the discussions in Paris, European officials said, by his non-confrontational manner and his willingness to see the European Community take the lead on shaping policy toward Eastern Europe.</p>
        <p>Although the seven leaders were in a self-congratulatory mood on the world economy, they did not openly address troubling issues like the large American budget deficit and its contribution to high interest rates and third world debt. Moreover, hopes that Mexico would reach agreement here with its bank creditors on lowering its debt, in line with conditions laid down by Washington, were dashed.</p>
        <p>In a break with recent summit practice, the seven nations today said nothing specific about their objectives for the dollar. High-ranking American and European delegates explained privately that the summit partners wanted to avoid any possibility that financial markets might determine that the Paris gathering had taken a new initiative on the dollar. Committed to Earlier Policy</p>
        <p>Rather, the officials said, the seven remained committed to the policy announced at a finance ministers' meeting in April. That policy stated that a rise in the value of the dollar or any ''excessive'' decline would be ''counterproductive'' to the health of the world economy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitterrand and other leaders concurred in highlighting the imperiled environment as a compelling issue.</p>
        <p>''The interaction between man's activities and the global environment is such that if we are to pass on the heritage safe to our children's future, we must take action now,'' Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher of Britain told a news conference before leaving Paris. ''That is the imperative.'' After calling for ''decisive action,'' the seven nations also pledged ''to work together to achieve the common goals of preserving a healthy and balanced global environment in order to meet shared economic and social objectives and to carry out obligations to future generations.'' Several Environmental Issues</p>
        <p>The communique touched on virtually every major environmental issue, but offered no commitments to the problems, which include reducing carbon dioxide emissions even though the United States, Japan, Britain, West Germany, France, Italy and Canada account for about 40 percent of the world's carbon dioxide emissions generated by fossil fuel combustion.</p>
        <p>Instead, the seven said they ''strongly advocate common efforts to limit emissions of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases, which threaten to induce climate change, endangering the environment and ultimately the economy.'' Third World Debt Stance</p>
        <p>Despite its cautious tone, the communique did endorse the innovative notion of forgiving in ''special cases'' some third world debt in exchange for commitments to protect the environment.</p>
        <p>The communique also urged giving ''specific attention'' to moving beyond the landmark Montreal Protocol of 1987 to eliminate the production of ozone-depleting gasses like carbon tetrachloride, halons and meethylchloroform.</p>
        <p>Several senior European officials said that the importance of the lengthy environmental declaration was not in its specifics but rather in having the issue so solemnly enshrined in a summit communique for the first time. One European Community official observed that the leaders ''have raised public expectations, and at next year's summit in America people are going to ask them what they've done in the meantime.''</p>
        <p>On the topic of drugs, the summit nations announced that they and ''other countries interested in these problems'' would set up a task force to tighten efforts to prevent banks and other financial institutions from being used for the laundering of drug money. Some estimates put drug revenues at $300 billion.</p>
        <p>The task force will have the mandate to consider new measures ''including the adaptation of the legal and regulatory systems so as to enhance multilateral judicial assistance.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitterrand, the sole Socialist leader among the seven, had sought to use the summit gathering to advance the cause of heavily indebted third world nations. Inviting several African, Asian and Latin American leaders to the bicentennial celebrations of the French Revolution - which overlapped with the economic summit - he sponsored the idea of another so-called North-South summit on the model of the Cancun gathering in Mexico in 1981. Proposal Rebuffed</p>
        <p>But this proposal was quietly rebuffed by the summit partners. Mr. Mitterrand finally was left with little to show for his engagement aside from backing in the communique for World Bank studies on the flooding in Bangladesh - after France had pushed for a $5 billion embankment undertaking there - and verbal support for the establishment of observatories to monitor land erosion in Saharan nations.</p>
        <p>In backing the debt-reduction plan outlined by United States Treasury Secretary Nicholas F. Brady last March, the summit did not incorporate elements of a more generous proposal outlined by President Mitterrand that would have effectively used taxpayers' money to ease the debt burden weighing on the third world.</p>
        <p>''We stress that official creditors should not substitute for private lenders,'' declared the communique, embracing the spirit of the Brady approach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
