<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Irvine's Story: Conservative Town Becomes Environmental Innovator</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="269111"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRVINE (CALIF)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">REPUBLICAN PARTY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">AGRAN, LARRY (MAYOR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REINHOLD, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFDB133BF936A15754C0A96F948260" item-length="1283" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Irvine's Story: Conservative Town Becomes Environmental Innovator</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT REINHOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REINHOLD, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>IRVINE, Calif., July 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: When the Irvine Company founded this city out of orange groves in Orange County, it planned everything down to the width of the grass strips along the broad streets, the color of roof tiles on the regimented houses and even the length of time residents could keep their garage doors open.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: When the Irvine Company founded this city out of orange groves in Orange County, it planned everything down to the width of the grass strips along the broad streets, the color of roof tiles on the regimented houses and even the length of time residents could keep their garage doors open.</p>
        <p>When the Irvine Company founded this city out of orange groves in Orange County, it planned everything down to the width of the grass strips along the broad streets, the color of roof tiles on the regimented houses and even the length of time residents could keep their garage doors open.</p>
        <p>But in 1960, when the founders drew up the first master plan for development of the city, they probably never anticipated that their creation - today overwhelmingly white, affluent and Republican - would produce a relentlessly liberal City Council that has turned this city into a crucible of municipal innovation.</p>
        <p>On July 18, the council adopted the most restrictive controls anywhere on the use of chlorofluorocarbons and other industrial chemicals that harm the ozone layer that shields the earth from the sun's ultraviolet rays.</p>
        <p>Some saw it as a quixotic gesture, others as heroic. Either way, the action spoke volumes about the growing potency of environmental issues in the suburbs. The concerns are not primarily the traditional ones, like saving owls in the north woods, but more modern and closer to home: keeping open space for jogging and cycling, preserving beaches and bays for swimming and boating, and fighting overdevelopment. Democrats at Home</p>
        <p>And increasingly, affluent and well-educated residents, while subscribing to the Republican credos of free enterprise and limited government on national issues, are turning locally to Democrats who advocate more government.</p>
        <p>It has happened in Suffolk County, L.I., a similarly conservative area that has also become a hotbed of environmental advocacy. And it has happened in Irvine, where the nominally conservative voters elected a Democrat, Mayor Larry Agran, a 44-year-old a veteran of the Berkeley student rebellion in the 1960's who now makes his living as executive director of the Center for Innovative Diplomacy, an organization based here that promotes the idea that local governments can influence global affairs.</p>
        <p>''They are downright radical on matters of environmental protection,'' Mr. Agran said of his constituents. ''You cannot expect the private sector to solve problems of environmental pollution.''</p>
        <p>Critics say the Mayor has taken advantage of his constituents' complacency to promote a personal agenda of social action on the environment and other issues. ''Larry Agran is an extremely fine politician,'' said his only rival on the City Council, Sally Anne Sheridan, a real estate broker. ''But people are extremely apathetic. They are busy making payments on BMW's and houses.'' She added, ''I hope people will wake up.'' Running Against Developers</p>
        <p>But many political experts say Mr. Agran has not misread the voters. ''He is an example of a populist local political leader in the new tradition,'' said Mark G. Baldassare, a social scientist at the University of California at Irvine. ''He represents the interests of the more affluent, highly educated and most Republican residents on local issues.''</p>
        <p>''They don't care if you're a Communist,'' said Ralph A. Catalano, a former council member. ''Our city councils have become increasingly Democratic because they will run against the developers. The same voters who will vote for Larry Agran for mayor would never vote for him for Congress. They are conservative people who know their local interests are best served by voting for Democrats.''</p>
        <p>Typical of Mayor Agran's fans are Bart and Erika Tucker, both moderate Republicans who voted for George Bush for President last year. Mr. Tucker, a competitive triathalon athlete, works in corporate relocation for Coldwell Banker, the real estate company; his wife is a recruiter for the Irvine Chamber of Commerce.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tucker applauded Mr. Agran's efforts to preserve open space and create a curbside recycling program. ''Many things Agran's been doing affect me, particularly the environmental issues,'' said Mr. Tucker, who added that he lacked the time to take part in traditional environmental groups like the Sierra Club. Environmentalism Without Pain?  Skeptics see in all this a selfish environmentalism, saying the sort of people who can afford to pay $350,000 for a house in Irvine are much less likely to be affected by the city's new controls on industrial chemicals than are those who work at service stations and on the assembly lines of local computer and aerospace factories. ''It's easy to be for cleaning up the environment when there is no pain,'' said Michael Stockstill, director of intergovernmental relations for the Irvine Company, which is still developing sites in Irvine. ''It would be decidedly different if you said everybody in Irvine can no longer have air conditioners in their cars because they use freon.''</p>
        <p>Some see Irvine as the American future. It is a city of nearly 100,000 with no center, no cemeteries, 42 square miles of rigidly controlled communities and neat industrial parks behind eucalyptus trees and manicured lawns. (The parks house high-technology companies like Western Digital, Printronix, Alton Geoscience and AST Research.) The original idea was that people would live, shop and work in the same town, but it has not worked out that way: Workers drive in from remote areas of Southern California, doubling Irvine's population each day and compounding traffic congestion and smog. Pioneering Social Measures</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Agran, a lawyer by training, the City Council has passed numerous measures that belie Orange County's conservative image. Among them have been a pioneering law to require those who use or carry hazardous materials to report them, a curbside recycling program, an ordinance that bans discrimination against homosexuals and programs to provide transportation for the handicapped and housing for people of modest incomes. Efforts to house the homeless have been less successful; a plan to convert a former animal shelter into housing fell through two years ago.</p>
        <p>''He wants to make a play for himself - he wants to be a leader,'' said Barry J. Hammond, who ran against Mr. Agran for mayor last year. Mr. Hammond said Mr. Agran's ''hostile'' attitude toward business would drive business away. ''We all have a responsibility to worry about the ozone layer, but we are also responsible to our business community,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Some say the liberal council might thwart the fulfillment of the Irvine master plan, which envisions a population of 225,000 by the year 2000. For example, the council recently blocked an extension and widening of Yale Road, a major north-south thoroughfare; critics say this has worsened traffic elsewhere. They also say that if plans for new housing are cut back, it will mean higher housing prices and will force people to commute greater distances to their jobs. Some say that Mr. Agran is too liberal for the voters, that he is vulnerable to a challenge next year.</p>
        <p>Some companies have said they may not be able to expand or relocate here because of the recent measure on industrial chemicals. But Thomas U. Wall, president of the Chamber of Commerce, said, ''The business environment is very healthy - I don't think businesses will leave Irvine.'' Though Mr. Wall, a conservative Republican, often disagrees with the liberal Mayor, he conceded that Mr. Agran had wide backing: ''He's in tune with the voters - he's a master politician.''</p>
        <p>Whatever the outcome of next year's election here, it is clear that Orange County, the wellspring of the Reagan revolution, is no longer as conservative as it once was. ''Basically they are progressive,'' Mr. Agran said of his constituents. ''They want efficient institutions to address real problems. They are supportive of well-thought-out government programs.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
