<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Urgent Help for Environment Is Plea at Forum</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="246708"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SCIENCES, NATIONAL ACADEMY OF</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION (WASHINGTON, DC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DC103BF937A35756C0A96F948260" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Urgent Help for Environment Is Plea at Forum</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Rapid changes in the global environment caused by human activity demand urgent corrective action on an international scale, scientists, government leaders and industry officials said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Rapid changes in the global environment caused by human activity demand urgent corrective action on an international scale, scientists, government leaders and industry officials said today.</p>
        <p>Rapid changes in the global environment caused by human activity demand urgent corrective action on an international scale, scientists, government leaders and industry officials said today.</p>
        <p>At a forum on ''Global Change and Our Common Future'' organized by the National Academy of Sciences and the Smithsonian Institution, speakers repeatedly urged that major economic, scientific and political resources be immediately committed to solving problems like global warming and the depletion of the earth's protective ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Several speakers emphasized that a broad perception of threats to the environment was relatively new and could soon profoundly affect diplomacy and national security considerations.</p>
        <p>''In the not-distant future,'' said Senator Albert Gore, a Tennessee Democrat, ''there will be a new 'sacred agenda' in international affairs: policies that enable rescue of the global environment. This task will one day join, and even supplant, preventing the world's incineration through nuclear war as the principal test of statecraft.''</p>
        <p>Many speakers also stressed that the global environment can be rescued only with an approach that assures sustainable economic growth around the world, including poor nations. International Fund Is Sought</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Gro Harlem Brundtland of Norway said her nation was proposing ''as a starting point'' that all industrial nations allocate one-tenth of 1 percent of their gross domestic product to an ''international fund for the atmosphere'' to help developing countries industrialize in ways that would not degrade the environment.</p>
        <p>A United Nations report that Dr. Brundtland directed found that sustained economic development and preservation of the natural environment are mutually dependent.</p>
        <p>Throughout the conference, speakers spoke of the interrelationship of population growth, economic growth, global warming and prospective food shortages, possibly on a catastrophic scale.</p>
        <p>''This finite world will have to provide food and energy and meet the needs of a doubled world population sometime in the next century,'' Dr. Brundtland said today, adding that this task cannot be accomplished ''by perpetuating present patterns'' of pollution and depletion of natural resources.</p>
        <p>Several speakers agreed that scientific understanding and public awareness of dangers to the environment had reached the point that aggressive actions by governments were now practicable. But there was also agreement that the scientific basis for solving such problems was far from complete and that the institutions for carrying out such solutions were not yet available in most cases.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, said Thomas Lovejoy, vice president of the Smithsonian Institution, ''Massive intervention in society is required over a very short time span, perhaps less than 20 years.'' 'Stupid' to Ignore Dangers</p>
        <p>A main message of the forum, said Martin Holdgate, director of the International Union for the Conservation of Nature and former chief science adviser to the British Government, was that ''we would be incredibly stupid not to take these dangers as real.''</p>
        <p>Governments can take certain steps now, Dr. Holdgate said, even without complete scientific data about changes in the global environment. Such steps include ending wasteful practices like the destruction of rain forests, he said.</p>
        <p>William D. Ruckelshaus, chairman of Browning-Ferris Industries and former Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, warned that even though governments could take some ''modest actions now'' to deal with environmental threats, ''something enormous may be pushing against some immovable limits regarding combustion of fuels and ecosystem damage.''</p>
        <p>''Our usual tendency,'' he said, ''is to assume that if shortages or problems arise, we will discover a technological fix or set of fixes.''</p>
        <p>''Imagination is harmless,'' Mr. Ruckelshaus added. ''But counting on such a rescue may not be.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
