<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.P.A. Chief Says Bush Will Not Rush Into a Treaty on Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="249459"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REILLY, WILLIAM K (ADMR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7DA1231F930A25756C0A96F948260" item-length="923" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.P.A. Chief Says Bush Will Not Rush Into a Treaty on Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush is committed to beginning negotiations on a ''framework'' for a treaty on global warming but is not ready to endorse specific elements, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush is committed to beginning negotiations on a ''framework'' for a treaty on global warming but is not ready to endorse specific elements, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency said today.</p>
        <p>President Bush is committed to beginning negotiations on a ''framework'' for a treaty on global warming but is not ready to endorse specific elements, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency said today.</p>
        <p>The Administrator, William K. Reilly, said the United States would take the lead in seeking a ''carefully prepared'' treaty committing the international community to action on global warming by the end of next year.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Reilly emphasized that the Bush Administration does not now endorse specific solutions, like an agreement to reduce the use of fossil fuels, a major source of the problem.</p>
        <p>He said the Administration does not support ''dramatic'' unilateral action by the United States to reduce the sources of global warming. 'The Issue Has Ripened'</p>
        <p>At a news conference here Mr. Reilly denied that the President had changed course on supporting a global warming treaty in response to political pressures over the past week. The Administrator said Mr. Bush was moving at this time because ''the issue has ripened.''</p>
        <p>There is a growing scientific consensus that gases resulting from industrial and other human activity are trapping heat from the sun in a process similar to what happens in a greenhouse. This is expected to warm the earth's surface by 3 to 9 degrees Fahrenheit by the middle of the 21st century.</p>
        <p>Rising temperatures are expected to cause the level of the oceans to rise as a result of thermal expansion and melting glaciers, and to make significant changes in the global climate. While these changes cannot be pinpointed yet, they are expected to include drought at temperate latitudes and severe storms. A rapid warming is also expected to have a wide adverse effect on forests, crops, wildlife and human health.</p>
        <p>The Administration was sharply criticized this week when it was disclosed that the White House's Office of Management and Budget edited the Congressional testimony of a top Government scientist to soften his conclusions about the reliability of computer projections of the effects of global warming. Critics in Congress and the news media said the testimony had been changed to tailor the scientific findings to the Administration's go-slow approach to a treaty aimed at reducing the extent and mitigatring the effects of a global warming trend. 'Workshop' in U.S. Proposed</p>
        <p>On Thursday night, however, John H. Sununu, the White House chief of staff, sent new instructions to a United States delegation attending a meeting in Geneva of a group sponsored by the United Nations, the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, authorizing it to propose a ''workshop'' in this country in the fall to prepare analyses of the legal, scientific, economic and social issues that must be resolved before a treaty can be negotiated.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly emphasized that the needs of developing countries would be recognized in any global agreement and that contributions from these countries to the planning process would be solicited. Many countries in Latin America, Africa and Asia, he said, are concerned that the international community would move too fast in taking steps to curb global warming, steps that could interfere with the industrialization of the developing countries.</p>
        <p>Several members of Congress and environmental groups, while welcoming the President's commitment to a global warming treaty, said he had acted because of political pressure.</p>
        <p>Senator Albert Gore, a Tennessee Democrat who is one of the more vocal critics of the Administration's response to the global warming threat, said: ''Once again, the President has been dragged slowly and reluctantly toward the correct position when the White House should have been providing leadership. I welcome their decision finally to begin recognizing the importance of global climate change as an international issue demanding attention, but it's too early for rave reviews of a policy developed in an atmosphere of political damage control in response to Congressional pressure.''</p>
        <p>Senator John H. Chafee, a Republican from Rhode Island, said the White House action was ''good news,'' adding, ''The President's attention was finally focused on this issue and he came through in fine fashion.'' 'A Very Big Opportunity'</p>
        <p>Michael Oppenheimer, an atmospheric phsyicist for the Environmental Defense Fund, said: ''This is a very big opportunity for the United States to grab back the leadership in a new era of global cooperation on the environment. The rest of the world has moved ahead of the United States. But if the United States is to move ahead again it must do its homework and start by listening to its scientists instead of telling the scientists what to say.''</p>
        <p>Senator Tim Wirth, a Colorado Democrat, urged that Mr. Bush emulate Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher of Britain and other world leaders and become personally involved in ''this new and rapidly emerging area of diplomacy.'' He suggested that the President go to the National Center on Atmospheric Research in Boulder, Colo., to be personally briefed on the global warming threat by leading scientists there.</p>
        <p>Several commentators said the United States should start taking unilateral action to meet the threat of global warming and set an example for other countries.</p>
        <p>''The Administration needs to come up with an energy policy and a carbon dioxide policy,'' said Rafe Pomerance, a senior associate of the World Resources Institute, a Washington-based research and policy group. ''The planet is waiting for action by governments.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
