<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Big Oil Spill From Home Mechanics</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="50" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="295356"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="CONSUMER'S WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6DC1F38F93BA15753C1A96F948260" item-length="1142" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Big Oil Spill From Home Mechanics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Only the biggest oil spills get much attention, but the smallest ones add up. The amount of oil dumped by do-it-yourself auto mechanics every two and a half weeks is roughly equivalent to the amount spilled by the Exxon Valdez, experts say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Only the biggest oil spills get much attention, but the smallest ones add up. The amount of oil dumped by do-it-yourself auto mechanics every two and a half weeks is roughly equivalent to the amount spilled by the Exxon Valdez, experts say.</p>
        <p>Only the biggest oil spills get much attention, but the smallest ones add up. The amount of oil dumped by do-it-yourself auto mechanics every two and a half weeks is roughly equivalent to the amount spilled by the Exxon Valdez, experts say.</p>
        <p>The environmental damage from lubricating oil is not nearly as dramatic as the results of the Valdez accident, in which the tanker dumped 11 million gallons of crude oil off Alaska, but it is still damage. Used engine oil contains lead and other toxic materials and has caused cancer in laboratory animals.</p>
        <p>When the oil is dumped into sewers, it can reach lakes, streams and harbors and leave slicks, which interfere with photosynthesis and the water's oxygen level and can introduce oil into the food chain. If oil goes through a sewage treatment plant, it can disrupt bacteria that break down organic wastes, resulting in the release of improperly treated sewage. A quart of oil can foul the taste of a quarter-million gallons of drinking water.</p>
        <p>''It's the thousand cuts kind of thing, rather than bleeding from the jugular,'' said Dr. Roberta E. Weisbrod, special assistant to the commissioner of the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation.</p>
        <p>Statistics from the American Petroleum Institute, the industry's main trade association, tell their own story of the hazard of pollution: Each year, 1.2 billion gallons of lubricating oil are used in vehicles; 600 million gallons are burned up in engines, and 600 million are removed at oil-change time. Drivers who change their own oil account for 350 million of the removed gallons, and they improperly discard 240 million gallons of used oil.  Democratizing Pollution</p>
        <p>Pollution from motor oil is an example of the democratization of pollution, with the damage coming from individual consumers, not big industry. It joins harmful products like the chlorofluorocarbons from air-conditioners that deplete the earth's protective ozone layer, the lawn-care products that kill wildlife or pollute streams and the carbon dioxide from home heating systems and cars that adds to the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>But experts say the failure to recycle oil is more than a hazard to the environment; each quart dumped also represents a lost opportunity to reduce dependence on imported oil. The petroleum institute estimates the oil dumped could, if burned, meet the annual electricity needs of 360,000 houses. The institute says it takes 42 gallons of crude oil - but only a single gallon of used oil - to make 2.5 quarts of virgin lubricating oil.</p>
        <p>The principle is enshrined in Federal law. ''Used oil is a valuable source of increasingly scarce energy and materials,'' says the Resource Conservation and Recovery Act, the main Federal statute to control pollution of water in the ground.</p>
        <p>By law, corner gas stations and 10-minute oil-change shops must send used oil for re-refining into new lubricating oil, or for burning as fuel. And Federal and state inspectors check on them.</p>
        <p>But consumers, about two-thirds of whom change their own oil, generally do not read laws and may not even know they are doing something illegal. The institute estimates that 61 percent of do-it-yourself mechanics dump their used oil or put it in the garbage, to be taken to a landfill, where it will leak into the soil. The Environmental Protection Agency thinks the figure could be 90 percent.</p>
        <p>Whichever number is correct, it appears to be rising, even though some places offer curbside pickup.</p>
        <p>''I'm really disappointed at how little is picked up,'' said Peter H. Spendelow, a recycling specialist at the Department of Environmental Quality in Oregon. ''I don't know how many people realize that curbside pickup is available for oil.'' In Oregon, cities with populations of 4,000 or more and with garbage pickup must recycle oil.</p>
        <p>Birmingham, Ala., used to fit its garbage trucks with racks to carry oil containers left at the curb, but when the city ordered new garbage trucks a few years ago, it did not bother with new racks. ''We don't pick up that much any more,'' said Jerry Adcox, assistant director of the Street and Sanitation Department. In general, from observing speed limits to insulating homes, people are doing less to conserve energy.</p>
        <p>Just how much gets dumped improperly each year is uncertain. Although the petroleum institute put it at 240 million gallons in a study a year ago, other estimates run higher. Almost all experts say that of the amount drained by do-it-yourselfers, more than half is disposed of improperly. To Mr. Spendelow, one clue is the empty cans or bottles of new oil that motorists leave at the curb. If they did not take away those containers, he said, they probably did not take away the old oil either.</p>
        <p>In some places, however, consumers who want to recycle their oil may find it hard to do. Many service stations will not accept the oil unless state law requires them to. The stations fear that consumers will give them antifreeze or degreasing agents that they have poured into the same container as the oil. That would put hazardous waste into their collection containers.</p>
        <p>More station owners accepted oil when it was worth something, environmental officials say. They could sell the used oil for 30 cents a gallon when crude oil sold for $30 a barrel. When oil fell below $10 a barrel in 1986, some service stations had to pay to have their oil hauled away. Now it brings in a few cents a gallon, hardly an incentive to gather it.</p>
        <p>Much of the oil that consumers buy comes from discount stores and auto supply stores, but few of those places take used oil back.</p>
        <p>At the University of Alabama in Birmingham, Janet Graham, director of a program that coordinates recycling in 12 communities, said that in rural areas, people use oil to keep down road dust or spread it on animals to kill insects. Neither is a good idea. ''There are several uses,'' she said, ''none of them sound.''</p>
        <p>SAFE DISPOSAL IS NOT ALWAYS EASY</p>
        <p>Drivers who change their own motor oil should collect it in a plastic container with a top that fastens securely. Disposing of it safely will require some effort.</p>
        <p>They should check with their local service stations. Stations are required to recycle their oil, and in some states they must accept small quantities from people who change their own oil; in New York, for example, they must take up to five gallons, free. But in most places there is no such requirement, and stations can refuse to accept it.</p>
        <p>Many communities have regular pickups for toxic waste. Drivers can call their local sanitation departments to get their schedules. Even if toxic-waste pickups are made once a year, drivers can store used oil at home until then. If a gas station will not take it and there are no special pickups, consumers can call their state environmental protection departments for advice.</p>
        <p>CONSUMER'S WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
