<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Personal Health</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="237737"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALZHEIMER'S DISEASE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALUMINUM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRODY, JANE E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PERSONAL HEALTH (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">HEALTH PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Alzheimer's</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alzheimer's Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DA123EF935A35757C0A96F948260" item-length="1282" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Personal Health</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jane E. Brody</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRODY, JANE E</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As if there weren't enough dietary pitfalls these days, many people are worrying about the aluminum pots, pans and utensils in which foods are often prepared or stored. The concern arises because aluminum has been linked to Alzheimer's disease, the devastating brain disorder that is becoming increasingly common and costly as the population ages.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As if there weren't enough dietary pitfalls these days, many people are worrying about the aluminum pots, pans and utensils in which foods are often prepared or stored. The concern arises because aluminum has been linked to Alzheimer's disease, the devastating brain disorder that is becoming increasingly common and costly as the population ages.</p>
        <p>As if there weren't enough dietary pitfalls these days, many people are worrying about the aluminum pots, pans and utensils in which foods are often prepared or stored. The concern arises because aluminum has been linked to Alzheimer's disease, the devastating brain disorder that is becoming increasingly common and costly as the population ages.</p>
        <p>Canadian researchers first noted a possible association between aluminum and Alzheimer's over a decade ago in finding abnormally large deposits of aluminum in the sick brain cells of Alzheimer's patients.</p>
        <p>Aluminum, a light, versatile, inexpensive and ubiquitous metal, is known to be toxic to nerve cells. Many studies since the initial report have associated the metal with brain abnormalities peculiar to Alzheimer's.</p>
        <p>The question is no longer whether aluminum is there, but rather how and when it gets there and what role it may play in producing the severe memory disturbances and disorientation characteristic of Alzheimer's. While many theories have been put forth to explain aluminum's role in diseased brains, no one has yet been able to show that aluminum's presence is the cause, rather than the result, of the disorder.</p>
        <p>Although there is evidence on both sides, the preponderance of research to date indicates that aluminum is a contaminant of brains already sickened by something else. Of course, once aluminum gains entry into diseased brain cells, it could add significantly to the damage. If this view is correct, limiting dietary exposure to aluminum would not prevent Alzheimer's disease, but it might slow its downhill course.</p>
        <p>Before discarding aluminum utensils, consider these facts and findings.  Aluminum Is Everywhere</p>
        <p>Cooking utensils, along with aluminum foil and trays and soft-drink cans, are hardly our main sources of exposure to aluminum. Actually, very little aluminum leaches out when food is cooked in aluminum utensils, and virtually none should leach from pots coated with a nonstick surface (which is recommended anyway to reduce dietary fat).</p>
        <p>Aluminum is the most abundant metal on earth. It is in soil, air and drinking water. The amount in water varies from region to region. Sometimes municipal water treatment increases the amount that reaches the tap, since an aluminum compound is commonly used in the process of removing solid particles and plant debris before chlorination. In the Northeast, acid rain is said to be adding aluminum to water by leaching the mineral from soil.</p>
        <p>Aluminum is in foods made with baking powder, like cakes and muffins, pancake and cake mixes, frozen dough and self-rising flour. It also is found in some processed cheeses, pickles and nondairy creamers.</p>
        <p>In addition, aluminum is the active ingredient in most antiperspirants and is found in many over-the-counter medicines, including a number of antacids, buffered aspirin products, antidiarrheal remedies, douches and hemorrhoid medications.</p>
        <p>Given the broad exposure to aluminum, if it was the primary cause of Alzheimer's disease, virtually all Americans should eventually get it. The fact that only 10 to 15 percent of the elderly develop the disorder suggests something else is the main trigger, said Dr. Leopold Liss, a neuropathologist at Ohio State University.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, if aluminum was the culprit in Alzheimer's disease, workers who are chronically exposed to the metal should be more prone to the disease. Thus far, however, there is no evidence of an increased risk among such workers.  Aluminum in the Body</p>
        <p>Despite the rather large intake of aluminum, very little is absorbed through the digestive tract. Most is in a form that cannot pass through the intestines, and since aluminum has no known biological function, the body has no mechanism for encouraging its entry.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, Dr. Liss noted that the normal brain, both in laboratory animals and in people, keeps aluminum out regardless of how much enters the body. He suggests that aluminum can get to the brain only when a disease or defect somehow destroys this protective barrier.</p>
        <p>''In any nerve cells that degenerate, the aluminum content increases tenfold,'' Dr. Liss said. For example, he said, in alcoholics whose brains become damaged by drink, aluminum can enter and cause harm. And in people born with the genetic abnormality Down's syndrome, which results in mental retardation, Alzheimer's disease tends to develop at a young age. Studies showed that the brain cells of people with Down's syndrome first degenerate and then take up aluminum, but there is no uptake before they develop Alzheimer's.</p>
        <p>But studies directed by Dr. Daniel P. Perl, a neuropathologist at the Mount Sinai Medical Center in New York, strongly indicate that when aluminum is inhaled, it can bypass the protective barrier and directly enter the brain from the nasal passages. In animal studies, he showed that inhaled aluminum accumulates in areas of the brain cortex near the olfactory bulb, the very areas that become diseased in Alzheimer's patients.</p>
        <p>Dr. Liss has noted in autopsies of Alzheimer's patients that the olfactory bulb and tracts contain more aluminum than any other area of the brain. He suggested that this may account for the lost or distorted sense of smell common in Alzheimer's.</p>
        <p>Thus far, the brain lesions found in animals that inhale large amounts of aluminum are not the same as those in Alzheimer's patients.</p>
        <p>Two lesions are considered hallmarks of the disease: neurofibrillary tangles, which resemble spaghetti strands within brain cells, and senile plaques, which consist of cells and cell extensions around a protein core. While both these lesions are found to some extent in normal aging brains, they are highly concentrated in the damaged parts of the brains of Alzheimer's patients. It is within these lesions that aluminum has been found in inordinate amounts.</p>
        <p>It is also known that very high levels of aluminum in the blood can damage the brain. Aluminum was shown to cause ''dialysis dementia,'' a reversible brain disorder that afflicted patients on chronic kidney dialysis in areas where the water supply contained high levels of aluminum. Here again, though, the aluminum-induced brain lesions and the resulting symptoms were different from those seen in Alzheimer's patients.  An Interim Course</p>
        <p>Most Alzheimer's researchers see no reason to become unduly concerned about environmental sources of aluminum.</p>
        <p>''If your brain is healthy,'' Dr. Liss said, ''you can swallow 25 aluminum-containing antacid tablets a day and never develop Alzheimer's disease. The normal brain is protected against aluminum. We kept rabbits on a high-aluminum diet for up to three years and they developed high levels of aluminum in all their body tissues except the brain.''</p>
        <p>But he added, ''If you have already begun to develop the disease, aluminum, which is always present, could enter the brain and cause damage.''</p>
        <p>Accordingly, Dr. Liss and his colleagues are now trying to slow the course of Alzheimer's in patients by giving them a substance that prevents absorption of aluminum through the digestive tract. He plans to treat 15 to 20 patients over three to five years, but he declined to identify the treatment lest it be used indiscriminantly and dangerously before proper tests are completed.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Dr. Liss said, a decision to throw away aluminum pots and pans would be like refusing to give milk to any infants because some babies are genetically unable to handle milk. If you wish to minimize the leaching of aluminum from cooking utensils, avoid using them to prepare acidic foods (like tomatoes and fruit), especially if they will cook for hours, and avoid storing such foods in aluminum.</p>
        <p>HEALTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
