<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Dry' Beers Flood Market: A Wave or a Mirage?</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19890821T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="275711"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RATINGS AND RATING SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DE1E39F935A2575BC0A96F948260" item-length="1501" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Dry' Beers Flood Market: A Wave or a Mirage?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ON television, in magazines and on the sides of city buses, the advertisements trumpet ''dry'' beer. Dry beer was first produced in Japan in 1987, and then American, Canadian and European brewers got into the act. At least 19 imported and domestic dry beers have been introduced in the United States in the last year or so, many just in time for the summer surge in beer drinking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ON television, in magazines and on the sides of city buses, the advertisements trumpet ''dry'' beer. Dry beer was first produced in Japan in 1987, and then American, Canadian and European brewers got into the act. At least 19 imported and domestic dry beers have been introduced in the United States in the last year or so, many just in time for the summer surge in beer drinking.</p>
        <p>ON television, in magazines and on the sides of city buses, the advertisements trumpet ''dry'' beer. Dry beer was first produced in Japan in 1987, and then American, Canadian and European brewers got into the act. At least 19 imported and domestic dry beers have been introduced in the United States in the last year or so, many just in time for the summer surge in beer drinking. Yet consumers are still asking, ''What is dry beer?''</p>
        <p>The brewers themselves do not always agree on the answer. All dry beers are less sweet than their regular counterparts, but other characteristics vary from brand to brand. In Japan they generally have more alcohol than ordinary beers, but that is not true of all American-made dry beers. American and Japanese brewers say dry beers have little aftertaste and higher carbonation, but this does not apply to European-made dry beers.</p>
        <p>In fact, dry beer is as much a product of market research as of the brewery, industry analysts and brewers say. It appears to be an elastic concept that the beer industry is stretching over a batch of stylish selling points, suggesting a product that is clean, lively, refreshing, less sweet and has no aftertaste.</p>
        <p>''We went to consumers and asked them to describe what they thought dry beer would be,'' said Bob Goughenour, brand director for Michelob beers for Anheuser-Busch. ''Everyone can describe a dry wine, a dry martini, but what was dry beer? They told us they wanted the taste of beer - the refreshment - but no aftertaste.'' Acting on this research, Anheuser-Busch introduced Michelob Dry last year. The Pabst Brewing Company of Milwaukee formulated Olympia Dry Beer and then Pabst Blue Ribbon Dry in much the same way.</p>
        <p>In a tasting of the 19 dry beers sold in this country, four food and beverage writers for The New York Times found that most had little or no aroma or aftertaste and were highly carbonated. Although some of them were thought to be well made and some were described as refreshing, few were considered distinctive.</p>
        <p>''Dry'' is not a new description for beer. Decades ago, as New York baseball fans might recall, there was Rheingold, ''the dry beer.'' One of the new dry beers, Esquire Extra Dry from the Jones Brewing Company in Smithton, Pa., near Pittsburgh, bears a name the company used in the 50's and 60's, and revived last year. But now brewers are using the term to refer to beer made with different strains of yeasts than they use for regular beer and that is fermented longer than usual.</p>
        <p>The first of the new dry beers was Asahi Super Dry, introduced in Japan in March 1987. The Asahi beer was developed as a result of consumer research and soon captured 20 percent of the Japanese market. Three other Japanese breweries, Kirin Brewery, Sapporo Breweries and Suntory International, followed suit, and now dry beers account for 40 percent of the Japanese market. The trend spread quickly to the United States. Although dry beer accounts for only about 1 percent ot the $38.7 billion American beer market, 10 of the 30 new domestic brands introduced in the first half of 1989 were dry. Some dry beers are available nationally, some regionally and some only in test markets. Canada and Australia are the only other countries where dry beers appear to have made any impact, though on a smaller scale than in Japan and the United States.</p>
        <p>Americans seem interested in dry beer, but it remains to be seen if they will be won over. ''When it first came out everyone wanted to try it,'' said Mike Haas, beverage manager for the Waterfront, a restaurant in Covington, Ky. ''Now it has leveled off to nice steady sales.''</p>
        <p>James Riggi, general manager of Roeblings Restaurant in South Street Seaport in Manhattan, was less enthusiastic. ''I'm stocking it because of the huge advertising,'' he said, ''but it hasn't done what I expected.''</p>
        <p>''It's too early to tell whether this is just a fad or will have the significant impact of light beer,'' said Robert Weinberg, president of R. S. Weinberg &amp; Associates, a St. Louis company that analyzes the beer industry. Light beers were introduced in 1974 and hold 26 percent of the market.</p>
        <p>''I do find it startling that a company like Anheuser-Busch went national last year with Michelob Dry with relatively little testing, and then moved as fast as they did with Bud Dry,'' Mr. Weinberg added. Anheuser-Busch, the world's largest brewer, controls more than 40 percent of the American beer market.</p>
        <p>Many brewing companies are hoping dry beer will spur growth in an industry that declined in the early 1980's and has had essentially flat sales since. They hope this style of beer will attract new beer drinkers instead of those who already drink regular or light beers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weinberg, who also teaches at the John M. Owen School of Business at Washington University, said he noticed that many of the young women in his classes prefer dry beers. ''They said they normally did not like to drink beer because they felt they smelled like a brewery afterward, but that does not happen with dry beer.''</p>
        <p>The European dry beers, Grolsch Premium Dry, brewed in the Netherlands by Grolsch Breweries, and Holsten Dry, brewed in West Germany by the Holsten Brewery, represent a somewhat different approach to making dry beers. Their dryness comes not only from longer fermentation but also from more hops. They have some aftertaste, but it is refreshingly bitter, and they tend to have more body than most of the others.</p>
        <p>''There are two ways of achieving dryness in a beer,'' said Michael Jackson, author of ''The New World Guide to Beer'' (Running Press, 1989, $29.95). ''Either you add hops, which increases the bitterness, or you remove something. With many of these new beers, they seem to make a virtue of having a very weak finish, or aftertaste, and I have trouble relating to that concept. There are plenty of traditional European beers, such as the pilseners, as well as American beers like Anchor Steam Liberty Ale, which could be called dry.''</p>
        <p>''Dry is a classic style of stout that goes back 200 years,'' said Charles Finkel, president of Merchant du Vin in Seattle, which imports two dozen specialty beers. His company is planning to import Dry Scot, made by the Caledonian Brewery in Scotland.</p>
        <p>Gaby Podlucky, president of the Jones Brewing Company, which introduced Esquire Extra Dry last year in the Pittsburgh area, said, ''By the way we make all our beers, you could consider them dry.'' But he said Esquire is fermented even longer than the company's other beers.</p>
        <p>Holsten Dry is the same beer that Holsten has produced for decades in Europe as Holsten Diat Pils; it has been given a new label for the American market, said David Dassler, regional sales manager for Holsten Import Corporation. It has always gone through a longer fermentation than conventional beers, removing more of the sugar, and has a higher alcohol content than regular Holsten, 5.8 percent compared with 5.2 percent by volume.</p>
        <p>In the manufacture of alcoholic beverages, the addition of yeast makes the sugar in a fruit or grain mixture ferment, converting it to alcohol and carbon dioxide. The longer the fermentation, the more sugar is converted to alcohol.</p>
        <p>Not all dry beers are higher in alcohol, and where there is a difference, the dry variety has less than one-half of 1 percentage point more alcohol by volume. Asahi Super Dry, for example, has a 5 percent alcohol content, while Asahi regular beer has 4.5 percent.</p>
        <p>American dry beers like Michelob Dry and Heileman's Old Style Special Dry have an alcohol content of around 5 percent. Sumiko S. Patrone, assistant marketing manager for Sapporo U.S.A., said American companies that have not raised the alcohol content in their products have altered the original concept of dry beer. Hugh Nelson, the marketing director for Colt 45 Dry, agreed, saying his beer is closer to the Japanese model precisely because it has a higher alcohol content than regular Colt 45 Malt Liquor (5.88 percent, as against 5.61 percent by volume).</p>
        <p>But Mary McHugh, a spokeswoman for Bud Dry, which has the same alcohol content as regular Budweiser, said the amount of alcohol was not important. ''Our beer has been created for the taste, not for more alcohol,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Many of the dry beers have slightly fewer calories than regular beers, but marketers are not emphasizing this for fear of encroaching on the light beer market. ''I see the dry beers as running in the light area,'' said Mr. Goughenour of Michelob. ''It's another viable alternative; it's in line with what the consumer wants, so there's room for growth.''</p>
        <p>The introduction of Michelob Dry and Bud Dry is seen by some market analysts as Anheuser-Busch's attempt to have an impact on the dry market before the rival Miller Brewing Company decides whether to produce its own. Jim Gollhofer, president of Grolsch Imports, said it also meant the category shows good potential. ''If a company that size is willing to make the move it has to be a significant product.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 21, 1989, Monday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>An article in The Living Section on Wednesday about dry beer misidentified the business school at Washington University in St. Louis. It is the John M. Olin School of Business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 21, 1989, Monday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>An article in The Living Section on Wednesday about dry beer misidentified the business school at Washington University in St. Louis. It is the John M. Olin School of Business.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
