<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Balancing Need and Risk in Pursuit of Oil</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="238048"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXXON VALDEZ (TANKER)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHIPS AND SHIPPING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALASKA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">VALDEZ (ALASKA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tankers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEED71438F934A35757C0A96F948260" item-length="778" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Balancing Need and Risk in Pursuit of Oil</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The ruinous tanker spill in Alaska demonstrates the perils created by efforts to wrest the nation's last supplies of undrilled oil from beneath the land and the sea.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The ruinous tanker spill in Alaska demonstrates the perils created by efforts to wrest the nation's last supplies of undrilled oil from beneath the land and the sea.</p>
        <p>The ruinous tanker spill in Alaska demonstrates the perils created by efforts to wrest the nation's last supplies of undrilled oil from beneath the land and the sea.</p>
        <p>As reserves of oil dwindle, the petroleum industry is engaged in a frantic and expensive search for new sources in ever more inaccessible and environmentally sensitive areas like the North Slope of Alaska and the outer continental shelf.</p>
        <p>The fate of the Exxon Valdez, carrying North Slope oil pumped the length of Alaska by pipeline, is only the latest demonstration that wringing the last drops of the nation's oil can exact a high environmental and economic price. Consequences Minimized</p>
        <p>Industry officials say that the United States and its economy run on oil and that the nation has no alternative to finding and producing more of it. One Exxon executive in Valdez, answering hostile questions about the spill, said that as long as people wanted to continue to drive their automobiles, oil would have to be brought to market.</p>
        <p>Government officials have tended to minimize the environmental consequences of further reliance on oil and have warned that the nation's economy and security are already dangerously dependent on unstable Middle Eastern sources and other foreign producers, which account for more than one-third of the oil consumed in this country.</p>
        <p>Therefore, they argue, the country must drill in such places as the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge and in valuable marine environments off California, Florida, the mid-Atlantic states and New England.</p>
        <p>President Bush said last Friday that despite the environmental havoc caused by the Exxon Valdez spill, he intended to continue to press Congress to open the Arctic refuge to drilling because ''we are becoming increasingly dependent on foreign oil.''</p>
        <p>''That is not acceptable to any President who is responsible for the national security of this country,'' he said. Finite and Dwindling Supplies</p>
        <p>But untapped pools of domestic oil are finite and dwindling. William Stevens, the president of Exxon U.S.A., said in an interview that the nation's known reserves would last nine years at the current rate of production. He quickly added that more reserves would undoubtedly be found and that Americans would be using oil for many years to come, but he also said that by the year 2020 there would not be enough domestic oil left ''to keep me interested.''</p>
        <p>By the mid-1990's, if current energy trends continue, the United States will be importing more than half its fuel, and shortly after the turn of the century the country will be almost entirely dependent on foreign producers, no matter how frantically the domestic industry scrambles for new reserves and no matter how high the price of oil goes.</p>
        <p>Moreover, there is a rapidly building scientific consensus that carbon dioxide released into the air by the combustion of oil and other fossil fuels is the single greatest source of a possible global warming caused when solar heat is trapped by industrial gases released into the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The combustion of petroleum, particularly in motor vehicles, is a major contributor to other forms of air pollution, including urban smog.</p>
        <p>To environmentalists, as well as to a growing number of scientists and lawmakers, these facts add up to an inescapable conclusion: the nation must begin now to wean itself from its slavish dependence on oil.</p>
        <p>The most immediate and practical alternative, they say, is a more efficient use of the oil now available. Several estimates have suggested that raising the gasoline mileage of private automobiles to 40 miles a gallon from the present level of about 27 miles a gallon could save within two years the equivalent of the estimated reserves beneath the Arctic refuge: 3.2 billion barrels. Kicking the Habit</p>
        <p>To get off the oil habit the nation will also have to develop fuels like ethanol, methanol and hydrogen and the technology to use them commercially.</p>
        <p>During the eight years of the Reagan Administration, Federal energy policy moved largely backward with respect to easing the nation's dependence on oil. Despite decrying the dependence on imported energy, the Reagan Administration rolled back fuel-effiency standards for automobiles, encouraged increased highway speeds and slashed research on alternative fuels and energy sources like solar power.</p>
        <p>So far, the Bush Administration has given little indication that its energy plans will go significantly further. And regardless of the course chosen by this or future Administrations, the curtain is likely to fall on the age of petroleum during the lifetime of children already born, whether or not the nation is ready.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
