<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="232647"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D61230F93BA25750C0A96F948260" item-length="1006" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International 2-5  Airplane bomb investigators believe they have recovered shards of the suitcase that contained the plastic explosive that destroyed a Pan Am jumbo jet over Scotland, two U.S. officials said.  Page 1  Bomb victim relatives urge tighter security 5</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International 2-5  Airplane bomb investigators believe they have recovered shards of the suitcase that contained the plastic explosive that destroyed a Pan Am jumbo jet over Scotland, two U.S. officials said.  Page 1  Bomb victim relatives urge tighter security 5</p>
        <p>International 2-5  Airplane bomb investigators believe they have recovered shards of the suitcase that contained the plastic explosive that destroyed a Pan Am jumbo jet over Scotland, two U.S. officials said.  Page 1  Bomb victim relatives urge tighter security 5  A missile caused an Italian jet crash, experts say 4  Poll workers in El Salvador resigned in 11 eastern towns, bowing to a heightened campaign by leftist rebels to disrupt presidential elections, provincial officials said. 1  The Sandinistas gave 1,894 pardons to former members of the Nicaraguan National Guard, following the regional accord signed last month by granting unrestricted freedom to all but 39 of the former guardsmen. 3  A 900-year-old tower collapsed in a downtown square of the northern Italian city of Pavia, killing 2 people and injuring 15.  5  Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi of India said a judicial report on the assassination of his mother, which had beensuppressed on the grounds of national security, would be released to Parliament in 10 days. 3  A car bomb in Beirut killed 12 people and wounded 120 when it went off during the morning rush hour, the police said. The blast devastated a Chritian area. 3  A 150-bed hospital in Kabul that the Red Cross opened last October constitutes a small beginning on what Western experts expect will ultimately be necessary to treat the Afghan war's medical legacy. 4  Prince Norodom Ranariddh said President Bush promised ''full support'' for the Cambodian opposition. But he acknowledged that his arms request had not received ''a clear and positive response.''  2  National 6-8, 28, 50  The worst two-month inflation in nearly eight years has been reflected in the Producer Price Index, which soared by 1 percent in both January and February, stunning stock and bond markets. 1  Stocks plunge across board; Dow down 48.57 points 33  New restrictions on Californians' life have been approved to reduce air pollution. The plan wouldeventually require electric powered cars and an end to free parking. 1  The U.S. Civil Rights Commission has been thrown into disarray by the arrest of its chairman at gunpoint last month on an Indian reservation in Arizona. 1  Chilean fruit will be allowed back in the American market, but grapes and other fruit already shipped to food stores and wholesalers will be destroyed, the F.D.A. said. 1  The Senate confirmed Dick Cheney as Defense Secretary in a 92-to-0 vote. He was sworn in a short time later in his office and went immediately to the Pentagon to take charge. 7  Senate Democrats issued an agenda of policy proposals, saying that Congress is a co-equal branch of Government and will not simply let the President take the initiative. 28  Senate fails to extend AIDS drug program 6  Drive in House on acid rain 8  Efforts for a drug-free workplace must be shown by companies that enter into Federal Government contracts of at least $25,000, starting today. But requirements are vague. 7  In his first week combatting drugs, William Bennett, announced a ban on importing semi-automatic rifles, targeted Washington for anti-drug efforts, in spite of a promise not to make a big splash. 7  President Bush's view on gun control has changed and he is actively seeking ''an accommodation'' between the police and sporting interests, he said. 7  Puppies expected in the White House 6  An inquiry into Ford and G.M cars has been opened to examine the potential danger of the cars rolling over. It follows an accident study that faulted the Ford Bronco II but cleared the Suzuki Samurai. 6  The Discovery astronauts got ready to end their five-day voyage, finishing up experiments aboard the space shuttle. Landing is set for 9:35 A.M. eastern time Saturday. 50  A servicewoman with a 6-month-old daughter has sued for a discharge from the Army, so that she will not be sent to South Korea, separating her from her child. 6  A fight against false Cajun food is being waged by Louisiana, because of what the state sees as a proliferation of ''copy-cat Cajun'' that is hurting the repute of state products. 6  I.B.M. said its profit would not meet analysts' expectations for the first quarter, undercutting the widespread belief that its 1989 earnings would be strong. 33  Apple Computer's suit gaining on Microsoft 35  Regional 29-31  A family was terrorized just after arriving in Manhattan from North Carolina when a gunman, who critically wounded his wife, abducted them. 1  An extra $193 million for nurses' pay was announced by Governor Cuomo in a step toward relieving the state's hospital crisis. A hospital ''summit meeting'' is also planned. 29  The St. Patrick's Day parade moved up Fifth Avenue with Edward Koch exultant amid only a smattering of boos and determined to march in a 13th parade next year. 29  The drought that has struck lower New York State might now look no more foreboding than previous ones, but there is a difference: the snow did not come this winter. 29  Ethics hearings ended with a whimper as the New York legislative leaders appeared to defend campaign fund-raising practices. 29  Students at Sarah Lawrence College, protesting school policies on racial issues, ended their occupation of an administration building after a commitment by the school to increase minority faculty hiring. 30  The top-rated female chess player in the world will join about 40 grandmasters for the New York International tournament. She is Judith Polgar, one of three chess-playing sisters from Hungary. 30  Eight ballerinas learn to dance without sight and without fear 31</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
