<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="310801"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DC133AF933A15751C1A96F948260" item-length="573" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  The Economy</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  The Economy</p>
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>The Consumer Price Index rose 0.4 percent in November, as food and shelter grew more costly while energy prices edged down, in an increase that was higher than expected.  [ Page D1. ]  Housing starts dropped by 4.7 percent last month.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>The unusual design of a destructive computer program may have undermined an elaborate extortion attempt.  [ D8. ] International</p>
        <p>President Bush waived a Congressional ban on loans to companies that do business with China.  [ A1. ]  Commerce Secretary Mosbacher said a deal to help lay a fiber-optic communications cable across the Soviet Union could proceed, provided the latest technology is not used.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>The European Community and six Western European nations agreed, as expected, to intensify negotiations about setting up a common economic space with minimal trade barriers.  [ D16. ]</p>
        <p>Bowing to public pressure, the Canadian Government will lower the rate on its proposed value-added tax to 7 percent.  [ A6. ] Companies</p>
        <p>Kohlberg, Kravis, Roberts is prepared to seek Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection for Hillsborough Holdings, the company it formed to acquire Jim Walter last year for $2.4 billion.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>American Airlines agreed to acquire Eastern's Central and South American routes.  [ D5. ]</p>
        <p>Bankers Trust said fourth-quarter earnings would be cut by $90 million after taxes, because of losses on two large loans.  [ D2. ]  Bank problems with real estate loans are growing, the Comptroller of the Currency said.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>TLC Beatrice abandoned a plan to sell a 35 percent stake to the public, citing what it called unfavorable market conditions.  [ D5. ]</p>
        <p>A.T.&amp; T. will reduce rates by 1.3 to 2 percent on interstate and international long-distance services.  [ D5. ]</p>
        <p>Xerox's $150 million copyright suit against Apple is an important skirmish in a battle to determine whether desktop computers should have a standard ''dashboard.'' News Analysis.  [ D7. ]</p>
        <p>I.B.M. introduced a personal computer based on Intel's powerful i486 micoprocessor.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>Reader's Digest is going public, in a move that will give its shareholders greater liquidity.  [ D19. ] Markets</p>
        <p>Stock prices declined broadly, and the Dow Jones industrial average lost 1.92 points, to close at 2,695.61.  [ D10. ]</p>
        <p>Prices of Treasury securities were narrowly mixed in light trading.  [ D16. ]  Yields were mostly mixed on C.D.'s and money market accounts for the week ended yesterday.  [ D22. ]</p>
        <p>The contract for January delivery of crude oil expired in volatile trading. Prices set contract highs before closing with a sharp decline.  [ D17. ]  The dollar finished slightly higher.  [ D17. ] Technology</p>
        <p>The race to develop stronger, lighter materials that will make aircraft more sturdy and more fuel-efficient is intensifying.  [ D6. ]</p>
        <p>A platform for the North Sea will be built to take account of higher waters that might result from the greenhouse effect.  [ D6. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>Times have changed at The New Yorker, which has lent its name to a luxury-car road rally and mailed advertising promotions to readers. Randall Rothenberg: Advertising.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Evidence that the house may not be worth what it cost may lead to a pullback by investors. Floyd Norris: Market Place.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Should anyone care if a company's stockholders are Japanese rather than American? Peter Passell: Economic Scene.  [ D2. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
