<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Vermont, a Proposal to Ban Disposable Diapers</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="313375"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DIAPERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VERMONT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KUNIN, MADELEINE M (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Babies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891231T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DC1F3DF932A05751C1A96F948260" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Vermont, a Proposal to Ban Disposable Diapers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>HINESBURG, Vt., Dec. 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Dotty Schnure, a mother who has a job away from home, always used disposable diapers on her two young daughters. She estimates that she used 90 small diapers a week per child when they were infants, 60 medium-size diapers a week per child for the next three months, and 30 large diapers for the next two years - roughly 4,920 diapers per child.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Dotty Schnure, a mother who has a job away from home, always used disposable diapers on her two young daughters. She estimates that she used 90 small diapers a week per child when they were infants, 60 medium-size diapers a week per child for the next three months, and 30 large diapers for the next two years - roughly 4,920 diapers per child.</p>
        <p>Dotty Schnure, a mother who has a job away from home, always used disposable diapers on her two young daughters. She estimates that she used 90 small diapers a week per child when they were infants, 60 medium-size diapers a week per child for the next three months, and 30 large diapers for the next two years - roughly 4,920 diapers per child.</p>
        <p>Ms. Schnure knows that she is contributing to an enormous environmental problem: 18 billion disposable diapers are dumped into American landfills each year, accounting for 2 percent of the nation's trash by weight, according to the Washington-based Environmental Action Foundation.</p>
        <p>But she disagrees with a proposal by Gov. Madeleine M. Kunin to ban disposable diapers in Vermont as part of a general recycling effort. The ban would become effective some time in 1993. Loss of a Necessity Seen</p>
        <p>''It's a tough thing,'' said Ms. Schnure, who lives in this western Vermont town and commutes to her job in South Burlington, 13 miles away; she is a public relations representative of an electric power utility. ''I take the trash problem seriously and I know that diapers are a major issue in landfills. But I would say disposable diapers are pretty close to a necessity.''</p>
        <p>The Governor's proposal follows a move by the Legislature last spring, banning the use of chlorofluorocarbons, a component of the refrigerant freon in automobile air-conditioners. That law takes effect in January 1993.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Kunin let the other shoe drop this month by making her proposal. Besides the ban on selling disposable diapers, it calls for mandatory recycling, would extend the bottle-deposit law to cover all non-dairy containers, and would force newspapers to use newsprint containing 20 percent recycled fibers. Nebraska has already banned non-biodegradable diapers. First Steps, Governor Says</p>
        <p>The Governor says prohibiting both disposable diapers and chlorofluorocarbons, which are known to erode the atmosphere's ozone layer, are essential first steps to a cleaner environment.</p>
        <p>''You can't have business as usual,'' said Governor Kunin. ''There can't be an entirely painless transition from this throw-away society to a conservation-minded society. I believe that as people start to understand the impact of their behavior, they will be willing to make adjustments.''</p>
        <p>She and other environmental leaders insist that industry will find a way to ''accelerate its schedule'' of developing new products in response to the market pressure that would result from regulation like banning disposable diapers. Making It Happen Via Bans</p>
        <p>''The only way to make it happen is through bans on products,'' said Lewis Milford, a Vermont-based staff attorney for the Conservation Law Foundation. ''Because industry has not kept up with the need for greater environmental protection, the only alternative is to force the market to change. You have to have a mix of carrots and sticks. You can't simply wait for consumers to stop buying.''</p>
        <p>Ray Desrochers, sales manager for a Burlington automobile dealership outside Burlington, said that while ''General Motors is striving to remedy the problem, I don't know of any good alternatives to freon that are on the market yet.'' He added: ''But they're coming, maybe a couple of years down the road. They have to, because this thing is going nationwide.''</p>
        <p>Giving up air-conditioning in Vermont, where it is usually hot for no more than a month, is one thing. Giving up throw-away diapers is another. There is some evidence of late that biodegradable diapers do not degrade as expected in a landfill.</p>
        <p>And the day-care center Ms. Schnure's children attend does not allow cloth diapers, which may help spread disease - a possibility that bothers Ms. Schnure. Sharing the Responsibility</p>
        <p>''If I were home and not working, it would be no problem,'' said Ms. Schnure, ''but I think the health thing is a serious issue. If the day-care could figure out a way to handle it, I would go along.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Milford, the conservation group's lawyer, said consumers like Ms. Schnure should not feel responsible alone for solving the nation's environmental problems.</p>
        <p>''Yes, people should use less, but you're not going to have successful programs that depend on significant deprivation,'' he argued. ''I'm a strong proponent of regulation to change institutional-industrial behavior. There must be a shared sense of responsibility for this problem.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
