<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Italy Embarks on Bold Effort To Save Fabled City of Venice From Threatening Tides</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="218970"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOODS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VENICE (ITALY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ADRIATIC SEA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HABERMAN, CLYDE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Venice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DA1E3AF932A05752C0A96F948260" item-length="2086" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Italy Embarks on Bold Effort To Save Fabled City of Venice From Threatening Tides</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HABERMAN, CLYDE</byline>
      <dateline>VENICE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IN the Bible, Moses parted the waters. In Venice, Moses intends to stop them cold.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IN the Bible, Moses parted the waters. In Venice, Moses intends to stop them cold.</p>
        <p>IN the Bible, Moses parted the waters. In Venice, Moses intends to stop them cold.</p>
        <p>Moses is the name of an experimental project designed to hold back the tides that for centuries have buffeted this jewel by the Adriatic Sea and now submerge its low-lying sections dozens of times a year.</p>
        <p>Since early November engineers have been testing a prototype sea gate that would be used to help seal off the entire Venice Lagoon from the Adriatic when its tides reach threatening levels.</p>
        <p>The idea is to build flexible walls at the three narrow openings in a land strip that separates the lagoon from the sea. The walls would consist of a series of about 80 flap gates that could be raised or dropped at will. Elevated, they would serve as barriers when waves run uncommonly high. Lowered, they would lie below the water, out of the way, so as not to interfere with sea traffic or with the normal, and critical, tidal flushing of the polluted lagoon.</p>
        <p>Engineers say the first gate, the so-called Moses prototype, has worked well in its tests. Their experiments are to end by mid-year and give way to a new phase of testing. If no problems develop, officials then expect to begin full production and installation of all the gates, a process likely to take until 1997.</p>
        <p>The effort to protect the 2-square-mile speck in the 212-square-mile lagoon is arguably Venice's most important public works project in centuries. The total cost is estimated at $5 billion, all of to come from the Italian Government. The money would be channeled through 26 private engineering, design and construction companies that banded together four years ago under the banner of the New Venice Consortium.</p>
        <p>While Moses is the most eye-catching project, much of the consortium's efforts are devoted to more mundane tasks like reinforcing sea walls, dredging canals and strengthening semi-submerged shoals in the lagoon to alleviate chronic silting problems. Holding back the sea is important, says the consortium chairman, Luigi Zanda, but improving the lagoon's ecology is critical, he adds.</p>
        <p>''Only by saving the lagoon is it possible to save Venice,'' said another official, Mauro Fabris.</p>
        <p>Venice has long been the Mark Twain of cities. Its obituary has been written many times, but always the reports have been exaggerated. In fact, one age-old question - when will Venice sink? - is no longer pertinent. Land subsidence essentially stopped in the mid-1970's when the area exhausted the underlying aquifer from which it had drawn water, primarily for industry. Some sinking continues, but not enough to be worrisome, engineers say.</p>
        <p>But that hardly means Venice is safe. A key problem is that over the last century, the Adriatic, along with the rest of the world's seas, is believed to have risen a few inches as glaciers left over from the last ice age slowly melted. Scientists predict further rises in sea level as a global warming associated with the greenhouse effect causes glaciers to melt and oceans to swell.</p>
        <p>In Venice, tides measured at the Piazza San Marco run an average of nine inches higher than in 1900, although much of the difference was caused by the city's sinking. Consortium engineers expect the tidal level to rise 24 inches over the next century, mostly because of the predicted rise in sea level.</p>
        <p>Acqua alta, or high water, is such an ever-present threat that hotels have hip boots ready for guests, just in case. Normally, February is a prime month for flooding, leaving the ground floors of many buildings dank and wet and forcing residents to negotiate temporary raised boardwalks over puddles and ponds. Tracking the Floods</p>
        <p>At their offices inside a remodeled palace, consortium officials use computer graphics to demonstrate acqua alta's devastating effects. Virtually every other day - an average of 150 times a year - tides run to a height of 70 centimeters, or 28 inches, as measured on a gauge at Punta della Salute, near the majestic Piazza San Marco. That is enough to send water trickling from the canals and the lagoon, across the smaller plaza beside the Doge's Palace, into the 11th-century San Marco basilica, the lowest point in the city center.</p>
        <p>At 80 centimeters, or 31.5 inches, the main square itself and other low-lying areas are awash. This occurs about 40 times a year. At 110 centimeters, or 43 inches, flooding is extensive across the city. Trouble of this magnitude used to be uncommon. From 1931 to 1945, according to the consortium, tides of 110 centimeters or more struck Venice only 8 times. But from 1971 to 1985, it happened 49 times.</p>
        <p>The granddaddy of floods, and the one that made Italy recognize the severity of the problem, came on Nov. 4, 1966. That day, an Adriatic storm lifted tides to a level of 1.94 meters -more than 6 feet. The Piazza San Marco was turned into a lake, its vast expanse covered by 4 feet of water.</p>
        <p>From then on, the need for a remedy became obvious, although it still took two decades for the need to be converted into concrete action. Dealing With Pollution</p>
        <p>But by then, Venice had fallen into the clutches of yet another serious problem, one that might be considered the flip side of flooding.</p>
        <p>Between bouts of acqua alta, the lagoon stagnates. Phosphate detergents, farm fertilizers, pesticides and other muck pour into the lagoon from the Adriatic and from connecting rivers. When the tides are strong, they recycle the lagoon water and serve as cleansing agents. When Venice is ''dry,'' it resembles a swamp, and the situation has reached crisis levels in recent years.</p>
        <p>Last summer was a noxious horror here. An uncontrolled growth of algae clogged the lagoon, emitting foul-smelling vapors of hydrogen sulfide and breeding millions of tiny flying insects, an infestation so thick that trains stopped and the airport shut down because engineers and pilots could not see where they were going. At one point last July, the city was scooping out 500 tons of algae a day just to keep even with each day's new growth. And because this has been an unusually dry winter, expectations for another bad summer run high.</p>
        <p>Given the severity of this problem, the consortium's engineers were forced into a delicate balancing act: How could they block high tides, yet preserve the tides' flushing function?</p>
        <p>That concern forced them from the start to rule out permanent dams. Any barrier would have to be easily raised, and then just as easily lowered, at the three openings in the whisps of land that separate lagoon and sea. The openings Porto di Lido, Porto di Malamocco and Porto di Chioggia, are also the lifelines for the city's fish market and port traffic. How It Works</p>
        <p>The next dilemma was what sort of impermanent structure to erect. After much discussion, Venice and the central Government settled on flexible barriers - a sophisticated echo of devices completed a few years ago on the River Thames in London and the Oosterschelde in the Netherlands. For testing purposes, a prototype was built, the Electromechanical Experimental Module. In Italian, this is Modulo Sperimentale Elettromeccanico, or MOSE. Mose is also the Italian word for Moses.</p>
        <p>The prototype gate is actually a 200-ton hollow steel box that is 66 feet wide, 11.5 feet thick, and 56 feet high, although most of its height will always remain below water. Depending on the degree of turbulence, only 10 feet to 13 feet of gate is expected to be visible above the surface when it swings up into action.</p>
        <p>As the engineers see it, about 80 gates should be enough to shut out the sea when it gets rough - 20 each at the Malamocco and Chioggia openings and 40 in the Lido aperture, which breaks off into two distinct branches inside the lagoon.</p>
        <p>The gates would rest just above the lagoon bed when they are in the horizontal position, well out of the way of shipping. The depth of the lagoon varies at the different openings, ranging from 49 feet at Malamocco to 26 feet in one of the Lido openings. In the other Lido opening, where the prototype is, the depth is 39 feet.</p>
        <p>To protect against corrosion from the brackish waters, the prototype has been plated with stainless steel and coated with special paints. ''The life span should be 50 years,'' said Franco de Siervo, the project's technical director.</p>
        <p>In the testing period, the engineers are not interested in seeing how well it holds back the sea. A single gate is hardly up to the task. Rather, they have focused on how different types of hinges perform, how much sediment the machinery collects and how easily it can be cleaned.</p>
        <p>For now, the gate has a 1,300-ton, open steel frame rising above the boxy base anchored on the lagoon floor. The frame, which holds monitoring equipment, air and water pumps and even a small kitchen for workers, will not be there when actual operations begin, because all support services for the many gates will be carried out on land. Held in Place by Water</p>
        <p>The gates would be attached by hinges to concrete bases buried in the lagoon bed, and they would be separated from one another by 4 inches.</p>
        <p>When not in use, the gates would be held in place by water that fills them. When tides threaten, pumps on land would shoot compressed air through the hinges, displacing the water and expelling it through holes on the surface that faces the lagoon bed.</p>
        <p>Once they have enough air, the gates would be sufficiently buoyant to swivel on the hinges and rise above the water at an angle of about 45 degrees facing the lagoon.</p>
        <p>At one point, the consortium considered a design that would have had the gates stand perpendicular to the water, but it was rejected out of fear that a powerful tide would knock them over. The present angle, engineers say, should enable the gates to oscillate with the sea, preserving a natural wave action and thereby achieving a measure of tidal cleansing even when the entrances are shut.</p>
        <p>Plans call for raising the gates two at a time, and all 20 at each opening are expected to be in place within 30 minutes. When an ''all clear'' has been sounded, water will be pumped back into the steel boxes, causing them to drop back to the sea bed until needed again. Political Decisions</p>
        <p>In the future, Venice may conclude that building the gates was the easy part of the job. Deciding when to put it into use may prove far trickier, and the final battle will be fought by politicians, not engineers.</p>
        <p>Some experts argue that it is reasonable to crank up the mechanism when tides reach 80 centimeters. That would be an average of 40 times a year, and it would protect virtually all of the city except for the highly vulnerable San Marco basilica. Experts say that the sea-wall reinforcement and the dredging operations under way throughout the lagoon should insure the safety of other low-lying quarters.</p>
        <p>''Forty closures a year do not jeopardize the city's port operations in a visible manner,'' Mr. de Siervo said.</p>
        <p>But even 40 is too high a figure for some Venetian shippers and fishermen. Environmentalists are also concerned about worsened lagoon pollution that might be caused by any interruption of water exchange.</p>
        <p>It is a formula for a controversy likely to endure well after the last gate has swung into place.  The Floods Of Venice  Venice has essentially stopped sinking, but with the Adriatic rising, flooding during high tides is becoming more and more frequent.  Tidal height:  76.4 inches  The record flood so far was on Nov. 4, 1966, when four feet of water covered Piazza San Marco.  43 inches  Extensive flooding is city-wide: 49 times from 1971 to 1985.  31.5 inches  Piazza and other low-lying areas are awash: 40 times a year.  28 inches  Water trickles into San Marco Basilica: 150 times a year.  A Delicate Balance  High water is only one side of the equation. Normal tides recycle the lagoon water, helping remove industrial and agricultural pollution. When tides are abnormally low, foul-smelling algae grow, flying insects multiply, and the lagoon resembles a polluted swamp. The challenge is to head off high water without permanently blocking beneficial tides.  The Proposed Solution  Engineers envision about 80 flexible sea gates for the lagoon's three inlets. A prototype, called MOSE, is being tested. When seas are high, the hollow hinged flap is filled with compressed air, making it float up at an angle against the waves. When tides ease, water is let back in and the flap sinks below the surface.  Source: New Venice Consortium</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
