<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="250970"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BUSINESS DIGEST (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6D91331F934A25756C0A96F948260" item-length="608" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  THE ECONOMY  Construction of new homes slid last month to the lowest level in more than six years, the Government reported. The real estate industry said in a separate report that prices of existing homes were rising with much less force nationwide. [ Page A1. ] The Senate and House might have to relinquish some control over top military programs if the U.S.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  THE ECONOMY  Construction of new homes slid last month to the lowest level in more than six years, the Government reported. The real estate industry said in a separate report that prices of existing homes were rising with much less force nationwide. [ Page A1. ] The Senate and House might have to relinquish some control over top military programs if the U.S.</p>
        <p>THE ECONOMY  Construction of new homes slid last month to the lowest level in more than six years, the Government reported. The real estate industry said in a separate report that prices of existing homes were rising with much less force nationwide. [ Page A1. ] The Senate and House might have to relinquish some control over top military programs if the U.S. is to maintain the superiority of its military technology, a Congressional study said.  [ D7. ]  The Air Force suspended payment on Loral's contract to build a radar warning system for the F-16 fighter. [ D7. ] INTERNATIONAL  The Senate defeated an attempt to block the Administration's agreement to build an advanced fighter plane with Japan. The 52-to-47 vote reflected lawmakers' anger over the $7 billion deal. [ D1. ] Robert Maxwell and Rupert Murdoch joined forces in a multimillion-dollar deal linking satellite and cable television. [ D1. ] Commerce Secretary Mosbacher called on Moscow to stop stealing high-technology secrets. [ D9. ] Talks resume today between Mexico and its commercial bank lenders on a debt reduction and restructuring package. [ D16. ] COMPANIES  Minorco conceded defeat in its $4.2 billion bid for Consolidated Gold Fields. British law bars another bid for a year. [ D1. ] Home Box Office will enter the basic cable business with a 24-hour all-comedy channel. [ D1. ] Continental canceled its increase in discount fares, saying competitors had not matched its move. [ D5. ] .  Procter &amp; Gamble has put Crush International up for sale, the latest giant to fail in the soft-drink business. [ D2. ] Cray Research's stock plunged $6, or 10.8 percent, to $49.75, after the news that its founder would start a new company. [ D5. ] A Federal bankruptcy judge said Eastern Airlines' management was acting properly in seeking to sell the shuttle. [ D5. ] I.B.M. introduced, as expected, an ambitious set of software that addresses the changing role of the mainframe. [ D4. ] Southmark lost more than $1 billion in the first quarter. It said the loss reflected problem real estate loans. [ D4. ] MARKETS  The S.E.C. charged a former paralegal with Skadden, Arps with violating securities laws by passing on insider information. [ D9. ] Stock prices fell after rising for four sessions. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 10.44 points, to 2,453.45. [ D10. ] Prices of Treasury securities were mixed in light trading, as longer issues outperformed short-term notes and bills.  [ D16. ]  Yields were flat for C.D.'s and bank money market accounts. [ D24. ] The dollar's rally stalled amid traders' nervousness over forthcoming Government data.  [ D17. ]  Grain and soybean futures prices plunged after forecasts of increased rain. [ D17. ] TECHNOLOGY  Experimental vehicles that burn methanol are turning up with increasing frequency. [ D8. ] Someday, shoppers will dig through the onion bin reading labels on each onion that indicate its sweetness and pungency. [ D8. ] TODAY'S COLUMNS  Can America curb its addiction to fossil fuels? Fears focus on demand. Peter Passell: Economic Scene. [ D2. ] Bergner's acquisition of Carson Pirie Scott shows how appealing regional retailers have become. Market Place. [ D10. ] David Ogilvy said he was ''miserable'' after Ogilvy agreed to be taken over by WPP. Randall Rothenberg: Advertising. [ D1. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
