<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="313420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891231T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3D71F3DF932A05751C1A96F948260" item-length="910" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International 3-17  American troops made a ''screw-up'' when they searched the Nicaraguan ambassador's residence in Panama City, President Bush conceded. The Nicaraguan government ordered 20 U.S. diplomats to leave Nicaragua within 72 hours in protest. 1  U.S. versions of search of embassy residence differ</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International 3-17  American troops made a ''screw-up'' when they searched the Nicaraguan ambassador's residence in Panama City, President Bush conceded. The Nicaraguan government ordered 20 U.S. diplomats to leave Nicaragua within 72 hours in protest. 1  U.S. versions of search of embassy residence differ</p>
        <p>International 3-17  American troops made a ''screw-up'' when they searched the Nicaraguan ambassador's residence in Panama City, President Bush conceded. The Nicaraguan government ordered 20 U.S. diplomats to leave Nicaragua within 72 hours in protest. 1  U.S. versions of search of embassy residence differ  6  U.S. denies it has top Noriega aide 6  Case against Noriega has not been bolstered by the invasion  8  Military analysis: The U.S. invasion of Panama on such a large a scale increased the number of casualties and possibily forfeited the opportunity to seize General Noriega. 1  Rumania's intelligentsia emerged this week from decades spent in the darkness of Ceausescu's shadow and found itself groping for words. 1  In a dictator's palace, lavish echoes of power  14  The Soviet republic of Moldavia appears on the verge of its own rebellion. Moldavians have been closely watching the revolt by their blood kin in Rumania, just over the border #15  Protesters expel Communist leaders from Azerbaijani city  15  News analysis: Poland's reform plan is leading the way among Eastern European nations in the move from Communism to capitalism. The trail- blazing experiment is being closely watched in the West. 14  The East bloc's espionage in the West has not slackened, despite the democratic revolt that has shaken Eastern Europe. 15  Vietnamese refugees in Hong Kong detention camps have made plans to resist the next forcible return of boat people to Vietnam by setting fires, using homemade weapons and taking hostages. 16  China condemns British decision to accept Hong Kong families  16  Policeman is your friend, Chinese are told  17  South Korea's former President, Chun Doo Hwan, is to answer questions today about the abuses of power and corruption that marked his repressive eight-year rule. 3  Segregated education in South Africa is being debated again after the disastrous showing this year of black high school seniors, 58 percent of whom failed their final examinations. 3  Trade dispute over wheat imports splits Nigeria and U.S.  9  On the Ganges River, a last waterlord's last stand  11  P.L.O. tries to block spread of Lebanese fighting  12  Jews and Palestinians hold a rally in Jerusalem  13  National 20-23  President Bush's image has changed in his first year in office. He is more complex than he once seemed, showing flaws that were not apparent before and not showing flaws for which he was once disparaged. 1  The threats to the nation's forests include ozone and other natural factors, as well as acid rain. Although acid rain appears to pose a long-term threat, evidence suggests these factors may be more harmful in the short run, scientists say. 1  A proposed ban on disposable diapers is part of a general recycling effort in Vermont that would push mandatory recycling, extend the bottle-deposit law and force newspapers to use partly recycled newsprint. 22  As giants battle for Maine paper mill, a town waits  21  Study finds no cracks in first of reactors at Savannah River  21  Two bald eagles build nest, and Florida project trembles  22  The nation's homicide rate has risen 5 percent during the year, reaching record levels in several major cities. Law-enforcement officials agree that criminal disregard for life seems to be growing. 20  An airplane threatened by terrorists landed uneventfully in Detroit amid media attention and fortress-like security. Northwest Airlines informed ticket holders Thursday of a ''security threat'' against the flight. 20  San Francisco Journal: A hotel's last New Year's Eve  20  D.E.A. refuses to relax restrictions on marijuana  20  Lelyveld succeeds Gelb at The New York Times  21  Taiwan held liable for killing of U.S. journalist  23  Growls and howls as North unleashes classic performance  22  Regional 24-30, 34-35  H.U.D.'s double subsidies for families in New York City have been uncovered. Eager to fill quotas, H.U.D. has given almost $2 million a year to 600 households already subsidized by the city and the state, records show. 1  Mayor-elect David Dinkins' salary, like that of other members of his administration, will go up significantly tomorrow, but whether the city and state need to pay such high salaries is being debated. 30  12,000 invitations, only 6,000 chairs at Dinkins' swearing-in  30  The cause of the gas main explosion in the South Bronx is still under investigation. The explosion killed two men and cut power and subway service in large parts of the Bronx and Manhattan. 24  Two killed, one injured in shooting at a nightclub  26  Two teen-agers arrested in drive-by killings in Queens.  34  Study finds that fewer teen-agers are using drugs  35  New York's anti-smoking law goes into effect tomorrow.  29  Neediest Cases 26  Arts/Reviews 50  Campus Life 39-40  Fashion 46-47  Life Style 41-42  Obituaries 32  Weddings 48-49</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
