<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>June 3, 1979: Shoreham's Rainy Day</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="255696"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND LIGHTING CO (LILCO)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SHOREHAM NUCLEAR POWER PLANT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, MIRIAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D61339F937A35755C0A96F948260" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>June 3, 1979: Shoreham's Rainy Day</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Miriam Goodman; Miriam Goodman of Huntington is former co-chairman of the North Shore Coalition for Safe Energy.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, MIRIAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: JUNE is a many-splendored month, but no June day in the memory of Shoreham opponents was more splendid than June 3, 1979. It was a watershed event for Long Island, that demonstration against the Shoreham nuclear plant 10 years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: JUNE is a many-splendored month, but no June day in the memory of Shoreham opponents was more splendid than June 3, 1979. It was a watershed event for Long Island, that demonstration against the Shoreham nuclear plant 10 years ago.</p>
        <p>JUNE is a many-splendored month, but no June day in the memory of Shoreham opponents was more splendid than June 3, 1979. It was a watershed event for Long Island, that demonstration against the Shoreham nuclear plant 10 years ago.</p>
        <p>Never before had more than 15,000 people converged in one place on the Island for the purpose of protest. Nor had as many as 600 individuals ever before placed themselves in jeopardy here by climbing over the fences surrounding the plant, as an act of nonviolent civil disobedience.</p>
        <p>The accident at Three Mile Island two months earlier had sent a shock wave across the nation and the world, and suddenly Long Islanders, some of whom had never heard of Shoreham and many who had never questioned the conventional wisdom that nuclear power was safe, clean and cheap, were clamoring to be heard.</p>
        <p>Those were heady days for activists like myself more accustomed to public apathy than to demands for information. Teach-ins, debates, meetings and literature increased exponentially. The Shad Alliance (Sound and Hudson against Atomic Development) knew that the demonstration they were planning for June 3 on the town beach at Shoreham would be a big one, but they had no idea how high the numbers would go.</p>
        <p>Discussions with the local police were a necessity to provide for vehicle parking and for shuttles to facilitate access on the winding country roads leading to the beach, though eventually some traffic snarls were inevitable. Also anticipated was the illegal occupation of the plant site. Word kept coming from across the breadth of the Island, from New York City, upstate and elsewhere to expect more and more chartered buses.</p>
        <p>My home, like that of a number of others, became a temporary headquarters for inquiries and bus reservations. It was hectic, but gratifying, to talk with and share mutual concerns with many residents of the surrounding North Shore communities in western Nassau, where I then lived.</p>
        <p>On the morning of June 3, the weather predictions cast a pall on conversation as my husband and I set out hours early by car, with folding table, literature and banners in tow. As we drove east on the L.I.E., the dark clouds gathering for a heavy downpour seemed an appropriate barometer of the solemn mood of the thousands to gather that day and a symbol, too, of the growing anti-Shoreham momentum that would release a flood of citizen actions.</p>
        <p>The rain began gently while we were still en route. Because we were among the volunteers providing printed matter, food, buttons, T-shirts and first aid, we were permitted to park close to the beach. As people began to arrive, the rain gathered force and continued throughout the afternoon. But the miracle that we hoped for was actually happening. The rain deterred no one. Waves of people, young and old and in between, kept coming in an endless stream down the sloping approach to the beach. The sand was soon covered with a sea of umbrellas and all other manner of rain cover shared by individuals with a common purpose, chanting slogans, listening to speaker after speaker and enjoying the music. The dramatic appearance of the Bread and Puppet Theater's fantastic giant, costumed and masked figures on stilts descending from the bluff above, regaling the crowd with their politically and socially relevant mime, was electrifying.</p>
        <p>That day was a turning point in what was to be a 22-year-long battle to prevent the operation of the Shoreham Nuclear Power Station. Those many-hued umbrellas gave birth to one large umbrella, the Shoreham Opponents Coalition, to help focus the activities of the many opposition groups on the legal intervention.</p>
        <p>Though the goal of closing Shoreham forever is now in sight, we must remain vigilant. Those same powers that foisted this hazard on what was then, with small exception, a largely unknowledgeable public, are now, led by the Department of Energy, brazenly pulling out all the stops to prevent decommissioning of the plant by having it mothballed for potential future operation.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department, with its long secret history of contamination of the environments and populations near its nuclear weapons complexes around the nation, and with its disastrous performance on nuclear waste disposal, is hardly an model of concern for public health and safety or of responsible policy making. The old scare tactic about ''freezing in the dark'' has been supplanted with warnings about ''blackouts,'' ''brownouts'' and ''the greenhouse effect.'' Our reply in 1979 remains: sound energy policy must be based on energy efficiency and on benign and renewable energy sources. The ultimate threat is not a shortage of energy, but the wasting of Long Island with radioactive poisons. It is this knowledge, shared by a majority of Long Islanders, that has kept Shoreham from operating. Let us make certain it never will.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
