<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Treat the Attack of Acid Rain, Add Limestone to Water and Wait</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19890208T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="218969"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIMESTONE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DB1E3AF932A05752C0A96F948260" item-length="1094" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Treat the Attack of Acid Rain, Add Limestone to Water and Wait</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IN a nascent counterattack on the effects of acid rain, American scientists and wildlife experts are increasingly bringing dead lakes and streams back to life by using the simple technique of adding limestone to the water.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IN a nascent counterattack on the effects of acid rain, American scientists and wildlife experts are increasingly bringing dead lakes and streams back to life by using the simple technique of adding limestone to the water.</p>
        <p>IN a nascent counterattack on the effects of acid rain, American scientists and wildlife experts are increasingly bringing dead lakes and streams back to life by using the simple technique of adding limestone to the water.</p>
        <p>The technique, long used in Sweden, is not a permanent solution to the problem of acidification, experts say. That will come only when the industrial emissions that cause acid rain are sufficiently reduced, even proponents of the treatment method say. But they believe that ''liming,'' as it is called, now offers a practical way to stave off some damage caused by acid rain until there is a permanent solution. It also restores the health of some lakes and streams where life has already been destroyed by acidification.</p>
        <p>''It works, but it's a stopgap,'' says Dr. Patricia Bradt, a biologist at Lehigh University who is an authority on the subject and who has recently completed a study of the effects of liming on lakes in the Poconos. Expanding Movement in U.S.  Liming has been tried in a few spots, including the Adirondacks, for years. But now the movement appears to be growing. From helicopters and barges and pumps in the warm months, and from fertilizer spreaders on the ice in winter, fisheries experts are applying granulated limestone to waters in New England to the Adirondacks and the Great Lakes states and south into Appalachia. An estimated 100 such projects are now under way, a bare beginning as against the large-scale Swedish program, in which about 500 lakes a year are limed.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, large scale or small, the effects are reported to be dramatic. The alkaline character of the limestone rapidly offsets a lake's acidity, rapidly restoring the water to a neutral condition, or nearly so. In one experiment in the western Adirondacks, ''we added fish four days after liming'' and they flourished, according to Dr. Donald Porcella, an environmental scientist with the Electric Power Research Institute, which conducted the experiment.</p>
        <p>From the smallest algae to the biggest fish in the food chain, the populations of acidic or acidifying lakes gradually re-establish themselves after liming, although restocking of fish speeds up the process.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bradt's study involved two 50-acre lakes, White Deer Lake and Bruce Lake, about 10 miles apart in Pike County, Pa. The two displayed similar characteristics when the study began in 1984. Both lakes had been declining because of acid rain, the investigators found. One Lake Treated, One Untouched</p>
        <p>Bruce Lake was not touched. White Deer Lake was treated with 100 tons of limestone, distributed by a tractor-drawn fertilizer spreader on the lake's frozen surface in February 1985. For about 2 1/2 years, this application held acidification at bay. When it became evident that the lake was acidifying again, 15 more tons of limestone slurry, granules mixed with liquid, were pumped into the lake from a barge.</p>
        <p>In those first 2 1/2 years, Dr. Bradt reported, acid-sensitive organisms like mayflies, clams, snails, dragonflies, caddis flies, zooplankton and diatoms, or microscopic algae, all re-established themselves. But in the untreated Bruce Lake, such organisms steadily declined. At the end of the four-year experiment in 1988, Bruce Lake had become acidified, while White Deer Lake had not.</p>
        <p>In the Adirondacks, Dr. Porcella and a research team limed three lakes beginning in 1983, two of them fishless and one with lake trout that, because of acid rain, were showing signs of being unable to reproduce. The two fishless lakes were stocked with brook trout and the fish ''have done quite well,'' said Dr. Porcella, adding that ''they have grown fast and are healthy fish.'' In the third lake, the lake trout resumed reproduction.</p>
        <p>Similarly positive results are being reported from other projects in Massachusetts, Rhode Island, Pennsylvania, West Virginia, Michigan and Minnesota. But for all the successes, there are major limitations as well. Need for Repeated Limings</p>
        <p>First, lakes must be periodically limed again because their water is constantly being replaced, washing out the limestone. Some lakes are considered unsuitable for the liming because they flush too rapidly.</p>
        <p>Liming is generally cost-effective in lakes that flush themselves out no more often than every six months, said Dr. Timothy Adams, a chemist who is a consultant for Living Lakes Inc., a Washington-based, nonprofit organization that has taken the lead in the renewed effort to promote liming in the United States.</p>
        <p>But, he said, costs must be judged on a case-by-case basis, taking into account the importance of the lake to the enonomy and the environment.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bradt believes that liming ''should be considered an expensive Band-Aid on a gaping wound.''</p>
        <p>Still, that Band-Aid is being applied more often. In the last three years, Living Lakes has limed 28 lakes. It is preparing to lime 10 more this year, and has helped support a number of research projects, including Dr. Bradt's. The organization is supported by the utility and coal industries as well as by some environmental groups, according to Dr. Robert Brocksen, a specialist in aquatic ecology who is executive director of Living Lakes. 'We Don't Solve the Problem'</p>
        <p>Actual treatment costs run from about $10 to about $15 an acre per year, Dr. Adams said. For instance, he said, the estimated treatment cost for a newly treated 350-acre lake on the Massachusetts-Rhode Island border, called Wallum Lake, is about $4,200 a year. The cost is based on an estimated flushing rate of once every two years.</p>
        <p>In Sweden, the Government is spending $35 million this year to lime that country's lakes, and expects to spend $50 million by 1992. ''Lake liming is not research any more,'' said Dr. Harald Sverdrup, a professor of chemical engineering at Sweden's Lund University, who is a consultant to the Government on the matter. ''We know how to do it, and in terms of aquatic management it works.''</p>
        <p>''We don't solve the problem this way,'' Dr. Sverdrup said in a telephone interview, ''but we take away from the worst effects. That buys time for us to work for emission reductions.''</p>
        <p>A few years ago, liming was criticized in the United States as representing an attempt by the utility and coal industries to avoid having to invest in devices to control acid rain. ''There might be some people who still view it as that,'' said Dr. Brocksen. ''If they do, they're incorrect.'' Liming, he said, is ''something that's got to be done no matter what happens, and it's something that can be done now.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 8, 1989, Wednesday, Late City Final Edition</p>
        <p>A chart in Science Times on Jan. 31 with an article about the use of lime to reduce acidity in lakes referred to the Pocono Mountains incorrectly. They are in eastern, not western, Pennsylvania.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 8, 1989, Wednesday, Late City Final Edition</p>
        <p>A chart in Science Times on Jan. 31 with an article about the use of lime to reduce acidity in lakes referred to the Pocono Mountains incorrectly. They are in eastern, not western, Pennsylvania.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
