<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="248837"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DF1430F933A25756C0A96F948260" item-length="896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International A3-17</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International A3-17</p>
        <p>International A3-17</p>
        <p>President Bush said Panama's vote was marred by ''massive irregularities at the polls'' and called for international pressure for General Noriega to step aside. Page A1</p>
        <p>The opposition leaders in Panama tried to press General Noriega to accept the results of Sunday's elections, which independent observers say the opposition won. A10</p>
        <p>Washington reassesses 1978 pact A11</p>
        <p>As the campaign for Polish elections next month warms up, voters accustomed to unopposed candidates with look-alike platforms are getting a crash course in a new approach to political pluralism. A1</p>
        <p>Solidarity joins Warsaw in urging end to strikes A13</p>
        <p>Soviet officials testified in Congress before the House Armed Services Committee, where the Joint Chiefs of Staff usually make their case. The officials appealed for a warmer approach by Washington. A5</p>
        <p>The Soviet Union's first soup kitchen has been set up for Leningrad's elderly poor by an organization of volunteers, in a triumph over public and official attitudes toward poverty. A4</p>
        <p>Six Navy sailors were killed in a fire when leaking fuel was ignited in the boiler room of a U.S. combat supply ship in the South China Sea,about 100 miles east of Hong Kong. A9</p>
        <p>Ronald Reagan's visit to Tokyo later this year for 10 days of paid speeches and ceremonies has been clouded by a turbulent political situation and by reports of a bidding war over the right to serve as his sponsor. A7</p>
        <p>Takeshita's would-be successor is still a might-be A6</p>
        <p>More than 1,000 Chinese journalists from official news organizations petitioned for talks with the nation's leaders in the strongest appeal so far for freedom of the press. A8</p>
        <p>Spain is feeling the tug of old ties to Latin America and new links to Western Europe, with 1992 marking both its discovery of the Americas and a turning point in Europe. A3</p>
        <p>Muslim side in Lebanon keeps up shelling to deny foe arms A14</p>
        <p>Nairobi bans 2d magazine A15</p>
        <p>National A18-33, B6</p>
        <p>In a move to defend Speaker Wright, his lawyers filed five motions with the House ethics committee, including one to bar the panel's counsel from having contact with panel members outside formal channels. A1</p>
        <p>Opposition to the civil rights nominee for the Justice Department, William Lucas, was announced by the Leadership Conference on Civil Rights and the NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund. A1</p>
        <p>The claim of creating nuclear fusion in a jar was staunchly defended by two chemists who said they have new evidence that their device produces bursts of energy. A32</p>
        <p>A world meeting on global warming and other environmental problems will be called by President Bush, the White House said. Uncertainty remains over whether to seek a treaty for the warming problem. B6</p>
        <p>States seek bigger role in nuclear waste cleanup A32</p>
        <p>Alaska presses complaints against Exxon on oil spill A28</p>
        <p>Abortion rights backers were bouyed this week by a court ruling that federally funded family planning clinics may inform their clients about abortion. A24</p>
        <p>A feminist accuses Boston College of denying her academic promotion and trying to ''starve'' her out of a position at the college for religious and ideological reasons. A31</p>
        <p>Mother charged in baby's death from cocaine A18</p>
        <p>Edwards to run for Lousiana governor again A29</p>
        <p>Bakkers seek to rebuild ministry A18</p>
        <p>Washington Talk B6</p>
        <p>Ralph Nader is back in currency with recent successes on issues as varied as insurance rates, Federal pay and automobile air bags.  Regional B1-7, B24</p>
        <p>Drug abuse is overwhelming hospitals in New York City, frustrating medical staffs, who feel they lack the tools to respond to the problem, public health experts say. A1</p>
        <p>Trains are now virtually graffiti-free in New York City, transit officials say. They plan to celebrate the achievement on Friday by taking the last graffiti-covered train out of service. A1</p>
        <p>At a benefit after ''Swan Lake'' at the Metropolitan Opera House, a corps of social swans was among 1,200 guests who danced in the tent that Blaine Trump had pitched on the Lincoln Center Plaza. B7</p>
        <p>Landmark panel vetoes request to raze church B3</p>
        <p>Does New York City need boroughs? That question has started to arise as the commission rewriting the city's charter considers the structure of municipal government and the fate of the borough presidents. B1</p>
        <p>Cuomo's crime plan gets mixed reviews in Albany B1</p>
        <p>Court overturns conviction in day-care sex scandal B3</p>
        <p>Four Princeton scholars resigned from the university's English Department recently. One cited the unversity's handling of a purported sexual encounter between a male student and a male professor. B1</p>
        <p>Property-tax revolt is in the air across Long Island as tax bills have skyrocketed. Governor Cuomo responded by visiting angry residents in Levittown B1</p>
        <p>G.O.P. hopefuls clash in debate for New Jersey's governorship B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
