<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>RISE OF 2 PLATEAUS LINKED TO ICE AGES</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="248962"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOLOGY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ROCKY MOUNTAINS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">HIMALAYAS</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">GEOPHYSICAL UNION, AMERICAN</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, WALTER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geology</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DB1438F932A25756C0A96F948260" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>RISE OF 2 PLATEAUS LINKED TO ICE AGES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER SULLIVAN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, WALTER</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE, May 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The rise of two great plateaus, one under the Rockies and one under the Himalayas, altered the world's air circulation enough to set the stage for the ice ages, according to a hypothesis presented here today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The rise of two great plateaus, one under the Rockies and one under the Himalayas, altered the world's air circulation enough to set the stage for the ice ages, according to a hypothesis presented here today.</p>
        <p>The rise of two great plateaus, one under the Rockies and one under the Himalayas, altered the world's air circulation enough to set the stage for the ice ages, according to a hypothesis presented here today.</p>
        <p>It is widely agreed that once the ice ages began 2.5 million years ago, their comings and goings were determined by periodic changes in the Earth's orbit around the sun and the tilt of its axis. But these became controlling factors only after changing air circulation at high latitudes deposited more snow in winter than could melt the next summer. When this happened, ice sheets began to grow and spread.</p>
        <p>Until now the role of rising plateaus has not been widely considered as a cause of climate change. The hypothesis was presented to the spring meeting of the American Geophysical Union in Baltimore by Dr. William R. Ruddiman of Columbia University's Lamont-Doherty Geological Observatory. His co-author was Dr. John E. Kutzbach of the University of Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>Their work was hailed by such specialists as Dr. John Imbrie of Brown University, a leader in efforts to understand what caused the ice age cycles. Computer Simulates Climate</p>
        <p>To assess the effect of the uplift, the researchers used a computer simulation of the world's climate at the National Center for Atmospheric Research in Boulder, Colo.</p>
        <p>Attempts were made to mimic the situation before the uplift occurred, as well as when it had reached its halfway point and when it was complete.</p>
        <p>It is known that in the past 20 million years, the Tibetan Plateau has risen three miles as the Indian subcontinent plowed into Asia, producing the Himalayas, and the Rocky Mountain area has risen a mile. That is possibly because the continent, as it drifted westward, pushed over a large area of Pacific floor.</p>
        <p>Before these rises occurred, the Northern Hemisphere was comparatively flat. The prevailing westerly winds blew straight across the continents of Eurasia and North America. But as the plateaus rose, the main wind flow tended to curve north and flow around these obstructions before again turning south.</p>
        <p>This carried frigid Arctic air to the interiors of both continents. The Himalayas blocked the flow of humid air into Central Asia, much of which is now desert. The northern plains of North America also became cold and dry. In summer the new cycle of air currents carried moisture from the Indian Ocean and dumped it as monsoon rains on India and Southeast Asia.</p>
        <p>The evidence from fossil plants and animals throughout the Northern Hemisphere indicates that such changes did occur, Dr. Ruddiman said. From geologic evidence it is believed the plateaus began to rise 20 million years ago, affecting about one million square miles in the Himalayan area and a similar area in the Rockies. But only about 2.5 million years ago did it proceed far enough to produce the ice age cycles. Shifts in Climate</p>
        <p>In a separate study of the late stages of the ice age in North America, a team of scientists has offered an explanation for puzzling back-and-forth shifts of climate.</p>
        <p>The researchers explained that as the last North American ice sheet melted, it sent a deluge of cold water down the Mississippi, which may have increased the river flow elevenfold. A similar deluge later poured down the St. Lawrence River, they theorized. These events so chilled the Gulf of Mexico and the North Atlantic that an ice age suddenly returned after a warmer period, the scientists said.</p>
        <p>The researchers, including Dr. Imbrie of Brown, pointed out in the April 13 issue of the journal Nature that from 13,000 to 12,600 years ago the ice-age climate rapidly became warmer. Then 11,000 years ago it suddenly returned to glacial conditions. Finally, about 1,000 years later, it warmed to its current level.</p>
        <p>The last period of chilling was especially marked in Greenland and Europe, which is attributed to a deluge of frigid melt water into the North Atlantic. The melting of the ice was voluminous enough to raise worldwide sea levels about 300 feet.</p>
        <p>The scientists have now found evidence that these sudden changes were also felt in the Caribbean and Gulf of Mexico. Evidence Seen in Shells</p>
        <p>The changes were shown in tiny shells of foraminifera, a species indicative of water temperature, extracted from the ocean floor. The scientists also studied pollen grains indicating moist and dry climates in old deposits from the southern coastal plain of the United States and from Florida.</p>
        <p>At the Goddard Institute for Space Studies in Manhattan one of the co-authors, Dr. David Rind, and his colleagues did computer simulations of the role that colder sea surface temperatures in the North Atlantic might have had on climate in Europe, Greenland and North America.</p>
        <p>The authors said the results supported their hypothesis, but they added that more data and simulations were needed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
