<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE AMAZON'S SAVVY INDIANS</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="226739"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDIANS, AMERICAN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRAZIL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AMAZON RIVER BASIN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">KAIAPO INDIANS (BRAZIL)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMONS, MARLISE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru/Amazon Basin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DA113DF935A15751C0A96F948260" item-length="3970" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE AMAZON'S SAVVY INDIANS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marlise Simons; Marlise Simons is a correspondent in the Rio de Janeiro bureau of The New York Times.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMONS, MARLISE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IT IS GETTING DARK WHEN Chief Kanhonk sits down in the yard outside his home, ready for a long evening of conversation. Night birds are calling from the bush that sparkles with fireflies. Whooping frogs make a racket by the river.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IT IS GETTING DARK WHEN Chief Kanhonk sits down in the yard outside his home, ready for a long evening of conversation. Night birds are calling from the bush that sparkles with fireflies. Whooping frogs make a racket by the river.</p>
        <p>IT IS GETTING DARK WHEN Chief Kanhonk sits down in the yard outside his home, ready for a long evening of conversation. Night birds are calling from the bush that sparkles with fireflies. Whooping frogs make a racket by the river.</p>
        <p>No one seems worried by the squadron of bats sweeping low overhead.</p>
        <p>It is that important moment of the day when Indians of the Amazon, who use no written language, meet to talk, pass on information and tell stories. The night is when they recall ancestral customs, interpret dreams and comment on changes in nature and other events of the day. But from a nearby home come the sounds of a powerful rival: a television set is screeching cartoons at a group of children. I understand now why, that morning, by way of saying hello, these naked children of the rain forest had shouted things like ''He-Man'' and ''Flintstones.''</p>
        <p>Three years ago, when money from the sale of gold nuggets and mahogany trees was pouring into Gorotire, Chief Kanhonk agreed to bring in television, or the ''big ghost,'' as it is called here. A shiny satellite dish now stands on the earthen plaza like an alien sculpture, signaling that Gorotire - a small settlement of some 800 people on the Fresco River, a tributary of the Amazon - has become one of the wealthiest Indian villages in Brazil.</p>
        <p>Yet Chief Kanhonk appears to regret his decision. ''I have been saying that people must buy useful things like knives or fishing hooks,'' he says darkly. ''Television does not fill the stomach. It only shows our children and grandchildren white people's things.''</p>
        <p>The ''big ghost'' is just one of the changes that have been sweeping over Gorotire, but it seems to be worrying the elders the most. Some believe it is powerful enough to rob them of their culture. Bebtopup, the oldest medicine man in the village, explains his misgivings: ''The night is the time the old people teach the young people. Television has stolen the night.''</p>
        <p>When I discuss this with Eduardo Viveiros, a Brazilian anthropologist who works with a more isolated Amazonian tribe, he seems less worried. ''At least they quickly understood the consequences of watching television,'' he says. ''Many people never discover. Now Gorotire can make a choice.''</p>
        <p>It was the issue of choice that first drew me to the Kaiapo Indians of the lower Amazon Basin. They seemed to be challenging the widely held notion that forest Indians are defenseless in face of the pressures of the competitive and predatory Western world around them. Unlike most of Brazil's 230,000 Indians, they go out into the white world to defend their interests, and it is no longer unusual to see Kaiapo men - in their stunning body paint and feathered headdresses - showing up in Congress in Brasilia, the nation's capital, or lobbying by doing a war dance outside a Government office. They have even bought Western gadgets to record and film their festivals.</p>
        <p>Once the masters of immense stretches of forest and savannas, the Kaiapo were for hundreds of years among the most skillful farmers and hunters and fiercest warriors of central Brazil. They terrified other tribes with their raids. From the 17th to the 19th centuries, they not only resisted the slaving raids of the Portuguese invaders but they also attacked white traders and gold prospectors with such a vengeance that royal orders came from Portugal to destroy the Kaiapo. The white man's wrath and his diseases killed many, yet there are still close to 3,600 Kaiapo in more than a dozen different villages near the Xingu River. They have quarreled and regrouped, but their lands, several vast reservations, are more secure than those of many other tribes.</p>
        <p>After many years of isolation in the forest, the Kaiapo now have to deal with the growing encroachments of white society. ''They are going through a great transition,'' says Darrell Posey, an American anthropologist who has worked in Gorotire for more than a decade. ''Their survival is a miracle in itself. But I worry whether they can go on making the changes on their own terms.''</p>
        <p>Colombia, Ecuador, Peru and Venezuela - four of nine nations in the Amazon Basin, which harbors some 800,000 Indians - each have large numbers of tropical-forest Indians. But nowhere are pressures on Indian land as great as they are in Brazil. As the Amazon is opened up, developers bring in highways, settlers, cattle ranchers, mines and hydroelectric dams. In Brazil alone, more than 90 tribes have disappeared since the beginning of this century.</p>
        <p>The clearing of large areas of the rain forest and the fate of the Indians are also rapidly becoming an issue of international concern. Interest in the region has risen as ecological concerns, such as ozone depletion, the greenhouse effect and other changes in the global environment become political issues. More attention is paid to scientists who are alarmed at the destruction of the rain forest - a vital flywheel in the world's climate and the nursery of at least half of the world's plant and animal species.</p>
        <p>This has also prompted an increasing interest in the highly structured world of the forest Indians and their ancient and intricate knowledge of nature that permits them to survive in the tropical jungle without destroying it. (The Hall of South American Peoples, which includes a life-size model of a Kaiapo warrior, recently opened at the Museum of Natural History in New York City.) As Indians find greater support among environmentalists, they also get more organized in their fight to protect their habitat. The Kaiapo held their first international congress last week in Altamira, in central Brazil, protesting Government plans to build several massive dams that would flood Indian land.</p>
        <p>In Brazil, Indian tribes occupy 10 percent of the nation's territory, although much of their land has not been demarcated. Brazil's past military regimes elevated Indian affairs to a national-security issue, because many tribes live in large areas of border land. It is official policy to integrate Indians into the larger society, and the National Indian Foundation, with its 4,900 employees, is in charge of implementing this.</p>
        <p>In my 18 years in Latin America, I have heard many politicians and anthropologists discuss what is usually called ''the Indian problem,'' what to ''do'' about cultures that have changed little in thousands of years. One school of thought holds that the remote tribes should be kept isolated and protected until they can slowly make their own choices. Another school accepts that the Indian world is on the wane, and talks about ''guiding'' the Indians toward inevitable change - a process that should take several generations.</p>
        <p>But some anthropologists and politicians, including the Brazilian Government, believe in still more rapid integration. When Romeo Juca was head of the Indian Foundation, he said that it was only right for Indians to exploit their wealth, even if it meant acculturation. ''We have to be careful how fast we go,'' he said, ''but being Indian does not mean you have to be poor.''</p>
        <p>Gerardo Reichel-Dolmatoff is one of Latin America's most respected anthropologists. He insists that the Indians are their own best guides into Western society. An Austrian-born Colombian, Reichel-Dolmatoff has worked in Colombia's forests, at the Amazon's headwaters, for almost 50 years. ''We cannot choose for them,'' he insists. ''And we cannot put them into reserves, ghettos, ashokas. They are not museum exhibits. . . . If Indians choose the negative aspects of our civilization, we cannot control that. If there is one basic truth in anthropology, it is that cultures change. Static cultures do not exist.''</p>
        <p>The Indians themselves are pleading for more protection and respect for their cultures. Conrad Gorinsky, son of a Guyana Indian mother and himself a chemist in London, recently said: ''We don't want the Indians to change because we have them comfortably in the back of our mind like a kind of Shangri-La, something we can turn to even if we work ourselves to death in New York. But we are hounding and maligning them instead of recognizing them as the guardians of the forests, of the world's genetic banks, of our germ plasm and lifelines.''</p>
        <p>THE ABORIGINAL peoples we call Indians are as different from one another as, say, Europeans are. Even the most isolated groups remain separate fiefdoms with widely varying experiences, beliefs and histories. The degree of contact they have with the outside world is just as varied.</p>
        <p>I first met Kaiapo tribesmen three years ago in Belem, a large city at the mouth of the Amazon. I saw them again in Brasilia, the capital. In both places, they demonstrated their political skills and capacity to mobilize, showing up in large numbers to protest measures by the Government. They seemed particularly adept at commanding the attention of the press. Their body paint, feathers and other paraphernalia made them appear warlike, exotic and photogenic.</p>
        <p>Back in Gorotire, as it turns out, they are more ''ordinary.'' Wearing feathers and beads, explains Kubei, a chief's son, is for special occasions. ''It's our suit and tie.'' Besides the satellite dish, the Kaiapo also have their own small airplane. Their new wealth has also given them the luxury of hiring non-Indians to help plant new fields. But they remain ready to attack white intruders; some of the adult men have markings on their chests that record the number of outsiders they have killed.</p>
        <p>Two roads fan out from the center of Gorotire. A new sand track leads east on a five-hour drive to the town of Redencao. The other road goes south and, in a sense, it leads into the past. Dipping into the forest, it becomes a path that meanders through open patches where the Kaiapo women grow corn, sweet potatoes, bananas, manioc. On the plain ahead, it joins an ancient trail system that once reached for hundreds of miles into northern and western Brazil.</p>
        <p>One morning, Beptopup (medicine man, shaman, connoisseur of nature), the anthropologist Darrell Posey (who speaks the Kaiapo language) and I wander into the bush. Beptopup walks past the plants the way you go down a street where you know everyone. Stopping, nodding, his face lighting up with happy recognition, he sometimes goes into a song - a soft, high-pitch chant for a particular plant. He picks leaves, each one familiar, each one useful. One serves to remove body hair. Another, he says, can prevent pregnancy. The underside of one leaf is so rough it is used to sandpaper wood and file fingernails. Beptopup collects his plants in the morning, he says, because ''that is when they have the most strength.''</p>
        <p>Stopping at a shrub, we look at the large circle around its stem, where nothing grows. ''This and other plants have been sent to a laboratory for analysis,'' says Posey. ''We think this one has a natural weedkiller.''</p>
        <p>Beptopup holds up a branch of what he calls the ''eye of the jaguar.'' ''This was our flashlight,'' he says, showing how to set it afire and swing it gently so its strong glow will light one's path.</p>
        <p>One afternoon, when the heat has crept into everything, the women and children come back from the fields to their village. They stop and sit in a creek to escape the swirling gnats and buzzing bees. Others sit outside their homes, going about their age-old business. One woman plucks the radiant feathers of a dead macaw. Another removes her eyebrows and eyelashes, because the Kaiapo women think they are ugly. (A nurse once told me that this custom might have a hygienic origin - to ward off parasites, for instance.) Kaiapo women also deepen their foreheads by shaving the top of their head in a triangle that reaches the crown - a fearsome sight to the unaccustomed eye.</p>
        <p>I envy a mother who is clearly enjoying herself fingerpainting her three children. She draws black designs with genipap juice. On the face and the feet she puts red dye from the ''urucu,'' or annatto, plant; Indians say it keeps away chiggers and ticks.</p>
        <p>CHANGE HAS COME TO Gorotire along the other road, the one leading east to Redencao. Recent Kaiapo history is full of ''firsts,'' but a notable turning point came when prospectors struck gold on Gorotire land in 1980. The Kaiapo raided the camp, 20 miles from the village, but failed to drive away the trespassers. Then they made a deal.</p>
        <p>Last fall, when I was visiting Gorotire, about 2,000 gold diggers were stripping the land to the bone farther upstream, and the River Fresco passed the village the color of mud, its water contaminated with oil and mercury. I heard no one complain about that. Gorotire gets 7 percent of the mine's profits - several pounds of gold a week.</p>
        <p>In 1984, a lumber company completed the first road. It signed a contract with the Indian Foundation for Gorotire's mahogany (the Indians are wards of the Brazilian Government). Most of the mahogany is gone now, and the Government agency split the profits with the Kaiapo. Gorotire chose to spend its gold and timber profits on new water and electricity lines and rows of brick houses. Only about half of the inhabitants now live in traditional palm-frond huts.</p>
        <p>The young Kaiapo who earn a salary as supervisors at the gold camp have bought their own gas stoves, radios, sofas and mattresses. For the community, the four tribal chiefs ordered several boats, trucks and a small plane that ferries people and goods among nearby Kaiapo villages.</p>
        <p>One evening, a truck arriving from Redencao - bringing rice, sugar, bottled gas, oil for the generator - is another reminder of how fast Gorotire is adapting to a Western economy. From being a largely self-sufficient community of hunters and farmers, it is now increasingly dependent on outside goods. In Gorotire, it is clearly money, no longer disease or violence, that has become the greatest catalyst for change. Money has given the Kaiapo the means and the confidence to travel and lobby for their rights. At the same time, it is making them more vulnerable.</p>
        <p>I have seen other villages where Indians have received large sums of money - for the passage of a railroad or a powerline, or from a mining company. Such money is usually released in installments, through banks, but its arrival has put new strains on the role of the chiefs. Money and goods have introduced a new, materialistic expression of power in societies that have been egalitarian. Among most Indians, a man's prestige has always depended not on what he acquires but on what he gives away.</p>
        <p>In Gorotire, some of the young men complain that the chiefs are not distributing community money and goods equally, that the chiefs' relatives and favorites are getting a bigger share and more privileges.</p>
        <p>Darrell Posey, the anthropologist, believes the greatest political change came with the road. With it, he says, ''the Kaiapo chiefs lost control of which people and what goods would come in.'' Previously, the chiefs had been the sole distributors. They had also played the vital roles of keeping the peace and leading the ceremonies. Now, the chiefs hardly know the liturgy of the ceremonies; their main task seems to be to deal with the outside world.</p>
        <p>The transition is also changing the role of the medicine man. Bebtopup, for example, has an arsenal of remedies for the common ailments -fevers, diarrheas, snake bites, wounds. But he and his colleagues have lost prestige because they do not know how to deal with the diseases brought to Gorotire by white men, such as the pneumonia that strikes the children and the malaria spreading from the gold miners' camp.</p>
        <p>Anthropologists sometimes say that when outsiders visit the Indian world, they often focus on themes central not to Indians but to themselves. This might explain why I was so bothered by the garbage, the flotsam of Western civilization.</p>
        <p>Gorotire's setting is Arcadian. It lies on a bluff overlooking the River Fresco, with views of the forests across and the mountains behind. Spring rains bring waterfalls and blossoms. But these days the village is awash with rusting cans, plastic wrappers, tapes sprung from their cassettes, discarded mattresses and clothes. New domestic animals such as dogs, pigs and ducks have left a carpet of droppings. And giant rats, which suddenly appeared some years ago, seem to be everywhere; some have bitten small children.</p>
        <p>''Indians have never had garbage that was not biodegradable,'' says Sandra Machado, a Brazilian researching Kaiapo farming techniques here. ''No one wants to take care of it.''</p>
        <p>IT IS A MILD MOONLIT evening, and in the men's house many Kaiapo are watching soccer on television. The bank of the river is a quieter place to talk.</p>
        <p>''If you look beyond the garbage and the stone houses, this is still a strong and coherent indigenous culture,'' says Darrell Posey, speaking of the mixed feelings he has about a decade of developments in Gorotire. ''Despite everything, the language is alive, the festivals and initiation rights are observed.''</p>
        <p>Posey says that the Kaiapo in Gorotire and in other villages continue with their age-old natural farming techniques, using plants to fix nitrogen in the soil, chunks of termite nests instead of chemical fertilizers, plant infusions to kill pests, the nests of ferocious ants to protect fruit trees from other ant predators.</p>
        <p>Biologists often complain that there have been many studies of exotic rituals, paraphernalia and kinships of Indians, but that Western science has paid scant attention to the Indians' use of animals and plants.</p>
        <p>Like others working in the Amazon region, Posey worries about the gap between the old and the young. ''The old chiefs are turning over decisions to the young because they can drive a truck or operate a video machine or go to the bank,'' he says. ''But the young people don't see the relevance of learning the tribal knowledge and its being lost.''</p>
        <p>''You can afford to lose one generation,'' he adds, ''because grandparents do the teaching of their grandchildren. But you cannot afford to lose two generations.''</p>
        <p>Gorotire has a small Government school, designed to help Indians integrate into the national society. The teacher, who speaks only Portuguese, has started organizing annual Independence Day parades. On the blackboard is a list of patriotic holidays, including Independence Day and the Day of the Soldier. I ask the children later what a soldier is. ''Something of white people,'' one of them says.</p>
        <p>Chief Poropot agrees that everyone must learn Portuguese. ''The language of the Kaiapo is very ancient and it will never end,'' he says. ''But the women and the children need to learn Portuguese to defend themselves.'' Defend themselves?  ''If they go to shop in Redencao, they have to talk,'' he says. ''If they get sick, they cannot tell the doctor what they have.''</p>
        <p>THIRTY MILES FROM Gorotire, in the village of Aukre, another Kaiapo tribe is choosing a different strategy for change. Its best-known member is Paiakan, 37 years old, the son of Chief Tikiri.</p>
        <p>Calm and articulate, Paiakan has been named to ''keep an eye on the whites'' in the state capital of Belem. He acts as a kind of roving ambassador for the Kaiapo, even though each village is autonomous. When Kaiapo interests are threatened, he sends out warnings to the communities.</p>
        <p>Paiakan's contacts with the outside world and the many pitfalls it holds for Indians have made him more conservative, he says, more so than in the early days, in the 1970's, when he first left home to work on the Trans-Amazonian Highway. As his father's main adviser, he has insisted that Aukre remain a traditional village.</p>
        <p>It is built in the age-old circle of mud-and-thatch huts. There is no television, running water, pigs or piles of garbage. Paiakan and his father have also banned logging and gold digging. This appears to have saved Aukre from the consumerism -and widespread influenza and malaria - of Gorotire.</p>
        <p>''The lumber men have come to us with their bags of money,'' he says. ''And we know we have a lot of gold. But we do not want to bring a lot of money in. The Indian still does not know the value of white man's objects or how to treat them.'' Paiakon cites clothing as an example. ''The Indian wears something until it is stiff with dirt, then he throws it out.''</p>
        <p>But people now want things from the ''world of the whites,'' he continues. ''Pressure from the white society is so strong, there is no wall that can stop it.'' It is the task of the chief to measure the change, provide explanations, he says. ''If someone wants to get a radio or a tape recorder, the chiefs cannot stop it.''</p>
        <p>In Aukre, where two aging chiefs are still in charge of buying goods for the community, they say that they will not buy gadgets. ''We explain we cannot buy this thing for you because we do not have the batteries you need and we cannot repair it,'' Paiakan says.  Of late, Paiakan has been invited abroad to campaign for the protection of the rain forest. He knows the problem only too well. Ranchers have moved almost to the reservation's doorstep, felled trees and set massive forest fires. Because of deforestation, there have been unusual changes in the water level of the Fresco River.</p>
        <p>''Our people are getting very disoriented,'' says Paiakan. ''It would be as if people from another planet came to your cities and started to tear down your houses. The forest is our home.'' With all the destruction going on, he continues, ''the breath of life is drifting up and away from us.''</p>
        <p>AT THE AGE OF 78 and retired from teaching at the University of California at Los Angeles, the anthropologist Gerardo Reichel-Dolmatoff lives in Bogota, Colombia, and is still writing. After studying changes in the Amazon for five decades, he is not optimistic about the prospects for the Indians.</p>
        <p>''In Colombia, I don't know of a single case where an aboriginal culture has found a strong adaptive mechanism,'' he says. ''Physical survival is possible. But I have not seen the ancient values replaced by a workable value system. I wish I could be more positive. But in 50 years I have seen too many traditions being lost, too many tribes disappear.</p>
        <p>''For 500 years we have witnessed the destruction of the Indians. Now we are witnessing the destruction of the habitat. I suggest more field work, and immediate field work, because soon it will be too late.''</p>
        <p>At a conference on ethnobiology last fall, Reichel-Dolmatoff urged scientists to insist on spreading the message that Western science has much to learn from Indians, from their well-adapted lives and deeply-felt beliefs, their view that whatever man subtracts he must restore by other means.</p>
        <p>What suggestions has he made to Indians?</p>
        <p>''Indians have to stay in touch with their language -that is absolutely essential,'' he says. ''It embodies their thought patterns, their values, their philosophy.'' Moreover, he says, talented young Indians should be given a modern academic education, but also the chance to keep in touch with their people. ''They come from cultures based on extraordinary realism and imagery. They should not be forced to enter at the lowest level of our society.''</p>
        <p>One night, I ask the chiefs in Gorotire: What happens if the gold runs out? After all, most of the mahogany is already gone. Young tribesmen have wanted to invest some of the income, and the chiefs have accepted the idea. Gorotire has bought a home in Belem for Kaiapo who travel there, as well as three houses in Redencao. There is talk of buying a farm, a curious thought, perhaps, for a community that lives on eight million acres of land. But the Kaiapo, so they say, want it so that white farmers can grow rice for them.</p>
        <p>And there is talk of planting new mahogany trees. Soon the conversation turns to a bird that a tribesman explains is very important. It is the bird, he says, that spreads the mahogany seeds.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
