<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Lesson in Citizenship</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="254004"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="WESTCHESTER OPINION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LERNER, JUDY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDB133AF93BA15756C0A96F948260" item-length="651" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Lesson in Citizenship</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Judy Lerner; Judy Lerner lives in Harrison.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LERNER, JUDY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: WHAT happened last summer on our beaches and in our skies made us more aware of the vulnerability of our environment as no other event since the bombing of Hiroshima. Media exposure and the visibility of the dangers caused our reac tions to be more immediate and widespread. My own experience, in a small way, bears witness to its impact.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: WHAT happened last summer on our beaches and in our skies made us more aware of the vulnerability of our environment as no other event since the bombing of Hiroshima. Media exposure and the visibility of the dangers caused our reac tions to be more immediate and widespread. My own experience, in a small way, bears witness to its impact.</p>
        <p>WHAT happened last summer on our beaches and in our skies made us more aware of the vulnerability of our environment as no other event since the bombing of Hiroshima. Media exposure and the visibility of the dangers caused our reac tions to be more immediate and widespread. My own experience, in a small way, bears witness to its impact. I am a teacher at the Hillside Elementary School in Hastings-on-Hudson. With the encouragement of our principal and the help of other teachers I organized a Green Committee of third, fourth and fifth graders. Our purpose was to teach the children about the importance of the environment and the extent of the dangers that threatened it.</p>
        <p>Each grade designated two or more representatives to the committee, which met every two weeks during lunch to plan and discuss various projects to deal with conservation and pollution. They adopted a new Three R's program: Recycle, Re-use, Reduce.</p>
        <p>The children took to it like bees to a clover patch. They brought their bottles in by the hundreds. I felt like Pied Piper as I led them down to the local A.&amp;P. to get the nickels that they are saving to give breakfast to homeless children.</p>
        <p>Inevitably, the parents became involved. Some helped the children put out a newsletter; one issue listed household hints on how to re-use and recycle. Other parents showed them how to start a compost heap from lunchroom leftovers. A cleanup of adjoining Hillside Park was scheduled.</p>
        <p>The children learned about chlorofluoro carbons, biodegradables, the ozone, the greenhouse effect and rain forests. Junior environmentalists in the kindergarten made models of dinosaurs and other extinct species out of discarded cereal cartons.</p>
        <p>Discussions at the Green Committee meetings ranged in subject matter from the hole in the ozone to the best ways to sort out garbage for pickups. The fifth graders constructed what they called a ''horrible heap'' out of non-biodegradable Styrofoams, aerosol cans, discarded paint cans, plastic containers and other materials. The fourth graders built a model to depict the depletion of the ozone, using cartons and tinfoil.</p>
        <p>More and more children ask to come to the committee meetings. In my 25 years as a teacher I have never seen a cause blossom into a crusade like this one.</p>
        <p>The parents are organizing their own group to help the teachers. The Parent-Teacher Association contributed a grant with which we were able to purchase ''Environmental Curriculum,'' a study guide for elementary schools. Our librarian has posted an environmental bibliography. Together with the student Green Committees, the parents are planning an environmental fair. There will be Three R's booths, energy-conservation booths, posters and mobiles depicting pollution, and T-shirts inscribed ''Hillside School Green Committee.''</p>
        <p>Two fourth graders have written a song for the event. It is called ''Clean Up.'' I quote a few of the verses:  ''You've got to learn to recycle faster  To save our world from total disaster  Stop the killing of endangered species  And that will put the animals at ease.  Don't pollute the water, it kills all our fish,  Eating poison seafood is not a tasty dish.  Nuclear power leaves waste for everyone.  We could get energy from the sea and sun.''</p>
        <p>These verses are from 9-year-olds.</p>
        <p>Another fourth grader told me one day about a program he saw on television about what was happening to the rain forests in Brazil. He wanted to write a letter to President Jose Sarney to tell him that this was hurting not only Brazil, but the rest of the world as well.</p>
        <p>This boy was learning about the environment; he was also learning citizenship in its best and broadest sense, to take responsibility for the world in which he lives. To instill these values and arm the children with knowledge is the role of parent and teacher. We hope our Green Committees will point the way.</p>
        <p>WESTCHESTER OPINION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
