<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Needy People Get New Ally In Foundation</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="235143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CUMMINGS, NATHAN, FOUNDATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HALPERN, CHARLES R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TELTSCH, KATHLEEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D91738F934A15750C0A96F948260" item-length="671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Needy People Get New Ally In Foundation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHLEEN TELTSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TELTSCH, KATHLEEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Charles R. Halpern, a prominent public-interest lawyer and civil liberties advocate, has been named president of the Nathan Cummings Foundation, a family philanthropy now expanding to become one of the 75 wealthiest American foundations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Charles R. Halpern, a prominent public-interest lawyer and civil liberties advocate, has been named president of the Nathan Cummings Foundation, a family philanthropy now expanding to become one of the 75 wealthiest American foundations.</p>
        <p>Charles R. Halpern, a prominent public-interest lawyer and civil liberties advocate, has been named president of the Nathan Cummings Foundation, a family philanthropy now expanding to become one of the 75 wealthiest American foundations.</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Halpern's direction, the Manhattan-based foundation said it intended to undertake a bolder program than in the past. With increased resources now totaling $200 million, it intends to devote more funds to helping the country's underserved.</p>
        <p>''We want to attack human misery and try to make a difference with our grants,'' said Beatrice Cummings Mayer, daughter of the founder of the philanthropy and chairman of its five-member board. ''There is no topic we fear to tackle, be it family planning, drug abuse or whatever it takes to help people help themselves.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Halpern, 49 years old, was the founding dean of the City University of New York Law School at Queens College, where he developed a curriculum to train students for public-interest law to protect the environment and the rights of the indigent. Foundation Created in '49</p>
        <p>The foundation, at 885 Third Avenue, was created in 1949 by Nathan Cummings, the son of immigrants, who made a fortune building Consolidated Foods - later the Sara Lee Corporation. Before his death in 1985, the foundation's resources were $30 million. When Mr. Cummings died, he left most of his wealth to the foundation, increasing its assets to $200 million.</p>
        <p>The foundation will be providing about $10 million a year in grants. It will continue to be a family institution, with two grandchildren joining the board, along with outside members.</p>
        <p>In the past the foundation had used its income for conventional philanthropy, like grants to hospitals and museums. The choice of Mr. Halpern -made from hundreds of candidates -underscores the foundation's plans to pursue an advocacy role on behalf of the poor, the homeless and the medically underserved and to work to preserve the environment.</p>
        <p>This new strategy is significant, because the number of influential foundations playing such an advocacy role has been reduced by the closing of the Field Foundation and, earlier, the Stern Fund. Advocate for 'Underclass'</p>
        <p>John Kramer, dean of Tulane University's Law School and the last president of the Field Foundation, praised Mr. Halpern as having ''one of the most inventive legal minds in this country.'' He added: ''As the Field Foundation goes out of business, we have now a foundation that has as its focus the needs of the underclass.''</p>
        <p>Eli Evans, president of the Revson Foundation, said Mr. Halpern was joining the ranks of progressive family foundations that have been ''pioneers committed to social justice - when they found unpopular truths, they kept the nation informed and forewarned.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Halpern graduated from Harvard College and Yale Law School and practiced law in Washington before he established the Center for Law and Social Policy, a public-interest law firm in Washington. He also founded in Washington the Mental Health Law Project, which pushed for more services for the mentally ill and retarded. A Promise to Remember</p>
        <p>Financing these activities was often difficult, Mr. Halpern recalled in an interview last week. He said that as the foundation president, ''I will not forget what it feels like to be turned down.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Halpern, who has campaigned against harmful insecticides, said he could see the foundation working to counter environmental threats. ''We do not have adequate institutions now,'' he said, ''to deal with the global implications of actions such as the burning of rain forests in Brazil or the depletion of the ozone layer in Antarctica.''</p>
        <p>He said the foundation was also concerned about expanding health services for the poor and the millions of Americans not covered by medical insurance. He envisioned greater access to the arts for minority and ethnic groups.</p>
        <p>In addition the foundation plans to continue its support of Jewish cultural and educational activities.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
