<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Editorial Notebook; Crying Wolf in the Greenhouse</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="263428"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WADE, NICHOLAS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5DD1F31F930A35754C0A96F948260" item-length="601" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Editorial Notebook; Crying Wolf in the Greenhouse</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS WADE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WADE, NICHOLAS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Who could want to endure another summer like last, with drought-stricken crops, fish kills and ozone alerts? Some environmentalists, that's who. They hope it will ''galvanize political opinion'' and make Congress pass legislation to combat the greenhouse warming of the earth's atmosphere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Who could want to endure another summer like last, with drought-stricken crops, fish kills and ozone alerts? Some environmentalists, that's who. They hope it will ''galvanize political opinion'' and make Congress pass legislation to combat the greenhouse warming of the earth's atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Who could want to endure another summer like last, with drought-stricken crops, fish kills and ozone alerts? Some environmentalists, that's who. They hope it will ''galvanize political opinion'' and make Congress pass legislation to combat the greenhouse warming of the earth's atmosphere.</p>
        <p>One trouble with this calculation is its false premise. Even another sweltering summer won't mean the greenhouse warming has begun. Droughts are part of the climate's natural variability. The danger in asserting they prove greenhouse warming has arrived is obvious. Come the next cool August, Congress will assume that neither the greenhouse effect nor its proponents need be taken seriously. A plan to avert the greenhouse effect needs a firmer basis than the state of the weather. It requires persuading Washington to act on uncertain information.</p>
        <p>It's certain that carbon dioxide, the chief gas of the greenhouse effect, has been steadily accumulating in the atmosphere since the industrial revolution and the widespread burning of coal, oil and wood. And it is a matter of physics that carbon dioxide is transparent to sunlight yet absorbs the heat rising from the earth's surface. But it is far from proved that the heat thus dumped in the atmosphere has yet caused a rise in global temperatures.</p>
        <p>Many climatologists believe this is likely to happen, sooner or later. But they don't believe the half-degree of global warming in the last century can yet be attributed to the greenhouse effect. Nor do they see reliable evidence that the greenhouse warming has yet begun. Any warming will be small, at least to start with, and hence very hard to detect amid the wide natural swings in climate.</p>
        <p>James Hansen of NASA is the only climatologist to have told Congress that the greenhouse effect is already here. He is a respected scientist but on this point very few of his colleagues agree with him, as Richard Kerr noted recently in Science. The Office of Management and Budget drew criticism when it heavy-handedly made Mr. Hansen qualify testimony to Congress last month. But its caveat, that his warnings ''should be viewed as estimates from evolving computer models and not as reliable predictions,'' was scientifically impeccable. The computer models of the greenhouse effect are indeed ''evolving'' -they're somewhere around the amoeba stage.</p>
        <p>Environmental lobbyists are tempted to emphasize the threat of the greenhouse effect because it reinforces so much of their other agenda. If real, it adds a strong argument to their laudable push for energy conservation, fuel efficiency and preserving tropical forests. It also constitutes a compelling case for reinvigorating the nuclear power industry, though this is seldom mentioned.</p>
        <p>Crying wolf on greenhouse warming will not work. Nor is it necessary. There is already an international agreement to prevent further thinning of the ozone layer in the high atmosphere, even though the predicted disaster - an intenser flux of ultraviolet rays from the sun - has not yet occurred. Over the last decade, ultraviolet radiation measured at the surface of the United States has, oddly enough, decreased. If the nations of the world can act to avert the ozone-layer threat before clear proof of harm, they will presumably do the same with greenhouse.</p>
        <p>But since the remedies will be far more costly, the case for preventive action needs to be argued with care and precision. Congress won't be rolled by a summer's heat wave. The case for preventive steps against the greenhouse warming, uncertain though it still is, can better be made with the cold facts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
