<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Selfish, Sanctimonious Anti-Smokers</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="217891"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOKING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DAVIS, DAVID SCOTT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">OP-ED</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DF153CF934A15752C0A96F948260" item-length="690" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Selfish, Sanctimonious Anti-Smokers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Scott Davis; David Scott Davis, a sociologist, works for a New York consulting firm. He says he is legally bound not to disclose whether the firm consults for the tobacco industry.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DAVIS, DAVID SCOTT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Recently, I boarded a flight from Boston to New York. As I sat down, the attendant announced that the flight was scheduled to take less than two hours (it actually took four hours) and consequently ''in accord with Federal Aviation Association regulations this is a nonsmoking flight.'' A large number of the passengers cheered and applauded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Recently, I boarded a flight from Boston to New York. As I sat down, the attendant announced that the flight was scheduled to take less than two hours (it actually took four hours) and consequently ''in accord with Federal Aviation Association regulations this is a nonsmoking flight.'' A large number of the passengers cheered and applauded.</p>
        <p>Recently, I boarded a flight from Boston to New York. As I sat down, the attendant announced that the flight was scheduled to take less than two hours (it actually took four hours) and consequently ''in accord with Federal Aviation Association regulations this is a nonsmoking flight.'' A large number of the passengers cheered and applauded.</p>
        <p>There was something so sanctimonious about this outburst that I spent the remainder of the flight trying to understand why. I concluded that I had witnessed a self-righteous exhibition of moral superiority. This is not something most people, in these days of subjective moral values, have much opportunity to do. However, smoking has now become a sin, so opposing it has taken on a sanctioned and religious quality.</p>
        <p>If one were to ask these smug passengers why they had reacted as they did, they would probably reply in either of two ways. They might say they were applauding a new regulation that removed from their presence a noxious substance from which they had no escape. Or they might answer that they were demonstrating their pleasure at not having to be involuntarily exposed to something they believe would injure their health.</p>
        <p>If we examined such motivations and the principles beneath them, we would see their specious reasoning involved and their virtuous hypocrisy revealed.</p>
        <p>I, for one, am extremely sickened by the smell of certain colognes and perfumes. In close quarters - a plane, for example - they can cause me great distress. The same can be said for crying babies, dirty men and fat people. Like cigarette smoking, many of these conditions involve an element of choice. Yet I believe that there would not be the same reaction if the flight attendant announced that ''in accord with F.A.A. regulations this is a non-Old Spice flight.''</p>
        <p>''Well,'' some of these Pharisees may reply, ''Old Spice won't give me lung cancer.'' Leaving aside the question of whether being on the same airplane for two hours with a smoker causes lung cancer in nonsmokers, it is still obvious that cigarettes are being unfairly singled out as a special case. If we follow the logic of the anti-smoker, it would make equal sense to screen out any person who has a contagious disease. People with colds, the flu, tuberculosis and pink eye would simply not be allowed to board. I would applaud that because I know those people threaten my health in the close confines of a cabin.</p>
        <p>Clearly, the underlying problem is that when people choose to fly, they are voluntarily exposing themselves to all kinds of unpleasant and possibly harmful noises, odors and essences.</p>
        <p>But still we are left with this curious phenomenon of venom directed at cigarette smoke alone. The choice to smoke cigarettes has taken on a moral component that the choice to wear some revolting perfume has not. The people that applaud the ''nonsmoking flight'' are applauding themselves in a sickening display of self-congratulation. There is a certain elitism in the antismoking movement, something that underlies most moral crusades. Undeniably, there are very serious health problems associated with smoking. Yet, for many people, smoking may be one of the few pleasures they experience. Increasingly, those people are members of the working class.</p>
        <p>Those who oppose smoking are not. They are people with the time and money to go out jogging every day, and belong to health clubs. They have their subscriptions to Consumer Reports, and every evening eat a nutritionally well-balanced meal. They also administer, manage, own, invest in and support industries that are destroying the ozone layer, polluting our oceans, decimating our forests and soiling our cities. It is, of course, much harder to do something about these than to complain about someone smoking on the other side of a restaurant.</p>
        <p>Given the enormous amount of knowledge of the health risks associated with smoking, should people be denied the right to decide for themselves that the benefits outweigh the risks? Instead, it appears that we place more importance on the gratification that certain people derive from denying others the gratification of smoking.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
