<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Governments Start Preparing for Global Warming Disasters</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="300979"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GASES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEAT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFDF143EF937A25752C1A96F948260" item-length="2773" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Governments Start Preparing for Global Warming Disasters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IN the quickening international debate over global warming, the spotlight has played mostly on the question of how and whether to control the growing emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases that trap heat in the atmosphere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IN the quickening international debate over global warming, the spotlight has played mostly on the question of how and whether to control the growing emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases that trap heat in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>IN the quickening international debate over global warming, the spotlight has played mostly on the question of how and whether to control the growing emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases that trap heat in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Now another concern is starting to come to the fore as well. No matter what action is taken, some scientists say, there are already enough of these ''greenhouse'' gases in the atmosphere to cause a major warming, and more are certain to accumulate before the buildup can be halted.</p>
        <p>As a result, climatologists, social scientists, planners and government officials are beginning to focus on how society might adapt to rising sea levels, shifting agricultural zones, changing climates and other problems that global warming would bring if it occurs on a significant scale.</p>
        <p>Already, state and local governments along the coast of the United States are starting to plan for a possible long-term rise in the sea level, and a few have taken action to cope with it. In the Netherlands, planning is well advanced for an expansion of that country's system of dikes, dunes and other coastal defenses, and the Dutch are also offering their expertise to Indonesia and the Maldives.</p>
        <p>Agricultural researchers are stepping up efforts to develop heat-resistant and drought-resistant crops that might gradually replace traditional crops if the climate changes.</p>
        <p>And the electric power industry in America is planning how to meet the increase in the demand for power for air-conditioning that would surely result from global warming. In one of the first studies, the Electric Power Research Institute has calculated that for every 1.8 degrees Fahrenheit in climatic warming, power demand in the summer would rise 2 to 3 percent in the New York metropolitan area - enough to have a sizable effect on the region's limited generating capacity.</p>
        <p>These stirrings are somewhat tentative, both because of uncertainty about the whole question of global warming and because of a tendency on the part of some environmentalists and politicians to play down the question of adaptation for fear it will divert attention from what they see as an overriding need to limit production of the greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>But reining them in is bound to be difficult. The world economy runs on fossil fuels, and burning these fuels generates increasing amounts of carbon dioxide, the most important greenhouse gas. Weaning the world away from them is likely to be a long and costly business. For developing countries especially, fossil fuels are tightly linked to prospects for development and a better life for their peoples, leaving those countries reluctant to give up the fuels.</p>
        <p>As the difficulty of reducing greenhouse emissions has come home, the focus has shifted somewhat ''from prevention to a focus on adaptation,'' said Michael H. Glantz of the National Center for Atmospheric Research in Boulder, Colo. Dr. Glantz, a social scientist, heads a group that studies the impact of climatic change on societies. And while a number of environmentalists, scientists and officials continue to believe that the first priority should be a reduction of emissions of greenhouse gases, some are now saying that adaptation must be considered as well.</p>
        <p>In a report to President Bush earlier this year, the National Academy of Sciences argued that adaptive measures should be assigned a high priority. ''We are already irrevocably committed to major global change in the years ahead,'' the report said, expressing the view prevalent among climatologists. ''The elevated concentrations of greenhouse gases produced to date by human activities will persist for many centuries and will slowly change the climate of the earth, regardless of our actions.''</p>
        <p>Still, although many scientists agree on the broad outlines of global climate change, the system is so complex they cannot predict exactly how great the change will be or when and how it will affect specific regions.</p>
        <p>This uncertainty means that in planning for a broad range of long-term activities like coastal development, construction of ports, location of waste-disposal sites, water projects and agricultural enterprises, flexibility is crucial, the academy told Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>In studying and planning for the expected impact of global warming, the Environmental Protection Agency is emphasizing this need for flexibility. ''You've got to leave yourself leeway,'' said John Hoffman, the director of the agency's global change division.</p>
        <p>The planning options for industrialized countries, with all their resources, are numerous, the academy's report said. But that is not the case for many developing countries. For instance, a one-meter rise in sea level, which some experts consider likely by the end of the next century, would cover broad areas of Bangladesh, Indonesia and Southeast Asia holding some of the world's largest populations and richest agricultural lands. Those countries, experts say, simply do not have the resources to deal with such a disaster.</p>
        <p>Some experts, moreover, express concern that the industrialized countries, following a well-documented human tendency, will not take adaptive action until disaster is near, when it may be too late.  The Science  Complexity Makes Prediction Chancy</p>
        <p>In the greenhouse effect, energy from the sun is trapped in the earth's atmosphere by carbon dioxide, methane, chlorofluorocarbons and other trace gases. The more gases, the more heat is trapped.</p>
        <p>Carbon dioxide, the principal greenhouse gas, is emitted by the burning of fossil fuels. Scientists say atmospheric concentrations of all these gases combined have increased from about 280 parts per million of carbon dioxide at the start of the industrial age almost 200 years ago to the equivalent of 400 parts per million today. At the present rate of increase, scientists say that the level will grow to 570 parts per million, more than double the pre-industrial level, possibly as early as 2030.</p>
        <p>Scientists calculating from mathematical models of the earth's atmosphere say this doubling could cause the atmosphere to warm by 3 to 8 degrees Fahrenheit. By comparison, the atmosphere has warmed by about 9 degrees since the end of the last ice age. But climatic and atmospheric change is so complex that there is great uncertainty about the predictive accuracy of the models.</p>
        <p>How long it will take for maximum warming to be reached is uncertain because the oceans slow such warming. Most scientists expect the maximum warming to take place by the second half of the next century.</p>
        <p>If change is slow enough, the Environmental Protection Agency said earlier this year in a report to Congress, adaptation may be manageable. But a sudden or rapid change, it said, might make it problematic.  Sea-Level Rise  Defending Coasts Is a Concern</p>
        <p>A rise in sea level is ''one of the most certain impacts of climate change,'' the agency said in its report to Congress. Higher global temperatures would probably cause glaciers to melt, as well as leading to an expansion of the oceans because warm water occupies a larger volume of space than cold water. If levels of greenhouse gases in the atmosphere double, sea levels will rise; estimates of the average rise are from 1.5 feet to 6.5 feet. Some leading experts regard a rise of 1 meter, a little more than three feet, as most likely. They expect it to occur gradually in the next century, affecting coastal areas where about a billion people, a quarter of the world's population, now live.</p>
        <p>In adapting to global warming, ''the primary issue is coastal defense,'' said Michael Oppenheimer, a senior scientist with the Environmental Defense Fund. ''Planning for sea-level rise must be done decades in advance of the actual unfolding of the consequences. If you're going to protect such areas with seawalls, or carry out a careful retreat of populations, which will be inevitable in some cases, or protect houses, those are measures that must be planned many decades ahead of time.''</p>
        <p>Gjerrit P. Hekstra, an ecologist in the environmental protection branch of the government of the Netherlands, said defending a settled coastline or coastal city from rising seas requires ''a complete restructuring of your hydrological infrastructure - ship channels, dikes, canals, rivers, everything.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Hekstra's country has been doing that for many decades, and the experience of the Netherlands may prove instructional for much of the rest of the world. For the Dutch, adapting to a sea-level rise means simply an expansion of the elaborate, modern coastal defense system it has developed in the last 30 years. Government studies have shown that to protect the country from a sea-level rise of 1 meter will require an investment, over the long term, of up to $10 billion. The Netherlands has already spent $15 billion on coastal defense in the last three decades.</p>
        <p>Coastal defense means building dikes and piling up sand on the coast to strengthen dunes and sculpting rivers and canals to keep sea water from penetrating the soil and ruining both fresh water supplies and agricultural land. Dr. Hekstra said it is his opinion as a private ecologist that all this is well within existing technology and requires only money.</p>
        <p>''So I don't think your country and my country is the real problem,'' he said. That is not to minimize the problem, he said, since the United States would have to spend billions of dollars to defend coastal cities and developments against a one-meter rise in sea level and might well have to abandon some low-lying regions altogether.</p>
        <p>''We can cope,'' Dr. Hekstra said. ''But not Indonesia, not Bangladesh, not Vietnam. They don't have the resources to do it. Who's going to pay the bill for the developing countries?'' In the United States, the E.P.A. has made extensive studies of the effect of a rise in the sea level, and most coastal states are beginning to plan for it. Questions being examined include not only coastal defense but matters like beach erosion and the intrusion of salt water into rivers and bays where it would foul drinking-water supplies. Possible solutions to salt-water intrusion include the construction of barrier dams in estuaries and canals to divert the salt water from drinking water intakes. Close attention is also being paid to the control of hazardous-waste disposal sites in areas likely to flood.</p>
        <p>Most of the efforts are in early stages. But ''I haven't talked to a single coastal state that isn't doing some hard thinking about this and where the government is starting to put together some plans,'' said Thomas W. Curtis, the director of the natural resources group of the National Governors' Association.</p>
        <p>South Carolina, North Carolina, Maine and Florida, with sea-level rise in mind, have all enacted standards designed to control construction on their shorelines.  Water Resources  Shortages Likely For California</p>
        <p>Some predictions of climate change, admittedly chancy, forecast drier conditions for much of the American West, with serious consequences for a region where water scarcity is already a major factor of life and prosperity. The E.P.A. study for Congress, for instance, found that California's water demand could increase, even as water supplies decrease. The decrease would come about partly because more snow would melt in the winter and less in the summer. Since reservoirs do not have the capacity to store all the winter runoff, spring and summer water supplies would drop.</p>
        <p>Experts say that a number of adaptive measures could help in such a situation. These could be as simple as lining irrigation systems so that less water is wasted or expensive solutions like building larger reservoirs or even such a harsh measure, should water become scarce enough, as imposing high prices on it.</p>
        <p>''Despite a growing awareness of the problem, the institutions involved in managing our water resources are not really taking account of the greenhouse effect,'' said Peter H. Gleick, director of the global environment program of the Pacific Institute for Studies in Development, Environment and Security, a nonprofit research institute in Berkeley, Calif.</p>
        <p>''The difficulty is that we don't know how precipitation patterns are going to change,'' said Dr. Oppenheimer of the Environmental Defense Fund. This, he said, underscores the limitations of adaptation.  Agriculture  Crop Adaptation Seems Promising</p>
        <p>No more critical activity stands to be profoundly affected by global warming than agriculture, but scientists also consider it one of the most adaptable.</p>
        <p>Almost all the crops now grown in the United States, for example, originally came from some other part of the world and were adapted to this continent.</p>
        <p>Building on this tradition, the Federal Department of Agriculture is preparing to ease the way for whatever transplants might be required by global warming. Jim Duke, an economic botanist at the department's research center in Beltsville, Md., has been collecting data for some years on the temperature and rainfall conditions in which 1,000 agricultural plants flourish. He is now preparing to use this data in mathematical models of climate, which would tell what crops would adapt best if, for instance, New York's average temperature rose three degrees and its rainfall also increased.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. report to Congress said that warming might force abandonment of 10 to 50 percent of the Southeast's agricultural acreage.</p>
        <p>''We might lose the conventional crops'' in the Southeast, said Dr. Duke. ''But assuming we didn't go dry, we would bring in semitropical crops. It's just a matter of selecting variety. We could bring in a wealth of tropical fruits and vegetables.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, agricultural researchers around the world have long been striving, through both genetic and cultivation techniques, to make many crops more adaptable to harsh environments. Gary Evans, a special assistant for global change issues at the Department of Agriculture, said, ''We are augmenting most of our current plant-stress programs with an eye to what would take place if temperature or moisture shifted.''</p>
        <p>Researchers are also striking out in new directions with important implications for adaptation to global warming. At the University of Arizona, for instance, researchers led by Carl N. Hodges are experimenting with getting plants to grow in sea water. If they succeed, the technique could save fresh water in arid areas near oceans.</p>
        <p>In Israel's Negev Desert, a team led by Yosef Misrahi of Ben Gurion University of the Negev is growing fruits and nuts at temperatures higher than 115 degrees. In the same area, the Jewish National Fund, the Israeli agency in charge of forestry and land conservation, is experimenting with a genetically improved species of loblolly pine, using seedlings donated by the Georgia-Pacific Corporation. Much of this sort of research is directly related to the prospect of global warming.  Prospects  Seeds of Change In Hurricane</p>
        <p>Even before Hurricane Hugo, Charleston, S.C., was attuned to two of the major effects scientists expect from global warming: a rising sea level and more frequent and more potent hurricanes. It had already required new buildings near the shore to be built far enough off the ground to escape flooding, which they did in the hurricane. The city had also begun installing pumping stations to insure proper drainage, unlike the situation with sewers that work by gravity, which do not drain when rising water covers their outlets.</p>
        <p>But the hurricane certainly made a difference. ''The hurricane deepened our resolve,'' Mayor Joseph P. Riley of Charleston said, ''and made us more confident that our decisions along those lines were wise ones, and it certainly deepened our commitment to new ways of thinking and acting.''</p>
        <p>That, according to the conclusions of a study directed by Dr. Glantz of the National Center for Atmospheric Research, is how action to combat a long-term threat usually gets started. A number of case studies sponsored by the center found that a catalyst was usually necessary before governments would act. Once they did act, ad hoc responses were favored over longer-term, planned responses.</p>
        <p>These responses, the study concluded, ''have often built into the existing social structures an additional degree of rigidity'' that make it more difficult to adapt flexibly.</p>
        <p>Those charcteristics illustrate the difficulties of adaptation, Dr. Glantz said, especially in a situation so fraught with uncertainty as global warming, where the threat, however serious it ultimately proves to be, may not become readily apparent for years or even decades.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
