<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>White House Says Bush Will Call Meeting About Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="248768"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="WASHINGTON TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DB1231F933A25756C0A96F948260" item-length="680" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>White House Says Bush Will Call Meeting About Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The White House said today that President Bush would call an international meeting to consider a response to global warming and other environmental problems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The White House said today that President Bush would call an international meeting to consider a response to global warming and other environmental problems.</p>
        <p>The White House said today that President Bush would call an international meeting to consider a response to global warming and other environmental problems.</p>
        <p>The Administration, however, is divided over the advisability of seeking a treaty to address the warming problem. The White House said Monday that the President believes there is insufficient scientific data on which to base rational policy decisions.</p>
        <p>Some Administration officials, particularly in the State Department and Environmental Protection Agency, are urging that the United States take the lead in negotiating such a treaty as soon as possible because of the seriousness of the threat.</p>
        <p>Scientists believe that global temperatures will rise because increasing levels of carbon dioxide and other manmade gases will trap and retain heat from the sun in a process similar to what happens in a greenhouse. Such a warming trend could cause sea levels to rise, cause severe droughts and storms and severely disprupt the earth's biological systems. Commitment to Meeting</p>
        <p>In a meeting this morning with the Dutch Prime Minister, Ruud Lubbers, the President committed himself to convening an international meeting on the environment, Marlin Fitzwater, the White House press secretary, said at a briefing. Mr. Fitzwater said Mr. Bush would discuss such a meeting when he met with other allied leaders later this year, probably at the economic summit meeting in Paris in July.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush pledged in his election campaign last year that he would hold an international meeting to consider the problem of global warming. While it is possible that such a conference could still take place this year, the international agenda may be too crowded to find time for such a gathering by December, said Stephen Hart, another White House spokesman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hart said the President wanted a gathering of experts on the global problems but that it was not yet decided whether heads of Government would be invited to attend. In addition to global warming, other issues likely to be on the agenda are the destruction of the earth's protective ozone layer by industrial chemicals, and acid rain.</p>
        <p>The President's pledge to call an international environmental conference comes amid growing criticism in Congress that he has failed to assert leadership on the threat of global warming. No Treaty Recommendations</p>
        <p>At an international meeting on the greenhouse effect now under way in Geneva, the United States, which heads a panel on potential policies to deal with global warming, is making no recommendations for action on a treaty, government officials here said.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. and its Administrator, William K. Reilly, as well as officials in the Department of State, have said that the United States should be in the vanguard in seeking international action to help lessen the expected warming trend and in planning for mitigating the effects of such change.</p>
        <p>The environmental agency has been arguing that the evidence is clear that a buildup of carbon dioxide and other gases in the atmosphere produce the greenhouse effect and that there is growing consensus that a long-term warming trend and severe climate change is inevitable. While many details on the nature and scope of the changes are still to be determined, prudent policy demands that some actions be taken now before it is too late to limit the damage, agency officials insist.</p>
        <p>But others in the Administration, including the budget office, the White House science adviser's office, the domestic policy staff and the Energy and Agriculture Departments, are arguing that more needs to be learned about the implications of a global treaty for domestic policy, including its potential effect on the economy.</p>
        <p>William R. Graham, the President's science adviser, said that while there is a theory that prudent steps could be taken now to meet the global warming threat, he subscribed to a second theory that ''we should have regulations be a consequence of what we understand and be determined by a knowledge of the consequences of regulating or not regulating.''  WASHINGTON TALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
