<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beware the Winged Tyrant</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="249996"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INSECTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KUNSTLER, JAMES HOWARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7DA1030F937A25756C0A96F948260" item-length="1192" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beware the Winged Tyrant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES HOWARD KUNSTLER; JAMES HOWARD KUNSTLER, who lives in upstate New York, is a novelist whose most recent book is ''Thunder Island'' (Bantam).</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KUNSTLER, JAMES HOWARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ANYONE who has ventured into the bosky back country in our part of the world - the Northeast - knows how easily the Garden of Eden can turn into Monster Island. All it takes is bugs. For instance, I recall 30 years ago as a child being jammed under a big old Army tent with 27 other campers on a witheringly hot and rainy night in the New Hampshire woods.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ANYONE who has ventured into the bosky back country in our part of the world - the Northeast - knows how easily the Garden of Eden can turn into Monster Island. All it takes is bugs. For instance, I recall 30 years ago as a child being jammed under a big old Army tent with 27 other campers on a witheringly hot and rainy night in the New Hampshire woods.</p>
        <p>ANYONE who has ventured into the bosky back country in our part of the world - the Northeast - knows how easily the Garden of Eden can turn into Monster Island. All it takes is bugs. For instance, I recall 30 years ago as a child being jammed under a big old Army tent with 27 other campers on a witheringly hot and rainy night in the New Hampshire woods. Roused from slumber out of a sleeping bag that felt like a steam bath, I chanced to shine my flashlight on the tent's ceiling. It appeared to be covered with thousands of tiny potatoes - little beige things - that presently began to move to and fro on hair-like legs, perhaps in response to the light. When I brought this curious phenomenon to the attention of my comrade, a scene ensued straight out of ''Riot in Cell Block D.''</p>
        <p>This may be slightly beside the point because the loathsome creatures in question that night were only harmless daddy-longleg spiders. What really spoils the fun out of doors are biting flies of the order Diptera, mosquitoes and their lesser-known cohorts. However, I wouldn't have been parboiling in that sleeping bag if it hadn't been for the ravening mosquitoes and hence wouldn't have awakened to those spiders in the dead of night and incited a riot.</p>
        <p>Of the little winged tyrants who rule the summer glades, the deerfly (Chrysops niger) may be the most diabolical. Commonly, this pest - which looks like a housefly with banded wings - goes into orbit around your head like a miniature satellite. Once a deerfly finds you, it is like finding a friend for life. Round and round your head it goes, dogging your every step, until you are slaphappy from hitting yourself about the skull.</p>
        <p>The question naturally arises, what did the Deity have in mind when creating these varmints? Fish food? As an angler, I can assure you that fish will just as readily eat all sorts of benign matter from pickeled pork rind to dough balls to kernels of canned corn.</p>
        <p>If it is hard to find a theological justification for the existence of deerflies, science can at least explain their behavior.</p>
        <p>''These are very visually oriented flies; they are attracted to movement,'' said John Burger, a professor of entymology at the University of New Hampshire and a leading expert on biting flies. ''They tend to circle around a moving object, taking in all sorts of chemical cues coming from you - moisture, carbon dioxide, volatile oils coming off our skin. These will tell them whether you are suitable to start feeding on.''</p>
        <p>O.K., but even in the insect world there must be some premium on intelligence. A fly that can't tell the difference between me and a white-tailed deer in less than a quarter of an hour doesn't deserve to survive another generation.</p>
        <p>''What you're seeing is probably a very large number of flies over a period of time, not the same one,'' Dr. Burger said. ''These things are very purposeful. They'll make three or four passes, staying close to your head, maybe even bouncing off.'' Why do they bounce off?  ''Basically, they're kind of clumsy,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Unlike the mosquito, with its syringelike proboscis, the deerfly's mouth is equipped with tiny razors.</p>
        <p>''Under the microscope they look like great big sword blades,'' Dr. Burger said. ''Some have serrated edges. Some have little hooklike things for anchoring the mouth parts into the bite. Basically what they do is punch a hole in you.''</p>
        <p>Homo sapiens do not make good hosts for deerflies because they don't hold still. Swatting is a limited defense at best, since wild hand motions only have the unfortunate side effect of attracting more deerflies.</p>
        <p>Bug repellent is also of limited value against them, the term repellant being something of a misnomer. Strictly speaking, the flies are not actually repelled. Rather, the chemicals jam their radar so that they lose the ability to locate you. The deerfly's blundering ways appear to be something of an advantage here, allowing it to keep tabs on a victim by accidentally bumping into him.</p>
        <p>Equally obnoxious, especially to anglers, is the hated black fly, whose prime season coincides with the best weeks of trout fishing in the Northeast - mid-May to early June. The black fly is much smaller than the deerfly and tends to attack in swarms.</p>
        <p>I recall one feckless Memorial Day weekend years ago when I drove for hours to go trout fishing on a famous North Country river. I wasn't out of the car for two minutes before the black flies found me, and by the time I rigged up a rod, my face looked like a pomegranate.</p>
        <p>The black fly's mouth contains razor-sharp mandibles like the deerfly's, and its manner of feeding is similar. It locates its victims by sensing traces of carbon dioxide from exhalation.</p>
        <p>This being the case, can you escape them by holding your breath?</p>
        <p>I put the question to Daniel Molloy, a scientist studying black fly control at a research station run by the New York State Museum in Washington County.</p>
        <p>''Once they're close, holding your breath will only result in your death,'' Dr. Molloy replied thoughtfully.</p>
        <p>In North America there are no known diseases that are spread to humans by black flies, though they carry a type of malaria that can be lethal to turkeys, ducks and geese. Individual black flies and deerflies can live as long as a couple of months and will mate and lay eggs repeatedly before expiring. It is only the females that bite, drinking blood after mating to have enough protein in their bodies to generate eggs. The males, meanwhile, survive by sipping nectar and lead lives of comparative indolence.</p>
        <p>Deerflies and black flies work the day shift in a world that never sleeps. When shadows steal across the lawns and the sound of cocktail shakers is heard through the gloaming, out comes the night shift, the mosquitoes and punkies.</p>
        <p>Enough has been said about mosquitoes in the annals of the outdoors. Punkies, or no-see-ums (Culicoides), are easily overlooked. At about two-tenths of a millimeter, punkies can easily fly through the mesh of ordinary household screening and, unlike mosquitos, punkies are attracted by light, making them particularly irksome to the screened-in porch crowd.</p>
        <p>It might seem hard to believe that such winged insects can inflict a painful bite, yet their mouth parts are similar to those of deerflies and black flies, and all they have to do is hit a nerve ending to be equally annoying.</p>
        <p>There are four or five species of punky that specialize in humans - others bite birds and animals - but the worst ones are denizens of the Atlantic salt marshes, Culicoides furens.</p>
        <p>''One time I was down at Assateague Island, Va.,'' Dr. Burger reminisced, ''and there were a lot of people on the beach. The sun was starting to go down. You could always tell when the punkies came out because all of a sudden everybody would start running around grabbing their stuff, and tearing off for their cars. It was like a mass exodus. In five minutes the beach would be deserted.'' Next time you're down at the seashore and would like a little more privacy, try this phrase in a moderately forceful tone of voice: ''Say, hon, is the air full of poppyseeds, or did the punkies just come out?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
