<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ON YOUR OWN: Fitness; Scientist Building A Better Stress Test</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="243302"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXERCISE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TESTS AND TESTING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STOCKTON, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ZOHMAN, LENORE R (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exercise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DB163CF937A15757C0A96F948260" item-length="929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ON YOUR OWN: Fitness; Scientist Building A Better Stress Test</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Stockton</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STOCKTON, WILLIAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE exercise stress test, in which you exercise on a treadmill while a doctor watches your heart's response on an electrocardiograph, is a time-consuming and expensive procedure. A cardiologist's bill for the test and its interpretation can easily exceed $300.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE exercise stress test, in which you exercise on a treadmill while a doctor watches your heart's response on an electrocardiograph, is a time-consuming and expensive procedure. A cardiologist's bill for the test and its interpretation can easily exceed $300.</p>
        <p>THE exercise stress test, in which you exercise on a treadmill while a doctor watches your heart's response on an electrocardiograph, is a time-consuming and expensive procedure. A cardiologist's bill for the test and its interpretation can easily exceed $300.</p>
        <p>There is a school of thought that says the test is a waste of time and money for someone about to undertake a fitness program, unless something is clearly wrong medically. There is no guarantee it will detect heart disease, and a cardiologist can learn just as much by listening to the heart and taking an electrocardiogram with the patient at rest and asking some intelligent questions.</p>
        <p>Still, the test is popular among those in their 30's and beyond who exercise, because it lets a specialist watch a heart beat under a stressful workload and might reveal an abnormality that could otherwise go undetected until something serious happened one day on a run in the park.</p>
        <p>This debate about the exercise stress test is unlikely to end soon.</p>
        <p>But Lenore R. Zohman, who is a professor of cardiology and rehabilitation medicine at Albert Einstein College of Medicine in the Bronx, has been studying how to speed up the test, cut its cost and thus make it more widely available. Her idea is to devise a battery of diagnostic procedures, of which the stress test is the centerpiece and could be used to screen people who exercise or want to begin a fitness program.</p>
        <p>Patients would take the stress test, undergo an orthopedic evaluation for joint, bone and tendon problems, have their percent of body fat measured and take a respiratory test.</p>
        <p>She has now put several hundred people - ranging from high school athletes to business executives -through the mass screening program at her laboratory at the Montefiore Medical Center and believes she has hit upon something with promise. She has charged these people, who have gone through the program in groups, about $60 each.</p>
        <p>The mass-screening approach begins with an extensive medical-history questionnaire. If any problems are present, the person is automatically excluded from the test. In a private doctor's office setting, the test might go forward under the careful scrutiny of the doctor. But here, where the emphasis is on speed, volume and low cost, the questionnaire becomes an important screening tool to help avoid testing those who should have more individual attention.</p>
        <p>The center of Dr. Zohman's program is the treadmill routine itself, which she has shortened from the cardiologist's standard protocol of about 15 minutes to a demanding session of about five minutes. In the standard protocol, the steepness of the treadmill incline on which you first walk and then run up is slowly increased to a steeper grade and a higher speed every three minutes until you can go no further. In Dr. Zohman's test, the speed and steepness go up every minute until you are exercising as much as you can.</p>
        <p>Dr. Zohman believes that the data obtained about the heart in this rapid test are just as revealing as those obtained in the 15-minute test.</p>
        <p>''We've shown that you can arrive at the same endpoint using the faster protocol,'' she said recently as I stood on her treadmill waiting to take the test. Electrocardiograph leads had been taped to my chest, and I wore a nose clip so that all the air I breathed in and out through a mouthpiece would be analyzed and recorded by a computer.</p>
        <p>The test began easily enough, but the minutes clicked by and the incline quickly became steep. By the third stage, the incline was difficult and a walking pace no longer sufficed. At five minutes, my breath was coming in labored gasps and the incline was 20 degrees and the speed 5.5 miles per hour.</p>
        <p>When they administer the test, Dr. Zohman and her assistant give their subjects guidelines about how far to run before stopping. They don't want someone to overdo it. However, they considered me to be in good shape, so they deliberately withheld cues about the progress of the test. There was no encouragement to keep on despite the raw feeling in my windpipe from the air being desperately sucked in with each breath. Nor was there any encouragement to stop.</p>
        <p>When I was finally overcome by a feeling of total exhaustion, I straddled the moving belt and the test came to an end at 5 minutes 32 seconds. The treadmill incline was slowly lowered as a cooldown walk brought the body back to normal.</p>
        <p>The most startling number to emerge from the test, however, did not reflect my fitness level as much as it did the grueling nature of the accelerated test. At 4:01 into the test, I began to exhale more carbon dioxide than the oxygen I was taking in, a point in exercise known as the anerobic threshold. It is the point at which the exercise has become so strenuous that the respiratory system cannot supply all the body's oxygen needs.</p>
        <p>This means that any oxygen still reaching the muscle cells must come from oxygen already in the blood. The ability to continue exercise is very nearly at an end. Within seconds, a minute or two at most, the body will be physically unable to go on.</p>
        <p>The computer printout told the story of what arriving at this state meant. I had lasted 5:32 and my maximum heart rate hit 169, from a resting rate of 44. Blood pressure at the most stressful point was 220/90, a reading that was perfectly normal. I managed to continue past the anerobic threshold another 91 seconds before exhaustion. Not bad for middle age. But the most uplifting finding was what the electrocardiogram trace revealed at the point of peak stress: a normal heartbeat.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
