<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Language; Diluting the Awe By Some</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="276939"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENGLISH LANGUAGE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENTHAL, JACK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6D7133AF933A1575BC0A96F948260" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Language; Diluting the Awe By Some</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY JACK ROSENTHAL; Jack Rosenthal is editorial page editor of The New York Times. William Safire is on vacation.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENTHAL, JACK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE GREENHOUSE effect may or may not be heating up the atmosphere, but there is no doubt the human propensity for hot words is raising the temperature of language.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE GREENHOUSE effect may or may not be heating up the atmosphere, but there is no doubt the human propensity for hot words is raising the temperature of language.</p>
        <p>THE GREENHOUSE effect may or may not be heating up the atmosphere, but there is no doubt the human propensity for hot words is raising the temperature of language.</p>
        <p>A firestorm, for instance, is no mere conflagration. The term describes a vast, intense fire initiated by, say, a nuclear explosion; a great rising column of heated air sucks in violent winds and rain. It was understood that way at the end of World War II, after monumental destruction in places like Dresden and Hiroshima.</p>
        <p>Not anymore. What's a firestorm by 1989 standards?</p>
        <p>There have been a dozen just in the first few months of the Bush Administration. What did the President unleash when he nominated John G. Tower to be Secretary of Defense? Not simply a flap, a controversy, an uproar or even a storm of opposition. Again and again, commentators strained to commit verbal arson.</p>
        <p>The proposed Congressional pay raise, Mr. Bush himself said, produced a firestorm. A new European abortion drug, The Christian Science Monitor reported, produced a firestorm. A proposed fee on savings and loan deposits, Newsday noted, produced a you-guessed-it. So did Mr. Bush's choice for chief diplomat for Latin America. So did a proposed Medicare surtax. So did the decision of the Corcoran Gallery to cancel a controversial exhibit. By July, the propensity for arson had spread to the cover of U.S. News &amp; World Report: ''The High Court Ignites a Flag-Burning Firestorm.''</p>
        <p>Even this degradation of a powerful term for cataclysm seems mild by comparison with the fate of a still-more-solemn term: holocaust. It refers to a fiery destruction of life so total as to require almost reverential use. Some discipline remains concerning the Holocaust - Hitler's effort to exterminate a people. But there's no such discipline concerning small-h holocausts.</p>
        <p>What Brazil is doing to its Amazon forests surely qualifies for the word. But does the house fire in New Jersey, reported on television news, in which four people died? A year ago, the Mayor of Bethlehem had reason to be shaken when King Hussein of Jordan decided to cut off support to the West Bank. But was he right to say, ''This is really a holocaust''?</p>
        <p>What may be the most tasteless all-time perversion of the word was reported last January by Ronald Smothers of The Times, in a story about Jim and Tammy Bakker, the high-living television preachers trying to make a comeback after their public disgrace. Jim Bakker said to a television audience: ''If Jim and Tammy can survive their holocaust of two years, I know God will help you to survive.''</p>
        <p>That may be the worst, but it surely won't be the last degradation, because such verbal excess springs from stronger pressure than tastelessness. The tendency to hyperbole arises from a desire for expressivity that seems universal in all times and all tongues.</p>
        <p>Semantic bleaching is what linguistic scholars call it. Speakers, eager for emphasis, seize on interesting words that have not yet lost their power to overuse, until the new verbal currency is itself cheapened, in an inexorable lingual inflation.</p>
        <p>The process was described in 1912 in an article, ''The Evolution of Grammatical Forms,'' by a French linguist, Antoine Meillet, and examples stretch back centuries.</p>
        <p>Not is an example offered by Gary B. Holland, a historical linguist at the University of California in Berkeley. People can't ever be negative enough, he observes. Hence the old negative na became supplemented by wiht, roughly equivalent to the modern ''No way!'' Under frequent use, the Old English na wiht turned into not.</p>
        <p>New English illustrates the same pressure for expressiveness with words like awfully, terribly and frightfully. They once conveyed much the same horror as firestorm or holocaust. Steady hyped-up use has bleached out the horror. They have become bland, ritualistic modifiers, no more frightful than frightfully sorry.</p>
        <p>Teachers, writers and editors concerned for endangered semantic species may mourn the degeneration of this generation's words of horror. They may even slow it by preaching against reckless verbal extravagance. But they won't stop it, for language is change, and the impulse to be emphatic is one of the engines.  Dial P for Press</p>
        <p>IF SOME ASPECTS OF language change, others have not. Consider the problem of the telephone verb.</p>
        <p>Many rotary phones are still in use, but in urban America, touch-tone number pads have become ubiquitous. The change speeds up calls and opens the way to computer applications. It also creates a small mystery (Why do the numbers on touch-tone phones start at the top but the numbers on calculators start at the bottom?) and an enduring question: What verb properly describes the act of initiating a telephone call?</p>
        <p>A story in The Times last winter was titled, ''Let the Dialer Beware: A New Pay Phone Era.'' Dialer? To say ''dial'' seems as obsolete as ''ring me.'' Yet what do people say instead?</p>
        <p>Press is what the automated voice instructs ''if you know the extension of the person you wish to reach.'' If it's room service you want, push is what some hotel guides counsel. In conversation, people sometimes also say punch, hit or enter.</p>
        <p>But an informal canvass discloses that the overwhelming verb of choice is still dial. It's not merely a neutral term for a mechanical act. The word, the act and the associations have entered the language and the culture.</p>
        <p>In an age of all-digit dialing, the letters on the telephone keys are also obsolete - except that customers clamor for numbers that spell rememberable words. (A radio jingle for an all-night drugstore in Boston still echoes in memory: ''How many cookies could Andrew eat? ANdrew 8-8000.'') Try to imagine a thriller movie titled, ''Dial 6 for Murder.''</p>
        <p>Dial may be an anachronism, but it's probably here to stay.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
