<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The New Priorities in the Solar System</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="278693"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D81E3FF934A1575BC0A96F948260" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The New Priorities in the Solar System</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <dateline>PASADENA, Calif.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: WHEN they ponder their good fortune to be living and working here and now, planetary scientists sometimes speak of this as the golden age in the exploration of the solar system. Planets once no more than points of light have finally been visited by spacecraft and photographed in striking detail. For the first time, they have emerged as distinct and varied worlds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: WHEN they ponder their good fortune to be living and working here and now, planetary scientists sometimes speak of this as the golden age in the exploration of the solar system. Planets once no more than points of light have finally been visited by spacecraft and photographed in striking detail. For the first time, they have emerged as distinct and varied worlds.</p>
        <p>WHEN they ponder their good fortune to be living and working here and now, planetary scientists sometimes speak of this as the golden age in the exploration of the solar system. Planets once no more than points of light have finally been visited by spacecraft and photographed in striking detail. For the first time, they have emerged as distinct and varied worlds.</p>
        <p>With Voyager 2's encounter with Neptune last week, the era of first-look reconnaissance has come to a successful climax. All the known planets, except Pluto, have now been surveyed up close. In its 12-year journey of 4.4 billion miles, Voyager 2 visited all the outer gaseous giants: Jupiter, Saturn and Uranus as well as Neptune.</p>
        <p>As the hardy spacecraft headed for interstellar space, scientists and engineers could turn their attention to places deemed worthy of a second look. The emphasis in planetary exploration is thus shifting from reconnaissance to a new era of prolonged and systematic investigation. ''This year is the beginning of the next generation in the American planetary program,'' said Dr. Lennard A. Fisk, associate administrator for space science of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.</p>
        <p>Already on its way to Venus is a spacecraft equipped with a radar mapping system capable of penetrating the enveloping clouds of carbon dioxide and sulfur to get clear images of the planet's blistering hot surface. Launched in May, the spacecraft Magellan is scheduled to circumnavigate Venus, beginning next August, and obtain radar images of the entire planet that should be 10 times better than those of an earlier Soviet mission.</p>
        <p>Magellan's departure broke an 11-year hiatus in the American program that stemmed from the diversion of most NASA money to pay for the space shuttles. No American spacecraft had set out for a planet since a Pioneer mission went to Venus in 1978. The two Voyagers were launched to the outer planets in 1977. And the Mariners and Vikings that explored Mars in the 60's and 70's had long since ceased operation.</p>
        <p>With the return to service of the shuttles, the tempo of launchings is expected to pick up. On Oct. 12, the long-delayed Galileo spacecraft is scheduled to be launched on a flight to orbit Jupiter in 1995, following up on the flyby explorations of Pioneers 10 and 11 and Voyagers 1 and 2. The plan is for Galileo to shoot an instrument-laden probe into the dense Jovian atmosphere and spend at least two years making repeated passes by the planet's four largest moons, several of which are the size of small planets.</p>
        <p>Although its sights will usually be on more cosmic targets, the Hubble Space Telescope, scheduled for launching from the shuttle next March, will occasionally focus on the solar system, looking out to Pluto and searching for any more distant planets that had gone undetected. The 94-inch telescope, operating above the Earth's distorting atmosphere, may also make the first unambiguous discovery of planets orbiting stars other than the Sun.</p>
        <p>Next, in October 1990, the Ulysses spacecraft is to head for a 1995 solar orbit in a mission conducted with the European Space Agency and aimed at learning more about the structure and dynamics of the Sun.</p>
        <p>If Congress does not balk, NASA plans to begin work next year on two new missions, one to fly by an asteroid and rendezvous with the comet Kopff and another to return to Saturn. The Comet Rendezvous Asteroid Flyby spacecraft would be launched in 1995 and travel along with the comet for three years, beginning in 2000. The Saturn-bound spacecraft, called Cassini, would be launched a year later and orbit the planet in 2002. A lander would be sent to the surface of the moon Titan, which the Voyagers showed to have a dense atmosphere and which may be covered with ponds or even oceans of liquid ethane.</p>
        <p>The only other approved project is Mars Observer, a spacecraft being built for launching in 1992. Its mission is to examine from orbit the surface, atmosphere and climate through a full Martian year of 687 Earth days. Many scientists hope this will serve as a precursor to more ambitious ventures to explore Mars, including preliminary plans to send an automated roving vehicle to pick up soil samples and bring them back to Earth.</p>
        <p>President Mikhail S. Gorbachev and other Soviet officials have proposed making the exploration of Mars an international undertaking. Soviet scientists are preparing a mission to orbit Mars in 1994 and another in 1996 to the Martian moon Phobos, trying to make up for the loss of its two Phobos-bound craft in the last year. Last week Soviet officials also announced their intentions to send a spacecraft to Venus again, this time in cooperation with France, and then another one to Mercury at the turn of the century.</p>
        <p>The renewed Soviet interest in Mars, along with suggestions of replacing cold war competition in space with cooperation, has already stirred American space officials and engineers to revive studies for missions to Mars that would culminate in human landings sometime in the next century. At a meeting on solar-system exploration here last week, Prof. Valery Barsukov, director of the Vernadsky Institute of Geochemistry and Analytical Chemistry in Moscow, said Soviet plans for future missions to Mars or the Moon would depend on what Americans decided to do, and what the two countries could agree to do together.</p>
        <p>At ceremonies celebrating Voyager 2's successful flyby of Neptune, Vice President Dan Quayle reiterated the Administration's commitment to American leadership in space and an expanded program of exploring the Moon and planets. Mr. Quayle, who is chairman of the National Space Council, said that he was working on a strategy for the next era in space exploration to be presented to President Bush in a few months. In the course of this, Mr. Quayle seemed to have picked up some of the thinking and language of the planetary scientists. His speech was laced with allusions to ''the dawn of a new era'' and the ''golden age'' of space science.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
