<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Oil Discovery Off But Recovery Gains</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="281448"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESERVES (NATURAL RESOURCES)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENERGY, DEPARTMENT OF</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAYES, THOMAS C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reserves (Natural Resources)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DA1531F93BA3575AC0A96F948260" item-length="610" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Oil Discovery Off But Recovery Gains</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS C. HAYES, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAYES, THOMAS C</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS, Sept. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Energy Department said today that its estimate of how much oil can be recovered from known reserves in the United States increased by a substantial margin in 1988, marking the fifth time in the last six years that the improvement exceeded 1.8 billion barrels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Energy Department said today that its estimate of how much oil can be recovered from known reserves in the United States increased by a substantial margin in 1988, marking the fifth time in the last six years that the improvement exceeded 1.8 billion barrels.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department said today that its estimate of how much oil can be recovered from known reserves in the United States increased by a substantial margin in 1988, marking the fifth time in the last six years that the improvement exceeded 1.8 billion barrels.</p>
        <p>The agency added, however, that discoveries of previously unknown oil reserves declined last year to less than 600 million barrels, the second-lowest level since the agency began keeping records in 1977.</p>
        <p>''The truth is, we're doing a lot better than most people expected in expanding our known reserves, even though it is not enough to get us through our current difficulties,'' said Dr. William L. Fisher, director of the Bureau of Economic Geology at the University of Texas, in Austin. An Overall Decline</p>
        <p>Over all, the amount of proven and recoverable oil reserves declined by 500 million barrels last year, to 26.8 billion barrels.</p>
        <p>Dr. Edward H. Murphy, an analyst at the American Petroleum Institute in Washington, said the decline in oil discoveries was likely to continue because Congress had refused to allow oil companies to explore for oil in the Alaska National Wildlife Refuge and Federal offshore areas, where many exploration experts believe the nation's largest undiscovered oil reserves lie.</p>
        <p>Many oil companies have reported improved recovery rates from existing oilfields in recent years by using computers and related analytical programs to give production engineers a clearer picture of how and where to drill in aging fields to bring more oil to the surface. Secondary Methods</p>
        <p>Also, secondary recovery methods, like the extraction of oil from known reserves by flooding them with water, carbon dioxide and other substances, have also improved production.</p>
        <p>Dr. Fisher said the percentage of recoverable oil reserves from existing fields had increased to 35 percent, from 30 percent, in the last decade and could increase to 55 percent in another 40 years.</p>
        <p>Several analysts attributed the decline in exploration to the sharp drop in oil prices early in 1986, and the uncertainty about future prices. Most big oil companies are cautious about searching for American fields because they fear oil prices could drop further. They are spending comparatively more money abroad, where fields are considered easier to find. Expanded Search for Gas</p>
        <p>At the same time, the industry is expanding the search for natural gas fields in the United States and has improved the recovery rates for existing natural-gas fields. Many companies, including Amoco and Chevron, bought natural-gas properties last year in expectation of rising prices in the 1990's.</p>
        <p>The Government recorded an overall decline of 19 trillion cubic feet last year, to 168 trillion cubic feet of natural-gas reserves, because it eliminated from consideration 24.6 trillion cubic feet of natural gas on Alaska's North Slope. No pipeline exists for shipping the gas, said John Wood, the official who directed the study from the Energy Infomration Administration's office in Dallas. The report showed that the industry increased the total discoveries of natural-gas reserves outside Alaska last year by more than 10 trillion cubic feet.</p>
        <p>The nation produced 16.7 trillion cubic feet of natural gas from known reserves last year.</p>
        <p>''There are also some new plays developing in areas where you have some potential for new discoveries,'' Richard Nehring, an indepedent energy analyst in Colorado Springs, said. A large natural-gas discovery by ARCO last year in the Arkoma Basin in southeastern Oklahoma encouraged other big oil companies to expand their drilling programs in the region, he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
