<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="298674"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DC173EF934A35752C1A96F948260" item-length="947" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-15  Political use of the diplomatic corps to reward the President's friends and contributors has gotten out of hand under President Bush, some experts say. Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-15  Political use of the diplomatic corps to reward the President's friends and contributors has gotten out of hand under President Bush, some experts say. Page A1</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-15  Political use of the diplomatic corps to reward the President's friends and contributors has gotten out of hand under President Bush, some experts say. Page A1</p>
        <p>East Germany proposed a law that declares for the first time that every citizen has the right to travel abroad or emigrate. But after another surge in emigration, the move seemed to attract little excitement. A14</p>
        <p>How many people can Bonn handle? That was on the mind of some leaders as 20,000 more emigrants arrived from East Germany. The Goverment reaffirmed its policy of automatic citizenship for all Germans. A1</p>
        <p>In Czech border town, another day of rush hour A14</p>
        <p>U.S. considers East German situation unstable A15</p>
        <p>Most Hungarians enjoy freedom from politics A14</p>
        <p>Hard-line Christians in Beirut virtually shut down the Christian sector in central Lebanon in support of Gen. Michel Aoun, the Christian army commander. A3</p>
        <p>Soviet human rights campaigners are asking Moscow to investigate the case of a rights advocate injured in a jailhouse fall. Family and friends suspect foul play. A9</p>
        <p>Richard Nixon met President Bush Sunday night to give a firsthand report on his trip to China. A13</p>
        <p>Carter urges Bush to match Gorbachev initiatives A16</p>
        <p>Two Greeks claimed a mandate to govern the country. But neither Constantine Mitsotakis nor Andreas Papandreou holds enough seats in Parliament to take power. A7</p>
        <p>The biggest threat to the Sandinistas appears to be the nation's deteriorating economy. Some opposition leaders accuse the government of raising the specter of war simply to distract from the daily hardships. A10</p>
        <p>U.S. and Japan refuse curbs on carbon dioxide A12</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A16-20, B8-9  A friend of Washington's mayor, Marion Barry, testified that he had given Mr. Barry crack on ''more than one occasion.'' A1</p>
        <p>Boeing has agreed to plead guilty to two charges of illegally obtaining internal Pentagon planning documents, Government officials said. A1</p>
        <p>A strike is making Seattle nervous as Christmas nears. A walkout at Boeing has all but shut down production at the airplane maker, cutting a $2 billion annual payroll in half. A16</p>
        <p>The F.B.I. investigated librarians earlier this year after criticism of the agency's effort to identify spies through a library surveillance program, internal documents show. A1</p>
        <p>An earthquake may benefit Oakland, showing off the city's best traits, raising morale and giving the economy an unexpected boost. A18</p>
        <p>Freeway collapse is linked to ground A18</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court agreed to decide whether state courts, in addition to Federal courts, can hear lawsuits brought under a Federal law against job discrimination. A16</p>
        <p>Justices reject challenges to Dalkon shield settlement D1</p>
        <p>An Energy official told senators that the department pays private management consultants substantially more than it pays its own employees for comparable work. A20</p>
        <p>Coca Cola will distribute $50 million through its private foundation over the next decade to support eucational institutions and programs throughout the United States, the company announced. B8</p>
        <p>Bishops intensify abortion fight A16</p>
        <p>Battle in Indiana looms on gambling B8</p>
        <p>Massachusetts town is divided over official language issue B8</p>
        <p>Jail sentences in Princeton/ Newport case D1</p>
        <p>Programs send Dow down 47.34 D1</p>
        <p>REGIONAL B1-7  David Dinkins and Rudolph Giuliani capped New York City's most contested mayoral race in 20 years with impassioned finales that epitomized their contentious campaigns. A1</p>
        <p>In final sweep, candidates for governor cross New Jersey B1</p>
        <p>From the libretto of the mayoral campaign, selected verses B5</p>
        <p>Dinkins admits to not listing friend's help on Riviera trip B4</p>
        <p>AIDS is spreading to babies by the thousands. In the years to come, experts say, many of the young will spend their childhood fighting AIDS with extensive, costly medical care. A1</p>
        <p>Battery Park City's development, which halted after the 1987 stock market plunge, has started again. But slow economic growth has prompted planners to rethink their vision. B1</p>
        <p>New Jersey's toxic waste cleanup is grinding along behind schedule. With years of work and tens of millions in expense ahead, the state's environmental commissioner is wondering if the high costs are justified. B1</p>
        <p>D'Amato aides asked Samuel Pierce in 1986 to approve $5.9 million in housing grants for a project with ties to a D'Amato contributor and to the law firm of Senator D'Amato's brother, Senator D'Amato acknowledged. B1</p>
        <p>Gay teachers are suing for benefits for their companions. They contend that New York City's health-benefits policies violate the State Constitution by discriminating on the basis of marital status and sexual orientation. B2</p>
        <p>Some 30 Gramercy Park residents, forced to abandon their apartments after an asbestos-lined steam pipe exploded 11 weeks ago, have learned in recent days that their homes have been ransacked. B3</p>
        <p>A judge acquits two police officers of beating man B3</p>
        <p>Families placed in welfare hotel faulted on lead B5</p>
        <p>Michigan utility eager to convert Shoreham for gas power B2</p>
        <p>Our Towns: A small crime and a big game divide a school B1</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
