<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="309149"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2D61F3EF937A25751C1A96F948260" item-length="911" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  International A3026  Soviet Jews are emigrating in record numbers, and Israel is bracing for its greatest explosion of immigration since its early days of independence. Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  International A3026  Soviet Jews are emigrating in record numbers, and Israel is bracing for its greatest explosion of immigration since its early days of independence. Page A1</p>
        <p>International A3026  Soviet Jews are emigrating in record numbers, and Israel is bracing for its greatest explosion of immigration since its early days of independence. Page A1</p>
        <p>Lebanese President and his chief rival live in tight security A13</p>
        <p>Crumbling sphinx: was it sabotage? A11</p>
        <p>A shift in Soviet economic planning from emphasis on heavy industry to consumer goods was announced by the Government. Skeptics questioned whether a workable recovery plan is even in place yet. A1</p>
        <p>Aid to Poland and Hungary will be stepped up to help the two countries make the difficult transition from centrally planned to market economies, Western governments announced. A22</p>
        <p>Europeans praise Baker blueprint A22</p>
        <p>News analysis: West Germany is caution on reunification</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>U.S. war game in West Germany to be cut back</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>U.S. Ambassador to East Berlin commands special authority</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Czech parties move to purge hard-liners</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Prague institute abolishes courses in Marxism-Leninism</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Bulgarian Communists expel Zhivkov A23</p>
        <p>Salvador deported an American who had been arrested after an arms cache was uncovered on her rented property. A military judge had ordered her release for lack of evidence. A1  U.S. aides see no victory in American's release</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>TV helps Brazilian leftist A20</p>
        <p>Argentine leader seeking labor-business pact</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>President de Klerk had a meeting with Nelson Mandela and discussed South Africa's future. The meeting raised expectations that the imprisoned anti-apartheid leader may be released early next year. A3</p>
        <p>Abducted woman freed in Kashmir A3</p>
        <p>1,000 a month reported slain in Sri Lanka strife</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Kabul's edge in civi war: its air force</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Zaire's battered economy inspires optimism</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Talks on Indian Ocean Isle stall A10</p>
        <p>British say they will resume deportations in 1990</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Cambodia agrees to vote controlled by U.N.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Agreement reached to end use of drift fishing nets</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>National A27-36, B14-24</p>
        <p>Workers at the Nevada Test Site, the desert proving ground for American nuclear weapons, were repeatedly exposed to dangerous levels of radiation, according to Government records made public in a court case. A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: U.S. priorities for the 1990's are beginning to be debated as it becomes apparent that there may be a huge windfall in the military budget. A1</p>
        <p>Washington Talk: Odd couple does ''clean air'' fandango</p>
        <p>A28</p>
        <p>A forgetful North remembers Poindexter as witness</p>
        <p>A32</p>
        <p>Two big American retail companies, subsidiaries of the Toronto-based Campeau empire, said they had to consider the possibility of going into bankruptcy. The companies operate Bloomingdale's and other well-known stores. A1</p>
        <p>Car sales down 28% this month D1</p>
        <p>Non-securities company guilty in stock case</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>A rape and murder conviction was set aside by a Texas appeals court in the case of a man who twice came within days of execution. The case had caused outrage throughout the black community. A28</p>
        <p>Star is found at the edge of the Milky Way B16</p>
        <p>Study supports global warming prediction A36</p>
        <p>Secret fund of Detroit police is investigated by grand jury</p>
        <p>A28</p>
        <p>Squatter camps on Federal preserve to be razed B24</p>
        <p>Drug violence in Atlanta: a lost generation A28</p>
        <p>Discipline urged for Atlanta school chief A33</p>
        <p>Two Iowa survivors defend accused shipmate A32</p>
        <p>South Carolina concern fined $580,000 for employing aliens</p>
        <p>A32</p>
        <p>Boston University head considers bid for governor B19</p>
        <p>Number of Boston poor is found to decline B20</p>
        <p>Topeka's integration efforts failed, judges find</p>
        <p>B17</p>
        <p>Regional B1-13</p>
        <p>The revised New York City Charter was approved by the United States Justice Department, removing the last obstacle to a new municipal government, which will begin to take shape Jan. 1. A1</p>
        <p>Plans for Dinkins inaugural grow with guest list B1</p>
        <p>Candidates ask for more public campaign money</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Ties to the G.O.P. political machine in Nassau County helped certain people obtain apartments in H.U.D.-subsidized buildings for the elderly, according to a former employee of the company that runs the buildings, as well as current and former elected officials. A1</p>
        <p>D'Amato cited in another complaint B11</p>
        <p>A woman charged with murder in the death of her three-year-old son has had a violence-scarred life in which she and her lawyers picture her as no less a victim than her son. B1</p>
        <p>New Jersey house prices may drop as much as 12 percent in the beginning of the 1990's, a report based on three million house sales says. B1</p>
        <p>Despite worries, mall's registers jingle</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>M.T.A. hinting at retaliation in Connecticut</p>
        <p>B13</p>
        <p>Inspectors jeered at nuclear-waste site B3</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases B13</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
