<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senators and Administration Reach Pollution Pact</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="300230"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DE1F38F931A25752C1A96F948260" item-length="660" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senators and Administration Reach Pollution Pact</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Bush Administration and the Senate Democratic leadership have reached a compromise on acid rain legislation that would require stricter standards on some pollutants than the President had originally proposed, would speed the deadlines for meeting the standards and would give six Western states credit for efforts to clean up power plants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Bush Administration and the Senate Democratic leadership have reached a compromise on acid rain legislation that would require stricter standards on some pollutants than the President had originally proposed, would speed the deadlines for meeting the standards and would give six Western states credit for efforts to clean up power plants.</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration and the Senate Democratic leadership have reached a compromise on acid rain legislation that would require stricter standards on some pollutants than the President had originally proposed, would speed the deadlines for meeting the standards and would give six Western states credit for efforts to clean up power plants.</p>
        <p>The agreement, announced today, gives new momentum in the Senate to the President's clean air legislation, which has moved slowly in that body since being introduced in July. The Senate Subcommittee on Environmental Protection had already approved tighter rules on smog and emissions of toxics and was awaiting an acid rain proposal acceptable to the Democratic leadership and the White House.</p>
        <p>The President's clean air legislation has been stalled in the House and faces a struggle there because representatives of Middle Western states are holding out for a provision that would prevent the costs from falling primarily on their region. The Administration opposes such a measure, which it intreprets as a tax. Such regional fights over who should pay for clean air have hindered revision of the Clean Air Act for more than a decade.</p>
        <p>Senator Max Baucus, a Montana Democrat who is chairman of the subcommittee, said today that the panel and the full Committee on Environment and Public Works would vote on the new acid rain legislation in the next week. Passage is likely.</p>
        <p>But the proposal will probably be challenged on the Senate floor by members from the Middle West and some coal-producing areas. Many power plants in the Midwest are big polluters and would face large cleanup bills under the President's plan. The compromise ignores the region's interest in spreading the cost of cleaning up and concern about the possible loss of some coal-mining jobs.</p>
        <p>The agreement retains the hallmarks of the acid-rain provisions of the President's plan to amend the Clean Air Act of 1970: a requirement for power plants to cut in half by the year 2000 emissions of sulfur dioxide, which reacts in the atmosphere to produce acid in precipitation; a limit on such emissions at the level found in 1980, and a system of permits that allows utilities to sell credits they receive for reducing pollution. Under the compromise, the Administration accepted greater reductions in emissions of nitrogen oxides, which has been sought by environmentalists. The White House also agreed to exclude until the year 2000 utilities in six states - Montana, North Dakota, Wyoming, New Mexico, Utah and Minnesota - from pollution cutbacks.</p>
        <p>In another measure favorable to the West, the Administration agreed to support a change in the law that now discourages use of low-sulfur coal by utilities. Such coal burns more cleanly than high-sulfur coal and is found in substantial quantities in states like Wyoming and Montana. Deadlines Set a Year Sooner</p>
        <p>Senators from the six states asserted that their constituents deserved the concession because many of their power plants had already been forced to spend billions to clean up.</p>
        <p>The chairman of the full committee is Quentin N. Burdick, Democrat of North Dakota. Republican members include Alan K. Simpson of Wyoming and Dave Durenberger of Minnesota. Mr. Baucus is from Montana.</p>
        <p>The compromise included and agreement to accelerate by a year compliance with the pollution reduction requirements called for in the Bush bill. The first phase of the plan would be completed by Jan. 1, 1995, and second phase by Jan. 1, 2000.</p>
        <p>In the compromise, Senator George J. Mitchell of Maine, the Democratic majority leader, agreed to include in the acid-rain program all 107 power plants in 20 states that the President had chosen for pollution cutbacks in the bill's first phase, scheduled for completion in 1995. Mr. Mitchell dropped his original acid rain plan, which would have required severe cutbacks at 20 power plants in a way that would have encouraged the use of high-sulfur coal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
