<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When the Sun Becomes a Deadly Enemy</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="264736"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND OPINION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CANCER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SKIN</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MANDEL, SEBA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Skin Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0D71630F93AA35754C0A96F948260" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When the Sun Becomes a Deadly Enemy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Seba Mandel; Seba Mandel lives in Jericho.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MANDEL, SEBA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: HOW I loved the sun. As a child on the beaches of Far Rockaway, later as a teen-ager strutting and sunning myself on the sands of Coney Island, my love affair with the outdoors gave me a happy outlook. Sunny days brought a sunny disposition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: HOW I loved the sun. As a child on the beaches of Far Rockaway, later as a teen-ager strutting and sunning myself on the sands of Coney Island, my love affair with the outdoors gave me a happy outlook. Sunny days brought a sunny disposition.</p>
        <p>HOW I loved the sun. As a child on the beaches of Far Rockaway, later as a teen-ager strutting and sunning myself on the sands of Coney Island, my love affair with the outdoors gave me a happy outlook. Sunny days brought a sunny disposition.</p>
        <p>Today, as I gaze out the kitchen window, the sunshine's bright rays touch the leaves and flowers. The bandages across my face pull at my skin underneath, healing from the onslaught of skin cancer surgery. Skin cancer had struck me again. Looking out, I look back.</p>
        <p>Contemplating the start of my first skin cancer, I recall 12 years ago, a small ''cut'' at my earlobe, bleeding intermittently. Always wearing my hair cut short, I put the blame on my hairdresser. Sharp scissors. I changed hairdressers.</p>
        <p>After three haircuts from three different hairdressers, I finally decided to see a doctor in order to stop this ''cut'' from bleeding. My doctor took one look and said, ''Skin cancer.''</p>
        <p>At first unbelieving, I accepted the diagnosis after the biopsy report. And I accepted the treatment recommended by my dermatologist and started to become informed about skin cancer.</p>
        <p>Carefully following the prescribed advice, I covered my face with sun screens and shaded myself with a sun hat. But within a short time, with my usual casual attitude and upbeat outlook, I decided it was nothing serious, not life-threatening. So what the heck; it won't happen again.</p>
        <p>Carelessly, I became a casual sun worshipper again, forgetting the sun screen, forgetting the sun hat.</p>
        <p>Within the next three years, three basal-cell skin cancers appeared and were treated surgically. The following two years brought two more episodes, all diagnosed as basal-cell carcinoma, needing surgical excision or radiation treatments.</p>
        <p>After each procedure, I again followed the preventive routine of sun screen and sun hat.</p>
        <p>By now, I became an avid reader on the subject of skin cancer. Scientific reports proved more and more that our sun, the source of life on this planet, was becoming a threat.</p>
        <p>The ozone layer was being penetrated by society's indiscriminate use of chemicals that were piercing protective layers of sun-screening atmosphere. More and more cases of skin cancer appeared, and I, as a person with fair skin and light eye color, had become another statistic.</p>
        <p>Finally, I rigidly maintained a sun-protective life style. Six years went by, and I did not suffer a recurrence.</p>
        <p>Last winter brought an optimistic change. My husband and I were going to sunny Florida to try the Southern winter, an experiment in snowbird living. Three months of golf, tennis, swimming. What could be bad?</p>
        <p>We left for Florida in high spirits. Four sunny weeks later, blood spurted from a circle of slightly reddened skin at the top of my nose. Warning bells rang in my head. But not unduly alarmed, I thought, ''Oh oh, skin cancer again.'' But, having a wonderful time, I simply cautioned myself to start putting on more sun screen and wore a sun hat. The winter was a rare one for Florida. The sun shone brightly every day. There was only one half-day of rain during the three months of winter.</p>
        <p>Week after week I would spot this warning, a spot of blood on my nose. I would wash it away, dry the area, then go out for my round of golf or set of tennis.</p>
        <p>Finally, after a few weeks of daily recurrences, I called my doctor in New York, reporting the suspected skin cancer and made a appointment for the first week after my return.</p>
        <p>Remaining uneasy about further delay, we came home earlier than we had planned. As suspected, I had a confirmed basal-cell carcinoma. But this time, it appeared, even on the skin surface, to involve a broader and deeper area, more serious than any other episodes.</p>
        <p>Two medical consultations later, the recommended procedure was Mohs surgery, a specialized precise operation with accompanying immediate microscopic review. This procedure, as explained to me by the plastic surgeon, would insure the success of a complete excision of the basal cells in that area.</p>
        <p>After reviewing the alternative medical treatments, I agreed to have this procedure. I was told a skin graft might be necessary, if the basal-cell penetration was deeply imbedded through layers of skin.</p>
        <p>Since Passover was approaching, I made an appointment for two weeks later and went about my busy schedule preparing for the holiday. I still was not unduly alarmed. ''After all, my other skin cancers were not so bad or disfiguring,'' I thought.</p>
        <p>I have now undergone the two procedures, recuperating from the surgery and the skin graft. There also appears to be another basal cell, at the side of my nose, that may require surgery.</p>
        <p>Physically and emotionally, I am now recuperating from this latest and most severe attack. And as I glance again at the lovely, warming sunshine, I have a gnawing, hovering anxiety: Where will these beautiful, threatening sun rays strike next? And when did you become an enemy?</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND OPINION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
