<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nuclear Industry Tries Again</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="304190"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DESIGN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0D6113FF935A15752C1A96F948260" item-length="2813" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nuclear Industry Tries Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Right now, the American nuclear power industry appears headed for extinction. Every plant of the more than 100 ordered since 1973 has been canceled, and many others are approaching retirement. But reactor manufacturers say that fears of global warming - the greenhouse effect - are giving them a second chance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Right now, the American nuclear power industry appears headed for extinction. Every plant of the more than 100 ordered since 1973 has been canceled, and many others are approaching retirement. But reactor manufacturers say that fears of global warming - the greenhouse effect - are giving them a second chance.</p>
        <p>Right now, the American nuclear power industry appears headed for extinction. Every plant of the more than 100 ordered since 1973 has been canceled, and many others are approaching retirement. But reactor manufacturers say that fears of global warming - the greenhouse effect - are giving them a second chance.</p>
        <p>Nuclear power advocates have, of course, been predicting the industry's rebirth for years. But the plans are becoming more specific, and political calculations are coming into play. Reactor builders are readying designs for a new generation of plants that, they say, will be far safer, less expensive and simpler to operate. The General Electric Company and the Westinghouse Electric Corporation, the two biggest reactor manufacturers, and General Atomic, a small company with an innovative reactor design, each received $50 million from the Department of Energy in September to work on their models. They are spending hundreds of millions of dollars to bring nuclear power back. And they are presenting the opposition with a tantalizing series of ''what-if's.''</p>
        <p>* What if fundamental design changes made plants a hundred times safer? So safe that many elaborate safety features in today's plants - equipment that must be radiation-proof, fire-proof, tornado-proof and generally failure-proof - were not needed?</p>
        <p>* What if all the power and all the pumps and valves could fail, all the operators could be seized with indecision - and the plant would come through without further damage? Designers say such a plant is in their blueprints.</p>
        <p>* What if, as designers promise, the parts that are most likely to fail were redesigned or even eliminated? If many of the parts that are trickiest to install - like earthquake-proof piping with flawless welds - were drastically reduced? What if cost overruns were the worry of the manufacturer, not the utility and its customers? Would such a reactor sell?</p>
        <p>* What if plants that were licensed for construction were accepted by the gvernment once built, not subject to costly new requirements before completion, or after? New rules approved by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission and now before Congress would accomplish as much, the industry's boosters say.</p>
        <p>Even those in the industry agreed that utility companies are unlikely to buy new plants soon. ''Anyone suggests a nuclear reactor to a utility board of directors, they will send for the guy with the net, and with good reason,'' said Shelby T. Brewer, head of the nuclear division at Combustion Engineering Inc. - a reactor manufacturer that has agreed to be bought out by ABB Asea Brown Boveri Ltd.</p>
        <p>But the manufacturers, who have been subsisting on paltry foreign sales, say they must prepare for a second nuclear age. With new equipment, new construction procedures and reformed regulation, they say, the orders will come. At Westinghouse, promotional material speaks of a new design ''restoring the domestic market.''</p>
        <p>The reactor vendors are counting on growing environmental consciousness and growing demand for electricity. The world's choices of other power sources will be constrained by fears of air pollution and global warming brought on by the burning of coal, oil and gas. As Hans Blix, the director general of the International Atomic Energy Agency, a United Nations agency based in Vienna, asked, ''Are you more scared of nuclear than of adding more carbon dioxide?'' The next few years, reactor manufacturers believe, will bring electricity shortages in this country and higher power needs abroad.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists are skeptical, suggesting that if there is a high-tech remedy for the greenhouse effect, it probably lies in more efficient light bulbs and motors, or photovoltaic cells and other new generating technologies. It is unclear what the leading technologies will be at the turn of the century, the very earliest that the first of a new generation of nuclear plants might be completed.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists also point out that even if all the nation's electricity came from reactors, global emissions of carbon dioxide would be cut by only about 3.5 percent.</p>
        <p>But utility executives say they would like a nuclear option; although mindful of public opposition and the huge cost overruns of the 1970's and 1980's, they are not lining up to buy. At a recent conference on nuclear power and the greenhouse effect, organized by the Institute for Resource Management, an environmental group, many experts said the revival of the industry was a realistic possibility, but that it depended heavily on public opinion.</p>
        <p>As Alan Crane, senior associate project director at the Office of Technology Assessment put it at the conference: ''You can't just keep the utilities happy. There's a jury of 240 million people out there.'' Though polls show the public believes nuclear power will be important in the future, he said, ''Nobody would countenance one in their own backyard.''</p>
        <p>Though some new reactor features have been tested, others exist only on paper. But the industry's basic selling point is that eight pounds of uranium can make as much energy as 6,000 tons of oil or 8,600 tons of coal. A single large reactor could supply 1.5 million households. If that energy had to come from coal, each household would aggravate the greenhouse effect by burning half a ton of coal each month. Among currently economical technologies, only hydroelectric power and perhaps wood replaced by replanting can provide electricity without worsening the greenhouse effect. But both sources are limited.</p>
        <p>By themselves, these arguments sway few outside the nuclear community. Safety and cost, which killed off the market for the current generation of reactors, still must carry the day.</p>
        <p>The United States invented the civilian nuclear reactor as a spin-off from the bomb. For decades, in the ''Atoms for Peace'' era, the nuclear industry had a near-messianic tone. The nation's resulting disillusionment was all the more severe. Now American manufacturers say this country can use standardization and other reforms to make nuclear power work again - at least as well as the French, Japanese and Koreans, who all prosper with American designs. ''As we see the world,'' said Bert Wolfe, vice president for nuclear services at General Electric, ''it's hard to see how you can meet the energy needs in the next century without nuclear power.''</p>
        <p>General Electric's Simplified Boiling Water Reactor and Westinghouse's Advanced Passive 600 are dramatic departures from the reactors these companies have built before. They are smaller, simpler and more forgiving and reliable. ''Even the current reactors tolerate a lot of stupidities,'' said Mr. Blix, in an interview at the United Nations. ''The ones that will come in the 90's will tolerate even more.''</p>
        <p>The designs for the 1990's differ in many ways, but all are only about half as large as the biggest now in service. General Atomic's plan is for even smaller reactors, which would be built in groups of up to four, with all four together only the size of a smallish plant today.  A Revolution in Design</p>
        <p>Down-sizing represents a revolution for reactor manufacturers, who, like auto makers, had long equated size with progress. For years the reactor designs grew larger because manufacturers thought the utilities could achieve economies of scale, generating more power with the same plant staff. But bigger plants took longer to build, raising costs and leaving utilities too dependent on single projects.</p>
        <p>Utilities also found that they had overestimated power demand for the early 1980's; smaller plants, more quickly built, do not require such accurate long-range projections. Smaller reactors also make it easier to design cooling systems without mechanical pumps or the need for quick action by operators.</p>
        <p>The other revolution in reactor concepts has been for vendors to complete their designs before they build. In the 1960's, utilities blithely broke ground on plants when only a quarter of the design was in hand, even when the plants were to be three or four times larger than any reactors already operating. ''Fast-tracking'' was the motto, with construction crews pouring foundations while engineers decided, in effect, where to put the kitchen and how many bedrooms to put upstairs. In a period of rapid inflation in building costs and high interest payments on an unfinished project, fast-tracking was meant to save money. Instead, it created confusion and raised costs, as piping ordered by one set of engineers often failed to fit equipment designed by another.</p>
        <p>Fast-tracking was especially difficult because the first generation of reactors included scores of one-of-a-kind designs. ''We had 50 separate learning curves,'' said Victor Gilinsky, a physicist and former member of the Nuclear Regulatory Commission. Virtually every plant was a prototype, and the experience of building one was of little help in building another. And there was no standardization in operations, either. ''It's as if the Navy had allowed every commander to design his own ship, hire his own contractor, designate his own ranks,'' said Mr. Gilinsky.</p>
        <p>Standardization is essential to swift construction, the experts say. As Howard J. Bruschi, the director of nuclear plant programs at Westinghouse, complained, ''The French are using Westinghouse reactors, and they build them in five years. We've managed to stretch that to 14 in the United States.''</p>
        <p>Westinghouse and General Electric are both seeking generic approval for their designs from the Nuclear Regulatory Commission by 1995. They also want one-step licensing, to replace the current process of applying for a construction permit and then, after construction is nearly done, applying again, for an operating license. Under the proposed changes, utilities could order a reactor the way a not-too-fussy homebuyer could order a house from stock plans, with only minor adjustments to conform to the particulars of a site.</p>
        <p>The commission has already approved simplified licensing for standardized plants. Watchdog groups have complained about the potential loss of public say, so the industry wants to head off legal challenges by having Congress write the simplified procedures into law.</p>
        <p>The new designs confront several other chronic problems of earlier nuclear reactors. Some examples:</p>
        <p>* In case of accident, existing reactors automatically pump in water to cool the fuel. But a cooling system failure could be catastrophic. New designs by Westinghouse and General Electric depend on gravity and convection to inject cold water and remove heat.</p>
        <p>* Existing reactors overheat quickly if cooling water flow is interrupted because they squeeze a large amount of fissionable uranium into a small space. Solution: Change the concentration of fissionable uranium in the fuel to lower the concentration of heat produced, by about 40 percent in General Electric plants and 30 percent in Westinghouse plants.</p>
        <p>* The current plants were plagued with questions about the adequacy of welds. As a result, one $2 billion plant, Zimmer, a General Electric design in Moscow, Ohio, is being converted to coal. Westinghouse has designed a new plant with long, gently curving pipes that have half the welds of a conventional design.</p>
        <p>* Reactors that boil water directly in the core now use pumps to circulate the water, but the stainless steel piping connected to the pumps has sometimes cracked. General Electric has designed a reactor that relies on natural convection instead of pumps to circulate water. This design also eliminates the need for large pipes to penetrate the reactor vessel below the level of the uranium core, so that if a pipe breaks, the water will not leak out.</p>
        <p>* Reactors today have emergency diesel generators, which provide power for crucial instruments, pumps and valves in case of a blackout. But the diesels require expensive maintenance and sometimes fail in tests, requiring a plant to close while they are fixed. Westinghouse has designed a plant that it says shuts down safely, dissipating heat with water delivered by gravity, convection and other passive means - without the use of valves, pumps or instruments, and thus without emergency diesel generators.  The Cost Contest</p>
        <p>Even an industry that meets all the safety criteria still faces huge challenges - most of all, cost. With more and more states requiring their utilities to solicit bids for new power supplies, rather than simply building another generating station and charging customers, nuclear will have to compete with new, highly fuel-efficient gas- and oil-fired generators.</p>
        <p>In extreme cases like New Hampshire's Seabrook nuclear plant, which recently took a major step toward operation, costs reached $5,400 per kilowatt of capacity. About $3,600 was for direct costs, the rest for interest payments. The Electric Power Research Institute, a utility research consortium in Palo Alto, Calif., believes that to be competitive, nuclear plants must be built for $1,500 a kilowatt in direct costs, a target that manufacturers believe they can meet. Westinghouse is convinced that its AP 600 can be built for $1,270 a kilowatt, not counting interest but including a 20 percent contingency fee.</p>
        <p>To limit costs, the builders of nuclear plants must limit construction time. ''If we're going to be effective with nuclear power,'' said Mr. Bruschi in an interview, ''we have to demonstrate as an industry, unequivocally, that these things can be built in a reasonable amount of time.'' Westinghouse, he said, can fulfill this goal with a strategy not used since the mid-1960's: the ''turnkey'' plant. It is sold at a fixed price, so the builder bears the risk of cost overruns.</p>
        <p>''I have been highly encouraged by conversations we've had with utilities,'' said Mr. Bruschi, ''But no single utility is going to stick its neck out. So we're willing to go forward with a turnkey plant.'' The risk might be shared, he said, among Westinghouse, an architecture and engineering firm, and other contractors.</p>
        <p>Nuclear power opponents raise several other challenges. They question special subsidies and protections for the industry, like the Price-Anderson Act, which limits the liability of reactor operators for accidents. ''What distinguishes nuclear power in benefit to the United States, that it is deserving of such treatment?'' asked Charles Imbrecht, the chairman of the California Energy Commission.</p>
        <p>The big reactor manufacturers, all of them divisions of larger companies, say Price-Anderson is a necessity for them to continue in the business. But Linden Blue, the vice chairman of General Atomic, said he is so convinced that his reactor could not cause damage beyond the plant boundaries that he would forswear the Price-Anderson benefits.  Suspect Subsidies</p>
        <p>Many energy experts question why the Department of Energy spends so much more to develop nuclear power than solar power or other technologies. Amory B. Lovins, a physicist and expert in electric efficiency, argues that skepticism over vendors' cost claims will persist ''until the promoters pay for that commercialization, and stop importuning the Treasury to put our money where their mouths are.'' If the nuclear companies paid all their development costs, he said, they would build no new reactors. The same funds invested in energy conservation and efficiency would save far more power, he added.</p>
        <p>Another problem is nuclear waste. California has barred the construction of more reactors until the Federal Government demonstrates a way to dispose of waste. The Department of Energy is making little progress toward its goal of opening a repository early in the next century.</p>
        <p>Then there are decommissioning costs, unmeasured even for plants now in operation. Also uncertain is how much of a hazard a decommissioned plant would be. As I.C. Bupp, a reactor expert at the Cambridge Energy Research Associates consulting firm, put it: ''The public expects the option to tear it down and make a baseball field. If that option isn't there, I think you're going to have one heck of a political problem.''</p>
        <p>The industry is convinced it can meet these objections. The first new reactor, the thinking goes, will be built where others already exist, in a region with scarce coal but growing electric demand. The Southeast, including Florida, might provide a site.</p>
        <p>Until now, the industry's greatest obstacle has been its own sorry record. But business will revive, industry executives say, when it becomes obvious that a standardized plant can be built quickly, under a licensing system that prevents challenges and changing requirements along the way.</p>
        <p>With nuclear power in such disrepute, it may take more than just blueprints to persuade a utility to order that first new plant.As Mr. Wolfe of General Electric said, ''Someone is going to have to have faith that the system will work.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
