<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deficit-Reduction Bill Changes Many Taxes</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="303798"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7DF103AF937A15752C1A96F948260" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deficit-Reduction Bill Changes Many Taxes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: While nobody in Washington seems eager to use the term tax increase, the $14.7 billion deficit-reduction package approved by Congress on Wednesday is built around almost $8 billion worth of measures that will raise a number of taxes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: While nobody in Washington seems eager to use the term tax increase, the $14.7 billion deficit-reduction package approved by Congress on Wednesday is built around almost $8 billion worth of measures that will raise a number of taxes.</p>
        <p>While nobody in Washington seems eager to use the term tax increase, the $14.7 billion deficit-reduction package approved by Congress on Wednesday is built around almost $8 billion worth of measures that will raise a number of taxes.</p>
        <p>''What constitutes new taxes is a highly subjective judgment,'' said Senator James Sasser, Democrat of Tennessee, chairman of the Senate Budget Committee.</p>
        <p>The White House said President Bush supported the package, even though some might view the bill as running contrary to his repeated pledges to oppose tax increases.</p>
        <p>The plan includes spending cuts, most of which extend several expiring tax breaks through Sept. 30, 1990, as well as some tax increases that affect only corporations, and others that are aimed at relatively few individuals.</p>
        <p>Here are some provisions and how they would affect the deficit this budget year:  Revenue Increases</p>
        <p>SOCIAL SECURITY TAXES, $400 million: Include deferred compensation, like wages that are set aside in a 401K retirement account, in the formula used to calculate the amount of wages that are subject to Social Security tax. That would mean a slightly greater increase each year in the Social Security ''wage base,'' which this year is $48,000 and next year will be $50,000.</p>
        <p>AIR SERVICE, $895 million: Delay until Jan. 1, 1991, scheduled reductions in the 8 percent tax on airline tickets and the 5 percent tax on air freight. Double, to $6 per passenger, the tax on international tickets.</p>
        <p>BANKS, $1 billion: Repeal tax breaks for interest earned on loans to permit workers to buy stock in a company through Employee Stock Ownership Plans, unless the plan owns a majority of the company's stock.</p>
        <p>TAKEOVERS, $226 million: Prohibit corporations from carrying back losses - and thus getting refunds of past taxes - generated by borrowing to finance the takeover of another company.</p>
        <p>OIL TAXES, $115 million: Impose a 5-cent-a-barrel tax on domestic and imported oil and oil products to help clean up spills - a measure that accounts for $106 million of the total -and impose a 3-cent tax on oil located on the Outer Continental Shelf in the Atlantic Ocean for pollution control.</p>
        <p>CHEMICALS, $489 million: Impose a gradually increasing tax on the sale or use of chemicals deemed to deplete the earth's ozone layer.</p>
        <p>''JUNK BONDS,'' $21 million: Reduce tax benefits for high-risk bonds sold at deep discount.</p>
        <p>PAYROLL SPEED-UP, $2.45 billion: Require large employers to turn over to the Treasury more quickly the Social Security and income taxes they withhold from workers' paychecks and the matching Social Security taxes they pay. Starting next Aug. 1, they would have to hand over the taxes the business day after any day on which collections totaled $100,000 or more. They now have limited holding periods.</p>
        <p>WITHHOLDING, $270 million: Require withholding of income taxes from wages of farm workers who already have Social Security taxes withheld.</p>
        <p>ACCOUNTING, $109 million: Repeal the completed-contract accounting method, which has allowed large builders and military contractors to defer taxes.</p>
        <p>''LIKE-KIND'' EXCHANGES, $100 million: Restrict the ability of those who hold certain assets to avoid capital gains taxes by exchanging their business or investment property for a similar asset, rather than selling it.</p>
        <p>CRUISE SHIPS, $4 million: Impose a $3-a-passenger tax on international overnight cruise ships and on gambling ships in international waters.  Tax Reductions</p>
        <p>CORPORATE MINIMUM TAX, $416 million: Simplify paperwork associated with the corporate minimum tax, which is intended to make sure that profitable companies pay some tax, even if large deductions would otherwise eliminate any tax liability.</p>
        <p>PENALTIES, no revenue effect in 1990: Simplify the 150 tax penalties in Federal law and prevent duplicate penalties for the same offense.</p>
        <p>RESEARCH, $550 million: A credit for increased spending for research and experimentation. In addition, a rule allowing corporations to allocate up to 64 percent of their research costs against foreign income would be extended a year.</p>
        <p>EDUCATION, $418 million: A tax exclusion for up to $5,250 a year of tuition assistance that an employee receives from an employer.</p>
        <p>SELF-EMPLOYED, $183 million: A deduction for 25 percent of the cost of health insurance for self-employed people, their spouses and dependents.</p>
        <p>LEGAL AID, $112 million: An exclusion from the taxable income of workers for a limited amount of employer-paid group legal assistance.</p>
        <p>TARGETED JOBS CREDIT, $36 million: A credit under which the Government in effect pays 40 percent of the first $4,000 of first-year wages of poor or disabled workers.</p>
        <p>LOW-INCOME HOUSING, $69 million: A credit that encourages the affluent to invest in building low-income rental housing.</p>
        <p>ENERGY CREDITS, $50 million: Subsidies for business investment in solar, geothermal and ocean-thermal property.</p>
        <p>MORTGAGE BONDS, $10 million: A tax exemption for bonds used to help lower-income families buy their first home.  Other Provisions</p>
        <p>POSTAL SERVICE: Remove the service, which has its own deficit, from the Federal budget, cutting $1.77 billion from the general deficit.</p>
        <p>INSURANCE: Raise $190 million by reauthorizing and extending national flood insurance and crime insurance programs.</p>
        <p>AGRICULTURE: Save $378 million by reducing 1990 crop deficiency payments for corn, other feed grains, wheat, upland cotton and rice by about 3 percent, and by limiting spending for export enhancement and targeted export assistance.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
