<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For the Pixies, Irony Begins At Home</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="240633"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="RECORDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDINGS (AUDIO)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PIXIES (ROCK BAND)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PARELES, JON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D6123DF935A25757C0A96F948260" item-length="1081" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For the Pixies, Irony Begins At Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PARELES, JON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ''I'm in a state, I'm in a state,'' Charles (Black) Francis of the Pixies sighs in one of the 15 songs on ''Doolittle'' (Elektra 60856, LP, cassette and CD); then he howls it. He never gets around to explaining just what that state is, but he doesn't have to. The band's music defines it for him better than anything he says.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ''I'm in a state, I'm in a state,'' Charles (Black) Francis of the Pixies sighs in one of the 15 songs on ''Doolittle'' (Elektra 60856, LP, cassette and CD); then he howls it. He never gets around to explaining just what that state is, but he doesn't have to. The band's music defines it for him better than anything he says.</p>
        <p>''I'm in a state, I'm in a state,'' Charles (Black) Francis of the Pixies sighs in one of the 15 songs on ''Doolittle'' (Elektra 60856, LP, cassette and CD); then he howls it. He never gets around to explaining just what that state is, but he doesn't have to. The band's music defines it for him better than anything he says.</p>
        <p>Call it the suburban-America syndrome: feeling affluent and impotent, brash and pointless, comfortable but at loose ends. The syndrome is spreading as more of the United States turns to suburbs distinguishable only by their zip codes, with the same (fast) food and (mall) clothes, the same (movie and television) culture, the same sense of rootlessness and unnamed loss.</p>
        <p>Suburban syndrome isn't the blues, which imply deeper suffering; it's not even a full-fledged malaise, because things just aren't as bad as all that. It's almost funny, but for that nagging undercurrent.</p>
        <p>On a 1987 EP (''Come on Pilgrim''), a 1988 album (''Surfer Rosa'') and now ''Doolittle,'' Mr. Francis (who grew up in Los Angeles) and his band yelp and bash through songs that can't take anything seriously - not music or love or sex, not alienation or violence, not even life and death, and certainly not themselves. Important subjects are all devalued and absurd, self-chosen targets of self-conscious irony; at the same time, they're all there is. The Pixies' songs hang amid the paradoxes like particles suspended in magnetic fields, dizzy with energy yet forever removed from the rest of the world.</p>
        <p>In most Pixies' songs, Kim Clark's bulbous bass lines roll in above stomping drumbeats; swaggering guitar chords (from Mr. Francis) or hooks (from Joey Santiago) float in slightly off kilter, as if they weren't from exactly the same song. Then along comes Mr. Francis' voice, a quavery falsetto suggesting a higher-strung Loudon Wainwright III; it's the sound of a twerp with an attitude problem.</p>
        <p>Mr. Francis cackles and shouts as if obnoxiousness were a state of grace. But while he's working himself up to a yell, his words might just be echoed by the cool, girlish voice of the Pixies' bassist, Kim Clark, who provides a placid veneer, like a well-groomed lawn surrounding a suburban madhouse.</p>
        <p>The songs are solidly danceable, but they also sound loose and jerry-built. Sometimes an extra beat slips in, sometimes a guitar lick slides one note over the line into dissonance, or the chord change deliberately arrives too late. The Pixies often recall the Fall, a British band that got started in the late 1970's, but where the Fall are dour and conspiratorial, the Pixies are jumpy and wild-eyed.</p>
        <p>Although the Pixies are based in Boston, the most collegiate of major American cities, they don't show off vocabularies or poetic ambitions like other college-circuit bands from Throwing Muses to Christmas. Mr. Francis' words are offhand rather than meticulous, primal rather than clever.</p>
        <p>He's blunt and bratty and fond of shock value, like a teen-age boy who wants a little attention. ''Surfer Rosa'' gleefully invoked sex, taboo and otherwise; ''Doolittle'' gets more of its occasional shock value from titles (and occasional lines of lyrics) like tabloid headlines.</p>
        <p>The album opens with ''Debaser,'' a tribute to the Luis Bunuel-Salvador Dali film ''Un Chien Andalou'' and its still-horrifying scene of an eyeball being slashed; the last song, ''Gouge Away'' is a victim's taunt. Another song with a tabloid title, ''Wave of Mutilation,'' is a fantasy about driving a car into the ocean (and riding the title's ''wave''), while ''I Bleed'' may be about a fierce hangover. As a wavering guitar note pesters the ear and Ms. Clark talks along with him, Mr. Francis painfully declaims:  As loud as hell</p>
        <p>a ringin' bell</p>
        <p>behind my smile</p>
        <p>it shakes my teeth</p>
        <p>and all the while</p>
        <p>as vampires feast</p>
        <p>I bleed.</p>
        <p>Except for ''Debaser,'' which suggests a film review by a goggle-eyed 14-year-old boy, the titles tend to be more brutal than the lyrics. In ''Monkey Goes to Heaven,'' Mr. Francis cheerfully considers pollution and the greenhouse effect: ''Everything is gonna burn/ we'll all take turns / I'll get mine too.'' ''Here Comes Your Man'' (with a beat and guitar line that allude to ''Here Comes the Night'' by Them, Van Morrison's band) is about hoboing, while ''There Goes My Gun'' offers inexplicit glimpses of random violence, as the title recurs amid lines like ''Friend or foe!'' and ''Look at me!''</p>
        <p>''Doolittle'' also offers songs about girlwatching (''No. 13 Baby,'' ''Tame'' and ''Dead,'' which declares, ''You crazy babe Bathsheba / I want ya''). And ''Hey,'' just as oblique as the other songs, sums up the tension between sexual attraction and independence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Francis rarely enunciates, much less spells things out; he likes to hide what he's saying behind a broad-shouldered guitar line or his own frenzied delivery. And even when the words are decipherable, he doesn't offer anything as simple as sincerity.</p>
        <p>With their glancing lyrics and skewed rock, Pixies songs turn up convoluted ironies. ''La La Love You,'' the album's jokiest novelty, answers a spaghetti-western guitar lick with wolf whistles, then moves on with male and female voices saying ''I love you'' and the band's drummer, David Lovering, crooning, like a lounge singer, ''love you don't mean maybe.''</p>
        <p>''Mr. Grieves'' starts with syncopated, dub-reggae guitar and Mr. Francis' voice, in a pretty good Bob Marley parody, singing ''Hope everything is all right''; he sings it ''all ri-i-i-i-i-ight,'' with each quaver sounding as if he's about to start laughing, or crying, or shrieking.</p>
        <p>More than the ambivalent messages, the tone of the music makes the Pixies worth hearing - it demonstrates its ambivalence with every unsupported power chord and every hot-and-cool vocal duet. Mr. Francis could almost be singing in another language for all the comprehensibility of songs like ''Crackity Jones'' or ''Dead.'' But long before the words are decipherable, the music puts across the band's insolent, uneasy humor.</p>
        <p>The one problem with ''Doolittle'' is that it suggests a less varied, slightly less adventurous facsimile of ''Surfer Rosa,'' down to including one song with a biblical allusion (instead of Bathsheba, ''Surfer Rosa'' cites the Song of Solomon). Having found their tone, the Pixies may already be tempted to turn it into a formula. But with nobody else doing anything much like it, that formula hasn't lost its impact. It's funny, but it's no joke.</p>
        <p>RECORDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
