<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Administration Is Divided Over Move to Halt Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="295115"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0D91631F934A15753C1A96F948260" item-length="1058" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Administration Is Divided Over Move to Halt Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Bush Administration is facing increasing pressure from other nations, Congress and environmental groups to take more aggressive action on the problem of global warming. But members of the Administration are divided on what course to follow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Bush Administration is facing increasing pressure from other nations, Congress and environmental groups to take more aggressive action on the problem of global warming. But members of the Administration are divided on what course to follow.</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration is facing increasing pressure from other nations, Congress and environmental groups to take more aggressive action on the problem of global warming. But members of the Administration are divided on what course to follow.</p>
        <p>On one side is the Environmental Protection Agency, which favors bolder steps by the United States, including stabilizing the emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases linked to a rise in temperatures worldwide, said people familiar with the Administration discussions. Several European countries have already set such goals, and others are considering similar action.</p>
        <p>Other top Administration officials, among them the White House chief of staff, John H. Sununu, and the President's science adviser, D. Allan Bromley, acknowledge that global warming is a threat. But they have resisted setting specific goals on carbon dioxide emissions before there is more conclusive scientific evidence on the problem.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the State Department official responsible for coordinating Government policy on global warming, William Nitze, said this week that because of growing international pressure, the United States would probably have to accept a goal of stabilizing carbon dioxide emissions. Expense of Reducing Emissions</p>
        <p>The carbon dioxide emissions are produced by burning fuels like coal and oil, the nation's major sources of energy, and are believed to be warming the earth by trapping heat in the atmosphere in a process like that in a greenhouse. Reducing those emissions would be costly to the nation's businesses, which are lobbying against quick action. The United States contributes about a fifth of the world's annual carbon dioxide emissions, according to Government statistics.</p>
        <p>The division in the Administration on global warming has become more apparent in recent days as officials discussed what position to take at an international conference that begins late next week in the Netherlands. The conference is expected to endorse at least stabilizing carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>William K. Reilly, Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, proposed that the United States support the stabilization measure at the Netherlands conference but was rebuffed at a meeting last Friday of a working group of the White House Domestic Policy Council, several people familiar with the meeting said.</p>
        <p>White House officials favor a worldwide agreement that would initially acknowledge the problem of global warming and later work out specific steps to deal with it. Such a process is similar to the Vienna Convention and Montreal Protocol that produced an agreement to phase out use of the chemicals that deplete the earth's ozone layer.</p>
        <p>The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, a United Nations-sponsored group, is currently working on ways to deal with possible global warming and is expected to produce a report next year that could lead to negotiations. Members of Congress and environmentalists assert that the process will take at least five years to complete. Criticism of White House Stance</p>
        <p>Marlin Fitzwater, the White House spokesman, today reiterated the President's support for that process and defended the Administration against criticism that it is moving too slowly.</p>
        <p>''I think there are very legitimate concerns about what these policies mean for long-term economic impact and, well, economic impact in the macro sense,'' Mr. Fitzwater said. ''And those issues need to be considered and are being considered. But that does not diminish our overall commitment to deal with the global warming problem. There are economic aspects of this that cannot be ignored just blindly in the search for global warming solutions.''</p>
        <p>The White House position was criticized today by 11 environmental and energy groups. ''President Bush said during the campaign that he would use the 'White House effect' to combat the greenhouse effect,'' the groups said in a statement. ''But a year later, the White House team hasn't even come out of the dugout.''</p>
        <p>The environmentalists are concerned that the Administration has not moved quickly enough to fulfill a commitment it made in July with six other industrial nations at the Paris Economic Summit to limit emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases.</p>
        <p>On Capitol Hill, the President's policies on global warming are being challenged by both Democrats and Republicans. Members in both houses have proposed legislation that would force reductions in carbon dioxide emissions. 'Dragging Its Feet'</p>
        <p>On the Senate floor Tuesday night, Senator Tim Wirth, a Colorado Democrat, accused the Administration of ''dragging its feet'' on the issue, which he says is the most urgent facing the nation and world.</p>
        <p>''We're getting the wool pulled over our heads by a group that has its head in the sand,'' Mr. Wirth said.</p>
        <p>In a letter to Mr. Bush this week, Senator John H. Chafee, Republican of Rhode Island, and four other Republican Senators, urged the President to use the Netherlands meeting to ''put the United States in a position of world leadership.''</p>
        <p>''We are concerned that, unless you provide personal leadership on this issue, the United States will continue to send mixed signals to the world community,'' the senators wrote.</p>
        <p>They proposed aggressive action calling for the signing of an agreement on global warming no later than March 1991 and a commitment to freeze carbon dioxide emissions in the United States at 1988 or 1989 levels.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nitze, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State, told a conference on global warming Tuesday that resisting a commitment to stabilize the emissions may prove difficult.</p>
        <p>''The pressure for some sort of stabilization effort is going to be very strong and very hard to resist,'' Mr. Nitze said. He said his comments reflected his personal views and not a change in the Administration position. But environmentalists said the statement is the first in which an Administration official has publicly suggested that the United States may have to change its stated position.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Nitze said his view on the subject had changed since he attended a meeting in Geneva earlier this month on climate change. More than a third of the 43 countries at the meeting expressed support for an agreement that included at least an initial goal of stabilizing emissions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
