<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Return L.I.'s Barrier Islands to Nature, a Panel Urges</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="307453"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAST EROSION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEACHES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ZONING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FIRE ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND REGIONAL PLANNING BOARD</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMITT, ERIC</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/Fire Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coast Erosion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3D81E38F93BA35751C1A96F948260" item-length="1240" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Return L.I.'s Barrier Islands to Nature, a Panel Urges</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMITT, ERIC</byline>
      <dateline>HAUPPAUGE, L.I., Dec. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A Long Island planning agency recommended today that almost 5,000 houses and businesses on Fire Island and in other shore resort areas threatened by erosion be gradually eliminated and that the barrier islands they stand on be returned to nature.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A Long Island planning agency recommended today that almost 5,000 houses and businesses on Fire Island and in other shore resort areas threatened by erosion be gradually eliminated and that the barrier islands they stand on be returned to nature.</p>
        <p>A Long Island planning agency recommended today that almost 5,000 houses and businesses on Fire Island and in other shore resort areas threatened by erosion be gradually eliminated and that the barrier islands they stand on be returned to nature.</p>
        <p>The proposal, by the Long Island Regional Planning Board, comes only a few months after Hurricane Hugo devastated the developed barrier islands off South Carolina and at a time of concern that global warming is raising sea levels.</p>
        <p>As adopted by the board the proposal is strictly a planning guide, and would require approval by several state agencies before it could be adopted. But to be enforceable, coastal communities would have to be persuaded to incorporate the plan into their zoning laws. The review process by the state and by municipalities could take at least a year. Even then, no buildings would be razed without significant damage.</p>
        <p>But property owners immediately attacked the plan as an unwarranted government intrusion that would do little to control erosion of the shifting barrier islands, buffers between the ocean and Long Island.</p>
        <p>Under the plan, buildings in vulnerable coastal areas that suffer storm or erosion damage costing more than half their replacement value would be destroyed. Either the state or local government would buy the property.</p>
        <p>Advocates of the program, which is part of a comprehensive strategy to control erosion and flooding along 106 miles of barrier beach in Nassau and Suffolk Counties, said it would reduce development pressures on the shoreline, increase public open space and recreation areas and reduce costly government programs that protect private waterfront development.</p>
        <p>''The policy is more environmentally sensitive as to how the barrier beaches should be maintained,'' said Lee E. Koppelman, executive director of the regional planning board.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koppelman and other planning board officials stressed that no one is talking about tearing down existing houses. ''No residential communities are going to disappear overnight,'' he said. The planning board recommended, for example, that some structures could be moved to higher ground.</p>
        <p>The plan would not prevent communities from taking steps to protect development from erosion.</p>
        <p>Just how many houses could be razed under the policy depends on the weather, the rate of erosion and other environmental factors, planners said. Erosion under normal conditions alone might claim only a handful of houses over the 35-year period that the planning board recommendations cover. A storm of Hurricane Hugo's magnitude, however, could have devastating consequences, planners said. Considering Compensation</p>
        <p>Long before Hurricane Hugo struck the Carolina coastline, the State of South Carolina moved to fight erosion. In 1988 the Legislature passed the Beach Front Management Act, which prohibits privately owned structures like businesses and sea walls from being rebuilt on the same spot if they are destroyed during a storm.</p>
        <p>South Carolina courts have upheld the law, but judges have ruled that the state must compensate owners for the loss of their property. In the South Carolina General Assembly meeting next January, legislators and Gov. Carroll A. Campbell Jr. are expected to grapple with a policy on compensation.</p>
        <p>In Massachusetts, concern for the shoreline, particularly on Cape Cod, led to a call in the state Legislature this year for a coastal planning commission. It would curb further development rather than return seaside areas to nature.</p>
        <p>About one-quarter of Cape Cod is protected by the National Parks Service as a National Seashore, a 27-year Federal program which acquires coastal lands and prohibits development.</p>
        <p>While environmental groups hailed the proposals as important safeguards for the barrier beaches, town officials voiced mixed reaction. ''No one can make the case that having all those houses on Fire Island is good for the barrier beach,'' said Frank Jones, the Supervisor of Islip, which includes several Fire Island communities. 'Doesn't Make a Lot of Sense'</p>
        <p>The reaction was more critical in neighboring Babylon, where the planning board recommended that the town not renew long-term land leases on about 450 homes in West Gilgo Beach, Gilgo Beach, Oak Island, Oak Beach and Captree Island that expire in 2000.</p>
        <p>''At a time of a serious housing shortage on Long Island, the notion that we should destroy 450 homes doesn't make a lot of sense,'' said Arthur Pitts, the Supervisor of Babylon.</p>
        <p>Property owners angrily denounced the plan. ''I'm scared and frustrated to think I may be losing my house because of this policy,'' said Jed Meade, a 39-year-old dockbuilder in Oak Beach who lives in a house that his grandfather built 80 years ago.</p>
        <p>''It's imposing too much government control over an individual's rights, and it won't accomplish anything anyway,'' said Edward B. Joachim, a resident on Dune Road in Westhampton Beach, where seven of 270 houses have been lost to severe erosion, and 40 more are in danger of falling into the sea. Possibility of Bond Act</p>
        <p>Gerard Stoddard, president of the Fire Island Association, an organization of 1,500 homeowners, said that ''many peoples' lives are centered around'' their homes on Fire Island. ''They have every right to be concerned now,'' Mr. Stoddard said.</p>
        <p>Several officials questioned how the program would be financed. Mr. Koppelman suggested that money to pay owners of damaged houses could be raised from a special state or county bond act.</p>
        <p>''Oh, yeah? And there's a Santa Claus and the tooth fairy, too,'' said Tony Bullock, Supervisor of the Town of East Hampton. ''What government can afford to do that now?''</p>
        <p>The plan adopted today advances work in a 1984 study that the regional planning board conducted to prepare for the impact of a major storm or hurricane. But the latest plan is a broader and more definitive set of strategies to protect existing residential and commercial development, insure safeguards for recreational areas, including Jones Beach State Park, and eliminate some private development altogether. Other Areas Reviewed</p>
        <p>In addition to Fire Island and the Gilgo Beach area, the Dune Road area of Westhampton Beach is identified in the plan as a threatened area where damaged houses should not be rebuilt and Montauk Point as an area that needs special protection.</p>
        <p>Another area listed as vulnerable is Long Beach, at the eastern end of the Island, but that area is so built up, the report said, that it should be preserved and protected. Other areas, like most of the Hamptons, are judged less threatened by erosion.</p>
        <p>The plan now advances to Secretary of State Gail S. Shaffer, whose office in Albany oversees coastal planning in the state. Ms. Shaffer, who has voiced support for principles outlined in the plan, is expected to approve the planning board's recommendations and incorporate them into the state's coastal plan.</p>
        <p>The plan would be subject to review by other state agencies, principally the Department of Environmental Conservation, and municipalities on Long Island. Each of the Island's South Shore towns is now drafting new, long-term waterfront zoning regulations.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Ms. Shaffer, William F. Brown, said the state would urge the towns to include the board's recommendations in their revised zoning codes, making the proposals enforceable. He said public hearings on the proposals might also be conducted.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
