<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Passing On the Legacy of Nature</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="240413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND OPINION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NATURE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLAUS, LINDA A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DE1039F935A25757C0A96F948260" item-length="880" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Passing On the Legacy of Nature</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Linda A. Claus; Linda A. Claus lives in Plainview.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLAUS, LINDA A</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ONE of my father's most nourishing gifts was an appreciation and deep love of nature. There are few things that fill me with joy more than the discovery of a fawn pausing to drink from an icy brook, or the sight of a porpoise swimming off the shore of a deserted beach. The vibrant cacophony of color that explodes on a hillside as autumn takes possession brings with it an ecstasy that enriches my life and leaves me searching for ever more fulfillment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ONE of my father's most nourishing gifts was an appreciation and deep love of nature. There are few things that fill me with joy more than the discovery of a fawn pausing to drink from an icy brook, or the sight of a porpoise swimming off the shore of a deserted beach. The vibrant cacophony of color that explodes on a hillside as autumn takes possession brings with it an ecstasy that enriches my life and leaves me searching for ever more fulfillment.</p>
        <p>ONE of my father's most nourishing gifts was an appreciation and deep love of nature. There are few things that fill me with joy more than the discovery of a fawn pausing to drink from an icy brook, or the sight of a porpoise swimming off the shore of a deserted beach. The vibrant cacophony of color that explodes on a hillside as autumn takes possession brings with it an ecstasy that enriches my life and leaves me searching for ever more fulfillment.</p>
        <p>When I was a child, Sunday, the day I looked forward to, gave me an opportunity to snuggle up to my father on the couch for an evening of television. Although ''Victory at Sea'' did not capture my attention, ''Mutual of Omaha's Wild Kingdom'' always kept me enthralled. My father would comment on the beauty of the landscape, even as a lion crouched for the kill.</p>
        <p>Dad also kept a copy of National Geographic around the house and pointed out how nature enhanced our lives. He could identify birds by their calls and often held whistling conversations with them before he left for work. I can also remember times, after winning the battle for the window in the back seat of the car, when my view of the landscape would be disturbed by roadside litter. The importance of preserving the beauty around us began to take form at that early age.</p>
        <p>As my intelligence grew, so did my knowledge of the scope of the problem. Litter was not the only material marring our precious heritage. There was the problem of air pollution caused by factories that burned fossil fuel inefficiently. Larger and faster automobiles produced rising amounts of carbon dioxide. Acid rain was found to cause large fish kills up north and was being blamed for the destruction of woodland.</p>
        <p>I also became aware that my lifelong hometown of Plainview-Old Bethpage was renowned for having one of the most hazardous landfills in the country. I felt hatred for the men who dumped these poisonous substances as well as for the people who were in a position to stop the abuse but who chose instead to accept bribes to turn the other way. I was overwhelmed by a sense of futility because of the magnitude of the situation. My inner feelings of rage could have no impact on the problem, however, and although I had fantasies of capturing someone in the act of illegal dumping I did not see what I could do single-handedly to assuage the destruction.</p>
        <p>In the summer of 1987 I read a book that helped crystallize my conviction. Rachel Carson's ''Silent Spring'' was published in 1962, but her insight into our current ecological problems was astounding. As the title suggests, if we fail in our efforts to stop the widespread annihilation of our natural resources through toxic chemicals, we may find ourselves approaching a day when there will be an absence of nature altogether.</p>
        <p>Besides the damage accomplished through industry's lack of concern and unwillingness to sacrifice profits, and government's infatuation with the destruction of life rather than improving the quality of it, each one of us contributes to the devastation of our planet. Miss Carson examines the effect of insecticides and herbicides on our scarce water supply, as well as on the food chain, from the smallest insect up to man.</p>
        <p>The toxic chemicals that have been introduced into our environment are cumulative in our bodies, and their deleterious effects have yet to be determined. The poisons we apply to our lawns and shrubberies will eventually wind up on our dinner table and in our breast milk. And as I read this enlightening book written almost 30 years ago, the New Jersey shore was experiencing an onslaught of dead porpoises washing up on shore, due to some ''mysterious'' illness.</p>
        <p>The legacy I hand down to my children is very different from the one I received from my father many years ago. I teach them never to accept nature the way it is, but to work hard to bring it back to its full potential. It frightens me to realize that they are growing up in an era in which toxic dumps, beach closings and smog alerts are taken for granted.</p>
        <p>It is important for them to realize that this is not the way it is supposed to be. I stress the importance of knowledge in an area in which deceptions abound, and the price we pay is our precious wildlife. An informed citizen does not place complete trust in an Environmental Protection Agency that allows destructive practices to continue. I teach them never to accept our current circumstances with apathy.</p>
        <p>Like my father before me, I have planted the seeds of conservation deep within my children. Our family camping trips provide many fertile opportunities to nourish the love and devotion that is needed to protect the future of our environment so that we may hand it on to future generations.</p>
        <p>As we packed our camping equipment to head home after our last vacation, I noticed my 14-year-old daughter, Katie, walking around the campsite picking up paper and debris with unaccustomed cheerfulness. I called her over to thank her and asked why she was performing this task voluntarily. She explained that when she sets up her tent, she cleans the area so she is not sleeping on trash. She realized that when we camp in the woods, we are living with the animals. She is sure that they would not want to sleep on garbage either.</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND OPINION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
