<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 30-Year Feud Divides Experts On Meteorology</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="294214"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRYSON, REID A (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUOMI, VERNER E (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7DA1530F937A15753C1A96F948260" item-length="1750" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 30-Year Feud Divides Experts On Meteorology</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
      <dateline>MADISON, Wis.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: REID A. BRYSON and Verner E. Suomi of the University of Wisconsin at Madison started their careers as best friends, colleagues who helped each other build homes on adjacent lots and who together ran the university's meteorology department, making it one of the best in the nation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: REID A. BRYSON and Verner E. Suomi of the University of Wisconsin at Madison started their careers as best friends, colleagues who helped each other build homes on adjacent lots and who together ran the university's meteorology department, making it one of the best in the nation.</p>
        <p>REID A. BRYSON and Verner E. Suomi of the University of Wisconsin at Madison started their careers as best friends, colleagues who helped each other build homes on adjacent lots and who together ran the university's meteorology department, making it one of the best in the nation.</p>
        <p>But then they clashed, mainly over the best way to approach their research. Their arguments, fueled by two powerful egos, became so sharp that eventually the two scientists simply stopped discussing the things they held most dear. Though they remained in the same department and lived in the same neighborhood, they went separate ways scientifically, avoiding each other's turf, moving ever deeper into different branches of the same field.</p>
        <p>At its root, the clash was over the scientific method. By nature, Dr. Suomi tended to be a fact gatherer, while Dr. Bryson was more interested in theories that tied facts together.</p>
        <p>Though most scientific battles are waged behind the scenes, their feud flared openly at times and has become famous among meteorologists. Their case shows how personal forces often drive the research enterprise.</p>
        <p>It also sheds light on different ways to approach a key environmental issue: whether the ''greenhouse gases'' accumulating in the atmosphere are warming the earth. Dr. Suomi, who won acclaim for atmospheric observations from space, would approach the problem by gathering more data, trying to tease new clues from nature on the riddle of long-term climatic shift. Dr. Bryson, who gained fame for theorizing about the Earth's climatic past and future, would press for new ideas to better understand current trends.</p>
        <p>Each scholar earned many honors during a long career. Dr. Bryson, who is now 69 years old, and Dr. Suomi, now 73, recently reflected on their differing styles in separate interviews. And still, decades after the initial battles, they made uneasy, wincing references to one another.</p>
        <p>''We had some fierce rows,'' said Dr. Bryson, gripping a pipe as he sat with his arms crossed in his office on the 13th floor of a university building. ''That's long since gone. Now we avoid them.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Suomi, three floors below, said: ''In the beginning, we worked together very well. But then our interests shifted. He was interested in climate at a time when everybody thought it was sinful,'' adding that some scientists still feel the field is ''sinfully'' unscientific because long-range climatic predictions are very difficult to do. A Truce in the Battle</p>
        <p>Colleagues and former students say the two have achieved an uneasy peace.</p>
        <p>''Both of them have big egos,'' said Robert A. Ragotzkie, a University of Wisconsin scientist who studied and worked with both. ''They almost had to go their separate ways.'' Champ B. Tanner, another Wisconsin scientist, said, ''They viewed science in very different ways,'' adding that Dr. Bryson was always trying to leap ahead to make predictions, while Dr. Suomi took a more incremental approach that focused on novel ways to gather new data.</p>
        <p>Dr. Suomi is a major figure among international scientists for his use of space systems to improve weather forecasting. He has won a National Medal of Science award and a presidential citation. In 1964, he invented the satellite camera that produces the photographs that appear in weather reports. He was also a driving force in the 1959 founding of the Global Atmospheric Research Program, an effort to gather meteorological data that involved dozens of countries.</p>
        <p>At Wisconsin, he founded the Space Science and Engineering Center, which he directed from 1966 to 1988. He is now a professor emeritus of meteorology. Pioneer in Climate Studies</p>
        <p>Dr. Bryson is known internationally for his pioneering studies in world climatology, especially in climatic changes resulting from human activities, and in paleoclimatology, which seeks to understand ancient weather patterns. He was on the council of the Smithsonian Institution and has written five books, one of which, ''Climates of Hunger,'' which he proudly says won a literary prize. He is a published poet and a weaver.</p>
        <p>At Wisconsin, he founded the meteorology department, the Center for Climatic Research and helped found the Institute for Environmental Studies, which he directed from 1970 to 1985. He is also now a professor emeritus.</p>
        <p>Both men received Ph.D's in meteorology from the University of Chicago, where they met in the early 1940's. Dr. Bryson initially got a job at Wisconsin in the geology and geography department, but soon founded the meteorology department. He quickly asked Dr. Suomi to join him. By 1948 the two men were happily working 60-hour weeks and skipping vacations to try to advance the fledgling effort. They took two-year rotations as departmental chairman.</p>
        <p>In the early 1950's, they bought a 2.7-acre lot on Madison's west side, flipped a coin to divide it, posed as contractors to get discounts on construction supplies, and helped build each other's houses. Also in the early 1950's, they wrote a series of papers together. A Split in the Friendship</p>
        <p>But by the late 1950's and early 1960's, things started to sour. Dr. Bryson had always been interested in history, having once considered a career in archeology. Now he wanted to move the department in that direction, looking not only into the short-range phenomena that make up the weather but climatic patterns over the millennia.</p>
        <p>Dr. Suomi, meanwhile, was becoming ever more fascinated with current weather patterns from space, inventing new gadgets to measure them. He joked with students about the ''ignorosphere,'' an area like the Earth's troposphere and stratosphere that scientists knew nothing about because they had failed to measure it.</p>
        <p>Some of the first disputes had do with hiring faculty, each man wanting to make an imprint. ''When you have to make a decision and you disagree, either one or the other is not going to like it,'' Dr. Bryson recalled. ''We had our differences.''</p>
        <p>Then came debates over how science should be done and what was the correct interplay between gathering data and theorizing. Raised voices often gave way to tense silence.</p>
        <p>As the two avoided each other more and more, their fields of interest drew increasingly apart. ''We decided to work in mutually exclusive areas so we wouldn't tread on the other guy's territory,'' Dr. Bryson said.  Dr. Suomi pioneered observing the earth's atmosphere from space. His first invention was a radiometer that measured the amount of heat the earth gives off. It was launched into orbit on the Explorer 7 satellite in 1959.</p>
        <p>Then came the weather camera, which ingeniously took rock-steady pictures even though it was spinning rapidly as the satellite rotated. First lofted in 1966, the camera is still used on weather satellites today. Yet another invention, first shot into space in 1980, measures the atmosphere's temperature and water vapor. 'I'm Basically Lazy'</p>
        <p>Hands clasped behind his head, Dr. Suomi said his chosen field was scientifically simple. ''It seems complicated to the person who doesn't understand technology,'' he said. ''But it's not. I'm basically lazy. I want to get as much out of this as I can with the smallest amount of work.'' His simple technologies, for instance, have produced reams of useful information that have kept thousands of scientists busy.</p>
        <p>By contrast, he said, Dr. Bryson's field, climate prediction, ''is a tougher job'' because complex changes in the earth's atmosphere over time make it difficult to accurately deduce past or future climatic states. ''We aren't able to do it well now. I mean, there are hints that you can do something. But not that much.''</p>
        <p>While Dr. Suomi takes pride in how his work has improved short-range weather predictions over days and sometimes a week or more, his scientific conservatism is such that he avoids forecasting. ''I like to observe more,'' he said, ''to see what's out there.''</p>
        <p>By contrast, Dr. Bryson became fascinated with tying together disparate observations to make discoveries and predictions that were inherently unobservable. He founded the Center for Climatic Research in 1963 to fathom the unseeable. For instance, he deduced past climates from analysis of ancient tree rings. In another case, he analyzed primordial pollen gains to discover that arid and dusty parts of India had previously been much wetter, and he devised a system of land use that helped reduce the overgrazing that had caused the dryness.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bryson also helped pioneer the use of computers for long-range climatic forecasts. In contrast to Dr. Suomi, who exhaustively tried to gather facts, Dr. Bryson fixed his computer models so they would single out one factor, like the slow wobble of the earth's axis or the dust from volcanoes, to see if these influenced past and future climates.</p>
        <p>''Scientists like to say they go from A to B to C to D - which is nonsense,'' Dr. Bryson said. ''A good scientist goes from A to D and then goes back and figures out how it really should be from A to D. The productive scientist is going to make a jump, which means that, generally speaking, a really creative scientist doesn't make a very good computer programmer.'' Risking a Career</p>
        <p>One way to foster leaps of logic is to study many different fields, he said, so new connections come into view. But such ''integrators'' face career risks, he said. ''You'll never get a Nobel Prize, for example,'' he said. ''For that you've got to be in a single discipline.''</p>
        <p>But there is a satisfaction in accurate predictions, he said. For example, he noted that the long-range forecasts he made in the 1970's of continued drought in Africa have turned out to be correct, and if taken seriously might have helped relieve the continent's suffering. ''Remember the big famine in Ethiopia?'' he asked. ''In 1973 I said that famine in that band across Africa could continue. I said the rains will not come back normally in this century. All kinds of people said, 'You can't say that!' Fact is, the rains haven't come back.''</p>
        <p>Today, each scientist is in hot pursuit of characteristic projects. Dr. Bryson is writing a book on climate and human ecology in collaboration with an archeologist. Dr. Suomi is helping the space agency gather and analyze data from distant planets, most recently, from the Voyager flyby of Neptune.</p>
        <p>And each scientist says their feud, though intense years ago, has left few hard feelings.</p>
        <p>''Heavens,'' Dr. Suomi observed, ''we're neighbors to this day and don't fight.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
