<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Clean Air Plan Called Energy Policy in the Making</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="285511"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUEL EFFICIENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6D61638F937A1575AC0A96F948260" item-length="1078" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Clean Air Plan Called Energy Policy in the Making</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As members of Congress and interest groups look more closely at President Bush's clean air proposal, many are saying it is not just an anti-pollution plan but a national energy policy in the making.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As members of Congress and interest groups look more closely at President Bush's clean air proposal, many are saying it is not just an anti-pollution plan but a national energy policy in the making.</p>
        <p>As members of Congress and interest groups look more closely at President Bush's clean air proposal, many are saying it is not just an anti-pollution plan but a national energy policy in the making.</p>
        <p>The measure would dramatically reshape the nation's use of energy in the 1990's and into the next century, promoting greater reliance on natural gas and other clean-burning fuels at the expense of coal and gasoline. And it has broad implications for energy conservation, fuel imports and regional economic development.</p>
        <p>The President's legislation, if passed, would have such an important effect on energy policy that it could undercut the national energy strategy the Administration is scheduled to complete in December 1990. Linda G. Stuntz, the Deputy Under Secretary of Energy for Policy, called the clean air measure ''the most profound energy legislation Congress considers this session'' and said it would have been better if the national energy plan had been in place first. But the President, she said, is determined ''to move now'' on environmental legislation. In his campaign, Mr. Bush promised to give the environment a high priority.</p>
        <p>The Bush bill ''is energy policy on a grand scale,'' said Representative Philip R. Sharp, an Indiana Democrat whose House Energy and Commerce energy subcommittee is reviewing the legislation's effects on energy. And William G. Rosenberg, an Environmental Protection Agency official, said energy and environment are ''two sides of the same coin,'' because the burning of oil and coal contributes so heavily to health hazards and environmental damage. The Focus Has Changed</p>
        <p>Though cleaner fuels like natural gas and low-sulfur coal may seem a self-evident solution to such problems, Mr. Rosenberg said, the nation has not always followed that path.</p>
        <p>In 1978, for example, Congress limited the use of natural gas for generating electricity because of fears of a gas shortage. In 1977, to protect miners' jobs in regions that produced high-sulfur coal, the lawmakers passed an amendment to the Clean Air Act that took away the economic advantages of burning low-sulfur coal. That is one reason many utilities use high-sulfur coal, a major cause of air pollution and acid rain. Mr. Sharp noted that when the Clean Air Act was amended in 1977, the energy subcommittee did not even have hearings on it.</p>
        <p>In Montreal this week, the 3,400 delegates to the World Energy Conference focused not on customary concerns like oil and gas reserves, but on environmental problems associated with those fuels: urban smog, acid rain and global warming.</p>
        <p>The President's bill, now under consideration in the House Energy and Commerce environment subcommittee, addresses urban smog, acid rain and airborne toxic chemicals. Other legislators are sponsoring measures that would attack other problems and in some cases impose more stringent restrictions.</p>
        <p>Proposals to strengthen existing acid rain and smog laws have been sidetracked for more than 10 years by conflicts among regions, industries and interest groups. Congress may try to smooth those differences, but the energy issues will still be crucial.</p>
        <p>The Administration says its clean air proposals favor no fuel over any other. But many participants in the debate say natural gas would be a clear winner.</p>
        <p>To fight acid rain, which causes widespread damage to forests, lakes and buildings and is suspected of endangering human health, utilities would have to cut sulfur dioxide emissions in half by 2000. About 20 million tons of sulfur dioxide are emitted annually into the skies; three-quarters of that comes from utilities, which would have to reduce their emissions by 10 million tons.</p>
        <p>The utilities expect this cutback to force some plants to switch from coal to the natural gas. The American Gas Association estimates a modest sales increase, and gas producers would welcome it. Gas consumption declined 25 percent since 1970, although there have been modest gains in the last two years.</p>
        <p>Low-sulfur coal is a another likely winner, since it produces fewer emissions than its high-sulfur cousin.</p>
        <p>The cost of reducing emissions creates an incentive for utilities to press their customers to conserve because less demand means less burned coal and lower emissions.</p>
        <p>The President's plan includes incentives to encourage utilities to use new anti-pollution devices so they can burn high-sulfur coal, which the nation has in abundance, without emitting large amounts of sulfur into the air.</p>
        <p>The Administration says the United States can enhance its national security by developing ways to burn coal cleanly, since it would then rely less on imported fuels.</p>
        <p>To reduce smog, the White House bill says that in 1997 manufacturers should be producing one million cars a year running on fuels like methanol that burn more cleanly than gasoline. The cars would be sold in the nine most polluted cities. Nuclear Power Could Benefit</p>
        <p>Methanol can be produced from natural gas, but much of what might be needed to supply a new fleet of methanol-powered cars would be imported. Another potential car fuel, ethanol, is made from grain and could open a new market for American farmers. But doubts have been raised by industry and others that the President's ambitious target can be reached.</p>
        <p>Nuclear power, now much out of favor, could benefit from the President's bill. The legislation would raise the price of fuel by requiring more anti-pollution equipment and the development of more expensive alternative fuels, and this could make the price of nuclear power more competitive. Nuclear power plants do not emit sulfur dioxide, but they do produce radioactive waste.</p>
        <p>Energy choices made in the legislation could affect regional development. A developing ethanol market could benefit the farms of the Middle West. Increased demand for natural gas could be a boon to the energy-rich Southwest, which has suffered hard times through much of the 1980's.</p>
        <p>''Between the clean air bill and the deregulation of natural gas, this could be the first good news in energy states in eight years,'' said Representative Mike Synar, an Oklahoma Democrat.</p>
        <p>Mr. Synar also said there would be winners and losers among states in industrial development. Businesses that use a great deal of energy would be tempted to move to states that have lower fuel costs, he said. By making some forms of energy more expensive, the clean air legislation could help determine which states they are.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
