<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times; When Winter Will Neither Chill Nor Charm</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="284609"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITGANG, HERBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCKIBBEN, BILL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">END OF NATURE, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DE1630F933A1575AC0A96F948260" item-length="943" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times; When Winter Will Neither Chill Nor Charm</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Herbert Mitgang</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MITGANG, HERBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  The End of Nature  By Bill McKibben  226 pages. Random House. $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  The End of Nature  By Bill McKibben  226 pages. Random House. $19.95.</p>
        <p>The End of Nature  By Bill McKibben  226 pages. Random House. $19.95.</p>
        <p>Toward the end of his pensive and alarming book, Bill McKibben declares with quiet assurance, ''There is no future in loving nature.'' A strange remark, but he explains that while he loves winter best of all the seasons, he tries not to love it too much because he fears that in some not so distant January the snow will fall as warm rain.</p>
        <p>''The End of Nature'' is written to have the effect of a fire bell in the night. In this respect it succeeds: a frightening tocsin comes through loud and clear. The author, a former staff writer for The New Yorker, is saying metaphorically that the sky is falling and it's not just Chicken Little talking, it's the view of some leading scientists in the United States and Europe.</p>
        <p>His falling sky is the greenhouse effect -the progressive warming of the earth's surface from the blanketing effect of man-made carbon dioxide in the atmosphere. Because heat is prevented from leaving the earth by carbon dioxide, water vapor and ozone (acting like the glass in a greenhouse), much of it goes back into the ground. A 10 percent increase in atmospheric carbon dioxide over the last century has caused some scientists to predict a long-term warming of the earth's climate - with disastrous results for the environment.</p>
        <p>Mr. McKibben has pulled together a great deal of scientific, environmental and Government information, joined it with first-hand observations from several unspoiled areas of the country, and placed his material in a historical context. His reasoning recalls the effort of 19th-century and early 20th-century naturalists to protect the earth and its bounties from despoilation in the name of progress. He has added a message of his own about the need for new thinking - calling, idealistically, even for a change in our everyday life styles to prevent the natural world from being destroyed by energy-hungry, labor-saving civilization.</p>
        <p>''In the course of about a hundred years, our various engines and fires have released a substantial amount of the carbon that has been buried over time,'' he writes. ''It is as if someone had scrimped and saved his entire life, and then spent every cent on one fantastic week's debauch. We are living on our capital, as we began to realize during the gas crises of the 1970's. But it is more than waste, more than a binge. We are spending that capital in such a way as to alter the atmosphere. It is like taking that week's fling and, in the process, contracting a horrid disease.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. McKibben casually introduces other elements of fear - genetic engineering, acid rain, depletion of the ozone - the main part of his book concerns what will happen to the weather as a result of the greenhouse effect. He is standing on the shoulders of giants in physics and other fields who have been aware of the hothouse threat at least since the turn of the century. Scientists have found that the upper layer of the oceans, where air and sea meet, absorbs very little excess carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Most of the carbon dioxide being pumped into the air by millions of smokestacks, furnaces and car exhausts remains in the air, presumably warming the planet. When this occurs, there is grave harm to rivers and oceans, to animal and plant life, to people on every continent.</p>
        <p>Taking his subject out of the hands of science-fiction futurists, Mr. McKibben writes: ''By the end of nature I do not mean the end of the world. The rain will still fall and the sun shine, though differently than before.'' And then - as often occurs in the book - he becomes elusive and hortatory: ''When I say 'nature,' I mean a certain set of human ideas about the world and our place in it. But the death of those ideas begins with concrete changes in the reality around us - changes that scientists can measure and enumerate. More and more frequently, these changes will clash with our perceptions, until, finally, our sense of nature as eternal and separate is washed away, and we will see all too clearly what we have done.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McKibben digests and conveys a great deal of difficult information about man-made dangers, and he does so stylishly. It is a measure of his skill that nearly all this material is explained clearly, often with vivid examples and analogies. Apparently inspired by the language and ideas of Thoreau, John Burroughs, John Muir, Edward Abbey and E. B. White, all of whom are quoted about the glories of the natural world beyond their doors in ''The End of Nature,'' Mr. McKibben also dares to create lovely sentences. To mention one: ''The earth is a museum of divine intent.''</p>
        <p>Where ''The End of Nature'' wanders off the track is when the author gets sentimental instead of delivering - as his difficult subject demands -hard facts and governmental solutions. He presumes to lecture the reader about his religious notions; it is a distraction that he likes to sing hymns on Sunday morning and that the American Methodist Church has just adopted a new hymnal.</p>
        <p>The fact that a street lamp has been installed as a safety measure not far from his isolated house in the Adirondacks does not seem as momentous as he makes it appear. And some of his offhand proposals, such as cutting the size of one's wardrobe to a minimum, come across as simplistic personal whim unrelated to the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, in ''The End of Nature,'' Mr. McKibben makes an eloquent contribution to our understanding of an earthly peril - one great challenge to Washington and the world's governments. Under leaden skies, it's long past the time that we can dream of living like Thoreau at Walden Pond.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
