<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="249312"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFDC103CF931A25756C0A96F948260" item-length="880" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-11  Moscow will cut its nuclear arsenal in Europe by the end of the year, Mikhail S. Gorbachev told Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d at a meeting in the Kremlin. Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL A3-11  Moscow will cut its nuclear arsenal in Europe by the end of the year, Mikhail S. Gorbachev told Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d at a meeting in the Kremlin. Page A1</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-11  Moscow will cut its nuclear arsenal in Europe by the end of the year, Mikhail S. Gorbachev told Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d at a meeting in the Kremlin. Page A1</p>
        <p>The cuts in Soviet nuclear arms described by Mikhail S. Gorbachev in a meeting with Mr. Baker, are likely to provide political ammunition for NATO nations. A11</p>
        <p>Kabul urges Bush to pursue peace A10</p>
        <p>To help oust Gen. Manuel Noriega, President Bush announced a series of measures, including the deployment of nearly 2,000 additional troops to Panama. A1</p>
        <p>Panama's plan to annul the election was rejected by the opposition, which said it was prepared for talks only if Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega stepped down. A8</p>
        <p>The armed force ordered to Panama by President Bush will be small and will move slowly into the country over the next three weeks. A8</p>
        <p>Venezuela urges Panama talks A9</p>
        <p>A worldwide ban on the ivory trade will be sought by Kenya, a move intended to preserve its fast dwindling elephant herds. A5</p>
        <p>In China, Mikhail S. Gorbachev is expected to face a snub so blunt as to remind him that there is still a chill in the air. There is a studied lack of enthusiasm among some Chinese officials. A3</p>
        <p>In Argentina, Carlos Saul Menem ended his campaign to outpourings of adoration and expectation. The memory of Juan D. Peron came vibrantly alive. A3</p>
        <p>In its Namibian peacekeeping force, the United Nations said that it was doubling the police component to get the stalled independence process moving again. A7</p>
        <p>Beirut rivals agree to respect truce A11</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A12-13, A32, B8-9  To Exxon's board of directors, an environmentalist may be named under a recommendation from the president of the company, bowing to pressure from large stockholders. A1</p>
        <p>Ronald Reagan's antimissile plan will not be developed by the Bush Administration for two years while it studies a proposal to alter it, the project director said. A1</p>
        <p>A top aide to Jim Wright resigned after reports on his criminal past sparked a wave of public outrage and fanned the controversy surrounding the Congressional leader. A1</p>
        <p>U.S. negotiators on global warming have been instructed to lead the way toward a treaty, a major switch in the position of the White House. A1</p>
        <p>In the world of computer software, fear is mounting that new patents will start a flood of lawsuits that will maintain that many programs have violated patents held by others. A1</p>
        <p>Richard V. Secord was indicted on nine criminal charges, including seven counts of lying to the Congressional committees investigating the Iran-contra affair. B8</p>
        <p>The smallest crop of winter wheat in 10 years will be produced by American farmers this year because of drought, the Agriculture Department reported. A12</p>
        <p>The hate crime is gaining attention because of its particularly harmful effect on the victim and its tendency to worsen the racial tensions that already grip some communities. A12</p>
        <p>Buying crack houses in New Orleans is the Third Shiloh Missionary Baptist Church's method of fighting crime. A12</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON TALK B8</p>
        <p>They are Washington quotemasters: those political analysts, economists, Sovietologists and Washington hostesses who provide the acute observation, the pithy quote.  The President has a short but strong enemies list  REGIONAL B1-7  Finding a new schools chancellor to replace Dr. Richard R. Green will be accomplished by the start of school in September, if not earlier, Mayor Edward I. Koch hopes. A1</p>
        <p>The victims of fatal asthma attacks fall largely into two groups: black and Hispanic people and patients who have suffered from the disease for a long time. B7</p>
        <p>Peter Schmidt is still missing after more than a year. The lawyer has simply vanished, leaving behind his livelihood, his family, investigators and chagrined bar officials. B1</p>
        <p>The city's voices have an angry edge since a gang of youths beat and raped a woman in Central Park. This brutal crime was seen by many as the last straw. B1</p>
        <p>Ideas on controlling New York land proposed by the Charter Revision Commission's chairman, Frederick A. O. Schwarz Jr., have changed in response to public debate. B2</p>
        <p>The right to enact zoning laws that force adult bookstores and theaters to move out of downtown shopping areas was upheld by New York State's highest court. B1</p>
        <p>A housing regulation was rescinded by Mayor Edward I. Koch, who rejected a regulation that would have compelled some residents to move into smaller apartments. B3</p>
        <p>Asbury Park is trying to change its image from a shore town gone to seed to an upscale community, and the aggressively declasse Stone Pony may be a victim of the change. B1</p>
        <p>As an AIDS benefit, the Love Ball at Roseland was to the typical charity affair what the Sex Pistols were to Mozart. The evening had all the elements that distinguish New York City nightlife. B5</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
