<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Halt Climate Change, Scientists Try Trees</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19890810T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="266698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREES AND SHRUBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D8133AF93BA25754C0A96F948260" item-length="1915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Halt Climate Change, Scientists Try Trees</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: An article and an illustration in Science Times on July 18 about tree planting to reduce global warming misstated part of the process in which trees absorb carbon dioxide and give off oxygen. The oxygen comes from the water taken in by trees. It is produced by photolysis, the light-induced splitting of water molecules.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: An article and an illustration in Science Times on July 18 about tree planting to reduce global warming misstated part of the process in which trees absorb carbon dioxide and give off oxygen. The oxygen comes from the water taken in by trees. It is produced by photolysis, the light-induced splitting of water molecules.</p>
        <p>SCIENTISTS, foresters, environmentalists and Government officials are seriously exploring the feasibility of an ambitious long-term enterprise: planting enough trees around the world to ease the threat of global warming.</p>
        <p>The goal is unlikely to be realized dramatically or quickly, if ever, but rather in increments, tree by tree, plot by plot, field by field. Nevertheless, fundamental facts of nature have convinced a number of experts that widespread planting of trees, along with conservation of existing forests, is one of the surest, easiest and least expensive ways to begin to halt or even reverse the buildup of carbon dioxide in the air.</p>
        <p>Carbon dioxide is the gas chiefly responsible for the greenhouse effect, in which heat from the sun is trapped within the earth's atmosphere instead of radiating back into space. Dead trees release carbon dioxide into the air. There it joins with even more carbon dioxide produced by the burning of fossil fuels like coal and oil. The combination, many scientists believe, is making the greenhouse effect more intense, future global warming inevitable and major climatic disruptions more likely.</p>
        <p>But growing trees absorb carbon dioxide, storing the carbon part of the gas and releasing the rest as oxygen. Foresters and environmentalists therefore see large-scale tree planting not only as one way to head off global warming but also, if carried out on a crash basis, as a possible emergency solution if warming should seem about to get out of hand.</p>
        <p>At the moment, the foresters face an uphill battle to overcome the widespread destruction of tropical forests taking place in Brazil, Indonesia and other developing countries. Experts are nevertheless working hard to find effective ways to stimulate the growth of new forests in every part of the world.</p>
        <p>The activity is taking place on a variety of fronts.</p>
        <p>In one of the first concrete actions, the American Forestry Association, a citizens' conservation organization, has undertaken a national campaign aimed at planting 100 million new trees in American cities and towns by 1992. Although that is just a tiny fraction of all the trees in the country, proponents of the effort see it as an important beginning.</p>
        <p>Foresters are pressing experiments in farming dense stands of fast-growing trees that suck up carbon dioxide at the maximum rate. Environmentalists are advancing an ''offset'' strategy, in which industrial companies would pledge to plant enough trees to absorb the amount of carbon dioxide produced by new plants that burn fossil fuels. One such arrangement, widely viewed as a model, has already been undertaken by a Connecticut company.</p>
        <p>Over the last 18 months or so, economists and ecologists have stepped up their studies of which approaches might work and which will not, what is practical and what is fanciful. Bills now before Congress seek to promote reforestation both domestically and abroad, and the Federal Environmental Protection Agency has undertaken an extensive study of how best to go about the job.</p>
        <p>The task is not as simple and straightforward as it may seem. Most possible courses of action are fraught with questions, difficulties and uncertainties. The expanding research efforts are trying to answer some questions, but many of the difficulties may prove intractable. In the third world, for instance, economic and population pressures force millions of people to cut forests for fuel and fodder. Large-scale development also eats up much forest land, both in the third world and industrialized countries. Taxing policies in some countries provide perverse incentives to clear forests. Common, Atmospheric Pool</p>
        <p>In Brazil, one of the countries where destruction of the tropical forest is greatest, tax rates on cleared land are lower than those on forested land, said Kenneth Andrasko, the chief forest analyst for the environmental agency's climate-change group. ''It costs you money to keep a standing forest,'' he said. Dealing with political factors like this, it is widely acknowledged, is going to be difficult.</p>
        <p>Forests in the earth's temperate regions take in as much carbon as they release, the E.P.A says. In the tropics, because more forests there are destroyed than are replanted, much more carbon dioxide is released into the atmosphere than is absorbed. But both regions could contribute to the solution by planting more trees, since all trees draw carbon dioxide from a common, worldwide atmospheric pool.</p>
        <p>The task of reforestation is also made difficult because of its sheer scale. Scientists who have studied the problem calculate roughly that to absorb the carbon dioxide released into the atmosphere by human activity, it would be necessary to plant enough trees to cover an area half the size of the United States, or more. This area, according to another estimate, is equal to about one-third that of the world's combined croplands. Each year, the E.P.A. says, an area the size of Tennessee is cleared in forests in the tropics. 'Acid Test' on Intent</p>
        <p>Dr. Roger Sedjo, a forestry expert at Resources for the Future, an independent research organization in Washington, has calculated that it would require $186 billion to $372 billion, depending on land costs, to establish enough new forests to absorb the 2 billion to 3 billion tons of carbon poured into the atmosphere each year. ''We spend those kinds of moneys on national defense every year,'' Dr. Sedjo said, while forestation would be a one-time cost.</p>
        <p>The size of the job appears daunting, acknowledges Daniel J. Dudek, a senior economist at the Environmental Defense Fund, a research and advocacy group, who has studied the matter. The same is true of the overall question of global warming.</p>
        <p>''When we consider solutions to the problem, frequently people back away,'' he said. ''It's just too awesome, too large, and it will involve too many painful sacrifices.''</p>
        <p>But in fact, he said, there are ways to break the problem down into many smaller, ''sane steps'' that can be taken to ''start down the long road of developing alternatives and solutions.'' Dr. Dudek advocates the planting of trees to offset new fossil-fuel plants as one of several steps involving trees that are ''so simple and so easy'' that they would provide ''a kind of acid test about how serious we are about managing the greenhouse problem.''</p>
        <p>The model effort is widely considered to be the one announced last fall by an electric utility in Connecticut, AES Thames. The company, a subsidiary of Applied Energy Services of Arlington, Va., is helping to pay for the planting of 52 million trees on plantations and small farmers' plots in Guatemala to offset the carbon dioxide emitted by a new generating plant at Uncasville, Conn. 'No Magic Cure'</p>
        <p>Virtually no one who has seriously examined the question believes that planting trees would be a total solution to the greenhouse problem. It is generally seen as one strategy among several.</p>
        <p>''There's no magic cure,'' said R. Neil Sampson, the executive vice president of the American Forestry Association. A number of measures will be necessary ''to start the trend swinging the other way,'' he said. These especially include weaning the world away from fossil fuels through better energy efficiency and shifting to alternative energy sources such as solar power.</p>
        <p>But the world essentially runs on fossil fuels, and the weaning is likely to be painful. Some experts say that if the pain proves too much to bear, and the world finds itself some years hence on the brink of climatic disaster, mass reforestation might be a relatively easy emergency measure, a stopgap that could buy two or three decades of time. The trees would begin absorbing carbon dioxide immediately and would go on doing so for 20 or 30 years or more.</p>
        <p>''If we were to decide we had to do something quick, then a tree-planting scheme might play a significant role,'' said Gregg Marland, an environmental scientist for the Department of Energy at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory in Tennessee. Dr. Marland was one of the first to study reforestation as a possible solution to the greenhouse problem. Proposals for Making a Dent</p>
        <p>Although most people are focusing for now on relatively modest beginnings, there is no lack of suggestions. The E.P.A., in an investigation requested by Congress, is looking into a number of foresting measures that it believes are feasible and that, when combined, could make a significant dent in the problem:</p>
        <p>* Planting up to 400 million trees in urban areas of the United States. Planted strategically around buildings, they not only would soak up carbon dioxide but would also provide shade to help reduce energy use in hot weather. The American Forestry Association's drive concentrates on this option.</p>
        <p>* Offering American farmers incentives to plant more trees on erodable lands that have been set aside and kept out of cultivation in the Conservation Reserve Program.</p>
        <p>* Managing existing forests more effectively to make them more dense. The E.P.A. says the total mass of American forests could be increased 60 percent in this way.</p>
        <p>* Reforesting 20 percent of the United States' highway corridors.</p>
        <p>* Substituting traditional ''agro-forestry'' for the slash-and-burn agriculture common in the tropics. In agro-forestry, which has operated for hundreds of years in some countries, crops and trees are planted together. Tree branches and leaves are cut for fertilizing mulch. By contrast, slash-and-burn agriculture uses ashes from burned forests as fertilizer.</p>
        <p>* Undertaking large-scale tree-planting programs on degraded lands in the tropics, some of them denuded and abandoned after slash-and-burn.</p>
        <p>* Establishing ''plantations'' of fast-growing trees, especially in third world villages. The trees would be harvested on a rotating basis in the hope that villagers would not then chop down wild trees. Trees as Crops</p>
        <p>In the United States, the Department of Energy's laboratory at Oak Ridge is experimenting extensively with what it calls ''short rotation'' plantations of fast-growing trees that are ready for harvest in 10 years or less. The idea is to apply agricultural principles to trees, rotating and harvesting them like crops.</p>
        <p>Fast-growing plantations are considered particularly attractive by some experts because young, growing trees absorb carbon dioxide at the fastest rate. Mature trees absorb much less, and some scientists believe that it would be best to leave them alone, since they store large amounts of carbon.</p>
        <p>Young growth, on the other hand, could be harvested on a rotating basis and the wood substituted for coal and oil in many applications. The theory is that the trees still growing would absorb the carbon dioxide given off by the wood that is burned. Because no fossil fuels are involved, the result would be no net increase in atmospheric carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Another step being considered is putting as much of the harvested wood as possible into long-lived products such as houses, where the carbon would be sequestered for years. The forestry association has commissioned studies to determine the effectiveness of this measure.</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 10, 1989, Thursday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>An article and an illustration in Science Times on July 18 about tree planting to reduce global warming misstated part of the process in which trees absorb carbon dioxide and give off oxygen. The oxygen comes from the water taken in by trees. It is produced by photolysis, the light-induced splitting of water molecules.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 10, 1989, Thursday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>An article and an illustration in Science Times on July 18 about tree planting to reduce global warming misstated part of the process in which trees absorb carbon dioxide and give off oxygen. The oxygen comes from the water taken in by trees. It is produced by photolysis, the light-induced splitting of water molecules.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
