<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Expected to Name Conservationalist to a Top Environmental Post</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="311482"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">STATE, DEPARTMENT OF</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WORLD WILDLIFE FUND</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOHLEN, E U CURTIS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1D9133BF930A15751C1A96F948260" item-length="594" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Expected to Name Conservationalist to a Top Environmental Post</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush will soon name a professional conservationist to the State Department's top environmental post, Administration officials said today. They said the move portended a higher profile for environmental issues in foreign policy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush will soon name a professional conservationist to the State Department's top environmental post, Administration officials said today. They said the move portended a higher profile for environmental issues in foreign policy.</p>
        <p>President Bush will soon name a professional conservationist to the State Department's top environmental post, Administration officials said today. They said the move portended a higher profile for environmental issues in foreign policy.</p>
        <p>The officials said Mr. Bush intended to nominate E. U. Curtis Bohlen, a senior vice president for public policy at the World Wildlife Fund, as Assistant Secretary of State for Oceans and Environmental and Scientific Affairs. Mr. Bohlen is 62 years old and a former Deputy Assistant Secretary of the Interior for Fish and Wildlife and Parks.</p>
        <p>William K. Reilly, Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, was president of the Wildlife Fund before joining the Bush Administration. The appointment of Mr. Bohlen would give Mr. Reilly a well-placed ally in his efforts to guide policy on such international issues as negotiating a treaty to cope with global warming.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly, who has strongly advocated environmental positions, has few supporters in the Administration other than Mr. Bush. The President has backed Mr. Reilly on a number of issues, including support for strengthening the Clean Air Act. But one of those allies has been Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d, who has supported international cooperation to deal with global warming and has shown an interest in environmental issues.</p>
        <p>Scientists say they believe carbon dioxide and other industrial gases accumulating in the atmosphere are trapping radiation from the sun and will cause the earth's temperature to rise significantly in the next century. This retention of heat from the sun, the greenhouse effect, is expected to change the global climate, producing severe drought in temperate areas and flooding along seacoasts as glaciers melt and oceans expand from the heat.</p>
        <p>The international response to global warming will have a high profile on the nation's diplomatic agenda in 1990. A number of multilateral meetings to address global warming have been scheduled, culminating with a conference at the end of the year to draft a treaty to combat the greenhouse effect. Other Environmental Issues</p>
        <p>Other issues that Mr. Bohlen would face next year include a revision of the treaty to reduce use of the chemicals that are destroying the ozone layer, which protects the earth from harmful ultraviolet radiation from the sun.</p>
        <p>Under the Montreal Protocol of 1987, nations that produce chlorofluorocarbons are committed to cut such production by 50 percent by the end of the century to protect the ozone layer. Scientific evidence presented since the treaty was signed suggests that a 50 percent cut would not be enough to protect the earth's surface from ultraviolet radiation, which causes skin cancer and cataracts in humans and damages wildlife. The next round of negotiations may produce an agreement requiring a total ban on the production and use of chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>The State Department will also seek to halt or reduce the use of driftnets, 30-mile-long nets used by fishing boats from Asian nations to mine the high seas for fish and other marine life.</p>
        <p>From 1955 to 1969 Mr. Bohlen served with the State Department. He was with the Interior Department from 1969 to 1977. He is a nephew of the late Charles E. Bohlen, a former United States Ambassador to the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>As head of policy for the World Wildlife Fund in this country, Mr. Bohlen played a major role in pushing through an agreement this year by the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species to bar international traffic in elephant ivory.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
