<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Just One More Flop</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="307409"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NUCLEAR WASTES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC WEAPONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUCCA MOUNTAIN (NEV)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEVADA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WICKER, TOM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDB1438F93BA35751C1A96F948260" item-length="741" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Just One More Flop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Tom Wicker</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WICKER, TOM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Federal Government's decision to abandon its current development of the Yucca Mountain Nuclear Waste Depository in Nevada, and to start again on a new plan for the same site, repeats an old, discouraging story: a ballyhooed ''solution'' to the radioactive waste problem that turns out to be just one more flop.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Federal Government's decision to abandon its current development of the Yucca Mountain Nuclear Waste Depository in Nevada, and to start again on a new plan for the same site, repeats an old, discouraging story: a ballyhooed ''solution'' to the radioactive waste problem that turns out to be just one more flop.</p>
        <p>The Federal Government's decision to abandon its current development of the Yucca Mountain Nuclear Waste Depository in Nevada, and to start again on a new plan for the same site, repeats an old, discouraging story: a ballyhooed ''solution'' to the radioactive waste problem that turns out to be just one more flop.</p>
        <p>After 30 years of failure, this latest fiasco - two years of effort and $500 million down the drain - involves more than another American technological failure. It suggests again that the disposal of dangerous nuclear waste is a political question almost as difficult to solve as the technological problem.</p>
        <p>Because the redesigned Yucca Flats depository cannot be opened before the year 2010, even if both technological and political difficulties are overcome, the use of nuclear reactors to generate electricity will be even more constrained in the United States. Already, California law sensibly prevents new reactor construction before a solution to the waste problem is demonstrated.</p>
        <p>Because the further generation of electricity by nuclear means has been set back for decades and perhaps for much longer, economic growth and expanding population will bring increasing pressures for the use of fossil fuels. But excessive burning of coal, oil and wood already causes heavy environmental damage to the planet.</p>
        <p>Thus the Yucca Flats failure puts higher priority on energy conservation and renewable energy sources. To what extent industry and the general population can be educated or might be lured or should be forced into adopting those alternatives are questions yet to be answered.</p>
        <p>As pointed out by Matthew Wald in The New York Times, moreover, the question now has to be asked whether a solution will ever be found to the safe disposal of vast quantities of wastes that will remain dangerous to all life for literally thousands of years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wald raised the question in a scientific context. The U.S. already has tried and failed to find the answer in salt caves in Texas, Louisiana and Mississippi; engineers have talked fruitlessly of firing the wastes into space or into the sun, or of burying them under the polar ice caps; ''reprocessing'' the stuff to make it less hazardous is costly, could facilitate the proliferation of nuclear weapons and still leaves the problem of safely storing the reprocessed wastes for thousands of years; above-ground storage in special casks offers a solution only into the next century. But the question also has to be asked politically. Popular resistance in the states affected was not the least reason salt-cave storage had to be abandoned; it was perhaps the primary reason granite repositories in New Hampshire, Michigan and Maine were ruled out; and even the desert storage at Yucca Flats that once was considered so promising produced tenacious opposition in Nevada.</p>
        <p>In the last case, the Government's faulty plans no doubt increased local resistance. But such resistance inevitably will arise wherever a repository is planned, and no wonder. Just ask yourself if you want highly radioactive material, that will remain so virtually forever, stored in your vicinity; and even if you are willing, ask yourself if, after 30 years of failure, inept management and deception (remember when nuclear power was going to be ''too cheap to meter''?), you could believe the assurances of either government or industry that the problem finally has been solved.</p>
        <p>No doubt dedicated opponents of nuclear power - they are numerous, on both environmental and safety grounds - will consider the Yucca Flats decision one more reason why nuclear power should be abandoned altogether. I am among those not yet convinced either that a safe nuclear-power program cannot be developed or that such a program can be made superfluous by conservation and alternative energy sources.</p>
        <p>But even if nuclear power production were to be entirely halted and the existing plants scrapped - even if nuclear weapons production were halted for good measure - the baffling problem of waste disposal would remain; in the short run it actually would be exacerbated by the greatly increased amounts of waste to be stored.</p>
        <p>Either way, therefore, whether nuclear power is abandoned or continued, much less extended, the lethal waste disposal problem, both technological and political, will remain -humbling evidence of the arrogance of a course confidently embarked upon before anyone knew where it would lead.</p>
        <p>IN THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
