<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Congress Seeks to Reduce Greenhouse Effect; Solar, but Not Nuclear</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="229590"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOSSONG, KEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3D61630F934A35750C0A96F948260" item-length="346" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Congress Seeks to Reduce Greenhouse Effect; Solar, but Not Nuclear</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>We strongly endorse your view in ''The Greenhouse Effect Is for Real'' (editorial, Jan. 27) that ''smokeless forms of energy generation like solar power,'' as well as energy conservation, should be pursued to forestall global warming.</p>
        <p>Solar and other renewable energy technologies account for 8.5 percent of the United States energy supply (compared with 6 percent for nuclear), and their contribution is expected at least to double by 2000, with only modest government support.</p>
        <p>However, there is little to your suggestion that a ''new generation'' of nuclear reactors could be designed to correct the economic, safety and environmental problems that have plagued the current generation.</p>
        <p>Most advanced reactor concepts exist on paper only; constructing demonstration models and subsequently building commercial units could take 20 years or more - too long to make a contribution to solving the global warming problem.</p>
        <p>The nuclear industry's most optimistic projections suggest that the economic cost to design, build and operate new advanced reactors would be at least as high as that for present-day reactors. If experience with other capital-intensive energy facilities is any guide, the true cost for these untried technologies, once they are built, could be 5 to 10 times higher than projected - hardly the ''cheap insurance'' you propose.</p>
        <p>Serious safety shortcomings characterize each of the ''new generation'' reactor concepts - even the so-called ''passively safe'' designs. And like today's reactors, these plants would continue to produce long-lived, highly radioactive waste, for which there is no known, safe method of permanent storage.</p>
        <p>The precautionary measures you advocate correctly include investments in energy efficiency and renewable energy technologies. However, investing in nuclear power could actually make a solution to global warming less likely by diverting funds from these more promising options. KEN BOSSONG  Washington, Feb. 13, 1989</p>
        <p>The writer is director of Public Citizen's critical mass energy project.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
