<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Skeptics Are Challenging Dire 'Greenhouse' Views</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="308822"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="SPLIT FORECAST: DISSENT ON GLOBAL WARMING - A SPECIAL REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6DA143DF930A25751C1A96F948260" item-length="2410" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Skeptics Are Challenging Dire 'Greenhouse' Views</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As governments try to come to grips with what is widely depicted as a potentially catastrophic warming of the Earth's surface, dissenting scientists are challenging what they see as unnecessarily gloomy predictions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As governments try to come to grips with what is widely depicted as a potentially catastrophic warming of the Earth's surface, dissenting scientists are challenging what they see as unnecessarily gloomy predictions.</p>
        <p>As governments try to come to grips with what is widely depicted as a potentially catastrophic warming of the Earth's surface, dissenting scientists are challenging what they see as unnecessarily gloomy predictions.</p>
        <p>The skeptics contend that forecasts of global warming are flawed and overstated and that the future might even hold no significant warming at all. Some say that if the warming is modest, as they believe likely, it could bring benefits like longer growing seasons in temperate zones, more rain in dry areas and an enrichment of crops and plant life.</p>
        <p>In any case, they argue, it would be a mistake to take drastic and costly steps to limit emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases that trap the sun's heat in the earth's atmosphere until more is known about the problem. These ''greenhouse'' gases are building up as a result of human activity, especially the burning of fossil fuels. Most Have No Firm Position</p>
        <p>Exactly how many scientists are involved in serious climatic research is unclear, but experts in the field say it includes fewer than 300 climatologists, meteorologists, geophysicists and people in related fields. Many of them, perhaps the majority, have not taken a firm position in the debate; they say that while the greenhouse theory is valid in general, there are too many uncertainties about its future effects.</p>
        <p>Both of the other factions - those who believe global warming to be a clear and definite threat and those who say there is likely to be no significant warming - appear to be in a minority. Authorities on weather and climate can be found in all three groups.</p>
        <p>Much of the dissenters' criticism is aimed at computerized mathematical models of the world's climate on which forecasts of global warming are largely based. The critics also cite data on past climatic trends, and they say the theory of greenhouse warming has not yet been fully explored.</p>
        <p>''It's not that we have a bad theory,'' said Reid A. Bryson of the University of Wisconsin, a leading climate theorist. ''It's that we have an incomplete theory with a lot of bad science being done.'' Forecast and Its Basis</p>
        <p>Most of the dissenters' assertions are being challenged in turn by scientists who adhere to the better-known view of global warming. This view holds that increasing concentrations of greenhouse gases are likely to cause the average temperature of the air at the Earth's surface to increase by three to eight degrees Fahrenheit some time in the next century, from the current global average level of 57 degrees. That amount of increase is generally accepted by a number of national and international scientific groups that have sought a consensus on the issue, including various panels of the National Academy of Sciences.</p>
        <p>The forecast is based largely on what the forecasters see as the inherent scientific logic of the greenhouse theory and on the computerized simulations of the future atmosphere. The forecasters expect the warming to raise sea levels, through the expansion of warming water and the melting of ice around the world; to change the climate of the globe, and to disrupt weather, human society and balances among plants and animals.</p>
        <p>Both the dissenters and those who call for action have been pressing their arguments in Washington as the Bush Administration grapples with pressures to reduce the burning of fossil fuels like coal and oil, which are the main source of human-produced atmospheric carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Current forecasts of global warming ''are so inaccurate and fraught with uncertainty as to be useless to policy-makers,'' Richard S. Lindzen of the Massachusetts of Institute of Technology and Jerome Namias of the Scripps Institution Oceanography in La Jolla, Calif., wrote in a letter to President Bush in late September. The two authorities on meteorology are both members of the National Academy of Sciences.</p>
        <p>Their warning was one of several cautionary pleas now coming forth in the aftermath of months of speeches, writings and testimony to Congress by scientists and environmentalists who urge prompt countermeasures. Some important officials in the Administration, including John H. Sununu, the White House chief of staff, have also urged caution until further research is performed. Arguments and Evidence Computer Models' Accuracy Debated</p>
        <p>Some of the dissenters, including Dr. Lindzen, say the scientific uncertainty could be reduced through a decade or less of intensive research, perhaps in three to five years. They counsel against drastic action to cut fossil-fuel emissions until then.</p>
        <p>''The expense is patently obvious,'' said one of the most outspoken skeptics, Patrick Michaels, a professor of environmental sciences at the University of Virginia and a former president of the American Meteorological Society. ''If the policy is going to be that expensive, the science should be much less murky than it is now,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Other scientists have long acknowledged the uncertainties of global warming predictions, but argue that they will not be eliminated in time for effective action to be taken.</p>
        <p>''My feeling is that the uncertainty will always remain,'' said Syukuro Manabe of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory at Princeton University, a leading climatologist. Dr. Manabe's laboratory runs one of the major mathematical models of the global climate on which attempts to forecast future warming are mostly based. ''We have to make decisions based on uncertain information,'' he said. ''I don't think we have any other choice.''</p>
        <p>In view of the uncertainty, some scientists favor taking actions that would bring major benefits in their own right, like increasing energy efficiency and pressing the development of alternative power sources. The Theory's Backers</p>
        <p>Among those who oppose dissenters like Dr. Bryson, Dr. Lindzen, Dr. Namias and Dr. Michaels are, for example, James E. Hansen of the Goddard Institute for Space Studies in New York City; Michael Oppenheimer, a senior scientist with the the Environmental Defense Fund; George M. Woodwell, director of the Woods Hole Research Center, and Stephen H. Schneider of the National Center for Atmospheric Research.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hansen helped propel the issue of global warming to the forefront last year when, at the height of the 1988 heat wave and drought, he testified before Congress that global warming caused by increasing concentrations of greenhouse gases was already under way.</p>
        <p>The climate models that draw much of the dissenters' criticism are mathematical equations that simulate the physical workings of the atmosphere. Scientists can insert any set of conditions they like - a given concentration of greenhouse gases, for instance -and a computer calculates how the climate would change, including changes in the average global temperature.</p>
        <p>Global warming theorists maintain that a relatively small increase in the temperature can have major consequences. For example, they point out, the average temperature since the end of the last ice age has increased by nine degrees.</p>
        <p>But the computer models ''are seriously exaggerating the warming by at least two to threefold,'' said Hugh W. Ellsaesser, a meteorologist at Lawrence Livermore Laboratory in California who retired in 1986. He has been working on the question of global warming since 1972. Complicating Factors Clouds and Oceans Poorly Understood All the models, said Dr. Lindzen, contain flaws that ''could easily reduce the predictions for warming to well under a degree'' centigrade, or 1.8 degrees Fahrenheit. Not least among the flaws, he and others say, is that the models fail to properly reflect the climatic effects of water vapor and clouds, which can each overwhelm the effect of the greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Skeptics say that clouds might well reduce the warming by reflecting sunlight back into space, but some of the model experts say they could also, through a complex set of feedback mechanisms, increase the warming.</p>
        <p>Clouds are poorly simulated in all the models, most climatologists agree. A team at the United Kingdom Meteorological Office in England reported in September that by representing clouds more realistically, its model had reduced the projection of expected warming from about nine degrees to about five. The British model has usually produced the highest estimates.</p>
        <p>The findings have been cited by the skeptics as evidence that they are probably right in their contention that the warming has been overstated. But John F. B. Mitchell, the chief scientist on the British project, said the result did not mean that the group was cutting its forecast in half.</p>
        <p>So little is known about the characteristics of clouds, he said, that even this latest simulation cannot be taken as realistic. Rather, he said, the result ''essentially illustrates our uncertainty'' and underscores a serious lack of data on how clouds behave. Without better data, he said, ''we can go on doing numerical experiments till we're blue in the face and we won't reduce the uncertainties.'' Oceans' Moderating Effects</p>
        <p>The models have only recently begun to reflect the enormous capacity of the oceans to absorb heat, a factor that scientists believe will slow down global warming substantially. Scientists studying a model at the National Center for Atmospheric Research in Boulder, Colo., recently completed a simulation that included the ocean's influence. It resulted in a warming of nearly three degrees when carbon dioxide in the atmosphere doubled, as against about seven degrees in an earlier model run.</p>
        <p>This was also seen by some dissenters and Government officials as a one-half reduction in the models' warming estimates, but Warren Washington, one of the chiefs of the Boulder experiment, said that was a misinterpretation. The modeling exercise was not fully played out because of lack of computer access, and the simulation was carried only 30 years into the future, he said. If it had continued to the point where full effects were felt, he said, the warming would have been substantially larger. Models and Measurements Both Sides Claim Support in Data To some scientists who see themselves as neither dissenters nor backers of specific warming predictions, the uncertainties are perplexing and frustrating.</p>
        <p>''Common physical sense tells us something is going to be happening'' to the world's climate because of the greenhouse effect, said Robert D. Cess, a professor of atmospheric sciences at the State University of New York at Stony Brook, who heads an international group that assesses the models. But he said the group's conclusion, soon to be published, is that ''we don't know what these models are doing.'' He said the models ''as presently formulated'' cannot be used to predict future global warming, and that ''whether they can ever be used for that purpose is problematical.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Hansen defends the models, pointing out that even as they have become more sophisticated, their conclusions about global warming have generally remained within the range predicted in the 1970's. Some defenders of the models say they doubt that another decade of refinements would substantially alter the range.</p>
        <p>Defenders also say the models have validated themselves by successfully simulating the waxing and waning of ice ages, present-day seasonal variations and the workings of the atmospheres of Venus and Mars. 'We Should Be Flabbergasted'</p>
        <p>But the critics say that the models have not done well at matching the climatic trends on the scale of a century. In the last century, according to some studies of temperature records, the average global temperature has risen by about one degree. Simulations by some models show that it should have risen by about twice that much.</p>
        <p>To the dissenters, this gap casts doubt on the models' credibility. To some environmental scientists it shows the opposite. ''We should be flabbergasted that the models can come that close, given the uncertainties,'' said Dr. Oppenheimer of the Environmental Defense Fund, a research and advocacy organization. The dispute on this point is muddied by the variations in temperature profiles for past decades that emerge from different studies. Some studies suggest little or no warming over the last century, depending on the data and methods used, and this has occasioned argument. Positive Views Some See Benefits In Warmer Earth Few scientists believe greenhouse warming can now be detected amid the normal swings of climate. But if it can, says Dr. Michaels, the evidence might be emerging from data collected by a team headed by Thomas Karl, a climate-change analyst at the Government's climatic data center at Asheville, N.C.</p>
        <p>Studies there found that since the mid-1950's, nighttime temperatures in much of the United States have risen in fall, summer and winter, while daytime temperatures have dropped slightly. There is evidence of the same pattern in China and Australia, Mr. Karl said. He said the reasons are unclear, although increasing cloudiness appears to have contributed to it in this country.</p>
        <p>''If nature is declaring her greenhouse with a relative rise in the nighttime rather than the daytime,'' said Dr. Michaels, ''then the severity of the problem is drastically reduced.'' In fact, he said, warmer nights in temperate regions would lengthen growing seasons.</p>
        <p>This could especially benefit northern regions, in the Northern Hemisphere, some scientists believe, and southern regions in the Southern. Some say, in fact, that countries like the Soviet Union and Canada might well benefit from even a high degree of warming. Russians Predict Benefits</p>
        <p>Two Soviet scientists, M. I. Budyko and Y. S. Sedunov, have said in a paper that increased rainfall over all the continents, along with the ''fertilizer'' effect on plants of carbon dioxide, ''will considerably enhance'' plant productivity, increase harvests, make large barren territories suitable for agriculture and permit the expansion of crops in other regions.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Woodwell of the Woods Hole Institute argues that global warming would produce even more atmospheric carbon dioxide by speeding the decay of organic matter and accelerating the respiration of plants. This new source of carbon dioxide, he believes, would more than offset the amount absorbed by plants in photosynthesis. It could easily exceed the amount from fossil-fuel burning, he says, and cause the planet to warm up even more.</p>
        <p>SPLIT FORECAST: DISSENT ON GLOBAL WARMING - A SPECIAL REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
