<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Long-Term Forest Studies Offer Insight Into Effect of Pollutants</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="233408"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DROUGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WHITE MOUNTAINS (NH)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">HUBBARD BROOKS EXPERIMENTAL FOREST (NH)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Hampshire/White Mountains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFDB173DF932A15750C0A96F948260" item-length="1052" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Long-Term Forest Studies Offer Insight Into Effect of Pollutants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>WEST THORNTON, N.H.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IN the longest continuous study of the chemistry of a forest in the United States, scientists have been carefully monitoring an experimental forest here in the White Mountains since 1963 to learn about growth patterns and how they are affected by different conditions, like pollution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IN the longest continuous study of the chemistry of a forest in the United States, scientists have been carefully monitoring an experimental forest here in the White Mountains since 1963 to learn about growth patterns and how they are affected by different conditions, like pollution.</p>
        <p>IN the longest continuous study of the chemistry of a forest in the United States, scientists have been carefully monitoring an experimental forest here in the White Mountains since 1963 to learn about growth patterns and how they are affected by different conditions, like pollution.</p>
        <p>The researchers, who in the early 1970's were the first Americans to detect acid rain, are now studying such vital ecological questions as the effects of drought and ozone on tree growth and animal life.</p>
        <p>Scrupulous record keeping at the 7,800-acre Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest has enabled the researchers to predict ways in which pollutants and the removal of trees will affect natural processes. Studies are conducted in nine watersheds, some of which serve as controls.</p>
        <p>The findings on acid rain were first described in a 1972 publication. In 1974 the researchers compared acidity levels at Hubbard Brook with readings from upstate New York and discovered that acid rain was a regionwide problem. They noted that high acidity levels had made streams uninhabitable for some kinds of aquatic life and made trees more vulnerable to disease. They predicted that if acidity levels remained high, the vegetation would deteriorate, as it has in polluted areas of Europe.</p>
        <p>''We really don't know, nor does anybody know, what the effects of acid rain per se are on the forest, but it's really not the question,'' said Gene E. Likens, director of the Institute of Ecosystem Studies at the Mary Flagler Cary Arboretum in Millbrook, N.Y. ''It's not just acid rain. It's ozone and lead in rainfall, and droughts and defoliating insects like gypsy moths.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Likens, a principal researcher at the forest, said: ''When all those things come together at the same time, they can cause a serious effect. When any one or even a few of them are there singly, then we don't see effects, but that doesn't mean there isn't stress.'' Guidelines for Forest Managers</p>
        <p>Researchers here have been looking at the way these stresses affect the forest, with its maple, yellow birch and beech trees, as well as the effects on Mirror Lake nearby. By showing the fragile condition of the lake and its shores, the researchers offered persuasive evidence that the lake should be preserved by the Forest Service instead of being developed commercially.</p>
        <p>Their experiments in tree harvesting have led to a set of widely followed guidelines for forest managers, recommending that forests not be cut more then every 70 years, not be cut in huge blocks or on steep, fragile slopes. This summer the researchers plan to study what stresses resulted from last summer's season of drought, heat and high air pollution.</p>
        <p>The backbone of the research done at Hubbard Brook has come from the constant measuring of water, sunlight and nutrients in nine of the forest's watersheds. In each of these microenvironments, bucket-like collecting devices measure the amount of precipitation coming in, while small dams at the bottom of the watersheds are used to measure the amount of water flowing out.</p>
        <p>Since the bedrock beneath the forest is watertight, these calibrations allow scientists to calculate exactly how much water is being used by the plants and animals in each watershed. The chemical content of the water and the soil is also examined so that the type and amount of nutrients used by the forest's various life forms can be measured.</p>
        <p>''Hubbard Brook is a uniquely ideal place to conduct this kind of research because we can very accurately gauge the amount of water coming into the system and the amount of water going out,'' said Robert S. Pierce, project leader for the forest. ''We try to discern the major processes that go on here - biological, chemical and physical - and study them with regard to the soil, animals, aquatic life and vegetation. We try to determine nutrient budgets for all the various pools in the forest.'' Trees Cut in Patterns</p>
        <p>Initially the water and nutrient needs of each of the watersheds was determined as accurately as possible. Then scientists began removing trees in experimental patterns to try to determine how quickly the ecosystems could restore nutrient levels needed for growth.</p>
        <p>In one watershed, all trees were felled in 1965 and left on the site, and the area was treated with herbicide for three years to prevent regrowth of vegetation. In another watershed, all trees were cut and removed in 1970. In a third watershed, all trees larger than 10 centimeters in diameter at roughly five feet from the ground were removed in 1983. The trees in a fourth watershed were removed every two years, starting in 1970, in progressive 25-meter strips. The remaining watersheds were left untouched as controls.</p>
        <p>As might be expected, the scientists found that the magnitude of ecological change varied according to the level of disturbance. In watersheds where the most trees were destroyed, nutrient losses were more severe and lasted longer, while concentrations of nitrates, which can harm plants, increased in water and soil.</p>
        <p>Despite elevated acidity levels, the trees here are healthy, but scientists fear that the long-term effects of pollutants could include stunted tree growth or the extinction of frailer species. The average pH of precipitation in the forest is 4.0, far more acidic than an ideal reading of 5.7, but slightly less acidic than in 1963.</p>
        <p>Dr. Pierce said that in the 26 years of monitoring at Hubbard Brook, the level of sulfurs has decreased, a result of industries and utilities switching to low-sulfur coal, while the level of nitrogen forms has steadily increased, a result of more automobiles.</p>
        <p>''The fact that we are emitting large amounts of pollutants into the atmosphere may mean long-term impacts, and we may not be able to detect those changes for another 20 years,'' Dr. Pierce said. ''But by that time, it may be too late, so it would be wise to act on the side of caution.''</p>
        <p>In a few more decades, Dr. Pierce said, even more will be known about the regrowth patterns of trees in the watersheds, and scientists will be able to draw firmer conclusions about the effects of elevated acidity levels.</p>
        <p>''When you're tired, you're more likely to catch a cold, and trees are the same way,'' Dr. Likens said. ''They have to respond to multiple stresses all the time.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
