<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thatcher Puts a Lid On Censorship in Britain</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="228945"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CENSORSHIP</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREEDOM OF THE PRESS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREEDOM AND HUMAN RIGHTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ATLAS, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">THATCHER, MARGARET H (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of the Press</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890305T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7DB143FF936A35750C0A96F948260" item-length="3965" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thatcher Puts a Lid On Censorship in Britain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By James Atlas; James Atlas is an editor of this magazine.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ATLAS, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Charter 88 arrived on the newsstands of Britain with the rhetorical force of a Tom Paine tract.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Charter 88 arrived on the newsstands of Britain with the rhetorical force of a Tom Paine tract.</p>
        <p>Charter 88 arrived on the newsstands of Britain with the rhetorical force of a Tom Paine tract.</p>
        <p>''We are losing our liberties - because they do not belong to us as citizens,'' read the text in colorful bold print on the cover of the New Statesman &amp; Society last December.</p>
        <p>Inside was a two-page manifesto: The untrammeled mandate of Margaret Thatcher, the most powerful Prime Minister in England since the end of World War II, had enabled her ''to menace the independence of broadcasting; to threaten academic freedom in the universities and schools; to tolerate abuses committed in the name of national security.'' What was urgently needed, the charter's authors declared, was a bill of rights, a written constitution that would guarantee the basic liberties on which democracy is founded: ''The time has come to demand political, civil and human rights in the United Kingdom.''</p>
        <p>Among the supporters of this fiery proclamation were the novelists Martin Amis and Julian Barnes, the philosopher Sir Alfred Ayer, the playwright Michael Frayn and 250 other highly recognizable names - a significant proportion of the English intelligentsia, in fact.</p>
        <p>But Charter 88 was more than a left-wing magazine's isolated protest. To hear people talk, England in 1988 was Prague in 1977. There was the 20th of June Group, founded last summer by a cadre of disaffected writers who convened for dinner at the home of the playwright Harold Pinter to form what the eminent barrister and novelist John Mortimer described as ''a strong and sensible Opposition.'' There was a special issue of Index on Censorship, featuring contributions from Stephen Spender, Richard Hoggart and other distinguished commentators on the cultural scene, dedicated to the proposition that freedom was being ''diminished'' in the United Kingdom. There was Samizdat, a newsletter established to ''challenge the divisiveness of the Government and the fear of the new of so many of its opponents.''</p>
        <p>The people may not have been ready to storm Parliament and exile Thatcher to France, as they did James II. Freedom of the press is an issue that excites the press and intellectuals more than anyone else. Yet it wasn't only the ''chattering classes'' (as disdainful Tory columnists refer to the Charter 88 constituency) who were up in arms. Even the glossy Illustrated London News published an article by the novelist Ludovic Kennedy in its December issue chronicling the Government's authoritarian drift: the British Broadcasting Corporation, long the showcase of British culture, was being brought to heel by attempts to censor programs hostile to Thatcher's policies; a ban on live radio or television interviews with terrorists was in effect, and Parliament was considering a revision of the Official Secrets Act that would essentially do away with the ''harm,'' or public interest, defense, making the disclosure of Government information a crime - no matter what kind or whether disclosing it would pose a danger.</p>
        <p>The remarkable thing about Kennedy's enumeration of grievances was the ideological diversity of the politicians he enlisted on their behalf: Roy Hattersley, deputy leader of the Labor Party; Richard Shepherd, a Conservative Member of Parliament; even J. Enoch Powell, a former Member of Parliament not known for his liberal sentiments.</p>
        <p>None of Kennedy's deponents was prepared to say that totalitarianism loomed on the horizon, but clearly something had gone wrong. ''Liberty is ill in Britain,'' warned the American legal philosopher Ronald Dworkin, a professor of jurisprudence at Oxford, writing in Index. ''The very concept of liberty - the universal, seamless idea at stake in all these separate and diverse controversies - is being challenged and corroded by the Thatcher Government.''</p>
        <p>CERTAINLY ''THE INTENSIFICATION OF AUTHORITARIAN rule'' that the authors of Charter 88 detected in contemporary Britain was more than a reflexive protest against the growing political power of Thatcher's ''regime'' - as her long tenure in office is often and without irony described, even by the Prime Minister herself. In the last few months, newspapers of every political persuasion have been obsessed with the new measures her Government has put forth, especially the Official Secrets Act reform and the protection of privacy bill now before Parliament, an attempt to crack down on the excesses of England's gossip-mongering tabloid press.</p>
        <p>The biggest furor was over ''Death on the Rock,'' a Thames Television documentary about three Irish terrorists who were gunned down by the Special Air Services regiment in Gibraltar in 1988. In Parliament, Thatcher denounced the program as ''trial by television,'' and tried to have it suppressed, even threatening to suspend the network's license. After an independent inquiry largely vindicated the program's findings this winter, Thatcher rejected the report as biased and inaccurate. By the end of January, even the normally conservative Sunday Times of London was warning that ''the defense of personal freedom has now slid alarmingly low in the priorities of Mrs. Thatcher's Government.''</p>
        <p>The press wasn't the only constituency under assault. Civil libertarians could point to the Public Order Act, designed to restrict the public's right to engage in political demonstrations; and, perhaps most sinister of all, a change in legal procedure that would limit a defendant's right to not testify. The purpose of this proposed amendment was to make it easier to convict terrorists unwilling to testify on their own behalf - but Home Secretary Douglas Hurd would like to see it become law throughout England, and in the end it probably will.</p>
        <p>To an American, accustomed to the defense of individual rights afforded by the Constitution and the Bill of Rights, the power concentrated in the hands of the British Government is extraordinary. Thatcher has often expressed her belief in the rule of law; but it's Parliament that makes the laws. The right to freedom of speech can be found in England's Bill of Rights of 1689 - parliamentary free speech. One axiom I heard a lot when I was over there in December: ''We're subjects. You're citizens.'' This difference is fundamental, inscribed in the two nations' divergent histories. The opposition to censorship affirmed by John Milton and John Stuart Mill, those classic defenders of liberty, is ''sewn into Britain's banner,'' notes Oxford's Ronald Dworkin. But so is official tyranny. Milton's ''Areopagitica'' was written as a protest against a 1643 Order of Parliament requiring a license to publish. ''There is, in fact, no recognized principle by which the propriety or impropriety of Government interference is customarily tested,'' Mill observed two centuries later.</p>
        <p>And so it still is in England. Freedom of the press, freedom of speech - what Dworkin calls ''the culture of liberty'' - is just that: a culture, not a legal code. There is nothing like our First Amendment, nor does Thatcher feel the need for one. In her view, measures such as the Official Secrets Act and the protection of privacy bill are essential to the maintenance of an orderly society. ''The Prime Minister does not believe that people have a right to know,'' contends Kevin Boyle, director of Article 19, an international organization devoted to monitoring censorship.</p>
        <p>''The White Paper  [ on the Government's proposed reform of the Official Secrets Act ]  is talking about information on any subject,'' objected Richard Shepherd, writing in The Times of London. ''E.E.C. proposals on taxation, consumer affairs, acid rain or the allocation of airline routes would be caught.'' In other words, only the Government can determine what constitutes a threat to it.</p>
        <p>But what makes Thatcher so powerful has less to do with any legislation she has put forward than with the sheer force of her personality and her determination to implement her beliefs - ''conviction politics,'' she calls them. England must become competitive; socialism must be ''killed'' (Thatcher's word); the Irish Republican Army must be stopped.</p>
        <p>Indeed, it's the doings of the I.R.A., I suspect, that have impelled the Prime Minister to strengthen her hand. Governments have always been obsessed with national security: Witness the Reagan Administration's persistent attempts to subvert the Freedom of Information Act. What is happening in England now is a response to an actual enemy within. There's a war on. When Amnesty International announced its intention to monitor the I.R.A. shootings in Gibraltar, Thatcher told the House of Commons, ''I hope Amnesty has some concern for the more than 2,000 people murdered by the I.R.A. since 1969.'' And when ''Death on the Rock'' was shown, she was asked by a foreign journalist if she was furious; her response, she said, went ''deeper than that.'' The I.R.A. bombed a Brighton hotel during a Tory conference in 1984, and several Government officials were killed; Thatcher herself nearly died in the attack. England, to her way of thinking, is under seige.</p>
        <p>WHY HAS RESISTANCE to Thatcher's repressive policies suddenly erupted with such vehemence? After all, they're nothing new. In 1983, a Government clerk who leaked to The Guardian a memorandum from the Minister of Defense that United States cruise missiles were about to be installed in England was sentenced to six months in jail. A year later, there was the notorious trial, and subsequent acquittal, of Clive Ponting, a Ministry of Defense official who gave Parliament details of a Government memo that raised questions about the sinking of an Argentinian battleship during the Falklands War.</p>
        <p>But these were misdemeanors compared with ''Spycatcher'' - a synecdoche for the disastrous effort to suppress Peter Wright's best-selling memoir of his life as a spy in the British Security Service. The Crown sued to prevent publication on the ground that the book contained state secrets. The court vindicated Wright, but the Government obtained an injunction enjoining newspapers in England from any mention of the case. Last October, after years of litigation, the Law Lords - England's Supreme Court -found against the Government. The book had already been widely read all over the world, they reasoned. Thanks to this bit of legalistic casuistry, ''Spycatcher'' could finally be published in England.</p>
        <p>What was it about Wright's memoir that provoked such stringent measures? To be sure, it does contain some embarrassing revelations, among them an account of the campaign (since substantiated by David Leigh in ''The Wilson Plot'') to discredit Prime Minister Harold Wilson as a Soviet agent and drive him from office. But, in the end, as Wright's collaborator, Paul Greengrass, says in his introduction, ''Spycatcher'' is ''just a book,'' war stories ''told by the fire, a drink in hand.''</p>
        <p>The Government saw it otherwise. To publish state secrets - or what were perceived as such - violated an ancient unwritten code of ethics. From the Privy Counsellor's Oath of Confidentiality, drafted in 1250 and still sworn by Cabinet ministers on bended knees before the Queen, to the Official Secrets Act of 1911, Government has required blind fealty of those in its service. The notion that a public official could be answerable to some higher authority, either moral or religious, is simply - in the English phrase -not on.</p>
        <p>Government employees aren't the only ones who've been singled out for prosecution. Duncan Campbell, one of the most zealous investigative journalists in England, was virtually put under house arrest after he did an episode for the BBC television series ''Secret Society'' about an $800 million spy satellite that the Thatcher Government had developed without informing Parliament. The Government seized film from BBC offices in Glasgow and raided Campbell's North London home.</p>
        <p>Donald Trelford, editor of The London Observer, has also run afoul of the Government. ''We're a bit beleaguered,'' said Trelford when I spoke with him in The Observer's offices. Dapper in a well-tailored dark suit, Trelford scarcely seems the beleaguered sort, but he has been dragged into court on a number of occasions.</p>
        <p>''Knowledge is an offense now,'' Trelford lamented. ''Information is Government property.'' It's not unusual, he says, for the Treasury Solicitor to demand that he promise not to publish certain information, otherwise he'll be served with an injunction. It has made for a contentious atmosphere: ''When the Government threatens, I say, 'Well, sod them, we'll publish.' ''</p>
        <p>If newspaper editors feel a chill in the air, television is braced for a storm. In November, the Government issued still another White Paper, on ''Broadcasting in the 90's,'' which put forth a series of proposals that could utterly transform the ''culture of television.''</p>
        <p>No one is more aware of television's potential influence than Thatcher, who has called it ''the most powerful form of communication known on this planet.'' But until now, control of this ubiquitous medium has eluded her grasp, especially the BBC, which Roy Jenkins, the Chancellor of Oxford, includes among the nation's ''four great institutions'' -the others being the Church of England, the House of Lords and ''the ancient universities, Oxford and Cambridge.''</p>
        <p>Even though it is subsidized by the Government, the BBC is supposed to be an independent entity, with its own editorial policy and its own board of governors. Virtually since she took office, Thatcher has struggled to subdue the network to her purposes. A decade ago she was scolding the BBC for giving publicity to Irish terrorists; when the Falklands War broke out, she objected to certain broadcasters who didn't know it was ''their duty to stand up for our boys.''</p>
        <p>What exasperates Thatch-er about the BBC isn't just its independence. The way it's financed, by a licensing fee in the form of a tax on television sets, contradicts her ''pay-your-own way'' philosophy. In 1988, she summoned the nation's leading broadcasters to Downing Street and unveiled an innovative plan. Her vision, as The Times of London described it, was ''new channels, more competition, and more efficiency.'' Deregulation, or ''privatization'' - a system of private financing - would make for ''a more open and competitive broadcasting market,'' contended the Government's White Paper on Broadcasting.</p>
        <p>John Birt, who took over as deputy director general of the BBC last year with a mandate to overhaul the system, was at first widely viewed as the Government's man, a television apparatchik. Despite his corporate demeanor, Birt is no company man. A few weeks earlier, he had published a stern article in The Independent opposing the ban on televised interviews with terrorists. To deny journalists the right to cover events as they saw fit, Birt argued, would undermine ''some of the most cherished elements of a democratic society.''</p>
        <p>During a visit to Broadcasting House, I noted my surprise that he had come out with such a strong denunciation of the Home Office. It was ''a departure,'' Birt conceded, but not the only instance. He reminded me that he had also resisted a Government injunction against another controversial program, ''Spy in the Sky,'' about Zircon, the Government's controversial spy satellite. The BBC, he made it clear, would continue to be ''very vigorous in wanting to assert its independence.''</p>
        <p>Whether it would be allowed to do so is another matter. As described in the recent White Paper on Broadcasting, the role of advertising would be greatly expanded. There will be open bidding for commercial television franchises, and the ''eventual'' replacement of the BBC licensing fee with some form of self-generated subsidy.</p>
        <p>The networks reacted vehemently, predicting an era of game shows and soap operas. For Stuart Prebble of the Campaign for Quality Television, the White Paper was ''a detailed epitaph for the television which has been the envy of the world.''</p>
        <p>But in a way, it was too late to do much more than mourn. Satellites had already been launched that would soon give viewers access to as many as 25 channels, compared with the four they receive today. For England, like it or not, the age of cable has begun. It promises to be a commercial free-for-all, but with an Independent Television Commission to oversee the ''liberalized commercial television sector,'' and a Broadcasting Standards Council to ''reinforce standards of taste and decency.'' Deregulation, in other words, will mean more regulation for the independents.</p>
        <p>IT IS HAPPENING,''</p>
        <p>Harold Pinter, a founding member of the 20th of June Group, said with quiet emphasis. We were talking in the comfortable, book-lined study of his Holland Park house. Pinter was troubled with ominous premonitions. ''The country is in a much more extreme situation than is commonly realized. The power of the police to do whatever they like is extraordinary.'' England today, he maintained, has ''a McCarthy period feel to it. The people are bewildered, fearful, undermined. Lost.''</p>
        <p>''Mountain Language,'' Pinter's new play, is a terse political allegory. The title refers to the dialect of the peasant women in the play, who have been forbidden by the authorities to speak their own language. It's a play, Pinter acknowledged, that says a good deal about what is happening in his own country.</p>
        <p>But wasn't he himself allowed to write and say whatever he pleased? Well, yes, but there was a kind of unconscious self-censorship at work, he explained. One felt the Government there . . . lurking: ''Phones are bugged. I know people who are under surveillance.''</p>
        <p>No doubt, there is an official vindictiveness emanating from Whitehall. But is it (Continued on Page 97) ''the death knell of a democratic society,'' as Pinter contends, or merely a squabble between factions of the ruling class? To find out, I called on Lord Rees-Mogg, chairman of the Broadcasting Standards Council and former editor of The Times of London, at his antiquarian bookstore, Pickering &amp; Chatto on Pall Mall. Lord Rees-Mogg, who is empowered to preview and prevent the showing of programs that he finds offensive, professed not to find the political climate ''so very sinister. I can't remember when it wasn't so.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, what did all these dissenting writers have to complain about? They were making lots of money, Tory columnists were quick to note. They wrote whatever they pleased. Perhaps; but events of recent weeks have given renewed urgency to their cause and made it distinctly more real. Acting in response to the Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini's death edict against Salman Rushdie, the author of ''The Satanic Verses,'' members of Article 19, Charter 88 and other writers' organizations convened to form an international committee for the defense of Rushdie. If there had ever been an instance of intolerable censorship, this was it.</p>
        <p>For once, a conflict was unambiguous. When it came to the media-Thatcher feud, which side you were on seemed to matter less than whether you had a visible byline. Paul Bailey had at John Mortimer, who had at The Spectator's Paul Johnson, who had at the whole British press. Writing in The Observer, Donald Trelford ended a vigorous editorial deploring the Official Secrets Act reform with a little anecdote: ''Over the strawberries at Wimbledon last week, Lord Armstrong'' - the Attorney General who tried the Government's case against ''Spycatcher'' - ''said to me: 'The test of a new act is whether it is better than what went before.' '' Over the strawberries at Wimbledon. . . .</p>
        <p>I THINK THERE'LL BE massive public indifference and ridicule to the whole thing,'' predicted a Thatcher spokesman, responding to a question about Charter 88. The press simply doesn't have the power in England that it does in the United States; it doesn't go about its business with the same investigative zeal. The practice of leaking information from Government sources is virtually unknown. Without a mandate to challenge the information it receives, the press has become a courier between the Government and the public. The Telegraph itself, in a recent editorial, noted that journalists were ''probably the most unpopular section of the community.'' So why bother about their problems? ''Thatcher is an extremely shrewd judge of what the public cares about and what it doesn't,'' says Max Hastings, editor of the right-wing Daily Telegraph. ''These are issues it doesn't care about.''</p>
        <p>I wondered if he wasn't right. One night, I attended a rally sponsored by the Campaign for Freedom of Information at the Friends Meeting House on Euston Road. I arrived early, expecting a noisy, passionate crowd. The auditorium was half-empty. The oratory was firm but polite. Paddy Ashdown, leader of the Social and Liberal Democrats, declared: ''We have a Government that believes in 'need to know' and never in 'the right to know.' ''</p>
        <p>''Hear, hear,'' muttered the audience.</p>
        <p>Listening to speech after speech in the drafty hall, I remembered something the American columnist Anthony Lewis had told me before I left: ''The issues that make us rise in passion don't move the English.'' Which doesn't make them any less important, I thought. The essence of a democratic society, Mill argued in ''On Liberty,'' is the right of its citizens to express unpopular beliefs, unfettered by ''the moral coercion of public opinion.'' And freedom of the press is the means by which that right is guaranteed. Whether or not a majority of the people care about it is beside the point.</p>
        <p>ON MY LAST NIGHT in England, I had a drink with Bill Buford, the editor of the literary magazine Granta. We met in the Groucho Club on Dean Street, a chic-seedy bar and restaurant straight out of an Anthony Powell novel. Black-stockinged waitresses circulated among the novelists and book reviewers lounging on sofas and plush chairs. Buford, a bearded, intense American who has made Granta a significant force on the Anglo-American literary scene, recounted how it came to pass that the summer 1988 issue carried on its cover the terse headline: ''Her Majesty's Government Does Not Want You to Know About the Life of Anthony Cavendish.''</p>
        <p>Cavendish was a former agent in MI6, Britain's Secret Intelligence Service (if MI5 is Britain's Federal Bureau of Investigation, MI6 is its Central Intelligence Agency). He had written a memoir about his clandestine life and submitted it to MI6, only to be threatened with a fine - perhaps even a prison sentence - if he went ahead with publication. After a long court battle, his publisher, Cassell, gave up on the project, discouraged by mounting legal fees.</p>
        <p>A year later, Cavendish self-published 500 copies of his book as a ''Christmas card'' to friends and associates. The Times of London acquired a copy and reported on the contents, upon which the Government obtained an injunction against any further printing of the book in any form.</p>
        <p>It was hard to understand what all the fuss was about. Cavendish was the prototype of the British spy, at once upper-class and faintly decadent. The story of his exploits in Germany and the Middle East was fascinating and vividly written, but largely innocuous.</p>
        <p>The Crown was adamant. The book couldn't appear. ''I testified before a Q.C.  [ Queen's Counsel ] ,'' Buford said, ''and he completely panicked. He'd been attending the Spycatcher hearings, and he was afraid the Government would sue Viking Penguin for illegal profits on 'Spycatcher.' Basically, what he said was: 'They will go for you. They will kill you.' ''</p>
        <p>In the end, Buford went ahead and published excerpts in Granta.</p>
        <p>As I was leaving, he gave me a copy of the Cavendish issue, and I read it on the bus out to Heathrow. Or tried to read it. Phrases, paragraphs, whole pages were blacked out. On others was a single word: CENSORED.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
