<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Cleaner Air, Give Utilities a Reason to Promote Mass Transit</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="269270"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRANSIT SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RATINGS AND RATING SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOBBY, EUGENE R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2D8173DF935A15754C0A96F948260" item-length="414" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Cleaner Air, Give Utilities a Reason to Promote Mass Transit</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>While it is good that the Bush Administration has finally made some proposals for dealing with acid rain, the proposals for urban smog are inadequate. Most disturbing is the proposal to allow cities to endure polluted air until the year 2000. It is unconscionable to allow another generation to grow up in poisonous air.</p>
        <p>Since most urban smog is produced by automobiles, it is distressing that New York, the city with the most comprehensive mass-transportation system in the country, has to be subjected to smog.</p>
        <p>The Bush approach to auto pollution can be summed up as more of the same. However, since more miles are driven each year, mere improvements in auto technology will not work - just as they have not worked.</p>
        <p>It has been reported that the Bush Administration reduced funds for mass transit in exchange for support for acid-rain legislation. Is more protection for trees logical in exchange for less protection for people?</p>
        <p>Let me suggest a solution that I think could be supported by conservative economists, environmentalists, utility officials and urban transit officials. Into the pollution-averaging formula proposed by the Bush Administration add the contribution to cleaner urban air made by that portion of a utility's electricity that is used by electric mass transit systems.</p>
        <p>There will almost always be a positive contribution made, even when moderately dirty electric generators supply mass transit. This is because the theoretical limit (from thermodynamic considerations) to the energy-conversion efficiency of an auto engine is on the order of 20 percent. On the other hand, electricity is produced by a coal-fired plant with an efficiency of about 40 percent, delivered with a transmission efficiency of about 95 percent and converted by electric motors into motion with an efficiency of a least 80 percent, for an overall efficiency of better than 24 percent.</p>
        <p>And this doesn't compare the efficiency of low-friction metal wheels on rail versus rubber on asphalt and the efficiency of high-capacity trains versus single passenger cars.</p>
        <p>I believe that letting the utilities take credit for their contribution to mass transit will create a desirable social change in the marketing of mass transit. There is no voice to speak out against the seductive ads Madison Avenue produces for the auto companies. Under my proposal, the utilities would have a reason to promote mass transit. EUGENE R. GOBBY  Allston, Mass., July 24, 1989</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
