<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recharting War on Smog; States Like California Are Taking the Lead Over Washington in Pollution-Control Law</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="289744"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATES (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D71138F933A25753C1A96F948260" item-length="1020" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recharting War on Smog; States Like California Are Taking the Lead Over Washington in Pollution-Control Law</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Civics textbooks say that Federal law is made in Washington and then applied around the country, but when it comes to clean air, a different pattern has emerged.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Civics textbooks say that Federal law is made in Washington and then applied around the country, but when it comes to clean air, a different pattern has emerged.</p>
        <p>Civics textbooks say that Federal law is made in Washington and then applied around the country, but when it comes to clean air, a different pattern has emerged.</p>
        <p>Sacramento makes the rules for California; a chorus of officials in eight state capitals from Trenton to Augusta, Me., embraces them; and finally, Washington tags along.</p>
        <p>This is an odd way to set policy for air pollution, which blows with the breeze across state lines, environmentalists say, but it seems to be working.</p>
        <p>''We're taking steps in New York that a rational person would say are better done by the Federal Government,'' said Thomas Jorling, the Commissioner of Environmental Conservation in New York, one of the eight states in the Northeast coalition. ''But this isn't a rational system. It's a messy system.''</p>
        <p>First the system tackled gasoline. Because evaporation of unburned fuel is a major source of the contents of smog, California insisted that refiners change the mix of gasoline ingredients to inhibit evaporation. Inspired by the example, the environmental commissioners of New Jersey, New York and the six New England states jointly decided last year to do the same. This spring, the United States Environmental Protection Agency announced it would follow suit nationally. Car Hardware Was Next</p>
        <p>This month, it appeared to be happening again, with the rules for the anti-pollution hardware on cars. For years California, with the nation's worst air, has been setting its own rules, and in August, the eight Northeastern states jointly agreed that they, too, would adopt the California standards. Last week, a crucial subcommittee in the House of Representatives voted 22 to 0 to embrace the same rules, and the bill, which would bring the remaining 41 states in line, is now before the full House Energy and Commerce Committee.</p>
        <p>Now California, where the air is so bad that there is a mandate for experimentation, is looking into carcinogenic components of gasoline, and officials in other states are watching with an eye to following along.</p>
        <p>As California breathes, it seems, so breathes the nation. And in the wings is the European Community, which is beginning to adopt some car pollution standards, based on Washington's.</p>
        <p>It is not only automobile standards over which Washington is losing the leading role. A dozen jurisdictions, from Phoenix to Chicago, are mandating changes in the composition of house paint and lacquer to reduce air pollution. Washington may act on that issue, too, but unlike the case of gasoline and cars, it will not be at the behest of environmentalists. The paint manufacturers, quivering at the prospect of dozens of sets of rules, are pleading for a national standard.</p>
        <p>On a global environmental issue, destruction of the earth's protective ozone layer by chlorofluorocarbons, Washington is committed to a 50 percent reduction by the end of the century, while governments from the state of Vermont to the city of Irvine, Calif., have moved toward a complete ban. A Stunning Reversal</p>
        <p>The new pattern of pollution control, from the bottom up, is a stunning reversal of the situation in the 1970's, when Washington dragged the states, kicking and screaming, into cleanup programs. The change is not lost on Mr. Jorling, who served in the 1970's as Assistant Administrator of the E.P.A. and before that was a staff member on a Senate committee with jurisdiction over air.</p>
        <p>''In those days, I'd have said if you're interested in improving the environment, the first thing you'd do is to abolish state governments,'' Mr. Jorling said.</p>
        <p>But now, 200 years after the states first gathered to write a Constitution to handle interstate problems, they are largely returning, at least on the issue of air pollution, to taking on the job themselves. Why? ''The glib answer is that nature abhors a vacuum,'' said one official of California's South Coast Air Quality Management District, Paul Wuebben, who is the manager of the clean fuels program. The Reagan Administration produced a vacuum in Washington for clean air policy, he said, and the Bush Administration has not filled it.</p>
        <p>Southern California's air is so much worse than that of other places that it is forced to move first, experts agree. And if California takes a step without falling on its face, others are persuaded that they can take the step, too.</p>
        <p>A result is to take the environmentalists' motto popularized by Abbie Hoffman, think globally and act locally, and turn it on its head. California thinks locally and the world acts.</p>
        <p>David G. Hawkins, another former Assistant Administrator of the E.P.A. and now a senior lawyer with the Natural Resources Defense Council, said a stumbling block for Washington is ''persuading decision makers that we know how to do it, that there is in fact a feasible way of responding to this pollution problem.''</p>
        <p>But if fuel can be reformulated in Calfornia, state officials elsewhere know they can set similar requirements. If Detroit can make better pollution control devices for the California market, then it can do the same for the rest of the country. Why Is Washington Last?  But why then are the California innovations embraced by policy makers in Providence, R.I., and Concord, N.H., before the District of Columbia?</p>
        <p>Officials in California and other states point to a political factor. In Washington, the American Petroleum Institute and the Motor Vehicle Manufacturers Association lobby effectively for the interests of the fuel and car industries, experts say, but neither of these lobbies is as powerful in Albany or Montpelier, Vt.</p>
        <p>That may change. The American Petroleum Institute, for example, sued in Albany - unsuccessfully, it turned out - to try to block the change in fuel requirements in New York.</p>
        <p>But California is taking steps that may keep it out front. In addition to preparing regulations on toxic chemicals in gasoline, Mr. Wuebben's agency, for example, is seeking to organize a consortium of public and private interests with an $88 million budget to commercialize electric vehicles. If successful, it will have applications in cities around the nation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
