<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Toward Smaller Lawns and Nurseries</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Design Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="62" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Arts; Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="290917"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="HOME TURF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAWNS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAIL ORDER COMPANIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CATALOGUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LACEY, ALLEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Turf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landscaping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mail Order Companies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D61538F936A25753C1A96F948260" item-length="1091" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Toward Smaller Lawns and Nurseries</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Allen Lacy; Allen Lacy's latest book is ''The American Gardener: A Sampler,'' published by Farrar, Straus and Giroux.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ON MANY A HOT SUMMER day, the crews of so-called landscaping services can be seen tending lawns on the street where I live.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ON MANY A HOT SUMMER day, the crews of so-called landscaping services can be seen tending lawns on the street where I live.</p>
        <p>ON MANY A HOT SUMMER day, the crews of so-called landscaping services can be seen tending lawns on the street where I live.</p>
        <p>Over the last few years, more and more of these work crews regularly mow and trim my neighbors' greenswards, and keep them doused with fertilizers, broadleaf weed killers, fungicides and other chemicals. The scene is not an unusual one in suburban America today. Maintaining a well-kept lawn has become almost a moral symbol signifying the decency and probity of the homeowner.</p>
        <p>This obsession with orderly lawns - one of several venerable American gardening trends that have continued over the past decade - actually began over a century ago. In his book ''The Art of Beautifying Suburban Home Grounds,'' published in 1870, the landscape architect Frank J. Scott set about to convince a nation that the lawnless life was not worth living. Writing during a period when prosperous middle-class families were beginning to take advantage of the railroad to work in cities and live on their once-rural fringes, Scott envisioned our suburbs as private property unified by flawless turf to form the visual equivalent of a great public park. His enormously influential ideas took hold and have endured on into the 1980's, aided by the almost universal use of gasoline-powered mowers, chemical fertilizers and pesticides for eliminating dandelions, crabgrass, grubs and fungus diseases.</p>
        <p>As the decade draws to a close, however, this preoccupation with the pristine, manicured lawn may be about to change. Our awareness of environmental issues - ranging from the diminishing ozone layer to increasingly polluted beaches - has been heightened, and once a lawn is looked at from a conservationist point of view, it becomes suspect. Lawn maintenance can be seen as a wasteful use of energy, in terms of the gasoline or electricity used to keep grounds mowed, trimmed and swept free of leaves, and as an environmentally dangerous use of petrochemicals, which are often used to keep them fed. The water that grass requires is another natural resource in short supply in many parts of the country and in periods of drought.</p>
        <p>I do not predict some overnight revolution in which all the homeowners across the nation will do away with their grass for environmental reasons. I do believe, however, that as we enter the 90's, we may learn to live with smaller lawns and to be more relaxed about them, to put up with a few dandelions or wild onions among our fescue and bluegrass and to let the grass grow higher and even turn brown in late summer.</p>
        <p>Another major development to come out of the 80's is the increasing number of small nurseries that sell primarily through mail-order catalogues. (Among the 10 nurseries I buy plants from on a regular basis, most are owned and run by an individual or a couple, and have been established only since 1981.) Instead of photographs, their catalogues feature detailed plant descriptions, and must be purchased - as opposed to those of the large nurseries, which are often elaborately illustrated and sent free to potential customers.</p>
        <p>Because their scale of operations is limited, these smaller nurseries have enormous flexibility in marketing new and often uncommon (Continued on Page 66) plants (unlike the bigger ones, which sell to a mass market and often cannot afford to carry a plant unless there is a great enough demand for it). The wide variety of small-nursery offerings makes them ideally suited for a select, often very choosy - and increasingly sophisticated - clientele. On a recent trip to a relatively new little nursery near my home in New Jersey, I fell into conversation with a fellow customer who could epitomize this new breed of gardener. She was admiring several sturdy plants of the little-known Asteromoea mongolica, a charming double daisy with flowers like powder puffs. She told me she had bought the plant last year from a mail-order nursery, and proceeded to enumerate an impressive list of other new mail-order acquisitions. When I asked how long she'd been gardening, she surprised me by replying, ''Just three years.''</p>
        <p>As the number of small nurseries and their customers has increased during the 80's, so has the interest in ornamental perennials, which have been made more easily available through the mail-order catalogues. Gardeners who a decade ago were content with marigolds and impatiens and petunias now want Crambe cordifolia and Salvia guaranitica - and they are less and less intimidated by the Latin names. Some evidence of this turn toward perennials is easily spotted in any good bookstore. Over the past year, three excellent books have been published on the subject: Frederick McGourty's ''The Perennial Gardener'' (Houghton Mifflin), Elisabeth Sheldon's ''A Proper Garden'' (Stackpole Books) and Ruth Rogers Clausen and Nicolas H. Ekstrom's ''Perennials for American Gardens'' (Random House).</p>
        <p>The small-nursery trend is also partly responsible for the current interest in North American native plants, which these small nurseries tend to promote. There has been a growing public recognition that Americans have neglected for far too long our indigenous perennials and woody plants. The great value of such plants - aside from the extraordinary beauty of many of them - is that, having evolved in our conditions of soil and climate, they are tough and rugged in the face of drought, severe winters and blistering summers. After more than a century in which varieties with exotic origins, such as most roses and many rhododendrons, have dominated the home landscape, we are beginning to discover the high merit of our own boltonia, yuccas, oak-leaf hydrangeas, franklinias and New England asters, among others.</p>
        <p>Thus, as we look forward to the next decade, we can envision, on the one hand, smaller and less manicured lawns - a response to environmental concerns - dotting our suburbs. At the same time, the 90's may bring a greater diversity in gardens themselves. Since World War II, suburban plots have tended toward a predictable sameness, with homeowners setting out the same plants from local garden centers that everyone else in the neighborhood has bought. But as gardeners come to rely more and more on mail-order nurseries, and as they become increasingly sophisticated in their plant selections, the suburban landscape will inevitably become more varied. People will choose plants to please themselves, not to conform to any preconceived idea about what is proper. Gardening for pleasure is, after all, what gardening is all about.</p>
        <p>HOME TURF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
