<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Energy Vandals</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="241877"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND LIGHTING CO (LILCO)</org>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SHOREHAM NUCLEAR POWER PLANT</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFDC113DF933A15757C0A96F948260" item-length="665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Energy Vandals</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Unswervingly, New York is about to commit a blunder so monumental that, like the pyramids, it may prompt future generations to marvel at the ruinous excesses of human folly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Unswervingly, New York is about to commit a blunder so monumental that, like the pyramids, it may prompt future generations to marvel at the ruinous excesses of human folly.</p>
        <p>Unswervingly, New York is about to commit a blunder so monumental that, like the pyramids, it may prompt future generations to marvel at the ruinous excesses of human folly.</p>
        <p>The rest of America may fret about oil spills, the greenhouse effect, acid rain and dependence on oil imports. Not New York. It has found a unique way to worsen all four - by abandoning a fully built nuclear power plant just at the moment, possibly this very morning, that Federal regulators declare it safe and ready to run.</p>
        <p>The Valdez oil spill has reawakened pressures to conserve oil rather than risk despoiling more wilderness. But even as gobs of oil befoul Alaska's pristine beaches, the Long Island Lighting Company is being forced to abandon its 800-megawatt nuclear power plant at Shoreham and to put up oil-burning plants in its place. Shoreham would have saved consumption of eight million barrels of oil a year. That's more than are transported by six ships the size of the Exxon Valdez.</p>
        <p>Nuclear energy also is a way to minimize the feared warming of the earth's climate. That threat seems more real than ever, and Western societies are wondering how to reduce use of fossil fuels whose waste gases help heat the atmosphere. But in the hothouse of New York politics, no one seems to care a fig about the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>Some New Yorkers worry about acid rain, which has rendered hundreds of Adirondack lakes lifeless and may threaten forests throughout the Appalachians. But New York's legislators would rather add to the acid rain burden with pollutants from new oil-fired plants than relieve it with nuclear power.</p>
        <p>Conscientious citizens fret about America's renewed and steadily rising dependence on foreign oil and the defense costs required to keep the Persian Gulf open. Such matters count for nothing in Albany. Lilco is already the only U.S. utility almost entirely dependent on oil. Now, in lieu of Shoreham, it plans four new plants, most probably oil-fired, making its dependence even greater.</p>
        <p>Nuclear power has its own risks. But they are vastly exaggerated by the claims that Shoreham is unsafe and its surroundings could not be evacuated in case of emergency. Suffolk County and Gov. Mario Cuomo repeated these arguments so often that the Nuclear Regulatory Commission finally lost patience and barred them from further intervention. The N.R.C. staff has concluded that the Shoreham area would be no harder to evacuate than other reactor sites.</p>
        <p>Who is to blame for the historic folly of scrapping Shoreham? First and foremost, Long Islanders. They have punished any politician who dared tell them the truth about Shoreham. Second, Governor Cuomo. Instead of educating public opinion and making Shoreham acceptable by reducing its cost to ratepayers, he joined the fear-mongers.</p>
        <p>Who then was left to speak in the public's interest and fight for the reactor to open? Not William Catacosinos, the president of Lilco. Not Peter Bradford, chairman of New York's supposedly independent Public Service Commission. Not Adm. Lando Zech, chairman of the N.R.C. in Washington. They all looked at the dragon Long Islanders had created and quailed.</p>
        <p>The Nuclear Regulatory Commission deserves special blame. It took years to mull over the Shoreham case, even though Lilco was under increasing pressure to close the plant. The commission is ambling to a conclusion that would permit the $5.5 billion plant to open just as the company has agreed to close it. Wonderful timing.</p>
        <p>But no worse than that of the New York Legislature. Public concern about oil spills, the greenhouse effect, acid rain and imported oil is building to a crest. It's not hard to imagine that in a few years, or even a few months, Americans will be straining to mobilize every alternative energy source that does not risk burdening water, air, forests and defense spending. And it's not hard to imagine what they will call the New Yorkers who, with such an alternative in their grasp at Shoreham, threw it away.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
