<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mountain Sickness a Sneaky Ailment</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="248133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="ON YOUR OWN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOUNTAIN SICKNESS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">NELSON, JANET</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFDE1E3BF93BA35756C0A96F948260" item-length="1258" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mountain Sickness a Sneaky Ailment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET NELSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NELSON, JANET</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE main problem with altitude sickness is that most people don't recognize that they have it. The symptoms are usually mild and may resemble flu or some other short-term illness. But a recent study that explores acute altitude, or mountain, sickness indicates that one out of every four people get ill when they go 6,000 feet or more above sea level.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE main problem with altitude sickness is that most people don't recognize that they have it. The symptoms are usually mild and may resemble flu or some other short-term illness. But a recent study that explores acute altitude, or mountain, sickness indicates that one out of every four people get ill when they go 6,000 feet or more above sea level.</p>
        <p>THE main problem with altitude sickness is that most people don't recognize that they have it. The symptoms are usually mild and may resemble flu or some other short-term illness. But a recent study that explores acute altitude, or mountain, sickness indicates that one out of every four people get ill when they go 6,000 feet or more above sea level.</p>
        <p>''Even some macho high-mountain-trek doctors take mountain sickness lightly if it is not severe and life-threatening,'' said Dr. A. Bruce Montgomery, an assistant professor at the State University of New York at Stony Brook and one of the authors of the study, which was published in February in the Journal of American Medical Association. ''The most widely-recognized symptom is shortness of breath, but that occurs mostly at extremely high altitudes.''</p>
        <p>More common symptoms are sleep disturbances, headaches, fatigue and nausea. Dr. Montgomery, who is an avid skier, said that on the first day or two of a vacation in the Rocky Mountains, he usually got a headache - sometimes severe - but that he tended to attribute it to something besides the altitude.</p>
        <p>''You travel across the country, you've got jet lag, you ride a bus and inhale carbon dioxide - there are plenty of reasons to attribute to a headache,'' he said. ''But we found in two studies, that even at 7,000 feet, which is really not high, more people than we expected get mild, but noticeable symptoms.''</p>
        <p>As more people take mountain vacations, both in the summer and the winter, altitude sickness is a growing nuisance. At higher altitudes, the air contains less oxygen, and the body must compensate by increasing its red blood cells. That takes time, so the conventional treatment for altitude sickness is to ascend as gradually as possible, to go at a leisurely pace for the first two to three days and to get lots of rest.</p>
        <p>But, Dr. Montgomery asks, ''at $500 or more per day for a vacation, who can afford to give up even one day of the pleasure you came for?''</p>
        <p>Dr. Montgomery studied the effects of altitude on 454 doctors attending medical meetings at Rocky Mountain resorts in 1985. Through a questionnaire, he determined how many of them had symptoms of altitude sickness and how serious the symptoms were. After determining that about one in four people had some discomfort, in 1986 and '87 he tested the effectiveness of a short-term drug treatment.</p>
        <p>One drug, acetazolamide (brand-name Diamox), has been approved by the Food and Drug Administration for treatment of mountain sickness, but it has the unpleasant side effect of making carbonated beverages like beer and colas taste terrible and may cause tingling of the fingers.</p>
        <p>For his study, in which a control group received a placebo and other subjects received a drug, Dr. Montgomery tested another drug, dexamethasone.</p>
        <p>Dexamethasone, which is a powerful steroid, was first tested in altitude chamber studies, but recently has been used by climbers in the Himalayas. Dr. Montgomery said the drug inhibited the swelling that affects the brain in mountain sickness. ''It works, but we don't quite understand why,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Drummond Rennie, another proponent of drug remedies for mountain sickness and one of the first people to do extensive tests with acetazolamide, cautions against relying too heavily on drugs for mountain sickness. ''Obeying nature and taking your time is the best way to take a vacation,'' said Dr. Rennie, a professor at the University of California Medical School at San Francisco. ''It's better to spend more time acclimatizing to high altitudes.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Rennie said, however, that there could be serious problems with exercise at high altitudes. Some climbers on mountain treks, for instance, submit to peer pressure and would rather die than stop, he said. ''Mountain sickness is caused by going too high too fast,'' Dr. Rennie said. ''It's an individual thing and has nothing to do with how physically fit a person is. It's your body reacting.''</p>
        <p>He said that people who have had mountain sickness tended to get it again and that, depending on the severity of the symptoms, they were the best candidates for taking a drug to alleviate illness. Dexamethasone is recommended for, at most, only two or three days.</p>
        <p>Because symptoms do not normally reveal themselves for six hours or more, short-term relief is not usually needed. But some people may be affected on a short trip, such as driving up to the top of Colorado's Pikes Peak, l4,110 feet, or they may need a quick fix in situations in which the only other choice is descending to a lower altitude.</p>
        <p>Dr. Marcus Raichle of Washington University School of Medicine in St. Louis, used an old remedy for quick, but momentary, relief of mountain sickness while on a Himalayan expedition: breathing into a paper bag.</p>
        <p>''In a matter of one minute, people feel much better after taking low concentrations of carbon dioxide,'' he said. Carbon dioxide makes the brain's blood vessels dilate, increasing circulation. Dr. Raichle said that although the blood is carrying less of the needed oxygen to relieve mountain sickness, the increased blood flow enables the brain to get more of what oxygen is available.</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Raichle, the Bolivians have used this remedy for the past century when riding trains over high mountain passes.</p>
        <p>While altitude has varying effects on the bodies of recreational athletes traveling to the mountains, it has very specific effects on the performance of their equipment. The thin air and the dry climate produce some favorable results in tennis and golf.</p>
        <p>''You don't have to swing as hard to get power,'' said Todd Grange, tennis director of the Snowmass Club, at 8,600 feet in Snowmass, Colo. ''For that reason, we tend to play more serve and volley. Your opponent doesn't have time to set up for a passing shot so you can get to the net and put the ball away.''</p>
        <p>He recommended additional topspin to keep the ball in and suggested opting for more control than power on serves. ''It takes two or three sets to adjust, but people often go home with quicker reflexes,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Golf balls may travel 15 to 20 percent farther in rarefied mountain air, said Rick Fretland, director of golf at the Copper Creek Golf Club, at 9,600 feet in Copper Mountain, Colo. A player who uses a 7 iron to hit 150 yards at sea level may choose an 8 or 9 iron for the same distance on a mountain course.</p>
        <p>The ball spins less at high altitudes causing it to travel at a lower trajectory and have less bite when hitting the greens. ''Balls with deep and large dimple patterns can overcome this because they will go higher and land softer,'' said Fretland. ''Also, the slicing or hooking action of the balls are less pronounced at altitude.''</p>
        <p>Fretland said the effect of more distance and greater accuracy is ego-boosting. ''Unfortunately, coming to the mountains does not offer a permanent cure for a slice,'' he said.  How to Relieve Mountain Sickness  Take it easy for the first two or three days. If you have headache, feel nauseous or unusually fatigued, rest and avoid vigorous activity.  Eat light, carbohydrate-rich foods, avoiding fats and meats. Drink plenty of fluids, but not alcohol, which acts as a diuretic at high altitudes.  Be alert to the most serious form of mountain sickness, pulmonary edema, which can occur abovw 10,000 feet. Symptoms begin with a dry cough followed by shortness of breath, wheezing and chest pain. Don't be alarmed. Going to a lower altitude produces almost instant relief for the condition.</p>
        <p>ON YOUR OWN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
