<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Frustrated by Global Efforts, City Fights Ozone on Its Own</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="267153"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR CONDITIONING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFRIGERATORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLASTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTAINERS AND PACKAGING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REPAIR SERVICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INSULATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRVINE (CALIF)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">REINHOLD, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Service Industries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electricity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DD1F3EF93AA25754C0A96F948260" item-length="1427" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Frustrated by Global Efforts, City Fights Ozone on Its Own</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT REINHOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REINHOLD, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>IRVINE, Calif., July 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The ranks of American states, counties and cities impatient with the pace of international efforts to protect the earth's ozone layer are swelling. The latest action comes from conservative Orange County, where tonight the City Council of Irvine approved what is believed to be the most far-reaching measure yet to control ozone-depleting chemicals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The ranks of American states, counties and cities impatient with the pace of international efforts to protect the earth's ozone layer are swelling. The latest action comes from conservative Orange County, where tonight the City Council of Irvine approved what is believed to be the most far-reaching measure yet to control ozone-depleting chemicals.</p>
        <p>The ranks of American states, counties and cities impatient with the pace of international efforts to protect the earth's ozone layer are swelling. The latest action comes from conservative Orange County, where tonight the City Council of Irvine approved what is believed to be the most far-reaching measure yet to control ozone-depleting chemicals.</p>
        <p>The Irvine ordinance will prohibit the use of nearly all chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, and related compounds in any industrial process, except in the manufacture of drugs and medical devices and when military specifications call for them. It will ban the sale and use of plastic foam food packaging, if the chemical compounds were used in their manufacture, and it will prohibit the use of building insulation containing the compounds.</p>
        <p>The ordinance will not bar the use of the compounds in automobile air conditioners and refrigerators, since there are no current substitutes. But it will require service stations and repair shops to capture and recycle the compounds, raising prices for consumers.</p>
        <p>The main provisions in the ordinance will go into effect on July 1, 1990. Center for Manufacturing</p>
        <p>Irvine (pronounced UR-vine) is a ''planned'' city of 42 square miles situated 55 miles south of Los Angeles. The city, which has a population of 105,000, was created out of orange groves 18 years ago and has since become a major center of aerospace, computer and other high-technology manufacturing.</p>
        <p>Mayor Larry Agran estimated about 400 to 500 of Irvine's 5,000 businesses will be affected by the ordinance and that they currently release almost half a million pounds of ozone-depleting chemicals into the air each year. ''We've got a moral obligation in this matter,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The vote tonight was 4 to 1. Councilwoman Sally Anne Sheridan, who voted against the ordinance, said it was ''unbelievable'' that Irvine could have a significant effect on the global problem. She added that the ordinance puts the city in ''splendid isolation'' by ''arrogantly forcing laws'' on businesses and residents.</p>
        <p>Industry leaders here remain uneasy about the economic consequences of the ordinance. ''This will have a significant economic impact on companies in the city,'' said Todd B. Nicholson, president of the Industrial League of Orange County, which represents 900 companies. ''This is an international problem. For one community to do this puts small employers at a significant economic disadvantage.'' Used Worldwide</p>
        <p>Chlorofluorocarbons are used worldwide in thousands of industrial processes like cleaning computer circuit boards and medical equipment, and as refrigerants and fire extinguishers.</p>
        <p>In recent months, world leaders have begun to take action to reduce the use of chlorofluorocarbons. In March, the 12 nations of the European Community agreed to phase out five of the most troublesome compounds by the end of the century to combat what scientists say is the alarming erosion of the ozone layer, which filters out the ultraviolent radiation from the sun. Some scientists have argued that as the ozone layer is depleted, temperatures on earth will rise and an increasing number of skin cancer and other diseases will result.</p>
        <p>Irvine officials say they want quicker action in reducing the compounds and hope that other cities around the country will follow their lead, creating a kind of international diplomacy from the ground up. ''We are very eager to prod our national Government and international bodies to act much more quickly in the face of this global emergency,'' Mayor Agran said in an interview. ''Local communities acting two to five years in advance of states and nations is how change takes place.''</p>
        <p>The Center for Innovative Diplomacy, which Mr. Agran heads, has called a national conference here for Friday and Saturday. Mayors and council members are expected from dozens of North American cities, including Denver, Toronto, Sacramento, Calif., and Albuquerque, N.M. Other Local Actions</p>
        <p>Other state and local governments have already taken some steps in fighting the compounds. Styrofoam packaging containing CFC's has been banned in Suffolk County, N.Y., Newark, Tempe, Ariz., Portland, Ore., Florida, and several California cities, including Los Angeles, San Francisco, Berkeley and Palo Alto. In California's Silicon Valley, which is probably the largest emitter of the compounds in the United States, the city of San Jose is drawing up an ordinance. Vermont requires recycling of CFC's in car air conditioners and has barred their use in cars starting with the 1993 models. In 1978, the Environmental Protection Agency banned chlorofluorocarbons as aerosol propellants. And now the European Community has vowed to eliminate altogether the five most dangerous.</p>
        <p>The Irvine ordinance goes beyond other measures and also covers the related halons, used in fire extinguishers, and the widely used solvents carbon tetrachloride and methyl chloroform. It will prohibit their use in ''the manufacture, production, cleansing, degreasing or sterilization of any substance or product'' apart from the exceptions. 'Unnecessary' and 'Redundant'</p>
        <p>But while they say they support the phasing out of the use of the compounds, the producers of the chemicals say the Irvine law may undermine the orderly transition agreed to by 46 countries in Montreal in 1987. The countries agreed to put an immediate limit on production of the chemical compounds and agreed to cut it by half by 1998.</p>
        <p>In Washington, Kevin J. Fay, executive director of the Alliance for a Responsible CFC Policy, representing the five American producers and about 500 users of the compounds, called the Irvine action ''totally unnecessary'' and ''redundant.''</p>
        <p>Industry, he said, had already voluntarily replaced the compounds in food packing, and the Montreal protocols, which are due to be strengthened in Nairobi this August, provide ''a reasonable transition'' that would protect both industry and consumers.</p>
        <p>Many executives in Irvine are dubious that substitutes can be found quickly enough to satisfy the ordinance's requirements, though most seem to support the notion philosophically. ''Down the road there will be replacements,'' said Kevin Clark, manager of facilities engineering for Parker-Bertea Aerospace, a division of the Parker Hannifin Corporation of Cleveland, which employs 3,500 people in Irvine making landing gear, rudder controls and fire fighting systems. ''But I don't know if it can be done in one year. It does not give industry enough time to switch over.'' The company, like most others, uses freon and trichloroethane for microscopic cleaning of precision components.</p>
        <p>Jim Jenal, a City Council aide, said the problem of substitution is ''not insurmountable.'' A number of alternative cleaners are under development, some of them water-based. One Irvine company, Western Digital, a maker of computer parts, is already switching to a water process to clean circuit boards.</p>
        <p>In recent days, to address industry concerns, city officials eased provisions in the bill to allow a waiver when a company shows there is no ''technically or economically feasible'' alternative chemical. Air Conditioner Repairs</p>
        <p>For consumers, the chief impact of the Irvine ordinance will be felt when they have their automobile air conditioners serviced. The ordinance will require service stations to buy ''vampire units,'' which cost up to $5,000 each, to suck the used freon out of air conditioners before replacement, rather than releasing the freon into the air as most now do. The ordinance will also forbid the sale of any ozone-depleting compound for use as a coolant to anyone who does not own a recyling system.</p>
        <p>Douglas H. Dupleix, proprietor of Expressly European Auto Service in Irvine, complained that business will suffer if only Irvine imposed such restrictions. ''People will just go to other cities,'' he said. ''It will just hurt the businesses that do air conditioning repair in Irvine.'' At the Vette Tech auto repair shop, Brian V. Geraci, estimated that the cost of air conditioning recharges would rise from $30 to $100, although city officials disputed that estimate.</p>
        <p>Mayor Agran agreed there would be some short-term difficulties. The law, he said, will ''require people to conduct business in new ways,'' but ultimately would put the city ahead in dealing with the new reality.</p>
        <p>''Over the long haul,'' the Mayor said, the ordinance it ''creates a more favorable business climate,'' he said. ''It's the old trade-off between short term and long term.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
