<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Everybody Into the Pool, but Carefully</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="54" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19890310T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="224488"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="CONSUMER'S WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SWIMMING POOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PROTECTION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SLOANE, LEONARD</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CONSUMER'S WORLD PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D71E3CF93BA25751C0A96F948260" item-length="995" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Everybody Into the Pool, but Carefully</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEONARD SLOANE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SLOANE, LEONARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: It's Opening Day for the swimming pool season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: It's Opening Day for the swimming pool season.</p>
        <p>It's Opening Day for the swimming pool season.</p>
        <p>Retailers of above-ground pools and builders of in-ground pools traditionally kick off their annual selling period on the Presidential holiday weekend. Consumers can see and choose from what's new early enough to have their pool in place this summer. The goal, of course, is to buy the right product at an affordable price.</p>
        <p>''Make sure that you understand up front just what the process is going to be,'' said William W. Sadd, the executive vice president of the National Spa and Pool Institute, a trade association for the residential pool industry, which held a convention and exposition this week in Las Vegas, Nev. ''Unhappy consumers are those who don't understand the process.''</p>
        <p>More and more families are learning about this process of acquiring and installing a swimming pool. The industry sold $7 billion worth of products in 1987, including about 125,000 in-ground residential pools and 305,000 above-ground pools, according to the most recent statistics. Volume this year is expected to rise as much as 10 percent or so, said Lester Kowalsky, a swimming-pool consultant in Merrick, L.I.</p>
        <p>''People buy a swimming pool to make a vacation spot out of their backyard,'' Mr. Kowalsky said. ''They also avoid the crowds and traffic of beaches, and know where their children are.''</p>
        <p>Along with comfort, other reasons cited by pool specialists for the growth of residential pool sales include a robust economy, the increase in the pollution of the nation's waterways and the scorching heat of the last two summers. Fear of the greenhouse effect - a buildup of heat-trapping pollutants in the atmosphere that may be warming the earth - was also mentioned as a stimulant to pool purchases.</p>
        <p>In addition, a pool is seen by many homeowners as an enhancement to their property that is likely to add to the resale value, although probably not the full amount invested. As Harry J. Friedman, president of the Friedman Group, a Los Angeles management consulting firm that has studied the industry, noted: ''In a lot of circumstances, it very much adds to the value of the house. But in a lot of areas, it is a deterrent because people don't want to maintain it.''</p>
        <p>Poorly built pools can create problems beyond the pool area. If the structure gives way, water could play havoc with the area around a house and the house itself. ''A swimming pool is a fairly complex construction job,'' said Frank Geremia Jr., president of Geremia Pools of Sacramento, Calif.</p>
        <p>Above-ground pools start at $500 and can go up to $9,000, depending on the model and the accessories and options. In-ground pools come in standard and custom versions and fit into one of three general classifications. Vinyl-liner pools, the most popular, usually cost $9,000 to $25,000; fiberglass pools cost $12,500 to $25,000, and pools made of Gunite - concrete sprayed under hydraulic pressure - cost $25,000 and can rise to as much as $150,000.</p>
        <p>But problems can begin with choosing a builder. As with any big-ticket item, there is less chance of something going wrong if a pool is purchased from a company recommended by a friend, relative or business associate. You can also ask two or three contractors in your area for the names of previous customers, although it is unlikely that anyone will give the names of those who have complained about shoddy work.</p>
        <p>Another important consideration is the contract. ''The contract should be readable and should be read,'' said Robert M. Hoffman, a marketing consultant in Fort Lauderdale, Fla. ''It should outline what's going to happen.''</p>
        <p>Then it is time for other vital decisions. Where should the pool be located? Which zoning and setback regulations are applicable? What size and shape should it be? Will the pool be used most of the time for swimming or for cooling off? Who will do the decking and landscaping?</p>
        <p>''Building a pool is like building a home, and we all know what a pain in the neck that is,'' said Albert Rizzo, president of the Rizzo Construction Pool Company in Newington, Conn.</p>
        <p>A key factor in building a backyard pool is the fencing, or barriers, to surround it. Accidents, particularly to children, are always a possibility. The Consumer Product Safety Commission has reported that drowning in residential swimming pools is the second leading cause of accidental death at home to children under 5. The commission also said there were more than 4,000 submersion injuries affecting children in 1987.</p>
        <p>The commission added: ''The use of effective residential swimming pool barriers is believed to be one of the very best ways available at this time to reduce these losses. A barrier is vital to the safety of children since parents cannot be expected to keep children in their line of sight 100 percent of the time.''</p>
        <p>Some states have laws governing concerning fencing, although New York does not.</p>
        <p>People interested in residential pools can obtain information and names of local vendors by calling the National Spa and Pool Institute at 800-528-6050.</p>
        <p>If a pool is in your future, ignore the chill winds and start planning now.  BEFORE DIVING, BUILD A FENCE</p>
        <p>In a proposal for a national barrier code for residential pools, the staff of the Consumer Product Safety Commission calls for a minimum fence height of four feet as well as locking devices on access gates.</p>
        <p>Fencing for in-ground pools is currently required by many states and localities. In New York, barriers are regulated by local governments.</p>
        <p>''We don't get involved in requirements regarding pools,'' said Richard M. Kessel, the executive director of the New York State Consumer Protection Board.</p>
        <p>Most experts agree that fencing is a good idea whether or not it is required, primarily to protect children.</p>
        <p>Frank Kessler, president of a company in Delair, N.J., that makes the Esther Williams and Johnny Weissmuller pools, noted that with above-ground models, the sides of the pool generally serve as the fence.</p>
        <p>CONSUMER'S WORLD  Correction:  March 10, 1989, Friday, Late City Final Edition</p>
        <p>An article on the Consumer's World page on Feb. 18 about swimming pools misstated fencing requirements for outdoor residential pools in New York State. Barriers at least four feet high are required by state law.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 10, 1989, Friday, Late City Final Edition</p>
        <p>An article on the Consumer's World page on Feb. 18 about swimming pools misstated fencing requirements for outdoor residential pools in New York State. Barriers at least four feet high are required by state law.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
