<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reagan Arms Adviser Says Bush Is Wrong on Short-Range Missiles</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="246563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC WEAPONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMS CONTROL AND LIMITATION AND DISARMAMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MISSILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">US-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-USSR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WEST GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NORTH ATLANTIC TREATY ORGANIZATION (NATO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NITZE, PAUL H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORDON, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHULTZ, GEORGE P (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KISSINGER, HENRY A (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BAKER, JAMES A 3D (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIDGWAY, ROZANNE (ASST SEC)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DC1330F930A35756C0A96F948260" item-length="1096" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reagan Arms Adviser Says Bush Is Wrong on Short-Range Missiles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL R. GORDON, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GORDON, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Paul H. Nitze, the Reagan Administration's top arms control adviser, said today that President Bush was making a serious mistake in refusing to open talks with the Soviet Union on short-range nuclear missiles in Europe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Paul H. Nitze, the Reagan Administration's top arms control adviser, said today that President Bush was making a serious mistake in refusing to open talks with the Soviet Union on short-range nuclear missiles in Europe.</p>
        <p>Paul H. Nitze, the Reagan Administration's top arms control adviser, said today that President Bush was making a serious mistake in refusing to open talks with the Soviet Union on short-range nuclear missiles in Europe.</p>
        <p>In an interview a day after he left office, Mr. Nitze made it clear that he strongly disagreed with the Bush Administration on an issue that has become a matter of sharp dispute within the Western alliance.</p>
        <p>He said he warned Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d this year that the two-pronged American approach of insisting on the development of a new generation of short-range nuclear weapons while opposing talks on the weapons, as advocated by Bonn, could not be sustained within NATO and would create a crisis in West Germany. In the West's Interest</p>
        <p>Moreover, the veteran negotiator said he believed that negotiations on reducing short-range nuclear weapons - those with ranges of less than 300 miles - would be in the military interest of the West because they would provide an opportunity to eliminate a large Soviet advantage.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nitze said the Administration approach was ''politically impossible for much of Europe.''</p>
        <p>''I cannot think of a German who would agree to that,'' he said. ''Many of the allies think it is a crazy proposition.''</p>
        <p>West German proponents of talks on short-range missiles say there is no reason to refuse such talks, on weapons primarily based on or aimed at German territory, when the alliance was willing to negotiate the elimination of medium- and shorter-range missiles.</p>
        <p>A top arms control adviser to President Reagan and Secretary of StateGeorge P. Shultz, the 82-year-old Mr. Nitze was often used as an emissary to North Atlantic Treaty Organization nations on critical arms issues during the Reagan Administration.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nitze has served in a variety of national security posts, including Navy Secretary and Deputy Secretary of Defense. In the early part of the Reagan Administration, Mr. Nitze was the chief negotiator of the treaty to ban intermediate-range nuclear forces in Europe. Turns Down a Bush Offer</p>
        <p>He ended his Government service after turning down an offer from the Bush Administration to serve as ambassador-at-large emeritus, saying that the position would have left him without any clearly delineated responsibilities.</p>
        <p>In an interview today and a discussion on Monday evening in his library at his homuse in Washington, Mr. Nitze said he has recently been studying ways to end acid rain.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nitze said the Bush Administration was positioning itself to the right of the Reagan Administration in its policy toward Moscow to demonstrate that it ''is not really a follow-on to the Reagan Administration.'' He said it was missing opportunities to improve American-Soviet relations.</p>
        <p>He said many of the appointments made by the Bush Administration had links to former Secretary of State Henry A. Kissinger, who was critical of the arms control approach taken by Mr. Shultz. Mr. Nitze said the Administration had let its strategic review carry on so long that it risked losing momentum toward new arms agreements.</p>
        <p>In a response to questions, he offered a highly critical assessment of Mr. Baker's management style, which he said sought to restrict important deliberations with a small group of advisers, excluding many career State Department officials. Critical of Baker Appointments</p>
        <p>He said Mr. Baker had failed to name some experienced Foreign Service officiers, like Rozanne L. Ridgway, the Assistant Secretary of State for European and Canadian Affairs, to influential positions.</p>
        <p>''Personnel-wise, it was a black mark on one's record to have worked closely with the Reagan Administration,'' Mr. Nitze said.</p>
        <p>Regarding short-range missiles, Mr. Nitze said he had counseled the Reagan and Bush Administrations to open talks on those weapons.</p>
        <p>He said the Administration officials ''should go to the Germans and say we are not against negotiating reductions on these weapons'' while securing assurances from Bonn that such talks would not result in the total elimination of the weapons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nitze said the West should try to negotiate equal ceilings at a low level of about 200 to 300 warheads on each side, a limit that would require huge reductions on the Soviet side.</p>
        <p>NATO has 88 Lance missile launchers in Europe. Each launcher is capable of firing numerous nuclear-armed or conventionally armed missiles. The exact number is classified.</p>
        <p>According to NATO, the Soviet-bloc has about 1,480 short-range missile launchers that can be used to fire nuclear-tipped as well as chemically armed and conventionally armed missiles. NATO has not publicly said how many nuclear-tipped short-range missiles it believes Soviet-bloc nations have and estimates vary. One estimate, Mr. Nitze said, is that the Soviet bloc has about 3,000 nuclear-tipped short-range missiles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nitze said the United States should also try to negotiate with Moscow for the withdrawal of nuclear artillery pieces. Such an agreement would have clear military benefit for the West, he argued. Not only would it eliminate Soviet advantages in these categories of weapons, but it would enable Washington to gather support for deploying a limited number of new, enhanced successors to the aging Lance.</p>
        <p>Unless the United States adopts such an approach he said, ''the political situation in Germany will further deteriorate,'' making it difficult for the Germans to form a coalition Government that NATO could work with. Other Arms Control Matters</p>
        <p>On other arms control matters, Mr. Nitze said the United States should try to negotiate a ban with Moscow on all nuclear weapons at sea except for submarine-launched ballistic missiles. He said it was a mistake for the American Navy to phase out three short-range nuclear missiles for ocean combat without trying to secure Soviet concession in return.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nitze said Washington should try to negotiate a ban on the deployment of anti-satellite weapons. The Pentagon is advocating the development of several new types of such weapons. He also said the Administration should consider ways to improve the American position in the strategic arms talks. Mr. Nitze said the United States should consider proposing a further limit, possibly a ceiling on warheads carried by multiple-warhead missiles.</p>
        <p>Looking back on his days in Mr. Baker's State Department, he said the secretary's approach of relegating key decisions to a tight circle of aides was an ''impossible'' way to run the agency. ''It means that you can't deal with many issues,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
