<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CHILDREN'S BOOKS/SCIENCE</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="287240"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LUOMA, JON R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMON, SEYMOUR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KNAPP, TONI</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WHITFIELD, PHILIP</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WHALES (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SIX BRIDGES OF HUMPHREY THE WHALE, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CAN THE WHALES BE SAVED? (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Children's Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D71E3AF932A35753C1A96F948260" item-length="637" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CHILDREN'S BOOKS/SCIENCE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  WHALES  By Seymour Simon.  Illustrated. Unpaged. New York:  Thomas Y. Crowell. $14.95. (Ages 5-8)  THE SIX BRIDGES OF HUMPHREY THE WHALE  By Toni Knapp.  Illustrated by Craig McFarland Brown.  Unpaged. Colorado Springs, Colo.  The Rockrimmon Press. $15.95. (Ages 9 to 13)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  WHALES  By Seymour Simon.  Illustrated. Unpaged. New York:  Thomas Y. Crowell. $14.95. (Ages 5-8)  THE SIX BRIDGES OF HUMPHREY THE WHALE  By Toni Knapp.  Illustrated by Craig McFarland Brown.  Unpaged. Colorado Springs, Colo.  The Rockrimmon Press. $15.95. (Ages 9 to 13)</p>
        <p>WHALES  By Seymour Simon.  Illustrated. Unpaged. New York:  Thomas Y. Crowell. $14.95. (Ages 5-8)  THE SIX BRIDGES OF HUMPHREY THE WHALE  By Toni Knapp.  Illustrated by Craig McFarland Brown.  Unpaged. Colorado Springs, Colo.  The Rockrimmon Press. $15.95. (Ages 9 to 13)  CAN THE WHALES BE SAVED?  By Philip Whitfield.  Illustrated. 96 pp. New York:  Viking Kestrel. $16.95. (Ages 10 and up)</p>
        <p>Two new books about whales, and another that appears to be, but isn't, suggest how rare it is to find children's books about the natural world that manage to meld sound scientific fact with a sense of the inherent beauty and wonder of nature.</p>
        <p>Any reader looking for just-the-facts will be satisfied by Seymour Simon's ''Whales,'' which examines the whales of the world in a simple text and color photographs. Mr. Simon, a veteran science writer for children, is especially adept at balancing routine details with the startling - explaining, to illustrate the immensity of a whale, that the tongue of a blue whale weighs as much as an entire elephant.</p>
        <p>''Whales'' covers its factual material nicely, from differences among species to feeding behavior, from respiration to hearts and bones. But, like too many of its kind, the book also helps promote the myth that science is a catalogue of objective truths, rather than a process of mystery and discovery. Young readers might have benefited had ''Whales'' been less a textbook and more an evocative account that showed what it is like out there at sea, and undersea, where the whales live.</p>
        <p>''The Six Bridges of Humphrey the Whale'' wanders far in quite another direction. It is a fanciful rendering of the journey of a humpback whale that strayed into California's Sacramento River in 1985. For nearly a month, and with constant television hoopla, scientists and wildlife officials attempted to move the whale, dubbed ''Humphrey,'' safely back out to sea.</p>
        <p>Anthropomorphism has a long and honorable tradition in children's literature, but in what Toni Knapp calls a ''true account and faithful retracing'' of a real whale's very real troubles, its pervasiveness may make parents, and savvy children, groan. The author baldly asserts, for example, that at the end of one particularly stressful day for Humphrey the whale's ''sense of humor was intact.''</p>
        <p>That she jettisons her credibility is regrettable, because Ms. Knapp's story is otherwise compellingly told, accompanied by sumptuous, blue-tinged illustrations, by Craig McFarland Brown, of Humphrey and his journey.</p>
        <p>''Can the Whales Be Saved?'' is not really about whales: it includes only five paragraphs about them. But it is, nevertheless, such a marvelous book for young people about animals, plants, habitats, ecology and environmental issues that no one need feel hoodwinked by the title.</p>
        <p>The biologist Philip Whitfield, of Britain's Natural History Museum, uses a question-and-answer format to look at rain forests, deserts, tundra, endangered species, decomposition, the greenhouse effect and more. A few questions that ordinary curiosity might not generate - ''Are island animals the same as mainland ones?'' - are used to introduce important issues in biology. And as a whole the questions, their answers and the detailed, lavish drawings and photographs that accompany them cover an astonishing range of concepts about the natural world, from ''Where do new types of animals come from?'' to ''Why don't trees grow on top of mountains?'' Mr. Whitfield shows how birds called oxpeckers coexist symbiotically with rhinoceroses, and he explains just exactly why the jungle is so noisy. Like all the best science books for children, ''Can the Whales Be Saved?'' will almost certainly prove irresistible to parents, too. Jon R. Luoma is the author of ''A Crowded Ark.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
