<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Our Towns; Naturalist Dies But His Legacy Still Blooms</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="256455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NATURE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CATSKILLS (NYS AREA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WINERIP, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMILEY, DANIEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Catskills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D71431F935A35755C0A96F948260" item-length="773" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Our Towns; Naturalist Dies But His Legacy Still Blooms</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINERIP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WINERIP, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>NEW PALTZ, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The woods will miss Dan Smiley. So will his research assistants, Anna Forster and Paul Huth. Before the memorial service for their boss Friday, the two took a walk along North Lookout, a ridgetop path Mr. Smiley loved most at dawn, when bird song filled the valley. Miss Forster listened. ''Hermit thrush,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The woods will miss Dan Smiley. So will his research assistants, Anna Forster and Paul Huth. Before the memorial service for their boss Friday, the two took a walk along North Lookout, a ridgetop path Mr. Smiley loved most at dawn, when bird song filled the valley. Miss Forster listened. ''Hermit thrush,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The woods will miss Dan Smiley. So will his research assistants, Anna Forster and Paul Huth. Before the memorial service for their boss Friday, the two took a walk along North Lookout, a ridgetop path Mr. Smiley loved most at dawn, when bird song filled the valley. Miss Forster listened. ''Hermit thrush,'' she said. She knew what Mr. Smiley would have said: ''Make a note, Anna!''</p>
        <p>Except for time away for college, Mr. Smiley spent his 82 years here, helping run his family's Mohonk Mountain Resort, (a National Historic Landmark), and learning everything he could about the surrounding woods. In 60 years of research, he compiled 14,500 note cards on every aspect of his woods, no matter how trivial, from the number of chipmunks seen in November 1931, to the day the mountain laurel bloomed in 1939 (June 13), to the damage done by acid rain.</p>
        <p>''There's a carpenter ant,'' said Mr. Huth. (A note.) Into the woods Mr. Smiley would go, collecting wasps in jelly jars, using a vacuum cleaner to suck gypsy moth eggs off trees.</p>
        <p>''The mountain sandwort is in full bloom,'' said Mr. Huth. (A note.) To outsiders it seemed crazy, all those note cards piling up. But Mr. Smiley loved information and kept collecting it, until he saw patterns emerge. He was an old-fashioned naturalist in the spirit of Charles Darwin. Instead of sailing the world, he learned all he could about his 7,500 acres of woods. Vincent Schaefer, the scientist who invented cloud-seeding, called him ''one of the great naturalists.''</p>
        <p>This wasn't simply quaint. In time those notes paid big dividends for ecologists.</p>
        <p>Acidity studies he took of local lakes in 1931 provided groundwork for modern studies on acid rain's danger. Notes made in the 1950's after the Government sprayed his woods with DDT to control gypsy moths later provided leads on ways to control the moth by natural means.</p>
        <p>The two researchers paused, looking across the valley to the Catskills. In the lush green they could see a patch of bare trees. ''We'd love to be able to tell him there's a vast tract of chestnut oaks dying,'' said Miss Forster.</p>
        <p>''It's opened the forest floor to sunlight,'' said Mr. Huth. ''The laurel is gorgeous. The forest floor should be watched.''</p>
        <p>Miss Forster said, ''I'd love to ask. . .'' and Mr. Huth put in, ''He'd say, 'Back in 1938, we had something similar and. . .' ''</p>
        <p>Daniel Smiley died two weeks ago and it would not be fitting to let it pass without making a note. His scientific method was serendipity. He believed that by pursuing whatever piqued his curiosity and copiously documenting it, observations that seemed unrelated might be linked to yield insight.</p>
        <p>He was a good man, but not an easy one, for he wasn't easy on himself. Each morning he was in the lab by 4:30, recording weather readings. He did it by hand because he felt that by using a computer he might overlook data trends. Computers cut serendipitous experience, he'd say.</p>
        <p>He wasn't for small talk. At 5 A.M. one black morning a reporter trying to keep up casually asked when Lake Mohonk freezes. ''Dec. 20, on the average,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Though in science he swore by serendipity, his personal life was all organization. A Quaker, he did not drink or smoke. The resort's old-fashioned charm reflects Mr. Smiley's values. No televisions in the rooms, no air-conditioning; lots of paths for hiking and lakes for swimming. In 1963 the family set aside 6,000 acres as a forever-wild sanctuary.</p>
        <p>When the resort board outvoted him in 1971 and decided to get a liquor license, Mr. Smiley retired, concentrating on research.</p>
        <p>Before he was done he compiled 225 research reports. The data base he established attracts scientists from all over. One is studying the decline of pink lady slippers, another is tracing rainfall's path to springs.</p>
        <p>Friday, while on their walk, a rain fell. It was 2:07; Miss Forster made a note.</p>
        <p>Though his cancer was painful, he kept working. In March he published a guided tour of Mohonk. Ten days before his death he asked a daughter, Pril, for a recorder with bigger buttons so he could continue an oral history.</p>
        <p>He was cremated two weeks ago, his remains buried in a biodegradable cardboard box. Though he was the biggest employer around, he was buried simply in the ''S'' section of New Paltz Rural Cemetery.</p>
        <p>''We should get back,'' said Miss Forster. Already hundreds from all over were arriving at the Mountain House parlor.</p>
        <p>After the service, Miss Forster, in high heels, took the afternoon lake samples, Mr. Huth the weather readings. The lake was 73 degrees; the pH 6.65, the air 75. His work continues, but still, the woods will miss Dan Smiley.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
