<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bless You, Marty</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="210756"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NINETEEN HUNDRED EIGHTY-EIGHT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">VOLK, PATRICIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DF123AF932A35752C0A96F948260" item-length="1380" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bless You, Marty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Patricia Volk; Patricia Volk is a novelist and short-story writer who lives in New York.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VOLK, PATRICIA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: O.K., SO 1988 WASN'T PERFECT. We had a drought, a flood, a record-breaking heat wave. A hurricane, a forest fire and, in Bloomsburg, Pa., a roller coaster stalled midloop, suspending 20 riders upside down for more than an hour. Planes fell apart, people ate flowers, grilled tuna meat half raw. A large hole spread in the ozone layer, nightmares washed up on beaches and voracious pear thrips ate Vermont's sugar maples.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: O.K., SO 1988 WASN'T PERFECT. We had a drought, a flood, a record-breaking heat wave. A hurricane, a forest fire and, in Bloomsburg, Pa., a roller coaster stalled midloop, suspending 20 riders upside down for more than an hour. Planes fell apart, people ate flowers, grilled tuna meat half raw. A large hole spread in the ozone layer, nightmares washed up on beaches and voracious pear thrips ate Vermont's sugar maples.</p>
        <p>O.K., SO 1988 WASN'T PERFECT. We had a drought, a flood, a record-breaking heat wave. A hurricane, a forest fire and, in Bloomsburg, Pa., a roller coaster stalled midloop, suspending 20 riders upside down for more than an hour. Planes fell apart, people ate flowers, grilled tuna meat half raw. A large hole spread in the ozone layer, nightmares washed up on beaches and voracious pear thrips ate Vermont's sugar maples.</p>
        <p>On a personal level, a bike messenger rode over my foot and my briefcase was stolen. But, hey, 1988 wasn't all bad. In fact, it had its high points. You just have to know where to look for them.</p>
        <p>First of all, I'm grateful I don't look like Cher. It's not easy looking younger today than you did 20 years ago. It's not easy looking younger than the man you live with who's 20 years younger than you are, either. It takes $45,000 worth of making big things smaller and small things bigger. Plus three hours a day with a merciless personal trainer, and nails made possible by the miracle of plastic.</p>
        <p>Happy New Year, Cher! You're living proof that anything is possible and a reminder of exactly what it takes.</p>
        <p>Yo, Marty! Bless you for giving us another chance. Every two weeks, Marty the seltzer man drops a case of seltzer off at our back door. Marty works hard for a living. A case of seltzer has 10 bottles in it, and those bottles are heavy. I've never actually met Marty. We communicate through notes squeezed between the bottles. But I see Marty as a short man with a cigar clenched between his teeth. He wears gloves with no fingers. He has spindly legs and a superhuman torso.</p>
        <p>I picture Marty, half Schwarzenegger, half 5-year-old, toting heavy wooden crates of seltzer up the back stairs. No wonder he's famous in New York for firing his customers. He lugs that crate up all those stairs without benefit of steroids and when he gets there, sometimes his customers have forgotten to leave their empties out. Then Marty has to lug that full crate down again. That's when he leaves his note. ''I DO NOT TOTE FOR FREE,'' it says in pencil dug so hard into the paper it leaves holes. ''YOU HAVE ONE MORE CHANCE.''</p>
        <p>Almost everyone I know has been fired by Marty. It gets so the moment he delivers your seltzer you start worrying you'll forget to put the empties out. This year, we forgot twice. I begged Marty to keep us on. I told him that orange juice without a spritz was like a day without sunshine. ''Marty,'' I wrote, ''you're not just delivering seltzer, you're delivering a way of life.'' Marty did the unheard of. He gave us another chance. Have a happy, Marty!  If nothing else goes right this year, it's enough to know my right thumb is no longer broken. When it broke, I thought, big deal, so what, I'm a lefty. But then I discovered there was one thing I was dependent on my right thumb for, something I'd never thought about: blowing my nose. I couldn't hold a Kleenex with my left thumb, and so for six weeks last winter I had a problem. Maybe I deserved it, taking my right thumb for granted all these years. Now I look at it with awe and respect and the touch of fear that comes from understanding how quickly one's well-being can be undermined.</p>
        <p>Let's raise a cup of good cheer to the greatest unsung hero of them all! Where would we be without evaporation? It works wonders on the kitchen floor. Can you imagine having to dry the kitchen floor? Evenings, rinsing out things people rinse out in the evening, you can count on those things being dry in the morning, ready to jump into - evaporation's daily gift.</p>
        <p>Here's to evaporation! It regulates the body's thermostat and defogs the bathroom mirror. Best of all, it's environmentally sound and you can't beat the price.</p>
        <p>Lucky me! Donald Trump didn't want to buy anything I own. What would I have done if he'd stopped by and noticed Grandpa Jake's dancing-girl lamp? I love that lamp. If the house was on fire and every warm-blooded thing was safe, that lamp would be the first thing I'd take. That lamp sat on my grandmother's piano, my mother's, now mine. What if Donald came by and said, ''My, what a pretty lamp!''</p>
        <p>''Sorry, Don,'' I'd say. ''It's not for sale. Coffee?''</p>
        <p>''I really like that lamp. Would you take a thousand for it?''</p>
        <p>''Absolutely not,'' I'd say. ''Cream and sugar?'' ''How about ten thousand?'' ''Donald,'' I'd say, ''I don't think you know what that lamp means to me. Let me explain what that lamp means. That lamp has been in our family since my grandfather brought it back from Bohemia on the Lusitania. Four generations of women in my family have had their sheet music illuminated by that lamp. That lamp helped my daughter learn the Minuet in G. That lamp is my heritage. That lamp is who I am. I love that lamp. Sooner or later, Don, you're going to have to learn, there are some things money can't buy.''</p>
        <p>Then he'd offer me a million.</p>
        <p>GUESS WHAT? NO one stole our car radio this year.</p>
        <p>Granted, they would have had to break into our apartment to do it. We take our car radio home with us every night now. That way, even if the car gets stolen again, we'll still have our radio.</p>
        <p>Always I am grateful for the mysteries of life. Like love and the artistic process and why the wrappers from Burger King never fit back into the bag they came in. Where does the black stuff in a kneaded eraser go? Why does hairspray get out ball-point ink? How come leftover birth-control pills, dissolved in water, make African violets grow? And speaking of birth control, I'm grateful to the United Kingdom Medical Research Council. They've announced a new, safe and inexpensive contraceptive for guinea pigs. It's not available to the public yet, so for the time being try keeping them in separate cages.</p>
        <p>Happy holiday, dear butcher! Veal's up to $22.98 a pound; now I don't have to wrestle with my conscience. And isn't it a relief not being Woody Allen? People keep expecting him to be as funny as Woody Allen. I'm also glad Kevin Costner isn't throwing himself at my feet. Though at the moment I forget why.</p>
        <p>And I'm grateful, too, that I live in New York and not New Port Richey, Fla. This year, New Port Richey was invaded by toads. It got so bad people couldn't open their front doors. Toads blocked the doors and the folks who retired to sunny New Port Richey for good times and early-bird specials couldn't go out. It's enough to make you grateful for New York roaches. If you've got to have a pest, at least have one that keeps different hours than you do. I'll take New York roaches anytime. In Madagascar, roaches hiss.</p>
        <p>A word of gratitude now for the gifts 1988 brought that I did not accept. The Armani Classic Robe, my special gift with any purchase of $30 or more. A set of four made-in-Japan mugs from Ralph Lauren, a very special gift with any $19.50 purchase of Polo fragrance. And a $45 anti-stretchmark moisturizer from Prescriptives, mine free with a $35 powder purchase.</p>
        <p>All these wonderful things! If only I was willing to pay for them. But what do I really want? What am I hoping 1989 will bring? Nothing special. Nothing I don't deserve. Clean rivers, clean campaigns. The return of public heroes, apples without daminozide for my kids, and a guarantee they'll have a future. I don't need much. I've got an Interplak. I've got a Cuisinart. I've got a perfume named after an extreme psychiatric disorder.</p>
        <p>Best of all, I have my health. The secret? I sing ''There's No Business Like Show Business'' as loud as I can once a day. I sing it just like Ethel Merman. Norman Cousins made a case for laughing yourself well. If he'd sung ''There's No Business Like Show Business'' every day as loud as he could like Ethel Merman, maybe he wouldn't have gotten sick in the first place. No kidding. This really works. If you're concerned about viruses, try singing it to your computer.</p>
        <p>Last but not least, there's NASA. They've announced plans to fling a spacecraft at Jupiter. Galileo will be a pioneer in distant space. That's the space beyond outer space but closer than remote space. Who knows what they'll find up there. A spare room for guests? Aged Parmesan at an affordable price? A safe dump for sludge? Don't you love suspense?  In any case, have a glorious new year. May 1989 bring you health, bliss and a friend as good as Doris Duke.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
