<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Forest Murder: Ours and Theirs; Brazil's Season of Shame</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="284650"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CATTLE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIVESTOCK</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRAZIL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AMAZON JUNGLE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SARNEY, JOSE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cattle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDF1330F933A1575AC0A96F948260" item-length="468" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Forest Murder: Ours and Theirs; Brazil's Season of Shame</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: This is the time of year when Brazil's farmers torch the Amazon forest, the ancient home of 80,000 different species of plants and 30 million species of animals, many still unknown to science.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: This is the time of year when Brazil's farmers torch the Amazon forest, the ancient home of 80,000 different species of plants and 30 million species of animals, many still unknown to science.</p>
        <p>This is the time of year when Brazil's farmers torch the Amazon forest, the ancient home of 80,000 different species of plants and 30 million species of animals, many still unknown to science.</p>
        <p>Thick clouds of smoke will billow up from the dying forest, drifting for miles over the green canopy. Animals and plants will perish by the millions, as intricate communities that took eons to evolve are destroyed in a day. Moreover, the fires emit huge amounts of carbon dioxide, contributing to the feared warming of the atmosphere known as the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>The horrifying destruction does not even have the excuse of economic necessity. Most of the burning is by ranchers turning the forest to cattle pasture. But cattle rearing in the Amazon is inherently uneconomic. It persists only because of a web of subsidies and tax incentives offered by the Brazilian Government and Sudam, its agency for the development of Amazonia.</p>
        <p>The poor farmers who hope to hack a living out of the forests are invariably disappointed. When stripped of its trees, the land becomes inhospitable; the soil can support no more than a couple of years' crops. Then it turns to mud. Even then, the farmers and ranchers keep on clearing and burning. Forest land is taxed at a lower rate if the trees are cut down. Less than 1 percent of Brazil's forests had been cleared in 1975, but by last year 12 percent was gone. That is not the full extent of Brazil's folly. Instead of turning its natural patrimony into a desolation, it could be harvesting its biological riches at a profit. Only 5 percent of the trees are sold as lumber; the rest are burned or left to rot.</p>
        <p>Sustainable forestry and rubber tapping are only two of the profitable and benign alternatives. One hectare of forest in Peru, for example, has been found to produce fruit worth almost $650 a year and rubber yields of $50, according to Charles Peters of the New York Botanical Garden. That's even more than the $490 that he estimates is the sustainable value of its timber.</p>
        <p>Last year, when satellite photos recorded 170,000 fires in the western Amazon alone, President Jose Sarney called them a ''red light.'' Despite the world's growing horror, Mr. Sarney has done little to halt the annual torching that so besmirches Brazil's reputation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sarney's Government, due to leave office in six months, presides over an irreparable ecological catastrophe, destroying the richest assemblage of plants and animals created in the planet's history. The Government pleads economic necessity; yet its projects are inherently uneconomic. It ignores alternative approaches that would provide income while preserving the forests. It encourages a desolation that will, unless the next government is wiser, become an enduring monument to the limits of human wisdom.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
