<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Proposal For Clean Air Is Dealt a Blow</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="290227"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REILLY, WILLIAM K (ADMR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUNUNU, JOHN H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7DB143EF931A25753C1A96F948260" item-length="871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Proposal For Clean Air Is Dealt a Blow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: After a confused White House lobbying effort, a House subcommittee voted narrowly today to weaken a major section of President Bush's clean air legislation that was intended to increase the use of fuels other than gasoline in motor vehicles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: After a confused White House lobbying effort, a House subcommittee voted narrowly today to weaken a major section of President Bush's clean air legislation that was intended to increase the use of fuels other than gasoline in motor vehicles.</p>
        <p>After a confused White House lobbying effort, a House subcommittee voted narrowly today to weaken a major section of President Bush's clean air legislation that was intended to increase the use of fuels other than gasoline in motor vehicles.</p>
        <p>By a 12-to-10 vote, the House Energy Subcommittee on Health and the Environment amended a provision that would have forced auto makers to produce more cars that burn alternative fuels. The action came after John H. Sununu, the White House chief of staff, and William K. Reilly, Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, sent contradictory messages to the panel.</p>
        <p>As a result, eight of nine Republicans on the subcommittee voted against Mr. Bush's plan, leading to a situation in which Democrats were fighting for the President's bill, against members of his own party. Bill Sent to Full Panel</p>
        <p>Following the vote on alternative fuels, the subcommittee voted 21 to 0 to report the clean air package, including provisions on smog and acid rain, to the full Energy Committee. Consideration by that committee could begin before the end of the month.</p>
        <p>The Democrats vowed to try to restore the Bush proposal in the full committee or on the House floor.</p>
        <p>The Senate's clean air legislation has no alternative fuels provision comparable to Mr. Bush's, but there is discussion about introducing one.</p>
        <p>Democrats on the Energy subcommittee said it was the second time in two weeks that senior members of the Administration were lobbying at cross purposes. Representative Norman F. Lent of Nassau County, who is the ranking Republican on the panel, said Mr. Sununu had told him that Mr. Bush did not oppose the amendment watering down his proposal for increased use of clean-burning fuels like methanol.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Reilly was urging Representative Henry A. Waxman, Democrat of California, to fight the amendment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Waxman said the confusion about the White House position recalled a similar situation last week over efforts in Congress to repeal expanded Medicare coverage for older Americans. While Dr. Louis W. Sullivan, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, was issuing a strong plea for retaining the insurance program, Mr. Bush's budget director, Richard G. Darman, informed a Congressman in writing that Mr. Bush took no position on the issue. Nation's Smoggiest Cities</p>
        <p>The President's bill would require that by 1997 auto makers make and sell in nine of the nation's smoggiest cities a total of one million vehicles a year that would be capable of operating on fuels like methanol, ethanol and natural gas. Under the amendment that passed today auto makers would only have to certify that they could build such cars.</p>
        <p>Democrats said the amendment gutted the Administration proposal and made it harder to reduce air pollution in the nation's most polluted cities. Oil and auto industries had lobbied intensively to weaken Mr. Bush's alternative fuels provision because of the expenses of redesigning cars and starting production of the fuels.</p>
        <p>After the vote, Stephen Hart, a White House spokesman, said that Mr. Bush stood by his alternative fuels program and that if an amendment had to be adopted, ''we want the one closest to the President's position.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hart added that the Administration was proposing changes to restore the mandate to produce cars that run on alternative fuels, but that the changes were not immediately accepted. But Mr. Hart said one of the amendment's sponsors, Representative Jack Fields, Republican of Texas, had told the White House that he would support the changes sought by the White House. Mr. Fields could not be reached tonight for comment. 'Lost in the Translation'</p>
        <p>Asked about Mr. Lent's statement today that Mr. Sununu had said the President did not oppose the amendment, Mr. Hart said, ''Perhaps something got lost in the translation.''</p>
        <p>Despite the Administration's statement backing alternative fuels, the White House apparently did not do much arm-twisting to defeat the amendment, which was offered by Mr. Fields and a fellow Texan, Ralph M. Hall, a Democrat, several people said.</p>
        <p>An Environmental Protection Agency official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said the Republican members broke ranks because the leaders of the full committee, Representative John D. Dingell, Democrat of Michigan, the chairman, and Mr. Lent favored the amendment. He also said that the members felt pressure from the alliance of the auto and oil industries and that they thought the measure ''passed the test of environmental respectability.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall and Mr. Fields said their amendment aimed at ''fuel neutrality.'' They said the President's bill overtly favored methanol, a fuel derived from either natural gas or coal, at the expense of other fuels like gasoline reformulated to burn more cleanly.</p>
        <p>The measure adopted by the subcommittee requires that clean fuel programs meet an emissions reduction standard based on a mixture of 85 percent methanol and 15 percent gasoline. Oil companies say they would be able to meet this standard using reformulated gasoline.</p>
        <p>But environmentalists say the 85 percent standard would not result in cleaner air than with use of conventional gasoline.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
