<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; Behind Surge in the Utility Average</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="306739"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS (CORPORATE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC UTILITIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORRIS, FLOYD</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDD113BF936A35751C1A96F948260" item-length="906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; Behind Surge in the Utility Average</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NORRIS, FLOYD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Laggards for much of the bull market, utility stocks have turned into top performers in the last few months, with their performance accelerating in recent weeks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Laggards for much of the bull market, utility stocks have turned into top performers in the last few months, with their performance accelerating in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>Laggards for much of the bull market, utility stocks have turned into top performers in the last few months, with their performance accelerating in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>As a result, the Dow Jones utility average rose 0.44 yesterday, to a historic high of 228.24, breaking a record set in early 1987. Last week's gain of 2.8 percent for the Dow utilities outstripped all other major averages and was the best for that index in more than a year.</p>
        <p>Since the end of September, the Dow utility average is up 5.6 percent, compared with a 2.3 percent gain for the Dow Jones industrial average. The utilities average is the only leading market indicator to have risen above the 1989 highs set before prices plunged on Oct. 13.</p>
        <p>The surge in utility stocks has been broadly based and in part represents a growing investor consensus that interest rates will fall further, notwithstanding the on-again, off-again status of credit easing that has perplexed watchers of Federal Reserve policy in recent weeks. Many utility stocks are bought for their high dividend yields, which look better when rates are falling.</p>
        <p>''I'm getting calls from money managers who say, 'I haven't owned utilities in years,' '' said Barry Abramson, a utility analyst for Prudential-Bache Securities. The managers are seeking recommendations on which stocks to buy.</p>
        <p>Individual investors are also buying, said Edward J. Tirello, an analyst at Shearson Lehman Hutton. ''We started pressing them heavily in October,'' he said, urging utility stocks as an alternative to certificates of deposit, on which yields are lower than they have been in some time.</p>
        <p>Utilities, principally electric and gas companies serving retail customers, have long been known as defensive stocks that may lag in a bull market but hold up better than others when the economy turns down. Their business tends to be steady, as consumers keep turning on lights even after they are laid off.</p>
        <p>Profits for the electric utility industry will be up 2.5 percent to 3 percent in 1990, Mr. Abramson said. ''When people are looking at a fast-growing economy, those are laughable numbers,'' he added. ''But they don't look so bad now.''</p>
        <p>Many non-utility companies are reporting lower earnings, and the Commerce Department reports that overall corporate earnings from current production dropped in both the second and third quarters of this year. In November, according to the Standard &amp; Poor's Corporation, 21 companies eliminated dividends, the most for any month in more than three years.</p>
        <p>''The stocks are acting better than bonds,'' said Robert Farrell, chief market analyst at Merrill Lynch. ''So there may be something to the idea that there is defensive buying in the stocks now.''</p>
        <p>Much buying seems to be coming from portfolio managers who might be characterized as nervous bulls. With corporate profits slipping, and more and more companies slicing or eliminating their dividends, such a manager is worried about a bear market. But he or she also fears that a decision to sell stocks could look foolish if share prices keep rising. Buying utility stocks can offer an attractive compromise.</p>
        <p>Utility stocks are also benefiting from the fact that the realm of defensive stocks is not so large as it used to be. In recessions, people keep eating just as they keep using electricity, and food stocks used to be defensive standouts. But in the late 1980's, those shares have zoomed in price amid buyouts and takeover speculation.</p>
        <p>There was a mini-takeover boom in the utilities as some tried to grow by acquisition. But the presence of state regulators has helped to hold that down. ''People who buy utilities don't have reason to fear bubbles bursting,'' Mr. Abramson said. ''I've got the only defensive group that is still trading like a defensive group.''</p>
        <p>Utilities have long been known as interest-sensitive stocks as well. Their dividend yields now range from about 5.5 percent to 10 percent, with higher yields generally attached to companies with significant business problems, often involving nuclear plants. In addition, because utilities are big borrowers, they can benefit from lower interest rates on the money they borrow.</p>
        <p>The last time the Dow utilities average hit a record was on Jan. 22, 1987, when it closed at 227.83, just before bond prices began to fall rapidly.</p>
        <p>The best performing of the electric utilities this year have tended to be ones where nuclear worries receded. The two best performers in the Dow average are Centerior Energy, an Ohio company that received an adequate rate increase from regulators and is up 46.3 percent in 1989, and Detroit Edison, which is up 44.6 percent after getting a rate increase and calming investor fears about how well it was operating its Fermi nuclear plant.</p>
        <p>Even without such gains, the average is up nicely. Most stocks are up 15 to 30 percent this year, with Niagara Mohawk Power the only stock in the Dow average to be up less than 10 percent. It is up 8.7 percent despite continued nuclear problems that have forced it to eliminate its common stock dividend.</p>
        <p>Of course, some problems that have bedeviled utility shareowners have not gone away. There are worries that acid rain legislation will add costs to coal-burning utilities and that regulatory changes will make some of them pay extra to transmit power over long distances. But for now, share buyers are focusing on yield, and on relative safety, and utility stocks are hot.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
