<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Still Limping Along</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="248386"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GUN CONTROL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIREARMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WICKER, TOM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DA1F3DF93AA35756C0A96F948260" item-length="739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Still Limping Along</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Tom Wicker</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WICKER, TOM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: When I criticized President-elect Bush for indecision last December (he had ''hit the ground limping,'' I wrote), the remark was labeled a ''cheap shot.'' Now that Mr. Bush actually is having to face Presidential decisions, it looks more and more like an expensive truth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: When I criticized President-elect Bush for indecision last December (he had ''hit the ground limping,'' I wrote), the remark was labeled a ''cheap shot.'' Now that Mr. Bush actually is having to face Presidential decisions, it looks more and more like an expensive truth.</p>
        <p>When I criticized President-elect Bush for indecision last December (he had ''hit the ground limping,'' I wrote), the remark was labeled a ''cheap shot.'' Now that Mr. Bush actually is having to face Presidential decisions, it looks more and more like an expensive truth.</p>
        <p>The latest example, and one of the most serious, is his Administration's hesitance to lead the world against ''global warming'' - although Mr. Bush promised to do so in his campaign, and Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d made it the theme of his first major speech.</p>
        <p>Now the White House chief of staff, John Sununu, is reported to have rebuffed officials who wanted the U.S. to propose an international conference to draft a treaty on global warming. Mr. Sununu replied that Mr. Bush did not yet know enough about the economic costs of a treaty that would limit the man-made gases that trap solar heat and cause the ''greenhouse effect.''</p>
        <p>Then Dr. James E. Hansen, the director of the Goddard Institute for Space Studies, complained that the Office of Management and Budget had watered down his planned Congressional testimony on the subject. He intended to say that enough was known about the causes and effects of global warming that major steps to curb harmful emissions were necessary and practical. When O.M.B. got through censoring the statement, Dr. Hansen was made to claim, contrary to his professional opinion, that ''it remains scientifically unknown'' how much human actions contribute to global warming.</p>
        <p>All this sounds like a retreat into the flaccid inactivity of the Reagan Administration on acid rain, when for eight years it was claimed that not enough was known about its causes to do anything about its effects. The need to get started on global warming, however, is not in doubt. At a recent international forum in Washington, a parade of speakers urged immediate steps to limit emissions of carbon dioxide and other harmful gases.</p>
        <p>Thomas Lovejoy, the vice president of the Smithsonian Institution, who had previously suggested that ''the great environmental struggles will be either won or lost in the 1990's,'' repeated that ''massive intervention in society is required over a very short time, perhaps less than 20 years'' if global warming and ozone depletion are to be dealt with. William D. Ruckelshaus, twice the Republican director of the Environmental Protection Agency, warned that it would be illusory to assume that there would be ''a technological fix,'' and Martin Hodges, a former chief science adviser to the British Government, said that the world ''would be incredibly stupid not to take these dangers as real.''</p>
        <p>Apparently, George Bush doesn't. And saving what's left of the environment is not the only pressing issue he's ducking. Last week he declined to send representatives to a Senate subcommittee that was waiting to hear his proposals on controlling semiautomatic assault rifles. Even a Republican Senator, Arlen Specter of Pennsylvania, was upset.</p>
        <p>''I think the Administration ought to be here,'' he said. ''I say that flatly and I said that to the Administration.''</p>
        <p>Two bills limiting importation, sale, transport and possession of such weapons have been introduced - one by Dennis DeConcini, Democrat of Arizona, usually an opponent of gun controls. He was contemptuous of the Administration's failure to testify, saying ''they don't have a position, that's what it amounts to.'' White House officials conceded that the President hadn't made up his mind on what legislation he wanted, if any.</p>
        <p>Even the biggest Republican enchilada is getting itchy over the Bush Administration's pussyfoot performance. Ronald Reagan took time off from his memoirs last week to let it be known that he was concerned about his successor's ''excessively cautious approach to nuclear arms reductions negotiations with the Soviets,'' among other things.</p>
        <p>This statement was attributed to the ex-President's ''friends'' by Lou Cannon, a Washington Post reporter who has been shrewdly interpreting Ronald Reagan for many years; but Mr. Cannon clearly was using this ancient journalistic device to camouflage an interview with Mr. Reagan himself.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reagan's ''friends'' also allowed that his campaign comment about George Bush last year - ''he's been part of everything we've done for the past eight years'' - now had ''an ironic aftertaste.'' Or maybe that's just what you get when you've put your foot in your mouth.</p>
        <p>IN THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
