<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HOUSE PANEL VOTES STRICT NEW LIMITS ON CAR POLLUTION</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="287948"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON MONOXIDE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WAXMAN, HENRY A (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DINGELL, JOHN D (REPR)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CLEAN AIR ACT</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DA103AF930A35753C1A96F948260" item-length="1310" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HOUSE PANEL VOTES STRICT NEW LIMITS ON CAR POLLUTION</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A House subcommittee voted unanimously today to tighten automobile tailpipe emission controls, establishing national pollution standards as strict as California's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A House subcommittee voted unanimously today to tighten automobile tailpipe emission controls, establishing national pollution standards as strict as California's.</p>
        <p>A House subcommittee voted unanimously today to tighten automobile tailpipe emission controls, establishing national pollution standards as strict as California's.</p>
        <p>The measure, approved 22 to 0, would phase in from 1994 to 1996 an emission control program modeled after the toughest in the nation. The six New England states along with New York and New Jersey agreed this summer to bring their emission laws in line with the California standards. The House move would basically extend those rules to the 41 other states.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists hailed the action, while auto makers, expressing disappointment, said it could hurt fuel economy and increase the cost of vehicles. The Environmental Protection Agency estimated that the new standard would add $100 to the price of a new car in the first phase and $500 when the most stringent standards go into effect. The industry did not offer an estimate. A Political Milestone</p>
        <p>The plan, a compromise between two longtime Democratic adversaries, Representatives Henry A. Waxman of California and John D. Dingell of Michigan, is a political milestone in the long effort by environmentalists and others to strengthen provisions of the Clean Air Act of 1970 aimed at reducing smog.</p>
        <p>The agreement will probably become the position adopted by the House of Representatives. The standards it embraces go beyond those proposed by President Bush in his new clean air bill but are less restrictive than emission measures specified in a bill pending in the Senate.</p>
        <p>A White House spokesman, Stephen Hart, said the Administration thinks that its bill was more ''cost-effective'' than the subcommittee's measure but is ''glad to see the President's package is moving forward.'' The White House is not expected to seek changes in the House bill. Turning Point in Relations</p>
        <p>Members of the House Subcommittee on Health and the Environment today described the agreement as a landmark. It represents a turning point in relations between Mr. Waxman, an advocate of stronger controls to combat the smog that hangs over his hometown of Los Angeles, and Mr. Dingell, whose constituents include Detroit's auto makers.</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for environmental groups, who were generally pleased with the vote, said Mr. Dingell accepted the compromise because he thought it was the best deal he could make for auto makers. There is considerable support among House members for tougher auto emission standards, since motor vehicles are responsible for 50 percent of the nation's smog. 'Momentum Was Building'</p>
        <p>''I think Dingell could see momentum was building and discretion was the better part of valor,'' said A. Blakeman Early, a Washington representative of the Sierra Club, a national environmental group.</p>
        <p>In a news conference after the subcommittee vote, Mr. Dingell described the auto makers' reaction as ''unenthused.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dingell would not directly address why he changed his position on auto emission standards. Calling the measure a ''fair compromise, honorably achieved,'' Mr. Dingell said it would be ''very hard'' on the auto industry but provide a ''stable manufacturing situation.''</p>
        <p>Through the 1980's, Mr. Dingell has frustrated moves by Mr. Waxman, chairman of the subcommittee, to toughen the Clean Air Act, last amended in 1977. Mr. Dingell is chairman of the House Energy and Commerce Committee, where clean air legislation originates. Mr. Dingell said today's agreement probably marked the first time he has sided with Mr. Waxman on motor vehicle pollution controls.</p>
        <p>The two men said subcommittee members had agreed to push for adoption of the auto emissions measure by the full House without amendment. Mr. Waxman said he expected a House-Senate conference committee to consider a revised Clean Air Act within the next six weeks and that Congress could accommodate the President's request for final legislation by Jan. 1.</p>
        <p>The measure adopted today, while stronger than the White House bill, which was co-sponsored by Mr. Dingell, is weaker than the one proposed by Mr. Waxman.</p>
        <p>Under the bill's first stage, California's auto emission control program would be phased in for new cars nationwide from 1994 to 1996. The program requires reductions in emissions of hydrocarbons, oxides of nitrogen and particulates. That timetable is about one year behind the California schedule.</p>
        <p>The measure also requires that pollution control equipment last for 10 years or 100,000 miles, as in California. Under the Clean Air Act, that requirement is 50,000 miles. Compromise on Standards</p>
        <p>Mr. Waxman's original bill called for a second phase to cut emissions even further, beginning in the year 2000. Under the compromise, the Environmental Protection Agency must study the need for tighter standards in the years 2003 to 2006. The agency can retain existing standards or establish new ones. If it does not establish new standards or formally reaffirm existing ones, new and tighter standards go into effect.</p>
        <p>''We're disappointed that they went as far as they did in their proposal,'' said Timothy C. MacCarthy, director of government liaison for the Motor Vehicle Manufacturers Association.</p>
        <p>He said the provisions are more severe than air quality problems would dictate and that they could result in higher automobile costs, loss of fuel economy, a shortage of available models, problems with driving and more recalls. Mr. MacCarthy said the industry could not estimate how much the measures might add to the price of a vehicle.</p>
        <p>''The House compromise on auto pollution control standards is a welcome and constructive step that will greatly improve chances of early enactment of a revitalized Clean Air Act,'' said Richard E. Ayres, chairman of the National Clean Air Coalition, an organization representing environmental and other groups.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ayres added that the agreement had shortcomings because the strictest standards would be delayed 13 years, and may never go into effect if the E.P.A. decides they are unnecessary. He said a program authorized by the bill to control substances like benzene and formaldehyde, which are contained in emissions but do not contribute to smog as such, could also be strengthened.</p>
        <p>The auto industry had suffered two earlier defeats in the subcommittee, which environmentalists suggested may have led Mr. Dingell to move ahead with a compromise on tailpipe emissions.</p>
        <p>In one, the panel voted to require tougher auto pollution standards car by car. The Administration had wanted manufacturers to meet the standards on average, which might have permitted some cars to emit more pollution than they do right now.</p>
        <p>In a vote last week, the subcommittee moved to force auto makers to install special canisters in 1994 models to reduce emissions during refueling.</p>
        <p>Members of the subcommittee also said today they hoped the compromise reached on auto emissions would carry over to other contentious areas the subcommittee has yet to address. These include acid rain, toxic air emissions and alternative fuels.  Stricter Auto Standards  A House subcommittee voted yesterday to apply California auto emission standards, the strictest in the country, to all 50 states.  What would the measure do?  New cars would be required to carry equipment that would sharply reduce three major pollutants: carbon monoxide, hydrocarbons and nitrogen oxide. Pollutionj control equipment would have to be built to last 100,000 miles, twice as long as it must now.  What would it cost?  The Environmental Protection Agency estimates that th emeasure would add $100 to the price of a car during the first phase, and $500 per car when the most stringent limits take effect. Automobile manufacturers say it could reduce fuel economy.  When would it take effect?  The measure would begin to take effect with 1994 models and be fully effective in 1996.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
