<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Innovators and Investors Hindered In the Business of Pollution Control</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="279158"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">POLLACK, ANDREW</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3D9173BF93AA1575BC0A96F948260" item-length="1616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Innovators and Investors Hindered In the Business of Pollution Control</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">POLLACK, ANDREW</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Aug. 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The nation's effort to overcome its pressing environmental problems is being slowed by barriers that discourage technologically innovative companies and the people who invest in them, Government officials, investors and executives at the companies say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The nation's effort to overcome its pressing environmental problems is being slowed by barriers that discourage technologically innovative companies and the people who invest in them, Government officials, investors and executives at the companies say.</p>
        <p>The nation's effort to overcome its pressing environmental problems is being slowed by barriers that discourage technologically innovative companies and the people who invest in them, Government officials, investors and executives at the companies say.</p>
        <p>The barriers arise because polluters see little reason to spend on new and better technology unless the Government makes them do so. While standards have historically become stricter over time, investors are often reluctant to risk money betting on how and when the regulations will change. Moreover, the need to obtain permits from several levels of government greatly slows the introduction of technology.</p>
        <p>These factors could inhibit the kind of successful small businesses that were spawned in electronics and genetic engineering, making the United States the envy of the world in those fields. Inadequate Response</p>
        <p>''We're not getting an adequate technology response to the environmental problems in this country,'' said David R. Berg, an Environmental Protection Agency official who directs a new committee formed by the agency to explore ways to foster innovation.</p>
        <p>Some investors say they have also been put off by a lack of management experience at many new companies and by the fact that the successful environmental companies so far have largely been service companies, not the manufacturing concerns they are more accustomed to.</p>
        <p>Even with these obstacles, venture capitalists, as the investors who previously provided the backing for electronics and genetic engineering companies are called, are nevertheless starting to gamble on fledgling companies developing equipment to clean up the environment.</p>
        <p>''This has all the earmarks of being the next high-growth segment,'' said Nancy E. Pfund, co-manager of a new environmental technology fund established by Hambrecht &amp; Quist, a San Francisco company that has been one of the largest investors in young electronics and biotechnology companies.</p>
        <p>Hambrecht &amp; Quist's $16 million environmental technology fund is only the second venture fund exclusively devoted to this industry. The Environmental Venture Fund, run by the First Analysis Corporation in Chicago, has already invested $12 million of its $37 million in about a dozen companies in the environmental field.</p>
        <p>Other venture companies are investing in environmental companies without setting up special funds. Robertson Stephens &amp; Company, a San Francisco firm, has invested in more new environmental companies recently than in electronics companies.</p>
        <p>One small new company being formed and backed by these investors sells a machine that recovers the sulfuric acid with which semiconductor companies clean chips, reducing the amount of waste that must be disposed of. Another sells a device that uses algae cells to remove toxic metals from water.</p>
        <p>The venture capitalists think that with $85 billion being spent in the United States each year on pollution prevention or cleanup, there are opportunities for successful companies. Moreover, returns are dropping in the more crowded and mature areas like electronics, forcing venture capitalists to seek new pastures.</p>
        <p>But the venture capitalists and executives in the pollution-control industry caution that there might be no fast-growing equivalent of an Apple Computer or a Genentech developing in the environmental business.</p>
        <p>''You just can't go wandering in from the semiconductor business or the pharmaceutical business and think you're going to do the same thing in the environmental area,'' said Russell K. Burbank, president of Siva International, a small recycling firm in South San Francisco.</p>
        <p>Venture investment in pollution control is growing slowly and is still tiny compared with investment in electronics and biotechnology. 'A Lot of Skittishness'</p>
        <p>''There's a lot of skittishness in the venture capital community,'' said Peter C. Wendell, general partner in Sierra Ventures of Menlo Park, Calif., which has made several investments in the industry.</p>
        <p>Both Hambrecht &amp; Quist and First Analysis had more trouble raising money from institutional investors than they had hoped. Venture capitalists also say they have trouble finding investments to make in the industry.</p>
        <p>''I figured with all those billions floating around, there's got to be a ham sandwich in it for me somewhere,'' said Kevin Kinsella of Avalon Ventures in San Diego, who tried for a year to find an investment in the area. ''I've yet to find the ham sandwich.''</p>
        <p>Almost everyone agrees that the biggest obstacle for the new industry is the way the Government sets the environmental standards that created the industry in the first place. Best Available Methods</p>
        <p>Many Federal pollution control laws require polluters to treat wastes using the best available technology or its equivalent. Although the E.P.A. is supposed to upgrade the standards as new technology becomes available, such upgrades are made only sporadically and require a long review process.</p>
        <p>Once a technology is established as a standard, companies have little incentive to try something new.</p>
        <p>''If your product achieves a significant benefit, you don't get paid a superior price,'' said Mr. Burbank of Siva International, who has tried to sell a new technology. ''Nobody's going to spend any more than they have to to meet the standards set by the Government.''</p>
        <p>Permits have also been a problem, especially for incinerators for hazardous waste and other equipment that tends to arouse local opposition. Moreover, a permit obtained for one state or locality might not be valid in another. Running Out of Money</p>
        <p>The Thermolytica Corporation is a case in point. The Richmond, Calif., company, founded in a garage by a scientist from the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, received $4 million in venture financing from Hambrecht &amp; Quist to develop a furnace that breaks down spent solvents into carbon dioxide and water.</p>
        <p>But the company saw that it would run out of money before it could get needed permits, said Mr. Burbank, who was president. Thermolytica merged last month with a company using more conventional technology, forming Siva. By relying on the income from the conventional business, Siva will have more time to get the permits needed for Thermolytica's advanced technology, Mr. Burbank said.</p>
        <p>Some industry officials say Europe has been more receptive to technological innovation than the United States, probably because the population density has made finding new approaches more pressing. ''The European companies actually have more innovative technologies,'' said Robert C. Keefer, editor-in-chief of The Environmental Business Journal in San Diego. Better Markets Overseas</p>
        <p>William Haney, who started a company early in the decade, said he had to go to Europe for financing and a place to test his equipment, which was aimed at reducing hydrocarbon emissions from oil-fired boilers. ''Innovative technologies developed in the United States are first marketed outside the United States,'' Mr. Haney said.</p>
        <p>Such problems have made some venture capitalists, even those willing to invest in the environmental area, shy away from companies with new technologies.</p>
        <p>Summit Partners, a venture firm based in Boston, has instead invested in service companies like Pace Laboratories of Minneapolis, which does chemical analysis of wastes. Sierra Ventures has invested in a temporary-personnel agency serving the industry. Overcoming the Obstacles</p>
        <p>Despite the obstacles, however, many small, innovative companies are being started.</p>
        <p>Alameda Instruments, based in Pleasanton, Calif., has developed the equipment that recovers sulfuric acid used in cleaning semiconductors. The machine, which sells for about half a million dollars, has been sold to several companies, including I.B.M., Hewlett-Packard and Motorola. The company is arranging financing from Hambrecht &amp; Quist.</p>
        <p>Sierra Ventures has backed Bio-Recovery Systems Inc. of Las Cruces, N.M. The company sells the device that uses algae cells immobilized in a column to remove toxic metals from water. Recently, the Manville Corporation bought a 20 percent stake in the company.</p>
        <p>Summit Partners and Robertson Stephens have invested in American Recovery Technology Systems Inc. of Cleveland, which has developed technology for recycling dross, a byproduct of aluminum smelting. Dan Yerushalmi, founder and president, said that the technology results in far less waste going to a landfill and that big aluminum companies are looking at the product. Removing Bottlenecks</p>
        <p>With increased attention being given to innovation, various moves are under way to remove the bottlenecks. The E.P.A. last year established the National Advisory Council for Environmental Technology Transfer, composed of representatives from Government, industry, universities and environmental groups, to make recommendations. The Technology Innovation and Economics Committee, directed by Mr. Berg, is part of that effort.</p>
        <p>E.P.A. also began a program known as Superfund Innovative Technology Evaluation, which allows new technologies to be tested for cleanup of hazardous waste sites. Before that, Mr. Berg said, companies with new technology could not try it out on a cleanup site be cause it had not been approved.</p>
        <p>The University of Pittsburgh and the New Jersey Institute of Technology have both started programs to help nurture new technology, by providing regulatory advice and testing of new cleanup equipment.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. does provide grants for research on pollution control. But Mr. Berg thinks more could be done. He wants the Government to establish its own venture capital fund to help spur innovation in the environmental area.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
