<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Outdoors; New Limit for Striped Bass in Northeast</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="245529"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISHING, SPORT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STRIPED BASS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRYANT, NELSON</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">OUTDOORS (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDE113BF933A05757C0A96F948260" item-length="995" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Outdoors; New Limit for Striped Bass in Northeast</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nelson Bryant</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRYANT, NELSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Striped bass angling has begun in some areas of the Northeast, and fishermen should remember that minimum-length limits for the species have once again inched upward.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Striped bass angling has begun in some areas of the Northeast, and fishermen should remember that minimum-length limits for the species have once again inched upward.</p>
        <p>Striped bass angling has begun in some areas of the Northeast, and fishermen should remember that minimum-length limits for the species have once again inched upward.</p>
        <p>From Massachusetts to New Jersey, the minimum was 33 inches in total length last year, and in most states, the daily limit was one fish. This year the length limit is or will be 36 inches and the bag limits are unchanged.</p>
        <p>In this decade, the production of stripers from the Chesapeake system, which has historically accounted for most of the migratory stocks of the species in the region, has been far below par except for 1982.</p>
        <p>The minimum-length limit is aimed at protecting the females of the '82 class until 95 percent of them have had a chance to spawn at least once. This should have taken place by next spring. A female striper hatched in 1982 would now be about 30 inches long and weigh about 18 pounds.</p>
        <p>These restrictions are consistent with the Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission's management plan for striped bass, which embraces the coastal states from Maine to North Carolina. Commission membership includes state fish and game agencies and the Department of Interior.</p>
        <p>The precipitous decline of stripers of Chesapeake Bay origin began in the 1970s and no one cause has been identified. But pollution, including acid rain, and inorganic contaminants like aluminum, copper, lead, mercury and zinc, are sometimes involved, as are natural factors such as low water temperatures during the spawning periods, or a drop in salinity. Overfishing also plays a role.</p>
        <p>The quest to determine and weigh the causes of the striper's troubles is filled with complexities and contradictions. There is, for example, strong evidence suggesting that the upsurge in Chesapeake Bay populations of the fish in the 1950's was linked to increased amounts of sewage, caused by a rise in human population, going into the bay in the same decade.</p>
        <p>Sewage nurtures various microscopic organisms upon which striped bass larvae feed. The trend toward chemical treating of such effluent, which greatly reduces its nutrient content, may be linked with the striper's decline in some areas. On the other hand, overenrichment from this source can reduce the dissolved oxygen content of the water, particularly in midsummer, and produce conditions that are lethal to fish.</p>
        <p>Those entrusted with the striper's well-being took the one main course available to them: severe reduction of harvest by sport and commercial fishermen. There is also a state and Federal stocking program for striped bass in Chesapeake Bay.</p>
        <p>New York sets a season for stripers. The season opens May 8 and from that day through May 23 the limit is one fish daily, 33 or more inches long. On May 24, the minimum will be 36 inches.</p>
        <p>Stripers that spawn in New York's Hudson River are thriving. On the Hudson between the George Washington Bridge and the Troy Dam, the season opened March 16 and the one fish a day allowed an angler must be 18 inches or longer.</p>
        <p>New Jersey's striper regulations are established by the State Legislature. This year's regulations will probably become law in a few weeks. They call for a 34-inch minimum until July 1, when it will become 36 inches.</p>
        <p>Last year, the state had a five-fish possession limit, and the same will probably apply this year.</p>
        <p>Rhode Island and Connecticut have set the minimum at 36 inches; the limit is one fish a day. Connecticut has long banned the sales of stripers taken from its waters. It also restricts the importation and sale of stripers smaller than the state's minimum length for the species. The only exception to this - and tagging and documentation is required - is that smaller, farm-raised hybrid stripers may be sold.</p>
        <p>Massachusetts' one-fish, 36-inch minimum length limit went into effect April 15. Massachusetts, which is the northernmost of the Atlantic Coast states in which large numbers of striped bass are caught, also has a substantial rod and reel commercial fishery for the species.</p>
        <p>No nets are allowed. A $10 permit allows an angler to catch all legal-size stripers he wishes from the June through September commercial season for the species.</p>
        <p>In 1988, 103,000 pounds of bass (4,384 fish) were taken in this endeavor. Of the 1,418 permit holders last year, 405 reported catching stripers. Sport fishing interests have reacted against the commercial season and have petitioned the state's Marine Fisheries Advisory Commission to ban the sale of bass. Public hearings on the petition are under way.</p>
        <p>According to Randy Fairbanks of the state's marine fisheries division, no commercial striper permits for 1989 will be issued until the commission makes a ruling on the matter.</p>
        <p>New York shut down its commercial fishery - both net and rod and reel - for stripers in May 1986 and included recreational anglers as well.</p>
        <p>This was caused by the discovery of too-high concentrations of polychlorinated biphenyls (PCB's), which are known carcinogens, in stripers of Hudson origin. The sport fishing ban was lifted the next year. The state is now involved in a study to determine whether limited commercial fishing for the species might be allowed.</p>
        <p>In general, the older the bass the more PCB's it accumulates. As an example, stripers up to 28 inches long taken one fall off eastern Long Island averaged well below two parts per million of PCB's, the maximum level allowed by the Food and Drug Administration in fish and fish products. It might be possible to confine such an endeavor to smaller fish in areas where most of the stripers present are of Hudson River origin.</p>
        <p>Establishing the origin of bass taken in the state's waters at various times of year and in various locations is essential to consideration of this plan by the Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission.</p>
        <p>The stock-discrimination technique being used by the state involves analysis - with sophisticated optical equipment linked with a computer -of the shape of striped bass scale samples.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
