<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush 'Environmentalists' - Who's Watt, and Why</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="245084"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">OAKES, JOHN B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DA123AF93AA15757C0A96F948260" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush 'Environmentalists' - Who's Watt, and Why</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John B. Oakes; John B. Oakes is former Editorial Page Editor of The New York Times.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">OAKES, JOHN B</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: If President Bush believes that all he had to do to prove himself an ''environmentalist'' was to name William K. Reilly head of the Environmental Protection Administration, he is dead wrong.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: If President Bush believes that all he had to do to prove himself an ''environmentalist'' was to name William K. Reilly head of the Environmental Protection Administration, he is dead wrong.</p>
        <p>If President Bush believes that all he had to do to prove himself an ''environmentalist'' was to name William K. Reilly head of the Environmental Protection Administration, he is dead wrong.</p>
        <p>The President's muted reaction to the Alaska oil spill is strong evidence that he fails to understand what environmental leadership is all about. Even stronger evidence comes from the caliber of his top-level environmental appointees - E.P.A. alone excepted.</p>
        <p>The appointment of Manuel Lujan Jr., an amiable New Mexico politician, to head the Interior Department was bad enough. But what is one to make of the decision to give James F. Cason, a clone of Ronald Reagan's first Interior Secretary, the savagely anti-environmental James G. Watt, controlling power over the Forest Service?</p>
        <p>Or of the equally disturbing appointment of James Ridenour, described by informed Indiana environmentalists as Mr. Watt's ''ideological soul mate,'' to be director of the National Park Service?</p>
        <p>Or of the nomination of Delos Cy Jamison, at one time an aide to Mr. Watt and more recently to a virulently anti-conservationist Montana Congressman, to head the Bureau of Land Management? That is the agency responsible for the use (and misuse) of some 300 million acres of public lands.</p>
        <p>Or of the proposed nomination of Constance Harriman, a lawyer in the Interior Department with minimal environmental but strong political qualifications, to the crucial post of assistant secretary in charge of fish, wildlife and parks?</p>
        <p>Or of the failure to revive the moribund Council on Environmental Quality, the Congressionally mandated long-range advisor to the White House on environmental affairs?</p>
        <p>As a high official of the Reagan Interior Department, Mr. Cason has promoted Federal giveaways of shale-oil claims (some have been sold to claimants for $2.50 an acre and immediately resold to speculators for $2,000). He has undercut regulations against strip mining. He has pushed for oil and gas leasing in the very national forests that, as Assistant Secretary of Agriculture, he is supposed to protect.</p>
        <p>The Forest Service is under tremendous political pressure to continue the subsidized devastation of the nation's most valuable timberlands - for benefit of a few American lumber companies and many Japanese consumers. Mr. Cason's appointment can only add to that pressure.</p>
        <p>His record is so bad that leaders of 10 national environmental organizations have written President Bush that ''given Mr. Cason's proven record of antagonism toward the environment and his extreme bias in favor of those who financially benefit from the exploitation of the nation's public land resources, he is unsuited for the position to which he has been nominated.''</p>
        <p>Of similar stripe is Mr. Ridenour, new director of the National Park Service, who was finance chairman for one of Vice President Quayle's earlier campaigns and later director of Indiana's Department of Natural Resources.</p>
        <p>As such, Mr. Ridenour consistently favored commercial development over environmental protection. In one suit involving destruction of a historic site, an Indiana court held he had acted ''not solely for public purposes and in good faith but instead in bad faith and for the benefit of private persons and entities.'' He was sworn in last week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jamison has been the cattlemen's, oil men's, lumber men's and miners' best friend as a staff aide on the House Interior Committee. If he is confirmed as director of the Bureau of Land Management, the erosion, pollution and deforestation of America's already gravely mutilated and overgrazed public lands will certainly continue with enthusiastic support from the top.</p>
        <p>What these various appointments say is that while President Bush may talk a good line - on the destruction of Brazilian rain forests, for example, or control of global warming - when it comes to the crucial domestic environmental issues with political overtones, he folds up and silently steals away.</p>
        <p>That isn't good environmental leadership. It isn't good economics. It isn't even good politics.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
