<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEW FEDERAL LAWS TAKE EFFECT TODAY</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="210673"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFDB1539F932A35752C0A96F948260" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEW FEDERAL LAWS TAKE EFFECT TODAY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Dozens of changes in Federal laws and regulations go into effect Sunday, including a vast expansion of Medicare to cover financially devastating illnesses, faster pension fund vesting that will benefit millions and tax changes reducing the Government's subsidy of purchases on credit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Dozens of changes in Federal laws and regulations go into effect Sunday, including a vast expansion of Medicare to cover financially devastating illnesses, faster pension fund vesting that will benefit millions and tax changes reducing the Government's subsidy of purchases on credit.</p>
        <p>Dozens of changes in Federal laws and regulations go into effect Sunday, including a vast expansion of Medicare to cover financially devastating illnesses, faster pension fund vesting that will benefit millions and tax changes reducing the Government's subsidy of purchases on credit.</p>
        <p>Other changes scheduled to take effect early in 1989 would require employers to give 60 days' notice of plant closings and large layoffs and would prohibit landlords from discriminating against the handicapped and families with children.</p>
        <p>A few changes may not have an immediate direct effect on Americans but will eventually be felt. Environmental Changes</p>
        <p>For example, the Environmental Protection Agency's regulations to carry out a 46-nation environmental treaty aimed at halting the depletion of the ozone layer take effect Jan. 1. But chemical companies will not be required to act until July. At that time, the companies will have to cut back their production of chlorofluorocarbons by an estimated 20 percent to 1986 levels. The ozone layer protects the earth from ultraviolet rays.</p>
        <p>As a result of the regulations, consumers may notice fewer plastic food containers from fast-food outlets, thicker insulating panels and possibly slightly harder seat cushions.</p>
        <p>The biggest of the immediate changes on Jan. 1 is the expansion of Medicare coverage for 32 million Medicare beneficiaries to include catastrophic costs of health care.</p>
        <p>Prior to passage of the measure last summer by Congress, in the first major expansion of Medicare in 22 years, the program paid full hospital bills for no more than 59 days a year.</p>
        <p>With the changes going into effect Sunday, Medicare recipients will still have to pay the first-day deductible of $560. But that charge will be assessed no more than once a year no matter how many times the patient is hospitalized. The other 364 days are fully paid. Higher Medicare Premiums</p>
        <p>Medicare recipients will pay for the new benefits through an increase in the premium, which is deducted from their monthly Social Security checks. The extra cost will be $4 a month immediately, and it will climb to $10.20 a month in 1993.</p>
        <p>About 40 percent of the elderly, those who pay Federal income tax, will be charged an additional premium, which is expected to rise from a maximum of 15 percent of regular income tax liability in 1989 to about 28 percent in 1993.</p>
        <p>Many of the changes effective Jan. 1 result from the 1986 Tax Reform Act. The largest new benefit from that law going into effect Sunday is faster vesting in pension plans.</p>
        <p>The maximum waiting period for employees to become fully vested in a pension plan is being cut in half from 10 years to five years.</p>
        <p>But employers can adopt an option that denies full vesting before seven years. To do so, they have to offer 20 percent vesting after three years and an additional 20 percent vesting annually until the seventh year, when it reaches 100 percent. Expansion of Pension Benefits</p>
        <p>The Employee Benefit Research Institute estimates that the pension changes will provide a retirement stake to two million more workers a year.</p>
        <p>''We'll especially see more women being vested than in the past because they tend to be in the workforce or with the same employer for shorter periods,'' said Stephanie Poe, a spokeswoman for the institute.</p>
        <p>The tax law also reduces the percentage of interest payments on credit card charges and automobile and student loans that can be deducted from Federal income taxes, from 40 percent in 1988 to 20 percent in 1989.</p>
        <p>The Government will also be taking more Social Security taxes.</p>
        <p>In 1988, the Social Security tax took $3,380 at most out of employee paychecks. In 1989, the maximum amount of income subject to the tax increases to $48,000 from $45,000, so that the maximum tax will be $3,605. Stricter Airline Inspections</p>
        <p>These are among the other changes taking effect in the new year:</p>
        <p>* Effective Sunday, United States airlines will have to inspect by hand or X-ray all luggage checked aboard flights from Western Europe and the Middle East. The new inspections, prompted by the bombing of a Pan Am jet over Scotland on Dec. 21 and announced by the Federal Aviation Administration on Thursday, are expected to slow passenger check-ins.</p>
        <p>* A 47-year-old ban on homework in five apparel trades is being removed Jan. 8, unless unions that support the prohibitions can get a court to stop the change. Affected are an estimated 50,000 to 75,000 workers in the production of mittens and gloves; embroidery; buttons and buckles; handkerchiefs, as well as some jewelry trades. They will be able to work legally at home for the first time.</p>
        <p>* A law requiring employers to provide 60 days' advance notice of plant closings or layoffs affecting 50 or more people officially takes effect Feb. 4.</p>
        <p>In addition, regulations carrying out a law passed by Congress last summer forbidding landlords from discriminating against the handicapped or families with children take effect March 12. Violators can be fined up to $10,000 for a first offense, $25,000 for a second violation in a five-year period and $50,000 for two or more violations within a seven-year period.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
