<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Washington Talk: The Environment; Clean Air Backers Like Way Wind Is Blowing</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="229412"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOG</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CLEAN AIR COALITION, NATIONAL</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITCHELL, GEORGE J (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">AYRES, RICHARD E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BYRD, ROBERT C (SEN)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CLEAN AIR ACT</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON TALK PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7DE153EF934A35750C0A96F948260" item-length="1189" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Washington Talk: The Environment; Clean Air Backers Like Way Wind Is Blowing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Almost every year for the last eight years legislation to strengthen the Clean Air Act has been introduced in Congress, and each time it died.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Almost every year for the last eight years legislation to strengthen the Clean Air Act has been introduced in Congress, and each time it died.</p>
        <p>Almost every year for the last eight years legislation to strengthen the Clean Air Act has been introduced in Congress, and each time it died.</p>
        <p>Now there is some optimism that the law may be changed by the 101st Congress. There is, it might be said, something in the air this year.</p>
        <p>One thing in the air is more pollution. The Environmental Protection Agency recently reported that urban smog last year was the worst on record. And the Clean Air Act has been in place since 1970.</p>
        <p>Richard E. Ayres, chairman of the National Clean Air Coalition of environmental, public health, consumer, labor and church groups, recently told a House committee, ''We believe that the declining air quality of our cities can fairly be characterized as a public health crisis.'' New Year, Same Issues</p>
        <p>The issues in the legislative debate over the Clean Air Act remain essentially unchanged over the years. In addition to dealing with urban smog and the 100 cities across the country that are not cleaning it up, the debate on Capitol Hill will also take in what to do about acid rain in particular and emission of toxic substances in general.</p>
        <p>But this year the lineup of players involved in the legislative contest has been significantly reshuffled. The new heavy hitter favoring tougher air pollution controls is President Bush.</p>
        <p>After an an early attempt to weaken the law's standards on protecting public health, the Reagan Administration basically took no direct role in the Congressional debate over clean air. That absence of executive leadership was often mentioned by members of Congress and environmentalists as a prime reason for the lack of progress toward tighter controls.</p>
        <p>President Bush, however, has pledged support for a stronger law, including action to reduce the pollutants that cause acid rain, industrial emission of sulfur and nitrogen oxides that fall to earth in rain and snow and kill fish and threaten forests. William K. Reilly, an environmentalist Mr. Bush appointed to head the Environmental Protection Agency, is now preparing the Administration's clean air bill. 'Refreshing,' a New Yorker Says</p>
        <p>''For the first time in the history of the acid rain battle in Congress we have in the Oval Office a President who acknowledges the problem exists and has made a commitment to be part of the solution rather than part of the problem,'' said Representative Sherwood Boehlert, a New York Republican who favors strong legislation because acid rain is harming lakes in his Adirondacks district. ''What a refreshing change.'' Some recent changes on Capitol Hill could smooth the way for clean air legislation. Most important, perhaps, was the election of Senator George J. Mitchell, Democrat of Maine, as Senate majority leader, replacing Senator Robert Byrd of West Virginia. As chairman of the Senate Environmental Protection Subcommittee in the 100th Congress, Senator Mitchell fought hard for passage of a tighter clean air bill. Senator Byrd, concerned that a such a bill might cost coal miners their jobs, was an obstacle to Senate legislation for years.</p>
        <p>Year after year, the Senate Environment Committee, with heavy representation from the New England and Mid-Atlantic States, which suffer the worst effects of acid rain, would report out a new clean air bill; year after year, the bill failed to come to a vote on the floor.</p>
        <p>This year, said Senator Max Baucus, Democrat of Montana, the new chairman of the Environmental Protection Subcommittee, an effort would be made to reach out to senators from all parts of the country to try to work out a bill that would be widely acceptable. New Mood of Compromise</p>
        <p>''Things are clearly different this year,'' said Senator Baucus. ''We have a new President who wants an acid rain bill. We have a new majority leader and a new mood to compromise on the bill. The states are less polarized this year than they were before. I just think that all the factors you look at tend to point overwhelmingly to passage of the bill.''</p>
        <p>In the past the legislative politics affecting the clean air bill in the House was almost the opposite of what obtained in the Senate. There was a good chance that the House would vote a stronger law, but the House Energy and and Commerce Committee could not agree on a bill to send to the floor.</p>
        <p>Representative Henry A. Waxman, Democrat of California, chairman of the Health and Environment Subcommittee, tried again and again to draft legislation that would require much stronger controls on acid rain and urban smog. But Representative John D. Dingell, Democrat of Michigan, chairman of the full committee, sought legislation that he believed would not compromise the competitive position of Detroit's automobile industry.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Waxman has recently expressed optimism that a strong clean air bill will pass this year. In part this optimism is based on the fact that the House Speaker, Jim Wright of Texas, has made clean air a top priority. Industry Hints at Accepting</p>
        <p>While industry usually opposes regulation restricting industrial moves and costing industry money, there is a growing business community trend now to accept a strengthened clean air law. For one thing, it looks like it is going to happen whether they like it or not. ''Industry sees that the ship is leaving the dock this year and they want to be on it,'' said a Congressional aide.</p>
        <p>S. William Becker, executive director of the State and Territorial Air Pollution Administrators, said that the states were coming up with their own programs like limiting emissions from car exhausts and requiring vapor controls on gas pumps. Industry, he said, is more inclined to compromise ''because the alternative in this debate is not to escape regulation but to be regulated 50 different ways by state governments.''</p>
        <p>He also said the agreement between the Governors of New York and Ohio last year on acid rain legislation showed that the issue was no longer polarizing the states. Pressure on Economy</p>
        <p>William D. Fay, director of the Clean Air Working Group, an industry coalition formed to influence the legislative debate, said that business would welcome a strengthened law if ''it doesn't place undue pressure on the economy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fay also said he hoped industry would be represented in the debate and that whatever legislation was acted on would not be written by the National Clean Air Coalition. He said that unless the environmentalists abandoned their ''stridency,'' progress was unlikely.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ayres of the Clean Air Coalition said that the environmental groups were willing to work with industry for an acceptable bill. But he added that any adequate bill would have to reduce sulfur emissions by 10 to 12 million tons over 10 years, reduce pollution from automobiles and trucks and sharply cut toxic substances that businesses pour into the air. He said he expected the automobile and electric utility industries to present the chief obstacles.</p>
        <p>''If we go at the problem with a positive attitude it is possible to come up with a solution that can reduce pollution without adversely affecting any part of the country,'' Mr. Ayres said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
