<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ozone Losses Are Reported Wider Than Thought</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="301383"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATURE (JOURNAL)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D61138F935A25752C1A96F948260" item-length="668" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ozone Losses Are Reported Wider Than Thought</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Chemically induced losses of protective ozone in the stratosphere over Antarctica cover a wider area than had been thought, scientists are reporting today in the British journal Nature.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Chemically induced losses of protective ozone in the stratosphere over Antarctica cover a wider area than had been thought, scientists are reporting today in the British journal Nature.</p>
        <p>Chemically induced losses of protective ozone in the stratosphere over Antarctica cover a wider area than had been thought, scientists are reporting today in the British journal Nature.</p>
        <p>The region of ozone loss, reaching almost to Cape Horn at the southern tip of South America, extended nearly 350 miles beyond the well-known ''ozone hole'' that covers Antarctica, the scientists said, basing their findings on an analysis of measurements made in 1987. The ozone-depleted area is not expected to widen farther or to threaten populated areas, nor is the loss of ozone as great outside the vortex of winds that form the ozone hole itself.</p>
        <p>The discovery nevertheless surprised atmospheric scientists, who say that it raises many questions about the chemical mechanisms of ozone loss and underscores how much remains unknown about the atmospheric processes that govern the phenomenon. Ozone Depleted Air Transported</p>
        <p>Other investigators have found that air partly depleted of ozone has been transported from the ozone hole, after it breaks up in late spring, to New Zealand and southern Australia by currents in the upper atmosphere. How much this dilutes the ozone layer globally, if at all, is an open question. Scientists say that ozone is constantly being produced and destroyed naturally.</p>
        <p>In the study being published today, the ozone loss outside the polar vortex was found to result not from the transport of ozone-poor air from the vortex but from reactions between ozone and other chemicals in the regions beyond Antarctica.</p>
        <p>Scientists say reactions between ozone and chlorofluorocarbons, the industrial chemicals widely used in refrigerants, air conditioners, spray cans and solvents, are responsible for ozone loss over both the North Pole and the South Pole. There, in winter and spring, lower temperatures in the stratosphere cause ice crystals to form that catalyze the chemical reactions. Over the South Pole, the most serious ozone depletion is contained within the ''hole'' formed by a towering vortex of winds. After the vortex breaks up with the onset of warmer weather, scientists say, the ozone level recovers.</p>
        <p>Ozone in the stratosphere protects life forms from harm caused by ultraviolet rays from the sun. Ultraviolet radiation can cause skin cancer and eye cataracts in humans. Under an international agreement signed in Montreal in 1987, the emission of chlorofluorocarbons is to be reduced by 50 percent in the next decade by industrialized countries, and over a longer period by developing nations. Fifty countries have joined the agreement or are planning to join. Whether the ozone loss outside the Antarctic hole is caused by chlorofluorocarbons is uncertain, but the scientists who discovered it say this is possible. ''That's what most people would look for first,'' said M. H. Proffitt, an atmospheric scientist with the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Aeronomy Laboratory at Boulder, Colo., and the University of Colorado. Dr. Proffitt headed a research team that also included D. W. Fahey, K. K. Kelly and A. F. Tuck, all of the aeronomy laboratory. 'Rather Provocative'</p>
        <p>While calling the latest findings ''rather provocative,'' Guy P. Brasseur, an atmospheric scientist at the National Center for Atmospheric Research in Boulder, wrote in a commentary in Nature that they do not show unambiguously that the ozone loss outside the polar vortex is chemically caused. But he said that alternative explanations could be readily discounted and that a chemical process thus seemed to affect ozone outside the vortex.</p>
        <p>The study was conducted in August 1987. Flying through the stratosphere, the researchers measured ozone levels in slices of air reaching from the southern tip of South America well into the polar vortex.</p>
        <p>They found that the loss of ozone began about 550 kilometers, or 342 miles, outside the boundary of the polar vortex, which encompasses most of Antarctica. From the boundary on to the South Pole, it is about 1,700 miles.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
