<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Methane From Guts of Livestock Is New Focus in Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="303058"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIVESTOCK</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHANE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D8163FF932A15752C1A96F948260" item-length="1290" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Methane From Guts of Livestock Is New Focus in Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: CARBON dioxide, the heat-trapping gas whose concentration in the atmosphere is rising steadily as humans burn more and more coal and oil, has lately captured the attention of a world that is confronting the question of global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: CARBON dioxide, the heat-trapping gas whose concentration in the atmosphere is rising steadily as humans burn more and more coal and oil, has lately captured the attention of a world that is confronting the question of global warming.</p>
        <p>CARBON dioxide, the heat-trapping gas whose concentration in the atmosphere is rising steadily as humans burn more and more coal and oil, has lately captured the attention of a world that is confronting the question of global warming.</p>
        <p>But another gas that contributes to this ''greenhouse effect'' and is 20 to 30 times more potent in trapping heatclose to the earth, has been largely overlooked. It is methane, perhaps best known as the major constituent of natural gas.</p>
        <p>Methane also arises from rice paddies, forest fires, termites that flourish in deforested areas, coal mines, landfills and from the digestive tracts of animals, including the estimated 3.3 billion domesticated cattle, sheep, goats, buffalo and camels that have proliferated around the world as human societies have expanded.</p>
        <p>Scientists say that because of human activity, methane in the atmosphere has doubled in the last 300 years, from 650 parts per billion by volume to 1,700; that it is increasing at a high rate of 1 percent a year, and that in its present concentration relative to carbon dioxide, it would be responsible for 20 to 25 percent of whatever global warming results from greenhouse gases that are caused by human activity. Carbon dioxide would be responsible for 50 to 55 percent.</p>
        <p>Another 20 to 25 percent is blamed on chlorofluorocarbons. These gases widely used in refrigerants, air conditioners, spray cans and solvents, have been the object of intense international scrutiny because they also deplete the earth's protective ozone layer. Fifty nations have agreed to reduce chlorofluorocarbon emissions. Report Cites Livestock</p>
        <p>Now methane is also beginning to attract attention in the discourse over global warming, including the publication today of a report by the Environmental Protection Agency on the prospects of reducing methane emissions, in particular those from livestock.</p>
        <p>Of all the major greenhouse gas emissions, the report says, methane in one respect might be the easiest to control. Its lifetime in the atmosphere, at about 10 years, is relatively short, and less reduction of it is therefore required to either stabilize or cut overall levels in the atmosphere. Scientists estimate that it would require a reduction of 50 to 80 percent to stabilize carbon dioxide levels, and almost a 100 percent cut to stabilize chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>By contrast, the E.P.A. report says, a cut in emissions of 10 to 20 percent would halt the increase of methane in the atmosphere. Reducing emissions from one or two sources would not be sufficient to halt it, the study concluded. Instead, small reductions in each of the major sources will likely be preferred, the report says.</p>
        <p>But the study also found that if methane emissions from ruminant animals like cattle, sheep, goats, buffalo and camels were reduced by 50 percent, this would accomplish 50 to 75 percent of the reduction needed to halt the growth in methane.</p>
        <p>It concluded that this goal can be achieved through a number of techniques, including, for instance, improved feed and nutrition. This would reduce emissions from ruminant, or cud-chewing, animals in the third world that eat vegetation low in nutrition but high in fiber and methane production. Dietary additives could also reduce methane, the report said, and the use of hormones, along with improved nutrition, could increase the animals' productivity. This would allow a reduction in the number of animals per farm. Economic Gains Are Seen</p>
        <p>''Methane from livestock can probably be controlled or reduced in the developing nations, often by a significant amount, and in developed nations by still a reasonable amount,'' said John S. Hoffman, the director of the E.P.A.'s global change division, who was an author of the report. The other authors were Michael J. Gibbs and Lisa Lewis of ICF Consulting Associates Inc., an environmental consulting concern in Washington.</p>
        <p>Since the reductions in methane from livestock would be accompanied by an increase in productivity of milk-producing and meat-producing animals, Mr. Hoffman said, there would be economic benefits as well. The agency is also studying methane reductions in coal beds and landfills, and Mr. Hoffman said these studies ''will also be showing that signficant reductions can be made, often at a profit; this creates a very economic picture for methane'' as an avenue for greenhouse gas reduction.</p>
        <p>Not everyone familiar with the situation is as confident about the possibility of reducing methane emissions. ''I'm skeptical,'' said Ralph Cicerone, the head of geosciences at the University of California at Irvine, who has studied the methane problem extensively. ''It's not clear that we can slow down the sources of methane as easily as they think'' with ''a technological fix of zapping a cow with antibodies, enzymes or whatever,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffman acknowledged that ''we need to validate all this with field experiments, which we're in the process of doing.'' Livestock Gas: 15 Percent</p>
        <p>All in all, Dr. Cicerone said, scientists estimate that between 425 million and 675 million tons of methane a year are emitted. ''It took years to come up with that number,'' he said. Human-induced sources of methane, the E.P.A. report says, account for an estimated 60 percent of the total. The remaining 40 percent comes from natural sources like swamps, marshes, lakes and oceans.</p>
        <p>Livestock contributes about 15 percent of atmospheric methane, according to scientists' best estimates. Rice paddies are estimated to account for 20 percent; coal mining, 6 percent; oil and natural gas systems, 8 percent; landfills, 7 percent, and animal waste, 3 percent.</p>
        <p>Despite these estimates, scientists remain uncertain of the relative importance of the various sources of increasing methane emissions. This, apparently, is one reason there has been a reluctance to focus on the issue or to encourage specific solutions. ''A number of us around the world are trying to solve this puzzle of why methane is increasing so fast in the atmosphere,'' said Dr. Cicerone. But he termed evidence of the rapid increase compelling.</p>
        <p>Atmospheric levels of methane are reflected and preserved in samples of glacial ice dating back at least 150,000 years, or two ice ages ago.</p>
        <p>These samples, Dr. Cicerone said, show that over that period the concentration ranged between natural limits of one-third to two-thirds of a part per million. The level began to exceed those natural limits after about 1850, rising to 1.1 parts per million in 1951 and 1.7 parts per million today.</p>
        <p>A major uncertainty for the future, scientists say, involves methane locked in frozen tundra and in permafrost in the sediments at the bottom of arctic seas. Significant global warming, they fear, might cause the permafrost to melt and the tundra to thaw, releasing vast new amounts of methane that would further promote atmospheric warming.</p>
        <p>''We agree completely with the scientists who say there's a tremendous amount of uncertainty about the sources and atmospheric chemistry of methane,'' said Mr. Hoffman. ''We're also saying that we think the imbalance is small'' between methane emissions and methane destruction by natural causes in the atmosphere, meaning that it should be easier to halt the rise in atmospheric methane. The latest E.P.A. study on livestock, he said, ''suggests that there are going to be some very good options out there'' for reducing emissions.</p>
        <p>Despite his reservations on specific solutions and despite all the uncertainties, Dr. Cicerone said livestock are clearly a large part of the problem. ''When you look at the cattle source, it's got to be 80 or 100 million tons a year,'' he said. ''Then you know cattle are a big part of the answer.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
