<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PRESIDENT'S PLAN FOR CLEANING AIR GOES TO CONGRESS</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="268125"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CLEAN AIR ACT OF 1970</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6DD133FF931A15754C0A96F948260" item-length="954" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PRESIDENT'S PLAN FOR CLEANING AIR GOES TO CONGRESS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF; Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush sent his air pollution legislation to Congress today, saying the bill would ''see to it that every American in every city in America will breathe clean air.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush sent his air pollution legislation to Congress today, saying the bill would ''see to it that every American in every city in America will breathe clean air.''</p>
        <p>President Bush sent his air pollution legislation to Congress today, saying the bill would ''see to it that every American in every city in America will breathe clean air.''</p>
        <p>But a number of Congressional Democrats as well as environmentalists said the specific proposals fell far short of the goals of the Clean Air Act of 1970, even short of the promises made by the President in a June 12 speech announcing his plans to strengthen the act.</p>
        <p>On the other side, industry groups complained that some provisions went further than Mr. Bush's speech had suggested and that they could cause problems in the marketplace. Acid Rain to Urban Smog</p>
        <p>The bill, nearly 300 pages long, includes all the elements Mr. Bush addressed in his speech. It calls for reducing pollution that causes acid rain and for new restrictions on pollution from automobiles and other sources of urban smog. It would also require engineering controls to curb emissions of toxic chemicals by industry.</p>
        <p>But critics said the bill had been weakened to reflect the interests of the automobile industry and other business sectors. And even some supporters of the President said there was room for improvement.</p>
        <p>Critics cited several areas where they said the plan fell short of what what was needed to clean the air. For example, the bill calls for a new system of averaging auto pollution for a fleet rather than regulating pollution by vehicles individually. Critics denounced this as a less stringent approach. Officials Say It's Misread</p>
        <p>They also said that the legislation would not meet the acid reduction levels specified by Mr. Bush and that the engineering requirements for controlling toxic chemicals in the air were inadequate to protect public health.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said the critics were misreading the legislation and that the bill would meet Mr. Bush's goal of assuring clean air.</p>
        <p>''This bill is going to achieve the goals of the Clean Air Act,'' said William K. Reilly, Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>People on all sides agreed that Mr. Bush's initiative would break the impasse that has kept Congress from amending the clean air law since 1977. The deadlock developed as states and environmental and public health groups called for toughening the law, while industry warned of harm to the economy, and the Reagan White house showed no interest in pushing the issue.</p>
        <p>''It's time to break the gridlock on this issue,'' Mr. Bush said in a speech in the White House Rose Garden today.</p>
        <p>Several members of Congress said today that there was probably not enough time to complete the legislative process this year. But all agreed that clean air legislation, which has the solid support of Senate and House leaders, would be approved before this Congress ends in 1990. Among major provisions of the legislation are these:  Urban Smog</p>
        <p>New controls would be imposed on motor vehicles, industry and other sources of ozone, hydrocarbons, nitrogen and other gases that react with sunlight to form smog. Smog has been found to cause widespread respiratory illness, to create haze and damage crops.</p>
        <p>The bill would lower maximum permissible levels of pollution from auto tailpipes, require some of the most polluted cities to use cleaner-burning fuels like methanol in some vehicles, and require cities with the most serious pollution to reduce smog-causing emissions by at least 3 percent.</p>
        <p>Critics say specific parts of the plan could weaken current law. In particular, they fault the provision to permit automobile companies to meet Federal standards by measuring average pollution of fleets rather than having each individual car remain below maximum pollution level. They say that this would increase urban smog, and that the bill contains loopholes that would permit cities to evade the requirement of reducing pollution by 3 percent a year.</p>
        <p>But Administration officials said the smog provisions were drafted to give industry and cities the ability to act in the most cost-effective way.  Acid Rain</p>
        <p>The bill calls for a 10-million-ton reduction in sulfur dioxide emissions, the chief pollutant causing acid rain, by 2000. It would allow the buying and selling of permits to pollute in an effort to encourage industry to try to reduce pollution in the most cost-efficient manner. But, in a last minute change, the bill would place a ceiling on the amount of pollution that could be emitted by a single plant or unit of a plant.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said his acid rain provisions were tougher than any legislation introduced so far in Congress, and even environmental groups said they were the strongest part of his legislation.</p>
        <p>The Edison Electric Institute, which represents privately-owned utilities, said the ceiling on individual pollution sources sharply reduced the flexibility industry had expected and might require some plants to curtail the output of electricity or to install expensive equipment to capture smokestack emissions.  Toxic Air Pollution</p>
        <p>The bill would require industry to install ''maximum achievable control technology'' to reduce emission of hazardous chemicals. Many of these chemicals can cause cancer and other serious illness, but virtually none are controlled by the Government.</p>
        <p>Critics said that the proposal did not go far enough and that it allowed technological requirements to be tempered by cost considerations and set no numerical standard for keeping pollutants below levels that threaten health.</p>
        <p>Administration officials insisted that the law would be administered in a way that would assure that citizens were not threatened by such chemicals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's proposal provides for stiff new penalties, including criminal penalties, against violators.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
