<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Diverted Jet Stream Creates Weird Weather Patterns</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="250370"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DROUGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D81E3AF935A25756C0A96F948260" item-length="1631" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Diverted Jet Stream Creates Weird Weather Patterns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: FOR a year, it seems, the weather has gone crazy in America.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: FOR a year, it seems, the weather has gone crazy in America.</p>
        <p>FOR a year, it seems, the weather has gone crazy in America.</p>
        <p>First there was last summer's disastrous three-month drought in the nation's midsection. Then an unusually warm, dry winter in the Northeast began to dry up reservoirs, raising fears that some big cities would run out of water this summer. Last month southern California baked in one of the century's worst heat waves. Then, as the early spring of 1989 turned the corner into May, record cold invaded parts of the Southeast and unusually heavy rains wiped out the Northeast's drought threat at a stroke.</p>
        <p>''Weather is always abnormal; that's the name of the game,'' said Jerome Namias, a research meteorologist at the Scripps Institution of Oceanography at La Jolla, Calif., who is a founding father of long-range weather forecasting. ''Every abnormality frequently gives rise to another.''</p>
        <p>Even so, the last 12 months have seen an unusual sequence of weather events, brought on by out-of-the-ordinary behavior of the grand global forces that determine climate.</p>
        <p>Now, meteorologists say, there are signs that the latest climatic contortions in the United States are signaling readjustment to a less extreme pattern in much of the country. But they say there could be a big exception: global atmospheric forces could conspire once again to bring serious drought to the mid-continental farm belt for the second consecutive summer. Spring is the critical transition season in which the summer's weather patterns take shape, and the midsection's fate should become clearer in the weeks just ahead.</p>
        <p>Neither last year nor this year, most scientists say, can any of this climatic stress be attributed to the greenhouse effect, in which gases such as carbon dioxide combine with water vapor to trap heat inside the earth's atmosphere. Most climatologists believe that this will cause a gradual warming of the earth's surface over the next few decades, probably causing important climatic disruptions.</p>
        <p>A few believe that it is already making extreme weather events such as droughts and severe storms more likely. But most say that the effects of manmade global warming cannot yet be demonstrated. They appear to agree with Dr. Namias when he says, ''I don't think what's going on, by any stretch of the imagination, is caused by the greenhouse effect.''</p>
        <p>Rather, a number of the experts say, the last year's events can be readily explained by natural variations in the workings of the atmosphere, most of which have been observed in the past and will be observed again in the future.</p>
        <p>The earth's atmosphere is a constantly swirling sea of air currents whose flow, temperature, moisture and intensity are governed by an extremely complex interaction between the air and the oceans. Part of this swirl consists of the North American jet stream, a high-altitude river of air that flows generally west-to-east across the continent. Most precipitation occurs near the track of this flow, which also plays a major role in blocking or facilitating the movement of moisture from the sea to the land.</p>
        <p>The jet stream's course is largely determined by the placement of systems of high and low atmospheric pressure, which divert its flow much as big rocks divert the current of a river. The positions of the highs, lows and the jet stream are influenced to a great extent by changing sea-surface temperatures, and their behavior is also affected by such factors as the amount of moisture in soil. An event in one part of the ocean-atmosphere system can affect weather thousands of miles away through what climatologists call ''teleconnections.''</p>
        <p>This swirl of constantly shifting influences and feedbacks is seamless, with no beginning or end, and one can dip into it at any point to try to analyze how weather is shaped. In the United States, one place to begin is 1984, when both the Pacific Northwest and the Southeast endured the first of four consecutive hot, dry, withering years.</p>
        <p>The Northwestern drought was caused by a massive high pressure system, or ''ridge,'' that developed every winter and spring from late 1984 through 1988. This prevented Pacific storms from entering the Northwest, said Art Douglas, a meteorologist who is chairman of the atmospheric sciences department at Creighton University in Omaha.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the spring jet stream from 1984 to 1988 split in two, part of it flowing through Canada and part through Mexico. Normally, this jet stream would flow, without splitting, through the Southeastern United States; its absence deprived the region of precipitation.</p>
        <p>As the spring of 1988 arrived, the two major drought areas had expanded to such a degree that they nearly met in the middle of the country. Soil became increasingly drier. The result, as spring and summer temperatures rose, was that solar radiation, instead of dissipating itself by evaporating water, heated the soil and the air above it. At the same time, the Northwestern high pressure system moved slowly into the Plains. This combination of factors created a very large, hot system over the midsection. Shift in Jet Stream</p>
        <p>The jet stream shifted far to the north around this large ridge of hot, high-pressure air. It was pushed there partly, climatologists believe, by complicated interactions between a large pool of unusually cold water along the Equator, ''La Nina,'' and unusually warm water in the east-central Pacific. With the jet stream far to the north, the Plains got very little rainfall.</p>
        <p>This system was locked into place from late April 1988 until almost August largely by two large high-pressure ridges, one in the Atlantic and one in the Pacific.</p>
        <p>But inevitably conditions change with the seasons. Last winter's weather pattern, said Dr. Douglas, was partly dominated by a huge low-pressure trough angling from the northwestern United States into northeastern Canada. Strong westerly winds associated with this trough blocked both moist air from the Gulf of Mexico and Arctic air from Canada from flowing into the Northeastern United States, producing the region's mild, dry winter.</p>
        <p>With the advent of the spring of 1989, an entirely different constellation of forces came into play. The major factor, perhaps, has so far been a huge peanut-shaped ridge of high pressure over the Western part of the country, with two big centers, one over Alaska and one over Arizona. It was responsible for this spring's heat and dryness in southern California and Arizona. The jet stream, punching through the weak middle of the peanut-shaped ridge, has brought rainfall to the parched Pacific Northwest.</p>
        <p>The big high-pressure ridge was also responsible for diverting the jet stream to an almost north-south course through the Plains States during April and early May. This had two effects: it kept moist air from the Gulf of Mexico from pushing into the Plains states, thereby intensifying persistent dry conditions in parts of the midsection and possibly setting the stage for another important summer drought. It also sent Arctic air sluicing down into parts of the Southeast, creating unusually frigid temperatures there early this month.</p>
        <p>The jet stream during this period dipped down nearly to the Gulf of Mexico before turning northeastward. Carrying Gulf moisture with it, it converged with a big low-pressure system in the Northeast to give the region its heavy May rains. Difference in Weather Patterns</p>
        <p>The key difference between this year and last year, so far, is that no large persistent high-pressure system appears locked into place over the middle of the country, said A. James Wagner, a meteorologist in the predictions branch of the National Weather Service's Climate Analysis Center. This time of year ''is normally a period in which climate anomalies do not persist,'' he said. ''They occur, but they don't stick around for two or three months without a break.''</p>
        <p>But there are again two high-pressure systems in the Pacific and the Atlantic, Dr. Douglas pointed out, and they could lock the present pattern into place. If they do, some of the midsection could be in for another long summer drought. ''There is no doubt the potential is there,'' he said. ''The bottom line is that we've gone into a new circulation pattern that can also favor drought.'' Similar patterns in the 1930's and 1950's did in fact lead to mid-continent droughts, he said.</p>
        <p>The Weather Service's long-range forecast for the critical May-through-July period says there is a 55 to 60 percent chance that temperatures will be above normal in Missouri, Nebraska, Kansas and most of Iowa and Illinois. Forecasts on Rainfall</p>
        <p>The forecast also says there is a 55 percent chance that rainfall will be below normal in most of that region. Rainfall is expected to be normal or above normal in the rest of the country.</p>
        <p>In a shorter-range forecast for mid-May to mid-June, issued Friday, the Climate Analysis Center predicted a dry month for much of the same region, as well as for North Dakota, Minnesota, Wisconsin and western Michigan. ''The pattern that's setting this up, basically, is looking a bit like what we had this time last year,'' Mr. Wagner said. In the last five days, in fact, the ridge of high pressure that dominated the West Coast in the early spring has moved into the midsection. How long it will stay there is uncertain.</p>
        <p>But, said Dr. Namias, ''It's statistically unlikely we would have a drought of the dimensions, extent and intensity of last year, strictly on the basis of past history.'' Nevertheless, he said, there is a tendency not only for dry springs to be followed by hot, dry summers, but also for one dry summer to be followed by another. ''I would not be too surprised if some drought emerged over a part of the Plains,'' he said, ''though I'm not categorically predicting it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
