<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times; Mexico as a Hellish Parody of Civilization</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="275448"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KAKUTANI, MICHIKO</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FUENTES, CARLOS</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CHRISTOPHER UNBORN (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D7173FF936A2575BC0A96F948260" item-length="984" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times; Mexico as a Hellish Parody of Civilization</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KAKUTANI, MICHIKO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  Christopher Unborn  By Carlos Fuentes  Translated by Alfred Mac Adam and the author. 531 pages. Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $22.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  Christopher Unborn  By Carlos Fuentes  Translated by Alfred Mac Adam and the author. 531 pages. Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $22.95.</p>
        <p>Christopher Unborn  By Carlos Fuentes  Translated by Alfred Mac Adam and the author. 531 pages. Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $22.95.</p>
        <p>Three decades ago, in his first novel, ''Where the Air Is Clear,'' Carlos Fuentes created a prismatic picture of Mexico City, and in delineating a gallery of urban characters -including the rich and the poor, workers, aristocrats and intellectuals -he also left us with a vivid portrait of Mexico as a whole, a conflicted, multi-racial country struggling to reconcile its present and its past.</p>
        <p>Now, in his latest novel, ''Christopher Unborn,'' Mr. Fuentes returns to Mexico City to give us another portrait of his native land. Although the setting is faintly futuristic (1992), although the plot embraces all the up-to-the-minute pyrotechnics of magic realism and post-modernism, the questions addressed by this novel are essentially the same ones raised by ''Where the Air Is Clear'' - namely, how is Mexico to enter the modern era without betraying its history? How is the nation to come to terms with America, its giant, influential neighbor to the north? And how is it to cope with a daunting array of social and economic problems?</p>
        <p>Indeed, the fictional Mexico portrayed in ''Christopher Unborn'' is a hellish parody of civilization - ''a narrow, skeletal and decapitated nation.'' Thoughtless industrialization has turned Mexico City (''Makesicko City'') into a replica of the metropolis in ''Blade Runner'': a foul acid rain falls constantly over the earthquake-devastated city, while the poor search aimlessly for jobs and the rich build themselves imitation Bloomingdales. In order to help pay off the nation's debt (estimated at $1.492 trillion), the Yucatan has been ceded to the ''Club Mediterranee''; and Chiapas, Tabasco and Campeche have been handed over to a United States-controlled oil consortium known as the Five Sisters. Veracruz, meanwhile, has been mysteriously cut off from communication with the rest of the country - the cause is rumored to be an agrarian revolution or an American invasion.</p>
        <p>Politicians, almost without exception, have become hopelessly corrupt. A superminister, Don Ulises Lopez, who has supervised most of this geographical dismemberment, has risen to power by manipulating the nation's money flow and selling imported consumer goods at inflated prices. His rival, Minister Federico Robles Chacon, has gained influence by cynically manipulating the people's yearning for symbols. Most recently, he has succeeded in turning a modest office worker into ''Mamadoc,'' a combination of Mae West and the Virgin of Guadalupe, who promises to ''confess, and sublimate in the name of the system, all the corruption of the system.''</p>
        <p>We learn of these developments in Mexico not through conventional means, but through Mr. Fuentes's anomalous narrator, an unborn fetus named Christopher, who is to be born on Oct. 12, 1992, the 500th anniversary of Columbus's discovery of America. As in Laurence Sterne's ''Tristram Shandy'' - which seems to have served as a model for this book, along with ''Midnight's Children'' by Salman Rushdie - the narrative is ostensibly concerned with the narrator's family history, and it largely takes place before his much-awaited birth.</p>
        <p>Typographical oddities abound (blank pages, E. E. Cummings-like arrangements of words, authorial asides), as do endless digressions about everything from reproductive cell division to the intricacies of Mexican history. Long-winded and discursive, Christopher seems possessed of both omniscience and a need for total disclosure - traits that make for a novel that's more ambitious than satisfying, more vigorous than shapely.</p>
        <p>Silly subplots involving comically named characters (Deng Chopin, Hipi Toltec); colorful but superfluous set-pieces; pointlessly self-referential allusions to Mr. Fuentes's own earlier works; anecdotes involving political functionaries, who appear to have been introduced simply to make some sort of sociological or ideological point - these aspects of the novel persuade the reader that Mr. Fuentes has used the license afforded by Christopher's unstructured tale as an excuse for self-indulgence. Whereas his last novel, ''The Old Gringo,'' worked a series of dazzling improvisations on a straightforward story (the life and death of Ambrose Bierce), the nearly infinite possibilities afforded by Christopher's stream-of-consciousness narrative lead, in this case, not to inventiveness but to windiness and pretension.</p>
        <p>When Christopher leaves off philosophizing about the fate of his country and sticks to the story of his own family, the results are considerably more engaging. We learn about the courtship and marriage of his parents, Angel and Angeles, an ill-matched but romantic pair; and we learn of another pair of opposites -Christopher's two uncles, the idealistic Don Gernando Benitez, an ethnologist, pledged to democracy; and the scheming Don Homero Fagoaga, an ambitious politician, reputedly involved in a nefarious scheme with the Marcoses in the Philippines.</p>
        <p>In addition, we meet Christopher's grandparents, Diego and Isabela Palomar, known as the Mexican Curies, who lived during that period ''when Mexico thought it could be technologically independent''; and his great-grandfather, Gen. Don Rigoberto Palomar, ''whose life ran neck and neck with that of the century'' - the youngest general in the Mexican Revolution, who believed that ''the Revolution had triumphed and carried out all its promises.''</p>
        <p>If the allegorical weight carried by each of these characters underscores Mr. Fuentes's epic ambitions, it also points to the schematic, polemical nature of ''Christopher Unborn.'' In the end, of course, Christopher, too, becomes a symbol - perhaps the novel's ultimate symbol, a symbol of the failed promises of the New World discovered by Columbus, as well as a symbol of its hopes for rejuvenation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
