<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Bush Budget: Promises to Keep, Messes to Mop Up</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="222766"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="WASHINGTON WORKOUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7DD1F31F931A25751C0A96F948260" item-length="1024" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Bush Budget: Promises to Keep, Messes to Mop Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER T. KILBORN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: FEDERAL budgets are pies of taxpayer money that the President and Congress slice up and pass around to aircraft builders, disabled miners, urban transit authorities and, directly or indirectly, to virtually all the other participants in the economy. Usually the pie grew from year to year, so that even less favored sectors and constituencies could get a little more than before.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: FEDERAL budgets are pies of taxpayer money that the President and Congress slice up and pass around to aircraft builders, disabled miners, urban transit authorities and, directly or indirectly, to virtually all the other participants in the economy. Usually the pie grew from year to year, so that even less favored sectors and constituencies could get a little more than before.</p>
        <p>FEDERAL budgets are pies of taxpayer money that the President and Congress slice up and pass around to aircraft builders, disabled miners, urban transit authorities and, directly or indirectly, to virtually all the other participants in the economy. Usually the pie grew from year to year, so that even less favored sectors and constituencies could get a little more than before.</p>
        <p>But George Bush does not have much to pass around. He is committed to reducing the deficit from $163 billion this year to $100 billion next year and to keeping his promises -no new taxes, no curbs in Social Security spending and stable military spending. He also has to find money to guarantee the deposits held by almost 300 insolvent savings and loans and finance the cleanup of the Government's crippled nuclear weapons plants - two big problems, involving tens of billions of taxpayer dollars, that became so big because other Presidents left them untended.</p>
        <p>The new President's men quickly began to spread the word that if Mr. Bush's budget was perceived as lacking in innovation, it was because he had to attend first to inherited problems.</p>
        <p>''We have to bring the deficit down,'' the President's budget director, Richard G. Darman, told some reporters at breakfast Friday. ''We do have to fix up the S &amp; L mess. We do have to fix the atomic weapons plants and get the cleanup associated with it going. There's a host of other such things that constrain the freedom to do some other bold new things that might be a little more exciting.''</p>
        <p>Thus last week, from a total of $1.16 trillion in spending that he budgeted for fiscal 1990, which starts Oct. 1, Mr. Bush could scrape up just 1 percent, or about $12 billion, for issues he raised in the campaign: education, drug abuse, the environment, the homeless and space exploration.</p>
        <p>''We have more will than wallet,'' the President had warned in his inaugural. It was a far cry from the promises of predecessors who spoke of building great societies and putting men on the moon. A Selective Freeze</p>
        <p>Those in Congress who do not share the President's priorities were infuriated when Mr. Bush ordered a freeze on spending for what Mr. Darman called ''black box'' programs: $136 billion of discretionary spending in such areas as urban mass transit and welfare programs - nearly everything outside Social Security, the military, interest on the national debt and most of the small increases Mr. Bush seeks. He proposed no specific spending increases or cuts among the frozen items, leaving that to negotiations with Congress.</p>
        <p>But even some members of Congress who share the President's priorities express doubt that he can meet his goals, however modest, without breaking his promises on taxes or spending cuts. Said Representative Stephen L. Neal, a North Carolina Democrat: ''Drugs, education, acid rain. I talked about the same things in my campaign. The problem is, how do you pay for it?''</p>
        <p>The financial markets seemed to have similar concerns. Many people believe that the markets stand ready to pummel the President upon any shred of evidence that the budget deficit is not on the way down or that inflation is on the way up. Sure enough, the Dow Jones industrial average responded to the President's Thursday night budget message, and to a report the next day that wholesale prices leaped 1 percent in January, by dropping 36.97 points on Friday. The prime rate rose half a point, to 11 percent. But there were similar spasms after the election before the markets settled down.</p>
        <p>Despite the budgetary reins on his policies, or perhaps because of them, the fog that has obscured George Bush's desires for the nation and his view of the Government's role has begun to lift here and there. Scattered among the 193 pages of his budget document are proposals, albeit small-money ones, that represent a nudge toward changing a fundamental feature of the economy. Tax Breaks for Industry</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush wants to wean the country of its propensity for borrowing and to encourage saving and investment and productivity growth, the measure of the nation's ability to compete with the likes of Japan.</p>
        <p>He apparently believes that tax breaks are one way to accomplish this. He would make permanent a tax break to encourage industry to invest in expansion, an incentive that would have expired this year, and he would help both cities and industry with incentives to put factories in urban ''enterprise zones,'' where many of the unemployed live. He would set up programs to aid education, especially in the sciences, mathematics and engineering, the fountainheads of new technology and the nation's future industries. But these ''competitiveness'' proposals, as he called them, also include some that Democrats put under the rubric of partisan politics.</p>
        <p>For example, the President kept his campaign promise to propose reducing the tax rate on capital gains to 15 percent. Democrats in Congress see this as a sop to the rich. Mr. Bush hopes to deflect them in contending that long-term investment is essential to long-term growth; he would require that investments be held for at least a year, and eventually for three years, to qualify.</p>
        <p>But this ''competitiveness'' President also has an interventionist side. Mr. Bush proposed a sweeping overhaul of the regulatory apparatus that oversees the savings and loan industry and gave it new power, which the regulators promptly displayed in seizing control of 10 ailing savings institutions. (Regulating the thrifts, page 5.) ''He obviously does not view Government as Ronald Reagan did,'' said Representative Leon E. Panetta, the California Democrat who is chairman of the House Budget Committee. ''He clearly believes the Government has a role to play.''</p>
        <p>But he is no Franklin D. Roosevelt. He set up a Resolution Trust Corporation to take over the failed savings institutions, but its mission is to get rid of them, not hold them. ''Look at his education and child-care programs,'' said Marvin H. Kosters, director of economic policy studies at the American Enterprise Institute. ''He's a believer in parental choice - not big Government programs.''  WASHINGTON WORKOUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
