<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Capitol Hill's High-Tech Tutor</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="266315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TECHNOLOGY ASSESSMENT, OFFICE OF</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIBBONS, JOHN H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEED91730F935A25754C0A96F948260" item-length="1549" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Capitol Hill's High-Tech Tutor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: When the Office of Technology Assessment took on a study of how technology was changing the American economy a few years ago, it found more than it was looking for - as usual.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: When the Office of Technology Assessment took on a study of how technology was changing the American economy a few years ago, it found more than it was looking for - as usual.</p>
        <p>When the Office of Technology Assessment took on a study of how technology was changing the American economy a few years ago, it found more than it was looking for - as usual.</p>
        <p>Agreeing with some economists' worst fears, analysts at the agency, an arm of Congress, reported that it was indeed possible that the economy would lose its vitality and that the future work force would consist of a relatively small white-collar component with interesting, well-paid jobs overseeing swarms of nonskilled workers.</p>
        <p>But O.T.A. also reported another, much brighter possibility: that technology would raise the living standards of all. And the researchers included something else they had found along the way: that because of statistical inadequacies, the United States was understating its exports of services by some 40 percent.</p>
        <p>The wide-ranging report was typical of the agency's interdisciplinary and thorough approach to the many subjects it tackles. It is an approach that is contributing to O.T.A.'s reputation in both the public and private sectors as one of the nation's most and efficient authoritative research bodies. ''It has earned an extraordinary amount of respect,'' said Donald Kennedy, president of Stanford University. ''The quality of the work is very high, and more importantly, people have managed to keep it pretty clear of politics.''</p>
        <p>The O.T.A., created in 1972 to advise Congress about a swelling volume of technically related subjects it couldn't hope to comprehend on its own, contends that it is able to think big by remaining small. ''When you're small you are constantly called on to remember that the source of wisdom is outside your institution,'' said John H. Gibbons, the physicist who has led the O.T.A. for a decade, sitting in his office at the agency's red-brick building just blocks from the Capitol. ''It reminds me a little bit of Japan. They are so well plugged into the world market because they're little, and their market has to be, by definition, 'out there.' ''</p>
        <p>Indeed, by augmenting its small but diverse staff of 145 with an elaborate network of advisers and consultants from industry and academia, the agency - whose budget for the current fiscal year is $17.9 million - is able to produce a score of major studies each year. On average, each takes two years and costs about $500,000. And each is a comprehensive survey of what is known about a subject to which is added, without recommendation, a list of policy options.</p>
        <p>Business and economics have always had a place in O.T.A.'s technology-driven agenda. Studies are under way, for example, on how technology is reshaping the securities markets and the trade in manufactured goods.</p>
        <p>''We're spending a lot of time looking at Japan,'' said Dr. Gibbons. ''We feel Japan and Europe 1992 are both cards that are being played that we are going to have to understand quite intimately - not just their industrial sectors but what they're doing in their educational systems, how they're thinking about problem-solving, the relation of government to the private sector and how they view their place in a global climate as well as a global market.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Gibbons, a mathematics and chemistry graduate of Randolph-Macon College with a doctorate in physics from Duke University, talks as easily about economics as about science or almost any other subject. His depth of knowledge and experience account for a good part of O.T.A.'s reputation.</p>
        <p>The O.T.A. chief began his career at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory in Tennessee, where he directed studies of nuclear reactions and the evolution of stars. Proximity to depressed Appalachia played a role in broadening his perspective, he said. His introduction to Washington was in the mid-1970's, when he worked for the Federal Energy Administration.</p>
        <p>The O.T.A. is governed by a 12-member Congressional board, six Democrats and six Republicans, equally divided between Senate and House. Although its original creators in Congress, including Emilio Q. Daddario, a Representative from Connecticut who became the agency's first director, tried to insulate the O.T.A. from politics, Dr. Gibbons knows that political forces surround every Washington undertaking.</p>
        <p>In fact, he says, he was a bit reluctant to accept the O.T.A. job when it was offered because he was not sure he could handle the political pressures. After he took it, he kept his house in Tennessee for three years so he could ''walk out'' if necessary.</p>
        <p>''You have to be very careful in the way you come out with findings and with options not to give a tilt to the bottom line,'' Dr. Gibbons said. ''What we try to do is to be Congress's own little band that helps keep the Administration's claims and the claims of others a little bit more honest.''</p>
        <p>Still, its avoidance of policy recommendations does not keep the O.T.A. from being ensnared in political controversy. One example: its work on the Reagan Administration's Strategic Defense Initiative, which broughta heavy Pentagon attack for stating, among other things, that the dependability of S.D.I. software ''would always be'' irresolvable. The chief S.D.I. scientist called this assessment ''only a philosophical opinion with no technical basis.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes the political pressures are more subtle but just as real. Without good antennae, Dr. Gibbons said, ''you could get mouse-trapped within 24 hours'' by, say, someone proposing a study simply as a ploy to delay a likely committee decision that the member opposed. A sort of political Archimedes principle is at work here, he once told an interviewer: ''You stay upright by having pressure applied from all sides.''</p>
        <p>The O.T.A.'s process for deciding what to study is somewhat more elaborate than those of its larger and better-known sister agencies - the Congressional Budget Office, the General Accounting Office and the Congressional Research Service. Although requests may come from the chairman or ranking minority member of any Congressional committee, the O.T.A.'s board must give its approval.</p>
        <p>Despite the complexity of much of its subject matter, the O.T.A. usually manages to make its reports not just understandable but often engaging.</p>
        <p>Take its report on infertility problems: ''It is 2:00 P.M. You are sitting with your wife in the doctor's office, waiting to be told what to do next to get your wife pregnant,'' reads one passage. ''You gave a semen sample two days ago to some lab person. You are sure that humiliating experience was just the beginning of many more. You are wondering how bad your sperm are.''</p>
        <p>Such lively writing is important to the agency, which often hires professional editors for its projects. ''We make a big effort,'' said Jean K. McDonald, an O.T.A. spokesperson, explaining that in writing for Congress, ''we're not dealing with science majors, we're dealing with a lot of lawyers.''</p>
        <p>Princeton University has reprinted S.D.I. reports for its graduate students. (When the O.T.A.'s own inventory runs short, it buys from the university, whose 40 percent discount brings the price below that of the Government Printing Office.) The O.T.A.'s work isn't always praised. Besides the S.D.I. controversy, there were some complaints that one of its studies on the uses of biotechnology gave too much weight to the concerns of activists worried about genetic misuse or accidents.</p>
        <p>Nor has the agency always had the enviable reputation it enjoys today. ''They started out on shaky ground,'' said Frank Press, president of the National Academy of Sciences, of O.T.A.'s early days. For various reasons, including project decisions geared largely to the short-term political desires of board members, he said, ''they were very vulnerable, almost went out of business.'' When Dr. Gibbons was installed, he was warned that he represented the agency's last chance.</p>
        <p>Now that he's had a chance to revive the agency and review the nation's technological problems, what issues worry him most? He mentions global warming (''Its momentum is such that you can't turn it around''), the need for greater energy efficiency and the problems of the solid-waste stream (the subject of a June report). He mentions the troubles with public education and with drugs (''We're trashing our children. . . . It's a travesty what we're doing to our kids.'') An area where he sees major improvement, he says, is in the potential for arms control. ''Our paradigm of the cold war has shifted,'' he said, referring to the agency's work on seismic measurement of nuclear weapons testing. ''The question is, how well can technology be a surrogate for trust in international agreements?''  SOME UPCOMING O.T.A. REPORTS  Expected dates of publication are in parentheses.  Copyright and Home Copying  (Fall 1989)  High-Temperature Superconductivity inPerspective  (Fall 1989)  Superfund Implementation  (Fall 1989)  Forensic Uses of Genetic Tests  (Fall/Winter 1989)  Agricultural Approaches to Reduce Agrichemical Contamination of Groundwater in the United States  (Winter 1989-90)  Technology, Innovation and U.S. Trade  (Spring 1990)  Securities Markets and Information Technology  (Spring 1990)  Training in the Workplace: Implications for U.S. Competitiveness  (Fall 1990)  Source: Office of Technology Assessment</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
