<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Congress Seeks to Reduce Greenhouse Effect; Warming and Cooling</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="229372"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">EPHRON, LARRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DA1E3FF934A35750C0A96F948260" item-length="487" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Congress Seeks to Reduce Greenhouse Effect; Warming and Cooling</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>There is a grave misunderstanding in public discussions of the greenhouse effect, and it threatens our survival. When the greenhouse effect heats up the atmosphere, more water is evaporated from the surface of the oceans, forming more clouds. R. T. Wetherald and S. Manabe estimate that increased carbon dioxide greatly increases cloud cover in the middle and higher latitudes, and decreases it in the tropics.</p>
        <p>V. Ramanathan and others have just reported that satellite data show cloud cover over the mid-and high-latitude oceans to have a substantial net cooling effect - a cooling four times as large as the predicted warming from a doubling of carbon dioxide. The greatest cooling effect was in winter. And Ray Bradley and others found ''marked increases'' in Northern Hemisphere mid-latitude precipitation over the last 30 to 40 years, with the greatest increases occurring in winter (mainly, one presumes, as increased snowfall). They also found increasing drought in the lower latitudes during the same period, especially in summer and fall.</p>
        <p>In other words, the greenhouse effect is not only doing some major warming (the tropics, and higher latitude summers), but it is at the same time doing some major cooling (mid- and high-latitude winters) - and has been doing both for decades. The drought that has killed millions of people in northern Africa in the last 17 years is the result of greenhouse warming. (The likelihood that it was caused by normal variability has been calculated as one in 130,000.) Many North American winters have been extremely and increasingly cold during precisely this period.</p>
        <p>By continuing to look only at global averages, in which warming and cooling effects cancel each other out, and inexplicably to ignore the kinds of research described above, climatologists who project a greenhouse warming into the middle of the next century are doing us a terrible disservice. We are being lulled into a false sense of security that the worst consequences of the greenhouse effect are decades away, and that we have time to take appropriate action.</p>
        <p>Most of what needs to be done is well known, except for remineralizing forest soils with finely ground gravel dust, somewhat comparable to liming lakes killed by acid rain. The evidence for remineralizing is presented in my book ''The End: The Imminent Ice Age and How We Can Stop It.''</p>
        <p>The growth rate of existing and newly planted forests can thus be increased 300 percent to 500 percent, which will consume large quantities of atmospheric carbon dioxide. (That's how the glaciers revitalize the earth during a major ice age: by grinding up rocks into a fine dust that remineralizes the soil.) Remineralizing farm soils will increase agricultural output similarly, replace all the chemicals and increase our food reserves substantially at this most critical time. LARRY EPHRON  Berkeley, Calif., March 1, 1989</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
