<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shoreham: Excruciating Minuet</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="231125"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND OPINION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND LIGHTING CO (LILCO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">POLIMENI, VINCENT</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SHOREHAM NUCLEAR POWER PLANT</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890312T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DC1631F931A25750C0A96F948260" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shoreham: Excruciating Minuet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT POLIMENI; Vincent Polimeni, a developer in Hauppauge, is on the executive board of the Association for a Better Long Island.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">POLIMENI, VINCENT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IT is an excruciating minuet danced by lawmakers, the courts, Federal agencies and special-interest groups around the dormant Shoreham atomic energy plant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IT is an excruciating minuet danced by lawmakers, the courts, Federal agencies and special-interest groups around the dormant Shoreham atomic energy plant.</p>
        <p>IT is an excruciating minuet danced by lawmakers, the courts, Federal agencies and special-interest groups around the dormant Shoreham atomic energy plant.</p>
        <p>But the dancers keep swirling even while the tempo changes, and it is a mystery just when it all will end. The latest step, in which Shoreham is given to the state for the legal dollar so that it may be dismantled, leaves many in the business community skeptical.</p>
        <p>We have been asked to watch the last dance many times before, and each time the band has played on.</p>
        <p>But more importantly, while an enormous amount of energy is being expended to shut down an enormous source of energy, Long Island's economy is now being threatened by government indecision, bizarre regulations, erupting property taxes and the most dominant political force in the region today: Nimby, or Not in My Backyard.</p>
        <p>Nimby is the force that prevents the Governor from using the empty Pilgrim State Psychiatric Hospital for a desperately needed jail.</p>
        <p>Nimby is the force that prevents the construction of an autoclave on the Island that would help reduce the chances of another summer of syringes along our precious beaches.</p>
        <p>Nimby is sending our garbage on flatbed trucks to landfills in other states at astronomical cost to the taxpayer.</p>
        <p>And Nimby is the force behind the blockage of emergency gas turbines that the Long Island Lighting Company needs to prevent electrical brownouts during peak periods.</p>
        <p>More powerful than all the major political parties put together, perhaps more powerful than evisceral issues such as abortion, Nimby has effectively cowed our most popular politicians while threatening beyond all reason our region's ability to build anything for any reason at any cost.</p>
        <p>It seeks to dictate a policy that says we would rather close our beaches, paralyze our economy, fortify our homes and pay more for hauling garbage than educating our children just as long as solutions to the problems are kept out of my backyard.</p>
        <p>It is time to break the back of Nimby and, in doing so, cast a clear and unequivocal vote of confidence in our region's future.</p>
        <p>The Association for a Better Long Island believes that this latest effort to close Shoreham threatens our region with the permanent loss of 800 million kilowatts of electricty needed to power our bicounty area well into the next century.</p>
        <p>We believe that Nimby will prevent the replacement of that power by fossil fuel plants that would be massive in size and contributors to the greenhouse effect and acid rain. It is a critical issue that Governor Cuomo and Lilco only allude to in this, the supposed final chapter in the Shoreham saga.</p>
        <p>The Long Island business community is allowed a measure of skepticism about the latest Shoreham death sentence when the Governor suggests that he will literally dismantle the plant.</p>
        <p>At a time when Long Islanders can't get other regions to accept its household garbage, who will be willing to take the construction debris of an atomic energy plant irradiated from 5 percent power?</p>
        <p>With language that must have been cleverly crafted by Lilco lawyers, it is clear that the signed ''agreement'' to end the 10-year-old debate still allows the utility to move forward in licensing the plant.</p>
        <p>Lilco recognizes that there is a lot of life left in the Shoreham debate before the final act is played out. In fact, if you listen closely, you can hear the musicians tuning up for yet another movement in this bizarre concert.</p>
        <p>It's time that Long Island got on with its future. If we confront and disarm Nimby, historians might just mark 1989 as the milestone year that Long Island not only recognized its problems but also solved them.</p>
        <p>One effective milestone in that fight will be the eventual opening of Shoreham.</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND OPINION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
