<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Proposing Talks in U.S. on Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="306889"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORBACHEV, MIKHAIL S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7DA133DF935A35751C1A96F948260" item-length="655" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Proposing Talks in U.S. on Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In a policy shift, President Bush has proposed that the United States sponsor an international conference in Washington next fall to begin negotiating a treaty on global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In a policy shift, President Bush has proposed that the United States sponsor an international conference in Washington next fall to begin negotiating a treaty on global warming.</p>
        <p>In a policy shift, President Bush has proposed that the United States sponsor an international conference in Washington next fall to begin negotiating a treaty on global warming.</p>
        <p>Until now, White House officials have resisted a specific commitment to begin such negotiations, choosing instead to play down the urgency of the global warming issue. In recent months, however, Mr. Bush has faced pressure from members of Congress, Administration officials and several European nations to take stronger action.</p>
        <p>The President made the treaty proposal at the Malta summit conference with the Soviet President, Mikhail S. Gorbachev. The United States and the Soviet Union lead in emissions of carbon dixoide, which scientists say is accumulating in the atmosphere and contributing to global warming. A Hint of Greater Action</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration has made no specific commitment to reduce such emissions. But in seeking an international conference, the United States is tacitly acknowledging that it will take further steps, environmentalists say.</p>
        <p>As host of such a conference, the United States is likely to subject itself to heavy pressure to make specific commitments. Representatives of several environmentalist groups, which have criticized Mr. Bush for failing to deal with the global warming issue, said the President would not have made the offer unless he was prepared to move ahead more quickly.</p>
        <p>Administration spokesmen today denied that the President had shifted his strategy, and suggested that the offer was part of a natural policy evolution. ''I don't think for a moment it represents a change of heart,'' said Dr. D. Allan Bromley, the President's science adviser. ''This really is part of a coherent program that we have been working on for a long time.''</p>
        <p>''Whether it's evolution or revelation, I think the President is to be congratulated on taking this initiative,'' said Senator John Heinz, a Pennsylvania Republican who has criticized the President's policies on climate change. Gore Is Wary</p>
        <p>But Senator Albert Gore Jr., a Tennessee Democrat and another critic of Mr. Bush's climate-change policies, said, ''It remains to be seen whether this is a real change.'' Mr. Gore termed the proposal a ''begrudging acceptance of political reality.''</p>
        <p>At the summit conference, Mr. Bush also offered to convene in Washington next spring an international meeting of scientific, environmental and economic officials to address climate change. The Soviet Union did not respond to Mr. Bush's proposal to host the treaty conference, a White House spokesman said today. The President's offer will be formally considered by the United Nations Environment Program, under whose auspices international talks on climate change are now taking place.</p>
        <p>The United States and the Soviet Union, along with Japan, have been hesitant to discuss negotiating a treaty on global warming because of doubts about whether emissions of carbon dioxide and other so-called greenhouse gases are changing the climate. Stabilizing and reducing carbon dioxide emissions, produced by the burning of fossil fuels like coal and oil, would have enormous social and economic costs.</p>
        <p>The Administration has been divided about how quickly to move on global warming. John H. Sununu, the White House chief of staff, and Dr. Bromley have urged a deliberate pace until more data are available.</p>
        <p>The United States has backed a United Nations-sponsored panel that is scheduled to report its findings next fall.</p>
        <p>The report would be followed by an international conference aimed at obtaining a general consensus. Then, a second round of talks would produce specific national commitments on cuts in emissions.</p>
        <p>Other Administration officials, like William K. Reilly, Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, have advocated more aggressive steps to show that the United States considers global warming a serious environmental threat.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
