<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>119 Seized in Drive to Halt Indoor Marijuana Growing</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="295095"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MARIJUANA</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FOOD AND DRUG ADMINISTRATION (FDA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSTON, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DA1E3EF934A15753C1A96F948260" item-length="739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>119 Seized in Drive to Halt Indoor Marijuana Growing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID JOHNSTON, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSTON, DAVID</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Federal drug agents arrested 119 people today and raided retail stores in 46 states that sell specialized horticultural equipment that investigators say is used for growing marijuana indoors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Federal drug agents arrested 119 people today and raided retail stores in 46 states that sell specialized horticultural equipment that investigators say is used for growing marijuana indoors.</p>
        <p>Federal drug agents arrested 119 people today and raided retail stores in 46 states that sell specialized horticultural equipment that investigators say is used for growing marijuana indoors.</p>
        <p>Officials of the Drug Enforcement Administration said that agents entered 22 businesses selling horticultural lighting and watering equipment and that 8 or 9 were closed.</p>
        <p>Agents also seized business documents like shipping records and customer lists that could lead to indoor marijuana growers, the officials said. Charges Are Unclear</p>
        <p>But most of those arrested today appeared to be people accused of growing marijuana indoors. It was not made clear where they were arrested, or on what charges.</p>
        <p>Sixty-five sites where marijuana was being cultivated, in addition to the stores, were raided and shut down today by Federal drug agents in conjunction with state and local law-enforcement officials.</p>
        <p>Terrence W. Burke, Acting Deputy Administrator of the drug agency, said the investigation was a broad attack ultimately aimed at reducing occasional marijuana use. Users Held to Account</p>
        <p>''Users are a major factor in the drug trafficking problem and they are going to be held accountable and subject to suitable penalties, both civil and criminal,'' he said.</p>
        <p>More broadly, an Administration official said, the action was a signal to drug-producing countries, whose leaders have complained that American officials have asked them to curtail production while failing to take similar steps at home.</p>
        <p>Representatives of groups that back liberalizing marijuana laws scoffed at the crackdown. Doug McVay, the projects coordinator of National Organization for the Reform of Marijuana Laws, said it was a ''publicity stunt.'' Fear for the Innocent</p>
        <p>He said the inquiry was a waste of Federal resources because the effort to track down the purchasers of the growing equipment would lead drug agents to innocent people. ''A lot of gardening clubs around the country will be shocked,'' he said.</p>
        <p>An agency spokesman said operators of stores that sell the equipment could be charged with cultivating marijuana or aiding in it by selling the equipment or providing advice to the growers. What It Is, What It Could Do</p>
        <p>The equipment these stores sell is not in itself illegal. But one official said evidence obtained through wiretaps and undercover investigators showed that operators of some stores conspired with marijuana growers to cultivate the illegal plant.</p>
        <p>The specialized equipment is well suited to promote the growth of marijuana indoors: track lighting, containerized irrigation tubs, ventilation gear, humidifying devices and carbon dioxide enrichment systems.</p>
        <p>The manager of Worm's Way, a gardening supplies store in Tampa, Fla., said that early today two drug agents asked him to provide a mailing list of his customers. ''I told them I didn't have a mailing list,'' said the manager, Wallace L. Heydt. ''I don't know what to think, I'm selling fertilizer and hydroponics'' - enriched water for growth.</p>
        <p>The raids were conducted in every state except Hawaii, Nebraska, North Dakota and West Virginia. Singled Out, Some Owners Say</p>
        <p>Some store operators said the Government had singled them out because they advertised their products in publications that cater to the drug culture, like High Times. The magazine displays a photograph of an exotic drug in each issue, like ''Tennessee Tea,'' a potent form of marijuana, in the October issue.</p>
        <p>''The Government is trying to prove that somehow every single person who buys from these stores is a marijuana cultivator,'' said John E. Holmstrom, executive editor of High Times. ''They want nothing to do with illegal cultivation.''</p>
        <p>Many marijuana growers have moved indoors in recent years as aerial surveillance and other drug enforcement actitivities against them has increased.</p>
        <p>The drug agency said that in the past month, 112 people have been arrested in the investigation on charges of cultivating marijuana at 94 indoor growing sites that had 17,000 marijuana plants.</p>
        <p>Domestic suppliers produce about 25 percent of the marijuana consumed in the United States, while Colombia produces about 40 percent, Mexico 25 percent and other countries 10 percent, according to Government estimates.</p>
        <p>The drug agency said it selected marijuana growing because of estimates that domestic production increased from 2,100 tons in 1986 to 4,350 to 4,850 tons in 1988.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
