<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where the Mushroom Is King</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="224817"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="FARE OF THE COUNTRY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSHROOMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">KENNETT SQUARE (PA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDSTEIN, ELAINE DANN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mushrooms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6DC113FF93AA25751C0A96F948260" item-length="1860" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where the Mushroom Is King</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE DANN GOLDSTEIN; ELAINE DANN GOLDSTEIN is a writer who lives in Rockville Centre, L.I.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDSTEIN, ELAINE DANN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: MUSHROOMS have always been the stuff of fairy tales but in Kennett Square, Pa., the noble fungus is a way of life. The town is the heart of Chester County, which calls itself the world's mushroom capital. According to the Federal Department of Agriculture, two-thirds of the country's annual crop of nearly 400 million pounds is produced in the county by 160 growers, the largest concentration anywhere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: MUSHROOMS have always been the stuff of fairy tales but in Kennett Square, Pa., the noble fungus is a way of life. The town is the heart of Chester County, which calls itself the world's mushroom capital. According to the Federal Department of Agriculture, two-thirds of the country's annual crop of nearly 400 million pounds is produced in the county by 160 growers, the largest concentration anywhere.</p>
        <p>MUSHROOMS have always been the stuff of fairy tales but in Kennett Square, Pa., the noble fungus is a way of life. The town is the heart of Chester County, which calls itself the world's mushroom capital. According to the Federal Department of Agriculture, two-thirds of the country's annual crop of nearly 400 million pounds is produced in the county by 160 growers, the largest concentration anywhere. Almost every mushroom for sale in the Northeast is from this region.  Through European history mushrooms were reserved for royalty.Mushrooms have been blamed for the deaths of Emperors Tiberius and Claudius, Czar Alexander I, Pope Clement VII and Charles V of France. (Indeed, the poisonous varieties were a favorite of the Borgias.) Although there is some evidence of cultivation by the Japanese as long as 2,000 years ago, the common Agaricus campestris was first grown at the beginning of the 18th century in limestone quarries near Paris (the word comes from moisseron, the moss in which they were grown), but it wasn't until early in this century that they became affordable. At 14 calories a cup, low in fat, cholesterol and sodium-free, they are a good diet food. Annual per capita consumption has gone from 6 ounces to 3 1/2 pounds in the last 30 years, according to the American Mushroom Institute.</p>
        <p>Mushrooms were originally a farmer's winter crop, grown in very limited amounts and with difficulty. The problem was threefold: temperature, fragility of the spores that produce the mushroom and disease.</p>
        <p>Temperature control was first addressed in 1896. William Swayne, a florist in Kennett Square, began growing the familiar Agricus bisporus (brown until a mutant white variety was discovered) in the unused space under his greenhouse benches. He went on to build the first house to be used exclusively for mushroom growing, and modern mass cultivation was born, centered in the Kennett Square area because the spore couldn't be kept alive during transport.</p>
        <p>It was the growers William K. Phillips and the Cordivano brothers who pioneered the use of ice and then air-conditioning to make mushrooms a summer crop.</p>
        <p>At Phillips Mushroom Farms the mushrooms are produced in a total of 25 growing houses, 60-foot-long windowless concrete buildings. Six flushes, or crops from a single spawning, can be harvested before the nutrients in the bed are exhausted, but three or four are more usual. The largest and most nutritious fungi come from the first; the second produces smaller but more uniform ones. Each succeeding flush every five to seven days yields less as the beds go from solid mushrooms to white patches in brown topsoil.</p>
        <p>In each 13-week growing cycle, the temperature, humidity and level of carbon dioxide must be continuously controlled. First there is steam sterilization of everything (mushrooms are very susceptible to disease), then pasteurization of the newly prepared growing medium, the compost, spread by filling gangs working in great heat and ammonia fumes. Next is conversion, when the ammonia smell has gone and a certain texture achieved to receive the spawn, sterile seeds innoculated with spores. In 14 to 21 days gray-white filaments have grown throughout the eight-inch thick bed; mushrooms are their fruiting bodies.</p>
        <p>Then enriched topsoil, called casing, is spread, and it's time to ''pin the house.'' This is the time when the temperature is dropped and the humidity is raised, shocking the filaments into pulling together into pinhead-size mushrooms. So, contrary to popular belief, mushrooms don't pop up overnight; it takes 23 to 25 days from casing to picking.</p>
        <p>The mushrooms, up to this time, have been growing in total darkness, but now the pickers turn on portable fluorescent lights, although some still wear the traditional miners' lamps. Mushrooms are picked just before they are fully ripe because retailers say consumers like them with a fully closed veil, the membrane that holds the edge of the cap to the stem. Two more myths fall: first, a fully mature, open, dark cap is not ''bad'' - Europeans prefer them that way - but is simply stronger flavored; second, they don't become poisonous with age. Like any food, a spoiled mushroom looks spoiled: dark and slimy.</p>
        <p>Less than 24 hours after picking, the mushrooms are at the retailer.</p>
        <p>Phillips grows five kinds: white; cremini, a white-freckled brown with a nuttier, denser flavor and less water; portabella, which can reach eight inches across, very meaty and flavorful; shiitake (whose stem isn't eaten), a woodsy exotic variety cultured on oak sawdust logs that takes four to six years to grow in the wild but only six weeks at the farm, and the spicy fan-shaped oyster, grown on bags of straw.</p>
        <p>All of them are sold at the farm from refrigerated cases (which is how fresh mushrooms should be kept), but, better yet, Phillips Mushroom Place has a shop, model farm, museum and short film about mushroom growing and harvesting.</p>
        <p>Modern Mushroom Farms is one of the few that has automated everything that it can. The crop is still hand-picked though, and it still takes the same length of time to grow the three-flush cycle. A wholesaler, Modern Mushroom packs under its own label and those of other farms to distribute throughout the Northeast. They will sell to visitors to the office, from 1 to 10 pounds white at prices up to $10 for 10 pounds.</p>
        <p>The area abounds in restaurants with mushroom specialties. At the Longwood Inn on Route 1 there is a mycophagists (fungus eaters) section in the menu. The Sampler reflects the Greek heritage of the owners, Peter Skiados and his brothers: mushrooms a la grecque and in flaky phyllo pastry, along with mushrooms stuffed with crabmeat and sauteed in garlic butter.</p>
        <p>The Korean chef, Ki Ho Kim, brings the menu an oriental touch with mushrooms a la Longwood Inn, shiitake and white mushrooms over angel hair pasta in a light demiglaze soy sauce. Shiitake mushrooms Longwood style combines the exotics with smoked Norwegian salmon, also over angel hair, in a cream, vodka, soy and garlic sauce. Mushroom soup, omelets and fritata are always available; a nice idea at dinner is a demi-serving of the mushroom soup and the soup du jour.</p>
        <p>Down the block and across from Longwood Gardens is a white clapboard house with a large sign, Hugo's, and a small one, Mushroom Specialties. The father of the owner, Hugo (Bob) Maucher, opened the inn in 1957. He didn't think to feature the various mushroom dishes he had always served until 20 years ago, when a University of Pennsylvania professor came in complaining he couldn't find a restaurant that did, so up went the little sign. (Mr. Marcher - ''everyone calls me Bob'' - said the first restaurant to sell breaded mushrooms in the area was the Quarry Diner, in 1960. It, like the quarry, is no longer open.) Hugo's uses 600 pounds of mushrooms a week. Fifty gallons of mushroom soup (full of large, meaty slices and, like everything else here, from a family recipe) are sold weekly, sized from a cup to a takeout quart. This is a good place to go if mycophobes are mixed with mycophagists; there's a ''Taste of Italy'' section on the menu, a children's menu, moderate prices and at the back of the inn is their takeout pizzeria, which will also pack some of the mushroom specialties.</p>
        <p>A short drive from Kennett Square is Vickers, housed in a farmhouse that was once a stop along the Underground Railway. Each table carries a history of the prominent abolitionist Vickers family of potters (one a direct ancestor of Richard M. Nixon), whose work is in the Philadelphia Art Museum.</p>
        <p>Arturo Burigatto, the owner, began his career at 14, training in hotels in Switzerland, England and Bermuda before restoring this house in 1972. The tavern anteroom belies the Williamsburg elegance and sophisticated menu of the dining rooms.</p>
        <p>There are always at least three daily mushroom specialties (including some imported varieties) in addition to the six permanently on the menu.  A TOUR OF MUSHROOM COUNTRY  Getting There</p>
        <p>Kennett Square is in the historic Brandywine Valley. The Brandywine Valley Tourist Information Center (800-228-9933; 215-388-2900 in Kennett Square) has opened an information center in the Longwood Meeting House at the entrance to Longwood Gardens on Route 1. There are displays and exhibits on the history of the building, which was built in 1855, and its role in the abolitionist movement, with maps and information about the area.  Farms</p>
        <p>Mushrooms can be bought at the following:</p>
        <p>Phillips Mushroom Farms, 1011 Kaolin Road, Kennett Square, Pa. 19348. 215-444-4492.</p>
        <p>Phillips Mushroom Place, Route 1 and Orchard Avenue, Kennett Square, Pa. 19348; 215-388-6082. A three-pound basket of medium whites is $4; large ones are $5. The other varieties are available in various sizes and prices. Mail orders of fresh mushrooms are filled only from November to April, when cool weather permits shipping. Bottled mushrooms are available all year; marinated, pickled and hot or regular salad are available at the farm or at the store in sizes of from 6 to 32 ounces and cost from 95 cents to $20.50 for a large gift-pack, shipped within the United States. Telephone orders are accepted.</p>
        <p>Modern Mushroom Farms, Route 1 Bypass and Newark Road, Toughkenamon, Pa. 19348; 215-268-3535.  Restaurants</p>
        <p>The first two establishments are in Kennett Square; Vickers is north of Kennett Square.</p>
        <p>Longwood Inn and Motor Lodge, Route 1 and Longwood Gardens; 215-444-3515. Open daily; breakfast 8 to 10:30 A.M., lunch 11 A.M. to 3 P.M., dinner 4 to 9 P.M. Monday to Thursday, 4 to 10 P.M. Friday and Saturday, 3 to 8:30 P.M. on Sunday, when brunch is served from 11 A.M. to 2:30 P.M. Dinner for two, not including wine, is about $40; reservations recommended.</p>
        <p>Hugo's Inn, Route 1, south of Route 52; 215-388-1144. Open Monday to Saturday 11 A.M. to late night, Sunday 11 A.M. to 10 P.M. Sixteen mushroom dishes are featured, beginning with simple grilled mushrooms at $1.95 a serving, up to $10.65 for mushrooms stuffed with crab.</p>
        <p>Vickers, Gordon Drive, Lionville, Pa. 19353; 215-363-6336. Open 5:30 to 11 P.M. Monday to Friday, to midnight on Saturday. Reservations suggested. The dishes sampled at dinner were beautifully presented: shrimp and frogs' legs with oyster mushrooms in garlic and white wine; muscovy duck with crimini in a warm raspberry vinaigrette; pheasant with chanterelles in Pernod sauce; buffalo medallions with porcini; foie gras with shiitake and truffles in red wine sauce; lobster and portabellas in Champagne sauce. Dinner for two, not including wine, about $70. Also open for lunch 11:30 A.M. to 2 P.M. Monday to Friday, with a simpler menu.  Lodgings</p>
        <p>The following provide bed and breakfast:</p>
        <p>Meadow Spring Farm, 201 East Street Road, Kennett Square, Pa. 19348; 215-444-3903. $65 double with private bath; $50 with shared bath.</p>
        <p>Whitethorne Past-Time Farm, Post Office Box 92, Unionville, Pa. 19375; 215-793-1748. $65 double.</p>
        <p>Campbell House, 160 East Doe Run Road, Kennett Square, Pa. 19348; 215-347-6756. A room for two people with private bath is $60; $50 with a shared bath. - E. D. G.</p>
        <p>FARE OF THE COUNTRY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
