<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Good Times Again for Carbide?</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19890820T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="274707"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PESTICIDES AND PESTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAZARDOUS AND TOXIC SUBSTANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BHOPAL (INDIA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNION CARBIDE CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GAF CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEUTSCH, CLAUDIA H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DC1E38F930A2575BC0A96F948260" item-length="2334" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Good Times Again for Carbide?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA H. DEUTSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DEUTSCH, CLAUDIA H</byline>
      <dateline>DANBURY, Conn.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: If Robert D. Kennedy were the type of man to brood, he'd probably be pretty miserable right now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: If Robert D. Kennedy were the type of man to brood, he'd probably be pretty miserable right now.</p>
        <p>If Robert D. Kennedy were the type of man to brood, he'd probably be pretty miserable right now.</p>
        <p>After all, the Union Carbide Corporation, the chemical company he has served for 34 years and run for three, has just come off its best year ever, and he certainly expected at least a few huzzahs from Wall Street. Instead, analyst after analyst, worried that the bottom is about to fall out of the ever-cyclical chemical market, has been advising clients to dump Carbide stock. In fact, the word on the Street is that the best thing Carbide could do for its shareholders is to liquidate.</p>
        <p>It is the kind of talk that could depress the staunchest optimist. But moping does not come naturally to Mr. Kennedy, an affable 56-year-old with a perpetual twinkle in his eye. Indeed, his main response is mild irritation.</p>
        <p>''Liquidation is just such a mindless thing,'' he said. ''We can acquire, we can hook up with others in joint ventures and strategic alliances. There are so many things we can do to turn this into a world-banging company.''</p>
        <p>Apparently, Mr. Kennedy is trying all of them, as he tries to prove to a skeptical world that yes, a company can recover, and even thrive, after a cataclysm.</p>
        <p>Nearly five years ago, an accident at a Carbide plant in Bhopal, India killed more than 3,300 people, leaving Carbide broken spiritually. A year later, a destructive takeover battle broke it financially and strategically, pushing it deep into debt and derailing its move into consumer products.</p>
        <p>To many analysts, Union Carbide became the Humpty Dumpty of its industry, a company that could never be put back together again. Mr. Kennedy is trying to switch the mythical metaphor to that of the Phoenix - a company that can rise triumphant from its ashes.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year he reorganized Carbide into a holding company with three independent businesses - chemicals and plastics, industrial gases and carbon. Each has almost total autonomy, as long as it operates on its own cash flow and returns more than its cost of capital. And lest any would-be raider earmark one of these stand-alone businesses as an asset sale to finance a takeover, Carbide announced a ''shareholders' rights plan'' late last month that would make it a lot harder and more expensive to make a run at the company.</p>
        <p>For Carbide, the value of this poison pill is as much symbolic as it is tactical. Until recently, Carbide's track record was so shaky that it was loath to do anything that smacked of management entrenchment. Now it has some success to point to. Last year, Carbide - along with most of the chemical industry - had a banner year, with sales hitting $8.3 billion and net income reaching $662 million. Debt, which had soared to 80 percent of capitalization in 1986, was down to 53 percent, and John A. Clerico, Carbide's treasurer, says it is heading toward 40 percent. And in February of this year, the Government of India - which had once sought $3.3 billion from Carbide in damages for the 1984 accident in Bhopal - settled for $470 million.  Getting Through Cycles</p>
        <p>''We've already shown that we could outperform every other company in the up cycle,'' Mr. Kennedy said. ''Now we'll show that we can outperform during the down cycle. Five years from now our shareholders will have seen a greater growth in the value of their investment than any alternative chemical investment.''</p>
        <p>If he makes good on that promise, there will be some very surprised people on Wall Street. For Carbide is still a troubled company.</p>
        <p>Its three businesses are relatively mature, and its chemical assets are concentrated in the United States - a severe drawback in the increasingly global chemical business. Moreover, Carbide's chances of finding an affordable acquisition are slim. The only way the company can grow now is to become a low-cost producer or to come out with new products.</p>
        <p>Each of Carbide's businesses is seeking ways to do both of those things. But Wall Street does not have high hopes that they will succeed. The company's stock, which traded in the $50 range in the pre-Bhopal days, has never stayed above $30 for more than a few days since then.</p>
        <p>And now, as the chemical industry moves into the downside of its cycle, most analysts say that Carbide, which derives most of its sales from basic chemicals, will not be able to withstand a trough. Carbide's second-quarter earnings, which were down slightly from the same quarter last year, seemed to prove their point.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kennedy, meanwhile, offers nothing concrete to change their minds. The official reason for this year's reorganization was to make the three businesses more entrepreneurial, but most Carbide watchers believe there is an underlying reason: With each business as a stand-alone entity, Carbide will find it easier to spin any one of them off into a joint venture or to shareholders.</p>
        <p>But if that is Mr. Kennedy's plan, he is not telling. Ask him where Carbide will be in five years, and you get a shrugged shoulder and a simple ''I have no idea.'' Press him for benchmark goals on profits or on the assorted financial ratios by which companies are judged, and he will say that ''financial things are not what you put in at the top, but what comes out at the bottom.'' What about synergies between Carbide's businesses? ''Whether the businesses complement each other is irrelevant.'' But isn't synergy the raison d'etre for diversified corporations? ''There is nothing sacred about corporations. Corporations don't make money. Businesses make money.''  Still a 'Sleeping Giant'?</p>
        <p>Wall Street finds such waffling rather unamusing. ''We would use any strength in the stock as a selling opportunity,'' George Krug, an analyst at Oppenheimer &amp; Company Inc., wrote to investors in July.</p>
        <p>Leonard Bogner, an analyst at Prudential Bache Securities Inc., refers to Carbide as a ''sleeping giant that no one ever seems able to goose.'' Even William R. Young, the Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc. chemical analyst whose ''hold'' recommendation on Carbide's stock makes him, by contrast, almost a fan, has no unequivocal praise. ''They need to do a lot more restructuring,'' he said.</p>
        <p>It is all quite a comedown for a company that, until the Bhopal tragedy, was getting its act together.</p>
        <p>Like most chemical companies, Carbide had suffered mightily during the industrywide recession of the early 1980's. The company tried to sell some of its commodity operations, but buyers were not to be found. So Carbide responded by paring plants and people, emphasizing commercially oriented research and moving heavily towards consumer businesses that would hedge it against the cyclicality of commodity chemicals.</p>
        <p>It was becoming a force in antifreeze, in batteries, in plastic wraps like Glad Bags - products that Carbide, with its strength in basic chemicals, could make at a cost advantage.  The Price of Freedom</p>
        <p>Then came Bhopal, and Carbide's fortunes plummeted. Television cameras recorded for posterity the humiliating arrest of Warren Anderson, Mr. Kennedy's predecessor, as he stepped off a plane in Bhopal. Social critics accused Carbide of callousness toward human life.</p>
        <p>Samuel J. Heyman, then the head of the GAF Corporation, made a run at the company a year later. With Bhopal hanging over its head, Carbide could not find a friendlier suitor. (''Sure, we tried, but other companies wouldn't touch us with a barge pole,'' Mr. Kennedy recalled).</p>
        <p>Instead, Carbide sold its consumer products businesses, as well as its agricultural businesses and its plush Danbury headquarters building, to buy back stock and to appease shareholders. All told, the company sold $3.5 billion in assets and returned $4.5 billion to shareholders in special dividends and other payouts.</p>
        <p>Carbide emerged with its independence intact, but so stripped of assets and so deep in debt that Wall Streeters dubbed it a Pyrrhic victory. ''Carbide mortgaged its future to remain independent,'' Mr. Bogner said.  Three-Part Invention</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, the heads of Carbide's three businesses do not concede that point. Each is pursuing a future in his own way:</p>
        <p>* Union Carbide Chemicals and Plastics Company Inc., by far Carbide's largest company, has been closing its highest-cost domestic plants while ''scouring the world'' for opportunities to build or buy assets overseas, said H. William Lichtenberger, the subsidiary's president. It also is providing seed money for employees who want to investigate new ideas. The new-business program, which has a goal of creating 30 $50 million businesses in 10 years, has yielded at least one success: supercritical carbon dioxide, which Carbide is pushing as a substitute for environmentally problematic solvents used to spray-paint cars.</p>
        <p>* UCAR Carbon Company Inc. is concentrating on better processes, since its products are used primarily in the steel industry and do not lend themselves easily to new uses. ''When you're stuck with finite applications, you have to find an infinite number of ways to make the product,'' said Robert P. Krass, UCAR's president.</p>
        <p>Mr. Krass has been arranging for researchers, marketers and other people at his plants to exchange process ideas with each other, rather than feed them up through any management hierarchy. And he is soliciting cost-savings ideas from employees. One plant is saving $10,000 a year on tires after workers suggested equipping forklift trucks differently in various parts of the plant.</p>
        <p>* Union Carbide Industrial Gases Inc. is looking for new uses for old gases. It has just brought to market a method to use oxygen to incinerate solid waste. And it is promoting the use of nitrogen - long used by fast-food companies to freeze hamburgers and such - to freeze vegetables.  Joint-Venture Hunts</p>
        <p>With the companies setting their own growth strategies, hiring their own lawyers and setting up their own banking arrangements, one obvious question arises: What does Union Carbide bring to the party? In other words, would the companies be better off on their own?</p>
        <p>There is little consensus on that, even among the three company presidents. ''Carbide's worth to us is its reputation, its stability, its clout with suppliers, and I believe the best thing for UCAR is to continue inside Carbide,'' said Mr. Krass.</p>
        <p>But his counterparts are not nearly as enthusiastic. Mr. Lichtenberger: ''I don't think being independent would make a difference one way or another.'' And Jack R. Maclean, the industrial gas company's president: ''If it's best for the shareholders that we stay together, then we should; if not, then we shouldn't.''</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, the corporate executives have a loftier idea of the value they add. What they offer, they say, is an ability to comb the world for joint venture partners and ideas.</p>
        <p>They have already had a measure of success. The year-old UOP Inc., a joint venture between Carbide and the Allied Signal Company, has quite profitably paired the technologies of the two companies to sell catalysts and adsorbents to the oil industry.</p>
        <p>A joint venture with the Shell Chemical Company involving polypropylene is also doing well. And Leonard M. Baker, Carbide's vice president of technology, recently arranged for Union Carbide scientists to go to Moscow to help find commercial applications for Soviet science.</p>
        <p>''The research is done within the existing businesses,'' Mr. Baker said. ''My job is to make sure everyone is abreast of emerging technologies.''</p>
        <p>Carbide's corporate staff will also have to decide what to do about the Danbury building, which the company moved into in the early 1980's. The building, which is dotted with empty offices, stretches across 1.1 million square feet of usable area. Carbide is just a tenant now, but its contract says it will share in profits if the land is developed for housing, small business or other uses. ''We are waiting breathlessly for an uptick in the real estate market,'' Mr. Kennedy said.  'Visioning' the Future</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Mr. Kennedy is trying to re-create an esprit de corps. When he took the helm in April of 1986, Carbide had stripped down to 50,000 employees, from 98,000 two years earlier. Those who were left were miserable. ''Everyone was so sick and tired of being beaten up all the time,'' Mr. Kennedy said.</p>
        <p>Since then, he has spent a lot of time on ''visioning'' work - communicating to the troops what he calls basic values, like technological excellence and concern for the environment. He has started presenting ''chairman's awards,'' for performance exemplifying those values.</p>
        <p>And he is stepping up intracompany communications. Late last month Mr. Kennedy and the heads of the three businesses broadcast a 20-minute state-of-the-company presentation, complete with questions and answers, to all Carbide locations. If employees say they liked the presentation, it will become a regular event.</p>
        <p>Soon, Mr. Kennedy maintains, Carbide's image will shine again. ''We hired more than 90 Ph.D.'s last year,'' he said. ''They must be sensing some kind of excitement here.''</p>
        <p>Maybe so - but Carbide's future may depend on its generating some excitement on Wall Street. And for now, it is still getting yawns.  AT A GLANCE  Union Carbide  All dollar amounts in thousands, except per share data.</p>
        <p>$</p>
        <p>Three months ended</p>
        <p>June 30</p>
        <p>1989</p>
        <p>1988</p>
        <p>Revenues</p>
        <p>$2,277,000</p>
        <p>$2,130,000</p>
        <p>Net Income</p>
        <p>186,000</p>
        <p>187,000</p>
        <p>Earnings per share</p>
        <p>$1.27</p>
        <p>$1.33</p>
        <p>Year ended</p>
        <p>Dec. 31</p>
        <p>1988</p>
        <p>1987</p>
        <p>Revenues</p>
        <p>$8,324,000</p>
        <p>$6,914,000</p>
        <p>Net Income</p>
        <p>662,000</p>
        <p>232,000</p>
        <p>Earnings per share</p>
        <p>$4.66</p>
        <p>$1.75</p>
        <p>Total assets, Dec. 31, 1988</p>
        <p>$8,441,000</p>
        <p>Current assets</p>
        <p>2,883,000</p>
        <p>Current liabilities</p>
        <p>2,455,000</p>
        <p>Long-term debt</p>
        <p>2,295,000</p>
        <p>Book value per share,</p>
        <p>June 30, 1989</p>
        <p>$15.46</p>
        <p>Stock price, Aug. 10, 1989</p>
        <p>N.Y.S.E. consolidated close</p>
        <p>29 1/8</p>
        <p>Stock price, 52-week range</p>
        <p>20 7/8-33 1/4</p>
        <p>Employees, Dec. 31, 1988</p>
        <p>43,992</p>
        <p>Headquarters</p>
        <p>Danbury, Conn.</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 20, 1989, Sunday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>An article last week about Union Carbide referred incompletely to the price history of the company's stock since the 1984 Bhopal accident. The article noted that the stock traded at $50 before the accident and that it is now trading at below $30. But the comparison failed to take into account a 3-for-1 stock split in 1986.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 20, 1989, Sunday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>An article last week about Union Carbide referred incompletely to the price history of the company's stock since the 1984 Bhopal accident. The article noted that the stock traded at $50 before the accident and that it is now trading at below $30. But the comparison failed to take into account a 3-for-1 stock split in 1986.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
