<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Offers Compromise On Garbage Recycling</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="305620"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCINERATORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6DD123BF932A35751C1A96F948260" item-length="718" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Offers Compromise On Garbage Recycling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Under strong pressure from industry, the Environmental Protection Agency today proposed a compromise regulation aimed at reducing garbage burning 25 percent by forcing incinerator operators not to burn recyclable material.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Under strong pressure from industry, the Environmental Protection Agency today proposed a compromise regulation aimed at reducing garbage burning 25 percent by forcing incinerator operators not to burn recyclable material.</p>
        <p>Under strong pressure from industry, the Environmental Protection Agency today proposed a compromise regulation aimed at reducing garbage burning 25 percent by forcing incinerator operators not to burn recyclable material.</p>
        <p>The proposal, now being circulated for public comment, gives incinerator operators more time to comply than the agency had originally sought and puts some of the burden for recycling on cities, counties and towns. The proposal took into account some objections of incinerator industry officials who had seen a draft of the regulation.</p>
        <p>But environmentalists expressed satisfaction that the requirement remained despite the opposition from industry, which had argued that local governments should bear the responsibility for recycling.</p>
        <p>And agency officials said the plan would cut emissions of toxic substances, would lower the amount of toxic ash that has to be placed in landfills and would advance the Government's goal of reducing the disposal of garbage by 25 percent by 1992. Multibillion-Dollar Investment</p>
        <p>The incinerator industry, which has a multibillion-dollar investment at stake, did not want to be saddled with having to sort garbage to separate glass, metal, plastic, paper and other recyclable materials. Municipalities were concerned that incinerator builders would halt projects if the regulation went into effect, leaving them with no choice but to dump their waste in landfills. About 10 percent of the nation's garbage is burned, but that percentage is expected to rise as new incinerators are built and landfills are closed.</p>
        <p>The industry and municipalities said that although they favor recycling, any Government mandate should be part of broader legislation that addresses the entire solid waste issue, especially regulation of landfills.</p>
        <p>The Federal Office of Management and Budget, which reviews such regulations, shared these concerns. But the office and most of the industry were apparently reassured by the compromises to which the E.P.A. agreed.</p>
        <p>Among these were a provision that gives incinerator operators two more years, until 1994, to show that they are complying with the rule; gives more of the recycling responsibility to municipalities; opens the possibility that the final regulation could call for less than 25 percent recycling, and relaxes the limits on emissions of toxic substances from incinerator smokestacks. No Burning of Batteries</p>
        <p>Under the plan, incinerator operators and municipalities would be responsible for separating recyclable material, either at the plant site or through a community sorting program. The proposal would also prohibit burning car batteries; the agency says this would mean less emission of lead, cadmium and mercury and of gases that contribute to acid rain.</p>
        <p>The recycling plan, which is to go into effect in a year, is part of a broader regulation on incinerator emissions that a Federal court had ordered released for public comment by today. The deadline was a result of a suit brought by the State of New York and the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental group, under which the E.P.A. is required to regulate incinerator emissions. The public has 75 days to comment.</p>
        <p>The regulation says its requirements will be superseded if Congress passes comprehensive legislation on solid waste by 1994. The industry and local governments favor such legislation.</p>
        <p>''The way to solve the big national problem is to go comprehensively,'' said Allen Moore, president of the National Solid Wastes Management Association, which represents many disposal companies. In the meantime, Mr. Moore said, the industry supports the proposed recycling provision.</p>
        <p>But Wheelabrator Technologies Inc., a leading builder of plants that burn waste and generate power, dissented from that view.</p>
        <p>''We believe Federal initiatives to advance recycling are essential,'' said Rodney C. Gilbert, Wheelabrator's president and managing director, ''but we don't believe they have a part or place in an air emissions standard.'' The company is not a member of the solid waste association.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gilbert said his industry should not have to shoulder the burden of recycling when only about 10 percent of the nation's garbage is burned, while the 80 percent that is placed in landfills is under no such mandate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
