<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSH VISIT TODAY GRATIFIES OTTAWA</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="222010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">OTTAWA (CANADA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KAUFMAN, MICHAEL T</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6D8153AF933A25751C0A96F948260" item-length="550" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSH VISIT TODAY GRATIFIES OTTAWA</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL T. KAUFMAN, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KAUFMAN, MICHAEL T</byline>
      <dateline>OTTAWA, Feb. 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Declaring that relations with Washington are as hearty as they have ever been, Canadian officials say they expect them to grow still warmer under the Bush Administration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Declaring that relations with Washington are as hearty as they have ever been, Canadian officials say they expect them to grow still warmer under the Bush Administration.</p>
        <p>Declaring that relations with Washington are as hearty as they have ever been, Canadian officials say they expect them to grow still warmer under the Bush Administration.</p>
        <p>The Canadians say they are confident that President Bush, who is to make a four-hour visit here Friday, will do much more than President Reagan did to reduce border-crossing pollution.</p>
        <p>''Acid rain, that is the only major blemish,'' Donald W. Campbell, the director of the United States Bureau at the Department of External Affairs, said as he reviewed the irritants in what he called an incredibly complex relationship. ''But now, given the comments that President Bush has made and those made by his appointees, we expect that for the first time a U.S. Administration will submit legislation to limit emissions of sulfur dioxide into the atmosphere.''</p>
        <p>In Canada such emissions from power plants and industrial smelters arouse more passion than any other issue. The anger is greatest in the eastern half of the country, where the wind-blown rains have done the most damage by killing life in many lakes, damaging trees and eating away the stone facades of buildings. Canada Reducing Emissions</p>
        <p>At both national and provincial levels, laws have been passed to curb the levels of polluting fallout on a schedule that is to cut two million tons of Canadian-generated emissions each year until 1994. Lucien Bouchard, the Canadian Minister of Environment, says the program is on target.</p>
        <p>Successive Canadian governments have hoped that the United States would pass parallel legislation to force industrial plants, notably those in the Midwest, to reduce the harmful emissions either by shifting to low-sulfur fuels or by introducing expensive scrubbers to filter smokestack exhausts.</p>
        <p>Michael Perley, the director of the Canadian Coalition on Acid Rain, a public interest group, said Washington had effectively ''stalled'' on the issue for eight years under the pretense that it was studying it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perley said he and his group were gratified that even before Mr. Bush's inauguration there were indications that ''his view as more sympathetic to our own.'' Mr. Perley has been publicly citing certain phrases from the President's campaign speeches almost as if to challenge him to live up to his own words.</p>
        <p>''The waiting period for action on acid rain is over, and I - as President - will be ready to move,'' he quoted Mr. Bush as saying in August. Baker's Promise Cited</p>
        <p>Canadian officials who follow events in Washington say they were similarly gratified when Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d promised ''a new approach on acid rain'' during Congressional testimony last month. Similarly they were pleased when William Reilly, the new environmental protection chief, said during his confirmation hearings that legislation on acid rain ''would be first out of the box.''</p>
        <p>Officials at the Department of External Affairs said they did not expect any breakthrough to be announced at meeting between Mr. Bush and Prime Minister Brian Mulroney on Friday, a meeting that Mr. Campbell emphasized would be devoted to setting agendas. It will be Mr. Bush's first foreign trip as President.</p>
        <p>An announcement is expected, however, on an agreement for the exchange of university scholars under the Fulbright program.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
