<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oilfields Scar Arctic Wildlife Refuge Even Now</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="237107"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WILDLIFE SANCTUARIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARCTIC NATIONAL WILDLIFE REFUGE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALASKA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MUSCAT, PAUL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GILSON, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska/Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wildlife Sanctuaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2D71738F937A35757C0A96F948260" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oilfields Scar Arctic Wildlife Refuge Even Now</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>One of the greatest myths perpetuated by the United States oil industry in the debate over future development of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge's coastal plain is that exploitation of Alaska's North Slope petroleum resources has had minimal effect on the area's fragile environment. But the Environmental Protection Agency's draft report on the North Slope contradicts this view (''Oilfield Practices Viewed as Threat to Land in Arctic,'' front page, March 5).</p>
        <p>Simply because of the remoteness of the wildlife refuge, few members of the public or Congress, which will likely vote this year on the fate of these lands, have ever traveled to Prudhoe Bay. We rely on the multimillion-dollar public-relations campaigns of the oil companies to assure us that development is following strict environmental standards. It is not.</p>
        <p>During our third trip to the wildlife refuge last August, we were weathered in at Prudhoe Bay while awaiting a flight to an interior region of the refuge. Unlike politicians who visit the area and who, accompanied by industry officials, are usually whisked by helicopter to the more modern drilling sites off the coast, such as ARCO's Endicott well, we had a firsthand look and self-guided tour of a part of the complex near its heart at Deadhorse, where we flew by 737 from Fairbanks.</p>
        <p>The sheer size of the oilfields is what strikes one first. Visible from the air from 100 miles, the 900-square-mile region is crisscrossed by dozens of airstrips and roads, pipelines and drilling pads. Hundreds of prefabricated buildings are clustered around Deadhorse.</p>
        <p>On the ground, one becomes aware of thousands of vehicles, in use and abandoned, ranging from pickup trucks to massive mobile drilling equipment. Stacks of discarded oil drums, small ponds with greasy slicks and general debris add to the impression the E.P.A. report gives that ''Alaska, which has responsibility for regulating waste management on the North Slope, does not have enough authority or resources to enforce antipollution laws properly.''</p>
        <p>In addition, in and around Deadhorse lie dozens of abandoned structures that once served as hotels, pipeline service companies, travel agencies and general stores. There seems to be no move afoot to remove them or convert them to other uses. Judging from the state of Prudhoe Bay, it would be nearly impossible to restore the region to its pristine state when the oil is depleted, as it will be in the near future. Merely to remove the accumulated vehicles, buildings and drilling equipment from this distant place, not to mention detoxifying the polluted tundra and dismantling the roads, airstrips and pipelines, would take years and hundreds of millions of dollars. Who will pay?</p>
        <p>The Arctic National Wildlife Refuge is a majestic place, truly the last great wilderness in our country, and its Arctic ecosystem is highly sensitive. Unfortunately, we still do not have a comprehensive national energy policy and continue to use fossil fuels at a per capita rate that is far greater than that of any other country on earth.</p>
        <p>The issue of oil exploration and drilling in the last region of the North Slope that is not accessible to the oil companies therefore becomes primarily economic, and the prospects that Congress will protect the area thus seem dim.</p>
        <p>But if drilling is to be allowed, we must learn from the example of Prudhoe Bay, and set strict Federal guidelines, with rigid monitoring, not only for exploration and production, but also for thorough cleanup of the area after its resources have been exploited. If the environmental impact of development is as minimal as the petroleum industry would have us believe, then surely it can shoulder the expense, from its enormous profits, of returning the land to its pristine state.</p>
        <p>If we are to lessen our dependence on foreign energy, as the oil companies patriotically argue in promoting the development of the wildlife refuge lands, we cannot do so at the risk of jeopardizing the future of this beautiful and fragile land in which we, the people of this country, should take pride. The oil will be gone within years; if the land is not zealously protected, the scars it will bear will be permanent. PAUL MUSCAT  MICHAEL GILSON  New York, March 18, 1989</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
