<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Doubts Are Voiced on 'Degradable' Plastic Waste</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="294327"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLASTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LANDFILL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLUSHA, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landfill</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DC1738F936A15753C1A96F948260" item-length="1552" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Doubts Are Voiced on 'Degradable' Plastic Waste</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN HOLUSHA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLUSHA, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: An innovative and widely promoted effort to sell plastic products that are ''degradable'' could be causing more environmental problems than it is solving.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: An innovative and widely promoted effort to sell plastic products that are ''degradable'' could be causing more environmental problems than it is solving.</p>
        <p>An innovative and widely promoted effort to sell plastic products that are ''degradable'' could be causing more environmental problems than it is solving.</p>
        <p>The very ingredients added to make a plastic break down can make it less fit for recycling programs that are far more beneficial, say environmental groups, researchers and some major plastics producers. They also say that many degradable products have little value because disintegration takes place slowly in the oxygen-starved, dry environment of modern landfills. And they note that it is unclear whether the plastic breaks down into elements that are any less harmful than the plastic itself.</p>
        <p>What is more, they say that such products may divert people from participating in fledgling plastic-recycling efforts and encouraging the creation of better recycling technologies and broader programs. Recycling of plastic is far less common than that of aluminum and glass.</p>
        <p>''These plastics are being sold as a way to reduce waste and that is a hoax,'' said Jeanne Wirka, an official of the Environmental Action Foundation, based in Washington, which studies environmental issues. ''The notion is that these things will go away, but very little happens to waste that is entombed in a landfill.''</p>
        <p>''Degradable is a warm and fuzzy word, like organic and natural,'' said Richard A. Denison, a senior scientist at the Environmental Defense Fund, which is based in New York. ''The concern is that if people think you can toss plastic away and it magically disappears, they will just toss it away.''</p>
        <p>Manufacturers in some industries have moved swiftly toward degradable plastic products to reach people worried about the environment and respond to hundreds of legislative proposals nationwide to ban or restrict such goods. Degradable plastic products, which are supposed to break down into their basic components more quickly, now include trash bags, disposable diapers, six-pack rings and sheets used on farms to hold down weeds. What is more, proponents of degradable products have been moving in recent months to promote their use in a broad variety of plastic packaging.</p>
        <p>The Archer-Daniels-Midland Company, for example, raised the anger of environmental groups earlier this year by showing a television commercial that suggested a bin full of plastic containers would simply fade away if treated with the company's biodegrading agents.</p>
        <p>Many of the products are now packaged to emphasize degradability. On boxes of Hefty trash bags, for example, an eagle soars over a tree with the headline word ''Degradable,'' and text on the back says the bags represent ''a step in our commitment to a better environment.''</p>
        <p>The makers of degradable plastic products argue that they help make roadside litter disappear more quickly and certainly cannot hurt in landfills.</p>
        <p>The debate comes as the popularity of plastic products, particularly for consumer goods, continues to grow. In a new report on the use of plastics and waste disposal, the Environmental Action Coalition, a New York-based group, estimated that plastics would constitute 10 percent of municipal solid waste by the end of the century, compared with about 3 percent in 1970. In a survey of supermarkets, it found that 50 percent of all items were packaged entirely in plastic.</p>
        <p>And plastic containers are a disproportionately large disposal problem because of the space they take up in landfills. Estimates are that plastics consume 30 percent of landfill space.</p>
        <p>Plastics-industry officials say the very qualities that have made the materials popular in packaging -light weight, strength and inertness - work against them once a package has been used. A plastic box that held a hamburger for a few minutes can foul the environment for decades after being thrown by the roadside.</p>
        <p>''Plastics are 7 percent of the solid waste stream by weight, 30 percent by volume and 40 to 50 percent of the litter,'' said Anthony E. Redpath, an official of Ecoplastics Ltd., speaking at a recent plastics conference in New York. He noted that in the past the visibility of bottles and cans discarded along roadways caused them to be singled out for new laws requiring deposit-and-return programs, and suggested that plastics might be subject to similar treatment.</p>
        <p>Plastics-industry officials say that more than 350 legislative initiatives have been introduced at the Federal, state and local levels in the last year to curb the use of products like foam hamburger boxes.</p>
        <p>Degradability means that a material decomposes into basic constituents like water and carbon dioxide through some natural process. Because all complex materials will eventually degrade, the term is usually applied to products that have been treated to accelerate breakdown.</p>
        <p>There are two major types of degradable plastic materials. Both operate by breaking down the very long chain molecules that give polymeric plastics their strength.</p>
        <p>Photodegradable materials break down because of the effect of ultraviolet radiation on chemicals that have been blended with the basic plastic resin. Photodegradable products include Hefty and similar trash bags and the plastic rings that hold six-packs of cans.</p>
        <p>Biodegradable plastics are susceptible to attack by microorganisms in the soil through an added organic material, usually corn starch. Biodegradable bags and disposable diapers are available in some areas. Because biodegradables represent a new market for corn products, farm groups and food processors like Archer-Daniels-Midland have been pressing their merits.</p>
        <p>But the plastics industry has said it prefers recycling as the way to reduce waste.</p>
        <p>''Degradable plastic is inherently a less valuable material,'' said Karl Kamena, an official of the Dow Chemical Company. a plastic maker. He said products made from recycled degradable plastic were likely to be weaker and performed less well than those made from virgin chemicals. Most of the major plastics producers have joined an industry group, the Council for Solid Waste Solutions, to promote recycling.</p>
        <p>''Degradability could put a silver bullet in the heart of recycling,'' said Dr. Daryl Ditz, a researcher at the Cornell Waste Management Institute. ''You don't want recycled products breaking down.''</p>
        <p>Plastics are more difficult to recycle than aluminum or glass because they come in a variety of chemical formulations. Under the threat of legislative bans, however, plastics producers have begun to sponsor efforts to sort and recycle some products.</p>
        <p>But degradable products are appealing because they appear to offer an easy way out for the public, Mr. Kamena said. ''Degradability sounds better than recycling because people do not have to do anything,'' he said. ''It puts all the responsibility on the manufacturer.''</p>
        <p>Producers of degradable products defend them as at least a partial answer to garbage and litter problems. ''Is it a perfect solution? No,'' said Rajeev Bal, the president of Webster Industries, which makes Good Sense photodegradable shopping and trash bags. ''But it is better than no solution.''</p>
        <p>Proponents of degradability say the plastic producers simply fear losing part of their market as products that used to be pure plastic are diluted with nonplastic materials like corn starch. ''We can replace 6 percent of plastic'' in thin sheets used in bags ''and up to 20 percent in polystyrene,'' said Jerry L. Petak, an official of Archer-Daniels-Midland. ''No plastic producer will stand for losing 6 to 20 percent of his market.''</p>
        <p>Experts on landfills say the degradability feature could help dispose of roadside litter but has little value in modern landfills because disintegration takes place so slowly. Indeed, officials of the Mobil Corporation, which makes Hefty bags, concede that the bags' degradability will do little to solve the environmental problem of garbage disposal, because most will be buried in landfills soon after use. But they say many customers want them anyway.</p>
        <p>''They may be some help with the litter problem but they are no help with solid waste,'' said Allen Gray, a Mobil spokesman. He added, however, that competing brands had been using degradability to increase sales. ''We are putting them out there because that is what people are buying right now,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Most environmentalists favor recycling over degradation, although at the same time many deplore the shift to plastic containers from glass and aluminum, which are already heavily recycled.</p>
        <p>One important issue concerning degradability, environmentalists say, is just what used plastics degrade into. Biodegradable products based on starch wind up as plastic dust after microorganisms eat the starch. ''I consider this to be a consumer scam,'' said Nancy A. Wolf, executive director of the Environmental Action Coalition. ''People think it becomes soil, but it does not. You end up with shards of plastic.''</p>
        <p>What happens to the little pieces of plastic is not well understood, researchers say. ''We have no good answers,'' said Dr. Ditz of Cornell. ''As the molecules become smaller, they become more mobile. They may migrate or become volatile.'' Other potential dangers of all plastics, environmentalists say, are the release of chemicals used in their preparation, and the escape of toxic coloring agents once the plastic starts to break down.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
