<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Polls Show Contrasts in How Public and E.P.A. View Environment</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="252413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RATINGS AND RATING SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAZARDOUS AND TOXIC SUBSTANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROPER ORGANIZATION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLYMER, ADAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFD91F39F931A15756C0A96F948260" item-length="949" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Polls Show Contrasts in How Public and E.P.A. View Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLYMER, ADAM</byline>
      <dateline>ST. PETERSBURG BEACH, Fla., May 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The American public and the Environmental Protection Agency rank environmental threats quite differently, with the public's fear focused most sharply on hazardous waste sites that the Government views much less seriously, a pair of surveys show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The American public and the Environmental Protection Agency rank environmental threats quite differently, with the public's fear focused most sharply on hazardous waste sites that the Government views much less seriously, a pair of surveys show.</p>
        <p>The American public and the Environmental Protection Agency rank environmental threats quite differently, with the public's fear focused most sharply on hazardous waste sites that the Government views much less seriously, a pair of surveys show.</p>
        <p>Richard N. Baxter, senior vice president of the Roper Organization, reported the findings of surveys by Roper and an internal E.P.A. ranking of environmental hazards, and maintained that public concerns were especially high about hazards that receive great attention on television and in newspapers and magazines.</p>
        <p>For that reason, he predicted that the news coverage of the Exxon Valdez's grounding off Alaska would cause oil spills to advance sharply among public concerns. Oil spills ranked only 18th out of 28 concerns offered the public in a pair of Roper surveys conducted in December 1987 and January 1988, well before the spill in Prince William Sound on March 24.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baxter also said at the 44th annual meeting of the American Association for Public Opinion Research that he expected to see a dramatic advance in concern about the ''greenhouse effect,'' the accumulation of gases in the atmosphere that is regarded as a cause of global warming. The effects ranked very high on the E.P.A.'s lists, but the matter only tied for 23d position among public concerns. Mr. Baxter said the Roper organization would be examining public environmental priorities again next winter. Availability of Information</p>
        <p>Along with his own presentation of the public data and that of the environmental agency, which included a series of assessments of each problem and did not provide numerical rankings as the public findings did, Mr. Baxter offered a discussion of the results written by Frederick W. Allen of the E.P.A.</p>
        <p>Mr. Allen, in an analysis of the two studies written last year, examined reasons for the different sets of ratings. ''The most obvious reason,'' he wrote, ''is that the general public simply does not have all the information that was available to this task force of experts.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Allen, acting deputy director of the agency's regulatory integration division, said, ''People often overestimate the frequency and seriousness of dramatic, sensational, dreaded well-publicized causes of death and underestimate the risks from more familiar, accepted causes that claim lives one by one.'' He also said the public was especially quick to denounce a problem if a scapegoat, such as a polluting company, could be identified.</p>
        <p>The highest public ranking of hazards was given to active and abandoned hazardous waste sites. About as much concern was also shown for workers exposed to toxic substances. Sixty-two percent of the public termed active sites a ''very serious'' problem, 29 percent called them somewhat serious and only 6 percent said they were not too serious or not at all serious. Differences Were Very Small</p>
        <p>The percentages differed by no more than 1 point for the other two toxic issues. The E.P.A. had rated active hazardous waste sites barely in the top half of its list as a cancer risk, as a ''relatively low risk'' for other health problems, ''relatively low'' in ecological effects, and as ''relatively medium'' in other threats to the general welfare.</p>
        <p>The ratings for inactive waste sites differed only slightly; they ranked in the top third for cancer risks and ''relatively medium'' as an ecological threat. Otherwise they were the same as for active sites.</p>
        <p>But the agency's rating for workers being exposed to toxic chemicals was comparable to the public concern. The agency ranked this problem highest on its list as a cancer risk and called it a ''relatively high'' noncancer health risk.</p>
        <p>The differences showed again on the greenhouse effect, which was called ''very serious'' by 33 percent of the public, somewhat serious by 37 percent and not too serious or not at all serious by 17 percent. Risks for the Future</p>
        <p>But the E.P.A. called it a ''relatively high'' risk for ecological damage and relatively high as a threat to the general welfare. The agency called its risks ''potentially very significant,'' but said that ''partly because the risks are in the future and partly because they are difficult to understand, the public is not strongly concerned.''</p>
        <p>That passage was written before last summer's rising concern and publicity over the problem.</p>
        <p>These are the public rankings of various environmental risks with the percentage of the participants in the Roper surveys calling them ''very serious'' listed here in parentheses:  1. Active hazardous waste sites (62%).  2. Abandoned hazardous waste sites (61%).  3. Workers exposed to toxic chemicals (60%).  4. Industrial water pollution (58%).  5. Nuclear accident radiation (58%).  5. Radioactive waste (58%).  7. Underground storage tank leakage (55%).  8. Pesticide harm to farmers (54%).  9. Pesticide residues harming consumers (52%).  10. Industrial accident pollution (51%).  11. Farm runoff pollution (50%).  12. Contaminated tap water (49%).  13. Industrial air pollution (48%).  14. Ozone layer destruction (47%).  14. Contamination of oceans and coastal waters (47%).  16. Water pollution from sewage (45%).  17. Vehicle exhaust air pollution (38%).  17. Oil spills (38%).  19. Acid rain (36%).  20. Water pollution from runoff on city streets (35%).  20. Contaminated and destroyed wetlands (35%).  20. Release of genetically altered materials (35%).  23. Nonhazardous waste sites (33%).  23. The greenhouse effect (33%).  25. Indoor air pollution from cleaners' smoke etc. (26%)  26, X-ray radiation (22%).  27. Indoor radon gas pollution (21%).  28. Microwave oven radiation (14%).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
