<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Europe's Politicians Thinking Green As Concern Grows on Environment</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="239517"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE, WEST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">THATCHER, MARGARET H (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITTERRAND, FRANCOIS (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARKHAM, JAMES M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0D8143DF931A25757C0A96F948260" item-length="1264" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Europe's Politicians Thinking Green As Concern Grows on Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES M. MARKHAM, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARKHAM, JAMES M</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, April 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Across Western Europe, mainstream politicians are scrambling to embrace the cause of the endangered environment as small ecological parties register startling electoral triumphs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Across Western Europe, mainstream politicians are scrambling to embrace the cause of the endangered environment as small ecological parties register startling electoral triumphs.</p>
        <p>Across Western Europe, mainstream politicians are scrambling to embrace the cause of the endangered environment as small ecological parties register startling electoral triumphs.</p>
        <p>Making sharp U-turns, Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher and President Francois Mitterrand - one a Conservative, the other a Socialist - have emphasized that they want to put environmental concerns at the top of their policy agendas.</p>
        <p>The sudden emergence of ''green,'' or environmental, issues - from the dumping of toxic waste to the sinking of a Soviet nuclear submarine off Norway - coincides with a sharp decline in East-West tensions and a shift away from fears about the danger of war in Europe.</p>
        <p>''There's a sea change,'' said Richard Davy of the British research organization Oxford Analytica. ''People are talking quite openly and consciously about global security far more in terms of the ecological threat and economics than in terms of nuclear weapons.'' A Meeting in Paris</p>
        <p>The list of concerns in Western Europe is growing: toxic spills in the Rhine and the North Sea, dying seals and forests, polluted beaches, traffic jams in many capitals, shrinking space to dispose of ordinary garbage and the menace of the ''greenhouse effect,'' the heating up of the atmosphere by chemical pollutants.</p>
        <p>Growing anxiety about an imperiled environment has spurred the 12-nation European Community to take measures on eliminating chemicals that damage the atmosphere's ozone shield and considering tougher measures to cut automobile pollution. Britain and France, which have rather poor records in defending the environment, last month sponsored major international conferences on the issue, and last weekend Green parties from all over Europe gathered in Paris.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitterrand's conversion has occurred as the once-marginal French Green Party, which had been little more than a gadfly, demonstrated in municipal elections last month that it might be able to claim as much as 10 percent of the electorate in national elections. This would put the Greens ahead of both the faltering Communist Party and the far-right National Front.</p>
        <p>In West Germany, the Greens' strong showing in elections in West Berlin in January and Frankfurt last month have obliged the Social Democrats to accept them as coalition partners. With Chancellor Helmut Kohl's ruling Christian Democrats' popularity at its lowest in seven years, politicians in Bonn are talking seriously about a governing coalition of the anti-NATO Greens, the left-of-center Social Democrats and the centrist Free Democrats after the 1990 general elections. Seats in Parliament</p>
        <p>Since 1983, environmentalist parties have won seats in national parliaments in West Germany, Sweden, Austria, the Netherlands, Belgium, Switzerland, Finland, Portugal and Italy, demonstrating that they can pull voters away from traditional left-wing parties but also from the right. Last November, the big Italian Communist Party was stunned when the Greens outpolled it in regional elections in Trentino-Alto Adige.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Thatcher's adoption of the environmental cause has enabled her to soften her image as an uncaring politician solely interested in unleashing the creative energies of capitalism.</p>
        <p>Last month, she was host to a 124-nation conference in London that pondered the threat to the globe's ozone layer, an issue that appears to have personally engaged the Prime Minister, a former research chemist.</p>
        <p>''It's a made-to-measure issue for Mrs. Thatcher, who suffers from a number of perceived personality characteristics that are less than happy ones,'' said Robert Worcester, head of the Mori polling group in London. ''The environment has been rising pretty steadily as one of the most important issues facing Britain today.'' Interest is Rising</p>
        <p>Mr. Worcester said that a recent poll of 2,000 respondents found that 10 percent agreed that environmental policies would be ''crucial'' in determining their votes in June's elections to the European Parliament in Strasbourg. Since December, the number of Britons calling the environment the nation's paramount issue has risen from 5 to 14 percent, he said.</p>
        <p>For long, France's political elite tended to regard passionate concern about the environment as a German problem that blended dangerously with neutralist attitudes on strategic questions. The sinking of the Greenpeace ship Rainbow Warrior in 1985 by French secret service agents stirred little outcry in France, even though a photographer was killed. The ship was involved in protests against French nuclear testing in the South Pacific.</p>
        <p>But the Chernobyl nuclear catastrophe in 1986 marked the beginning of a major shift in French attitudes, one that Mr. Mitterrand and his Prime Minister, Michel Rocard, have sought to exploit. In forming his predominantly Socialist Cabinet last May, Mr. Rocard picked Brice Lalonde, a former Green presidential candidate, as Environment Secretary, a sub-Cabinet post.</p>
        <p>The French Greens have steered clear of the neutralist positions of their German cousins, but they, too, have their greatest pool of supporters among young city dwellers. In the municipal elections, the Greens drew voters from all over the country and not just in eastern France, where several nuclear reactors had already kindled sympathy for their cause.</p>
        <p>In their statements, Mr. Mitterrand and Mr. Rocard have now joined Western Europe's staunchest defenders of the environment. At a French-sponored conference of 24 nations in The Hague last month, they pushed for the creation of an international authority called Globe, whose rules would be enforced by the International Court of Justice.</p>
        <p>''One day there will be 'green helmets' just as today there are 'blue helmets,' with the power to inspect and verify the polluting nature of this or that installation or product,'' Mr. Rocard predicted confidently, referring to the blue-helmeted United Nations peacekeeping forces.</p>
        <p>Within the European Community, however, France remains a stout opponent of adopting stringent emission-control standards for automobiles. Last month, the community executive in Brussels found itself in a bind after ruling that the Netherlands had exceeded the community's norms by introducing tax incentives to encourage the purchase of cars that met tough, American pollution-control standards. Effective as Presssure Groups</p>
        <p>After a meeting of the community's full Cabinet in Brussels, Carlo Ripa di Meana, the commissioner for the environment, announced that the disciplinary measures against the Netherlands had been softened. The dramatic reversal was a reflection of the growing importance of environmental concerns.</p>
        <p>So far, Green parties have been most effective as pressure groups, spurring mainstream parties of the left and the right into action. But in West Germany, the Greens are solidly entrenched at the local and national level and, with a claim on about 7 to 10 percent of the electorate, now have a long shot at getting into the Government.</p>
        <p>A splintering of the political spectrum in West Germany - thanks first to the Greens and now to the emergence of several far-right nationalist formations - has raised the possibility that Mr. Kohl's coalition of Christian Democrats and Free Democrats will lose its majority in the 1990 elections.</p>
        <p>''It could take three parties to form the next coalition, and we could be one of them,'' said Daniel Cohn-Bendit, a Greens leader in Frankfurt. ''All over Europe it is becoming clear that the problems of modernization mean that we need the ecological movement to offer solutions.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
