<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brazil Wants Foreign Aid to Fight Pollution, but No Strings</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="236170"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRAZIL</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKE, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SARNEY, JOSE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890331T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0DA173AF932A05750C0A96F948260" item-length="608" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brazil Wants Foreign Aid to Fight Pollution, but No Strings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKE, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>PORTO VELHO, Brazil, March 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Addressing Brazil's growing environmental problem, President Jose Sarney appealed today for foreign aid, but rejected foreign supervision.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Addressing Brazil's growing environmental problem, President Jose Sarney appealed today for foreign aid, but rejected foreign supervision.</p>
        <p>Addressing Brazil's growing environmental problem, President Jose Sarney appealed today for foreign aid, but rejected foreign supervision.</p>
        <p>Speaking in Brasilia, Mr. Sarney warned his audience, a gathering of Latin American environment ministers, that international concern over the Amazon could lead to ''a return of the time of interventions, to a new colonial system.'' ''Persuasion is giving way to at= ''Persuasion is giving way to attempts at intimidation, to explicit and veiled threats that even question the veiled threats that even question the principle of sovereignty of states,'' he 'Poverty of Pollution'</p>
        <p>At the same time, the President denounced ''the poverty of pollution'' and asked international organizations for new credits for environmental programs in Brazil.</p>
        <p>Brazil's two-track approach was evident today in this Amazonian frontier city during a visit by four American senators concerned about increasing deforestation rates in the Amazon.</p>
        <p>''True inquisitors'' was how Jeronimo Santana, Governor of Rondonia, described to local reporters the senators' fact-finding visit.</p>
        <p>''Daily we are receiving caravans of reporters, photographers, scientists and researchers attracted by the sensationalism of the news of the devastation,'' the Governor complained. Satellite surveys show that about 22 percent of Rondonia has been deforested in the last five years.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, Ernandes Amorim, the Mayor of an agricultural boomtown carved out of the Amazonian forest in the 1980's, suggested in published interviews here that the visiting Americans could more profitably spend their time reforesting Vietnam.</p>
        <p>Asserting that Americans ''burned Vietnam's forests with napalm and other bombs,'' the Mayor of Ariquemes said: ''Now they want to wash their consciences by blocking the development of Brazil, and principally of Rondonia.'' 'Men or Monkeys'</p>
        <p>Today, in a front-page editorial in Estadao, a local newspaper, Mouricio Calixto urged the senators: ''Please state your choice: men or monkeys. Both find the Amazon their natural habitat.''</p>
        <p>Despite the verbal fireworks, Rondonia's Vice Governor, Orestes Muniz, greeted the Americans courteously.</p>
        <p>When Senator Arlen Specter, Republican of Pennsylvania, asked if Brazilian sensitivities over sovereignty rule out international environmental aid, Mr. Muniz responded, ''We need foreign aid.''</p>
        <p>American aid would be welcome in the Amazon for soil surveys, for reforestry projects and for researching medicinal plants, he said.</p>
        <p>Later, Senator John H. Chafee of Rhode Island, ranking Republican on the Environment and Public Works Committee, said that the visiting group, which also includes Senators Steve Symms, Republican of Idaho, and Dale Bumpers, Democrat of Arkansas, recognizes that international environmental cooperation on the Amazon will only be possible if Brazilian feelings of sovereignty are respected. Senator Cites Concern</p>
        <p>Senator Chafee said the group came to the Amazon out of concern that the annual burning of large swathes of the Amazon forest contributes to the ''greenhouse effect.'' According to this theory, carbon dioxide is steadily accumulating in the earth's ozone layer, increasing the risk of global heating in coming years.</p>
        <p>Fires in the Amazon account for about 7 percent of the world's annual carbon dioxide production. The United States contributes another 20 percent, largely through automobile exhaust.</p>
        <p>''We have to do everything we can to straighten out our own act, so we can come to the Brazilians with clean hands,'' said Senator Chafee, who advocates raising automobile fuel efficiency standards in the United States.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
