<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>We Should All Be Driving Electric Cars by Now; Slim-Line Autos</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="312070"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC VEHICLES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D8133FF936A15751C1A96F948260" item-length="329" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>We Should All Be Driving Electric Cars by Now; Slim-Line Autos</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I believe there is a simple way to reduce the problems of highway traffic, our trade imbalance, acid rain and perhaps even the greenhouse effect. Only strong leadership and the innovative qualities that built our country are needed.</p>
        <p>The solution? Limit automobile width to four feet, which is half the present legal allowable width. This, and some gallons of road paint, will double the existing road miles.</p>
        <p>Auto gas consumption at highway speeds is relative to wind resistance, which is proportional to a vehicle's frontal area. Frontal area is more important than streamlining. Halving the frontal area can result in a fourfold savings in fuel.</p>
        <p>A Federal auto width mandate could come into effect in, say, 10 years. Older autos and commercial vehicles, using two lanes, would co-exist with the new passenger cars, and soon there would be few older cars on the road. The average life of a passenger car is only 12 years. Highway congestion would be alleviated. Two-lane roads could even accommodate a narrow passing lane. Four-lane highways would become eight-lane highways.</p>
        <p>Today most families in the United States are small, and most vehicles on our roads are occupied by only one person. With narrower autos we would consume a smaller proportion of the world's resources, import less fuel, cause less air pollution and increase traffic flow. Parking spaces would be almost doubled too.</p>
        <p>There would be no sacrifice of comfort with the new, narrower autos. Physical constraints would naturally limit other dimensions. Many cars, such as the popular British Austin Seven, were four feet or less wide. Single-engine private aircraft have cabins less than four feet wide and seat two abreast.</p>
        <p>By acting right away, we could get the jump on the Japanese and other auto exporters. The United States would be assured the lead, at least for a few years, until other countries could catch up. DEREK VAN LOAN  Mill Valley, Calif., Dec. 8, 1989</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
