<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Watch; Curing the Greenhouse Effect Could Run Into the Trillions</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="302328"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19891119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DF1338F93AA25752C1A96F948260" item-length="1997" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Watch; Curing the Greenhouse Effect Could Run Into the Trillions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER PASSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: World political leaders may be rushing to broad accord on the urgent need to halt global warming, but since the mid-1980's economists have been worrying about the bill. Their misgivings have been deepened by recent estimates of the cost of limiting emissions of carbon dioxide, which is the primary cause of the problem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: World political leaders may be rushing to broad accord on the urgent need to halt global warming, but since the mid-1980's economists have been worrying about the bill. Their misgivings have been deepened by recent estimates of the cost of limiting emissions of carbon dioxide, which is the primary cause of the problem.</p>
        <p>World political leaders may be rushing to broad accord on the urgent need to halt global warming, but since the mid-1980's economists have been worrying about the bill. Their misgivings have been deepened by recent estimates of the cost of limiting emissions of carbon dioxide, which is the primary cause of the problem.</p>
        <p>Economic analysts do not speak with one voice on the issue. But all recent studies, including those carried out by environmentalists, implicitly share one conclusion: unless it proves remarkably easy to adapt technologies that drastically cut the need for oil, natural gas and coal, the price of correcting the carbon dioxide problem will run to trillions of dollars through the next century.</p>
        <p>By one pessimistic but not implausible estimate, the United States' annual cost of holding the line on carbon dioxide production could rival the current level of military spending. Obstacles to Consensus</p>
        <p>Economists also agree that the benefits of reducing carbon dioxide are sure to vary greatly from place to place. That will make it difficult for countries to develop a consensus for a collective response to the problem.</p>
        <p>Carbon dioxide and other pollutants trap infrared radiation from the sun in the earth's atmosphere, in much the same way a greenhouse works.</p>
        <p>Some effort to curb carbon dioxide may eventually prove to be a cost-effective means of coping with the greenhouse effect. But in the near term, most economists conclude, a major effort to limit carbon effluent makes little economic sense unless it can be justified on grounds of energy security or tax revenue. Overwhelmed Natural Processes</p>
        <p>Scientists have long understood that certain trace-gases in the atmosphere efficiently trap solar energy and heat the planet. Some are naturally produced. But many, notably carbon dioxide, methane and chlorofluorocarbons, are also byproducts of modern civilization, and are being spewed out faster than the biosphere can neutralize their effects. It is now generally if not universally believed that a resulting warming effect is overwhelming natural processes that tend to cool the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>How fast the greenhouse gases are heating the air is not known. Neither the heating effect nor the accumulation of carbon dioxide in the air is thought to have direct effects on human health. But there is at least a chance that another century or perhaps less of unchecked accumulation would melt polar ice and alter weather patterns, leading to coastal flooding and radical changes in land fertility patterns.</p>
        <p>For many environmental advocates, those who believe in the ethical obligation to pass on the biosphere intact to future generations, the policy message is clear and simple: move quickly to reduce the production of carbon dioxide, which accounts for about half the greenhouse effect. Using Fear to Get Action</p>
        <p>The cause has drawn support from diverse interests who share what David Harrison of the National Economic Research Associates consulting firm, calls ''the Christmas tree view.'' These groups hope to use greenhouse worries as a lever for everything from promoting nuclear power to tightening automobile mileage regulations.</p>
        <p>This month, all 68 nations taking part in a high-level conference in the Netherlands agreed that carbon dioxide emissions would have to be stabilized.</p>
        <p>Only objections from the United States, the Soviet Union and Japan prevented the conference from endorsing a goal of cutting emissions to 1988 levels by the year 2000. But William Nitze, a State Department official coordinating Bush Administration policy, acknowledges there is now heavy diplomatic pressure for an accord next year. Simulations by Computer</p>
        <p>Greenhouse politics have yet to be influenced by sober economic analysis, however. And while environmental groups would generally be inclined to draw different lessons from a new utility-financed simulation by Alan Manne of Stanford University and Richard Richels of the Electric Power Research Institute, almost everyone agrees that the computer model does illustrate the potential cost dimensions of carbon-dioxide containment.</p>
        <p>The Manne-Richels model compares a hypothetical future of unconstrained carbon dioxide output with one in which carbon emissions are limited to the 1990 rate through 2000 and then gradually cut by 20 percent.</p>
        <p>Even if no technological adaptation to break the link between energy production and fossil fuels proved possible, consumers could muddle through for a while by switching to natural gas, which delivers 70 percent more energy per pound of carbon effluent. But the carbon limit begins to bite deeply around the year 2010.</p>
        <p>With cheap supplies of gas exhausted, the model estimates that a twentyfold increase in the price of coal would be needed to force sufficient changes toward energy conservation. Annual losses in output would reach about 5 percent of national income, or about $500 billion, in the year 2030.</p>
        <p>Optimists, including the economist Irving Mintzer of the World Resources Institute, argue that technological innovations might sharply cut these costs. And the computer model bears him out. Some reasonably priced way of trapping smokestack carbon would reduce the economic impact by one-tenth.</p>
        <p>A low-cost source of electricity from non-carbon fuels, providing solar, nuclear or geothermal energy, would trim it further. Technical change that increased the efficiency of energy use for the entire economy by 1 percent each year at low cost would do yet more. Drop in American Incomes</p>
        <p>But even the happy circumstance of technological victories on every front would still permanently reduce American incomes by about 1 percent, according to the Manne-Richels model. And 1 percent in a $5 trillion economy is a whopping $50 billion a year.</p>
        <p>Other studies suggest that this most optimistic Manne-Richels scenario is too optimistic. William Nordhaus, an economist at Yale University, pegs the cost of containing carbon emissions to 1990 levels at 1 percent to 2 percent of national income by the middle of the next century. A study in progress by the Congressional Budget Office is reportedly yielding numbers in the same range.</p>
        <p>High cost alone need not rule out action, of course, if the alternative is catastrophe. The mere possibility that the greenhouse effect could lead to greater climatic changes in the next 100 years than those experienced in the previous 10,000 might be expected to give even the most detached bean-counters cause to lose sleep.</p>
        <p>But according to Thomas Schelling, an economist at the Kennedy School of Government at Harvard, such projections can be misleading. While climate has not changed rapidly in the last century, both the will and technological ability to adapt to radically different weather obviously has. In 1860, he says, 2 percent of Americans lived outside temperate or subtropical zones. By 1980, the percentage had increased to 22 percent. Adjusting to Climate Changes</p>
        <p>While changes in rainfall, temperature and sea level could be dramatic, there is yet no reason to believe that the process would be completed too quickly to allow evolutionary responses - expanding irrigation, for example, or building dikes. The cost of growing food might conceivably rise by 20 percent, Mr. Schelling speculates. But this loss, he argues, is almost certain to be overwhelmed by a century's worth of improvements in seed strains and growing techniques.</p>
        <p>By the same logic, Mr. Schelling says, the appealing idea of bequeathing the biosphere intact seems arbitrary. The quality of life in 100 years, he suspects, will depend as much or more on the endowment of technology and capital as on the percentage of carbon dioxide in the air. And if money to contain carbon emissions comes out of other investment, future civilizations could be the losers.</p>
        <p>This hardly means that the greenhouse effect can be safely ignored. But it does imply that it should be viewed as a problem in balancing costs against benefits. And here, crude initial estimates suggest that for the next half-century or more it may be cheapest to deal with the effects of global warming rather than the causes.</p>
        <p>For example, according to the Environmental Protection Agency, the cost of protecting America's coastal cities against a three-foot rise in sea level would be $73 billion to $111 billion, a lot of money but not so much compared with the likely cost of prevention.</p>
        <p>A doubling of atmospheric carbon dioxide, likely to occur by the middle of the next century if output is not constrained, would dramatically reduce yields for some crops in some regions. But according to a 1989 study by three Agriculture Department economists, the net losses would be less than one-tenth of 1 percent of income in industrial countries. Argentina and Australia would actually be economic winners, since the likely fall in yields would be smaller than the increases in world prices. Nations Most at Risk</p>
        <p>This illustrates a looming problem in prevention strategies. The benefits from controlling greenhouse gases would be far greater in some countries than in others. Bangladesh, India and the Netherlands are at great risk from coastal flooding. But many countries would be able to expand farming into regions that are now too cold or too dry to support it. And a few, like Saudi Arabia, would lose much of their national income in a successful attempt to curb the use of fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>The costs of carbon conservation would vary enormously. China, for example, is counting on its rich supplies of coal to develop with limited dependence on imported energy and capital.</p>
        <p>Yet without a broad, enforceable agreement on containing carbon, expenditures by individual countries would not pay off. Lester Lave, an economist at Carnegie-Mellon University, argues that an early commitment by the United States to tough carbon standards could lead to the worst of both worlds. ''We pay attention to treaties,'' he says. But big carbon emitters like China and the Soviet Union might ignore their obligations, undermining the whole logic of collective action.''</p>
        <p>Such considerations lead many economists, including Mr. Lave, to counsel waiting until more is known before trying to devise preventative measures. Dan Dudek, an economist for the Environmental Defense Fund, draws a different conclusion. He wants to buy a modest amount of insurance against the small possibility of a true greenhouse effect disaster, some as yet undiscovered ecological effect that is impossible to reverse.</p>
        <p>This is the time, he argues, to experiment with flexible ''emissions-trading'' systems that ''improve the menu of options'' for slowing global warming at minimum cost. Electric utilities might, for example, buy the right to emit carbon from existing emitters, or plant a sufficient number of trees to absorb an equivalent amount of carbon effluent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nordhaus offers a different rationale for action soon. The potential damage from the greenhouse effect has not been pinned down yet, he concludes; but some damage is almost certainly being done. And any sensible approach to balancing costs and benefits in the future will almost certainly involve a limited attempt to control greenhouse gas emissions, along with parallel efforts to sequestor carbon and mitigate the effects of global warming. A Financial Incentive</p>
        <p>A modest tax on greenhouse gases, one targeted at heavily damaging chlorofluorocarbons as well as carbon dioxide, would thus be very likely to increase economic efficiency; it would also give emitters a financial incentive to search for alternative carbon-free technologies. And it could provide billions in taxes to offset the Federal deficit.</p>
        <p>Virtually all economists seem to agree on the need to get beyond what Mr. Lave calls the ''Earth Day come back'' syndrome. The symbol of greenhouse effect, they argue, cannot be allowed to obscure the dimensions of the perplexing, high-stakes problem that lies beneath.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
