<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Cloudy Crystal Balls, Scientists Race to Assess Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="221098"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MODELS (SIMULATIONS)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0D91E3BF934A35751C0A96F948260" item-length="2227" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Cloudy Crystal Balls, Scientists Race to Assess Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: SPURRED by the anxiety of a public suddenly alert to the potential dangers of global warming, a small fraternity of scientists is running a high-stakes race against the environmental clock, trying to predict the precise impact of the greenhouse effect in time to take effective countermeasures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: SPURRED by the anxiety of a public suddenly alert to the potential dangers of global warming, a small fraternity of scientists is running a high-stakes race against the environmental clock, trying to predict the precise impact of the greenhouse effect in time to take effective countermeasures.</p>
        <p>SPURRED by the anxiety of a public suddenly alert to the potential dangers of global warming, a small fraternity of scientists is running a high-stakes race against the environmental clock, trying to predict the precise impact of the greenhouse effect in time to take effective countermeasures.</p>
        <p>Armed with powerful computers, the scientists are using advanced mathematical models - sets of equations that express the physical workings of the atmosphere - to simulate the world's climate under varying conditions. Their findings underlie almost all current forecasts about global warming. But because the evolving art and science of global climate modeling is still so imperfect, it is often a confounding business made all the more frustrating by policy makers' demands for answers.</p>
        <p>The scientists all say with confidence that the greenhouse effect, in which carbon dioxide and other gases combine with water vapor to trap heat inside the earth's atmosphere, is going to make the earth warmer in the decades ahead. They say climatic changes will result with important consequences for life on earth.</p>
        <p>But they cannot prove or agree on how much the earth will warm, or how fast, or how the warming will affect individual countries or regions, or whether it has already begun.</p>
        <p>The reason, climatologists say, is that although the climate models are steadily improving, they are still crude approximations of an atmosphere-ocean system so vast and complex that it nearly defies analysis.</p>
        <p>''They are dirty crystal balls,'' said Stephen H. Schneider, a climatologist at the National Center for Atmospheric Research in Boulder, Colo.</p>
        <p>For instance, widely differing answers emerge from attempts by three of the major models to gauge the effect on the United States of a doubling of greenhouse gases in the atmosphere. Two show an increase in summer rainfall the Southeast, but one shows a decrease. A different two show a drop in rainfall in the Great Plains, while the third shows an increase. Still another combination of two shows an increase of rain in California, while the third indicates a drop.</p>
        <p>This uncertainty intensifies the dilemma faced by scientists and the policy makers they advise. They do not have precise answers about global warming, but if they wait for the answers and they are too long in coming, it will be too late to take effective action.</p>
        <p>At this stage of their evolution, climate models are as much tools for basic learning as they are practical instruments of prediction. Are they any good, then, as guides to public policy?</p>
        <p>The scientists who use the models say yes, because although the models' estimates vary in specifics, they point in the overall direction of change. At the least, they say, the models demonstrate that weather systems everywhere are sensitive to global warming, that disruption is likely and that a range of consequences is possible.</p>
        <p>''There are going to be sizable effects, we know that much,'' said Michael E. Schlesinger of Oregon State University, who heads one of the four teams in the United States that have modeled the global greenhouse effect. A team in Britain's Meteorological</p>
        <p>Office has also done so.</p>
        <p>Many scientists are therefore strongly convinced, despite all the uncertainties, that it would be prudent public policy to reduce the emission of the so-called greenhouse gases, like carbon dioxide, methane, nitrous oxide and chlorofluorocarbons, that are known to have a heat-trapping effect. This is especially so, they say, since such measures as reducing the use of fossil fuels and halting deforestation would bring major long-term environmental benefits whether there is significant global warming or not.</p>
        <p>Perhaps no principle in atmospheric science is more firmly established than that of the greenhouse effect. If fact, the trapping of warmth has been exerting an influence since the earth had an atmosphere. Without it, the planet would be an icy ball devoid of significant life. It is likewise well established that since the start of the industrial revolution, humans have been pouring greenhouse gases into the atmosphere at an increasing rate, virtually insuring that the earth's climate will warm significantly over the next century.</p>
        <p>But beyond these basic propositions, little is certain. Complicating Factors</p>
        <p>How fast will the earth warm and by how much? The climate modelers' latest findings indicate that if, as projected, atmospheric carbon dioxide doubles between now and the second half of the next century, the world's average surface temperature will increase by 2 to 9 degrees Fahrenheit.</p>
        <p>The earth has warmed by about 9 degrees since the last Ice Age.</p>
        <p>But the latest estimates are being questioned as scientists identify a variety of complicating climatic factors that the models do not include.</p>
        <p>Some do not reflect the impact of other greenhouse gases besides carbon dioxide. These include ozone in the lower atmosphere, methane, chlorofluorocarbons and nitrous oxide, all of which are more effective in trapping heat than carbon dioxide. One of the five modeling groups, at NASA's Goddard Institute for Space Studies in New York, has calculated that growing concentrations of these gases could speed up the warming by as much as two decades.</p>
        <p>Modelers think it likely that the melting of glaciers and the expansion of seawater as it is heated will cause ocean levels to rise; that warming will be greatest near the poles; that rainfall patterns will change and that crop zones and natural ecosystems will migrate with the change in climate. 'Putting Numbers on It'</p>
        <p>Apart from these broad considerations, what will be the local impact of global warming in specific countries or their regions? Modelers get different answers to this, and the answers are invariably qualified by ''may'' or ''could.''</p>
        <p>At this stage of the modeling art, climatologists are mostly ''learning about the mechanisms of climate,'' said John F. B. Mitchell of the British team. ''The next stage is putting numbers on it.''</p>
        <p>Some confusion has attended the greenhouse issue since last June, when dramatic testimony before Congress about global warming coincided with the 1988 drought and pushed the issue into the spotlight.</p>
        <p>James E. Hansen, who heads the Goddard team, testified that the global warming trend measured over the last century was consistent with models of the greenhouse effect, and that in his view, the pollution-induced warming was already under way.</p>
        <p>Many of his colleagues decline to go that far. They say that so far, the effects of greenhouse warming would not be large enough to be distinguished with any confidence from those produced by natural variations in the global climate. Last summer's American drought, they say, was most likely a result of natural variation.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hansen says that he has not changed his mind and that, in fact, his group's mathematical model indicates that while natural forces bring on any given drought, heat wave or severe storm, the greenhouse effect is already acting on those natural forces to make such weather extremes more likely. Looking at the Same Data</p>
        <p>Even scientists who disagree with Dr. Hansen on whether greenhouse warming has already arrived agree with him that it should become apparent in the decades just ahead, and that droughts and heat waves will become more probable. It is as if the greenhouse gases are loading nature's dice, Dr. Schneider said.</p>
        <p>In a way, the argument over whether greenhouse warming has arrived illustrates how imprecise and ambiguous the climate models are.</p>
        <p>All the scientists look at the same data, provided by each other's models and by climate records. But some read the data more cautiously than others. ''Different scientists will retain or shed their skepticism in different degrees and at different times,'' Dr. Schneider said.</p>
        <p>Climate models are sets of mathematical equations that express the basic physical principles that govern the workings of the atmosphere. A computer calculates how the basic principles act on such factors as temperature and rainfall over time, under differing conditions. Scientists can insert any set of conditions they like - including any given concentration of greenhouse gases, for example - to see how this causes the scenario to change.</p>
        <p>But no computer now made or likely to be made any time soon can handle the vast number of calculations necessary to simulate the atmosphere's full complexity. Consequently, results are only approximate and can vary from model to model.</p>
        <p>This is especially true of the largest and most sophisticated of the models, called general circulation models, which cover the globe.</p>
        <p>Scientists compromise by making calculations only at widely spaced points that form a three-dimensional grid at and above the earth's surface.</p>
        <p>A typical spacing between grid points is about 300 miles, with the three-dimensional grid reaching to about 20 miles above the earth. Improving the Resolution</p>
        <p>The wide spacing, or coarse ''resolution,'' as scientists call it, means that many important climatic phenomena are not included in the simulation because they are smaller than an individual grid box. Clouds are a prime example. Scientists therefore try to calculate average cloud cover for a given grid box on the basis of its humidity and the buoyant properties of the air within it.</p>
        <p>The coarse resolution means that different models are bound to produce different pictures of climatic change for, say, regions of the United States.</p>
        <p>Climatologists are constantly trying to improve the resolution of the general circulation models. But they are hampered because the finer the model, the more computing time and capacity is required and the more expensive the exercise becomes. To cut the size of the grid squares in half would require a supercomputer to perform eight times as many calculations, said Warren Washington of the National Center for Atmospheric Research, who heads another of the five greenhouse modeling groups.</p>
        <p>''If you want to get down to the Congressional district level,'' he said, noting that politicians have been asking him about the impact of global warming on their constituencies, ''it is eight times eight times eight.'' Other Shortcomings</p>
        <p>The difficulty is expected to ease as computers gain in speed and capacity. But quite apart from the resolution problem, the modelers acknowledge, their models have other shortcomings. Only one model, at Goddard, has tried to take into account the way in which greenhouse gases actually make themselves felt: gradually, over a period of years. The others mostly assume a one-time, massive doubling of the gases, which produces different results.</p>
        <p>Moreover, say those who use the models, they reflect only crudely, or not at all, such factors as soil moisture, sea ice, clouds, volcanic ash in the atmosphere, fluctuating solar radiation, evaporation, forests and the mechanism, called convection, by which moisture is transported upward into the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Nor, many scientists believe, do they include a number of atmospheric interactions, or ''feedbacks,'' that might intensify, lessen, hasten or delay global warming.</p>
        <p>Not least of the effects that are inadequately included in the models, climatologists say, is that of the oceans. ''On our planet, it is the ocean that sets the time scale for the response of the climate system'' to greenhouse warming, Dr. Schlesinger said.</p>
        <p>Through vertical movement of water, the ocean takes heat from the surface down into its interior, and in so doing delays the warming. But most of the models that have so far tried to forecast the rate of global warming take account only of the upper layers of the ocean. Nor, says Dr. Schlesinger, do they adequately account for such factors as horizontal currents or salinity. Hemispheric Variations</p>
        <p>Both at Oregon State and at the Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory at Princeton University, modelers have made some early attempts to include ocean actions more fully.</p>
        <p>Preliminary findings by Dr. Schlesinger's group at Oregon State have shown that the oceans cause a 50- to 60-year delay in warming. Earlier models models had shown the delay to range anywhere from 10 to 100 years. At the Princeton laboratory, Syukuro Manabe and Kirk Bryan have demonstrated what earlier had been only suspected: that because there is more ocean in the Southern Hemisphere, it will warm up more slowly than the Northern Hemisphere. ''We're confident we've got a significant result,'' Dr. Bryan said.</p>
        <p>But no modelers have yet reliably coupled two equally sophisticated general circulation models, one for the atmosphere and one for the ocean, in a synchronized fashion, and used the coupled models to assess the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>''It's likely to take 10 or 20 years before we do that well,'' Dr. Hansen said. And until that happens, modelers say, reliable predictions about the regional effects of global warming are going to be extremely difficult.</p>
        <p>Some climatologists are beginning to talk about merging their efforts to construct one comprehensive model that they hope would eliminate most of the big uncertainties.</p>
        <p>Until such a comprehensive model emerges, they say, greenhouse warming is likely to cause many surprises. ''We can promise change,'' Dr. Schneider said, ''but we can't tell you what in terms of Iowa versus India.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
