<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Summit's Leaders Focus on Debt, Drugs and Ecology</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1989" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="265923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1989"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG ADDICTION AND ABUSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BALANCE OF PAYMENTS AND TRADE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE, EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PARIS (FRANCE)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">GROUP OF SEVEN</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRADY, NICHOLAS F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19890715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DE1231F936A25754C0A96F948260" item-length="1011" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Summit's Leaders Focus on Debt, Drugs and Ecology</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, July 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: When the industrial world's 15th annual economic summit meeting opened today in the Louvre's new gleaming glass pyramid, the leaders talked about the big issues of the day, and they were already making a little progress on Eastern Europe, third world debt and other issues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: When the industrial world's 15th annual economic summit meeting opened today in the Louvre's new gleaming glass pyramid, the leaders talked about the big issues of the day, and they were already making a little progress on Eastern Europe, third world debt and other issues.</p>
        <p>When the industrial world's 15th annual economic summit meeting opened today in the Louvre's new gleaming glass pyramid, the leaders talked about the big issues of the day, and they were already making a little progress on Eastern Europe, third world debt and other issues.</p>
        <p>On the 200th anniversary of the storming of the Bastille, President Bush and the other summit leaders focused for the first time as a group on two rapidly growing problems - the environment and drugs - while they continued their perennial discussions on trade imbalances and inflation.</p>
        <p>Between all the parades, fireworks and lavish feasts celebrating the Bicentennial of the French Revolution, the leaders of the Group of Seven nations - France, West Germany, Britain, Italy, Canada, Japan and the United States - have somehow found time to work toward resolving some of the immense problems facing the world. These were among the developments:</p>
        <p>* The United States and Japan today announced an agreement that seeks to reduce Japan's trade surplus and the American trade deficit, and thereby help ease trade tensions. They agreed to set up talks aimed, among other things, at making it easier for American companies to sell products in Japan.</p>
        <p>* Several officials indicated that the Group of Seven were moving toward establishing a multilateral framework in which Western nations and Japan would provide financial assistance to Eastern Europe to promote democratization and economic growth.</p>
        <p>* The Secretary of the Treasury, Nicholas F. Brady, said several other Group of Seven nations might join Washington in providing a proposed bridge loan of $1 billion or more to help Mexico as it seeks to negotiate a reduction of its debt load. To Discuss and Dissect</p>
        <p>In the three days of nonstop dinners and discussions that the industrial world's leaders have scheduled, they will no doubt fulfill the goals of the economic summit conference: to give the West's leaders the opportunity to calmly discuss and dissect the issues on their mind.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, the summit leaders are scheduled to take up economic policy coordination, the environment and regional conflicts at the Arche de la Defense, a 35-story building built like upside-down U. As they met in the I. M. Pei-designed pyramid, many of the leaders congratulated themselves on the industrial world's strong economic growth and its seven-year economic expansion.</p>
        <p>''We want to recognize the good things that are happening,'' said Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d. ''And we want to make sure, though, that we take notice of the fact that we need further progress on trade, we need to avoid protectionism, we need progress on third world debt. We are going to discuss in greater detail at this summit than we have in the past questions of the environment.'' Conference on Drug Abuse</p>
        <p>Government spokesmen said that, at the leaders' two-hour round-table discussion this afternoon, Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher called for concerted action to fight inflation and to combat drugs, noting the ravages of crack in particular. British officials say they are close to getting Summit leaders to back a proposal to have an international conference in London next year on the menace of drug abuse.</p>
        <p>For his part, President Mitterrand, seeking to be the third world's spokesman at the summit conference, said more must to be done to help the poor nations. He said their economic problems resulted not just from poor economic management, but also from sometimes being shortchanged in their relations with the industrial world.</p>
        <p>Echoing the pleas of many of the third world leaders he invited to the bicentennial, Mr. Mitterrand called for a North-South summit between the industrial world and the third world to discuss debt and development problems. American and British officials object to such a meeting, asserting that more can be done to help the third world on a case-by-case basis than by bundling up the poor nations in a rhetoric-rich meeting with the rich nations. In Poland and Hungary</p>
        <p>In his efforts to spur democracy in Eastern Europe, President Bush, who was in Poland and Hungary earlier this week, has strained to make increasing aid to that region the summit's principal theme. American officials have proposed the industrial nations take a unified approach, but France and West Germany have bridled at the idea. They want to maintain autonomy about the type and amount of aid they give.</p>
        <p>A West German Government spokesman suggested today, however, that the Group of Seven was moving toward a compromise that would set up a multilateral framework to review what individual nations do on providing aid to Eastern Europe, while continuing to allow those nations a good deal of independence on giving aid.</p>
        <p>At a bilateral meeting today, President Bush and Japan's Prime Minister, Sousuke Uno, agreed to set up an American-Japanese study group that will aim to ''identify and solve'' problems in both countries that prevent reduction of their trade imbalances. Seiichi Kondo, Mr. Uno's spokesman, said the group would study how to open up Japan's distribution system to more imported goods and how to increase America's savings rate, which would reduce consumption and imports. Locked in Trade Dispute</p>
        <p>Japan and the United States have been locked in a trade dispute since May, when the Bush Administration, invoking Section 301 of the Trade Act, threatened to order penalities against Japan unless it lowered what American officials said were trade barriers. Under today's agreement, the bilateral group will issue an interim report in the spring of 1990, several months before the deadline by which Washington must decide whether to penalize Japan.</p>
        <p>On environmental issues, one European official said that to protect the ozone layer, the industrial nations would confirm their commitment to slash production of chlorofluorocarbons. Several officials said there would probably be no agreement on reducing carbon dioxide emissions, which many scientists believe has contributed to global warming.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
