<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some View Battle in Snow Country As Turning Point in War Over Fur</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="325908"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFERENDUMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRUELTY TO ANIMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PROFITS (INDUSTRY-WIDE)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ASPEN (COLO)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, DIRK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado/Aspen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fur</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cruelty to Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DF1E3DF931A25751C0A966958260" item-length="1160" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some View Battle in Snow Country As Turning Point in War Over Fur</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIRK JOHNSON, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSON, DIRK</byline>
      <dateline>ASPEN, Colo., Feb. 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: This wealthy resort town, where mink coats are nearly as common as ski poles, has become the symbolic battleground in a broadening debate over the ethics of wearing fur.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: This wealthy resort town, where mink coats are nearly as common as ski poles, has become the symbolic battleground in a broadening debate over the ethics of wearing fur.</p>
        <p>This wealthy resort town, where mink coats are nearly as common as ski poles, has become the symbolic battleground in a broadening debate over the ethics of wearing fur.</p>
        <p>In what animal rights advocates hail as a turning point, and furriers scoff at as a publicity stunt, a referendum on the ballot here Tuesday will ask voters whether to ban the sale of fur.</p>
        <p>''We have the opportunity now to send a shining example to the rest of the world,'' said Katherine Thalberg, the leader of the Aspen Society for Animal Rights. ''We can eliminate a cruel and outmoded trade that has no place here. Other communities will follow. We already have been contacted by many.''</p>
        <p>While Aspen can hardly be considered a barometer of attitudes of those who live or work far from these snowy peaks, there are unmistakable signs that the debate over fur has reached the American mainstream.</p>
        <p>Into the Living Rooms</p>
        <p>Not just clothing designers and actors, but also sports figures, like Tony LaRussa, manager of the Oakland Athletics, have renounced fur. Paul Harvey, the conservative radio commentator, has voiced his opposition to fur. Anti-fur buttons have become commonplace on campuses.</p>
        <p>The notion of animal rights has existed for more than a century, but it has mostly been limited to a small group of political activists and intellectuals. Now the debate over fur has reached living rooms round the country.</p>
        <p>''I defend my right of choice to wear fur,'' said Penny Abrams, dressed in a full-length mink as she strolled about the mall in downtown Aspen. ''But I have a daughter who is a vegetarian. She won't even wear leather or suede.'' In Wisconsin, the state that produces more than 30 percent of the nation's mink pelts, a recent newspaper survey found that 61 percent of those surveyed opposed of killing animals for fur coats.</p>
        <p>Slump in the Industry</p>
        <p>The debate comes against a backdrop of slumping earnings in the fur industry. Fur Vault Inc. on Wednesday sold its retail fur unit to the Jindo Corporation of South Korea. Antonovich Inc. last December filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy. The Evans Fur Company has reported millions of dollars in losses over the last two years.</p>
        <p>While industry spokesmen say the slump has little to do with the animal rights' crusaders - they point instead to mild winters, the 1987 stock market crash and a glut of furs in Europe -they have begun a $2 million advertising campaign defending the wearing of fur.</p>
        <p>The industry, which generated about $2 billion last year, has placed large advertisements in newspapers in New York, Chicago, Los Angeles, San Francisco, Seattle and Phoenix.</p>
        <p>One advertisement declares: ''Today fur. Tomorrow leather. Then wool. Then meat . . . After that, medical research. Even circuses and zoos.'' Where to Draw the Line?  Indeed, some of the anti-fur groups, like People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals and Trans-Species Unlimited, oppose all forms of what they term ''animal exploitation.''</p>
        <p>These groups say they do not condone the scores of acts of vandalism against fur retailers in recent years. But they have endorsed acts of civil disobedience, which have sometimes led to arrests. In some cases, they have blocked the entrance to fur stores, chanted slogans like ''Fur is Murder,'' and confronted passers-by who wore fur.</p>
        <p>But the fur industry faces a potentially far graver threat from a newer foe, the Humane Society, which has hardly been considered extremist.</p>
        <p>''We're considered to be the middle-of-the-road folks in all this,'' said Patricia Ragan, a spokeswoman for the Humane Society. ''And we believe it is simply not right to cause animals to suffer and die for luxury. We're not opposed to killing animals for food or for leather, which is a byproduct of that process. But we think that fur is the logical place to draw the line.''</p>
        <p>The Humane Society has placed an advertisement that features a photograph of the Vogue model Carrae, with the printed words, ''I'd be ashamed to wear fur.'' Underneath the photograph, the advertisement states: ''When you choose to wear fur, animals suffer and die needlessly. It's that simple. Don't wear fur.''</p>
        <p>Turnabout in Europe</p>
        <p>Anti-fur groups hope to achieve the consumer turnabout that has sent sales crashing in many European countries. In the Netherlands, sales of fur have dropped by nearly 90 percent since 1982. In Switzerland and Britain, fur sales have fallen 75 percent in the past five years.</p>
        <p>People in the anti-fur movement say their cause has been helped by a growing concern for environmental matters. It is impossible to be concerned about the air, water and land, they contend, without also being compassionate about the animals that inhabit the earth.</p>
        <p>Fur industry spokesmen say, however, the growth of animal rights groups has resulted from the increasing urbanization of American society.</p>
        <p>''Urban people can't imagine themselves killing something and enjoying it,'' said Janice Henke, a lobbyist for the National Trappers Association. ''What these people don't understand is that animals suffer when they are not harvested. They don't understand the way disease works. They don't understand the prey-predator relationship.''</p>
        <p>How the Harvest Works</p>
        <p>Some facts of the prey-predator relationship are unpleasant.</p>
        <p>About 2 million animals are killed every year for fur clothing. Most wild animals, like coyotes, lynx and sables, are caught by steel leg-hold traps. In some cases, the animal will try to chew off its legs to get away. The steel-jaw trap is outlawed in about 70 countries.</p>
        <p>When the trapper finds the animal, he either shoots it through the brain, or clubs it to death.</p>
        <p>The traps for otters, muskrats, beavers and nutrias are usually placed under water, so the animal drowns within about a minute.</p>
        <p>Most minks and foxes are raised on farms. The minks are killed by being placed in a chamber filled with carbon monoxide or carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>No Federal laws regulate the raising or killing of fur-bearing animals. Every state has an anti-cruelty statute, but such laws are almost exclusively used for household pets or farm livestock.</p>
        <p>Trying to Minimize Stress</p>
        <p>The Fur Farm Animal Welfare Coalition, which represents fur ranchers, has recently established guidelines to promote the humane treatment of animals.</p>
        <p>''You won't get a quality pelt without good care of the animal,'' said Marcia Kelly, a spokesman for the group. ''Ninety percent of the mink and fox raised in this country are getting healthy and suitable nutrition, safe housing, prompt veterinary care and a stress-free environment.''</p>
        <p>In Aspen, merchants are grumbling that fur-wearing tourists might feel unwelcome and decide to vacation elsewhere. Ms. Thalberg, the anti-fur leader, thinks otherwise. ''This issue has brought Aspen more attention than money can buy,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, advertisements have been appearing in newspapers here from a friendly rival up the road: ''Furs are welcome in Vail.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
