<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Loss of Tropical Forests Is Found Much Worse Than Was Thought</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="359667"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WORLD RESOURCES INSTITUTE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DE1731F93BA35755C0A966958260" item-length="1172" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Loss of Tropical Forests Is Found Much Worse Than Was Thought</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Tropical forests, which play a vital role in regulating the global climate, are disappearing much more rapidly than previously estimated, an international research group said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Tropical forests, which play a vital role in regulating the global climate, are disappearing much more rapidly than previously estimated, an international research group said today.</p>
        <p>Tropical forests, which play a vital role in regulating the global climate, are disappearing much more rapidly than previously estimated, an international research group said today.</p>
        <p>Each year recently, 40 million to 50 million acres of tropical forest, an area the size of Washington State, has been vanishing as trees are cut for timber and to clear land for agriculture and other development, the World Resources Institute said in a report. The group said 1.9 billion acres of tropical forest remained.</p>
        <p>The report, ''World Resources 1990-91,'' prepared in collaboration with the United Nations, was described by its authors as the first comprehensive estimate in a decade of tropical-forest losses around the world.</p>
        <p>The rate of loss, measured in most countries in 1987, was nearly 50 percent greater than the last global estimate, prepared by the United Nations Food and Agricultural Organization in 1980, according to the institute.</p>
        <p>''We were startled to uncover this rate of global deforestation,'' said James Gustave Speth, president of the institute, a nonprofit Washington-based research and policy organization that specialized in environmental issues. ''We were saying we were losing the forests at an acre a second, but it is much closer to an acre and a half a second.''</p>
        <p>The disappearance of tropical forests is regarded by environmental experts as one of the most serious global environmental problems. Through photosynthesis, the forests absorb huge quantities of carbon dioxide, the most important of the gases that are accumulating in the atmosphere. Many scientists believe that carbon dioxide, if not kept in check, will cause a significant warming of the earth in the next century, through a process known as the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>From Satellite Data</p>
        <p>The report on forests was based on remote sensing data from National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration and Landsat satellites that was orginally analyzed by each of the affected tropical countries. Dr. Allen L. Hammond, editor in chief of the report, said at a news conference here that for most of the countries the satellite data covered 1987, but for Brazil it covered 1988, since newer data were available for that country.</p>
        <p>He said the estimates of actual forest loss were ''very conservative,'' and that the actually losses probably were considerably higher.</p>
        <p>The group's report said that in nine major tropical countries, the estimates of total annual losses of tropical-forest acreage were about four times as high as estimates from the years 1981 to 1985. The nine countries were Brazil, India, Indonesia, Vietnam, Thailand, the Philippines, Costa Rica, Cameroon and Myanmar (formerly Burma). Dr. Hammond said, however, that in Brazil, the rate of deforestation declined in 1988 from 1987, largely because the levels from the latter year were the highest on record.</p>
        <p>As the tropical forests shrink, their capacity to absorb carbon dioxide declines, hastening the onset and increasing the magnitude of the warming phenomenon. And as the vegetation from the cut forests decays or is burned, it emits more carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>The tropical forests also contain the largest and most diverse populations of plant and animal species of any habitat. As the forests vanish, so do many of these species, many before they ever have been discovered, named and analyzed.</p>
        <p>Tropical forests have infertile soil because most of the nutrients are in the vegetation, not the soil. Thus, when these forests are cleared they tend to regenerate slowly, if at all.</p>
        <p>'An Unparalleled Tragedy'</p>
        <p>''Tropical deforestation is an unparalleled tragedy,'' said Mr. Speth. ''If we don't reverse the trend soon, it will be too late.''</p>
        <p>Senator Patrick Leahy, Democrat of Vermont and chairman of the Senate Agriculture Committee, said in a statement: ''This is the first reliable data we've had on tropical deforestation in 10 years. A situation we knew was bleak is now shown to be truly horrendous.''</p>
        <p>The World Resources Institute report was prepared in collaboration with the United Nations Environment Program and the United Nations Development Program. Joan Martin Brown, special adviser to the executive director of the United Nations Environment Program, said at the news conference that her organization did not have its own capacity to do the kind of research contained in the report.</p>
        <p>Since preagricultural times, the report said, the world has lost about one-fifth of all its forests, from more than 12 billion acres to under 10 billion acres. In the past, most of the losses were in the temperate forests of Europe, Asia and North America. In recent years, however, it is the tropical forests of the developing countries of Latin America, Asia and Africa that have been disappearing most rapidly.</p>
        <p>Forests Without Trees</p>
        <p>Brazil, with the largest remaining tropical forest area, is also experiencing the worst losses - between 12.5 million and 22.5 million acres a year, the report found. Myanamar is losing 1.7 million acres a year, more than 500 times the 1980 estimate by the Food and Agricultural Organization.</p>
        <p>India, according to the data, is losing its forests at a rate of 3.7 million acres a year. Large areas legally designated as forest land ''are already virtually treeless,'' the report said. Indonesia is losing 2.2 million acres a year, and Costa Rica 300,000 acres, both substantially more than the 1980 estimate.</p>
        <p>The problem of deforestation in developing countries ''has been exacerbated by government economic, land tenure and agricultureal policies as well as population pressures, poverty and debt,'' the report said.</p>
        <p>The World Resources report also contains a new index of countries that are the greatest net contributors to the atmosphere of carbon dioxide, chlorofluorcarbons and methane, the major gases contributing to global warming.</p>
        <p>Surprises on List</p>
        <p>The United States and the Soviet Union are the first and second-largest net producers of these greenhouse gases, the report found. It added that if the European Community were considered a single country, it would rank second behind the United States.</p>
        <p>But the next three countries on the index, surprisingly, were developing nations, Brazil, China and India.</p>
        <p>It has been widely believed that the industrialized countries are the main producers of greenhouse gases. But the research group found that the developing countries already account for 45 percent of emissions of these gases, and that their contribution is likely to rise sharply as they consume more energy for industrial development.</p>
        <p>While there is still uncertainty about global warming, Mr. Speth said, the scientific consensus is that ''the risks of global climate change are very real and it would be very shortsighted to conclude otherwise.''</p>
        <p>''The conclusion of the great bulk of credible scientists is that enough is known to act now,'' said Mr. Speth, who was chairman of the Council on Environmental Quality in the Carter Administration. ''It is our view that it is already late.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
