<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q&amp;A</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="319286"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DA1739F930A15752C0A966958260" item-length="456" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q&amp;A</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>Whooping Cranes</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>Whooping Cranes</p>
        <p>Whooping Cranes</p>
        <p>Q.Do whooping cranes really whoop?</p>
        <p>A.''Absolutely,'' said Tom Stehn, a biologist at the Aransas National Wildlife Refuge in Texas, where 145 of the world's 214 known whooping cranes live. ''They make a great big old whooping sound,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Field guides describe the cranes' call as a shrill trumpeting, the National Audubon Society said. One guide transcribed it as ''ker-loo, ker-lee-loo.''</p>
        <p>''They have a huge, long windpipe that curls around like a French horn,'' Mr. Stehn said. ''The call can be heard two miles.''</p>
        <p>Hold Your Breath</p>
        <p>Q.How long can a person hold his breath?</p>
        <p>A.''On average, a healthy young person can hold his breath about three minutes,'' said Dr. John G. Mohler, medical director of the pulmonary physiology laboratory at the University of Southern California School of Medicine. ''With training, that might be extended some,'' he said, but beyond that, a person might start to lose consciousness, because the body does not store a lot of oxygen.</p>
        <p>What triggers breathing is not a lack of oxygen, Dr. Molhler said, but a buildup of carbon dioxide in the bloodstream. ''When the carbon dioxide pressure in the blood gets to 60 to 70 millimeters of mercury,'' he said, ''the need to breathe gets very intense.'' That is because the carbon dioxide triggers breathing centers in the brain, forcing the person to take a breath.</p>
        <p>''When children hyperventilate at the side of a swimming pool, breathing deeply and rapidly for a few minutes, they think they are loading up on oxygen, but they are actually unloading carbon dioxide,'' Dr. Mohler said. They can hold their breath 30 seconds longer, he said, but the danger is that they don't in fact have that extra oxygen. This can cause the brain to malfunction because of low oxygen pressure, he said, so that the person starts breathing water and drowning.</p>
        <p>''The body has no strong sensors for loss of oxygen,'' Dr. Mohler said. In fact, he said, oxygen shortage, or hypoxia, causes a temporary euphoria. That is one reason people feel a ''Rocky Mountain high'' when they first get to the mountains, he said. Temporary euphoria also affected many high-flying pilots in the early days of airborne warfare, before oxygen masks.</p>
        <p>''Trying to push through the 20,000-foot barrier to get above anti-aircraft fire, they became euphoric, started to make bad judgments, became unconscious, crashed and died,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Readers are invited to submit questions about science to Questions, Science Times, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036. Questions of general interest will be answered in this column, but requests for medical advice cannot be honored and unpublished letters cannot be answered individually.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
