<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="324677"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D6113DF93BA35751C0A966958260" item-length="1288" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-19</p>
        <p>Soviet Communist Party leaders agreed to surrender the party's historic monopoly of power and accept a program that recommends the creation of a Western-style presidency and cabinet system of government.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-19</p>
        <p>Soviet Communist Party leaders agreed to surrender the party's historic monopoly of power and accept a program that recommends the creation of a Western-style presidency and cabinet system of government.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-19</p>
        <p>Soviet Communist Party leaders agreed to surrender the party's historic monopoly of power and accept a program that recommends the creation of a Western-style presidency and cabinet system of government.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: The Party of Soviet Communists is not likely to dissolve any time soon. It has deep roots in the Soviet Union's psychology and system of power, a fractured opposition and the strategic prowess of President Gorbachev.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Skepticism in the streets and no excited crowds</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>A sense of wonder in Washington</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>A victory for a faction silenced 70 years ago</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Chinese press is silent on Soviet plan to end Party monopoly</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Kohl to visit Moscow to calm fears of German reunification</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Baker cautions Soviets on further lowering of troop cuts  A13</p>
        <p>Negotiations are to begin on ending curbs on Soviet imports</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>A Romanian pediatric AIDS crisis may be emerging. The problem, concentrated in orphanges and clinics, was spread by an old-fashioned practice of giving blood transfusions to newborn infants.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>W.H.O. team is sent to Romania to assess AIDS cases</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Prague reclaiming its position at center of Europe</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Bonn panel to plan for common currency with east</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Bush sees virtue in cautious approach to Eastern Europe</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Belgrade steps up Army's presence in Kosovo</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Felix Bloch will be dismissed, the State Department announced. Mr. Bloch, a diplomat, had come under Federal investigation last year when officials said he was photographed in the company of a Soviet spy.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The commander of the contras has been removed from his post by younger officers, according to rebel radio reports and American diplomats.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>An aid plan for Panama was passed by Congress. The $42 million package would also lift numerous trade sanctions that had been imposed to pressure General Noriega.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Security tight for Rev. Jackson on arrival in South Africa</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>South Africa Democrats seek a new relevance</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Arabs plan U.N. opposition to Soviet Jewish immigration</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>General accepts cease-fire after victory north of Beirut</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>News analysis: Desert raid had a rare effect</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>China orders students going abroad to pay fees</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>U.S. official urges ''real world'' view of China</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Talks on a joint Korean team for games fail</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A22-27, B8-12, B24</p>
        <p>An Arizona law promoting English as the language ''of all government functions and actions'' was nullified by a Federal judge, who ruled that the state amendment violated free speech rights.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Regulations protecting wetlands were altered by the White House over the objections of the Bush Administration's chief environmental official, Administration officials said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Environmentalists say pact deletes clean air provision</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>An immigration detention policy will be implemented that allows for the detainment of large numbers of Central Americans who cross the border and illegally seek political asylum, the Government announced in a reversal.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Washington at Work: Pat Choate is regarded as Washington's most-feared Japan-basher. He has written a book about the ways in which Japan shapes American trade and economic policies.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Tougher enforcement of child labor laws is vowed</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Reagan court filing clarifies claim of executive privilege</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Bill would overturn Court's rights decisions</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Senate votes education bill with plan for teacher standards</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>Energy Dept. says it still plans to repair nuclear arms plant</p>
        <p>A27</p>
        <p>Coal mining is going high-tech, and the resulting productivity gains are becoming important as the nation uses up its other fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>A euthanasia advocacy group, the Hemlock Society, has been shaken by its founder's decision to leave his wife, who has developed breast cancer.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>First recipient of lung-assist device is dead</p>
        <p>B12</p>
        <p>Antigravity report is challenged</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>Liberal Jewish bimonthly magazine to close</p>
        <p>B24</p>
        <p>REGIONAL</p>
        <p>B1-7</p>
        <p>A stringent Connecticut budget was proposed by Governor O'Neill. The plan would would eliminate 2,000 jobs and borrow against reserve funds, but would not raise taxes.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>A yearlong murder investigation into the killing of a Westchester woman has resulted in the indictment of a 26-year-old teacher, who had been romantically involved with the woman's husband.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>A ban on decorative gold teeth caps was ordered by a Brooklyn high school principal because he believes they do not convey the serious image his students need to be successful in the business world.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Dissension reported on Gotti jury</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Columbia campus split by invitation to rapper</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>New York City accuses Exxon of fraud in spill</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>U.S. judge dismisses challenge to Columbus Center project</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Suspect in four slayings dies in shootout with the police</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Giuliani is sending signals he won't run for Governor</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Macchiarola starts job at Covenant House</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>New Jersey Supreme Court reprimands one of its own</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>NEEDIEST CASES</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DIGEST</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>THE HOME SECTION</p>
        <p>Ralph Lauren's Safari collection</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Cocooning doesn't sell furniture</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Teaching children self-protection</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Close to Home</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Where to Find It</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Currents</p>
        <p>C3</p>
        <p>Home Improvement</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Parent &amp; Child</p>
        <p>C8</p>
        <p>ARTS/ENTERTAINMENT</p>
        <p>Jessica Tandy, at 80, may add an Oscar to her Tonys</p>
        <p>C17</p>
        <p>Words that shook a government</p>
        <p>C17</p>
        <p>Theater: Pearl troupe's ''Medea''</p>
        <p>C15</p>
        <p>Music: The reunited Meters</p>
        <p>C17</p>
        <p>Cannes Chamber Orchestra</p>
        <p>C18</p>
        <p>Dance: Les Ballets Trockadero</p>
        <p>C16</p>
        <p>City Ballet's mixed menu</p>
        <p>C21</p>
        <p>Word and Image: The state of network news</p>
        <p>C22</p>
        <p>CBS and Andy Rooney to discuss statements</p>
        <p>C22</p>
        <p>Book by Don Gifford</p>
        <p>C22</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>Baseball: Commissioner won't overrule a lockout</p>
        <p>D27</p>
        <p>Basketball: Union vs. agents</p>
        <p>D28</p>
        <p>Scoring star at Nazareth High School</p>
        <p>D28</p>
        <p>Column: Vecsey on colleges</p>
        <p>D27</p>
        <p>Football: Coslet wastes no time hiring three assistants</p>
        <p>D29</p>
        <p>Golf: Trevino proves himself on Senior Tour</p>
        <p>D29</p>
        <p>Hockey: Rangers beat Oilers</p>
        <p>D27</p>
        <p>Yachting: Finish line in sight for America's Cup dispute</p>
        <p>D27</p>
        <p>HEALTH</p>
        <p>A seizure drug used by many infants and young children is ineffective and may inhibit intellectual activity, researchers have found.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Changing nutritional needs put elderly at risk</p>
        <p>B13</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>Jimmy Van Heusen, songwriter</p>
        <p>B15</p>
        <p>Nat Wartels, Crown publishing founder</p>
        <p>B15</p>
        <p>S. R. Weiss, leader of Orthodox Jewry</p>
        <p>B15</p>
        <p>EDITORIALS/LETTERS/OP-ED</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>A28</p>
        <p>The third Russian Revolution</p>
        <p>Transforming the Soviet Union</p>
        <p>Too cool on global warming</p>
        <p>Covenant House beyond Ritter</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>A28</p>
        <p>A. M. Rosenthal: Russia and Germany</p>
        <p>A29</p>
        <p>Tom Wicker: No end to the threat</p>
        <p>A29</p>
        <p>James MacGregor Burns: U.S., model for Eastern Europe?</p>
        <p>A29</p>
        <p>Peter Ivan Hoffman: Next, the ''Flee Decade''</p>
        <p>A29</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
