<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Does Holiday Waste Make You Feel Guilty?</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Lifestyle Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="410653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHRISTMAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHRISTMAS TREES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PAPER PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HALL, TRISH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paper and Pulp</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DD1430F930A15751C1A966958260" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Does Holiday Waste Make You Feel Guilty?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRISH HALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HALL, TRISH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's always a little disappointing: the mountain of wildly colored packages trailing streamers turns into a little pile of, well, things. True, the can openers and sweaters and gloves wouldn't have seemed nearly so glamorous if they hadn't been wrapped. But in these days of bulging landfills and global warming, it's hard not to feel a bit guilty about so much packaging, even for Christmas presents.</p>
        <p>The American Paper Institute says it has no statistics on how much wrapping paper Americans rip open every December. But for the earnest souls who tie their newspapers in bundles and wash out their bottles, there are ways to counteract Christmas waste.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's always a little disappointing: the mountain of wildly colored packages trailing streamers turns into a little pile of, well, things. True, the can openers and sweaters and gloves wouldn't have seemed nearly so glamorous if they hadn't been wrapped. But in these days of bulging landfills and global warming, it's hard not to feel a bit guilty about so much packaging, even for Christmas presents.</p>
        <p>The American Paper Institute says it has no statistics on how much wrapping paper Americans rip open every December. But for the earnest souls who tie their newspapers in bundles and wash out their bottles, there are ways to counteract Christmas waste.</p>
        <p>"Most wrapping paper is recyclable," said David Stuck, the manager of the packaging papers division at the institute, which is based in New York. Some exceptions are the wax-coated or foil papers.</p>
        <p>Some highly glossy papers use what's called clay coating, and while they may not seem recyclable to the naked eye, they are, Mr. Stuck said. You local recycling center should be able to tell you if the paper can be reused. The Destination</p>
        <p>So where do these recycled papers end up? At places like Earth Care Paper Company in Madison, Wis., which sells recycled wrapping paper, stationary, greeting cards and other paper products.</p>
        <p>In tune with the growing anxiety over the environment, sales are more than doubling every year, said Julie Biwott, a customer assistant at the company. Recycled wrapping paper, she said, is especially popular this year. "It can be recycled up to seven times," she said.</p>
        <p>What about the Christmas tree? The only thing more depressing than the mountain of waste on Christmas Day is the dying tree, slowly shedding needles.</p>
        <p>There are choices. You can be very, very good and take the tree to a garden center and have it turned into chips, to be used as mulch. And some coastal communities collect Christmas trees after the holidays and use them on beaches to fight erosion.</p>
        <p>Or if you have waited until the last minute to get a tree, consider buying one with balled roots and planting it in the yard when the season is over. (This may require preparing the hole in advance; a garden center can guide you.)</p>
        <p>If you don't have a yard, and you don't want to cart a tree to some tree-starved suburban friend, maybe you should instead choose an indoor plant that can be fetchingly decorated.  Thinking Ahead</p>
        <p>As for the gift-wrapping paper, when presents are unwrapped, carefully remove the tape and save the paper for use next year. Granted, if you are either averse to the wrinkles that remain in used paper or simply not dedicated, organized or storage-rich, those steps might be unappealing. It is ultimately better for the environment, and easier, to use reusable materials -- or, in the jargon of the day, to precycle.</p>
        <p>Packages aren't much of a problem, either, if you redefine appropriate wrapping. Any kind of cloth -- old scarfs lying in a drawer, new towels to be used in the kitchen -- can make decent wrapping. Earth-colored twine, which can be used again, can substitute for ribbons.</p>
        <p>The matter has been thought about at length by Katherine Tiddens, who several weeks ago opened Terra Verde Trading Company, a store on Spring Street in Manhattan, between Crosby and Lafayette Streets, that sells environmentally correct products.</p>
        <p>"I like a beautifully wrapped gift as much as the next person," said Ms. Tiddens, a former freelance editor and researcher who said she has been thinking about the environment since she attended the first Earth Day celebration in 1970, when she was 19 years old. Creativity Is the Key</p>
        <p>She doesn't use or sell wrapping paper in the store. She considered stocking recycled wrapping paper but decided against it, partly because it is not always easy to find a recycling center that will accept it.</p>
        <p>"We get so much paper in our lives that can be used creatively," she said. Magazines, newspapers (especially the comic pages), in fact, all kinds of paper can be used to wrap gifts.</p>
        <p>Even better, she said, is to use materials that have endless lives and can be transmitted from person to person. "I recommend using Japanese furochiki," she said. "They're wonderful rayon cloths that they use to wrap gifts." To make it look gift-like, use a cardboard base for the gift and then wrap.</p>
        <p>Next year Ms. Tiddens plans to buy beautiful boxes that will not have the store's name on them, so they can be used again and again.</p>
        <p>And what about gifts this year for her family and friends? Ms. Tiddens, obviously a person who is capable of planning ahead, said, "I'm using paper from last year."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
