<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. TO BACK FUND TO PROTECT OZONE</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="361484"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DA1E3EF935A25755C0A966958260" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. TO BACK FUND TO PROTECT OZONE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Reversing a policy decision, the White House said today that it would support a new international fund to help poorer countries phase out chemicals that are destroying the earth's ozone layer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Reversing a policy decision, the White House said today that it would support a new international fund to help poorer countries phase out chemicals that are destroying the earth's ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Reversing a policy decision, the White House said today that it would support a new international fund to help poorer countries phase out chemicals that are destroying the earth's ozone layer.</p>
        <p>The new policy removes the last big hurdle to an international agreement for a ban on the chemicals, including chlorofluorocarbons. The accord is expected at a meeting in London next week.</p>
        <p>Bush Administration officials said the United States expected to contribute $20 million to $25 million to the fund, which would total $150 million to $250 million. Today's announcement did not change the expected amount of the American contribution.</p>
        <p>Scientific Findings</p>
        <p>Although the amount of money involved is relatively small, White House officials led by the chief of staff, John H. Sununu, originally opposed setting up a new fund rather than providing the same amount of aid through existing institutions like the World Bank. The White House feared that a new fund would set a precedent for expensive new foreign aid programs on the environment.</p>
        <p>Chlorofluorocarbons and certain other chlorine-containing chemicals produced by industry have been found by scientists to be severely depleting ozone molecules in the upper atmosphere. That ozone shields the earth's surface from excessive ultraviolet radiation from the sun, which can cause skin cancer and cataracts and suppress the immune system in humans; the radiation also damages crops and wildlife.</p>
        <p>The White House has been under heavy domestic and international pressure to reverse its decision. Many other countries have warned that the American opposition to a fund to help the poorer countries could undermine the effort to bar future production of chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>Thatcher Writes Bush</p>
        <p>Last week, for example, Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher of Britain wrote to President Bush urging him to reconsider, Administration officials say. On Tuesday, Mustafa K. Tolba, executive director of the United Nations Environmental Program, called on the United States to provide help to the developing countries. Environmental organizations and even the industries that make and use chlorofluorocarbons, called the original White House decision a mistake and asked for its reversal.</p>
        <p>The House of Representatives has already authorized $30 million to help the developing countries protect the ozone layer. A similar proposal has been introduced in the Senate. Members of Congress from both parties have written to the President urging him to change policy.</p>
        <p>Stephen Hart, a White House spokesman, said today that the change came as result of ''internal Administration discussions.'' Mr. Sununu issued a statement today saying that at the London meeting the United States would propose a new fund, operated and administered by the World Bank, to help the poorer countries phase out chlorofluorocarbon production.</p>
        <p>A U.S. Condition</p>
        <p>But Mr. Sununu's statement said the United States would support the fund only if it was not considered a precedent for dealing with other international aid programs. Mr. Hart said the White House intended to have such a caveat written into any agreement.</p>
        <p>The United States proposal would also build in strict controls to assure that the financial aid is used for its intended purposes.</p>
        <p>A treaty signed in Montreal in 1987 under the auspices of the United Nations Environment Program requires a 50 percent reduction in the production and use of chlorofluorocarbons by the year 2000. But subsequent scientific data on the seriousness of the problem have shown that such a reduction would not be adequate. The United States and most other countries now support a total phaseout by 2000 and sharp reductions in other ozone-depleting chemicals, including methyl chloroform.</p>
        <p>Many developing countries have insisted that they would not be able to phase in substitutes without additional assistance. India and China, two countries with development plans that call for substantially expanded use of the chemicals, have said they will not join a treaty to eliminate the use of the chemicals without substantial new economic and technical help.</p>
        <p>Praise for White House Change</p>
        <p>The change of White House policy was praised today by members of Congress, environmentalists and industry representatives.</p>
        <p>''Hurray for the President,'' said Senator John H. Chafee, Republican of Rhode Island, one of those who wrote to Mr. Bush urging him to reconsider. ''This is a very wise political decision but more than that it is a very wise decision for the future of the world.''</p>
        <p>David D. Doniger, a lawyer and expert on chlorofluorocarbons for the Natural Resources Defense Council, a national environmental group, said of the White House decision: ''They have closed the hole in ozone policy that they opened themselves.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Doniger also complained that the American plan for phasing out chlorofluorocarbons by 2000 was too slow and that members of the European Community had been urging a faster schedule to reflect the gravity of the threat to the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Kevin J. Fay, executive director of the Alliance for Responsible CFC Policy, an association of companies that make and use the chemicals, said, ''Hopefully, with this measure, government, industry and environmental community can move forward with a solution for solving this global problem.''</p>
        <p>On a separate issue involving the global atmosphere, the West German Cabinet on Wednesday decided to reduce that country's carbon dioxide emissions by 25 percent by 2005. West Germany thus is the first major nation to formally adopt a target and timetable for reducing industrial emissions that, many scientists believe, will lead to a warming of the earth.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
