<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spare That Tree or Else</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="372326"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORMAN, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MANES, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">GREEN RAGE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D6173FF93AA15754C0A966958260" item-length="734" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spare That Tree or Else</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES GORMAN; James Gorman's most recent books are ''Digging Dinosaurs,'' written with John Horner, and ''The Man With No Endorphins.''</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GORMAN, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>GREEN RAGE</p>
        <p>Radical Environmentalism and the Unmaking of Civilization.</p>
        <p>By Christopher Manes.</p>
        <p>291 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Little, Brown &amp; Company. $18.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>GREEN RAGE</p>
        <p>Radical Environmentalism and the Unmaking of Civilization.</p>
        <p>By Christopher Manes.</p>
        <p>291 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Little, Brown &amp; Company. $18.95.</p>
        <p>GREEN RAGE</p>
        <p>Radical Environmentalism and the Unmaking of Civilization.</p>
        <p>By Christopher Manes.</p>
        <p>291 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Little, Brown &amp; Company. $18.95.</p>
        <p>In ''The Stones of Florence,'' Mary McCarthy chronicled the birth of the Renaissance and wrote of ''the feeling that a terrible mistake was committed here . . . a mistake that had to do with power and megalomania, or gigantism of the human ego.'' She cites the ''cold, vain stare of Michelangelo's 'David,' in love with his own strength and beauty.'' The members of the environmental group Earth First! would sympathize with Ms. McCarthy's feeling. However, they would date the megalomaniacal mistake earlier - at the very beginning of civilization. Indeed, one of the slogans of Earth First! is ''Back to the Pleistocene!''</p>
        <p>In ''Green Rage,'' Christopher Manes, a law student and Earth First! member who has produced a documentary about the group, writes with unabashed partisanship about radical environmentalists, the activists known for defending the wilderness with such daredevil and often illegal actions as destroying logging machinery and driving spikes into trees so as to shatter loggers' saws. The tone of the book drifts from loud rhetoric to long catalogues of, for instance, the subtleties of environmental politics in Europe. But Mr. Manes does fulfill his central mission: to outline the roots, rationale and methods of radical environmentalism.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Manes describes it, the first premise of Earth First!, and one with which moderate environmentalists would agree, is that the earth is in dire danger: species are becoming extinct at a higher rate than ever before, society is drowning in its own toxic waste and humanity is threatening itself with the greenhouse effect. The second, and far more controversial, premise is that human life is not the highest value on earth. Other life forms and indeed the planet itself -apart from any sustenance or pleasure they may offer our species - are at least as valuable as humans. Thus Dave Foreman, one of the founders of Earth First!, argues that a Gooding's onion, an endangered species in the Gila wilderness of New Mexico, has as much right to live on the planet as he does.</p>
        <p>From these premises Earth Firsters conclude that moderation and compromise have proved useless, that civil disobedience and sometimes even the destruction of property (which they refer to as ''ecotage'') are justified in the defense of the wilderness and that our technological way of life is irredeemably corrupt, unjustifiable and doomed. Mr. Manes writes that ''our culture is lethal.'' He refers to our preoccupation with ''such minor distractions as two world wars, space flight, and the nuclear arms race.'' And he argues for (among other things) an end to commercial logging, the banning of the automobile, the eradication of the multinational corporation and the reduction of the human population.</p>
        <p>Mr. Manes is good at detailing the abuses of logging companies and the United States Forest Service, as well as the occasional successes of radical action. But there are some distressing issues that he raises and fails to resolve, particularly in his treatment of deep ecology, the philosophy espoused by most radical environmentalists. In one case, Mr. Manes briefly refers to statements by some Earth Firsters that both famine in Africa and AIDS might be the inevitable outcomes of ecological imbalance in the human population. Do these statements reflect realism or insensitivity? Are the Earth Firsters in question facing facts or resting complacent in the face of immense human suffering? It is impossible to find out from ''Green Rage'' because Mr. Manes does not explore these particular questions in detail. They are treated almost as asides.</p>
        <p>In any struggle, somebody has to take the extreme position. And one cannot help admiring the courage it takes to dig a trench in a logging road (in Oregon's Siskiyou National Forest), fill it with quick-setting cement and step into it, as a few Earth Firsters once did. But one thing about this group is clear, both from this book and from other sources. It has its own form of arrogance and pride, so much so that the countenance of the David springs to mind once more. Dave Foreman of Earth First! recently described humanity as ''a cancer on nature.'' ''And,'' he said, with his metaphorical sling and rock in hand, ''I am the antibody.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
