<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene;   Penny-Wise On Ozone?</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="353751"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ECONOMIC SCENE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD81231F935A25756C0A966958260" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene;   Penny-Wise On Ozone?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IT was time to ante up last week on the latest global deal to save the ozone layer, and the Bush Administration decided not to play: The White House announced it would not share the cost of weaning poor countries from the use of ozone-depleting chemicals before they became truly addicted. Subsidies to encourage the substitution of nonpolluting gases in air-conditioners, refrigerators and plastic insulation, the Administration suggested, would have to come from the existing resources of the World</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IT was time to ante up last week on the latest global deal to save the ozone layer, and the Bush Administration decided not to play: The White House announced it would not share the cost of weaning poor countries from the use of ozone-depleting chemicals before they became truly addicted. Subsidies to encourage the substitution of nonpolluting gases in air-conditioners, refrigerators and plastic insulation, the Administration suggested, would have to come from the existing resources of the World</p>
        <p>IT was time to ante up last week on the latest global deal to save the ozone layer, and the Bush Administration decided not to play: The White House announced it would not share the cost of weaning poor countries from the use of ozone-depleting chemicals before they became truly addicted. Subsidies to encourage the substitution of nonpolluting gases in air-conditioners, refrigerators and plastic insulation, the Administration suggested, would have to come from the existing resources of the World Bank.</p>
        <p>This decision may not have surprised hard-line ''greens'' who have always interpreted President Bush's efforts to find a middle road to environmental virtue as a rationale for pollution as usual. But it bewildered political operatives who viewed American leadership on ozone as an easy way for the President to win points with folks who reach for their checkbooks whenever they see a picture of a baby seal. Perhaps most important, it confounded policy analysts within the Administration who are eager to apply economic principles to pollution control and thought they had an ally in the White House.</p>
        <p>Chlorofluorocarbons - CFC's for short - are cheap, nontoxic gases that are almost perfect as refrigerants and aerosols. Once released, however, they wreak havoc on the layer of ozone in the upper atmosphere that absorbs much of the ultraviolet radiation from sunlight. Most experts believe that a failure to control the production of CFC's and a few related chemicals would lead to dramatic increases in skin cancer and eye cataracts, as well as disrupting plant life at the base of the aquatic food chain. According to the Environmental Protection Agency, the projected loss of ozone would lead to an extra 170 million cases of cancer by the year 2075 within the United States alone. The estimated cost in medical bills and premature mortality: $3.5 trillion. That is no misprint: $3.5 trillion.</p>
        <p>Happily, though, an ozone fix would be relatively cheap. The E.P.A. estimates that a 50 percent cut in CFC production would eliminate about 95 percent of the damage. And the cost of the switch to less damaging chemicals would run to less than $40 billion. Or perhaps much less: Stephen DeCanio, an economist at the University of California at Santa Barbara, believes that cheaper, more efficient substitutes for CFC's now in the technological pipeline would reduce the cost to about $3 billion.</p>
        <p>That is why the Reagan Administration signed onto the Montreal Protocol in 1987, agreeing to cut CFC use in half by the year 2000. Congress later put teeth into the decision, imposing a tax on CFC's that will encourage recycling and substitution, as well as collecting some $5 billion over the next five years. And this year President Bush went a step further, responding to new evidence of accelerating deterioration of the ozone layer by agreeing in principle to a complete phaseout of CFC's.</p>
        <p>While the industrialized countries all seem prepared to bear the domestic costs of a rapid phaseout of CFC's, two large potential users, China and India, do not. And their failure to go along would undercut the logic of a global agreement. China alone, Mr. DeCanio notes, plans to produce some 300 million refrigerators over the next few decades.</p>
        <p>Consequently, northern Europe has been lobbying hard for a fund to subsidize the transfer of benign refrigeration technologies to the have-nots. And since Washington was asking Americans to spend billions of dollars to rid the country of CFC's, analysts widely assumed the Bush Administration would view its 20 percent slice of a $100 million-a-year carrot as a minuscule price to pay for broad compliance. But something happened to the Administration's position on the way to the latest global forum.</p>
        <p>The least implausible explanation for Mr. Bush's tough line is that he fears the precedent. The $20 million token may be enough to convince the poorest third of the world to forgo CFC's. But delivery might lead to demands for a hundred times that much to reduce the use of fossil fuels that are implicated in global warming. Better, then, to rely on the stick rather than the carrot: The Administration wants to make CFC treaty compliance a condition for receiving loans from the World Bank.</p>
        <p>But even many of the Administration's friends believe the President's advisers are worrying about the wrong precedent. Since Mr. Bush took office, his economists have been urging caution before committing big bucks to solving poorly understood environmental problems. By failing to act decisively when action plainly does make economic sense, the President is in danger of losing the initiative to those who care not a whit about costs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
