<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>6 Environmental Issues In Exxon Proxy Report</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="333155"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHIPS AND SHIPPING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXXON VALDEZ (TANKER)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY REPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALASKA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">EXXON CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SECURITIES AND EXCHANGE COMMISSION (SEC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FOWLER, ELIZABETH M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tankers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900309T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DD1E38F93AA35750C0A966958260" item-length="663" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>6 Environmental Issues In Exxon Proxy Report</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH M. FOWLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FOWLER, ELIZABETH M</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The proxy statement issued by the Exxon Corporation yesterday includes six shareholder proposals addressing environmental concerns, which indicates that the Securities and Exchange Commission approved their inclusion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The proxy statement issued by the Exxon Corporation yesterday includes six shareholder proposals addressing environmental concerns, which indicates that the Securities and Exchange Commission approved their inclusion.</p>
        <p>The proxy statement issued by the Exxon Corporation yesterday includes six shareholder proposals addressing environmental concerns, which indicates that the Securities and Exchange Commission approved their inclusion.</p>
        <p>That means that the management of the company, already beleaguered by bad publicity surrounding some large oil leaks in recent months, will face a debate over its corporate environmental policy at its annual meeting April 25 in Houston.</p>
        <p>At the meeting a year ago, some stockholders angrily asked questions about the company's Valdez oil spill off the coast of Alaska. But this year formal votes will be held on the resolutions, including those inspired by the Valdez Principles, a 10-point agenda that urges corporations in general to take steps like reporting annually on their environmental activities.</p>
        <p>Terms of Other Proposals</p>
        <p>The other proposals call on Exxon to take many steps, ranging from limiting emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases to establishing an environmental committee on its board.</p>
        <p>The company said it opposes all six shareholder proposals. Its proxy statement gives several reasons, one of which is that the board thinks some of the resolutions do not recognize the need to ''balance the environment with important adequate energy resources and stable, healthy economies.''</p>
        <p>The company also said it was preparing a report on its ''past and continuing efforts on environmental protection, health and safety.''</p>
        <p>Even supporters say they doubt the proposals will pass.</p>
        <p>A Trend Seen Forming</p>
        <p>Several experts called environmental proposals the trend of the future and the start of a campaign that will equal in fervor the one that compelled many institutions, as a protest against apartheid, to sell shares in companies that operated in South Africa.</p>
        <p>Lewis Gilbert, long a stockholder advocate, said he would attend the meeting and vote for the proposals. ''I think a great thing has happened,'' he continued. ''A lot of institutional holders have indicated they will vote for the proposals.'' He added that the proposals might persuade many more large pension funds and other institutional holders to ask questions.</p>
        <p>''I say it is their fiduciary duty,'' he said, ''and not many of their representatives have been coming to annual meetings. We support Tim Smith.''</p>
        <p>Institutional Support Seen</p>
        <p>Timothy Smith, executive director of the Interfaith Center on Corporate Responsibility, confirmed that a large number of institutions heavily invested in Exxon stock, like the New York City pension funds and the California state retirement system, would vote in favor of at least some of the environmental proposals on the proxy statement now in the mail to shareholders.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith said that 75 percent of the 25 companies he had asked to approve the Valdez Principles had agreed to do so. He said those companies included Chevron, Texaco, Mobil and Amoco, all oil companies; Union Pacific, a holding company; Waste Management; Aetna, the insurance company, and McDonald's, the fast-food chain.</p>
        <p>Dr. James Post, professor at the Boston University School of Management and an expert on environmental problems, called the proposals ''very reasonable and modest requests.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''I think Exxon's initial positions opposing the proxy proposals are without merit. The attitude casts doubt about the integrity of Exxon's management system.''</p>
        <p>Outside Audit Group Suggested</p>
        <p>Professor Post yesterday suggested the need for an external audit commission. He is a member of such a commission organized in 1981 by former Senator Edmund S. Muskie to monitor Nestle S.A.'s infant formula, about which there were health difficulties in developing countries some years ago.</p>
        <p>''It is called the Nestle Infant Formula Audit Commission,'' Professor Post said. ''It meets quarterly or more often to provide continuing oversight by an outside group. This includes investigating complaints and doing field investigations.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
