<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Outlook at Book Fair: Global and Historical</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="383915"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK FAIRS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LUKAS, J ANTHONY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DA1538F937A2575AC0A966958260" item-length="1736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Outlook at Book Fair: Global and Historical</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By J. Anthony Lukas; J. Anthony Lukas is the author of ''Common Ground: A Turbulent Decade in the Lives of Three American Families,'' which won the Pulitzer Prize for nonfiction in 1985.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LUKAS, J ANTHONY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Like ducks and geese winging across the Long Island marshes, writers and editors are flocking back to their winter roosts. But the sure signal that the book industry has resumed after the summer doldrums will come this Sunday when marketing managers and publicity agents get down to the serious job of selling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Like ducks and geese winging across the Long Island marshes, writers and editors are flocking back to their winter roosts. But the sure signal that the book industry has resumed after the summer doldrums will come this Sunday when marketing managers and publicity agents get down to the serious job of selling.</p>
        <p>Like ducks and geese winging across the Long Island marshes, writers and editors are flocking back to their winter roosts. But the sure signal that the book industry has resumed after the summer doldrums will come this Sunday when marketing managers and publicity agents get down to the serious job of selling.</p>
        <p>That takes place at the 12th annual New York Is Book Country street fair, an event at which publishers traditionally display their wares for the coming season. This year's hoopla is dedicated to the proposition that ''Books Know No Boundaries.''</p>
        <p>That is scarcely titillating news. But its emphasis on the global marketplace is appropriate in a year when many Americans have felt like slightly irrelevant spectators at the great dramas of their time. When a dissident playwright becomes the first freely elected president of Czechoslovakia in half a century; when the former president of Nicaragua, the bane of two American Administrations, ensconces himself in a Wall Streeter's town house to receive a parade of editors eager to bring out his memoirs; when a transforming Soviet leadership authorizes the publication of Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn's ''Gulag Archipelago,'' New York's tight publishing world does well to forswear parochialism.</p>
        <p>But national frontiers are not the only boundaries that hedge us in; we are constrained by time as well as by space. As the British novelist L. P. Hartley put it: ''The past is a foreign country. They do things differently there.''</p>
        <p>So I am pleased to report that while a host of our ablest reporters is harvesting the astonishing news from Central and Eastern Europe, another pack of journalists has quietly been breaching the frontiers of the past.</p>
        <p>Consider this partial list: David Halberstam is writing on America in the 50's; Taylor Branch on the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. and the civil rights movement; Tom Powers on German efforts to build a nuclear bomb during World War II; Robert K. Massie on British-German naval competition early in this century; Jean Strouse on J. P. Morgan and his era; David McCullough on the world of Harry S. Truman; Robert A. Caro on Lyndon B. Johnson; Geoffrey Ward on the Civil War; Richard Reeves on the truncated Administration of John F. Kennedy; Gay Talese on Italian immigration to this country, illuminated by his family's own experience.</p>
        <p>Mr. Talese is scarcely alone in addressing history in a personal vein. Suddenly it seems memoir is one of our most vital genres. A path brilliantly blazed by Frank Conroy and Geoffrey Wolff has been followed of late by Geoffrey's brother, Tobias Wolff, Lance Morrow, John Gregory Dunne, Joyce Johnson, Russell Baker, Carl Bernstein, Jonathan Yardley, John Edgar Wideman, Annie Dillard and others.</p>
        <p>For some reason, my generation of reporters - having earned our spurs in the multiple alarums and excursions of the 60's and 70's - have turned its eyes backward, trying to find out how we all got here.</p>
        <p>In part, this is probably a function of our age - most of us are in our 50's now - a time when many people feel impelled to measure their experience against those who have come before.</p>
        <p>Then, as my friend Nicholas Lemann has pointed out, there is a notion among many journalists - probably exaggerated - that the story on the street is simply not as vivid as it was in the chromatic decades past. The civil rights movement, Vietnam, Watergate, long hot summers in Detroit and Watts, the pyrotechnics of Woodstock and Haight-Ashbury, the trials of the Chicago Seven and Daniel Ellsberg - these were dramatic yarns that seized journalists by the throat in a way that the savings-and-loan crisis and acid rain do not. (Though, as demonstrated in Mr. Lemann's own forthcoming book on migration from the Mississippi Delta to Chicago housing projects, there is still plenty of incendiary tinder to be found in the contemporary lives of ordinary Americans.) Finally, reporters are like tailbacks: they run to daylight. Quick to seize opportunities, they seize opportunities others fail to exploit. Tom Wolfe argued that the New Journalists of the 60's appropriated the techniques of fiction precisely because many academically trained and academically based novelists had forsworn narrative. Similarly, it could be argued that a new generation of academic historians has abdicated the vital narratives of Allan Nevins and Henry Steele Commager for quantitative analyses of census tracts in Worcester, Mass.</p>
        <p>Certainly there are many fine professional historians out there who write old-fashioned narrative with style and brio: Alan Brinkley, James McPherson, Patricia Limerick, Eric Foner, Stephen W. Sears are a few names that come to mind. But much contemporary historiography is uncomfortable with dramatic tales of conflict and sweeping movements for social change, particularly if they focus on the exploits of ''great men.''</p>
        <p>Yet the thirst for narrative - indeed, for the exploits of heroes - is as old as Thucydides and Homer. If historians fail to satisfy it, journalists surely will try.</p>
        <p>My own bewitchment by history goes back 15 years to the spring of 1975 when I went to Boston to research a magazine article on that city's busing struggle set against the background of the Bicentennial celebration of the battles of Concord and Lexington.</p>
        <p>What struck me then was how all the participants in the desegregation fight invoked the past to justify their present actions. White proponents of desegregation called up the liberties for which Americans had spilled their blood 200 years before; blacks invoked Crispus Attucks and other blacks who had died fighting for American independence and, by extension, their own freedom; opponents of busing pictured Federal District Judge Arthur Garrity, who had ordered the busing, as an unelected tyrant, the judicial equivalent of George III.</p>
        <p>As I pondered O'Brien's line to Winston in George Orwell's ''Nineteen Eighty-Four'' - ''Who controls the past controls the future; who controls the present controls the past'' - I began to hunger for history, not as a mere record of past events, but as a way of perceiving the present and guiding the future.</p>
        <p>In the book that I later wrote about Boston - ''Common Ground: A Turbulent Decade in the Lives of Three American Families'' - I found myself insistently tugged back to the earliest roots of that city's struggle. I pursued the story of each family back as far as I could, to 18th-century County Louth for the Irish McGoffs, to Burke County, Ga., in the 1830's for the black Twymons, to Revolutionary Maine for the Yankee Divers.</p>
        <p>My preoccupation with the past led to a good-natured tug-of-war with my strong-willed editor at Alfred A. Knopf Inc., Robert Gottlieb. ''Do we always have to carry everything back to the 18th century?'' he would groan.</p>
        <p>No, I said. I'd try to pare some of it. But one of my principal themes was the burden of history. I didn't believe in fate, certainly not in predestination. But I did believe that the weight of history, the accumulated experience of generations of Irish, blacks and Yankees, nudged the families into conflict with one another.</p>
        <p>''Oh come on!'' Mr. Gottlieb would exclaim. ''My family came off a 19th-century Russian shtetl. What does that have to do with who I am in mid-Manhattan at the end of the 20th century?''</p>
        <p>Opting for a strategic retreat, I conceded that Alfred A. Knopf's distinguished editor in chief, a guiding light of the New York City Ballet, might have severed his last ties with the shtetl. But for the McGoffs, living in an intensely Irish community by Charlestown's docks, or the Twymons, the products of a union between an illiterate Georgia sharecropper and an assimilationist Nova Scotian farmer, the past was more salient. Mr. Gottlieb and I agreed to disagree on that point. But when I chose my next subject I felt the time had come to tackle a work of outright history for the first time.</p>
        <p>The subject I chose was one of those events that once electrified a nation, but has now passed into almost total obscurity: the assassination of the Governor of Idaho, Frank Steunenberg, in 1905. This led to the trial of ''Big Bill'' Haywood for orchestrating the assassination. With Clarence Darrow as defense attorney and Senator William Borah as prosecutor, the trial opened in Boise in the summer of 1907 and was recorded for posterity by half a hundred reporters from all over the country who believed they were covering ''the trial of the century.'' Central to the story is the role of James McParland, the legendary Pinkerton detective, who decades before had infiltrated the Molly Maguires in the Pennsylvania coal fields. His testimony was responsible for sending virtually the entire leadership of the violent ''Mollies'' to the gallows. Now, 30 years later, McParland at age 67 was pitted against one of the most feared and hated labor leaders in the nation, the man who had just formed the ''Wobblies.''</p>
        <p>It is a great drama, which asks big questions about the American experience. I believe that 1905 to 1907 in the Rocky Mountain states was the time and place when this nation came closest to class war. Assassination and bombings were common. Labor and capital glowered at each other across a widening chasm of hatred and suspicion. Federal troops and state militias, private detective armies and vigilante bands were routinely thrown into the struggle. Many of the working class were girding for such a fight. Surely the upper classes desperately feared it, and mobilized to halt the revolution they believed was imminent.</p>
        <p>We know now that neither revolution nor class war took place. But the question that bedevils me is, Why not? My friend David McCullough, one of the finest of all narrative historians, believes that the secret of writing such history is allowing the reader to overcome what he knows now was the outcome and to entertain the notion, if only briefly, that ''it might have turned out differently.'' That requires the author to soak himself in the assumptions of the period he is writing about, until he, too, momentarily forgets how it turned out.</p>
        <p>So while others have been in Bucharest and Leningrad, or tracking Saddam Hussein's legions across the Kuwaiti sands, I have spent the summer in 1905.</p>
        <p>If I came first as a skittish tourist, now I have taken up temporary citizenship there, determined to find out how they did things in that strange land we call the past.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
