<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PERSONAL HEALTH</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="330661"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTHMA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXERCISE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATHLETICS AND SPORTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRODY, JANE E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOYNER-KERSEE, JACKIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOCH, BILL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, KARIN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PERSONAL HEALTH (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">HEALTH PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Asthma</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asthma</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exercise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DE1439F932A35750C0A966958260" item-length="1281" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PERSONAL HEALTH</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jane E. Brody</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRODY, JANE E</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The image of the asthmatic child wheezing on the sidelines, pale and puny, while other children run and jump is fading fast as physicians and patients discover that exercise is not only possible but actually helpful for people with asthma.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The image of the asthmatic child wheezing on the sidelines, pale and puny, while other children run and jump is fading fast as physicians and patients discover that exercise is not only possible but actually helpful for people with asthma.</p>
        <p>The image of the asthmatic child wheezing on the sidelines, pale and puny, while other children run and jump is fading fast as physicians and patients discover that exercise is not only possible but actually helpful for people with asthma.</p>
        <p>The turnabout has been fostered in recent years by a number of world-class athletes who have asthma. Among them are Jackie Joyner-Kersee, the Olympic gold medalist who is widely regarded as the top woman in track and field in the world; Bill Koch, America's top cross-country ski racer; Karin Smith, a four-time Olympian in the javelin throw; Danny Manning, the 1987-88 N.C.A.A. College Basketball Player of the Year, and Nancy Hogshead, the swimmer who won three gold medals and one silver medal in the 1984 Olympics.</p>
        <p>Researchers now realize that exercise can be even more helpful to people with asthma than to those without any respiratory problem. Regular aerobic exercise - the kind that raises the heart rate and can be done continuously - makes the body more efficient in its use of oxygen, enabling it to get by with less.</p>
        <p>As a result of aerobic conditioning, lung capacity increases, the heart can pump more oxygen-containing blood with less effort and the muscles need less oxygen to do the same amount of work.</p>
        <p>In her new book, ''Asthma and Exercise,'' Ms. Hogshead tells her story of triumph despite asthma. The book, written with Gerald S. Couzens, a sports writer, and published by Henry Holt &amp; Company ($19.95) also tells of other champion athletes, all of whom insist that physical fitness has improved their lives as well as their health.</p>
        <p>Athletes with asthma and medical specialists alike have praised the book as helpful in dispelling the myth that people with asthma cannot exercise. Ms. Hogshead and Mr. Couzens present straightforward information about the disease, how it can be managed effectively and how people with asthma, both mild and severe, can exercise safely.</p>
        <p>For years, Ms. Hogshead experienced mysterious breathlessness, frightening coughing fits and occasional blackouts after races and intense workouts. Then a treadmill test revealed that she had exercise-induced bronchospasm, a form of asthma that is provoked by physical exertion. In episodes of asthma, the breathing passages to the lungs go into spasm, narrowing so that adequate air cannot get in or out.</p>
        <p>The American Academy of Allergy and Immunology estimates that 12 to 15 percent of the population shares her problem of exercise-induced asthma, including 40 percent of those with hay-fever-type allergies and 85 percent of those with allergic asthma.</p>
        <p>As in Ms. Hogshead's case, the symptoms of exercise-induced asthma often go unrecognized, particularly if the person has no asthma symptoms at other times. The symptoms can range from mild wheezing and coughing to severe wheezing, coughing, shallow breathing, chest pain and even loss of consciousness.</p>
        <p>The severity of symptoms varies with the person, the temperature and amount of moisture in the air, the presence of other allergic triggers and irritants, such as air pollutants, dust or viral infection, and the type, intensity and duration of exercise.</p>
        <p>The symptoms of exercise-induced asthma rarely appear unless high-intensity activity is continuously maintained for five minutes or longer, the allergy academy said. The symptoms may occur during or immediately after exercise. The most common trigger is rapid breathing of cold, dry air.</p>
        <p>Most people with other forms of asthma are affected by exercise. However, preventive use of medications that keep the airways open and a gradual increase in the intensity and duration of exercise can enable most people with asthma to participate in demanding physical activities.</p>
        <p>Benefits of Exercise</p>
        <p>Dr. Francois Haas, a pulmonary physiologist at New York University Hospital, has shown in preliminary studies that exercise can improve lung function in people with asthma. At the start of an exercise program, the sedentary people with asthma whom he tested experienced a 30 percent drop in lung capacity after exercise. But after three months of regular workouts, lung capacity fell only 10 percent after exercise.</p>
        <p>For a person who was once incapacitated by asthma, especially those who feared that every little exertion would set off an asthma episode, exercise can be a great confidence-builder. It can also provide opportunities for social interactions.</p>
        <p>Sandy Samberg, a physical therapist at New York University Medical Center who participated in Dr. Haas's project and who now runs 10-kilometer races, said that exercise has completely changed her feelings about herself, giving her ''a real sense of accomplishment.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hogshead also describes the experience of Dr. Joseph Nieder, a New York child psychiatrist who has had asthma since he was 3 years old. He said he was an ''asthma cripple'' until his mid-30's when he started running to lose weight. Now a veteran marathoner, he said he runs almost every day because it makes it easier for him to bring up the mucus from his lungs and puts him in a ''good frame of mind,'' which also helps to reduce his asthmatic symptoms.</p>
        <p>But running can be a challenge for a person with asthma, particularly during cold weather or in dry climates. The ideal sport is the one Ms. Hogshead happened to choose: swimming. Swimmers, at least those who swim in pools, breathe warm, moist air, which is least likely to trigger asthma symptoms.</p>
        <p>Exercising With Asthma</p>
        <p>Modern medical treatment and sensible precautions make it possible for people with asthma to exercise safely and enjoyably. Ms. Hogshead acknowledges that many athletes are reluctant to use medications and would rather ''tough it out.'' But this can be a short-sighted and possibly dangerous approach.</p>
        <p>She herself makes certain that before any bout of vigorous exercise she uses an inhaler containing medication that opens the bronchial tubes. Others may need to take daily preventive medication as well. For example, cromolyn sodium (marketed as Intal) lessens the likelihood of an allergy-induced asthma episode by blocking the effects of allergens.</p>
        <p>To counter an asthma episode, a cautious person with asthma always keeps an inhaler handy, especially during exercise. Dr. Nieder always runs with an inhaler clenched in his hand just in case. Unfortunately, many children with exercise-induced asthma are reluctant to use their inhalers at school. A recent study of 20 such children in California revealed that only four used their inhalers regularly before exercise at school.</p>
        <p>When exercising in air that is cool or cold or dry, a person with asthma would be wise to wear a scarf or mask over the nose and mouth to help warm and moisten incoming air.</p>
        <p>Other helpful practices include a slow warm-up, then up to five minutes of maximum exertion followed by a rest. Or try two to three minutes of warm-up, then a brief rest, then more vigorous exercise. After a workout, breathe deeply and slowly and, if necessary, exhale air into a paper bag. Then inhale the same air to increase the level of carbon dioxide, which reduces the risk of bronchial spasm.</p>
        <p>Regular deep-breathing exercises in which the diaphragm does much of the work can significantly increase the amount of air a person with asthma can inhale and exhale. Sit, stand or lie on your back and place the palm of one hand against your stomach between the navel and rib cage. Breathe in deeply, allowing your diaphragm to push your stomach out against your hand. As you exhale, you should feel your stomach go down. Start the exercise by inhaling to a count of four and exhaling to a count of eight. Then gradually increase the count on the exhale.</p>
        <p>HEALTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
