<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="364413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D91E3FF93BA15755C0A966958260" item-length="1376" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-16</p>
        <p>A terrorist was harbored in Hungary in 1979, according to letters and documents produced by Hungary's new Interior Minister. The international terrorist known as Carlos reportedly received asylum from Janos Kadar, the long-time Communist leader.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-16</p>
        <p>A terrorist was harbored in Hungary in 1979, according to letters and documents produced by Hungary's new Interior Minister. The international terrorist known as Carlos reportedly received asylum from Janos Kadar, the long-time Communist leader.</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-16</p>
        <p>A terrorist was harbored in Hungary in 1979, according to letters and documents produced by Hungary's new Interior Minister. The international terrorist known as Carlos reportedly received asylum from Janos Kadar, the long-time Communist leader.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>American opposition to financial aid for the Soviet Union from Western Europe appears to have softened following pressure on the Bush Administration by some NATO allies.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>House approves more assistance for East Europe</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Negotiators fix curbs on armies</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Moscow journal: From Russia with love</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>The residents of Quedlinburg, a small town in East Germany, should be rejoicing that some of its greatest treasures had been found in Texas. But most have more pressing matters on their minds.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Deutsche Bank plans venture in East</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>The earthquake relief effort in Iran has been viewed by President Hashemi Rafsanjani as an opportunity to improve long-strained relations with the U.S. and other Western nations, diplomats said.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Iran's relief society drops estimate of death toll</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>A West German businessman is jailed in sale to Libya</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Destruction of the ozone layer is proceeding even faster than scientists had feared, Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher of Britain warned representatives of more than 100 nations.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>France's far-rightist National Front appears to be setting the country's political agenda. The Socialist Government is pledging a new fight against social inequality and two conservative parties have buried their differences to form an alliance.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Guatemala has been hit by violence and human rights abuses five months before elections. Prominent businessmen, politicians, diplomats and human rights campaigners have been killed or have just disappeared.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Contras yield arms in ceremony</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Communist unrest in the Philippines prompted the Peace Corps to order its 261 volunteers out of the country. Intelligence reports indicated that the volunteers had become targets of Communist insurgents.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>National</p>
        <p>A18-23, B8-9, D21</p>
        <p>A major flaw in the Hubble telescope was found by engineers. It is likely to cripple the ability of the $1.5 billion space observatory to view the depths of the universe for several years.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Two affirmative action programs aimed at increasing minority ownership of broadcast licenses were upheld by the Supreme Court. The ruling affirmed the power of Congress to enact programs that favor blacks and other minorities.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Child abuse victims may be shielded by testifying on closed-circuit television rather than facing their accused assailants in the courtroom, the Supreme Court ruled.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Panel declares child abuse represents ''national emergency''</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Abortions harder to get in rural areas of nation</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Louisiana passes tough law to limit abortions</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Two studies on America's youth paint a portrait of a generation that is indifferent toward public affairs. These members of the ''baby bust'' seem to be rebelling against rebellion.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The star witness in the Barry trial took the stand. Rasheeda Moore spun out a tale of an adulterous two-year relationship with Mayor Barry in which she used drugs with him more than 100 times.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A revolt by Republicans in Congress followed President Bush's decision to renounce his 1988 campaign pledge to oppose new taxes. The White House struggled to contain the political damage.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Economic analysis: Proposal to raise taxes is a huge gamble</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Bush's shift on taxes brings better mood to budget talks</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>A heat wave in the Southwest has driven temperatures to record highs in the 120's and brought life to a slowdown as distant mountains shimmer in the harsh light.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Health agency wants uniform food labels</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Nelson Mandela visited a church in Atlanta, the cradle of the civil rights movement, to listen to the rhythmic preaching that helped fuel that now long-ago struggle.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>De Klerk speaks of a new constitution</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Union head in Alabama race</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Hispanic district in Los Angeles</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Regional</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>A rate increase for cable customers in Manhattan became likely as the Board of Estimate renewed the franchises of the two cable television companies serving the borough until the year 2003.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>New York City may meet a deadline it set two years ago to stop putting children in tawdry welfare hotels. But in rushing to move the children into public housing projects, the city has pitted their families against working-class tenants of those projects.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>It was the last day of the school year at P.S. 94 in the north Bronx. It was a year of enormous change for hundreds of children there, but the school has remained essentially the same as it was last September.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Board of Education gives up power to investigate</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Baruch college is reaccredited</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>New York's Planning Commission ended its 52-year life, approving land-use changes for a raft of projects, from a huge development along the Queens waterfront to a biomedical laboratory in upper Manhattan.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>A factory in Hoboken, N.J., will close. The conglomerate that owns Maxwell House announced that it would phase out its coffee plant, the city's largest industrial employer.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Cuomo rules out action for Adirondack park</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Dinkins seeking to speed $1 billion in taxes</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Zodiac detectives turn to computers and stars</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Four testify on gang terror on night of jogger rape</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>CUNY teacher admits he lied in gun testimony</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Lawyer says Khashoggi backdated papers</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>The Home Section</p>
        <p>Gardens bloom in jars and pots</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Electronics Notebook</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Design conference focuses on children</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Close to Home</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Currents</p>
        <p>C3</p>
        <p>A playground of recycled plastic</p>
        <p>C5</p>
        <p>Parent &amp; Child</p>
        <p>C8</p>
        <p>Colorful couture from Gene Meyer</p>
        <p>C9</p>
        <p>A studio that stars Manhattan</p>
        <p>C10</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>Re-creating black vaudeville</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>A restored Grand Army Plaza</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>Joseph Papp's Festival Latino</p>
        <p>C15</p>
        <p>Music: Tracy Chapman</p>
        <p>C14</p>
        <p>Nascimento and Shorter</p>
        <p>C16</p>
        <p>Torme and Laine</p>
        <p>C16</p>
        <p>Jim Hall, a guitar and friends</p>
        <p>C16</p>
        <p>Word and Image: $12.3 million for two books by Ken Follett</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>On child prodigies</p>
        <p>C17</p>
        <p>Health Pages</p>
        <p>Personal Health</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>Study says short women have higher risk of heart attacks</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>Court rejects disability pay policy</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>Sports</p>
        <p>Baseball: Canseco becomes highest-paid player</p>
        <p>D23</p>
        <p>Mets win again</p>
        <p>D23</p>
        <p>Brewers defeat Yankees</p>
        <p>D24</p>
        <p>White Sox move into first</p>
        <p>D24</p>
        <p>Little to celebrate for Braves</p>
        <p>D24</p>
        <p>Basketball: Nets take Coleman</p>
        <p>D23</p>
        <p>Knicks draft Mustaf</p>
        <p>D25</p>
        <p>Column: Anderson on N.B.A. draft</p>
        <p>D23</p>
        <p>Golf: Trevino's caddie a success</p>
        <p>D26</p>
        <p>Soccer: Italian and Czech heroes</p>
        <p>D25</p>
        <p>Obituaries</p>
        <p>B12</p>
        <p>Kemper Marley Sr., an Arizona rancher and liquor distributor</p>
        <p>Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>The deficit, without pretense</p>
        <p>Squeeze apartheid, not de Klerk</p>
        <p>Last chances in Albany</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Tom Wicker: Revenues, not taxes</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Ronald Steel: Germany in NATO? Not important</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>John Allen Paulos: The S &amp; L tab</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>George Chapline: The folly of mega-science</p>
        <p>A25</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
