<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Eastern L.I. Spots a Dreaded Foe: The Brown Tide Surfaces Again</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="372072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALGAE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCALLOPS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D7123EF93BA15754C0A966958260" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Eastern L.I. Spots a Dreaded Foe: The Brown Tide Surfaces Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
      <dateline>HAMPTON BAYS, L.I. July 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: After a two-year absence, a mysterious algal bloom that devastated the bay scallop industry in eastern Long Island has reappeared.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: After a two-year absence, a mysterious algal bloom that devastated the bay scallop industry in eastern Long Island has reappeared.</p>
        <p>After a two-year absence, a mysterious algal bloom that devastated the bay scallop industry in eastern Long Island has reappeared.</p>
        <p>Suffolk County officials this week reported high concentrations of the algae, a species of microscopic plankton, in Shinnecock and Moriches Bay on the South Shore and in West Neck Bay at Shelter Island.</p>
        <p>The algae is measured in cells per millileter and turns the water brown when concentrations reach 200,000 - thus its popular name, brown tide. The latest reading, on July 12, showed a count of 800,000 in western Shinnecock Bay.</p>
        <p>But concentrations elsewhere have been smaller, and unlike five years ago, when the algae blanketed the open water and cell counts reached 2 million, the problem this summer appears far less pervasive.</p>
        <p>Facing the Unknown</p>
        <p>The large Peconic Bay system, for example, which separates the North and South Forks, has been largely free of the brown tide. Officials believe the outbreak will remain spotty across the East End of Long Island and have seen signs of its decline. Even a modest scallop harvest is expected at the end of the summer.</p>
        <p>But though less severe this year, the problem has nevertheless refocused attention on the search for answers to one of the biggest environmental threats in eastern Long Island, where the open water plays such an important recreational and economic role.</p>
        <p>In addition, the rise and fall of brown tide here has implications for much of the East Coast, where sheltered bays behind barrier beach islands are the typical geography.</p>
        <p>Despite substantial study in the last five years, no one still knows why the brown tide developed in 1985, why it receded the last two summers and why it has now made a comeback.</p>
        <p>''We don't have an answer to the brown tide, but we do have clues,'' said Elizabeth Cosper, a professor at the State University of New York at Stony Brook who is researching the phenomenon. She spoke at a conference here today to discuss early results of a two-year study of brown tide.</p>
        <p>The return of the algae this year is particularly disconcerting because much money has been spent to revive bay scalloping. But so far the blooms have spared reseeded scalloping areas.</p>
        <p>The algae crippled the scallop and shellfish industries in the summers of 1985, 1986 and 1987. In the worst year, 1985, scallop harvests plummeted in value from an annual total of $1.5 million before the brown tide appeared to $1,000. Many other fish and shellfish populations suffered.</p>
        <p>Scientists were astounded by the size of the 1986 bloom. It covered the Peconic Bay system, from Flanders Bay on the west to Gardiners Island on the east. And it extended south to the Shinnecock, Moriches and Great South Bays.</p>
        <p>''I have never seen a bloom that widespread and composed of one single organism,'' said Dr. Bob Nuzzi, chief of the Bureau of Marine Resources of the Suffolk County Department of Health Services. In 1985, brown tide also swept across Narragansett Bay in Rhode Island and Barnegat Bay in southern New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Reseeded Areas Safe, So Far</p>
        <p>The problem is less serious this year. In the one part of the Peconic Bay system that has been tainted by the algae - the small West Neck Bay at Shelter Island - concentrations rose to nearly 600,000 cells per milliliter in early July. But the number has since fallen to 7,000, Dr. Nuzzi said today. In eastern Moriches Bay, concentrations were recorded at 360,000 last Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Speakers at today's conference said it was a good sign that concentrations had declined dramatically in some areas and that the outbreaks were limited geographically.</p>
        <p>''While I'm concerned about where concentrations are getting high, I'm buoyed by the fact the brown tide hasn't hit the reseeded areas'' for scallops, Dr. Nuzzi said.</p>
        <p>Four years of work by Long Island's baymen have been involved in the reseeding. After 1985 there was ''really little hope for the future,'' said Chris Smith, a Cornell Cooperative Extension agent who has helped the baymen reintroduce scallops.</p>
        <p>Indigestible Menace</p>
        <p>Scallops are hurt by brown tides because they apparently cannot digest this plankton species, Aureococcus anophagefferens. In addition, eel grass, a habitat for scallop larvae, can be devastated when the surface is covered by brown tide and no light can penetrate for photosynthesis.</p>
        <p>As a result of reseeding, millions of tiny scallops rest at the bottom of Great Peconic Bay, not a lot by normal standards but far more than anyone could have hoped several years ago, Mr. Smith said. A limited scallop harvest is possible this September and commercial-size harvests in coming years.</p>
        <p>This assumes the brown tide remains quiescent. Results of the two-year brown-tide study, led by the Suffolk County Health Department, are expected in the fall and may offer conclusions about causes of the algae blooms and how they can be avoided.</p>
        <p>Thriving in Stagnant Bays</p>
        <p>So far, research points to a combination of circumstances that foster brown tide. An increase in water salinity brought on by drought may be a precondition; this occurred during the last three blooms. Also, bays that are blocked from ocean currents and thus rarely flushed may be particularly vulnerable. Flanders Bay is one of these.</p>
        <p>The nutrients can come from many sources: effluent from sewage treatment plants or duck farms; fertilizer from farms, homes and golf courses, and other stormwater runoff. Nutrients in acid rain might also be a factor.</p>
        <p>The study is expected to discuss ways to control such nutrients and prevent them from fouling the waters.</p>
        <p>Peconic Bay is ''one of the most pristine estuaries in the Northeast,'' said Patrick G. Halpin, the Suffolk County Executive. ''The test for us is whether the next generation will be able to say the same thing.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
