<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Presses Conferees to Accept Compromise on Clean Air</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="386977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DA1338F934A1575AC0A966958260" item-length="727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Presses Conferees to Accept Compromise on Clean Air</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In what he called an effort to prod lawmakers to enact acceptable clean air legislation this year, President Bush proposed a set of compromise measures today that would lower the costs of the environmental cleanup being considered by Congress.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In what he called an effort to prod lawmakers to enact acceptable clean air legislation this year, President Bush proposed a set of compromise measures today that would lower the costs of the environmental cleanup being considered by Congress.</p>
        <p>In what he called an effort to prod lawmakers to enact acceptable clean air legislation this year, President Bush proposed a set of compromise measures today that would lower the costs of the environmental cleanup being considered by Congress.</p>
        <p>The President has made enactment of a clean air bill the centerpiece of his environmental program. Earlier this year both the Senate and the House adopted legislation to strengthen the clean air law. The two chambers are moving slowly to resolve differences between their bills in conference.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said the White House's proposal, which largely chooses the least costly provisions from each bill, would achieve the same environmental goals while cutting $2 billion to $3 billion a year from the estimated $25-billion-a-year cost of compliance.</p>
        <p>In a letter to members of the conference committee, Mr. Bush said he feared that the prospects for enactment of a stronger clean air law this year were being jeopardized by the slow progress of the conference as well as the costs of the bills' provisions.</p>
        <p>Plea and Hint of a Veto</p>
        <p>''It would be a terrible shame, and a disservice to the American people, if the prospects for cleaner air were to be scuttled because of a continuing impasse in the conference, or inefficient provisions that saddle the American people with additional costs but yield not additional benefits,'' Mr. Bush wrote.</p>
        <p>He did not raise the possibility of a veto in his letter, but the threat appeared implicit in his expressions of dissatisfaction with the pending legislation.</p>
        <p>One White House official who spoke on condition of anonymity said that without the changes proposed by the President, there might not be enough support in the Senate to cut off debate on the conference report and bring it to a vote.</p>
        <p>But members of Congress said they doubted that the White House proposal would have much influence on the legislation.</p>
        <p>Impact Seen as Unlikely</p>
        <p>''We will, of course, give consideration to the President's proposal but, realistically, it is not likely to have much impact,'' said Representative Henry A. Waxman, a California Democrat who is chief author of the House bill.</p>
        <p>Mr. Waxman said Congress had already considered and incorporated many of the proposals made by the President in the legislation Mr. Bush submitted last year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Waxman said all sides were determined to complete work on the clean air legislation before Congress adjourns next month, adding that no prodding from the President was necessary.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's proposal largely selects from provisions already adopted in the Senate or House bills, choosing what the White House describes as the least costly and most efficient option in each case.</p>
        <p>For instance, the President called on the conferees to adopt the House version of new rules for reducing automobile tailpipe emissions, which would require more stringent controls on car exhausts at the end of the decade only if the Environmental Protection Agency deems such controls necessary. The Senate bill would automatically require that more advanced controls be placed on auto tailpipes. One E.P.A. official said that provision could reduce the cost of the bill by $2 billion.</p>
        <p>Elements From Both Versions</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush recommended selected elements of both the House and Senate versions of proposals to require motor vehicles to use cleaner-burning gasoline. He urged adoption of the Senate version that orders nine cities with the dirtiest air to meet minimum pollution standards by requiring the use of passenger cars that burn cleaner fuels. The House version covered more cities, but with different and in some cases less stringent requirements.</p>
        <p>The Bush proposal urged the conferees to adopt the Senate version of provisions to reduce acid rain. Both House and Senate bills would require coal-fired electric power plants to cut emissions of sulfur dioxide by 10 million tons.</p>
        <p>The President urged adopting the Senate proposal for cities that have not yet achieved the smog-reduction requirements of the current clean air law. But the conferees have already accepted the House bill, which would crack down on pollution from smaller factories and businesses other than those that would be controlled under the Senate version. Congressional aides said there was virtually no chance that the agreement would be reversed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
