<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Three Key Economic Issues Undecided as Meeting Ends</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="367681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="THE HOUSTON SUMMIT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENBAUM, DAVID E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDB1E31F931A25754C0A966958260" item-length="1301" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Three Key Economic Issues Undecided as Meeting Ends</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. ROSENBAUM, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENBAUM, DAVID E</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, July 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The leaders of the seven most powerful industrial democracies wrapped up their three-day meeting here today by proclaiming their united goal of fostering worldwide prosperity, but they hardly resolved the three main economic issues that had divided them at the outset.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The leaders of the seven most powerful industrial democracies wrapped up their three-day meeting here today by proclaiming their united goal of fostering worldwide prosperity, but they hardly resolved the three main economic issues that had divided them at the outset.</p>
        <p>The leaders of the seven most powerful industrial democracies wrapped up their three-day meeting here today by proclaiming their united goal of fostering worldwide prosperity, but they hardly resolved the three main economic issues that had divided them at the outset.</p>
        <p>On trade policy, the leaders at the 16th annual economic summit meeting endorsed an ambiguous statement about agriculture subsidies that was finally drafted at 2:30 this morning. It promised to put trade talks back on track, but it allowed all competing sides to assert victory.</p>
        <p>On aid to the Soviet Union, they took the time-honored step of politicians unable to reach consensus: they formed a committee to study the situation.</p>
        <p>Little Movement on Environment</p>
        <p>And on the environment, they agreed that climate change was ''of key importance,'' but they acceded to President Bush and announced no timetable for limiting the emission of gases that might cause global warming.</p>
        <p>In many instances, the final communique presented by President Bush, the host of the meeting, was a masterpiece of euphemism and understatement, as such documents often are. But its language about the changes in Eastern Europe since last year's economic summit meeting was exultant.</p>
        <p>''When people are free to choose,'' it declared in the first paragraph, ''they choose freedom.''</p>
        <p>In his news conference afterward, Mr. Bush said, ''We are united in a common goal to extend to those who seek political and economic freedom a helping hand with our resources, talents and experience.''</p>
        <p>Similar Points Made</p>
        <p>The other leaders made similar points about the group's harmony. Summit meetings, said Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher of Britain, are looked to by people of the world for leadership on the great issues of the times. ''Once again,'' she continued, ''we have provided that leadership.''</p>
        <p>But the comity on the overriding issues of war and peace, democracy and communism, was overshadowed this week by the tensions over the more mundane economic topics that are likely to dominate the alliance in the years ahead.</p>
        <p>The most contentious issue, by far, was the question of farm subsidies, and the final communique gave something to everyone.</p>
        <p>For the United States, it pledged that export subsidies and import protection would be reduced. And it specifically mentioned a proposal by Aart De Zeuuw, the Dutch chairman of the agriculture committee at the international trade talks, that the United States sees as a favorable basis for negotiations.</p>
        <p>Under Mr. De Zeuuw's proposal, separate limits would be negotiated for each specific form of farm subsidy, including export supports.</p>
        <p>Influential Political Force</p>
        <p>For the European countries, where farmers are an especially influential political force, it recognized that ''social and economic conditions'' must be reflected in farm policy and that Government subsidies could be considered as a whole, rather than individually, when the level of protection is measured. The Europeans have been unwilling to make a commitment to reduce their export supports.</p>
        <p>For Japan, the document said farm policy should take into account ''concerns about food security,'' a reference to Japan's prohibition on rice imports.</p>
        <p>Whatever the ambiguity, Mr. Bush succeeded in putting the issue at the top of the international economic agenda, and that could give a political impetus to the current round of international trade talks that are scheduled to end in December.</p>
        <p>The priority Mr. Bush gave to limiting farm supports seemed to surprise most of his counterparts, who tend to view agriculture policy as a matter to be handled by underlings.</p>
        <p>Stifling of Growth Seen</p>
        <p>The President maintained that unless the industrial countries began to limit their support for farmers, which distorts the world market for foods and feed grain, the current round of trade talks would break down. If that happened, Mr. Bush argued, worldwide economic growth would be stifled.</p>
        <p>All seven of the countries here - the United States, Canada, Britain, France, West Germany, Italy and Japan - subsidize farmers in one way or another. The subsidies in Europe and Japan are much more extensive than they are in North America. The United States and Canada find the Europeans' export subsidies the most onerous form of protection because they believe they distort the market the most.</p>
        <p>The Americans maintained that the summit agreement could get deadlocked trade talks restarted when negotiators meet next in Geneva on July 23. Carla A. Hills, the United States trade representative, said she was encouraged by the summit agreement, but she would not go so far as to call it a breakthrough.</p>
        <p>''We gave a tremendous political impetus to the final negotiations of the round,'' Mrs. Hills told reporters. ''We did not come here to negotiate specific words. But we will get on with that on the 23d and put some meat on the bones.''</p>
        <p>Delight Voiced by Europeans</p>
        <p>The Europeans also expressed delight with the outcome. ''It's much better than I had hoped for,'' said Henning Christophersen, the European Community's vice president for economic and financial affairs.</p>
        <p>On aid to the Soviet Union, Mr. Bush got a statement encouraging the steps toward a free market economy being taken by President Mikhail S. Gorbachev.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush maintains that the United States can provide technical assistance to the Soviets but no money so long as the Soviets continue to spend vast sums on their military and on support of Cuba.</p>
        <p>The Allies accepted his proposal for a study of Soviet economic needs under the auspices of the International Monetary Fund and other international economic organization.</p>
        <p>To Reassure Gorbachev</p>
        <p>At his news conference, Mr. Bush said the formation of the study committee was ''not an effort to delay anything,'' and he said he would ''make clear to President Gorbachev that he ought to view this outcome of this summit very positively.''</p>
        <p>Later, the President added, ''I think Mr. Gorbachev understands that at this juncture, sending money from the United States is not in the cards.''</p>
        <p>The summit meeting left other countries free to give aid to the Soviets. That pleased Chancellor Helmut Kohl of West Germany, who has promised more than $3 billion in credits to the Soviet Union and who favors an international commitment of $15 billion. Mr. Kohl is going to Moscow this weekend to meet with Mr. Gorbachev.</p>
        <p>Joint Program Predicted</p>
        <p>''The necessary steps are being initiated in the Soviet Union now,'' Mr. Kohl said at a news conference. ''If this continues by the end of the year, we should be able to achieve a joint Western economic assistance program.''</p>
        <p>Did Mr. Bush agree with that assessment? ''It doesn't work that you have to march in lockstep on all these questions,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush seemed to have won a victory on environmental policy. The leaders rejected a West German proposal, which Mr. Bush opposed but the other leaders supported, that would have set a timetable for limiting the emission of gases that could contribute to global warming. They did approve, with Mr. Bush's support, development of a pilot program to help Brazil preserve its tropical rain forest.</p>
        <p>The leaders also dealt with such areas as third world debt, aid to underdeveloped countries, narcotics control and international money laundering. These were central topics at previous summit meetings, and little new ground was broken this year.</p>
        <p>Bettino Craxi, the former Prime Minister of Italy who heads a United Nations study on underdeveloped countries, was influential in the preparation of the section of the communique dealing with that area.</p>
        <p>It asserted that the industrial countries' commitment to helping Eastern Europe would diminish their support for developing countries elsewhere in the world.</p>
        <p>THE HOUSTON SUMMIT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
