<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene;   What Price Cleaner Air?</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="376322"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PORTNEY, PAUL R</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CLEAN AIR ACT</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DC1E38F936A2575BC0A966958260" item-length="778" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene;   What Price Cleaner Air?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Like purer hearts or thinner thighs, cleaner air is an unalloyed virtue. But like other virtues, cleaner air can only be attained through sacrifice. And according to Paul R. Portney, an environmental economist at Resources for the Future in Washington, Americans may be on the verge of giving up too much for too little: They are not likely to get their money's worth from the sweeping amendments to the Clean Air Act now being cobbled together by</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Like purer hearts or thinner thighs, cleaner air is an unalloyed virtue. But like other virtues, cleaner air can only be attained through sacrifice. And according to Paul R. Portney, an environmental economist at Resources for the Future in Washington, Americans may be on the verge of giving up too much for too little: They are not likely to get their money's worth from the sweeping amendments to the Clean Air Act now being cobbled together by</p>
        <p>Like purer hearts or thinner thighs, cleaner air is an unalloyed virtue. But like other virtues, cleaner air can only be attained through sacrifice. And according to Paul R. Portney, an environmental economist at Resources for the Future in Washington, Americans may be on the verge of giving up too much for too little: They are not likely to get their money's worth from the sweeping amendments to the Clean Air Act now being cobbled together by Congress.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Portney's startling analysis, to be published in the next issue of the American Economic Association's Journal of Economic Perspectives, the amendments will double the current $30 billion cost of the air quality regulation. But the benefits will probably be worth just $14 billion, Mr. Portney concluded. His analysis is all the more depressing because the legislation is the first to draw on the expertise of efficiency-minded economists.</p>
        <p>The first of the three big-ticket items in the clean air package would require coal- and oil-fired power plants to slash emissions of sulfur and nitrogen oxides. The likely bill for antipollution equipment and more expensive fuel: about $4 billion annually. But the benefits should exceed the costs. Mr. Portney reckons that the value in better health and reduced damage to forests, lakes and farms will run about $5 billion.</p>
        <p>Thereafter, however, the economics of the clean air amendments is all downhill. Tougher regulation of urban polluters will cost $19 billion to $22 billion annually. But the benefits, everything from reduced incidence of asthma to increased crop yields downwind, will probably fall in the $4 billion to $12 billion range, Mr. Portney says. The third expensive item, reductions in emissions of 190 cancer-causing industrial chemicals, Mr. Portney estimates, will probably run $6 billion to $10 billion annually. But by Government analysis, the risks from these toxic effluents is much smaller than commonly supposed; lives saved will probably not exceed 500 annually. Valuing these lives at $3 million each, the total benefits will fall short of $2 billion.</p>
        <p>These estimates, Mr. Portney readily acknowledges, are educated guesses. But the guesses, from a variety of sources ranging from the Congressional Office of Technology Assessment to studies commissioned by the Environmental Protection Agency, do apparently represent the state of the scientific art.</p>
        <p>Some environmental advocates - perhaps a majority - deny the relevance of such analysis. Cleaner is better, they insist, no matter what the green-eyeshade types say. But for economists (and those who think like economists), comparisons of costs and benefits must matter in a world of limited resources. An extra billion spent sanitizing the air around oil refineries is a billion less to spend on, say, safer tankers or tastier tomatoes. And if regulation itself breeds inefficiency - if less money spent elsewhere could accomplish the same task -the approach is even more problematic.</p>
        <p>That raises a troubling question. Never have so many smart, free-market-oriented economists been so involved in drafting new environmental rules. If resulting legislation is such a bad deal, why are they now silent?</p>
        <p>One reason is that the free-market enthusiasts within the clean air lobby did win one big victory: Utilities will be allowed to buy and sell rights to pollute, insuring that the polluters who can cut emissions most cheaply will do the cutting.</p>
        <p>This will reduce the acid rain cleanup cost by $2 billion to $3 billion annually, Mr. Portney says. Moreover, ''emissions trading'' on acid rain could serve as the precedent for a least-cost solution for the big kahuna of environmental problems, containment of the ''greenhouse effect'' gases that cause atmospheric warming. But the price of this victory was acquiescence on air toxics regulation, which many environmental economists privately concede will be about as cost-effective as the Pentagon's $600 toilet seats.</p>
        <p>The other bargain for silence cannot be rationalized so high-mindedly. President Bush's economic advisers have long been unhappy with the urban air quality amendments as well as the air toxics provisions; the former, it is argued, would effectively force the whole country to use expensive emission controls that make sense only for the dozen most heavily polluted cities.</p>
        <p>But the self-proclaimed environmental President seems readier to settle for a wasteful bill than to share the blame for a legislative deadlock. And the pinchpennies in the budget office, who might have been expected to stiffen Mr. Bush's spine, seem unconcerned because Washington won't foot the bill. Consumers will.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
