<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush's 'Whitewash Effect' on Warming</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="331441"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUNUNU, JOHN H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHEUER, JAMES H (REPR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900303T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDB123EF930A35750C0A966958260" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush's 'Whitewash Effect' on Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By James H. Scheuer; James H. Scheuer, Democrat of New York, is chairman of the House Subcommittee on the Environment.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHEUER, JAMES H (REPR)</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In his recent speech to the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, President Bush, who promised in his campaign to use the ''White House effect'' to counter the ''greenhouse effect,'' delivered the ''whitewash effect'' instead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In his recent speech to the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, President Bush, who promised in his campaign to use the ''White House effect'' to counter the ''greenhouse effect,'' delivered the ''whitewash effect'' instead.</p>
        <p>In his recent speech to the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, President Bush, who promised in his campaign to use the ''White House effect'' to counter the ''greenhouse effect,'' delivered the ''whitewash effect'' instead.</p>
        <p>Coming in the wake of the Hague conference, in which the U.S. was virtually alone in opposing proposals to cut emissions of gases that cause global warming, the speech was another example of his abdication of global leadership on the environment.</p>
        <p>His top advisers reportedly were unanimous in urging him to take action to reduce emissions. They included William Reilly, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency; James Watkins, Secretary of Energy; Secretary of State James Baker, and the science adviser, Dr. D. Allan Bromley.</p>
        <p>Such unanimity is astonishing: for years, the Energy Department fought to protect the U.S. fossil fuel industry from E.P.A. forays. But this hard-won unanimity was overturned by the White House chief of staff, John Sununu, whose supposed qualification is a mechanical engineering degree.</p>
        <p>Attacking ''faceless bureaucrats'' for trying to ''create a policy in this country that cuts off our use of coal, oil and natural gas,'' Mr. Sununu defended his veto on the grounds of two beliefs: that scientific evidence was insufficient to warrant action and that antipollution measures would sap U.S. economic growth. The first proposition is dubious; the second, preposterous.</p>
        <p>Days later, when eight prestigious environmental organizations sent Mr. Bush a letter criticizing his aide's action, Jay Hair, president of the National Wildlife Federation, said with exasperation, ''The American people did not elect John Sununu.''</p>
        <p>No one denies that pollution has dramatically changed the world's atmosphere. What is in question, and fiendishly difficult to prove, are the effects of the changes.</p>
        <p>Most scientists agree that increasing levels of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases will inevitably lead to global warming. But no one is certain how fast and how much temperatures will rise, and what the effects will be in any geographical area.</p>
        <p>Scientific uncertainty does not mean we have to wait for more research to take action. We do not need to know everything in order to do anything. The relevant policy question is not whether the scientists are right but whether policy makers can afford to be wrong. Suppose we take reasonable, cost-effective steps to slow down global warming, and learn later the scientists were wrong and we didn't have to do anything after all.</p>
        <p>Admittedly, we will have spent billions of dollars to reduce emissions of greenhouse gases. But, wisely spent, that investment will have brought us billions of dollars of benefits: reduced pollution, improved health, more energy-efficient cars, U.S. industry that is more internationally competitive and the creation of new global markets for American-made environmental technologies and services.</p>
        <p>But suppose we gamble that global warming won't happen, and are wrong. When we have unambiguous evidence that warming is happening, it will be too late to slow it down.</p>
        <p>Scenarios of sudden change - temperatures climbing three to five degrees in a decade - pose the greatest risks. Predicted plagues will come to pass: forests will die, crops will wither, oceans will rise, disease will increase. And we will be defenseless before them. Money in the bank, unspent to reach environmental goals, will then be cold comfort.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and Mr. Sununu would have us believe we can protect ourselves from global warming only at the expense of economic growth. But Japan's impressive economic growth has hardly been stymied by its huge investment in some of the world's toughest air pollution controls and its development of an economic sector twice as energy-efficient as ours.</p>
        <p>On the contrary, Japanese companies see environmental protection as a major market opportunity, and are aggressively developing and selling environmental technologies.</p>
        <p>The ''jobs vs. environment'' argument is a myth handed down by an earlier generation of industrialists and long discredited. It deserves a decent burial, even by Mr. Sununu, who surely knows better - or should.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
