<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Session Ended, Capitol Glories Are Campaign Grist</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="353098"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD61F3EF930A25756C0A966958260" item-length="1236" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Session Ended, Capitol Glories Are Campaign Grist</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kirk Johnson</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Just before midnight on Wednesday, House Speaker Richard J. Balducci banged his gavel, at once signaling the end of the General Assembly's 1990 session and the start of the campaign season for the statewide elections in November.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Just before midnight on Wednesday, House Speaker Richard J. Balducci banged his gavel, at once signaling the end of the General Assembly's 1990 session and the start of the campaign season for the statewide elections in November.</p>
        <p>Just before midnight on Wednesday, House Speaker Richard J. Balducci banged his gavel, at once signaling the end of the General Assembly's 1990 session and the start of the campaign season for the statewide elections in November.</p>
        <p>For the 151 members of the House and the 36 members of the Senate, almost all of whom are running for re-election, the bills, amendments and resolutions of the three-month session are now history. What remains is the political fallout of what they achieved. The lawmakers must now decide what they can take home to brag about and what should remain unsaid or unemphasized in the interest of re-election.</p>
        <p>For both Democrats and Republicans, legislators said, boasting emphasis is very likely to be placed on what polls have identified as two of the hottest political topics in Connecticut: crime and the environment.</p>
        <p>Bipartisian Support</p>
        <p>In the final days of the session, lawmakers approved bills that provide election ammunition on both counts, including measures that would seek to reduce the state's contribution to global warming through more efficient use of fossil fuels, make more money available to the Department of Environmental Protection for law enforcement and require prison inmates to spend more time behind bars. All those measures were approved with support from both parties.</p>
        <p>Leading the list of items that incumbents will not want to emphasize, members of both parties agreed, was the $7.05 million budget. The budget, battered by a decline in corporate tax revenues, was balanced by the Democratic majority with a battery of short-term solutions including one-time revenue infusions, transfers among budget lines and increased borrowing.</p>
        <p>The Assembly's nonpartisian research arm has already projected a deficit for the fiscal year that begins in July 1991, because the one-time revenue increases used in the budget that takes effect this July 1 will have dried up.</p>
        <p>''It's intelectually tough to be proud of what we've done,' said Representative George C. Jepsen, a Democrat from Stamford.</p>
        <p>Some other bills, lawmakers said, will not be natural campaign fodder, because they are either purely local in effect, like a bond authorization for a building project in a legislator's district, or because they might not be universally popular with voters.</p>
        <p>''Most legislators will have obtained something through the bond package or an appropriation,'' said the minority leader in the House, Richard G. Jackle, a Republican of Stratford. ''They can say, ''I got the roof fixed,' or 'I got the new fire engine.' That's all individual bragging.</p>
        <p>Use of Abortion Law</p>
        <p>Bills that could prove to be double-edged swords for incumbents in both parties addressed some of the more emotional issues that the Assembly confronted during the session. The new state law on abortion, for example, while approved by both chambers and signed with little opposition, contains enough vague language that lawmakers said it could be used about as effectively for or against an incumbent candidate, depending on the district and the group being targeted.</p>
        <p>One Democratic legislator, who asked not to be identified, said polls had shown strong support for abortion-rights legislation among Republican women in the state -- a group that candidates from both parties will seek to court this fall. On the other hand, the lawmaker said, the legislation will also have to be handled delicately as a campaign issue. ''No one's going to take out a billboard that says, ''I supported abortion,'' the legislator said.</p>
        <p>The abortion measure essentially codifies into state law the provisions of the United Sattes Supreme Court decision in Roe v. Wade, and thus it would guarantee a woman's right to seek an abortion in consultation with her physician if the Roe decision were struck down by the High Court.</p>
        <p>But the law contains a number of ambiguities, specifically the question of when viability of the fetus begins and abortion becomes prohibited under the law. Officials at the Pro-Life Council of Conecticut, which did not oppose the final bill, have already announced that lawsuits would be filed against the law in the months to come, challenging the courts to define the ambiguities and perhaps make the law more restrictive through interpretation.</p>
        <p>But the game of running on one's record also contains a vast array of subtleties that go beyond a bill's ultimate fate.</p>
        <p>''In a real crass political senses, it doesn't matter whether it became law or not,'' said one member of the House. 'You can still run on it.''</p>
        <p>And because there are dozens of ways for lawmakers to make a stand, vote for a bill and then quietly scuttle the legislation through parliamentary procedure, the list of dead bills that could be reborn this fall is extensive. For instance, a majority of lawmakers in both chambers voted to restrict the sale of military-style assault rifles, which have been linked by the Federal Government to use by drug gangs.</p>
        <p>No Time Left</p>
        <p>The bill would have brought assault rifles under the same law that covers handguns. Buyers would thus have been required to go through the same lengthy process as people who want to be allowed to carry a concealed weapon. That bill died on the final day of the session, after the Senate approved it with an amendment that required reconsideration by the House, even though there was not enough time remaining.</p>
        <p>A majority in the House also voted in support of a bill that would have made it easier to impose the death penalty in Connecticut. That bill died in the Senate, when the members voted to send the measure back for more committee consideration, although, again, there was no time for that.</p>
        <p>Although the death-penalty bill was known to be opposed by many Democrats in the Senate's majority -- they derailed a siilar measure last year -- no one had to go on the record as voting against the proposal in an election year, because the technical Senate vote only concerned whether the bill needed tinkering.</p>
        <p>Political experts in and outside the Asembly said that no matter how successfully incumbents defend their records, those who return next year will face a completely changed legislative landscape.</p>
        <p>Power Struggle Ahead</p>
        <p>Gov. WIlliam A. O'Neill, who has spent the last 23 years exploring the corridors of power at the Capitol -- as a legislator, Democratic Party chairman, Lieutenant Governor and Governor -- is not running for re-election.</p>
        <p>And the three front-running candidates seeking to replace him -- United States Representative John G. Rowland, a Republican from Waterbury, United States Representative Bruce A. Morrison, a Democrat from Hamden, and former United States Senator Lowell P. Weicker Jr., a Republican from Greenwich -- are relative outsiders to the Assembly and its ways.</p>
        <p>Many lawmakers are already predicting something of a power struggle with the new kid on the block, whoever is elected.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Neill ''is one of the last governors, if not the last Governor, who will be able to dominate the process,'' said Senator John B. Larson, a Democrat from East Hartford and the President pro tem of the Senate. The next General Assembly, Mr. Larson predicted, will be far more active in setting the state's agenda than any before it.</p>
        <p>''There's a whole generation of leadership that is moving on and new leadership is waiting in the wings,'' he said. ''It will be a whole new ball game.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
