<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Editorial Notebook;   Purity vs. Politics</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="358546"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CZECHOSLOVAKIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">HUNGARY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAVEL, VACLAV (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GONCZ, ARPAD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOCTOROW, E L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Hungary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D9173CF930A35755C0A966958260" item-length="494" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Editorial Notebook;   Purity vs. Politics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nicolas Wade</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The novelist E. L. Doctorow was waxing lyrical the other day about literary men in politics like Vaclav Havel, President of Czechoslovakia, and Arpad Goncz, President of Hungary. Unlike professional politicians, he said, amateurs don't cling to office by twisting the truth. In fact, Mr. Doctorow declared, ''I know of no better qualifications for a president anywhere: a total integrity on the one hand, and a precious lack of political experience on the other.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The novelist E. L. Doctorow was waxing lyrical the other day about literary men in politics like Vaclav Havel, President of Czechoslovakia, and Arpad Goncz, President of Hungary. Unlike professional politicians, he said, amateurs don't cling to office by twisting the truth. In fact, Mr. Doctorow declared, ''I know of no better qualifications for a president anywhere: a total integrity on the one hand, and a precious lack of political experience on the other.</p>
        <p>The novelist E. L. Doctorow was waxing lyrical the other day about literary men in politics like Vaclav Havel, President of Czechoslovakia, and Arpad Goncz, President of Hungary. Unlike professional politicians, he said, amateurs don't cling to office by twisting the truth. In fact, Mr. Doctorow declared, ''I know of no better qualifications for a president anywhere: a total integrity on the one hand, and a precious lack of political experience on the other.''</p>
        <p>Eastern Europe is suddenly full of amateur politicians, and if they succeed, they may prove Mr. Doctorow's point. But just as likely, Eastern Europe will flounder until its amateur politicians learn to be professionals.</p>
        <p>Intellectuals, confident they possess the truth, underestimate the difficulties of making others see it, and thus underrate the politician's skills. A flood of issues batters at the politician's door. He or she must understand the greenhouse effect, mobile missiles and milk price supports. At the drop of a hat, senators like Bill Bradley, Bob Packwood or Tim Wirth can provide deft expositions on such issues, at 20-second or 20-minute length.</p>
        <p>The intellectual's business - understanding and explaining the issues - is a small part of the politician's craft. He must shake every hand and seem to remember every face. He must persuade veterans, farmers, teachers and pensioners that he has their disparate interests at heart. He must direct a staff, raise money and jostle for reporters' attention. The best politicians also somehow find time to devise creative solutions to national problems.</p>
        <p>It's rarely a job for amateurs. If writers and intellectuals would do it so much better, why don't they get elected? The politician who is perceived as a writer will run at a disadvantage, Mr. Doctorow explained, ''as was the case of Adlai Stevenson, who spoke in beautiful sentences and was beaten handily by a man who garbled the English language.'' But the public has enough sense to select politicians, not prose stylists, for office. Besides, Dwight Eisenhower's English was excellent but, as the historian Fred Greenstein notes, he would deliberately use emotive or ambiguous language when it suited his purposes.</p>
        <p>Shelley believed that poets were the unacknowledged legislators of the world, and Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn asserts that a great writer is like a second government. But the pure, unyielding truth so effective in denouncing bankrupt regimes is one thing. The language of consensus that informs ordinary politics is quite another.</p>
        <p>For deciding between guns and butter, the truth is not an adequate arbiter. The art of politics also includes posturing, drama, ambush and braggadocio. Flag-burning and pornography make for hokey scripts. But on small issues or great, amateurs get hissed quickly off the stage and better politicians perform with skill. They do it so artfully that their unappreciated art is often invisible, even to the smartest intellectuals.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
