<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. Takes Step Toward Global Climate Pact</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="313846"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DC133FF930A35752C0A966958260" item-length="657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. Takes Step Toward Global Climate Pact</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Jan. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: After difficult negotiations, the nations of the world have laid the groundwork for an accord between rich and poor countries on protecting the atmosphere and encouraging ecologically sound development.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: After difficult negotiations, the nations of the world have laid the groundwork for an accord between rich and poor countries on protecting the atmosphere and encouraging ecologically sound development.</p>
        <p>After difficult negotiations, the nations of the world have laid the groundwork for an accord between rich and poor countries on protecting the atmosphere and encouraging ecologically sound development.</p>
        <p>The agreement, reached at the 1989 United Nations General Assembly session, which ended late last month, commits the 159 member countries to draft a treaty on stabilizing the earth's climate and convene a world conference in Brazil in 1992 to discuss ways of reducing the environmental impact of economic development.</p>
        <p>As now envisioned, the climate treaty would be adopted at the 1992 conference and would require signers to take appropriate action to prevent warming of the earth's atmosphere, setting goals on such issues as the destruction of forests and the emission of so-called ''greenhouse gases'' which trap heat in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>At the same time the 1992 environmental conference will try to establish a consensus in favor of a more environmentally sound approach to development, with the industrialized countries offering to help the third world meet the additional costs involved. But while the United Nations unanimously approved the plan for a conference, diplomats say agreement was reached only by papering over differences on delicate issues that could still disrupt a final accord in 1992.</p>
        <p>The most important relates to the underdeveloped countries' demands for affordable access to the new technology that they say they will need to make their development environmentally benign.</p>
        <p>Many developing countries also believe that the industrialized world's growing environmental concern offers them a chance to press for a wide range of economic concessions in return for cooperation.</p>
        <p>Arguing that poverty itself promotes environmental degradation by encouraging deforestation or overgrazing, they are pressing the industrialized countries to make debt relief and higher prices for their exports part of the final package.</p>
        <p>This led to a dispute between the industrialized and developing countries at the General Assembly, with the industrialized countries trying to entrust preparation of the climate treaty and the 1992 conference to technical experts, while the third world sought to put the work under its political control.</p>
        <p>The final compromise gives the main task of drafting the climate treaty to the United Nations Environment Program and the World Meteorological Organization, as the industrialized countries wanted. But the 1990 General Assembly session will give instructions to the negotiators.</p>
        <p>Developed countries also strove to put the United Nations Environment Program in charge of planning the 1992 conference, with the preparatory meetings in Geneva, where third-world countries are less well representated than in New York. But the third world gave the job to a committee of the General Assembly, with meetings divided between New York, Geneva and Nairobi.</p>
        <p>No Specific Pledges of Help</p>
        <p>The industrialized countries accepted that the developing world needs help in combating environmental degradation, particularly through easier access to Western technology. But they refused to give specific pledges before the 1992 conference and completion of the climate convention.</p>
        <p>The United States, in particular, argued that most environmentally safe technology - such as solar cells for electrifying villages or ''scrubbers'' for smokestacks - belongs to private corporations and cannot be given away by governments.</p>
        <p>India, Sweden and several other countries tried to solve this problem by proposing an international fund, financed from taxes on pollution and voluntary contributions, to finance the purchase of enviromentally sound technology by developing countries.</p>
        <p>But the industrialized world would go no further than saying the 1992 conference should ''consider'' such ideas and ''explore the concept of assured access for developing countries to environmentally sound technologies.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
