<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>North Salem May Ban Foam Cups</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="316531"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLYSTYRENE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORTH SALEM (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MELVIN, TESSA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Polymers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED9173BF937A25752C0A966958260" item-length="918" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>North Salem May Ban Foam Cups</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TESSA MELVIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MELVIN, TESSA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: NORTH SALEM could become the first community in Westchester to ban polystyrene foam containers when village officials consider the measure later this month. But opposition from local retailers is mounting, and the outlook for passage of the local law is uncertain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: NORTH SALEM could become the first community in Westchester to ban polystyrene foam containers when village officials consider the measure later this month. But opposition from local retailers is mounting, and the outlook for passage of the local law is uncertain.</p>
        <p>NORTH SALEM could become the first community in Westchester to ban polystyrene foam containers when village officials consider the measure later this month. But opposition from local retailers is mounting, and the outlook for passage of the local law is uncertain.</p>
        <p>The ban, being drafted by the chairman of the Zoning Board of Appeals, Peter C. Bliss, would prohibit retail food establishments in town from using containers made with chlorofluorocarbons, chemicals some scientists say are destroying the earth's ozone layer.</p>
        <p>He decided to bring the action, Mr. Bliss said, after reading of a similar law enacted last year in Portland, Ore. Although lawmakers in Suffolk County on Long Island recently passed nearly identical legislation, that law, which is to go into effect on Jan. 31, is being reviewed in the courts.</p>
        <p>An Increasing Problem in Area</p>
        <p>Mr. Bliss said he planned to propose the local law as an officer of the North Salem Improvement Society, a 57-year-old volunteer organization dedicated to improving the visual qualities of North Salem. Among other projects, the organization sponsers a yearly cleanup of roadside litter.</p>
        <p>The volunteers agree that polystyrene foam, which is not biodegradable, is becoming an increasing problem in the area. ''People here are very conscious of the environment,'' Mr. Bliss said. ''When a Styrofoam cup hits the road, it stays there forever, unless someone picks it up. We just can't have a throwaway society.''</p>
        <p>While conceding that the influence of one town - North Salem has a population of 4,700 - might not be great, he said that ''we hope our ban will spread to other towns and to Albany.''</p>
        <p>Cost Factor Said to Be Small</p>
        <p>He said he did not expect that the extra cost of paper cups would pose an undue hardship on local merchants. ''Styrofoam cups costs $19 per thousand,'' Mr. Bliss said, ''while paper cups are $43.00 per thousand. That's 2.4 cents more per cup. No one who buys coffee will mind the extra costs. Do you think they'll drive to the next town to save 2 1/2 cents? That's silly.''</p>
        <p>But Paul Pavlou, an owner of Swan's Deli and Grocery on Route 22 in Purdys, said the efforts of Mr. Bliss and the Improvement Society were misguided. The ban, he said, ''will hurt those it is trying to help.''</p>
        <p>Saying he was ''not opposed to the concept of protecting and conserving environment,'' Mr. Pavlou suggested that prohibiting polystyrene foam cups would not keep North Salem any cleaner. The paper cup alternative is not only more expensive, he said, but the wax coating on those cups is not biodegradable. Others say it breaks down slowly.</p>
        <p>If a ban on polystyrene foam is imposed, Mr. Pavlou said, ''It will cost me money, and I'll lose business.'' The proposed ban, he added, would discriminate against his customers. One of the attractions of Swan's Deli is the ''commuter cup,'' a plastic cup molded so the lid sits inside and coffee can be carried easily without spilling.</p>
        <p>''If my customers can't buy a commuting cup here,'' the deli owner said, ''these people will go to the next town, to Goldens Bridge or Somers, that has the cup and won't have this ban.''</p>
        <p>The plastics industry is working on alternatives to plastic foam, Mr. Pavlou said. ''Let's give them a chance.'' One of Mr. Pavlou's customers is Andrew Benson of Purdys, who has spent the last three months working with manufacturers of products made from recycled plastic foam. Mr. Benson said he would soon begin marketing pens, scissors and rulers through his new company, Pimby, which stands for Products In My Back Yard.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pavlou has organized a petition drive to oppose the passage of the proposed local law, and he said last week he had obtained ''several hundred'' signatures during the five days the petition had been in his store.</p>
        <p>Other Reaction Is Mixed</p>
        <p>The reaction of other store owners in the town was mixed. Claire Mills manages the Peach Lake Market on Route 121 in North Salem. Banning polystyrene foam, she said, is a ''wonderful'' idea. ''Where is all this waste going anyway,'' she asked. ''We have no place to put our garbage as it is now, and Styrofoam is just an excess of something we really don't need.''</p>
        <p>Peach Lake Market recently switched from polystyrene foam coffee cups to paper and is planning to begin using paper cups for soup as soon as the current stock of plastic cups runs out. ''We haven't figured out the costs,'' Mrs. Mills said. ''I don't think it will affect the price. We'll just take less of a profit.'' The owner of a similar retail outlet, who asked that her name not be used, disagreed. ''There are expenses enough,'' she said. ''We go all out to save our customers money, and it's just not fair.'' If the ban takes effect, she added, ''we will have to raise the price of our coffee.''</p>
        <p>Plastic foam litter is not a problem in North Salem, she contended. ''I see more beer cans lying by the side of the road, and they even have a 5-cent deposit.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the members of the North Salem Improvement Society are starting to plan their yearly spring cleanup day. They expect that polystyrene foam containers will once again be a frequent discovery. ''A lot of stuff we picked up last year was Styrofoam, especially the proverbial coffee cup,'' said Debby Moore, a former president of the society. She added that most of the cups came from local delicatessens.</p>
        <p>Banning polystyrene foam in North Salem is a small step, Ms. Moore said. ''It's a first step,'' she said. ''We have to start someplace.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
