<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Veteran of Earth Day 1970 Looks to a New World</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="344037"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH DAY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAYES, DENIS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD61339F935A25757C0A966958260" item-length="1030" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Veteran of Earth Day 1970 Looks to a New World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Twenty years ago Denis Hayes wanted to change the nation. Now, dissatisfied with progress over the decades, he is trying to change the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Twenty years ago Denis Hayes wanted to change the nation. Now, dissatisfied with progress over the decades, he is trying to change the world.</p>
        <p>Twenty years ago Denis Hayes wanted to change the nation. Now, dissatisfied with progress over the decades, he is trying to change the world.</p>
        <p>As chairman of Earth Day 1990, Mr. Hayes is replaying a role he filled in 1970 when he was national coordinator of the first Earth Day. It was born of the social unrest of the 1960's and it produced an unanticipated outpouring of public concern over the toll of pollution on the nation's earth, air and water.</p>
        <p>Twenty million Americans, many of them young, rallied in city streets, on college campuses, on river banks and on mountaintops on April 22, 1970, to demonstrate their concern for the environment and to demand that action be taken to save it.</p>
        <p>''I remember standing on the steps of the Museum of Natural History in New York and seeing a sea of faces in front of me,'' Mr. Hayes recalled in a recent interview. ''I was astonished at how many people there were.''</p>
        <p>Activity in Other Lands</p>
        <p>He said he expects Earth Day 1990 to dwarf the original. This year the event is being organized in other lands as well. Participants in 136 countries have officially signed on; the Yap Islands are the latest. Mr. Hayes said he estimated that 200 million people would take part in some event to commemorate Earth Day on April 22.</p>
        <p>A separate group based in Seattle, Earth Day 20, is sponsoring a team of superpower climbers (from the United States, the Soviet Union and China) that plans to reach the peak of Mount Everest. Other events are planned by an internationally active organization founded by Jeremy Rifkin that is based here in the nation's capital.</p>
        <p>Groups from farmers, to students to television viewers will have their own ways of marking the day. At Dartmouth college, students plan to carry with them all the trash they produce over five days; the Nature Conservancy is completing land protection deals in all 50 states; a New York celebration begins in Times Square at 9 A.M. with a model of the earth taking the place of the traditional New Year's Eve ball. And ABC plans ''The Earth Day Special'' with Carl Sagan and Meryl Streep from 9 to 11 P.M.</p>
        <p>It is a long way from the national environmental teach-in of 20 years ago planned by Senator Gaylord Nelson, a Wisconsin Democrat, who is generally regarded as the father of the original Earth Day. Mr. Hayes was attending Harvard Law School and the Kennedy School of Government in 1969 when he read a newspaper article about the planning. He went to Washington to volunteer to organize the event in the Cambridge, Mass., area. Instead, a few days later he found himself the coordinator for the entire country.</p>
        <p>Some people who helped organize Earth Day 1970 questioned the significance of Mr. Hayes's role in that event. Barry Commoner, the environmental scientist who was active in the first Earth Day and is playing a role again, said, ''I was not impressed with the importance of any particular leadership in 1970, nor am I impressed now.''</p>
        <p>While he was not the intellectual or ideological founder of Earth Day, Mr. Hayes was ''the starter, the one who did the unglamorous, wearisome job of starting it up,'' said Ralph Nader, the consumer advocate, who is the special counsel to Earth Day 1990. Mr. Hayes, he said, ''is an orchestrator of environmental events which were national 20 years ago and now are global.''</p>
        <p>Disappointment the First Time</p>
        <p>From his 20-year perspective, Mr. Hayes, now 45 years old, says he thinks the first Earth Day accomplished both more and less than he hoped for. ''We hoped it would lead to a new kind of ideology, a new value system based on ecology and a reverence for life,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Instead, he said, ''Earth Day was translated into a series of local and regional issues, like dirty air in Los Angeles, concern in Chicago about the pollution of the Great Lakes and in New York about the Hudson River.''</p>
        <p>But the environment became ''a new item on the political agenda,'' Mr. Hayes said. At the beginning of 1970 there was little interest in a clean air law; by the end of that year Congress had adopted the Clean Air Act. Statutes for cleaning the water and for reducing toxic chemicals in the environment quickly followed, he said.</p>
        <p>And new institutions like the Environmental Protection Agency were formed, and private conservation and environmental organizations grew rapidly in members and money. In the process, Mr. Hayes said, they developed a substantial amount of lobbying and political influence.</p>
        <p>But, Mr. Hayes said, what came out of that first Earth Day was mostly an ''upper middle-class movement'' that was ''disconnected from the grass roots, from labor, from minorities.'' He said it was a movement that focused on local and regional issues and was not prepared to meet international challenges like global warming or the destruction of ozone in the upper atmosphere by industrial chemicals.''What I would like to see come out of Earth Day 1990 is a new movement based on the original foundation,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hayes was born in Wisconsin Rapid, Wis., and moved with his family to Camas, Wash., when he was 6. Growing up in ''spectacularly beautiful surroundings,'' he said, ''gave you a sense of what the world could be like.''</p>
        <p>A Mill Fouling a River</p>
        <p>But, he continued, a paper mill that was the town's chief employer fouled a river and the air and gave him a sense of how pollution could degrade the beauty of the natural world.</p>
        <p>He is a graduate of Stanford University and the Stanford Law School, He has practiced law, was a senior fellow of the Worldwatch Institute in Washington, D.C., director of the Illinois State Energy office, and Director of the Federal Solar Energy Research Institute until he was asked to leave by the Reagan Administration. He was serving as an adjunct professor of engineering at Stanford this year and left to take up the Earth Day cause once more.</p>
        <p>The environmentalist is looking somewhat haggard these days as he crisscrosses the country drumming up activities for the big day. While he no longer seems to be the angry young man in press accounts of the 1970 event, his face is still intense. After 20 years, he said, ''I am both frustrated and hopeful.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
