<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="344770"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DF123FF93BA25757C0A966958260" item-length="1332" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Soviet officials threatened Lithuania with reducing or cutting off natural gas and crude oil supplies. The threat prompted calls in the republic's Parliament for scaling back measures toward independence.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>President Bush then warned Moscow that he would retaliate for a cut in fuel shipments to Lithuania. Administration officials said possible responses range from canceling exchanges to stalling trade talks.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Soviet criminal justice system came under rare review in the Parliament. A special commission criticized two former criminal prosecutors and suggested that the prosecutor general be dismissed.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Visit by Soviet writers sparks debate over anti-Semitism</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>NATO allies still lag on arms, Pentagon study says</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>West Germany's Deutsche Bank A.G. announced that it would jointly establish an East German bank with Deutsche Kreditbank A.G., the first private commercial bank in East Germany.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>U.S. official says contra camps will be dismantled this week</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Court freezes U.S. bank accounts thought to hide drug profits</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Pretoria won't accept majority rule but is prepared to negotiate a formula for whites to share power with blacks in South Africa, President de Klerk announced.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>The political leader of the Zulus in South Africa, both widely admired and detested, is a force with which President de Klerk and Nelson Mandela must reckon as they negotiate the nation's future.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Eleven die in clashes between Shiite Muslims in West Beirut</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Thousands of Burmese are fleeing advances by Burmese troops against rebellious ethnic minorities along the Thai border, creating a new refugee problem for Thailand.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Nepal's fledgling political parties, which emerged after King Birendra lifted a 30-year ban on politics, are reveling in freedom and denouncing the Government without fear.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>New Delhi Journal: A revolutionary among India's poor</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>National</p>
        <p>A14-23</p>
        <p>Consumer prices climbed in March by five-tenths of 1 percent to make the annual inflation rate 8.5 percent for the first three months of 1990, the most rapid increase in a quarter in nearly eight years.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Citicorp says earnings fell 56 percent in first quarter</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court supported unions by ruling that permanent replacements hired during a strike need not be presumed to be anti-union for purposes of deciding whether the union still has majority support.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Use of drugs in religious rituals can be prosecuted, court rules</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>A buried treasure in Puerto Rico? In the town of Vega Baja, F.B.I. agents are looking for leads after residents uncovered drums stuffed with as much as $20 million. Residents who enjoyed a giddy spending spree are reluctant to share details.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A gene that is linked to alcoholism has been indentified for the first time, scientists reported. The finding holds promise for the prevention and treatment of alcoholism.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A rise in AIDS cases in rural Georgia has caught many health officials by surprise, confronting them with difficult choices on how to provide care and testing community values.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Washington at Work: Party loyalty? Representative Constance Morella of Maryland voted against her Republican colleagues 76 percent of the time. She does not get many invitations to the White House, but neither is she shunned.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>A Catholic anti-abortion campaign worth $3 million to $5 million has sharply divided employees at Hill &amp; Knowlton, the public relations firm hired to conduct it.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Mayors press Bush for support to avert census crisis</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>F.D.A contradicts its report on antibiotics in milk</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>San Francisco's worst eyesore, many people believe, is the monstrous Embarcadero Freeway. The earthquake may well have rectified that, but controversy has arisen over how to replace it.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Twin Peaks Journal: Town relishes television notoriety</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Regional</p>
        <p>B1-4</p>
        <p>New York's air quality has delcined again after years of improvement. With more automobiles spewing pollutants into the city's atmosphere, only Los Angeles has dirtier air.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Bush calls for more research on global warming</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>Fear follows Bronx livery drivers after the recent wave of killings. Scores of livery cars clogged the 225th Street Bridge to demand stronger police action. ''You can't trust anybody,'' one driver said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The New Jersey Attorney General ordered the grand jury investigation of the fatal shooting of a black youth by a white policeman in Teaneck moved to the state level because of mounting tension in the community.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Bid for a special prosecutor is rejected in Teaneck shooting</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Bensonhurst trial defendant admits group gathered with bats</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>News analysis: Conflicts of interest for Mayor Dinkins and City Council President Andrew Stein over cable television franchises have put both men in the unusual position of asking staff members to vote ''independently'' in their place.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Matinee day in New York City lures to Broadway dozens of suburban groups, organized by churches, schools and social clubs. For many, matinee day is one of the few chances they have to visit the city.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Scheduled passenger service began at Stewart International Airport. The state, which owns the former Air Force base at Newburgh, hopes it will spur economic growth in the region, but still faces opposition from environmentalists.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Baruch College's re-accreditation had been deferred</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Witness says commissions were routine in Marcos dealings</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>New York City pension trustees criticize A.T.&amp;T.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>The Living Section</p>
        <p>Food</p>
        <p>Star chefs are on the outside looking in</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>U.S. bars Kobe beef from Japan</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Eating Well</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Wine Talk</p>
        <p>C9</p>
        <p>Living</p>
        <p>How children helped to save the tunas</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Diary</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Fashion students win gold thimbles</p>
        <p>C8</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>Inside Cincinnati's art world</p>
        <p>C11</p>
        <p>NBC stays on top of the ratings</p>
        <p>C11</p>
        <p>Theater: A Soviet portrayal of an unsaintly but heroic Lenin</p>
        <p>C11</p>
        <p>''Related Retreats''</p>
        <p>C12</p>
        <p>Music: Solisti New York Chamber Orchestra</p>
        <p>C12</p>
        <p>Pop Life</p>
        <p>C16</p>
        <p>Dance: Exotic motions</p>
        <p>C16</p>
        <p>Word and Image: Virginia Woolf's letters</p>
        <p>C17</p>
        <p>Sports</p>
        <p>Baseball: Yanks top Tigers, 4-1</p>
        <p>D23</p>
        <p>Cubs beat Mets in extra innings</p>
        <p>D23</p>
        <p>Boxing: Notebook</p>
        <p>D25</p>
        <p>Foreman scores knockout</p>
        <p>D25</p>
        <p>Colleges: Ivy money woes</p>
        <p>D24</p>
        <p>Column: Vecsey on Eddie Lee Wilkins</p>
        <p>D23</p>
        <p>Hockey: Stanley Cup scramble</p>
        <p>D23</p>
        <p>Education</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Lessons</p>
        <p>Modest campus blazes trail to business careers</p>
        <p>Obituaries</p>
        <p>Ralph David Abernathy, pioneer in rights struggle</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>Lawson P. Ramage, submarine hero</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Senator Dole's duty</p>
        <p>Black militancy</p>
        <p>Cloud over cable in New York</p>
        <p>Topics: Shrinking secrets</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Russell Baker: Beating the Sphinx</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>John Ralston Saul: Drugs, torture - and Western cash</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Dennis Barrie: Pandering? That's nonsense</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Richard Pollock: Census - getting the lead out</p>
        <p>A25</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
