<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Out of the Belfry, Into the Garden</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="338933"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BATS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAIL ORDER COMPANIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWN, PATRICIA LEIGH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mail Order Companies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900329T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DE113CF93AA15750C0A966958260" item-length="949" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Out of the Belfry, Into the Garden</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA LEIGH BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWN, PATRICIA LEIGH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: HANGING upside down in a rough-hewn chamber of red cedar with 30 to 50 companions might not be everybody's idea of a happy home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: HANGING upside down in a rough-hewn chamber of red cedar with 30 to 50 companions might not be everybody's idea of a happy home.</p>
        <p>HANGING upside down in a rough-hewn chamber of red cedar with 30 to 50 companions might not be everybody's idea of a happy home.</p>
        <p>But home to a human being is one thing, and to a bat it's quite another.</p>
        <p>Be that as it may, what makes a habitat desirable to bats seems to be increasingly fascinating to humans. Gardener's Eden (P.O. Box 7307, San Francisco, Calif. 94120; 415-421-4242), a division of Williams-Sonoma, is offering a bat house among the terra-cotta planters and garden chairs in its mail-order catalogue.</p>
        <p>The Nature Company (P.O. Box 23170, Berkeley, Calif. 94702; 800-227-1114) will have a bat house in its new catalogue, too.</p>
        <p>The Plow and Hearth (P.O. Box 830, Orange, Va. 22960; 800-627-1712) has been selling bat houses for 18 months. Its smaller model (28 inches high by 11 wide by 4 deep) will accommodate up to 20 bats; the other has space for 30. They are meant to be hung on walls or tree trunks. The Plow and Hearth catalogue also offers a book on bats under the printed plea, ''Learn the truth about our friends, the bats.''</p>
        <p>''Everyone is feeling pressure on housing right now, including the bat,'' said Matthew Carhart of Gardener's Eden. He said bats' favored roosts in old barns, houses and hollow trees are steadily disappearing.</p>
        <p>The catalogues' bat houses, all essentially the same, have no doors and no floors; bats enter from below. Some have fixed partitions inside that form the narrow crevices bats like to roost in. A bat house should be hung 12 to 15 feet from the ground, sheltered as much as possible from the wind, and unobstructed by utility wires and other obstacles to flying. Bats are happiest living in easy flying distance of a permanent source of water, especially a marsh or lake.</p>
        <p>The bat house offered by Gardener's Eden comes with decorative Victorian trim. ''The bats couldn't care less,'' Mr. Carhart said. Still, he is convinced that the time is right for No. 74-443614, the 24-inch-high, $55 house big enough to shelter 50 bats. The main reason is that bats are ecologically sound pest controllers, perfect for these days of fashionable environmental thinking.</p>
        <p>North American crevice-roosting bats, among them the little brown bat (Myotis lucifugus) and the big brown bat (Euptesicus fuscus), both quite common in the northern two-thirds of the United States, live on insects. A single bat can eat up to 3,000 mosquitoes a night without, as bat advocates like to point out, causing a ripple in the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>It was mostly the mosquito factor that led Verne Read, a retired money manager in Milwaukee, to put up five bat houses at his vacation house on Oconomowoc Lake in Wisconsin. While remodeling the yellow Victorian house, Mr. Read found a colony of some 2,000 bats in the spaces of a wall he was tearing down. Mr. Read put his bat houses on posts in the yard, and now he gets to watch the wondrous winged creatures' aerobatics at dusk above the lake shore.</p>
        <p>''People have been misled,'' said Margie Hale, a retired chemist in Austin, Tex. ''Bats are cute. Any time a bat wants to kill a mosquito, I'm all for him.'' Two years ago Dr. Hale and her husband, Cecil, also a retired chemist, put up a bat house they bought from Bat Conservation International, a nonprofit organization in Austin that has been a prime mover in fostering appreciation of bat houses and of bats themselves.</p>
        <p>So far the Hales have not had any tenants. The common vacancy period for new bat house s is a year to 18 months, bat experts say.</p>
        <p>But the Hales' vacancy may have something to do with local competition. Austin is also home to what is considered the largest urban bat colony in North America - housed, if you will, in the world's largest bat house, the Congress Avenue Bridge in downtown Austin, where scientists have counted some 700,000 Mexican free-tailed bats roosting in the expansion crevices under the bridge deck. The spectacle of their nightly departure has become a tourist attraction.</p>
        <p>The bats of this colony have been found to eat about seven tons of insects every night. They live under the bridge from spring through fall.</p>
        <p>Housing for bats has long concerned Dr. Merlin D. Tuttle, who started Bat Conservation International eight years ago to promote bat conservation. The group sells two bat houses ($29.95 and $42.95, plus shipping; the address is P.O. Box 162603, Austin, Tex. 78716, telephone 512-327-9721). The houses are decorated with the organization's logo, a Chinese symbol of peace, prosperity and happiness surrounded by stylized bats. The group also has a booklet of bat basics, ''About Your Bat House.''</p>
        <p>The booklet answers questions like ''How many bats can live in a bat house?'' (usually about 30) and ''How can I tell if bats live in my area?'' (watch for them at dusk, and if that doesn't work check with local nature centers or pest control companies).</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Karl F. Koopman, curator emeritus of mammalogy at the American Museum of Natural History in New York, bats are inactive in daytime. Snug in their bat houses or other roosts, they are likely to be sleeping or nesting. They go out to feed at night, but may come back briefly during the night to digest.</p>
        <p>Dr. Tuttle said bats are ''better than a bug zapper,'' and are also vital pollinators and seed dispersers and thus important to rain forests. A single fruit bat in Costa Rica, for instance, may carry 60,000 seeds a night. ''They are among the world's most valuable animals,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Bats recently received a touch of glamour from Michael Keaton, and their image seems to be improving. Though the purchase of a bat house doesn't guarantee residents, it does guarantee, Dr. Tuttle said, ''one heck of a conversation piece.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
