<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GIFTED CHILDREN'S PROGRAMS: A MATTER OF CLASS</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="350896"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GIFTED STUDENTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STONE, ELIZABETH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gifted Students</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D8143DF935A35756C0A966958260" item-length="4612" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GIFTED CHILDREN'S PROGRAMS: A MATTER OF CLASS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Elizabeth Stone; Elizabeth Stone teaches journalism at the Fordham University College at Lincoln Center. She is working on a book about the Hunter College Campus Schools.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STONE, ELIZABETH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: RECENTLY, A CLASS OF kindergartners and first graders at Hunter College Elementary School for the gifted in Manhattan were discussing with their teacher what Mayor David N. Dinkins might do for the city's 5- and 6-year-olds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: RECENTLY, A CLASS OF kindergartners and first graders at Hunter College Elementary School for the gifted in Manhattan were discussing with their teacher what Mayor David N. Dinkins might do for the city's 5- and 6-year-olds.</p>
        <p>RECENTLY, A CLASS OF kindergartners and first graders at Hunter College Elementary School for the gifted in Manhattan were discussing with their teacher what Mayor David N. Dinkins might do for the city's 5- and 6-year-olds.</p>
        <p>''Well,'' said Allegra, ''he can spend some of the money getting kids more education. He could build new schools. Many are very, very broken down.''</p>
        <p>''He could use the money to buy teachers that are very smart and that could teach very well,'' said Josh. ''And another thing - some kids might not feel comfortable in their schools, and he could reassure them to be comfortable.''</p>
        <p>''What happens to kids,'' wondered the teacher, Darlene Freeman, ''when they don't feel comfortable in school?''</p>
        <p>Molly raised her hand. ''They wind up not wanting to go, and then the Japanese would get ahead,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Molly isn't the only one thinking about the Japanese. Legislators, industrialists and educators are too, and about the unpleasant possibility of America falling permanently behind as a world power. And the same awful scenario goes through their minds when they consider the prospect of Europe pooling its resources in 1992. Meanwhile, despite a decade of educational reform, each new study of American schoolchildren offers more bad news. A recent report from the National Assessment of Educational Progress found that, among other things, American schoolchildren possess the capacity to absorb information but falter when it comes to using that information to reason effectively.</p>
        <p>As a result, attention is once again being focused on ''gifted and talented'' students - in practice, the 3 to 5 percent of the elementary-school and high-school population with the highest standardized-test scores. Twenty-six states require that gifted children be identified; some also require that they be served. Others have discretionary programs.</p>
        <p>Even the Federal Government is watching these children - as it did in the 1950's, post-Sputnik, and again in the early 70's, following a heavy emphasis on disadvantaged children - sizing them up as a national resource to be cultivated. The clearest sign of this interest is the passage of the Jacob K. Javits Gifted and Talented Students Education Act of 1988, championed by Senator Bill Bradley, Democrat of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Under the bill, money has been appropriated to subsidize 28 educational pilot projects (many of which focus on economically disadvantaged students, who account for a disproportionately small percent of those currently identified as gifted), to establish a research center on the gifted and to re-establish an Office of Gifted and Talented Education in Washington. The bill defines gifted children as those ''who give evidence of high-performance capability in areas such as intellectual, creative, artistic or leadership capacity, or in specific academic fields, and who require services or activities not ordinarily provided by the school in order to develop such capabilities.''</p>
        <p>No one would argue with the idea that some children are smarter than others. Smart is smart, but ''gifted'' is a word with an agenda. To decide who gets into ''gifted'' programs, which may start as early as the nursery level, schools have traditionally relied on the I.Q. test. The children who do best on these tests, say educators, are those who've had the most ''mediated'' experience - been read to, talked to, listened to, taken on car trips and had every last cow pointed out. In short, the middle-class child.</p>
        <p>In a culture uneasy at admitting that it has a class structure, ''gifted'' can become a code word for middle class, and especially white middle class, adding a fantasy patina of merit to what is merely money, and tacitly reinforcing the most unsavory racial stereotypes. Programs for the gifted are largely a phenomenon of public education. In urban areas, gifted education at the elementary level often seems little more than a lifeboat for white middle-class children on the sinking ship of public education.</p>
        <p>Not that there aren't occasional innovative efforts to find minority children's incipient strengths and serve them: the Program of Assessment, Diagnosis and Instruction, in Montgomery County, Md., looks for and nurtures bright minority children, a quarter of whom later come to be identified as ''gifted''; an innovative program using creative means of finding bright minority children is just beginning in Austin, Tex.; another program, in District 18 in East Flatbush, Brooklyn,(Continued on Page 68) will use a $900,000 Javits grant to identify and develop ''multiple intelligences'' in minority kindergartners over a three-year period. And Hunter College's graduate program in education has recently put an emphasis on disadvantaged gifted children, says Prof. Rena F. Subotnik. But these efforts, while promising, can hardly be called indicative of the field's general orientation.</p>
        <p>Despite more than 70 years of educational interest in bright children, there is no consistent research that demonstrates in general how gifted children should be identified, or what or how they should be taught. (Interest in the gifted began around 1920 in the United States, thus introducing educational tiers just at the time mass education was promising educational equality.) What is clear is that those identified as gifted are not necessarily the ones who have gone on to make the most stellar contributions in life.</p>
        <p>''It's my opinion that most gifted programs turn their backs on most of the people that history comes to designate as gifted,'' says Joseph S. Renzulli, professor of educational psychology at the University of Connecticut at Storrs and director of the National Research Center on the Gifted and Talented. He cites Woody Allen, Charles Schulz and Steven Spielberg among those overlooked as talented students.</p>
        <p>So it's no wonder the renewed interest in gifted children has stirred up controversy. That interest is not welcomed by Deborah Meier, recipient of a MacArthur Foundation grant who established several well-regarded public-school programs in East Harlem. ''Are we saying gifted children are more valuable to society?'' she asks. ''A society which picks out some children as more valuable than others is sending a terrible message. Any time people talk about what the gifted need - problem-solving abilities, critical thinking, creative thinking - they're describing what every child needs. In fact, other children may need it even more.''</p>
        <p>Jerome Bruner, research professor of psychology at New York University, takes a different view. ''Goodness gracious,'' he says, ''when the world's leading industrial producer has become the world's leading debtor, I would think we need as much as we can get by way of thoughtful people. If you don't have high aspirations for your gifted, you don't have them for anyone. Why does 'gifted' produce such shudders?''</p>
        <p>THE SHUDDERS BEGIN within the field of gifted education - a collection of several thousand teachers, parents, administrators and education professors in curriculum development or research. ''We're a practice without a theory,'' says Prof. James H. Borland of Columbia University Teachers College. ''We don't have a research base, we don't have a knowledge base, we don't have a theoretical base.''</p>
        <p>Curriculum comes in for criticism, too. ''We spend a lot of time thinking about how to get kids and less time on what to do once we get them - on content areas and program planning,'' says Patricia O'Connell Ross, new director of the Federal Government's Office of Gifted and Talented Education. She was speaking to the 2,000 conventioneers of the National Association for Gifted Children, an advocacy group made up of teachers, administrators and parents, who gathered for a breakfast meeting in Cincinnati last October.</p>
        <p>Robert J. Sternberg, a Yale psychologist and author of ''The Triarchic Mind: A New Theory of Human Intelligence,'' says what bothers him most is that ''a lot of what passes for gifted instruction is a little on the mindless side. I see some kids doing idiot work on worksheets.''</p>
        <p>In elementary schools, there are two common approaches to education for the gifted. The first - more common because it costs less - is instituting ''pullout'' sections, where a small group of children are taken out of their regular classroom for an hour or so of special-education goodies, usually several times a week. At an elementary school in Hazlet, N.J., last fall, bright fourth graders met for special work in literature and creative writing, oceanography, social studies and problem-solving. That meant, says one unenthusiastic parent, that four times a week her child missed her regular science and social-studies classes and was required to make up the work and get the assignments on her own.</p>
        <p>The second approach is the ''self-contained classroom,'' putting all the smart children together for the entire school day. Children who hang out with smart children tend to turn out smarter, which is why the practice is in disrepute. Besides, it's incompatible with the newest education trend favoring ''cooperative learning'' and frowning on ''ability grouping.''</p>
        <p>Ability grouping excludes. Abraham J. Tannenbaum, emeritus professor of education and psychology at Teachers College, is one who favors an inclusive approach. You offer every child the opportunity to write haiku, or play the clarinet, or work on the class mural, says Tannenbaum. Next you look at what they actually produce - not potential but performance. Only then might you make decisions about sifting. This is how the Westinghouse Talent Search, which can claim a few Nobel Prize winners among its alumni, proceeds. This seems to make more sense than designating children as gifted before they've even started school, as Hunter Elementary does.</p>
        <p>Whatever the class structure, the field's ideal these days is ''differentiated'' curriculum, rather than ''acceleration'' (which may, however, be favored at the high-school level, especially in advanced-placement courses). If a bright child learns quickly, say the curriculum developers, don't just race the child through the standard curriculum. Instead, offer the same material in a more textured way. In practice, curriculum adapted to bright children often boils down to ''mots and plops,'' says Arthur I. Pober, principal of Hunter College Elementary School.</p>
        <p>''Mots'' is More of the Same, ''and it's often followed by More of the Same Times 2,'' says Pober. ''Twice as many math problems, twice as many spelling words, twice as many book reports.'' ''Plops'' is what may happen when the curriculum is enriched. ''So you take a kid to the museum and you plop him down,'' Pober says. ''It has nothing to do with what the kid's been studying or will be studying.''</p>
        <p>Others in the field find the abundant criticisms unfair, and point out that teachers of gifted children are among the first to pick up on innovations that later become standard. For a while now in programs for the gifted, the focus has been on reasoning ability, for which the buzzwords may be ''critical thinking,'' or ''problem solving,'' or ''higher-level thinking skills.'' Just recently, Darlene Freeman adapted her class's unit on ''health'' (required by the state) to give it appropriate depth for her kindergarten children and first graders; her differentiation included a variety of problem-solving skills.</p>
        <p>Her focus was on how much sugar the children were eating, and it was a critical thinker's heaven. Students identified various sugars - molasses, brown sugar, honey, corn syrup or dextrose. They brought in cereal boxes and analyzed the contents. Then they classified the cereals as heavy in sugar or not. Guilty boxes - Cap'n Crunch and Fruit-e-O's - were pilloried on the wall.</p>
        <p>Next the children collected data on their own sugar intake for a week, sorting the results as high, low or average. Then they repeated their survey, and compared and contrasted the two sets of results: sugar intake was down. The children speculated as to the cause, concluding: ''This happened because we're learning that too much sugar is not good for you.''</p>
        <p>SOON HUNTER ELEMENTARY School will celebrate its 50th anniversary as a school for the ''gifted.'' It's harder to get into than Harvard, with 1,500 applicants applying for 48 spots in nursery and kindergarten classes. At stake is an education - at the public's expense - that feels good and is good, with excellent teachers, an interesting curriculum, and a nice bunch of children, racially mixed to reflect the city's diversity and in accord with the school's explicit policy. Hunter has tried to find qualified children who are not middle-class, but, even with its change to the Stanford-Binet 4, a less culturally biased I.Q. test than most, the school has not succeeded. An informal 1988 survey among families whose children qualified for Hunter suggested the average income was $60,000.</p>
        <p>The process of identifying a child as gifted is a complicated and stressful one for parents, as Terry Mattei, a secretary at Hunter Elementary, well knows. It is Mattei who fields all the phone calls and sends out all the applications. Although school systems in Texas, Virginia, Maine, Iowa and elsewhere are increasingly considering ''student portfolios'' among their criteria for entrance into gifted programs, Hunter discourages it. ''We tried it one year,'' says Nancy Goldman, an educational consultant at Hunter. ''Little Jimmy sent in his tape and little Betty sent in her picture, but we couldn't figure out any way to quantify it, so we dismissed it.''</p>
        <p>Hunter does require parent evaluations, even though such evaluations favor the middle-class applicant. Parents squinch their handwriting into the tiniest size possible to fill Hunter's one-page questionnaire with examples of their child's abstract reasoning powers and analytic ability, curiosity and self-motivation, persistence and love of learning, memory and self-direction. Eventually, some even get to take their child to Hunter's ''second round,'' to a classroom whose window is covered over with paper so no one can see in. There, testers meet groups of six or seven children at a time, and carefully plumb each child's depths for signs of problem-solving ability, verbal ability, mathematical ability, creativity and leadership, says Evelyn J. Rich, associate dean of the Hunter College Campus Schools, which, in addition to Hunter College Elementary, includes Hunter College High School.</p>
        <p>But nobody's cramped handwriting will be read and no child will be invited to the room with the paper-covered windows unless the child first scores at or above the required percentile on the Stanford-Binet 4. (Last year, Hunter Elementary required an I.Q. score at the 98th percentile, and the year before that at the 97th.) The Stanford-Binet, first used in 1916, for years heavily emphasized verbal ability and knowledge of certain kinds of verbal information. Although the argument has been made for 40 years that such skills are indicative of cultural privilege rather than intelligence, use of the I.Q. test continues to be widespread. Even in its current less ''biased'' form, it remains controversial. Dismissing it as a ''hegemonic instrument,'' Jerome Bruner says, ''We know perfectly well it paints certain kinds of kids right out of the room - poor kids, late starters.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Ernest L. Boyer, president of the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching, agrees: ''As long as we end up using the wrong yardstick, we're going to be doing mischievously dangerous things to children. These instruments tend to screen out potential rather than to define it.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the I.Q. test still has the weight of the CAT scan. Forty states recommend or require its use in identifying a gifted child, and estimates are that it governs acceptance in close to 90 percent of all gifted programs in public schools.</p>
        <p>JOSEPH RENZULLI WAS among the first to say the field's exclusive emphasis on high I.Q. was misguided. He suggests instead that the combination of ''well above average'' ability (translated as 120 I.Q.), creativity and persistence would yield more.</p>
        <p>As for minorities, he says, ''We've kind of been at the lip-service level for a long time.'' At the recent convention of the National Association for Gifted Children, seminars held on ''Special Populations'' focused as much on the Learning Disabled Gifted, the Underachieving Gifted, the Rurally Isolated Gifted as on the Minority Gifted. (''Severely Gifted'' or ''Chronically Gifted,'' terms people use with a straight face, refer to those who are very, very bright.) Renzulli's approach is used in all 50 states and in every major city. His is the official approach of the Gifted and Talented Unit of the New York City Board of Education. His model, the Renzulli Enrichment Triad, is based on a step-by-step approach not unlike Tannenbaum's initial come-one-come-all approach. Type I activities expose children to new realms (say urban planning) through field trips or visits from experts. Type II activities teach students skills pertinent to the area (surveying or rudimentary map making). And Type III activities are individual or group projects (doing a study to determine the best site for a second neighborhood candy store).</p>
        <p>The appeal of Renzulli's work is that it is easily accessible and inexpensive to implement. With his emphasis on development of specific ''gifted behaviors'' rather than on a general state of ''being gifted,'' he has offered the field a way to refute charges of ''elitism.''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, inequities continue. State financing for the gifted has long been largest in the South. In 1987, Florida led the nation in funding its gifted programs with $68 million and Georgia was second, with $23 million. ''Florida, Georgia and North Carolina have had mandates to serve the gifted since the early 1960's,'' says Valerie Terry Seaberg, president of the Council of State Directors of Programs for the Gifted. Asked why, she paused. ''Well, you think about why.'' Many in the field privately say the money was to perpetuate segregated classrooms, with white students filling the gifted classes.</p>
        <p>Gifted programs have made a heavy reappearance in northern cities in the last decade. Gary Timmons, a legislative specialist for the National Education Association, speculates that in a burdened educational system, middle-class parents who might never have thought of identifying their children as gifted now hurry to do so. ''It's the politics of pressure groups,'' he explains. ''You've got to have a cause. You can't just come in and say, 'My kid isn't being served.' You've got to say, 'My gifted kid isn't being served.' '' Virtually all of New York City's school districts have gifted programs. On Manhattan's Upper West Side, in Community School District 3, seven new programs for gifted children have been instituted over the last eight years.</p>
        <p>The district's school enrollment is currently 88 percent minority. The white enrollment is heavily concentrated in classes for the gifted and in P.S. 87, the district's most middle-class school, which uses the Renzulli Triad. One school, P.S. 9, has two gifted programs. One of them, the Anderson Program, originally requiring an I.Q. at the 99th percentile, was instituted after a campaign by parents who felt the district's gifted program - requiring an I.Q. at the 95th percentile - was ''watered down.''</p>
        <p>It is commonplace within the field to act as if the cupboard were financially bare, but a peek into the cupboard suggests otherwise. Nationally, state financing specifically tagged for gifted children added up to $297 million in 1987, according to the most recent report of the Council of State Directors of Programs for the Gifted. Sometimes the money for gifted programs comes from dipping into resources meant for desegregation - through the Magnet School Assistance Program - thanks to a loophole in Federal legislation. Eleven of the 54 grantees for 1989-91 - including urban schools in California, Georgia, Michigan, New Jersey, New York and Wisconsin - stipulated that a gifted program would be included as a part of their overall desegregation plan.</p>
        <p>P.S. 163, on Manhattan's Upper West Side, is one of several schools in District 3 to receive a share of $3.25 million in Federal Magnet School Assistance funds during 1989-91. These funds were designed to ''reduce minority group isolation'' by bringing in white students. These schools also qualify for special city and state financing for the gifted. Sheri Lynn Behr, who teaches a first-grade gifted class, says her class takes more trips and has more creative and advanced math programs than other first-grade classes. In the same school, the children in the gifted program have a music teacher while others do not, because the parents raised the money. In District 18 in Brooklyn, teachers of the gifted receive more instruction on how to teach than teachers in other programs. The Hunter Campus Schools cost the public $7 million to $8 million annually.</p>
        <p>Even though some of the financing is designed to reduce ''minority group isolation,'' minority children do not have to be represented in these classes in proportion to their presence in the school community. On the national level, black children account for 16.2 percent of all school children, but only 8 percent of those are identified as gifted.</p>
        <p>IF THE I.Q. TEST GOES the way of phrenology, how are we to find, nourish and cultivate the gifts and talents in our children? Once, when I was pressing Dean Rich of the Hunter Campus Schools about the elementary school's continued use of the I.Q. test, the dean got exasperated. ''Look,'' she said, ''do you know the work of Howard Gardner? Do you know his book 'Frames of Mind'? We're interested in his work. And do you know the work of Robert Sternberg, the Yale psychologist? Him, too.'' She held the names up as if she were brandishing a cross to ward off demons.</p>
        <p>Today, these are indeed the names to brandish, along with Renzulli's. ''I was considered to be the screaming liberal of the business,'' Renzulli says. ''And then when people like Gardner and Sternberg started to say the same things I was saying, the fabled I.Q. guard in the field softened up, and I started to get more respect.'' Whether the regard for this triad of academics is sincere or cynical, they have been pushed to the head of the parade for offering a broader, more inclusive definition of intelligence - and hence giftedness.</p>
        <p>Howard Gardner, a developmental psychologist and professor at the Harvard Graduate School of Education, has become well known for his view, which first grew out of his research with children and stroke victims, that there are distinct and autonomous intelligences. Gardner calls these ''multiple intelligences'' and identifies them as logical-mathematical, linguistic, musical, spatial, bodily kinesthetic, interpersonal and intrapersonal.</p>
        <p>These days, Gardner is assured a place on every scholarly bibliography, a seat on any educational dias he chooses and a citation on every grant application. ''If we're talking about gifted,'' says a source close to the Javits bill, ''Gardner and Sternberg are the coins of the realm in the cutting-edge conversations.''</p>
        <p>''I don't have a specific interest in giftedness,'' says Gardner. ''My theory has sort of become a buzz-thing, like 'right brain-left brain.' '' Does he believe that those who buzz it understand it? ''I think it's unrealistic to think that one administrator in one school system reading one book will fully understand the theory. But,'' he adds, ''it's not something I worry about very much. I can't afford to lose too much sleep over the uses people might make of my ideas.''</p>
        <p>Robert Sternberg says, ''I just go where my interests lead me.'' In recent years, they've led him to his ''triarchic'' theory of intelligence. Essentially, Sternberg wants to look, first, at the ''components'' of intelligence and how they function; second, at intelligence in relation to experience, as in how quickly a novel task can become automatic, and third, at intelligence in relation to everyday life - not just how smart people are in a vacuum but how well they succeed in finding a match between their strengths and the slice of the world they inhabit.</p>
        <p>Both men are already affecting how children are identified as gifted. One successful Javits grant applicant cited Gardner (and, for good measure, Renzulli) for a project devoted to selecting children with talent in dance and music. They have asked for $930,000 over a three-year period.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, a few tendrils that grow out of Sternberg's theory have already found their way into Hunter Elementary's testing. One is Sternberg's interest in context. ''Vocabulary,'' he has written, ''is such a good measure of intelligence because it measures, albeit indirectly, children's ability to acquire information in context.'' Now Hunter's test, designed by Nancy Goldman, an educational consultant, may include telling children a story with selected ''nonsense'' words in place of real words and asking them to suggest what sensible words might be substituted.</p>
        <p>One year, Goldman treated the children to a concrete variation of a problem devised by Sternberg, an ''insight'' problem involving mathematical thinking, but not computational skill. In Sternberg's words, the question is: ''If you have black socks and brown socks in your drawer, mixed in the ratio of 4 to 5, how many socks will you have to take out to make sure of having a pair of the same color?''</p>
        <p>In adapting this problem, Nancy Goldman got three pairs of socks - each pair respectively adorned with the face of Goofy, Donald and Mickey - and put them in a paper bag. After making sure that the children being tested understood ''pairs,'' she asked them how many dips into the bag (without looking) it would take before they could be sure of having two socks that made a matched pair.</p>
        <p>''I can solve that easy,'' one child told Goldman. Then he took the bag and dumped all the socks out. ''Here's a matching pair'' he said. Goldman thought the child had aced the question and so, too, when he was told, did Sternberg. Some people might feel that the child had simply disregarded the rules of the question, but for Sternberg real-life creativity involves innovation, even changing the nature of the question.</p>
        <p>Would that one could as easily ace questions about bright children. For what is the point of broadening the definition of ''giftedness'' if in the end finances are not available to nurture all these gifts? All that will happen is that there will be an increased number of children competing for a fixed amount of money. All children have strengths in need of nurture, but - with all due respect to the Congress and the ''Education President,'' George Bush - a Federal budget that allocates to primary and secondary education less than 1 percent of its resources isn't putting its money where its mouth is.</p>
        <p>Still, Robert Sternberg is a practical man, all for reaching into the drawer while it's open. ''Interest in gifted children comes in cycles,'' he says, ''and I'll take my opportunities as they come. We're living in a time of chaotic problems. We're starting to lose the ozone layer. Where is the future of business, new products, science, technology, new computers? I really do think it's with the children we might call gifted.''</p>
        <p>And if their parents don't sort their socks before they put them in the drawer, by the way, the children will have to pull out no more than three socks to get a matched pair. Two, if they keep their eyes open.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
