<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times;   Race Against the Heat: Is Earth Getting Warmer?</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="339982"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON MONOXIDE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOYLE, ROBERT H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">OPPENHEIMER, MICHAEL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">DEAD HEAT: THE RACE AGAINST THE GREENHOUSE EFFECT (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DC173DF931A35757C0A966958260" item-length="1003" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times;   Race Against the Heat: Is Earth Getting Warmer?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER LEHMANN-HAUPT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>Dead Heat</p>
        <p>The Race Against the Greenhouse Effect</p>
        <p>By Michael Oppenheimer and Robert H. Boyle</p>
        <p>268 pages. A New Republic Book/Basic Books. $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>Dead Heat</p>
        <p>The Race Against the Greenhouse Effect</p>
        <p>By Michael Oppenheimer and Robert H. Boyle</p>
        <p>268 pages. A New Republic Book/Basic Books. $19.95.</p>
        <p>Dead Heat</p>
        <p>The Race Against the Greenhouse Effect</p>
        <p>By Michael Oppenheimer and Robert H. Boyle</p>
        <p>268 pages. A New Republic Book/Basic Books. $19.95.</p>
        <p>Here is a book that terrifies you, then proposes intelligent solutions to the crises it foresees. Unfortunately, or maybe fortunately, depending on your point of view, it also leaves you with an excuse to deny that the problem it addresses really exists in the first place.</p>
        <p>The two authors of ''Dead Heat'' are dedicated and articulate environmentalists. One of them, Michael Oppenheimer, is an authority on global climate who has testified before Congress and briefed such influential people as President Bush's science adviser, Dr. D. Allan Bromley, and Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher of Britain. The other, Robert H. Boyle, is a senior writer for Sports Illustrated who has published a respected book called ''Acid Rain,'' among others, and serves as president of the Hudson River Fishermen's Association.</p>
        <p>Together they write in ''Dead Heat'' that the earth's atmosphere is warming at a rate that has never before occurred in human history. This warming, they insist, is caused by the so-called greenhouse effect, or the tendency of certain gases like carbon dioxide to collect above the earth and, approximately like the glass of a greenhouse, prevent the sun's heat from escaping.</p>
        <p>If this warming is allowed to continue for another six decades or so, they predict, the earth will be visited by catastrophes the likes of which are difficult to imagine. But imagine them they do, in vivid and frightening detail that goes far beyond the familiar script of melting polar icecaps and rising sea levels, all the way to infestations of cutworms and maggots, to northward migrations of displaced workers and Florida alligators, to a plague of tropical storms and the end of human civility as we have known it.</p>
        <p>Then comes their solution. Stop burning fossil fuels. Switch to solar energy. Capture sunlight with photovoltaic cells, convert it to chemical energy, and ''store it in the hydrogen molecule, which can be viewed as a hydrocarbon without the carbon.'' In short, bring on a new wave of industrialism ''based on information technology, such as computers and fiber optics'' and ''characterized by efficient energy use; robotized, decentralized and customized production, and information services.'' Quick, before we melt.</p>
        <p>No, this conversion will not occur overnight. The authors are the first to concede this point. But having done so, they proceed to the most practical parts of their argument. A bridge to a workable future can be built on energy efficiency: longer-lasting light bulbs that use less electricity, cars that go 100 miles on a gallon of gasoline, those sorts of possible attainments.</p>
        <p>Governments can lead by creating tax incentives for more efficient energy use, the authors reason. The United States' military-industrial complex can become an environmental-industrial complex. The Cold War can yield to the war against warming. The world can finally confront the external enemy it has always needed to unite its nations.</p>
        <p>All of which would be convincing and inspiring except for one fundamental flaw in the argument. They say that the climate has warmed by approximately 1 degree Fahrenheit over the past 100 years or so, but the scientific community is far from unanimous on this conclusion, and the authors' assertion is confused by waffling over techniques of measurement and arcane talk about the vagaries of computer models.</p>
        <p>More prominently, they state: ''One symptom of the trend is that, as of 1989, 5 of the past 9 years have been the hottest in the 130-year record of global temperature measurement.'' But this assertion is based on what the authors themselves admit are earthbound measurements of varying reliability. And just this past week an Associated Press article reported that by the more accurate technique of weather satellite measurement, no long-term warming or cooling trend could yet be detected.</p>
        <p>The authors' lack of iron-clad data places them in the cruel bind of not being able to deliver decisive proof. According to their reasoning, global warming ought to be happening, considering the amount of carbon dioxide being released into the atmosphere and considering its proven contribution to the greenhouse effect. Moreover, in parallel situations involving the destruction of the ozone layer by chlorofluorocarbons and the negative impact of acid rain, dire forewarnings have eventually been confirmed by negative consequences.</p>
        <p>Most cruelly of all, from the viewpoint of the greenhouse catastrophe theorist, the two demons of global warming are considered to be its irreversibility and the lag time between its effect and its detection. As the authors vividly describe it, the public may soon be in the position of the cartoon character Wile E. Coyote just after his pursuit of the Roadrunner has carried him over the edge of a cliff. Civilization may find itself suspended in air for the interval it takes warming to work its calamitous ways. But once it does, there's no way back to safety, and the plunge into the abyss is inevitable.</p>
        <p>Some may be tempted to argue that the authors' vision of the future should be accepted regardless of whether global warming has been confirmed, if only because the steps they propose would forestall any possible threats and lead to other benefits as well, such as a shift to a more efficient global economy. But such a proposal has an Orwellian cast to it; it smacks of worshiping false gods.</p>
        <p>The fact remains that Mr. Oppenheimer and Mr. Boyle do not clinch the most basic premise of their thesis. And until scientists establish beyond doubt that the greenhouse effect is warming the earth, civilization will have the right to keep contending over the appropriate political stances of the future, be they benign or malign to the environment.</p>
        <p>Despite the force of ''Dead Heat,'' people will go on arguing whether the world is going to end in fire or in ice.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
