<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="364803"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D7153BF933A05755C0A966958260" item-length="1308" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: International</p>
        <p>2-5</p>
        <p>Lithuania approved a moratorium on its declaration of independence. The republic agreed to suspend the declaration for 100 days in exchange for negotiations with Moscow and the lifting of economic sanctions.</p>
        <p>Page 1</p>
        <p>New issue in Moscow: Televise the Congress?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: International</p>
        <p>2-5</p>
        <p>Lithuania approved a moratorium on its declaration of independence. The republic agreed to suspend the declaration for 100 days in exchange for negotiations with Moscow and the lifting of economic sanctions.</p>
        <p>Page 1</p>
        <p>New issue in Moscow: Televise the Congress?</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>2-5</p>
        <p>Lithuania approved a moratorium on its declaration of independence. The republic agreed to suspend the declaration for 100 days in exchange for negotiations with Moscow and the lifting of economic sanctions.</p>
        <p>Page 1</p>
        <p>New issue in Moscow: Televise the Congress?</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>Grocery stores in East Germany stood bare and people outside banks stood for hours as the country braced for the surrender of its economy to the West. For most, the suspense and uncertainty were tempered by anticipation of a promising new life.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Goods that Communism produced have been consigned to the past in East Germany. Virtually empty shop windows and shelves demonstrate this rejection in big cities and towns.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>The political debate in Poland is beginning to reflect a broad spectrum of interests and antagonisms. The traditional frictions between peasants, workers, intellectuals and even the cities of Gdansk and Warsaw are now finding voice.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>Production of harmful chemicals that destroy the atmosphere's protective ozone layer may be halted by the end of the century. In a landmark agreement, most of the world's nations vowed to stop producing and using chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>President Bush warned Israel that if he is ''stiff-armed'' by Jerusalem in his effort to help put Israel's own peace plan into effect, he will consider other approaches.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>Iranian President defends acceptance of quake aid</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>Deir Hanna journal: Poetry seared in the flames of passion</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>A royal wedding was held in Japan. Emperor Akihito's second son, Prince Aya, married a commoner, Kiko Kawashima, in a ceremony in a sacred Shinto shrine deep in the woods of the Imperial Palace.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>Canada's constitutional crisis has led the State Department and the C.I.A. to conclude that any loosening of Canada's federal makeup would severely affect a broad range of security, trade and other ties between Washington and Ottawa.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>Guerrillas free kidnapped U.S. miner</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>National</p>
        <p>6-10, 24</p>
        <p>The shuttle fleet was grounded. The space agency announced that it was suspending missions by the nation's three shuttles until engineers can find and fix an elusive fuel leak that has now struck two of the spaceships.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>The defects on the Hubble telescope are the latest example of the space agency's lack of attention to quality control, Senator Al Gore asserted. He is the chairman of a Senate panel on science and space.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>President Bush defended his decision to reverse his position on taxes by painting a bleak economic picture and saying he trusted Americans to understand why he was now prepared to accept higher taxes.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Bush vetoes bill to give workers's family leave</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>Food allotments would be restored for many of the poor women and children who have been cut from a Federal nutrition program under a bill approved by Congress.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Government bans mercury in interior latex paints</p>
        <p>24</p>
        <p>A television reporter has been jailed in San Antonio. He faces the prospect of months behind bars for refusing to name three people who helped him get an interview with a jailed murder suspect.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>The director of an abortion clinic in Corpus Christi, Tex., has been excommunicated from the Roman Catholic Church by her bishop, who sent her a formal decree separating her from the sacraments of the church.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>An outbreak of fires in California has resulted in at least two deaths. State officials offered rewards for information about the arsonist they say touched off some of the blazes.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Defense lawyers in the Barry trial went on the offensive, aggressively seeking to portray Mayor Barry's arrest in a videotaped undercover drug operation as overzealous conduct by the authorities.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Nelson Mandela went to Los Angeles, beginning the final leg of his American tour. He planned to attend a celebrity-studded fund-raising dinner and a concert that together were expected to raise over $1 million for the African National Congress.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>Mr. Mandela's plea for sanctions against South Africa has galvanized the continuing debate in South Africa over their effectiveness in hastening the demise of apartheid.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>Regional</p>
        <p>25-28</p>
        <p>A former Congressman's conviction was overturned by a Federal appeals court in New York. The extortion conviction of Robert Garcia of the Bronx was overturned and the case was sent back for a possible new trial.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>A $28 billion budget was agreed on by the Dinkins administration and the New York City Council after two days of intense negotiations. The budget would bring the largest annual tax increase in city history.</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>Jerseyans ask if tax increases are worth the pain</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>Dinkins reduces club task force</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>In Albany, any two chairs soon tilt at each other</p>
        <p>26</p>
        <p>Joe Doherty can apply for asylum, a Federal Appeals Court in Manhattan ruled. A former guerrilla with the Irish Republican Army, Mr. Doherty has struggled to escape a lifelong prison sentence in Britain.</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>Racketeering law applies to utilities, court rules</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>Power failure leaves commuters stranded for an hour</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>A stringent newspaper-recycling law was signed by the Suffolk County Executive. It requires newspapers with weekly circulations of 20,000 or more that are printed or sold in the county to publish only on recycled paper by the end of 1996.</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>A popular five-and-dime may close in Rye, N.Y. In a city where trendy boutiques have bloomed, the campaign to keep Woolworth's open seems to have as much to do with preserving a symbol as saving a place that sells a little bit of everything.</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>Donald J. Trump is good for a laugh. From the Doonesbury comic strip to ''Late Night With David Letterman'' to tourists in the shiny marble halls of his own buildings, people are reveling in reviling the real-estate developer.</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>Trump ousts president of shuttle</p>
        <p>31</p>
        <p>Business Day</p>
        <p>31</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>The N.E.A. rejected 4 of 18 grants recommended by the agency's theater peer panel. Each of the four who were denied grants is a performance artist whose act includes strong sexual content and each had received grants in the past.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>The Quedlinburg artworks may have been mailed home</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>Film: ''The Big Dis''</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>Music: Regina Belle sings</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>Dance: Russian provincial</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>Book: ''The Ends of Greatness''</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>British press gets warning</p>
        <p>46</p>
        <p>Sports</p>
        <p>Baseball: Mets win 11th straight</p>
        <p>43</p>
        <p>Stewart pitches no-hitter</p>
        <p>43</p>
        <p>White Sox beat Yankees</p>
        <p>45</p>
        <p>Column: Berkow on Eric Gregg</p>
        <p>43</p>
        <p>Golf: Trevino breaks a record</p>
        <p>43</p>
        <p>Obituaries</p>
        <p>29</p>
        <p>Irving Wallace, author</p>
        <p>Jerome K. Ohrbach, former president of Ohrbach's</p>
        <p>Consumer's World#30</p>
        <p>Lawn care company admits safety claims were too broad</p>
        <p>What windowless air-conditioners do - and don't</p>
        <p>Coping with pet portraiture</p>
        <p>To wash a flag, ''treat it like lingerie''</p>
        <p>Guidepost</p>
        <p>Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>Give Gorbachev credit</p>
        <p>Congress, still for sale</p>
        <p>Repairing the census</p>
        <p>An exceptional preacher</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>Flora Lewis: Mandela must judge again</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>Russell Baker: Herky-jerky bang bang</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>Ewa Zadrzynska: Nasty? Try New York</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>Stuart M. Butler: Bush's biggest blunder</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>Franjo Tudjman: All we Croations want is democracy</p>
        <p>23</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
