<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Several Governors Oppose Plan on Acid Rain</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="315927"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WYOMING</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WISCONSIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MINNESOTA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Minnesota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Wyoming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wyoming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Minnesota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D91F31F932A25752C0A966958260" item-length="676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Several Governors Oppose Plan on Acid Rain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Several governors whose states have already cut the air pollution causing acid rain today denounced a plan that would have them help pay for reducing the problem in other parts of the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Several governors whose states have already cut the air pollution causing acid rain today denounced a plan that would have them help pay for reducing the problem in other parts of the country.</p>
        <p>Several governors whose states have already cut the air pollution causing acid rain today denounced a plan that would have them help pay for reducing the problem in other parts of the country.</p>
        <p>At a news conference here, the Alliance for Acid Rain Control, a coalition of governors, environmentalists and business leaders from states that have made a substantial investment to reduce the smokestack emissions that lead to acid rain, said the plan was unfair.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to see why consumers in states that have already done their part should be paying a second time for those who have dragged their feet on environmental protection,'' said Gov. Rudy Perpich of Minnesota, co-chairman of the alliance. He was joined by Gov. Tommy G. Thompson of Wisconsin and Gov. Mike Sullivan of Wyoming.</p>
        <p>The alliance issued a study indicating that utilities in lower Midwestern states like Ohio, Indiana and Illinois that were responsible for much of the pollution charged substantially lower electric rates than power companies in states that have already acted to clean up their emissions. But government officials and utility spokesmen in that band of states disputed the rate survey findings. They also said that, under pending Federal legislation, their states would be required to bear too heavy a share of the economic burden of reducing acid rain.</p>
        <p>Legislation proposed by President Bush to strengthen the Clean Air Act, awaiting action in somewhat revised form in Congress, would require, among other things, that coal-fired power plants reduce their smokestack emissions of sulfur dioxide, a major contributor to acid rain, by 50 percent, or 10 million tons, by the year 2000.</p>
        <p>Acid rain is created when sulfur and nitrogen oxides flow up into the atmosphere and fall back to earth as acidic rain, snow, fog and dust. Much of this pollution originates in the industrial Midwest but is deposited in the Northeast and Canada, where, according to scientific studies, it destroys aquatic life, damages buildings and may play a role in damaging forests.</p>
        <p>Utilities Want Costs Shared</p>
        <p>Utilities from the lower Midwestern states, supported by their state governments, contend that acid rain is a national problem and that the cost of dealing with it should be shared by the entire nation. Several members of Congress from the Midwest have called for the addition of a cost-sharing provision to the pending legislation.</p>
        <p>Representative Philip R. Sharp, Democrat of Indiana who is chairman of the House Energy and Commerce Committee's Energy and Power Subcommittee, said the pending legislation ''is fundamentally unfair and flawed because it asks 13 states to make emissions reductions not only for themselves but for others as well.''</p>
        <p>The President opposes the cost-sharing proposal on the ground that it would be tantamount to a tax on the states with lower sulfur emissions and a subsidy for the heavily polluting states.</p>
        <p>''Asking other states to pick up the tab for their cleanup is like asking a middle class family to help a rich family absorb the financial shock of losing a tax loophole,'' Governor Thompson said.</p>
        <p>But John L. Stowell, chairman of the Coalition for Acid Rain Equity, a group of utilities and companies that is pressing for cost-sharing legislation, said that the alliance study released was misleading and that there was actually little difference in rate structures.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stowell said the study lumped industrial rates, which are lower because they are offered at a discount to heavy users, with residential rates. Because the Midwest is more heavily industrialized than other areas, the combined rates are lower, he said. But he added that residential consumers in the Midwestern states pay just as much as in other parts of the country.</p>
        <p>In addition to those at the news conference, the alliance includes the Governors of Colorado, Massachusetts, Montana, New Hampshire, New Jersey and North Carolina. Former Governors Scott M. Matheson of Utah, Anthony S. Earl of Wisconsin and Bruce E. Babbitt of Arizona are also members.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
