<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Utilities Call Proposals Feasible but Expensive</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="394394"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="THE CLEAN AIR ACT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CLEAN AIR ACT</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DD1E38F930A15753C1A966958260" item-length="901" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Utilities Call Proposals Feasible but Expensive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Coal-burning electric utility companies around the country said yesterday that they had not seen the text of the House-Senate compromise on acid rain, but that they did not believe it differed markedly from earlier proposals, which they characterized as feasible but expensive.</p>
        <p>"Everybody anticipated that something would pass," said Bruce D. Stoecklin, a spokesman for the Cincinnati Gas and Electric Company, which serves 670,000 customers in Ohio and Kentucky, and uses coal for 99 percent of its fuel. "I wouldn't say we expect to have any trouble meeting the provisions; it's just the expense," he added.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Coal-burning electric utility companies around the country said yesterday that they had not seen the text of the House-Senate compromise on acid rain, but that they did not believe it differed markedly from earlier proposals, which they characterized as feasible but expensive.</p>
        <p>"Everybody anticipated that something would pass," said Bruce D. Stoecklin, a spokesman for the Cincinnati Gas and Electric Company, which serves 670,000 customers in Ohio and Kentucky, and uses coal for 99 percent of its fuel. "I wouldn't say we expect to have any trouble meeting the provisions; it's just the expense," he added.</p>
        <p>Utility experts who opposed the provisions have said that by 2000, when the final phase takes effect, the cost could be $2 billion to $4 billion a year. Some customers would see nearly no impact because their utilities do not use coal or are already using clean-air technologies; others could see rises of 16 percent or more, utilities say.  Impact on Shareholders Seen</p>
        <p>Utilities that do not meet the deadlines in 1995 and 2000 would face fines that experts say would probably be absorbed by shareholders. "I don't know of any state that would allow a utlity to put fines for violating the law into their rates," said Charles D. Gray, assistant general counsel of the National Association of Regulatory Utility Commissioners, a Washington association of state officials.</p>
        <p>Because the cleanup costs are concentrated where the coal is, much of the increase would come in areas that now have below-average electric costs.</p>
        <p>But some companies said they were waiting to see exactly what rules emerged on toxic pollutants. There is no generally accepted effective technology for removing mercury from utility smokestacks, for instance, several said.  Not a Challenge Technically</p>
        <p>A reduction of 10 million tons a year in sulfur dioxide emissions will require utilities to wash the coal before they burn it, install smokestack "scrubbers," or burn lower-sulfur coal from more distant mines, all steps that can be accomplished without much technical challenge. Removing nitrogen oxide is harder, especially in some kinds of boilers, because it may involve changing the combustion temperature, and equipment vendors may be a bottleneck, some experts said.</p>
        <p>"The technical challenges now deal mostly with the timing, and the supply and demand," said Jerry L. Golden, manager of clean-air programs at the Tennessee Valley Authority, which burns about 34 million tons of coal a year, about 3 percent of all the coal used in the United States.</p>
        <p>"It's pretty clear that most Americans support a cleaner environment, and we'll comply with whatever law is passed out there to improve air quality in our region," he added.  Easy to Pass Costs On</p>
        <p>Utility analysts say that most companies will find it easy to pass costs through to customers. For utilities in the Middle West, where much of the high-sulfur coal is situated, the last round of big rate increases came during the era of nuclear power plant construction in the late 1970's and early 80's, said Gregory B. Enholm, an analyst at Salomon Brothers, and those increases were closely scrutinized by state regulators. This time, he added, "the regulators have a bias to be in favor of environmental expenditures."</p>
        <p>And building scrubbers, even if it raised rates, would be politically popular if it saved the jobs of local coal miners, he predicted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Enholm said that PSI Energy, the company that owns the Public Service Company of Indiana, was proportionally the most heavily affected, with 84 percent of its generating capacity requiring scrubbers. Other Companies Affected</p>
        <p>Other companies that would have to clean up more than half their plants, he added, were Allegheny Power System Inc., the Illinois Power Company and Ipalco Enterprises, which owns the Indianapolis Power and Light Company. Others heavily affected include Cipsco Industries, which owns the Central Illinois Public Service Company; the Kentucky Utilities Company; the Southern Indiana Gas and Electric Company, and the Union Electric Company.</p>
        <p>But on an absolute basis, Mr. Enhom said, the two companies facing the largest expenditures were the Southern Company and the American Electric Power Company, each of which may have to spend at least $1 billion. Interesting Regulatory Problems</p>
        <p>The new clean-air law may present interesting regulatory problems, according to Mr. Gray of the utility commissioner group, especially in emissions credits.  The idea in the legislation is that if one company can remove a ton of sulfur dioxide at its plant more cheaply than another company can do it at another plant, then the ton should be removed in the cheapest place, and the utility doing the extra work should be able to sell the credit to the other utility, thus reducing emissions at the lowest possible overall cost.</p>
        <p>If a market develops for emissions credits, shareholders and consumer advocates will probably both seek that money, Mr. Gray said. "I've heard some talk that maybe the shareholders should be entitled to a percentage of the gain from the sale of these things," Mr. Gray said. Without that, he added, the utility would have little incentive to go beyond the minimum cleanup the law requires. But, he said, "in theory, that should go to rate payers, since it's their investment in the control equipment."</p>
        <p>THE CLEAN AIR ACT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
