<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST: SATURDAY, OCTOBER, 6, 1990</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="389144"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">SUMMARY</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DB173CF935A35753C1A966958260" item-length="604" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST: SATURDAY, OCTOBER, 6, 1990</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>Britain will link the pound to other European currencies, Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher said, after years of resisting the move for fear it might restrict her Conservative Government's control over economic policy. The move was widely seen as an effort to bolster the nation's sagging economy and the Conservative Government's political standing. Britain also cut interest rates. [Page 1.]  Argentina was set back in selling its troubled telephone company when Manufacturers Hanover failed to provide the $2.2 billion worth of foreign debt paper needed to finance Bell Atlantic's purchase of half the company. The stake will be sold instead to a French-Italian consortium financed by J. P. Morgan. [33.]</p>
        <p>Markets</p>
        <p>The Treasury securities market, buffeted by strong crosscurrents, ended with shorter maturities posting moderate gains and the yield on the Government's 30-year bond unchanged at 8.78 percent. Dealers cited Congress's failure to approve a budget deficit reduction plan, which could stall future Treasury auctions. [31.]  Stocks also fluctuated wildly, but by the close the Dow Jones industrial average was down only 6.19 points for the day at 2,510.64. It was still ahead 58.16 for the week. [34.]  The price of oil rose $1.06 a barrel, to $37.99, on the New York Mercantile Exchange on harsh words from Iraq, but it was $1.52 lower for the week on hope for a diplomatic solution. [32.]  The surging British pound dominated foreign exchange trading, jumping to $1.9455 from $1.9185 before Mrs. Thatcher's announcement. The dollar rose against most other currencies. [40.]  Pork belly futures prices neared records on fears of a shortage. [40.]</p>
        <p>Companies</p>
        <p>Sun Microsystems put tight spending controls and a hiring freeze into place this week. [31.]  Hewlett-Packard announced a reorganization intended to streamline its computer business and prepare for succession at the top with a new chief executive's office. [33.]  A Congressional committee questioned the AV-8B Harrier's safety. McDonnell Douglas makes the plane for the Marines. [33.]  Travelers unexpectedly cut its dividend to 40 cents a share from 60 cents and said it planned to report losses. [33.]</p>
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>The nation's unemployment rate rose for the third straight month, to 5.7 percent in September, up one-tenth of a point. the Labor Department reported. In a report that left few analysts doubting that a recession was either imminent or had already begun, it also said that jobs in manufacturing tumbled by a further 66,000, the second-biggest loss since factory employment began to fall in early 1989. A total of 520,000 such jobs have disappeared since then. [1.]  Frederick H. Joseph, former chief executive of Drexel Burnham Lambert, may be called by Government prosecutors to testify against Michael R. Milken, people involved said. [31.]  Charles H. Keating Jr. pleaded not guilty to charges that he defrauded customers of the Lincoln Savings and Loan Association by selling them ''junk'' bonds that eventually became worthless. [31.]  A bill curbing the imports of textiles and shoes was vetoed by President Bush. [42.]</p>
        <p>Today's Columns</p>
        <p>Some withdrawals from tax-deferred retirement accounts are being recommended because of fear tax rates could rise and to take advantage of favorable state tax laws. Your Money. [32.]  Inventors have patented hair-care products to help people maintain the proper pH balance, despite acid rain, air pollution and the effects on hair of dyes and other products. Patents. [32.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
