<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All About/Meteorological Services;   The Diverse New Industry of Private Weather Forecasting</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="377612"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDUSTRY PROFILES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL WEATHER SERVICE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">COHEN, NOAM S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DC1539F93AA2575BC0A966958260" item-length="1765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All About/Meteorological Services;   The Diverse New Industry of Private Weather Forecasting</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NOAM COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COHEN, NOAM S</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Wertfilms Inc. chose to shoot Nissan commercials in Seattle because it wanted skies that were overcast but not on the verge of a deluge. So the producers called Northwest Weathernet Inc., a private company that could render specific forecasts. ''Five or ten miles can make a difference,'' said Phil Breuser, the vice president of Northwest Weathernet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Wertfilms Inc. chose to shoot Nissan commercials in Seattle because it wanted skies that were overcast but not on the verge of a deluge. So the producers called Northwest Weathernet Inc., a private company that could render specific forecasts. ''Five or ten miles can make a difference,'' said Phil Breuser, the vice president of Northwest Weathernet.</p>
        <p>Wertfilms Inc. chose to shoot Nissan commercials in Seattle because it wanted skies that were overcast but not on the verge of a deluge. So the producers called Northwest Weathernet Inc., a private company that could render specific forecasts. ''Five or ten miles can make a difference,'' said Phil Breuser, the vice president of Northwest Weathernet. ''We can go hour-by-hour if they want.''</p>
        <p>Private weather services, long used by fliers, farmers and shippers, are exploiting broad new markets. Although their annual revenues still total only about $200 million a year, many major industries depend on their work. Private meteorologists influence commodity prices, the outcome of lawsuits and government policy on global warming. They study where and whether new power plants should be built, and some - called forensic meteorologists - testify on the causes of airplane crashes.</p>
        <p>On radio and television, Accu-Weather and the Weather Channel feed the growing demand for weather news. And Europeans, frustrated by the expense of their own government weather services, sometimes buy information in the United States.</p>
        <p>Private weather companies have new opportunities because the National Weather Service wants to confine itself to general forecasts and emergency warnings. For other, more specific information, the agency plans to refer callers elsewhere. ''The policy of the Administration has been to encourage private meteorology,'' said Louis J. Boezi, a deputy director of the service.</p>
        <p>Under proposed new guidelines, the agency would shun what it calls ''specialized services.'' So someone asking whether the outlook for temperature, humidity and rain would be right for pouring a concrete foundation in the middle of next week would be told to call a private company. These companies typically charge $100 an hour, with the cost for a single forecast running between $25 and $75.</p>
        <p>Military Roots</p>
        <p>Filling a Niche Left by Government</p>
        <p>Private weather services are at least as old as the Old Farmer's Almanac, first published in 1792. But the modern industry began at the end of World War II, when meteorologists trained in the military started their own businesses to serve shipping and aviation. In 1955, the American Meteorological Society's directory listed 22 companies. Now it lists 112. Industry executives say the business is growing about 5 percent annually.</p>
        <p>About 30 percent of the growth in forecasting assignments has come from utilities, somewhat less than 30 percent from transportation and about 20 percent from construction, says Jeffrey C. Smith, executive director of the Commercial Weather Services Association, a trade group. Utilities need environmental advice and early warnings of when foul weather might bring down transmission lines. Construction crews need to have enough notice of storms to come down from high-rise projects.</p>
        <p>The increasing complexity of forecasts, and government's more restricted role, help increase revenues for private services. But sales remain dependent on the economy. ''We're a service industry,'' said Austin Dooley, general manager of the New York office of Oceanroutes Inc., which plans shipping routes. ''If cargo isn't produced and exported, and if the ships aren't sailing, we aren't going to have any business.''</p>
        <p>Air-Quality Specialists</p>
        <p>A New Emphasis On the Environment</p>
        <p>When North American Weather Consultants of Salt Lake City was founded in 1950, it provided forecasts and cloud-seeding for farmers. Now the company is more concerned about artificial weather of another sort: the pollution that issues from plants, especially those owned by utilities.</p>
        <p>Only two companies listed air quality as their specialty in the American Meteorological Society's 1965 directory. This year, 44 did.</p>
        <p>Gauging the amount of pollution escaping from a power plant smokestack is only half the task, weather services say. Determining how the emissions are dispersed and how they interact with other pollutants is also crucial. A power plant that would be fine in Omaha might fail to meet Federal standards in Los Angeles. ''Meteorology controls, to a large extent, the pollution in the air,'' said Don A. Griffith, a vice president at North American. Power companies also consult with meteorologists to decide on how much their emissions need cleaning up.</p>
        <p>North American's own fortunes have been a barometer of the nation's environmental concern. The company only entered the air-quality business in the middle 1960's. The Clean Air Act was passed in 1970, and air quality consulting grew to become two-thirds of the company's business. But in the early 1980's, when emissions enforcement eased up and power plant construction slowed, it shed nearly 40 of its 60 employees.</p>
        <p>Then came oil spills and a revived environmental movement. In the last few years, North American has begun expanding again, especially to help coal-generated power plants meet new governmentstandards. But so many pollution experts quit in the 1980's that the company cannot grow as quickly as it wants. ''We can hardly hire qualified people in air pollution anymore,'' said Keith J. Brown, the company president.</p>
        <p>He says that North American's revenues will approach $3 million this year, about half from pollution work - a ratio he expects to rise to 75 percent in another few years. As Mr. Brown said, ''The 90's is the decade of the environment.''</p>
        <p>An Insatiable Public</p>
        <p>The Appetite For Weather News</p>
        <p>For two private weather forecasters, the broadcasting business seems to be raining money. Accu-Weather Inc. in State College, Pa., furnishes forecasts for about 3,000 clients in radio, television and other industries. The Weather Channel is available on cable in 45 million homes.</p>
        <p>Accu-Weather, which considers itself the nation's largest private forecasting company, refuses to disclose its revenues but says that it has been growing at 10 percent a year. Founded by Joel Myers when he was a graduate student at Pennsylvania State University, Accu-Weather now has 225 employees.</p>
        <p>Accu-Weather provides not only the forecasts for 125 radio stations and 200 television stations, but also about 40 meteorologists to explain the news on the air. Dr. Myers asserts that Accu-Weather's success comes from a recognizable name and better forecasts than the National Weather Service. The service declined to respond.</p>
        <p>But Accu-Weather also owes some of its growth to the Weather Service's decisions in recent years to keep its own forecasters off the air. Alaska is one of the few places left where a Government weatherman delivers television and radio forecasts; river ice reports for fishermen are standard. Elsewhere, the Weather Service provides only the general forecasts that television and radio announcers can rip and read.</p>
        <p>The Weather Service also does not illustrate its forecasts with whiz-bang graphics, leaving more opportunities for Accu-Weather and the Weather Channel. The only cable network devoted to round-the-clock weather, the Weather Channel has artists and computer experts to keep finding flashier ways of presenting the weather. Their latest: three-dimensional renderings of storm systems.</p>
        <p>Media analysts say that the Weather Channel, founded in 1982 and owned by Landmark Communications Inc. of Norfolk, Va., is enjoying steady growth. Paul Kagan Associates. estimates its 1989 revenues at $31.5 million, with operating cash flow, or profits before taxes and depreciation, of $10 million. This year, Paul Kagan projects cash flow of $12 million on revenues of $35.3 million.</p>
        <p>The National Weather Service has been one of the channel's greatest supporters. The agency has computer-coded its local forecasts so the channel could present each area with its own weather report. And the Weather Service makes certain that the Weather Channel receives weather warnings and watches the moment they are issued.</p>
        <p>But just as specialized services have arisen to fill out the details in the National Weather Service forecasts, specialized cable channels - offering local reports for aviators or farmers, perhaps - might someday supplement the Weather Channel. ''I think you will see people popping up with this,'' said Edward Gross, the constituent affairs chief for the National Weather Service. But some might prefer receiving specialized forecasts on a different screen than their television, he added. ''The question is whether cable will satisfy those needs or the home computer will.''</p>
        <p>THE BUSINESS IN EUROPE</p>
        <p>The few private weather forecasting companies in Europe - an estimated 10 - find they get almost as much encouragement from America as at home. Harry A. Otten, whose Meteo Consult BV in 1986 became the first private forecaster in the Netherlands, was looking to package weather data for broadcasting, agricultural and energy companies. But the fees he was charged by the Dutch Government were hefty.</p>
        <p>''In the United States, it is thought that taxpayers pay for the data, so they should be able to get all the data,'' he said. ''In Europe, it is thought that taxpayers pay for the data, so they should not be able to make a profit from it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Otten initially paid his Government $600,000 a year, but threatened to get his information far less expensively by computer and telephone from private American services. (British weather companies are also obtaining information from the United States that is far cheaper than what's available at home.) By 1988, the Government had cut its price to $200,000. It was not a total victory, however. Mr. Otten says that companies forecasting weather in the United States can get good information for a tenth the price.</p>
        <p>Meteo Consult, with a staff of 16, still has the Government as its major competitor. The Dutch agency provides forecasts tailored to specific business needs - for a fee. ''Sometimes the Government is cheaper, but we have to be more accurate,'' Mr. Otten said.</p>
        <p>Meteo Consult's enterprise has its roots in the United States. Mr. Otten, who had worked for the Royal Netherlands Meteorological Institute as a forecaster and later as a television weatherman, took a year-long sabbatical at Pennsylvania State University. There, he consulted for Accu-Weather and came up with the idea of bringing private forecasting to the Netherlands.</p>
        <p>With trade barriers coming down in the European Community, Mr. Otten feels, governments will be less able to throttle private weather companies. The growth of private meteorology in Europe might be slow, but as Mr. Otten said, ''Accu-Weather didn't have 16 employees after its first five years.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
