<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Denies Putting Off Action On Averting Global Climate Shift</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="345085"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD71131F93AA25757C0A966958260" item-length="675" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Denies Putting Off Action On Averting Global Climate Shift</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush, responding to criticism that the United States had delayed taking concrete steps to address the threat of global warming linked to pollution, said today, ''We have never considered research a substitute for action.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush, responding to criticism that the United States had delayed taking concrete steps to address the threat of global warming linked to pollution, said today, ''We have never considered research a substitute for action.''</p>
        <p>President Bush, responding to criticism that the United States had delayed taking concrete steps to address the threat of global warming linked to pollution, said today, ''We have never considered research a substitute for action.''</p>
        <p>Closing a two-day White House conference on the issue, Mr. Bush said: ''To those who suggest we're only trying to balance economic growth and environmental protection, I say they miss the point. We are calling for an entirely new way of thinking, to achieve both while compromising neither, by applying the power of the marketplace in the service of the environment.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also proposed a series of steps for integrating international responses to the issue of global climate change. They included an international ''charter'' for cooperation in science and economics related to global change, a statement of principles to guide such research, the creation of international research institutes and a communications network to monitor global changes.</p>
        <p>Criticism From Europeans</p>
        <p>Although Administration officials said the drafting of the speech had begun some time ago, Mr. Bush's remarks clearly addressed concerns voiced Tuesday by European delegates to the 18-nation conference who complained that the United States only wanted to discuss the scientific and economic uncertainties surrounding the issue rather than specific remedial action.</p>
        <p>White House officials warned on Tuesday of the potentially huge cost of reducing the pollution that many scientists believe will raise the temperature of the earth's surface in the next century. They said more research was needed into the economic and scientific uncertainties.</p>
        <p>At today's session, a document was inadvertently released, revealing specific proposals made by Mr. Bush later in the day. The document was written in the form of a resolution, seemingly for the approval of the conference.</p>
        <p>Many of the delegates protested vigorously when they were given the document, saying they could not approve such sweeping proposals with only a short time to study them. Several commented that the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change convened by the United Nations was doing a good job and that there was no need to create more institutions to address the problem.</p>
        <p>Within an hour, the United States re-issued the paper with a cover sheet saying that it had been released in error and was not meant to be acted on by this conference.</p>
        <p>White House officials were uneasy over the unauthorized release to reporters of a document containing ''talking points'' for use by American delegates to the conference. Among the points listed under ''debates to avoid'' was the statement that it was ''not beneficial to discuss whether there is or is not'' global warming or how much or how little warming. ''In the eyes of the public,'' it went on, ''we will lose this debate. A better approach is to raise the many uncertainties that need to be better understood on this issue.''</p>
        <p>Suspicions of Environmentalists</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the President's science adviser, D. Allan Bromley, a co-chairman of the conference, said the talking points had been prepared by the conference staff to assist the American delegation.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists who provided the document to reporters said it confirmed their suspicions that the conference was called by the White House to plead scientific uncertainty as an excuse for delaying action to reduce emissions of carbon dioxide and other industrial gases in the atmosphere. Such gases, many scientists contend, will cause a substantial warming of the globe because they retain infrared radiation from the sun that would otherwise be reflected back into space.</p>
        <p>Several European officials praised Mr. Bush's speech today, saying it was an improvement over his remarks on Tuesday, which stressed the need for more research. Bert Bolin of Sweden, the chairman of the intergovernmental panel, said, ''I take the President's speech to be a clear signal to proceed very vigorously with what we are trying to do with the I.P.C.C.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
