<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Step Is Seen Toward Altering Photosynthesis</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="397452"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDA1E3BF931A35752C1A966958260" item-length="753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Step Is Seen Toward Altering Photosynthesis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a development that could eventually enable molecular biologists to manipulate a process basic to the maintenance of life, scientists have successfully inserted genetic material into the minute structures in which photosynthesis takes place in the cells of higher plants.</p>
        <p>If the technique does make it possible to manipulate the photosynthetic structures genetically, scientists say, it could lead to the development of bigger and more vigorous plants more readily.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a development that could eventually enable molecular biologists to manipulate a process basic to the maintenance of life, scientists have successfully inserted genetic material into the minute structures in which photosynthesis takes place in the cells of higher plants.</p>
        <p>If the technique does make it possible to manipulate the photosynthetic structures genetically, scientists say, it could lead to the development of bigger and more vigorous plants more readily.</p>
        <p>Researchers have been able to insert genes in the nuclei of plant cells since 1982, and most agricultural bioengineering works through this method of genetic transformation. But processes central to plant growth and productivity are controlled by genes in chloroplasts -- chlorophyll-containing structures in cell tissue outside the nucleus that are the seat of photosynthesis. Previous Efforts Frustrated</p>
        <p>Three years ago, scientists introduced foreign DNA, the basic genetic material, into the chloroplasts of single-celled algae. But because higher plants have many more chloroplasts and much more genetic material, efforts to transform their chloroplasts genetically have been frustrated.</p>
        <p>Now, in an experiment reported yesterday in The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, a team of scientists at Rutgers University's Waksman Institute led by Dr. Pal Maliga has for the first time inserted foreign DNA into the chloroplasts of tobacco plants. The DNA was successfully and stably integrated into the chloroplasts' genetic structure and then passed on, through seeds, to offspring plants.</p>
        <p>"It is a very important contribution," said Dr. John Boynton of Duke University, a leader of the team that first introduced foreign genes into algae three years ago. "We're now in a position to ask very fundamental questions" involving genetic manipulation of the process through which higher plants use sunlight to convert carbon dioxide to carbohydrates, he added. These carbohydrates, along with those produced by photosynthesis in microscopic plants like algae, are the basis of the planetary food chain.</p>
        <p>"We haven't been able to ask those questions because we haven't been able to manipulate the gene and then put it back in the cell to assess its function," he said.</p>
        <p>The Rutgers team applied a new technique in which microscopic particles are coated with DNA from outside the chloroplast and then shot into the chloroplast's genes with a special gun. The chloroplasts, contained in cells in a tissue culture, were bombarded with the coated particles.</p>
        <p>Plants were then regenerated from cells in which the genetic transformation was complete and stable, and the new plants produced seeds that contained the transformed genes.</p>
        <p>The next step, said Dr. Maliga, is to insert full genes into the chloroplasts. By doing so, he said, the team hopes to be able to implant genes in chloroplasts that would confer resistance to herbicides on the entire plant.</p>
        <p>If successful, this technique could enable scientists to bioengineer crops that would resist herbicides used to kill weeds, while still killing the weeds. This would be possible, Dr. Maliga said, because chloroplasts are not transmitted by pollen and could not affect the weeds. "If the pollen is flying off from the field and is fertilizing weeds outside the plot or in the plot, you can never make them resistant to the herbicide," he said.  Toward Better Photosynthesis</p>
        <p>But the ultimate goal, said Dr. Maliga and Dr. Boynton, is genetic manipulation of the process of photosynthesis. One basic question now open to investigation, said Dr. Boynton, is this: "Has nature selected the most efficient photosynthetic process or not?" If not, he said, it might well be possible to improve the process.</p>
        <p>For instance, he said, a particular enzyme that is fundamental to photosynthesis, rubisco for short, might now become a "logical target" for investigation and possibly for improvement through genetic manipulation.</p>
        <p>Rubisco is central to the first step in photosynthesis, in that it catalyzes carbon dioxide, the basic building block of chemical energy in the plant, and other chemicals.</p>
        <p>The prospects for improving rubisco's action through genetic engineering is worth testing, he said, adding that such manipulation might, for instance, enable scientists to cause plants to over-produce rubisco. "Presumably," he said, "you'd get a higher photosynthetic rate with lower carbon-dioxide concentrations." This would mean faster growth and bigger plants.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
