<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Acid Rain: Plenty Bad Enough</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="321545"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SULFUR DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DF1F3FF93AA15752C0A966958260" item-length="488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Acid Rain: Plenty Bad Enough</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The rain that falls over much of the northeastern United States is mildly acidic from pollutant gases. Like many weak poisons, its effects are subtle and hard to pinpoint. The preliminary results of a monumental 10-year Federal study now establish just how harmful this acid deluge is. They lend urgency to proposals now before</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The rain that falls over much of the northeastern United States is mildly acidic from pollutant gases. Like many weak poisons, its effects are subtle and hard to pinpoint. The preliminary results of a monumental 10-year Federal study now establish just how harmful this acid deluge is. They lend urgency to proposals now before</p>
        <p>The rain that falls over much of the northeastern United States is mildly acidic from pollutant gases. Like many weak poisons, its effects are subtle and hard to pinpoint. The preliminary results of a monumental 10-year Federal study now establish just how harmful this acid deluge is. They lend urgency to proposals now before Congress that coal-burning utilities sharply cut their emissions of acrid gases.</p>
        <p>The $500 million study - known as the National Acid Precipitation Assessment Program - began in 1980 and seven years later produced a much criticized interim report. In accord with the Reagan Administration's belief that acid rain was not a serious problem, the interim study indicated that no more lakes were likely to become acidified and damage to trees was highly unlikely.</p>
        <p>Drafts of the final report, as William Stevens has reported in The Times, paint a darker picture. Acid rain is not about to cause the sudden ecological collapse predicted by some accounts in the early 1980's. Lakes are acidifying over decades, not seasons. But acid rain is indeed a serious threat to the ecology, especially in regions where the soil lacks a natural capacity for neutralizing acid.</p>
        <p>In the southwestern Adirondacks, 11 percent of lakes are already acidified and 36 percent in danger of becoming so. In Appalachia, the Atlantic coastal plain, and parts of Wisconsin and Michigan, some 10 percent of lakes and streams have already been acidified past the point at which ecological damage is likely.</p>
        <p>The draft report does not settle the longstanding issue of the widespread decline in some American forests. It finds no evidence to link forest decline in North America to acid rain, other than for high-altitude red spruce. With these trees, acid rain seems to worsen natural stresses. But acid rain may reduce the fertility of some forest soils over the long term.</p>
        <p>Opponents of acid rain control have argued that all the lakes likely to go acid have already done so, and that reducing acid rain won't revive any of them. But James Mahoney, director of the study, told a Senate committee last year that more streams could acidify at current levels of pollution. And, significantly, he said that cutting pollutants by 30 percent would allow the recovery of half the acidified lakes in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>The National Assessment will not be completed until later this year, but the politics of acid rain seem to have been settled, at least in broad outline. President Bush has proposed reducing sulfur di-oxide emissions by 10 million tons each year. Congress and even electric utilities have accepted the goal and are now arguing about how to implement it.</p>
        <p>Political solutions should follow, not precede, scientific conclusions, especially conclusions reached at the cost of $500 million. Fortunately, the National Acid Precipitation Assessment Program has already provided ample evidence for acting to curb acid rain.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
