<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="323675"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DD143FF936A35751C0A966958260" item-length="1351" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A2-13</p>
        <p>Thousands demonstrated in Moscow, parading to the Kremlin walls to demand that the Communist Party surrender its monopoly on political power. It was the largest unofficial demonstration in more than 60 years.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: Mikhail Gorbachev has deftly slipped out of two politically perilous situations, in Lithuania and Azerbaijan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A2-13</p>
        <p>Thousands demonstrated in Moscow, parading to the Kremlin walls to demand that the Communist Party surrender its monopoly on political power. It was the largest unofficial demonstration in more than 60 years.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: Mikhail Gorbachev has deftly slipped out of two politically perilous situations, in Lithuania and Azerbaijan.</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A2-13</p>
        <p>Thousands demonstrated in Moscow, parading to the Kremlin walls to demand that the Communist Party surrender its monopoly on political power. It was the largest unofficial demonstration in more than 60 years.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: Mikhail Gorbachev has deftly slipped out of two politically perilous situations, in Lithuania and Azerbaijan. Today, he heads into another, the Communist Party conference in Moscow.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Central Committee: Communist Party nerve center</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Pact between Armenians and Azerbaijanis quickly falters</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>An approach to end the Afghan war that would allow President Najibullah to remain in power for a transitional period before having to step down is expected to be proposed to the Soviets by Secretary of State James Baker.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A veteran Romanian leader resigned. It was another sign that the ruling Council of National Salvation is groping for political equilibrium after a tumultuous week.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Democracy dazes some Romanians</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Slovenia breaks from Yugoslav Communist Party</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Five Eastern European leaders met in Switzerland for an extraordinary debate on Europe's future, but the meeting was overshadowed by anxiety over the prospect of German reunification.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Poland's army of the unemployed, like those sprouting throughout Eastern Europe, may be too sanguine about its job prospects, unable to grasp that more layoffs are likely, economists say.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Rights groups gather in Czechoslovakia to discuss changes</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>A tour bus was attacked near Cairo by assailants armed with assault rifles and grenades. At least eight Israelis were killed and 17 others wounded. A group calling itself the Defense for the Oppressed of Egypt's Prisons claimed responsibility.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Israel military speculates on attackers of tour bus</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>News analysis: Shamir's words at home cause a storm abroad</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Fighting between Christian factions vying for control of the 300-square-mile Christian enclave in Lebanon entered its sixth day. At least 20 people were reported killed.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Pact is signed to ease Mexico's debt burden</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Blacks still face major obstacles to the negotiations for a ''new democratic constitution'' that the South African President F. W. de Klerk has promised. But the Government moved swiftly to carry out some of his pledges.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Winnie Mandela forsees obstacles for husband's release</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>South African Communist leader says changes must go further</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Africa's leaders offer some measured praise</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>South Africa's shift unlikely to spur quick reinvestment</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Shanghai Journal: A writer in a land of controlled thought</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>National</p>
        <p>A14-17, B7-9</p>
        <p>Thousands of youths are runaways or ''throwaways,'' forced out of their homes each year by drug abuse, financial strains and the problems of single-parent homes. The Goverment has made its first attempt at counting them.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Pregnant women who abuse drugs are being prosecuted for abusing their children. Prosecutors say they must halt the rate of babies born to addicted mothers, but health and civil liberties groups say it is counterproductive to treat a health problem as a legal one.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>The causes of domestic violence remain elusive. A new study has failed to find any patterns of behavior that could help the police anticipate fatal incidents.</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Insurance for many occupations, from bartender and gas-station attendant to taxi driver and beautician, is being systematically denied by health insurance carriers in an effort to avoid losses.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Retraining workers who lose jobs when industries shrink or fold is an idea more often talked about than done. In Arkansas, a retraining program is being undone by the company that brought it into being.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Political Memo: The Democrats, newly confident, are preparing their message for the 90's. In the Reagan era, they seemed out of synch with the times; now they are moving the debate back to their own turf.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>The Housing Secretary, Jack Kemp, has awakened the once somnolent Department of Housing and Urban Development with an infusion of spirit and a sense of purpose, though uncertainty remains.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>Sununu says he revised Bush's speech on global warming</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>U.S. tells Virginia military academy to accept women</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Mayor Sidney Barthelemy of New Orleans wins re-election</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Los Angeles Journal: Bigger. Richer. Taller. It's Trump!</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Regional</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>The enigma of 110 Livingston Street, the Brooklyn address of the Board of Education's headquarters, is that its 5,200 workers seem trapped in the bureaucratic labyrinth they are accused of creating.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Child labor is still widespread in New York City, officials say. From the garment district and Chinatown to basement sweatshops in the suburbs, at least 7,500 children work illegally in the garment industry alone.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Visitors to New York City declined slightly in 1989, and tourism experts worry that the statistics portend a long slide for the industry.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>The crash of Avianca Flight 52 came after what appeared to be a routine flight. As the jetliner neared Kennedy International Airport, the crew had reliable information about how much fuel was on board. Still it ran out and went down.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Bishop Austin Vaughan is amazed, he says, at the furor he sparked with his comment from jail that Gov. Mario Cuomo was ''in serious risk of going to hell'' for not trying to limit abortion rights.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>The woman who abducted a baby from the maternity ward of a Brooklyn hospital on Saturday has been arrested, police officials said. The baby was not harmed.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Reporter's Notebook: Gotti jurors' guarded moments</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Signs raised on a Queens pier to ward off nuptials</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>A program for families of the critically ill</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>SportsMonday</p>
        <p>Baseball: Mets back Strawberry</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Strawberry: Problems amid potential</p>
        <p>C6</p>
        <p>Jackson loses in arbitration</p>
        <p>C6</p>
        <p>Basketball: Three-pointer an N.B.A. fixture</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Ohio State upsets Louisville</p>
        <p>C3</p>
        <p>Excitement in Southwest Conference</p>
        <p>C3</p>
        <p>Wary Knicks gear for Miami</p>
        <p>C9</p>
        <p>76ers win 11th straight</p>
        <p>C9</p>
        <p>Boxing: Camacho wins fans</p>
        <p>C7</p>
        <p>Column: Berkow on Strawberry</p>
        <p>C6</p>
        <p>Football: Cowboy owner under scrutiny in gas deal</p>
        <p>C3</p>
        <p>Hockey: Islanders top Sabres, 1-0</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Rangers edge North Stars</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Bruins find scorer in Neely</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Horse Racing: Dancing Spree wins</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Soccer: Drug issue amid Colombian soccer</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>Hard times in the dance world</p>
        <p>C11</p>
        <p>Hollywood invades Sundance</p>
        <p>C11</p>
        <p>Salman Rushdie speaks out</p>
        <p>C11</p>
        <p>Theater: ''Zora Neale Hurston''</p>
        <p>C14</p>
        <p>Music: By Philip Glass</p>
        <p>C12</p>
        <p>Musicians' recording contract</p>
        <p>C14</p>
        <p>Dance: Balanchine's ''Source''</p>
        <p>C14</p>
        <p>Word and Image: ''Homework,'' a novel</p>
        <p>C18</p>
        <p>''Murder in Mississippi''</p>
        <p>C18</p>
        <p>Panel explores drug abuse</p>
        <p>C18</p>
        <p>Obituaries</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>Kate Simon, writer</p>
        <p>Carroll V. Newsom, former N.Y.U. president</p>
        <p>Curtiss Frank, former mayor of Yonkers</p>
        <p>Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Year, hour, of the child</p>
        <p>Crack, out of the bottle</p>
        <p>Nicholas Wade: Nuclear winter</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Tom Wicker: After lyrics, what?</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>William Safire: Staying a superpower</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Victor Gilinsky: Send uranium to Romania?</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Samuel Lipman: The subway isn't a forum</p>
        <p>A19</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
