<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Acid Rain Report Unleashes a Torrent of Criticism</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="336258"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREES AND SHRUBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DF1638F933A15750C0A966958260" item-length="1798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Acid Rain Report Unleashes a Torrent of Criticism</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A comprehensive Federal report that was supposed to resolve the issue of how much damage is caused to forests by acid rain has come under criticism from some distinguished scientists who are reviewing it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A comprehensive Federal report that was supposed to resolve the issue of how much damage is caused to forests by acid rain has come under criticism from some distinguished scientists who are reviewing it.</p>
        <p>A comprehensive Federal report that was supposed to resolve the issue of how much damage is caused to forests by acid rain has come under criticism from some distinguished scientists who are reviewing it.</p>
        <p>The critics said that the report gave an incorrect impression that air pollution was not causing any large-scale problems for forest ecosystems. They also said that the report, still in draft form, ignored a number of studies suggesting serious air pollution problems.</p>
        <p>But other experts contend that the general conclusion of the report is essentially right. The report concluded that with the exception of damage to red spruce at high elevations in the East, forests in the United States are not suffering serious damage from acid rain.</p>
        <p>Clean Air Legislation</p>
        <p>The debate over the draft report has become important because Congress is now considering new clean air legislation and will almost certainly pass a new clean air law before the report can be issued in final form this summer or fall.</p>
        <p>The document on forest damage is one part of the final draft of a Federal assessment of current scientific knowledge about the effects of acid rain on lakes and streams, forests, health, atmospheric visibility and materials. After it is reviewed, the assessment will be the basis of a separate report, to be issued in September, on strategies for dealing with acid rain.</p>
        <p>Dr. James R. Mahoney, director of the National Acid Precipitation Assessment Program, or Napap, which coordinated the Federal research effort, said that he agreed with some of the reviewer comments about the forest problem and that the final report would probably be changed to reflect them. He said that there had been comments in ''both directions,'' with some reviewers saying, ''We don't have evidence of damage and we shouldn't try to find something that isn't there.''</p>
        <p>But lobbyists are using the draft report to try to influence the debate over legislation to amend the Clean Air Act of 1970 that is on the Senate floor. In the House, the Energy and Commerce Committee began drafting new clean-air legislation last week. Laws passed this year will affect the way the nation deals with air pollution problems for at least the next decade.</p>
        <p>Diane Smiraldo, a spokeswoman for the Edison Electric Institute, which represents the private electric utility industry, said the Napap report ''lends credence to our argument that the industry should be given flexibility in dealing with acid rain.'' She said the study ''shows that rain is causing damage but much less than anticipated.''</p>
        <p>Several senators have referred to the draft report in questioning whether the high cost of an acid-rain control program was proportionate to the seriousness of the problem.</p>
        <p>Napap was created 10 years ago when Congress ordered that an interagency Federal group be set up to study the nature and environmental consequences of acidic air pollution from coal-powered electricity plants and other sources. The idea was to enable lawmakers to make informed decisions when they came to vote on the problem.</p>
        <p>The report now being reviewed is the final draft, completed at a cost of nearly $500 million. It examines the effects of other pollutants, like ozone, as well as acid deposits, and it concludes that air pollution causes far less environmental damage than has been feared.</p>
        <p>An interim report issued by the study group in 1987, before Dr. Mahoney became director, was sharply criticized by many scientists. They contended that it tailored research findings into conclusions that matched the political goals of the Reagan Administration, which opposed new controls on air pollution. No such criticism has been leveled at the 28-volume final draft, which has been generally praised as a sound scientific document.</p>
        <p>There is, however, some unhappiness among scientists with the volume dealing with forest health and productivity in the United States and Canada.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ellis B. Cowling, associate for research at North Carolina State University's College of Forest Resources, said in a telephone interview: ''The tone is that we don't have a problem except in southern California, and with red spruce at high altitudes. That is not a fair statement of the state of scientific knowledge.'' He added, ''Perhaps the authors were a bit too hasty in reaching conclusions.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Cowling, who is highly regarded by colleagues as a conservative, solid scientist, wrote a memorandum to the authors of the forest health volume. He offered a series of suggestions for changing the wording of conclusions in ways that he said would reflect the state of science more accurately.</p>
        <p>The first of those would change a finding that stated, ''The vast majority of forests in the United States and Canada are not affected by decline.'' To be more consistent with the data, Dr. Cowling said, the conclusion should read: ''Most forests in the United States do not show unusual visible symptoms of stress, marked decreases in the rate of growth or significant increases in mortality.''</p>
        <p>Just because symptoms of forest decline are not currently visible, Dr. Cowling argued, does not rule out the possibility that they are under way.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cowling also urged that more studies be incorporated into the final report, including work by Dr. Robert Bruck, a plant pathologist at North Carolina State University who has done extensive research on tree damage in the Appalachians and believes that air pollution is seriously affecting the forests. Dr. Bruck said that he had submitted a number of papers on his work at the request of the Environmental Protection Agency and Agriculture Department, both participants in the Napap process, but that none were included among the roughly 400 studies in the report's list of references.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gerard Hertel, national program manager of the Forest Response Program, a joint research effort of the United States Forest Service and the Environmental Protection Agency, said the Napap forest report needed ''beefing up.''</p>
        <p>He noted that only 31 lines were devoted to what was happening to Southern forests, despite reports by Dr. Bruck and others of severe problems there. He also said the report gave short shrift to recently emerging evidence that pollution might be affecting hardwood forests in the East.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hertel and Dr. Jay S. Jacobson, a plant physiologist with the Boyce Thompson Institute at Cornell University, both said the report did not deal adequately with the issue of how acid deposition might be affecting nutrients in the soil.</p>
        <p>Sulfur and nitrogen carried in acidified water or dry particles are building up to high levels in the soil, Dr. Jacobson said. He added that other nutrients required by trees, particularly phosphorus, calcium and magnesium, appear to be replaced in the soil or leached from foliage by acid rain.</p>
        <p>While the seriousness of this problem is still uncertain, Dr. Jacobson said, it could create nutrient imbalances that over the long run could lead to serious forest declines.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cowling, Dr. Hertel and Dr. Jacobson are regarded by colleagues as highly competent, careful scientists, with no personal axes to grind with regard to the report.</p>
        <p>Report Is Defended</p>
        <p>Among those who defend the report is Dr. John M. Skelly, a professor of plant pathology at Pennsylvania State University. ''The report is well written and clearly states our present knowledge at the time the report was required to be submitted,'' Dr. Skelly said. ''The report says that there are species in decline, but that the causes are well identified and they are not air pollution. That is what I read in the report and that is what I strongly concur with.''</p>
        <p>Alex Manson, director of issues management for Environment Canada, the Canadian environmental agency, questioned the report's conclusion that all of the decline in sugar maples is attributable to insects, disease and other natural stresses.</p>
        <p>''We are not quarreling with the importance of natural stresses,'' he said, ''but we believe the report should not overlook the stress of acid deposition. Not only does acid precipitation remove nutrients from the soil, he said, but it also increases the solubility of aluminum in the soil that can be ''quite toxic to root hairs.''</p>
        <p>The Canadian Government has been pressing the United States to control acid rain, which it insists is causing serious damage to lakes and forests in Canada.</p>
        <p>Dr. Alan A. Lucier, an author of the forest report, said that he agreed with some of the comments made about his work and disagreed with others. He rejected the conclusion that the report understates the seriousness of the issue.</p>
        <p>''The report is clearly not a no-problem message,'' he said. ''It does say that there is no forest health crisis of a regional dimension.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Lucier, who is wetlands program manager for the National Council of the Paper Industry for Air and Stream Improvement, said that so little space had been given to the Southern forests ''because the data does not support the contention that there is an unusual decline or any sort of decline in the Southern Appalachians.''</p>
        <p>As for the soil nutrient issue, Dr. Lucier said, a lot of information on the subject is in another volume of the Napap report that deals with the mechanisms that affect air quality. He also said that the Eastern hardwoods issue was treated adequately in the report.</p>
        <p>C. Jeffrey Brandt of Battelle Pacific Northwest Laboratories, deputy national program manager of the Forest Response Program, defended the report, saying that when it was presented last month at a meeting of scientists in Hilton Head, S.C., ''no one really disagreed with the conclusions, as far as they went.''</p>
        <p>''What people took exception to were statements that appeared to be absolute; for example, that there is no decline in the forests. I agree. There needs to be a 'but' added. There are some places where the forests have changed.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Mahoney said that all comments received after the Hilton Head meeting would be considered by the authors of the various volumes of the report and that the reports would be changed or modified where appropriate. The revised report would then be peer reviewed by scentists and by Government agencies before it is released in September, he explained.</p>
        <p>KEY POINTS AT ISSUE</p>
        <p>A Federal report on acid rain and forests is in dispute on over these issues:</p>
        <p>* The overall extent of forest decline that is attributable to acid rain.</p>
        <p>* How big a role ozone, as opposed to acid rain, may have in the decline of southern California forests.</p>
        <p>* What role acid rain may have in the decline of sugar maples.</p>
        <p>* Whether air pollution is significant among the stresses harming Southeastern pines.</p>
        <p>* How acid deposition might be affecting nutrients in the soil.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
