<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>White House Gases</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="367443"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUNUNU, JOHN H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D7173EF932A25754C0A966958260" item-length="500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>White House Gases</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Reduce greenhouse gases? The Bush Administration has again made clear, at the economic summit meeting in Houston, that it wants no part of an international timetable to limit emissions of carbon dioxide, which many fear will lead to a catastrophic warming of the earth's climate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Reduce greenhouse gases? The Bush Administration has again made clear, at the economic summit meeting in Houston, that it wants no part of an international timetable to limit emissions of carbon dioxide, which many fear will lead to a catastrophic warming of the earth's climate.</p>
        <p>Reduce greenhouse gases? The Bush Administration has again made clear, at the economic summit meeting in Houston, that it wants no part of an international timetable to limit emissions of carbon dioxide, which many fear will lead to a catastrophic warming of the earth's climate.</p>
        <p>There are valid arguments against rushing into speculative, costly fixes. But Mr. Bush and his chief of staff, John Sununu, aren't making them. They cloak their inaction in gaseous language and dubious science. That's an insult to the allies and a political embarrassment for Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>The computer models that predict global warming are full of uncertainties - good reason to resist a draconian program to reduce emissions. But these same models, and many scientists, suggest that some warming is likely. And that's reason enough to take sensible precautions.</p>
        <p>Chancellor Helmut Kohl says that Germany is prepared to reduce its carbon dioxide emissions by 25 percent in 15 years and urges the allies to follow suit. Some economists think that's an affordable goal. Mr. Sununu thinks it's a recipe for national suicide that would force the U.S. to abandon fossil fuels and drive it into a depression.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sununu, whose impatience with environmentalists stops just short of contempt, adumbrates his dark vision with half-truths. Most carbon dioxide emissions, he says, come from decaying vegetation. That's true; but what threatens to shatter the global balance isn't nature but a century of man-made emissions from automobiles, electrical utilities and industry.</p>
        <p>Except for the U.S., every industrial nation represented at the summit meeting has pledged to stabilize greenhouse gases. Mr. Bush's negative response might be understandable if he would offer an alternative. But he's been so busy saying no that he hasn't even opened for public discussion any number of sensible ideas to reduce carbon dioxide that are worth pursuing on their own merits.</p>
        <p>Compared with other countries, for example, the U.S. uses energy recklessly. Improved automobile mileage standards would improve energy efficiency. So would an energy tax, which, quite apart from its value as insurance against global warming, would ease the deficit. A sensible plan would also include incentives for using forms of energy that don't produce carbon dioxide, like solar and a new generation of safe nuclear plants. There would also be incentives for third world countries to stop the burning of tropical forests, an act of ecological vandalism that releases huge amounts of carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush takes pride in his innovative clean air bill and his decision to join an international agreement to abolish ozone-threatening chemicals. Those are fine achievements, but they do not unhook him from a campaign promise he made on Aug. 31, 1988.</p>
        <p>''Those who think we are powerless to do anything about the 'greenhouse effect' are forgetting about the 'White House effect,' '' he said. ''As President, I intend to do something about it.'' Do what?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
