<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times; America, the Evermore Beautiful</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="412238"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WATTENBERG, BEN J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FIRST UNIVERSAL NATION, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901231T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D9143EF932A05751C1A966958260" item-length="1043" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times; America, the Evermore Beautiful</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER LEHMANN-HAUPT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The First Universal Nation Leading Indicators and Ideas About the Surge of America in the 1990's By Ben J. Wattenberg 418 pages. The Free Press. $22.95.</p>
        <p>In "The First Universal Nation," Ben J. Wattenberg comes at us like an Uncle Sam on stilts, with a smile on his face, a calculator in his hand and the message that everything in America is good and about to get a whole lot better. What a reader has to watch, however, are the shells and the pea Mr. Wattenberg is holding behind his back.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The First Universal Nation Leading Indicators and Ideas About the Surge of America in the 1990's By Ben J. Wattenberg 418 pages. The Free Press. $22.95.</p>
        <p>In "The First Universal Nation," Ben J. Wattenberg comes at us like an Uncle Sam on stilts, with a smile on his face, a calculator in his hand and the message that everything in America is good and about to get a whole lot better. What a reader has to watch, however, are the shells and the pea Mr. Wattenberg is holding behind his back.</p>
        <p>About the shell game first. In his introduction, Mr. Wattenberg writes: "What you see before you is an unusual book. It is an irregular piece of goods -- theme, memoir, data, reportage, futurism, analysis, policy. That's a lot, but after all, you will find out in these pages that I am a paleoliberal, a supply-side infrastructuralist, a neomanifest destinarian, a numbers nut, a pro-natalist redistributionist capitalist, and still a hawk. Perhaps it takes many formats to deal with that."</p>
        <p>This is enough fancy verbiage to lift the Goodyear blimp. What you actually see before you is a collection of Mr. Wattenberg's syndicated newspaper columns, interrupted by brief swatches of italicized commentary and an occasional page of statistics. Moreover, these columns are repetitive and meandering. A symptomatic sentence reads: "In any event, I think my basic political principles have remained essentially the same," which could have been boiled down to "My politics have remained."</p>
        <p>Mr. Wattenberg never met an infinitive he couldn't split. He likes unlovely phrases like "The De-otherization of America" and " neo-manifest destinarianism." He is so insensitive to language that he thinks Herman Wouk's late, flabby novel "Inside, Outside" is superior to Philip Roth's "Portnoy's Complaint" simply because he prefers Mr. Wouk's politics to Mr. Roth's. He knocks the first volume of Robert Caro's biography of Lyndon B. Johnson, for whom Mr. Wattenberg worked as a speech writer, though he clearly hasn't taken the trouble to read the book with any care. ("Sculptor Chisels Johnson") And he doesn't understand the first thing about the appeal of watching baseball. ("Is Baseball Snoreball?")</p>
        <p>Can anyone so misguided possibly have anything useful to tell us? Despite his habit of putting things clumsily, Mr. Wattenberg has a habit of being right. As he is not too modest to explain, he was the first to predict Violeta Barrios de Chamorro's victory in the Nicaraguan presidential election this year. He foresaw, even in the spring of 1988, that George Bush was no "preppy wimp" and would prove a formidable campaigner.</p>
        <p>He writes shrewdly about recent Presidential campaigns, holding that the Republicans have stolen the center of the ideological spectrum while the Democrats have become too enamored of not disagreeing with Jesse Jackson.</p>
        <p>Besides, one would like to believe the message of "The First Universal Nation." What this boils down to is that all the talk about America's decline is eyewash. We have the best schools in the world, and these produce the most Nobel Prize winners. Foreign companies may be buying us up, but that is only to get their hands on our culture, which, packaged in videocassettes, is the envy of the world, from Moscow, where they hold Elvis Presley look-alike contests, to Frankfurt, where Germany's Green party recently argued that so many Germans had listened to the American Forces Network for so long that the radio station had become part of "the German cultural heritage."</p>
        <p>Thus the United States is not only still "No. 1," but also poised on its most prosperous decade. The reason for this prospect of success? "In the 50 years prior to 1965, about 11 million immigrants, legal and illegal, came to the United States. About 75 percent of those were of white European ancestry.</p>
        <p>"But in the quarter-century since 1965 about 14 million immigrants have come to the U.S. -- 27 percent more in half the time. And about 85 percent of these are</p>
        <p>not</p>
        <p>of white European ancestry. Americans, for the first time, can be accurately said to come from 'everywhere.' "</p>
        <p>"This new universalizing of America, while not without its problems, should be very good for us. It can help tilt the balance of global commercial power in our favor. It can also tilt the related balance of geopolitical, technological and demographic power in our favor. It can accelerate a process already very much in motion -- the Americanization of world culture.  That may turn out to be the most important aspect of it."</p>
        <p>Mr. Wattenberg can sound like the most egregious jingoist: "We won the Cold War. It didn't just end. We won it because we stayed strong, because we rallied our allies, and because we were right. We ought to understand that and say it. It was probably the most titanic ideological struggle in the history of the planet, surely the most expensive, and we won it. No more of that pantywaist stuff about how one day it just ended."</p>
        <p>He has a way of sweeping the bad news under the carpet of his statistical snapshots: the deficit is a problem, but it is shrinking "as a proportion of the Gross National Product." American blacks have not been as successful as Hispanic and Asian immigrants, but more blacks are in college now than ever before, the high-school dropout rate is going down, and the black middle class has grown enormously. Global warming and ozone depletion are bothersome, but "our air is getting cleaner," and Federal spending on the environment is rising once again after dipping in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>Do we therefore have adequate grounds to share Mr. Wattenberg's optimism? Instinctively, I would say no: the sloppiness of his writing and the speed with which he shifts those shells around prevails over the numbers on his calculator and the cheeriness of his smile.</p>
        <p>But there's an undeniable appeal to his argument that for every culture that sends emigrants to this country, this country creates propagandists for its way of life in return. As he keeps insisting, no other country can come close to claiming the diversity with which the United States interacts with the world. There are worse ways to end a remarkable decade than to succumb to Mr. Wattenberg's overbearing, infectious optimism.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
