<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Peril Seen on Earth Warming</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="340846"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HYDROHALOCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DF103BF936A35757C0A966958260" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Peril Seen on Earth Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Chemicals counted on as substitutes for chlorofluorocarbons, widely used substances that are destroying the Earth's protective ozone layer, could contribute significantly to long-term global warming, scientists say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Chemicals counted on as substitutes for chlorofluorocarbons, widely used substances that are destroying the Earth's protective ozone layer, could contribute significantly to long-term global warming, scientists say.</p>
        <p>Chemicals counted on as substitutes for chlorofluorocarbons, widely used substances that are destroying the Earth's protective ozone layer, could contribute significantly to long-term global warming, scientists say.</p>
        <p>Chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, have two important but entirely separate environmental effects: By depleting the stratospheric ozone layer, they allow harmful ultraviolet rays to penetrate the atmosphere. And they are a powerful contributor to the greenhouse effect, in which a number of gases trap the Sun's heat in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Some of the chemical substitutes, called hydrohalocarbons, are about one-tenth as destructive to ozone as CFC's on average, and others do not destroy it at all, the scientists report. But like CFC's, carbon dioxide and other gases, all the hydrohalocarbons trap the Sun's heat in the atmosphere. They trap only about one-tenth as much as CFC's do, but their ''unbounded use'' could nevertheless contribute significantly to the greenhouse effect, the scientists said.</p>
        <p>Fear on Loss of Future Gains</p>
        <p>Unrestrained use of some of the substitutes could also erode future gains made by eliminating CFC's, said one of the chief researchers, Donald A. Fisher of the E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company Experimental Station at Wilmington, Del. He described the hydrohalocarbons as an interim measure pending a more ideal but still unknown solution.</p>
        <p>The research was described in two reports today in the British journal Nature.</p>
        <p>Chlorofluorocarbons, industrial chemicals widely used as refrigerants, aerosol sprays and cleaning agents, rise to the upper atmosphere, where they break down ozone molecules, allowing harmful ultraviolet radiation to penetrate the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Under an international treaty reached in Montreal, most of the developed nations have agreed to reduce the production of CFC's. Some have decided to eliminate them entirely by the end of the century, often by replacing them with hydrohalocarbons.</p>
        <p>The calculations of the effect of hydrohalocarbons on global warming were performed by Dr. Fisher and Charles H. Hales, also of the Du Pont experimental station in Wilmington, and Wei-Chyung Wang, Malcolm K. W. Ko and N. Dak Sze of Atmospheric and Environmental Research Inc. of Cambridge, Mass. In a second study, the calculations relating to ozone depletion were performed by Dr. Fisher, Mr. Hales and seven other scientists from Atmospheric and Environmental Research and from the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratories.</p>
        <p>Assessment of 2 Effects</p>
        <p>''The results of these two papers allow us to see whether 'ozone friendliness' implies 'greenhouse friendliness,' '' Keith Shine of the Department of Meteorology at the University of Reading, England, wrote in a commentary in Nature. ''The answer, in my opinion,'' he said, ''is an emphatic no.'' Mr. Shine wrote that ''unrestrained emissions'' of hydrohalocarbons ''could lead to climatically significant concentrations during the next century.'' He warned that prevention of ''unnecessary releases'' of hydrohalocarbons to the atmosphere ''will remain important.''</p>
        <p>Hydrohalocarbons break down more rapidly in the atmosphere than CFC's, and this is their chief advantage. Mostly for this reason, the new studies have found, hydrohalocarbons trap only about one-tenth as much heat as the CFC's. But a third study reported in today's Nature calculated that molecule for molecule, hydrohalocarbons are 410 times more powerful heat-trappers than carbon dioxide, the most abundant and important greenhouse gas. The study was reported by Daniel A. Lashof of the Natural Resources Defense Council and Dilip R. Ahuja of the Tata Energy Research Institute in New Delhi.</p>
        <p>At the levels at which hydrohalocarbons are expected to be used, Dr. Shine said in an interview, they are likely to contribute 5 to 10 percent of the total greenhouse effect over the next century. Any expansion beyond those levels would enhance the greenhouse effect accordingly. CFC's now contribute about 20 percent of the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>''We've been advocating a phase-out of hydrohalocarbons as well as CFC's,'' said Dr. Fisher. ''We don't have what is viewed as the ideal chemical. The impetus at this point is to get CFC's out of industrial use as quickly as possible. By 2030 or thereabouts, we should be looking for a third generation.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Fisher's company startled industrialists and environmentalists two years ago when it announced that it would unilaterally stop producing CFC's. Du Pont has been the world's leading producer of CFC's, with about 25 percent of the market. The company, along with others, is trying to develop hydrohalocarbons for commercial application.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
