<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Health Problems of Inner City Poor Reaching Crisis Point</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19901225T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <meta content="Islands of Illness/Health Crisis in the Cities" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="410744"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">URBAN AREAS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENTHAL, ELISABETH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Special Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DA1238F937A15751C1A966958260" item-length="2405" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Health Problems of Inner City Poor Reaching Crisis Point</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH ROSENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENTHAL, ELISABETH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While Americans elsewhere are living longer, healthier lives, residents of the inner cities inhabit islands of illness, epidemics and premature death. After decades of gradual improvement, the health of the urban poor took a turn for the worse in the late 1980's and has now reached critical condition.</p>
        <p>Experts blame new depths of urban poverty and inadequate medical services for the situation. Struggling for day-to-day survival, people have little time for niceties like doctor's visits. Poor nutrition and overcrowded housing create ideal conditions for the spread of disease. The arrival of AIDS and crack pushed chronic hardship into crisis, shattering families and monopolizing scarce health dollars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While Americans elsewhere are living longer, healthier lives, residents of the inner cities inhabit islands of illness, epidemics and premature death. After decades of gradual improvement, the health of the urban poor took a turn for the worse in the late 1980's and has now reached critical condition.</p>
        <p>Experts blame new depths of urban poverty and inadequate medical services for the situation. Struggling for day-to-day survival, people have little time for niceties like doctor's visits. Poor nutrition and overcrowded housing create ideal conditions for the spread of disease. The arrival of AIDS and crack pushed chronic hardship into crisis, shattering families and monopolizing scarce health dollars.</p>
        <p>In the past three years, cities have reported skyrocketing rates of tuberculosis, hepatitis A, syphilis, gonorrhea, measles, mumps, whooping cough, complicated ear infections and, of course, AIDS. The number of cases is still often small, but most of these diseases were considered on the verge of eradication only five years ago after steadily declining since the beginning of the century. Many of them are virtually unknown in middle-class or wealthy neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>'I've Seen Horrible Things'</p>
        <p>Dr. David Wood, a pediatrician at Cedars-Sinai Medical Center in Los Angeles, called 1990 a "gangbuster year" for inner city epidemics. "If you look at maps of measles outbreaks in Los Angeles and where the poverty is, they are the same."</p>
        <p>Studies also show that impoverished city dwellers with serious conditions like cancer and heart disease die far more quickly than their middle-class counterparts because treatment begins so late. "I never saw a woman die of cancer of the cervix until I came to the Bronx," said Dr. Carolyn Runowicz, a gynecologist at the Montefiore Medical Center. "On Park Avenue, women get pap smears, which prevent it."</p>
        <p>The death rate among the poor is also higher. In 1988, deaths from diabetes-related illnesses totaled five times as high in central Harlem as in the city's wealthier neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>But statistics, which at best count deaths and infectious diseases, capture only a glimpse of the big picture. They do not tally unnecessary suffering or the lifelong handicaps that result when treatable conditions like asthma and epilepsy go unrecognized or neglected.</p>
        <p>"I've seen horrible things," Dr. Wood said. "Kids who have such frequent seizures that they can't go to school. Kids with asthma who don't get medications and can't play outside because they get coughing fits. It's like years ago when people with unsalvageable conditions were hidden away."</p>
        <p>Dr. Harold P. Freeman, chief of surgery at Harlem Hospital in New York, caused a stir earlier this year when he reported in the New England Journal of Medicine that a black man in Harlem was less likely to reach 65 years of age than a man in Bangladesh. While violent crime is part of the problem, the paper said high rates of disease were the primary cause.</p>
        <p>"When 67 people die in an earthquake in San Francisco, we call it a disaster and the President visits," said Dr. Freeman. "But here everyone is ignoring a chronic consistent disaster area, with many more people dying. And there is no question that things are getting worse."</p>
        <p>In Newark, Dr. Beatriz Arpayaglou has learned to be a pessimist. "We're seeing scenes here straight out of underdeveloped countries, diseases that haven't been seen in the United States since the turn of the century," said Dr.  Arpayaglou, a pediatrician with the University Hospital in Newark's Children's Health Project, which sends medical teams to low-income housing projects in vans fitted like medical offices. "It's really very frightening."</p>
        <p>In the next room of the medical van at the Stella Wright Apartments, a nurse, Anne Young, was seeing Kison Chauvers, a 2-year-old boy with anemia from nutritional deficiencies. The day before the team had rushed a 5-year-old girl to the hospital with a life-threatening kidney infection whose symptoms had been neglected for several days. Her grandmother, the stoic guardian to seven children of two daughters who died of AIDS, could not get the child to a doctor sooner.</p>
        <p>Epidemics of Yesteryear</p>
        <p>To Poor, Vaccines Prove Elusive</p>
        <p>Different cities have fallen prey to different diseases:</p>
        <p>In New York City, 1,017 babies were born with congenital syphilis in 1988, the most recent year for which figures are available, up from only 16 in 1982. New York City accounts for about half the cases nationally.</p>
        <p>Newark has had a 35 percent yearly rise in the number of new tuberculosis cases between 1988 and '89, and the pediatric clinic at Newark's University Hospital reports a fourfold increase since 1987. There has been a 15 percent increase in tuberculosis cases in the country as a whole since 1988, largely in urban areas.</p>
        <p>In Los Angeles this year several hundred people have been hospitalized for measles, and 30 have died. The number of measles cases nationwide rose to 17,000 last year, from a low of 1,500 in 1983. The city had also played host to an outbreak of rubella, or German measles, which has left at least nine babies with serious birth defects. Rubella is a mild illness in adults but leads to blindness in the offspring of women who catch it while pregnant.</p>
        <p>Washington is just recovering from a three-year mumps outbreak. After seeing less than half a dozen cases a year for a decade, the city had about 200 reported cases in both 1988 and '89.</p>
        <p>"These epidemics are sentinel events for the crumbling of our public health services," Dr. Wood said. Measles, mumps, rubella and whooping cough are entirely preventable with vaccines, but many people do not get the shots.</p>
        <p>Nationally, asthma rates have undergone a dramatic and somewhat baffling rise, a rise doctors say is more pronounced among the urban poor. Dr. Michael Wietzman and colleagues at Boston City Hospital found that black children were twice as likely as white children to have asthma.</p>
        <p>In many studies, scientists compare black and white rather than rich and poor to eke out information about health care differences, since it is easier to figure out race than salary from medical records and far more blacks than whites live in the inner city. But most experts say it is primarily poverty, not race, that raises the risk.</p>
        <p>"It's mostly the social dimensions of being black," said Dr. Weitzman, now chief of Pediatrics at Rochester General Hospital in Rochester, N.Y. "Its being poor, living in overcrowded housing, having a low birth weight, being exposed to household toxins."</p>
        <p>In Need of the Basics</p>
        <p>Hazardous Homes, Dangerous Diets</p>
        <p>Experts say the growing number of people who live in substandard housing with poor sanitation creates conditions favoring the rapid spread of infectious disease. "Diseases transmit more effectively and rapidly in crowded living conditions," said Dr. Shirley Fannin, associate deputy director of disease control programs for Los Angeles County. "A few years ago we went out to investigate a typhoid case and we found 27 people living in one house sharing a bathroom."</p>
        <p>As middle-class people worry about clean air and the ozone layer, many scientists blame indoor pollution for the high rates of asthma and other diseases among the poor. In the Boston study, the factor most tightly linked to a child's risk of developing asthma was smoking by the mother, Dr. Weitzman said. Poor young women from minority groups are the country's fastest growing group of cigarette smokers.</p>
        <p>Living in decaying housing, 68 percent of very poor black children and 36 percent of very poor white children in central cities have blood lead levels greater than 15 micrograms per deciliter. The Centers for Disease Control now defines toxic levels at above 25, but the agency said last week that it would advise local health officials to take action when children have lead levels higher than 10.</p>
        <p>Diets rich in fat and low in nutrients also take a toll. Many poor children have chronic anemia, a low red blood cell count caused by a lack of iron in their diet, leaving them perpetually tired.</p>
        <p>Once sick, poor people in the inner cities tend to suffer serious complications. Dr. Wood remembers examining a 9-year old girl with a facial tic and discovering 20/200 vision and profound hearing loss from damage done by untreated ear infections. "She was holding her face funny partly because she couldn't see," he said. "Her parents had seen a few doctors and used up their money. No wonder she's failing in school."</p>
        <p>Quality of Care</p>
        <p>Prevention, And Much to Cure</p>
        <p>For poor people in the cities, access to care is part of the problem. To be treated in a public clinic for sexually transmitted disease in Washington, a patient has to be in the clinic by 9:30 A.M. and often must wait most of the day, said Dr. Reed Tuckson, former Commissioner of Health for Washington.</p>
        <p>The typical wait to schedule a pedriatric appointment in inner city clinics was several months, according to a survey done by the New York Children's Health Project, a medical outreach program affiliated with the Montefiore Medical Center in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>But many experts say an even greater issue is the quality of care. The Community Service Society of New York polled 248 primary care doctors in poor neighborhoods in the Bronx as to whether they offered 24-hour coverage, had 20 or more regular office hours a week, accepted Medicare and had admitting privileges at a hospital -- what the society defined as minimum components of a decent medical practice. Only six met the criteria.</p>
        <p>The society's study also found that more than 60 percent of doctors providing prenatal care could not actually deliver babies because they had no hospital affiliation; the mothers were referred to an emergency room.</p>
        <p>"The family says yes we're seeing a doctor, but when you look the care is not well organized," said Dr. Karen Burke, medical director of the New York Children's Health Project. Experts say that clinics in poor neighborhoods focus on acute illnesses and ignore routine care like pap smears, anemia screening and vaccinations, which are generally less profitable.</p>
        <p>Pediatricians are particularly worried about how early lives plagued by health problems will affect children as they age. Babies born in Central Harlem are four times as likely to have very low birth weight than babies born in more prosperous New York neighborhoods, a statistic with lifelong consequences since babies under 3.5 pounds are more likely to have seizures, mental retardation, heart problems, asthma, blindness, deafness and learning disabilities. In today's inner cities, drug abuse and poor prenatal nutrition often converge to yield tiny babies.</p>
        <p>"A kid in a middle-class suburb who has an ear infection gets antibiotics and gets better," said Dr. Irwin Redlener, director of the New York Children's Health Project. "A poor kid with an ear infection doesn't and progresses to chronic infection, hearing loss and language delays."</p>
        <p>In both Newark and New York, most of the preschool children seen in the mobile vans are not fully vaccinated, leaving them vulnerable to serious diseases.</p>
        <p>Other inner city children have been wastefully, though not harmfully, vaccinated over and over again because of a lack of medical records. At a health van in Harlem, 15-year-old Jewel S. had no records because his life has been a flurry of different welfare homes and schools as he and his mother flee an abusive father.</p>
        <p>The surging number of poor children and the rising costs of medicines have stymied vaccination programs, Dr. Woods said. In the early '70s, the total cost of a child's vaccinations was under $5; now it is several hundred dollars.</p>
        <p>Contrasts of the Crisis</p>
        <p>Determining Death By Money and Race</p>
        <p>In a study published in the International Journal of Epidemiology this year, scientists at the Washington, D.C., Commission on Public Health estimated that blacks in Washington were more than four times as likely as whites to die prematurely, before 65, of heart disease, asthma, pneumonia and some cancers. While the death rates for blacks in Washington have climbed steadily since 1982, the rates for whites have not changed.</p>
        <p>"We looked at conditions that people shouldn't be dying from in the prime of life," said Dr. Eugene Schwartz, the study's first author, and the chief of the Washington Bureau of Cancer Control. "And remember, death is a very crude measure. It's the tip of an iceberg, the end of a long chain of illness and disability that we don't have a handle on."</p>
        <p>Dr. Freeman tells of the shock of moving to Harlem Hospital from Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, also in Manhattan, but four long miles downtown.  "When I came to Harlem Hospital in the late '60s I suddenly found I was seeing extremely advanced cancer, and that hasn't changed," he said. Because they come so late to treatment, only 30 percent of women diagnosed with breast cancer at Harlem Hospital live 5 years, compared to 70 percent of white women and 60 percent of black women overall in the United States. Dr. Freeman has set up free cancer screening at Harlem Hospital two mornings a week.</p>
        <p>The fates of blacks and whites, rich and poor are diverging. The National Center for Health Statistic first started comparing black-white infant mortality in 1950, and the difference has never been greater than it is today, with black babies dying at twice the rate before their first birthday. While the life expectancy of whites rose to 75.6 years in 1987, that of blacks fell to 69.2.</p>
        <p>Doctors involved in outreach efforts hope they will save a few lives but know these are frail, jury-rigged solutions.</p>
        <p>"We're using Band-Aids, and things are getting worse rather than better," Dr. Freeman said. "You have to see disease in the context in which it occurs: poor education, unemployment, homelessness, hopelessness."</p>
        <p>Dr. Tuckson said: "It's hard to tell young black men in the inner city to practice safe sex or not to smoke. They'll laugh: 'You're telling me not to smoke so I won't get cancer when I'm 50? Hell, don't tell me about 50 'cause I'm not gonna make it out of my teens.' There are an extraordinarily large number of Americans who don't believe in any concept of a future and so don't believe in investing in it."</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 25, 1990, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A chart yesterday about inner-city health problems misidentified the neighborhood for which statistics were given. It was Central Harlem, not East Harlem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 25, 1990, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A chart yesterday about inner-city health problems misidentified the neighborhood for which statistics were given. It was Central Harlem, not East Harlem.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
