<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IT'S NOT TOO LATE, IF WE'RE NOT TOO CRAZY</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="345851"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOULD, STEPHEN JAY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">OPPENHEIMER, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOYLE, ROBERT H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COMMONER, BARRY</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">DEAD HEAT: THE RACE AGAINST THE GREENHOUSE EFFECT (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MAKING PEACE WITH THE PLANET (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DD1F38F931A15757C0A966958260" item-length="2014" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IT'S NOT TOO LATE, IF WE'RE NOT TOO CRAZY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN JAY GOULD; Stephen Jay Gould, a professor of geology at Harvard University, is the author of ''Wonderful Life.''</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOULD, STEPHEN JAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>DEAD HEAT</p>
        <p>The Race Against the Greenhouse Effect.</p>
        <p>By Michael Oppenheimer and Robert H. Boyle.</p>
        <p>268 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>A New Republic Book/Basic Books. $19.95.</p>
        <p>MAKING PEACE WITH THE PLANET</p>
        <p>By Barry Commoner.</p>
        <p>292 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Pantheon Books. $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>DEAD HEAT</p>
        <p>The Race Against the Greenhouse Effect.</p>
        <p>By Michael Oppenheimer and Robert H. Boyle.</p>
        <p>268 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>A New Republic Book/Basic Books. $19.95.</p>
        <p>MAKING PEACE WITH THE PLANET</p>
        <p>By Barry Commoner.</p>
        <p>292 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Pantheon Books. $19.95.</p>
        <p>DEAD HEAT</p>
        <p>The Race Against the Greenhouse Effect.</p>
        <p>By Michael Oppenheimer and Robert H. Boyle.</p>
        <p>268 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>A New Republic Book/Basic Books. $19.95.</p>
        <p>MAKING PEACE WITH THE PLANET</p>
        <p>By Barry Commoner.</p>
        <p>292 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Pantheon Books. $19.95.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists are faced with a paradox on this 20th anniversary of Earth Day. They wish to spread the news of environmental danger as widely as possible, yet a kwikwrite virus of books, timed to exploit the occasion, threatens both to weaken their message and to thin out the forests they have designated for protection. The two books under review rise above the ephemera of the occasion, though they also illustrate the twin perils of environmental preaching. Michael Oppenheimer and Robert Boyle's ''Dead Heat'' (on global warming) does not insulate itself sufficiently from the heat of the hype surrounding the subject, while Barry Commoner's ''Making Peace With the Planet'' (on the general global crisis) suffers the commonest of unkind fates: to be so self-evidently true and just that we pass it by as a twice-told tale.</p>
        <p>No ecological or environmental subject has received more attention in the past year than global warming - and quite rightly. What with ozone holes and rising levels of carbon dioxide, we have reason to suspect that the recent long hot summers are the inception of a potentially tragic trend, not just a random and reversible blip on a curve. In the face of such putative danger, we may understand Mr. Oppenheimer and Mr. Boyle's impatience with scientists who do not mount the soapbox. Yet good oratory demands not just passion but hard information and valid predictions. So we must also understand the caution shown by most scientists, who do not want their credibility buried in scenarios of imminent disasters that do not come to pass.</p>
        <p>Predictions of global warming derive from the most difficult and tentative of all scientific efforts - the modeling of complex systems. I doubt that the general public has any sense of the uncertainties that attend such an enterprise. Most people are taught that science is the discipline that makes predictions by evaluating data in terms of the universal laws of nature. They believe that when data go into a computer, which then churns out complex graphs, the result is rigor in canonical form. However, climatic modeling on a global scale requires not only that the computer be fed scores of variables (many of which cannot be precisely measured), but also, and more important, that the complex and nonlinear interactions among these variables be assessed (and here we haven't the ghost of adequate knowledge or even, in many cases, of suggestive theory). Thus, honorable people all trying their darnedest to model the global climate come up with the most disparate predictions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Oppenheimer, a senior scientist with the Environmental Defense Fund, and Mr. Boyle, the author of ''The Hudson River'' and ''Acid Rain,'' seriously compromise their otherwise valuable book by choosing but one of these computer models (from the Goddard Institute for Space Studies) among plausible alternatives, and then unleashing cannonades of dire predictions, often in a lurid mode. They write, for instance, that ''the potential loss of plant and animal species from the impending global warming appears overwhelming.'' As a paleontologist who knows that even the worst scenarios of global warming would yield an earth far cooler than that of many quite prosperous times of a prehuman past, I object. After all, species migrate as climates shift - and have done so up and down latitude throughout geological history. (Although Mr. Oppenheimer and Mr. Boyle recognize this, they conclude that migration will now be blocked by ''cities, towns, factories, rail lines, and other 'infrastructure.' '') I doubt that greenhouse warming is a danger to the planet at geological time scales, as Mr. Oppenheimer and Mr. Boyle suggest. Why make such hyped-up claims? Isn't it enough that global warming (and the consequent rising of sea level) would be tragic for us humans? Isn't it enough that most of our large cities, situated at sea level (ports and harbors), would be flooded, and that masses of people and agricultural systems would have to move? This parochial focus is entirely appropriate and defensible.</p>
        <p>Difficulties cannot be swept under a rug of invented concord for purposes of political clout. But surely environmentalists can make adequately strong statements without making unjustifiable predictions: they can say that greenhouse gases, byproducts of human technology, are increasing (the data on carbon dioxide are particularly impressive); that the ozone hole is real; that the warming of the past few years may well represent the beginning of a general trend; and that if the dumping of greenhouse gases into the atmosphere continues unabated, it will eventually induce global warming. Thus, at the very least, we may look upon the warming of the last few years, whatever its causes, as a model for a dangerous future.</p>
        <p>If many arguments are overstated by Mr. Oppenheimer and Mr. Boyle, their good points are often compromised by purple prose and downright silly imagery. Consider this mixed zoological and sexual metaphor for the ills of the internal combustion engine: ''The energy-inefficiency mouse embedded in the automobile is as big as a rat. . . . The mouse was conceived in the mating of two desires: fast, high-power driving and easy, single-clutch shifting.''</p>
        <p>The crux of my displeasure with Mr. Oppenheimer and Mr. Boyle's tactic, though, is their castigation of cautious scientists (ecologists are their main targets). ''For a modern ecologist,'' they write, ''it all comes to this: in drawing conclusions, don't wander too far from the data, or the 'ground truth.' '' In response, they argue ''that now, with the world changing so fast, a little more intellectual risk taking is required.'' Yet just two sentences later, they undermine their own prescription: ''Politicians don't want to hear what you don't know; they want to hear what you are confident about, particularly if you are a scientist.''</p>
        <p>How can we take the advised risks and, at the same time, proffer the necessary certainty? We cannot. History is littered with the refuse of overenthusiasms; necessary caution is a mark of vibrant and compassionate professionalism, not a conceit of effete disengagement. We will only be effective if we can speak with the authority of genuine intellectual integrity.</p>
        <p>I have no quarrel with Mr. Oppenheimer and Mr. Boyle's general path to salvation. They recommend that we pursue ''bridge'' technologies based on much more efficient use of current fuels until we can develop new technologies based on renewable energy sources that won't release greenhouse gases. I applaud their emphasis on solar power, but must note that their enthusiasm for hydrogen is by no means universally shared; the image of the Hindenburg in flames dies hard.</p>
        <p>Barry Commoner's ''Making Peace with the Planet'' - an enlarged prescription for a technosphere brought into harmony with our ecosphere - follows the same general route. Though his scope is broader and his image of reform more comprehensive than that outlined in ''Dead Heat,'' it is eminently achievable in a world where good will and coordinated dedication take precedence over the immediate profitability of corporations. Now how, in heaven's name, do we ever attain such rationality?</p>
        <p>Barry Commoner, the author of ''Science and Survival'' and ''The Poverty of Power,'' has been speaking with a consistent voice for more than 20 years. Although he has been branded by many as a maverick, I regard him as right and compassionate on nearly every major issue. He recognizes and documents the utter failure of governments and corporations to regulate and control environmental dangers. He opts for a model of prevention rather than controlled use (recycling, not incineration, for example). He points out that such a strategy requires a massive creative investment in new (and mostly smaller) technologies. He knows that such an investment must be supported by coordinated programs for a common, and largely future, good, and that it entails higher immediate costs at the sacrifice of corporate profit. Dare the word ''socialism'' be mentioned?</p>
        <p>He recognizes (as many in the environmental movement do not) that ''the root cause of the world population crisis is poverty,'' and that no acceptable solution will emerge without a massive amelioration of poverty by redistribution of the world's wealth (forgiveness of third-world debts to first-world nations for starters). He argues, against the radical romantics of prosperous nations, that advanced technology is here to stay, and that no back-to-the-soil or back-to-the-hunter-gatherer-style movement will ever alleviate the misery and crushing poverty of so many nations. Therefore he believes that a humane and reforming technology - based on solar power and massive recycling - must learn to be friendly to an unforgiving ecosphere. We must, in short, make ''peace with the planet.''</p>
        <p>Is this a pipe dream? Mr. Commoner worries, of course: ''Present reality is both illogical and so massive and entrenched as to appear unalterable. Are we then condemned to an ongoing and ultimately suicidal war with the planet?'' Now I may be hopelessly naive as a political observer, but why should we despair? Has not the nearly sudden dissolution of old Eastern European politics proved that the cold war was a happenstance of a moment in history, not a structural and effectively permanent inevitability? Is not true peace with the planet therefore conceivable?</p>
        <p>Am I being painfully stupid and impractical? Could not the world's massive military expenditures, rendered truly unnecessary, be redirected to planetary salvation without economic loss? Could we not take these military savings, launch the most massive Civilian Conservation Corps in the history of the world (the democratic counterpart of building the Egyptian pyramids or the Great Wall of China), hire every unemployed person in America at good wages for useful work, fix every bridge, fill every pothole, rake every roadside, clean every subway car, declare a two-week work project and pick up every piece of trash (for recycling of course) in every public park and on every street corner. This is not crazy. It really could be done. Where is the will, where the vision, where the coordination, where the knowledge that we must do it or ultimately perish?</p>
        <p>A PICKLE JAR AT THE CROSSROADS</p>
        <p>Recycling cures the ecologically harmful linearity of modern production technologies. . . . Suppose we capture, in a freeze-frame, the moment in which the glass jar is emptied of its last pickle. At this brief moment in its history, the container is still a useful object, for it is, after all, the same container that the pickle factory bought from the glass company. The container's potential usefulness could be realized by returning it to the pickle factory - as was once done with returnable beer bottles. Alternatively, the empty container could be returned to the glass manufacturer, where it would be remelted and formed into some other product or even into an identical jar that could once more carry pickles to their destiny. In either case, the once linear process is converted into a circular one. This eliminates the detrimental environmental impact that occurs at the end of the line, for it prevents the conversion of the otherwise useful container into trash.</p>
        <p>In sum, at the moment it is emptied, poised in the householder's hand, the pickle jar is at the brink of two alternative fates. If it is tossed into the trash pail, the jar is transformed into trash, fated to contribute to all the ensuing environmental problems. On the other hand, if - perhaps first rinsed - the jar begins a voyage back to the pickle company or the glass factory, its fate is environmentally benign.</p>
        <p>Indeed, it is even beneficial.</p>
        <p>From ''Making Peace With the Planet.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
