<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Poppers and the Plains</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="363302"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKS AND OTHER RECREATION AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUFFALOES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAND USE POLICIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AREA PLANNING AND RENEWAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POPULATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NATIONAL PARKS, MONUMENTS AND SEASHORES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT PLAINS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BUFFALO COMMONS (PROPOSED)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MATTHEWS, ANNE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">POPPER, FRANK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">POPPER, DEBORAH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/National Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD8163AF937A15755C0A966958260" item-length="4589" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Poppers and the Plains</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE MATTHEWS; Anne Matthews directs the nonfiction writing program at Princeton University.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MATTHEWS, ANNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: BUFFALOES THUNDER ACROSS POSTERS, POSE FOR BUMPER STICKERS and glower from coffee mugs in Frank Popper's crowded office at Rutgers University in New Jersey. There is even a sack of dried buffalo droppings. ''Genuine Virgin Buffalo Chips,'' the label reads. ''Pioneer Fertilizer and Fuel. Not for Microwave Ovens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: BUFFALOES THUNDER ACROSS POSTERS, POSE FOR BUMPER STICKERS and glower from coffee mugs in Frank Popper's crowded office at Rutgers University in New Jersey. There is even a sack of dried buffalo droppings. ''Genuine Virgin Buffalo Chips,'' the label reads. ''Pioneer Fertilizer and Fuel. Not for Microwave Ovens.</p>
        <p>BUFFALOES THUNDER ACROSS POSTERS, POSE FOR BUMPER STICKERS and glower from coffee mugs in Frank Popper's crowded office at Rutgers University in New Jersey. There is even a sack of dried buffalo droppings. ''Genuine Virgin Buffalo Chips,'' the label reads. ''Pioneer Fertilizer and Fuel. Not for Microwave Ovens. Contents Public Domain.''</p>
        <p>Frank Popper, chairman of the Rutgers urban studies department and an international expert on land-use planning, and his wife, Deborah Epstein Popper, a Rutgers geographer, want to convert much of America's prairie outback into public domain for its original residents - the buffalo. According to their research, vast areas in the 10 Great Plains states - from the 98th meridian to the Rockies - are already experiencing or will undergo a sharp decline in population and prosperity.</p>
        <p>In Nebraska, for instance, says Deborah Popper, the distressed locales are found in counties ''that have at least a 50 percent population loss since 1930. An over-10-percent loss between 1980 and 1988. Four people or fewer per square mile. High median age. Twenty percent or more in poverty. New annual construction investment under $50 per capita. All very bad news.''</p>
        <p>Over the next 30 years, the Poppers argue, the depressed areas should become a huge reserve, more than 139,000 square miles of open land and wildlife refuge. That zone, which the Poppers call the Buffalo Commons, includes much of the western Dakotas, western Nebraska and eastern Montana; portions of Kansas, Oklahoma and Texas, and selected counties in Colorado, New Mexico and Wyoming (map on page 26).</p>
        <p>Set in place, the Buffalo Commons - most likely to be administered by a consortium of government agencies and private groups - would be the world's largest national park, an act of ecological restoration that would, the Poppers contend, boldly reverse more than 100 years of American history. Commons visitors would once again see the heart of the continent as Lewis and Clark first knew it, a true frontier of waving grass and migrant game.</p>
        <p>The Buffalo Commons idea came to the Poppers late in the winter of 1987, while they were stuck in six-lane traffic on the New Jersey Turnpike heading into Manhattan. Their moment of inspiration, deep in the industrial wasteland, has turned these academics into the most controversial pair to wander the West since Bonnie and Clyde.</p>
        <p>Originally, the Buffalo Commons was only an exercise in land-use theory. Both Poppers assumed their prescription for the Plains was destined, like most academic efforts, for obscurity. To see their research find an audience - regional, national and international - has startled, pleased and sometimes alarmed them. ''We wanted to stimulate public debate,'' says Deborah Popper, ''not turn into public figures ourselves.''</p>
        <p>Reaction to their proposal in the Great Plains has been strong: people either love it or hate it. Among the Poppers' more vigorous supporters are the Plains' original buffalo hunters, especially the Sioux. ''Brilliant! The best idea I've heard in years,'' says Vine Deloria Jr. A lawyer and American Indian activist of long standing, author of ''Custer Died for Your Sins,'' he is a faculty member at the University of Colorado. ''As you might imagine,'' Deloria adds, ''the Poppers' research has major implications for South Dakota tribal land claims. We're very, very interested.''</p>
        <p>Detractors are equally vocal. ''Tell the Poppers that America's Great Plains do not equal the Sahara,'' says Gov. Mike Hayden of Kansas. ''Why not seal off declining urban areas as well, and preserve them as museums of 20th-century architecture?''</p>
        <p>Frank Popper, undeterred, is pacing his Rutgers office, imagining advertising copy for a 21st-century Plains. Rumpled and buoyant, he frequently tries out ideas on his collaborator, who sits across the room, sorting computer disks. ''Camera safaris across Oklahoma - Deborah, do you think that will work? Or maybe covered-wagon tours for the eco-chic?''</p>
        <p>Deborah Popper is used to her husband's hyperbolic sense of humor. She rolls her eyes and shrugs. They never expected so much fuss over a single idea. ''Isn't the essence of a scholar's life to deal responsibly with information?'' she says. ''When our data added up to a region in crisis, we couldn't just sit by.''</p>
        <p>As she leaves for the computer lab, her husband sorts through the day's mail: praise for a journal article from a former Cabinet member; speaking invitations from Gdansk and Toronto. By the door is a four-foot-high stack of mail on the Plains proposal: letters from tiny Western towns like Hamilton, Mont.; Walhalla, N.D., and Conlen, Tex. Some are temperate, others enraged. He will answer them all.  For the Poppers, the Buffalo Commons has been a two-way process of education. Mixed use of such a preserve, they have argued from the start, would be crucial to its success; tourism, recreation and retirement communities would all need to flourish in or near a Buffalo Commons. But the startling response to their idea - hundreds of calls and letters from business and government, as well as private citizens - has forced the Poppers to develop their original ideas with unexpected precision.</p>
        <p>Their early impulse to emphasize the poetry of place must now accommodate dozens of practical queries, from setting a possible Government price tag (''Billions, but still less expensive than current farm subsidies,'' says Frank Popper) to honing definitions of mixed-use land. On a Buffalo Commons, would they allow missile sites? (Yes.) Oil derricks? (Yes.) Predators for buffalo, such as mountain lion and prairie wolf? (Yes.) Indians? (Definitely.) The Plains begin where annual rainfall drops below the minimum standard for dependable farming, which is 20 inches. At the 98th meridian, the Midwest's rich, green corn- and dairy land begins yielding to arid range and wheat field. Windswept and austerely beautiful, suffering extremes of heat and cold, the Plains run hundreds of miles west to the Rockies, north into Canada, and south to Texas.</p>
        <p>For Indians and early cattlemen, this region was originally a commons. Animals and people constantly migrated, allowing the dry, fragile ecological system to renew itself. When 19th-century pioneers broke the sod to settle and farm, a grim cycle was set in motion, with results still felt today.</p>
        <p>''We tried to force waterless, treeless steppes to behave like Ohio, and got three or four boom-and-bust episodes for our trouble,'' Frank Popper explains. ''Now the classic Plains cycle of drought, financial woe and depopulation is rolling again, and this time it may go all the way. Thirty years of water-table depletion, S.&amp;.L's collapsing right and left, whole rural counties voting with their feet - and still no one's thinking ahead.''</p>
        <p>In December 1987, an article by the Poppers on the land-use future of the Plains appeared in Planning, a professional journal. Settling the prairies, they argued, was the largest, longest-running agricultural and environmental mistake in United States history. Fusing economics, landscape analysis and statistical modeling, the Poppers mapped a gloomy future for the region in unprecedented, county-by-county detail.</p>
        <p>The article attracted the attention of local, then regional newspapers and radio stations. Cries of outrage erupted across the Plains, which did not go unnoticed by staffers in the office of the Governor of North Dakota. Disparaging references to the Poppers began appearing in Gov. George Sinner's speeches in late 1988.</p>
        <p>''We're not saying, 'Out by Tuesday,' '' Frank Popper insists. ''This is not forced evacuation. The parts of the Plains that would form the initial core of the Buffalo Commons - 109 counties and about 413,000 residents, out of 6.5 million people on the Plains - are depopulating briskly, with no help from us.'' (Although the Plains cover a fifth of the land mass of the lower 48 states, they carry less than 3 percent of the country's total population - and that number is dropping.) ''We don't foresee a Mad Max, total-desolation scenario, but rather a gradual pullback by the private sector, and then nature taking its course across an area one and a half times the size of California.''</p>
        <p>But after two summers of severe drought and what promises to be another hot and dry summer, the Poppers have gained the heartland's reluctant attention.</p>
        <p>Across the Plains, isolated homesteads and sturdy small towns are drying up from lack of water, people and investment dollars. Some Plains state capitals, like Pierre, S.D., have almost no commercial air service. Other locales are losing bus stop, doctor, minister, school. Many rural Plains dwellers must now drive 50 miles for a quart of milk, 75 for a movie, 100 for a shopping mall. Economic growth exists on the Plains, but mostly in the larger towns and cities. Should current depopulation trends continue, almost two-thirds of today's Plains farms and small communities may vanish by 2020.</p>
        <p>The Poppers are suggesting an alternative to this slow abandonment: deprivatize the Plains. Many administrative channels for creating a Buffalo Commons, they point out, are already in place. A collection of Federal and state agencies and private interests already control much of the territory that might constitute the core of a Commons.</p>
        <p>They include the thousands of properties foreclosed by the Farmers Home Administration, the Farm Credit System and private banks; farms under the Department of Agriculture's Conservation Reserve Program (which pays farmers not to cultivate marginal land); holdings of the Interior Department's Bureau of Land Management; acreage held in trust by environmental groups like the Nature Conservancy; state parks and preserves, and national grasslands managed by the United States Forest Service.</p>
        <p>Within the agencies potentially affected by the Popper proposal, reaction has been a muted wait-and-see. ''To the average Government administrator, the Buffalo Commons looks like Frank Lloyd Wright's idea for a mile-high tower,'' says Robert Nelson, an economist and strategic planner in the office of the Secretary of the Interior. ''Proposing it is one thing; doing the engineering plans, quite another.''</p>
        <p>If the Popper plan becomes a reality, these government agencies and private groups would need to work together to consolidate the distressed areas before they can be restored to a presettlement condition, as the Poppers propose. And if a Buffalo Commons ever becomes reality, biologists, botanists and agronomists will have to design and manage it.</p>
        <p>The Poppers have done much to spark the national land-use debate, and the next stage must take place in Washington hearing rooms and New York offices. For administrative and electoral reasons, the short-term prospects of making the Commons a reality are not encouraging: the list of international, Federal, state and private interests involved in possible Commons management is long, and denouncements of the Popper plan are a recognized way for elected officials from Plains states to prove prairie patriotism.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, many longtime observers of American land-use trends, looking beyond the immediate election concerns, believe that some form of Buffalo Commons may well come into being in the not-too-distant future. In another generation, they say, huge tracts of Plains land will be retired, restored and reclaimed.</p>
        <p>''Two factors, in combination, will make the Buffalo Commons a reality,'' says Harold C. Jordahl Jr., a University of Wisconsin emeritus professor of urban and regional planning, and a state and Federal environmental policy adviser since the Kennedy Administration. ''A continuing series of droughts - some climatic disaster on the scale of the 1930's - combined with any evidence of enlightened commercial leadership among Plains business and agribusiness people. . . . Since World War II, the politicians have essentially abandoned rural America, and the result, in this case, is a region in genuine peril.''</p>
        <p>THE POPPERS' PROPOSAL is the most ambitious example to date of the worldwide revival of the commons concept. Cooperatively managed natural reserves are increasingly viewed as a workable answer to problems as difficult, and as different, as harvesting Costa Rican rain forests and saving Bangladeshi fishing grounds.</p>
        <p>In the United States, the concept of commons is a rediscovery, not an innovation. The Boston Common celebrates its 356th anniversary this year. But as recently as the mid-1980's, American land-use specialists regarded the commons idea as an essentially archaic tradition.</p>
        <p>In the summer of 1990, however, precisely a century after the official closing of the American frontier, the commons principle ranks among the hottest topics in land-use thought. In a field caught between practicalities and utopias, the principle's ingenious balancing of development claims and the concerns of those who believe in ''bioheritage'' (the idea that natural resources belong to the human race), its calm acceptance of social responsibility and stewardship, all look suddenly new and desirable.</p>
        <p>Revitalizing the American commons is taking many forms, on the Plains and elsewhere. The Institute of the Rockies, a citizens group in western Montana, is proposing the Big Open, an East African-style buffalo and game reserve. Nevada's Great Basin contains a new national park; the Snake River Plain of Idaho and Nebraska's Sand Hills and Buffalo Prairie may soon follow. Unesco's international biosphere reserves, devoted to the preservation of crucial ecologies, already include parts of the Appalachians, the Everglades and the Great Plains grasslands.</p>
        <p>The commons idea is increasingly popular on the research and philanthropy circuit. An Aspen Institute symposium last July examined the implications of a global commons. Last month, the W. K. Kellogg Foundation helped fund a conference sponsored by the Oregon-based National Rural Studies Committee on the problems of the Plains. An international network of specialists in natural resource management, working on commons questions, is financed by the Ford Foundation. In the complex landscape of policy debate, the Poppers, once pioneers, now have much unexpected company.</p>
        <p>Within university walls, the Poppers' proposal receives praise. ''They're onto something very important, and I admire their courage in taking ideas public, which few academics do,'' says Bret Wallach, a former MacArthur Fellow and a geographer at the University of Oklahoma. ''Since the 1920's, a lot of people in government and agriculture have argued we should retire the least productive, most ecologically fragile prairie land. Through their guts and insouciance, the Poppers may well be the ones to make this work.''</p>
        <p>FRANK AND DEBORAH Popper make an effective research team. Her computer skills verify his hunches; he drafts, she edits; he is the spokesman and animator, she the pattern-finder and corrective. Their roots are urban. He grew up in Chicago; she, in Manhattan. He was educated at Haverford and Harvard; she at Bryn Mawr and Rutgers (his degrees are in psychology and government; hers are in history, library science and geography), and their working lives have been spent in consulting firms, institutes, libraries and universities. On the Great Plains, they realize, such credentials are not endearing.</p>
        <p>The Poppers live in a 1900's frame house, a mile from the Rutgers campus. On this morning, juice cartons and cheese Danish perch atop a copy of ''Zoning and the American Dream.'' The Popper children - Joanna, 17 years old, and Nicholas, 12 - rummage for gym bags and physics papers. Their parents, at table-tennis speed, first debate North Dakota bond issues, then LULU's (locally unwanted land uses, another Popper interest), then Willa Cather's western novels.</p>
        <p>''Twenty-two years of marriage,'' says Deborah Popper, who is 42, ''and we've never stopped talking.''</p>
        <p>''Mostly, she wins, especially on Commons problems,'' her husband, who is 46, chimes in. ''I get too idealistic about the great open spaces. Deborah is a demon for fact.''</p>
        <p>Field-testing the Buffalo Commons concept has required every ounce of fact and idealism the two can summon. Most academic planners and geographers work from data tapes or computer simulations, and talk only to professional peers. What would happen, the Poppers wondered, if they took their ideas out West and explained them to the people most affected?</p>
        <p>Dozens of lectures and symposia later, one result is clear. When the Poppers give public talks anywhere on the Plains, security guards frequently watch the audience.</p>
        <p>''We upset people,'' Frank Popper admits. ''It's a bit like being Salman Rushdie.'' He thinks a moment. ''We have no detailed master plan for the Plains, no mandate or official backing, only the growing sense that history, for a multitude of reasons, is on our side.'' (Popper's years as a Federal consultant have made him extremely wary of six-point plans with rigidly organized subheadings.) ''Maybe, maybe we can inspire enough discussion to affect the American future, instead of watching passively while a wondrous region self-deludes and self-destructs.''</p>
        <p>THE INHABITANTS OF the rural Plains have long felt that those on the coasts perceive their land as flyover country, and are resentful. In difficult, unforgiving country, any change comes hard.</p>
        <p>''Naturally the Poppers' idea looks threatening out there,'' comments Theodore W. Sudia, senior scientist at the National Park Service and a 20-year veteran of preservation and restoration battles. ''For many Plains people, deep down inside, it's still 1870. Self-reliance and caution are profoundly important to them; outside interference, profoundly suspect. How else can they survive? In a landscape that harsh, you risk everything just getting out of bed in the morning.''</p>
        <p>For 10 strenuous days in late April, the Poppers travel some 1,400 miles through the heart of the High Plains, meeting farmers, ranchers, developers, planners and biologists, watching reactions to their proposal.</p>
        <p>The first speaking stop is McCook, Neb. (population: 8,000). McCook epitomizes the self-contained center favored by Deborah Popper's computers for long-term survival. The town has Amtrak service and a United Airlines feeder, a golf course, a CAT scanner, a junior college. Restored five-bedroom Victorian homes average $45,000, and supermarket lines are full of cowboys buying Dove Bars and Evian.</p>
        <p>''This is all very exotic,'' says Frank Popper, inhaling pure, dry prairie air. A half-day out of Newark Airport brings a degree of culture shock: McCook's residents seem extremely polite, blond and husky. ''Nebraska organs are the most requested for transplants nationwide,'' a local nurse says proudly. ''Ours is healthy land.''</p>
        <p>The Poppers' talk packs the high-school auditorium with nearly 400 people, an impressive turnout for a warm Saturday night in calving season. When Deborah Popper's computer-generated maps of doomed Plains counties move across the auditorium screen, there are audible gasps, then a rising hum of defiance and dread.</p>
        <p>Local panelists rise to reply, each rebuttal raising angry cheers. Everywhere they speak, the Poppers encounter a pattern of outrage they call the Four Responses: Pioneer Gumption (''Don't underestimate our determination and hard work''); Dollar Potential (''Plains food production can feed the world''); Eastern Ignorance (self-explanatory), and Prairie Zen (''Our landscape is a powerful source of spiritual renewal'').</p>
        <p>''Effective teaching,'' observes Charlie Gregory, 32, an instructor at McCook Community College, watching the crowd hand in comment sheets at the close of the presentation and walk out stony-faced, like people at a wake. ''This bunch responds to unemotional fact, not Donahue, and that's what they got. Before tonight, about 75 percent were dead set against the Poppers. Now, it's probably 35 percent.''</p>
        <p>The next day, the Poppers drive northwest from McCook through Hayes County, Neb., an area high on their endangered list. Nearly two-thirds the size of Rhode Island, the county has a population of 1,200. Here is the true Plains, a minimalist landscape of sun, wind and grass. One can drive for an hour and encounter few houses, no billboards, no human beings. Frank Popper peers around with interest. What does he see?</p>
        <p>''A severe landscape, made humanly more severe,'' he says, pointing to serpentine erosion gullies, 40 feet deep. ''A dispassionate place. A century ago, we'd count 70 varieties of grasses here, instead of the current two or three. And lots more game. This country is perfectly suited to buffalo, not a monoculture of wheat or corn, not using scarce water to grow crops already in surplus.''</p>
        <p>If many rural Nebraskans, faced with such conditions, have departed for more prosperous farm areas or for cities, other residents cite urban problems - AIDS, pollution and crime - as sound reasons to stay.</p>
        <p>''I got tired of traffic jams and crowds, and came to western Nebraska by covered U-Haul truck,'' explains Johnny R. Scott, 44, who used to live in Jacksonville, Fla., and Washington, and who is now owner of the grocery store in Hayes Center, the county seat.</p>
        <p>Ocia Weston, 76, agrees: ''The Poppers know nothing about us. No way will Hayes County go back to buffalo.''</p>
        <p>While Frank Popper examines a row of deserted buildings, as rapt as if touring Tibet, his wife snaps pictures of the town. He notices the unsmiling onlookers (one filming him with a video camera) and turns to his wife.</p>
        <p>''What have we done to the people of the Plains?'' he says, in mingled wonder and despair.</p>
        <p>''Alerted them,'' she replies. ''It's depressing, and necessary, and now no one is happy. Our next project may be safely overseas. Lithuanian housing reform sounds good.'' They drive west, stopping in Benkelman, Neb., to meet Robert J. Reichert's buffalo herd. Sixty million of these shaggy, one-ton beasts once roamed the Plains, but by 1900 over-hunting reduced the number to a mere thousand. Today, as the market for lean meat increases, Western stockbreeders have turned to buffalo-raising; some ranchers in Colorado and Wyoming now run more than 800 head. Reichert keeps a hobby herd of 24 impressive, big-chested, black-maned animals.</p>
        <p>''Thoreau was right: 'Eastward I go only by force; but westward I go free!' '' Frank Popper shouts, standing joyously in the bed of the rancher's pickup. The truck jolts across a rutted pasture, Colorado on one horizon, Kansas on the other, while a dozen shaggy brown buffalo gallop alongside, snorting and stamping, as splendid as the bison on the cave walls at Lascaux.</p>
        <p>''I could live here,'' Popper declares, his eyes riveted on the tossing horns. ''I could look at this land forever.''</p>
        <p>North of Denver, after some hours of inspecting ghost towns like Keota, Colo. (population: 4), the Poppers drive through a brief and violent cloudburst.</p>
        <p>''What amazing country this is,'' Popper says. He is hunched forward in the van seat as he watches storm clouds move across the front range of the Rockies, its snowfields brilliant against an indigo sky. ''My parents brought me out here on what I now realize were Americanization trips,'' he adds. ''We did a lot of those, the Grand Canyon, Navajo country, Yosemite.'' (His father, an Austrian physician, fled the Nazis in 1938, married another refugee, and settled in Chicago to raise two sons.) On the road, the Poppers live like political candidates: speech, reception, symposium, photo opportunity, debate, farm tour, speech. They have traveled more than 30,000 miles on Buffalo Commons research trips. Except for expense payments and honoraria, the couple bear the cost of these missions. ''We prefer,'' says Frank Popper, ''to remain unbought.''</p>
        <p>A few hours later, the Poppers find themselves in the middle of white wine and scallion beef, Hermes scarves and polished cowboy boots. A reception is being held for them by the Center for the New West, an economic and public-policy think tank in Denver. The suburban living room is crowded with lawyers and bureaucrats. Largely supported by corporate funds, the center encourages high-tech development in states beyond the Mississippi, including those in the Plains, and its work helps to attract East Coast and Pacific Rim investors there. Its picture of a rapidly urbanizing region holds no room for a Buffalo Commons or for the powerfully romantic past the Poppers have invoked.</p>
        <p>Also at the party is Joseph M. Luther, assistant dean of the University of Nebraska architecture school, who will debate Frank Popper in a special American Planning Association session the next day. Luther, too, dislikes mythic visions.</p>
        <p>''Out here we believe in maintaining a positive attitude of thinking,'' he explains. ''If global warming comes, we'll plant palm trees and make Omaha the next Sun Belt. Frank represents Europe, the East, Harvard, Federal interference - everything the good people of the Plains want to get away from, like my ancestors did, as early as the 1790's. . . . No, we will fight the Poppers, all the way.''</p>
        <p>The next morning's forum on the Plains offers rousing political theater. The Denver convention center hall is filled with about 200 city managers, zoning experts, preservationists and development commissioners, all eager to argue, as well as several camera crews. Frank Popper is on the podium. ''Discussion of the Buffalo Commons must spring from fact, not emotion and misperception,'' he declares. Joseph Luther implores the crowd: ''Let us not be buffaloed!'' SIX DAYS AFTER DENVER , an apprehensive Frank Popper stands in a suburban Chicago hotel ballroom, presenting the Buffalo Commons idea to more than 400 members of the Society for Ecological Restoration, the leading international research association that is concerned with restoring and preserving landscapes.</p>
        <p>Ten minutes into his speech, widespread excitement and approval are clear. Many listeners even find the Popper proposal too conservative. The question-and-answer period generates excited talk of similar restoration efforts for the Southern Californian chaparral, Maine's forests, and the great Southern wetlands. At 11 P.M., long after the session's close, hundreds of ecologists continue to mill about the ballroom, trading ideas on Plains re-creation.</p>
        <p>Frank Popper stands by the platform, tired but satisfied, his work as a catalyst done. ''The Buffalo Commons is a metaphor, really,'' he muses, watching the excited faces. ''It's a jumping-off point, a way into many complex land-use dilemmas. Scientists, farm-country people and wheeler-dealers are powerfully resistant to metaphor. Planners and geographers must deal in it constantly.''</p>
        <p>Back at Rutgers, Popper is thinking about the price of change. The view from his office embraces asphalt and concrete, warehouses and power lines, a strip of dying lawn. The local land-use board classes this zone as ''semirural.'' What does he see there?</p>
        <p>''On the Plains, I saw anguish, waste, a lack of sense and awful planning,'' Popper says. ''This, too, is a bleak and difficult landscape. We have seen the future, and it looks like Piscataway, N.J. Ultimately, the Buffalo Commons tries to convey that land use must be a deliberate national choice. The Plains are about to change, maybe for the worse. But they still retain a magnificent, terrifying sense of possibility.''</p>
        <p>''You get very few second chances,'' says Deborah Popper quietly, from the doorway, ''when playing with continents.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
