<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Evolution of Pollution</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="386294"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FINCH, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STONE, ROGER D</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">VOYAGE OF THE SANDERLING, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D91031F930A1575AC0A966958260" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Evolution of Pollution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT FINCH; Robert Finch is the author of ''Outlands: Journeys to the Outer Edge of Cape Cod'' and co-editor, with John Elder, of ''The Norton Book of Nature Writing.''</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FINCH, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>THE VOYAGE OF THE SANDERLING</p>
        <p>By Roger D. Stone.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 302 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>THE VOYAGE OF THE SANDERLING</p>
        <p>By Roger D. Stone.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 302 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $19.95.</p>
        <p>THE VOYAGE OF THE SANDERLING</p>
        <p>By Roger D. Stone.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 302 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $19.95.</p>
        <p>Since the beginning of human society we have clustered along the shores of this planet. It is not surprising then that on his recent 7,685-mile sail from Maine to Rio de Janeiro Roger Stone found booming human populations as the primary cause of the precipitous ecological decline along the Atlantic coast.</p>
        <p>Aboard the 38-foot cutter Sanderling, Mr. Stone, a journalist and a senior fellow at the World Wildlife Fund, set out to explore firsthand the environmental state of the most intensely settled and exploited sections of the New World coast. Much of what he discovered has been documented elsewhere, but his accounts of the decline, and of the heroic commitment of many of the environmentalists who are trying to stop it, are impressive. Some of the practices Mr. Stone describes will jar even jaded sensibilities; did you know that lead tailings were used to pave the walkways of a school in the city of Santo Amaro, Brazil? And the smattering of environmental ironies he includes are quite illuminating; for instance, the chicken manure that runs from Lancaster County's Amish farms in Pennsylvania into Chesapeake Bay - widely touted as a benign byproduct of agriculture - is killing the oysters in the bay.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Stone reports some local successes at coastal preservation and restoration, for the most part his book makes the ''gloomy assumption'' that ''the slide [is]  likely to continue,'' and he documents the decline all the way down the coast. His goal is ambitious, the issues he raises important, his energy unflagging and his documentation solid. The long, meticulous entries on weather, coastal features and the frustrating intricacies of harbor bureaucracies will appeal to sailing enthusiasts. And the capsule histories of the sites he visits are a virtual handbook on 500 years of coastal environmental degradation and 40 years of efforts to counteract it.</p>
        <p>But a continuous sailing trip down the Atlantic coast is not the ''organizing principle'' the author hoped it would be. The book is, in a way, too ambitious and too well documented. Confronted with the ''horrors'' he catalogues, we miss any real passion. His pessimistic assessment (at odds with his upbeat temperament) saps the narrative of any compelling drama or clear focus. There seems little time for candid reflection on what he sees. Individuals and islands are skillfully sketched, but they are too numerous. They begin to blur, like characters introduced and then forgotten in a novel.</p>
        <p>Even more disappointing, his mission aboard the Sanderling remains largely unfulfilled. In his introduction, Mr. Stone writes that he hopes to ''establish useful contrasts'' in the ways different regions handle their problems, but toward the end of his book he lamely concludes, ''One can only wonder what lessons the Brazilians, and the people of the Caribbean, might draw from the U.S. experience.''</p>
        <p>The reader wonders just what it was Mr. Stone learned that ''would be hard to get in any other way.'' Still, he is a perceptive and indefatigable observer, and his findings raise a larger issue that he occasionally hints at - namely the interdependence of all local ecosystems. He correctly points out, for instance, that coastal ecosystems are more resilient than terrestrial ones and that the capacity for self-restoration remains great even in many of the worst-polluted bays and estuaries. In Mr. Stone's eyes, the patchwork quilt of Caribbean island nations seems to have the best chance of keeping its environment intact because each island is isolated and self-governed.</p>
        <p>An island is an island, but in another sense no island is an island. Bahamian lobster fishermen may curb the use of bleach that kills coral, but that would not save those same coral reefs from a gradual rise in ocean temperatures caused by global warming. Likewise, it is possible to stop dumping industrial waste and stop letting fertilizers and pesticides from farms run into Chesapeake Bay, but who is to blame for the fact that one-quarter of the nitrogen entering the bay comes from acid rain?</p>
        <p>Mr. Stone goes to the heart of the Atlantic coast's troubles when he writes that ''no public entity has yet dared to place an absolute limit on the growth of human population.'' Unless we can somehow balance our democratic commitment to human freedom with a commitment to the environment, no amount of regulation, individual effort, money or political power will be enough to reverse the tide of degradation. ''The Voyage of the Sanderling'' demonstrates how nature puts democracy to the acid test.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
