<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>S.I.'s Relief Called Brooklyn's Headache</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="352039"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRIDGES AND TUNNELS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TOLLS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VERRAZANO-NARROWS BRIDGE (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">STATEN ISLAND (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BROOKLYN (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D91E3AF933A25756C0A966958260" item-length="1411" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>S.I.'s Relief Called Brooklyn's Headache</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In 1986, Staten Island got a break when the eastbound toll of the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge was removed to speed traffic to Brooklyn and reduce air pollution. To the delight of Staten Islanders, the change has worked as intended.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In 1986, Staten Island got a break when the eastbound toll of the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge was removed to speed traffic to Brooklyn and reduce air pollution. To the delight of Staten Islanders, the change has worked as intended.</p>
        <p>In 1986, Staten Island got a break when the eastbound toll of the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge was removed to speed traffic to Brooklyn and reduce air pollution. To the delight of Staten Islanders, the change has worked as intended.</p>
        <p>But four years later, residents in lower Manhattan and along the western edge of Brooklyn complain bitterly in community meetings and in letters to politicians that they are increasingly bearing the burden of the pollution and traffic backups that had afflicted Staten Island.</p>
        <p>Since the change, hundreds of thousands of motorists have altered their travel routes to save on tolls, which were doubled for west-bound bridge traffic. For example, instead of paying the toll traveling west to Staten Island, many drivers head for the Holland Tunnel in lower Manhattan, where there is no charge to New Jersey. The result has been big increases in pollution and traffic on the Gowanus and Brooklyn-Queens Expressways, and many Brooklyn and Manhattan streets, including Canal Street.</p>
        <p>Transferring Pollution</p>
        <p>Residents in Brooklyn and lower Manhattan say politicians simply moved the problems from a smaller part of the city, Staten Island, to a much wider area. The situation offers a vivid example of how environmental hazards can be transferred, intentionally or not, from one place to another by political and business decisions.</p>
        <p>Such a situation is most often seen on a national and international scale. Coal-burning power plants in the Middle West have contributed to the acid rain that pollutes lakes in the Adirondacks and Canada. Ozone formed in Virginia and Maryland adds to the smog in the New York metropolitan region, which helps pollute the air as far north as Bar Harbor, Me. In one sense, the situation on the Verrazano-Narrows is no different. Many Staten Islanders like to think of their area as a city far removed from New York, a notion expressed in the borough's secession movement.</p>
        <p>An apparent ''us against them'' mentality helps account for how the toll became one way in the first place. But it does not explain why it has remained one way, despite four years of opposition from neighborhood groups and considerable evidence of increased noise and air pollution in Brooklyn and Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''It would be hard to justify in terms of traffic congestion and air quality,'' Eric A. Goldstein, a lawyer with the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental advocacy group based in Manhattan, said of the one-way toll.</p>
        <p>The answer may lie in the politics of New York State. For one reason or another, Gov. Mario M. Cuomo, a Democrat, has not been eager to tinker with a situation that Staten Island clearly finds beneficial.</p>
        <p>In the mid-1980's, Representative Guy V. Molinari, a Staten Island Republican, decided that the pollution and congestion from traffic at the Verrazano-Narrows toll booths, which are on the Staten Island side of the bridge, were too much.</p>
        <p>Unable to get the state to address his concerns, Mr. Molinari persuaded his colleagues on Capitol Hill to pass a law in 1985 that eliminated the toll for eastbound traffic. The legislation included a provision under which New York State would lose 1 percent of its Federal highway money if the toll collections were not changed to conform to the measure.</p>
        <p>Called a 'Fair Approach'</p>
        <p>Under the law, the change could have been canceled any time, with no penalty, after six months if the Governor petitioned the Federal Transportation Secretary and showed that there had been a revenue loss and adverse traffic consequences.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't think of a more fair approach,'' said Mr. Molinari, who is now the Staten Island Borough President, in a recent interview.</p>
        <p>Even before the change took effect in March 1986, studies by the state had concluded that it would transfer the pollution and traffic to other parts of the city and cost the state millions of dollars in revenue from the bridge.</p>
        <p>Six months came and went. Congestion in the eastbound lanes was alleviated and pollution near the bridge in Staten Island decreased. But, as some studies predicted, drivers altered their routes and began traveling through Brooklyn and Manhattan.</p>
        <p>A 1987 environmental impact statement conducted by the state found, for example, that annual eastbound traffic - the free direction - had increased by 455,000 vehicles while westbound traffic - where cars pay a $5 toll and some trucks pay a $30 toll - had decreased by 1.4 million vehicles.</p>
        <p>Loss of Revenue</p>
        <p>The one-way toll has cost the Triborough Bridge and Tunnel Authority, which operates the bridge, more than $7 million a year, the study found. About 160,000 vehicles a day use the 26-year-old bridge.</p>
        <p>At the same time, tests at different spots along the Gowanus and Brooklyn-Queens Expressways found increased air and noise pollution.</p>
        <p>Mayor David N. Dinkins favors a return of the two-way toll, as he did when he was Manhattan borough president. So do Howard Golden, the Brooklyn Borough President; Ruth W. Messinger, the Manhattan Borough President, and Representatives Ted Weiss and Stephen J. Solarz, Democrats of Manhattan and Brooklyn, respectively, who represent the affected areas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Solarz said recently that he would be calling on the Governor to reinstate the two-way toll.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo, for the most part, appears to favor the two-way toll, suggesting in March 1988 that it be reinstated for trucks. But he did not act with dispatch, waiting a year and a half before petitioning the Federal Government to end the toll experiment. In April 1988, the Transportation Department agreed.</p>
        <p>New Studies Under Way</p>
        <p>Two years later, residents of lower Manhattan and the western edge of Brooklyn are no closer to reversal of the toll strategy. New state environmental and transportation impact studies are under way but there is no indication when they will be completed, said a spokeswoman for the Triborough Bridge and Tunnel Authority.</p>
        <p>''The Governor's interest in the issue is demonstrated by his desire for an exhaustive review by the M.T.A. of its three options: one-way, two-way, and two-way tolls for trucks only,'' said Thomas Conroy, a spokesman for the Governor. The Metropolitan Transportation Authority is the parent agency of the bridge authority, which is conducting the environmental studies.</p>
        <p>The situation has become a bureaucratic nightmare, the residents say.</p>
        <p>''It's like battering your head against the wall,'' said Linda Lawton, co-chairwoman of the Holland Tunnel Neighborhood Improvement Association, a community group concerned about traffic congestion in the tunnel area. ''It's very discouraging because facts don't count. The reality of the situation doesn't matter. It boils down to politics.'' Ms. Lawton lives on Broome Street near the tunnel entrance, where motorists trying to avoid the Verrazano-Narrows toll have added to traffic backups in the last four years, she said.</p>
        <p>''How could anyone who says he is an environmentalist want more traffic in Manhattan?'' said Kay Powell, a member of the SoHo Alliance, a community group, referring to Governor Cuomo. ''His silence means there's some kind of a political trade-off. He is doing a favor to someone in Staten Island.''</p>
        <p>There are several possible reasons for why Mr. Cuomo has not been more aggressive on the toll issue. One possibility, Staten Island residents say, is that Staten Island already bears an unfair share of New York City's environmental burdens - in particular, the Fresh Kills Landfill.</p>
        <p>''I think we have enough problems over here, with the dump,'' said Jack Sciarabba, who lives near the Verrazano-Narrows toll plaza. ''We're taking their garbage, let them take some traffic.''</p>
        <p>Another possibility is that Mr. Cuomo, faced with battles over the budget and education, has no desire to pick a fight with Republicans over what many might consider a minor issue. At the same time, some residents say, the Governor may feel there is little to gain in an election year from tinkering with what has become the status quo. Overall, the bridge is far more important to Staten Island than to Manhattan and Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Mr. Molinari said the Governor would not end one-way tolls for cars because ''simply, it works.'' Reinstating two-way tolls would do nothing to relieve congestion in places like the Holland Tunnel, he said.</p>
        <p>Those who favor such a change are ''misguided souls who want to turn the clock back,'' Mr. Molinari said. ''The battle is over; we've proved our point.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
