<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rise in Migratory Seals Poses Safety Concerns</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="339844"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEALS (ANIMALS) AND SEALING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RARITAN BAY (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ATLANTIC CITY (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">MARINE MAMMAL STRANDING CENTER</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARNEY, LEO H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHOELKOPF, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey/Atlantic City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDB1031F932A35757C0A966958260" item-length="937" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rise in Migratory Seals Poses Safety Concerns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEO H. CARNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CARNEY, LEO H</byline>
      <dateline>BRIGANTINE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: AN increase in migratory seals along the state's coastline, from Raritan Bay to Atlantic City, is posing a problem: where can the creatures find a safe haven in a heavily populated and developed region?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: AN increase in migratory seals along the state's coastline, from Raritan Bay to Atlantic City, is posing a problem: where can the creatures find a safe haven in a heavily populated and developed region?</p>
        <p>AN increase in migratory seals along the state's coastline, from Raritan Bay to Atlantic City, is posing a problem: where can the creatures find a safe haven in a heavily populated and developed region?</p>
        <p>That question has become an even more pointed one for Robert Schoelkopf, who, as the founder and director of the Marine Mammal Stranding Center here, is the only person in New Jersey licensed by the United States Fish and Wildlife Service to rescue and care for seals, other sea mammals and turtles.</p>
        <p>''What we're afraid of this year,'' Mr. Schoelkopf said in a recent interview at the center, ''is that many of these seals will become comfortable obtaining food in some back bays or rivers and never make their way north before the summer crowds and heavy boating traffic arrives. They will die.''</p>
        <p>In 1989, Mr. Schoelkopf said, eight seals were recovered by the center, a portion of those that die unnoticed or that survive and return north before being sighted and caught. This year, he said, nine seals have been rescued. Many more are expected by the year's end, he said.</p>
        <p>'There Is No Room for Them'</p>
        <p>''These animals used to be found here routinely in larger numbers in back bays and beaches,'' Mr. Schoelkopf said, ''but we've built homes and businesses and bulkheads right up to the water's edge and there is no room for them any more - no remote places for them to haul out.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the seals themselves have not been dissuaded from coming ashore this winter on bridge abutments, the backyards of summer homes and even on the hull of a half-sunken boat.</p>
        <p>''We don't recommend that anyone try to catch one,'' Mr. Schoelkopf cautioned, ''even someone who is used to handling other animals like dogs. Seals have a severe bite, and they can twist or turn and get you from angles you would never expect.''</p>
        <p>Because the increasing seal problem along the New Jersey coast is such a recent phenomenon, there has not yet been a scientifically documented cause given for it. But Mr. Schoelkopf speculated that the growth of the population of seals in Canada, where they breed, has caused them to extend their range southward in greater numbers.</p>
        <p>''There has been greater protection of breeding seals in general in Canada because of protests over the years by people in the United States,'' Mr. Schoelkopf said. ''Canadian officials have told the Wildlife Service that this is why we have a problem now, and the Canadians are shaking their fingers at us saying, 'See, we told you so. ''</p>
        <p>Considering that most of the seals in New Jersey are yearlings, Mr. Schoelkopf said, ''It is also possible that their habitat range has expanded simply because the younger seals cannot compete successfully with adults.''</p>
        <p>Global Warming Cited</p>
        <p>Another possibility, he said, was the overall global warming, which could be diminishing ice floes in Canada and northern New England, thus allowing the seals to travel farther in winter. Warmer weather, Mr. Schoelkopf said, could be causing the seals' food, like mackerel, to be entering New Jersey waters earlier, thereby creating food opportunities in the seals' southern range.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schoelkopf said there had been multiple daily sightings of seals reported to the center this winter from places like Sandy Hook, Sea Bright, Mantoloking and Atlantic City.</p>
        <p>Catching them is difficult. For example, Mr. Schoelkopf said, when the seals, even injured ones, are pursued by people, they simply dive back into the water, where they have an advantage.</p>
        <p>''We cannot catch them in the water,'' Mr. Schoelkopf said. ''They have to be on land, where they are vulnerable. We approach them very slowly, throw a net over them and gently transport them in one of our carriers to the center.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schoelkopf said the seals' illnesses, although fewer this year, were probably an indicator of the polluted waters through which they must migrate to get here.</p>
        <p>Eye and mouth lesions are common, he said, as well as localized infections and septicemia, a systemic blood infection. A few seals have had massive internal infections, visceral deterioration and high levels of mercury and other toxic metals in their fat tissues, Mr. Schoelkopf said.</p>
        <p>Human Bacteria in Dolphins</p>
        <p>Dr. Virginia Pierce, director of veterinary pathology at the Philadelphia Zoo, who has worked with the center in treating seals, and Mr. Schoelkopf said that because of the center's lack of funds, comparative and long-term studies and adequate testing of the seals, as well as the whales, sea turtles and dolphins that the center takes in, have never been performed.</p>
        <p>''It is impossible to get evidence that is incontrovertible,'' Dr. Pierce said, ''but pollution is probably the cause of the stress that the animals arrive with.''</p>
        <p>After the death of hundreds of bottlenose dolphins in the state in 1987, Dr. Pierce said, some 15 strains of bacteria were identified in their bodies. Many of these were known to come from humans or to cause dysentery in humans.</p>
        <p>This, Dr. Pierce said, raises the possibility that the dolphin deaths and the seal infections could be caused by the same polluted waters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schoelkopf said the harbor seals ''live in coastal waters and it is our coastal waters that are most seriously polluted.'' He added that ''the toxic metals that were found obviously came from the seals' food, fish, and those fish are from coastal waters.''</p>
        <p>It could be, Dr. Pierce said, that the toxic metals, which are stored in fat tissues, become recirculated throughout the entire body of the seal when it is stressed from some other cause and its body begins to call upon fat reserves.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
