<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="374238"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D81030F935A3575BC0A966958260" item-length="1220" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-8</p>
        <p>An Iraqi withdrawal from Kuwait is the only outcome that is acceptable to the United States, President Bush said, all but committing himself to use military force against Iraq if diplomatic efforts and economic sanctions fail.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-8</p>
        <p>An Iraqi withdrawal from Kuwait is the only outcome that is acceptable to the United States, President Bush said, all but committing himself to use military force against Iraq if diplomatic efforts and economic sanctions fail.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-8</p>
        <p>An Iraqi withdrawal from Kuwait is the only outcome that is acceptable to the United States, President Bush said, all but committing himself to use military force against Iraq if diplomatic efforts and economic sanctions fail.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: President Bush could be facing his undoing as the Persian Gulf crisis continues, after being held in high esteem by the American public for much of his foreign policy efforts.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Iraq's proxy government in Kuwait threatened possible hostage-taking or nationalization of foreign property in the face of international calls for sanctions against Iraq.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A world-wide ban on oil purchases from Iraq and occupied Kuwait is expected to be approved by the United Nations Security Council as well as a prohibition on all other trade and financial dealings with these countries.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Economic embargoes rarely succeed in changing the behavior of a target nation, but the sanctions by the industrial nations against Iraq could hobble Baghdad's economy, oil analysts and Middle East experts say.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Iraqi official urges Turkey not to shut pipeline</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Japanese will join allies in embargoes</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Minor blessing, not a windfall, for Mexico</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Psychology tops supply and demand in gasoline pricing</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Kuwait's ambassador to U.S. is embattled in his own way</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Jerusalem Journal: How to stretch a shekel</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>U.S. Marines flew into Liberia to evacuate Americans and foreign dependents, after a rebel leader threatened to start taking foreign prisoners.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>With care, U.S. presses Kenya to open political process</p>
        <p>A2</p>
        <p>The U.S.'s new Cambodia policy has been well received there, but it does not alter a domestic situation that is slowly deteriorating 11 months after the withdrawal of most Vietnamese troops.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>A plan to speed unification elections in Germany to an earlier date is creating much divisiveness in both Bonn and East Berlin.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>A Romanian move to free markets may be difficult. Many Romanians have a poor understanding of economic realities after Nicolae Ceausescu's isolationist policies.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>In Canada, war-crime charges haunt scientist</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Brazil's costly trip to market economy</p>
        <p>D8</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A9-11, A14, B8-9</p>
        <p>A study of infant mortality calls for spending about $500 million a year. But the report, a high-level Administration effort, appears to have been put on hold.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Some tenets of Christian Science, and particularly its absolute reliance on prayer in lieu of standard medical treatment, have come under intense attack in courtrooms and state legislatures.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Oregon Congressman Denny Smith had been a director of a savings and loan institution at the same time that he was trying to influence Federal regulations of the savings industry as a lawmaker.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Converting aging nuclear missiles to cheap rockets for launching satellites would take place under a plan that presents the Government with a difficult choice: gaining quick savings or investing in American industry.</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Changes in the ''Star Wars'' plan, introduced in legislation sent to the White House, will be fought by the Pentagon, the head of the Strategic Defense Initiative office said.</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Navy investigates reactors' safety</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Audit says Air Force misspent nearly $10 million</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Senate approves AIDS and transportation measures</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Adviser council rejects restriction on Endowment grants</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Tuninca, Miss., and areas like it, will be among the first to be pinched if Washington finally enacts new provisions of the farm law. Tuninca seems a throwback to the Old South and its sprawling plantations.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Washington Talk: Senate vs.</p>
        <p>Souter</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>A program to reduce drunk driving uses the techniques of modern advertising and marketing to sell the designated-driver concept. Martha's Vineyard is being used as a laboratory for the program.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>F.B.I. report confirms sharp rise in violent crime</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Vermont justices say Indians may fish without licenses</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>REGIONAL</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Floyd H. Flake's rise to power as a religious and political leader in southeast Queens is a story of uncommon idealism and ambition. He faces a 17-count Federal indictment on charges of misusing money from his church.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Flake received overwhelming support at church</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Thousands of mentally ill patients and others unable to care for themselves are being assigned by New York State authorities to live in unsanitary, dilapidated and poorly supervised group homes or halfway houses, inspections by a state agency have found.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Crime is rising in the West Village, as scores of muggers, prostitutes, drug dealers and ''gay bashers'' wander some streets. Alarmed residents have begun hiring private security patrols.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Mayor Dinkins to announce hiring of 1,058 police officers</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>A city program to promote recycling, which may test the limits of people's willingness to change their behavior for the common good, involves 13 buildings on Manhattan's Upper East Side.</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Judge Joseph Force Crater is still missing, but his case lingers on, 60 years after anyone remembers seeing him alive.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>New York's historical trees greeted with new registry</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>People with aviophobia left terra firma - and fear - behind</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Street bridge plan is roiling TriBeCa</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DIGEST</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY</p>
        <p>The fast track in tennis starts early for the increasing numbers of young tennis prodigies attending special tennis schools. Their ranks have grown rapidly since the ascension of Jennifer Capriati, who became a millionaire at 13.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Baseball: Fernandez falters in loss to Cards</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Kelly stars as Yanks win</p>
        <p>C3</p>
        <p>Boxing: Mercer defeats Cooper</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Column: Berkow on rain delay at Hall of Fame</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Football: Seifert makes 49ers team of his own</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Golf: Golfers uneasy over Shoal Creek</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Goodwill Games: Mixed views on success</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Horse Racing: Chief Honcho wins</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Outdoors: Finicky salmon</p>
        <p>C9</p>
        <p>Soccer: New leader for U.S. federation</p>
        <p>C5</p>
        <p>ARTS/ENTERTAINMENT</p>
        <p>Bourgeois's show in Lyons</p>
        <p>C11</p>
        <p>Young dancers visit from Puerto Rico</p>
        <p>C11</p>
        <p>Music: Jazz festival opens</p>
        <p>C11</p>
        <p>Word and Image: ''Working for the Japanese''</p>
        <p>C14</p>
        <p>Commercials limited in Italy</p>
        <p>C14</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B14</p>
        <p>EDITORIALS/LETTERS/OP-ED</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>The uses of force</p>
        <p>In verification, trust</p>
        <p>Civil rights: No steps back</p>
        <p>David Unger: Thailand</p>
        <p>LETTERS  A12</p>
        <p>Tom Wicker: Reacting to Kuwait</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Yossi Melman: Why Israel may show its nuclear hand</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>John Steinbeck: The author, on ''Grapes of Wrath''</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>David Doniger, Alan Miller:</p>
        <p>Global warming and business</p>
        <p>A13</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
