<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reflections On a Cold Place</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="337672"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DE103DF936A15750C0A966958260" item-length="3292" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reflections On a Cold Place</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Malcolm W. Browne: Malcolm W. Browne reports on science for The New York Times. He made his third trip to Antarctica last December.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: YOU'RE GOING TO SEE some changes on the ice,'' a construction engineer told me as we changed into polar garb for the flight from New Zealand to Antarctica. ''Whatever you do, don't get caught throwing away a cigarette butt or beer can.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: YOU'RE GOING TO SEE some changes on the ice,'' a construction engineer told me as we changed into polar garb for the flight from New Zealand to Antarctica. ''Whatever you do, don't get caught throwing away a cigarette butt or beer can.''</p>
        <p>YOU'RE GOING TO SEE some changes on the ice,'' a construction engineer told me as we changed into polar garb for the flight from New Zealand to Antarctica. ''Whatever you do, don't get caught throwing away a cigarette butt or beer can.''</p>
        <p>After six years away from Antarctica I was prepared to see unwonted cleanliness when I returned last December. Unfortunately, the style of travel was all too familiar. The flight from Christchurch to McMurdo Station aboard a Royal New Zealand Air Force cargo plane was as cramped and uncomfortable as ever; the only innovation in air transportation during the last quarter century has been the introduction of dogs to sniff for drugs in passengers' baggage. For nearly nine hours, the kettle-drum din of engines and vibrating metal crashed through our heads, and we sweated in our Antarctic gear. At last we staggered to the ice, our cramped knees faltering. Then came that first breath of deliciously cold air, the dazzling whiteness, the Shangri-la exhilaration. I've heard even grizzled polar veterans whoop with joy on touching the ice after a few years' absence. Antarctica seems almost as unearthly as Mars - in fact, Mars-bound experiments have been tested there - and travelers who manage to set foot on the seventh continent know they are among a happy few.</p>
        <p>On the night we arrived the air was radiantly clear, and the midsummer sun stood high in the sky. Fifty miles to the west, across the unbroken sheet of sea ice, the white and blue dome of Mount Discovery and the rugged Royal Society Range shimmered invitingly. At the base of the mountains one could spy a barrier of incredibly high cliffs, but veterans knew it to be only a mirage - one of the White Continent's bag of beautiful, dangerous illusions.</p>
        <p>McMurdo, our destination, a mile away in the opposite direction, on the coast of Ross Island, was marked by a barrier of high ice ridges squeezing against the rocky shore. Just past the pressure ridges, we could make out the station's bright red helicopters on their pad, and on higher ground the drab structures of ''Mac Town'' proper - McMurdo Station. Beyond loomed Mount Erebus, one of Antarctica's two active volcanoes. It is easy to forget the hundreds of lives Erebus has claimed and to see only the beauty of its white summit and plume of smoke.</p>
        <p>Intimations of the changes that are sweeping Antarctica appeared soon after our truck began jouncing across the ice cracks and deep pockets of melt water.</p>
        <p>Ahead lay Discovery Hut - the squat wooden cabin that Capt. Robert F. Scott and his crew erected in 1901 in the hope of conquering a continent. Preserved by Antarctica's cold, dry air, with a little help from New Zealand's landmark conservators, it has long been a reminder of the heroism and tragedy that marked old-time exploration, a conspicuous feature of McMurdo's skyline. But now a row of high, brown dormitory buildings dominates the site, making Discovery Hut as incongruous in its setting as Trinity Church amid the towers of Wall Street. Other new buildings now occupy a ceremonial patch of dusty ground called International Square, which commands a spectacular view of the distant mountains and glaciers. Flags representing nations subscribing to the 1959 Antarctic Treaty used to flank a heroic bust of Adm. Richard Evelyn Byrd - the very epitome of heroic polar tradition. But now the square, the flags and the Byrd statue have been replaced by a new laboratory complex with a maze of ugly gray walls. If a housing boom is making dingy McMurdo uglier than ever, other changes have been for the good. Gradually, I noticed that the mountains of junk that used to cover much of the upper part of the town had disappeared. Because the cold dry air preserves every scrap of waste, and the permafrost prohibits the construction of cellars where trash could at least be put out of sight, McMurdo will never look pristine. But the rusting piles of vehicles and machinery were gone, and so were the heaps of worn-out tires; discarded exercise machines, bicycles, stoves and sheet metal; the jumble of leaky fuel, chemical and urine drums - a mess that had been accumulating for more than 30 years. Some of it had been buried in a new landfill up the hill; most of it was arranged in orderly rows, awaiting shipment back to the United States. And, trudging over to the dining room in Building 155 - McMurdo's town hall, shopping mall and recreation area all rolled into one - we noticed other changes. Notices proclaimed that boots were henceforth banned from indoor areas. The Navy would no longer tolerate volcanic dust and mud tracked inside. Perhaps most significant, signs directed that all trash was to be sorted and placed in color-coded receptacles for recycling or ''retrograding'' - military jargon for shipment back to the United States, with the result that behind Building 155 there were no more skuas, the predatory seagulls that used to swarm around like rats at a dump.</p>
        <p>The new rules, some of them trivial in themselves, are symptoms of profound changes in official attitudes toward Antarctica. The days are past when the swashbuckling polar explorer could do what he felt necessary to survive and conquer; today, a concerned and critical world is looking over his shoulder.</p>
        <p>ANTARCTICA IS CAUSING AN uneasy stir among diplomats, conservationists and scientists. Both greed and anxiety have come into play. Although its working population is steadily rising and tourists visit its coastal stations and even its interior mountains in increasing numbers, Antarctica is scarcely overcrowded; during the peak summer season an estimated 4,000 people are spread over a continent equal in area to the United States and Mexico. (In addition, last year 2,500 tourists visited the continent.) Eighteen nations operate 41 permanent stations - McMurdo, with a summer population of 1,100, is by far the largest - and several scores of seasonal camps in Antarctica. With the encouragement of their Governments, a few Argentine and Chilean families are raising children on the Antarctic Peninsula, and Chile has opened a hotel at its Teniente Marsh Station. None of this adds up to a population explosion, but the impact of even a limited number of people can be immense, especially in an area as rich in resources as Antarctica.</p>
        <p>An ice sheet covers 97.6 percent of Antarctica; in places, it reaches a depth of nearly three miles. This sheet, containing about 90 percent of the world's ice, is so heavy that it compresses the rocky continent downward an average of 2,000 feet. Only a tiny part of Antarctica emerges at the edge of the ice sheet or protrudes above it as mountains. Still, the land holds minerals that include coal, molybdenum, chromium, nickel, tin, iron, copper, platinum and gold. The sediments beneath Antarctica's coastal waters contain traces of hydrocarbon, and the possibility exists that a supergiant oil field might be discovered.</p>
        <p>And although commercial operators no longer hunt fur seals in Antarctica, and whaling has been reduced to ''scientific'' catches, the Soviet Union, Japan and several other nations still fish Antarctic waters. The harvesting of krill (as food for livestock or for processing into edible proteins for humans) is increasing.</p>
        <p>The difficulties of exploiting Antarctica's considerable resources are formidable, but some experts believe the day will come when mining and perhaps even petroleum drilling will become practical and profitable. Against that day, the nations of the world are jockeying for position.</p>
        <p>Rival claims for territory and for Antarctica's real or imaginary mineral wealth have been in abeyance since the Antarctic Treaty was signed, in 1959; 39 nations now subscribe to that treaty, which also bans military activity (except in the pursuit of science) and restricts operations that pollute the environment or harm wildlife. Nations are permitted to conduct surprise inspections of one another's stations, and the treaty encourages them to cooperate in scientific endeavors.</p>
        <p>But the Antarctic Treaty will be eligible for review for the first time next year, and there are fears that it could come unstuck. An eight-year effort by the treaty nations to obtain international backing for a minerals agreement ''ran into problems,'' as the Department of State puts it, last summer when Australia and France refused to sign it.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, a coalition of third-world nations led by Malaysia has been insisting on a general distribution of Antarctica's presumed riches, on the ground that the continent belongs to all nations. The treaty nations, the protesters say, are exercising modern-day colonialism in Antarctica, barring participation by non-members of ''the club.''</p>
        <p>Greenpeace, the best organized and financed of international conservation groups involved with Antarctica, has mounted a parallel assault on the treaty powers, though one with a very different goal. Greenpeace has been a thorn in the side of the treaty powers ever since the arrival of a four-person year-round staff, which established headquarters at Cape Evans, 18 miles from McMurdo. Greenpeace has campaigned against the French at Dumont d'Urville Station, where an Adelie penguin rookery was dynamited to build an airstrip; castigated Great Britain for leaving leaking oil barrels at an abandoned station; and obstructed a Soviet factory ship that was hauling in fish in Antarctic waters. Two years ago, Greenpeace invaded McMurdo, gathering up a load of trash that had blown out of the dump, and deposited it in the vestibule of the Chalet administration building. ''I'd have gone after them with a fire ax if I'd been there,'' a National Science Foundation official said later.</p>
        <p>''The isolation of Antarctica has provided a shield behind which nations have operated for years,'' said Dr. Maj De Poorter, a Greenpeace spokesman. ''The Greenpeace expedition has removed that shield in order to pressure nations to act responsibly.'' The targets of that activism take a different view. ''Their methods are confrontational - Machiavellian,'' says Erick Chiang, senior United States representative in Antarctica. ''The sad thing is that their aims and ours are not really different. The pollution of Antarctica, by ourselves included, was a disgrace. But remember, it's only been in recent years that we Americans have started cleaning up our act at home. Every large town in America is having trouble with overloaded landfills and dumps, and what we're doing here is tackling the same problems. It didn't take Greenpeace to make us realize what we had to do.''</p>
        <p>AS JUNK BEGINS TO move out of Antarctica, a vast flow of new operating and scientific equipment is moving in - balloon-launching rigs, astronomical telescopes, gamma-ray spectrographs, gas analyzers, antennas, tracking stations, seismographs, computer centers and all the other paraphernalia of cutting-edge research. Antarctica has become a focus of scientific attention as never before.</p>
        <p>One reason is the growing perception of Antarctica as a crow's nest from which some of the planet's mounting environmental problems can be spied in advance. Typical of these is the ozone hole, which since 1979 has been opening alarmingly each spring over the continent. The hole, actually a region in the stratosphere where normal atmospheric ozone is severely depleted, worries scientists because its spread could ultimately rob the earth of its atmospheric shield against dangerous ultraviolet radiation. Even though the United States and some other countries have banned the use of certain chlorofluorocarbons that are believed to contribute to ozone depletion, the hole persists. Increased worldwide exposure to ultraviolet radiation could result in an epidemic of skin cancer and eye cataracts.</p>
        <p>Antarctica is also a uniquely useful site for gauging global warming, or the ''greenhouse effect.'' The accumulated layers of compacted snow contain a record of atmospheric conditions that goes back nearly a quarter of a million years. Analyses of cores of ice for two isotopes of oxygen give scientists a measure of the atmosphere's temperature at the time any given layer was deposited. By comparing fluctuations in temperature with fluctuations in the amount of carbon dioxide trapped in the ice, they hope to determine whether the greenhouse effect has operated in the past.</p>
        <p>The world can no longer afford narrowly provincial attitudes toward Antarctica, says John T. Lynch, science director of the United States South Pole Station.</p>
        <p>''There's been more international scientific cooperation down here than anywhere else in the world,'' he told me as we walked toward one of the new astronomical observatories being erected on the white desert a mile from South Pole Station. ''But there's got to be even more of it. The advanced science that needs to be done from now on will require money and resources beyond the capacities of most nations working alone. I'd like to see an international station built here on the polar plateau - a model, perhaps, for future international space stations.''</p>
        <p>Like many of his colleagues, Lynch believes that future stations should be built not so much to keep hostile nature at bay as to allow their occupants some feeling of identity with nature. As if to underscore his point, Dr. Lynch had dressed only lightly for our walk, leaving his parka behind. Despite the 10-degree temperature, the bright sun and still air made the day seem almost balmy. ''Take this damn dome enclosing South Pole Station,'' he said, referring to the enormous aluminum dome that encloses the insulated, windowless buildings making up the station. ''The design is what you'd expect from an era when an Antarctic station was considered in the same breath as an undersea habitat or a moon base - a kind of fortress. But what we need is light, air, and a view of our surroundings - a sense of belonging.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps. Other scientists point out that for half the year the South Pole lies in constant darkness except for the shimmering of the aurora, the blazing stars and the moon. The world's record low temperature (minus 129 degrees F.) and highest wind speeds (more than 150 miles an hour) have been registered in Antarctica. Fascinated though he was by the (Continued on Page 92) polar plateau, Scott wrote in 1903: ''Could anything be more terrible than this silent, wind-swept immensity?'' Most scientists prefer to let automata replace human labor on the terrible plateau. Robert M. Morse, an astrophysicist from the University of Wisconsin, is a strong believer in remote control. Dr. Morse and other scientists from the University of Wisconsin and Purdue University recently completed a large astronomical telescope whose 10 focusing mirrors are designed to gather light from the faint blue flashes (called Cherenkov radiation) in the upper atmosphere caused by the impact of gamma rays. Because the air at the South Pole is drier than the driest desert and snow falls only rarely, the telescope will be left open to the elements as it makes automatic observations during the continuous darkness of winter.</p>
        <p>''We can leave the instrument unattended except by a technician who will do most of the controlling from indoors,'' Dr. Morse said. Astronomers theorize that cosmic gamma radiation may come mainly from supernovas, and the new polar telescope will test this theory. ''I'm glad I won't have to baby-sit the instrument,'' Dr. Morse said. ''I prefer cold beer to cold hands.''</p>
        <p>CIVILIZATION HAS arrived at last,'' concludes Erick Chiang. As an administrator of America's Antarctic program for the last 13 years, the Hong Kong-born geologist, who is this year's senior United States representative in Antarctica, has presided over many of the changes. One of the most visible, Chiang points out, is the growing presence of women. ''In 1976, when I first came to Antarctica, women were very rare indeed,'' he said. ''Now, roughly one quarter of the Americans in Antarctica, including scientists, truck drivers and pilots, are women. They make a big difference.''</p>
        <p>This may be true, but Antarctica's women are not exactly typical of their counterparts in the United States. Like the men, they are carefully screened and must pass rigorous physical examinations. The selection process creates a population that tends to be young, healthy, intelligent, well educated and good looking. Antarcticans exercise, work hard, and only rarely (strictly against regulations) become pregnant.</p>
        <p>Not everyone looks like a Superhero but they all have an attitude that sets them apart. At the South Pole, where the thin air and high altitude make people gasp, the cook this year was Barbara Burns, a chubby grandmother from Coeur d'Alene, Idaho. Mrs. Burns said she was there because she had decided to have ''a midlife adventure instead of a midlife crisis.'' The Navy itself, formerly the stern arbiter of behavior and mores on the ice, welcomes both women and civilization to Antarctica. Personifying the change is Capt. Joseph Mazza, commander of the United States Naval Support Force Antarctica. Though the Navy has tacitly acceded its absolute leadership to the National Science Foundation, Mazza's command still operates the airplanes and helicopters essential to virtually all Antarctic (Continued on Page 100) operations, as well as the airfields, the station store, the meteorology services and many other support groups. Mazza dresses in sharply pressed green fatigues and stands rigidly erect. Although he looks every inch the military martinet, civilian administrators say he is far easier to work with and less resistant to change than many of his starchy predecessors.</p>
        <p>''The days are past when personnel in Antarctica needed to spend most of their energy just staying alive,'' Mazza says. ''Human beings now have a permanent foothold on the ice, and a more or less normal working environment now prevails. We have moved from the expeditionary to the operational phase in Antarctica, and attitudes must change accordingly.'' As people in Antarctica become more attentive to serious scientific and environmental issues, they have begun to look askance at activities once considered fun. Rarely these days do South Pole inhabitants run nude into the midwinter night to pose for quick photographs. The joyful barking of huskies at New Zealand's Scott Base was forever stilled last year because of criticism of the dogs' diet of seal meat; now scientists travel by snowmobile instead. Fewer visitors to New Zealand's Lake Vanda Station take up the traditional dare to join the Vanda Swimming Club by plunging into the lake's frigid water through a hole in the ice. Many of the people who live and work in Antarctica, for that matter, never get to see a penguin, a killer whale, an ice cave or ventifacts - boulders sculptured by hurricane-strength winds blowing through the dry valleys. Most of Ross Island's famous attractions are conveniently accessible only by helicopter, and rides on these are not easy to secure. So people watch videotaped movies, socialize at McMurdo's four bars, jog, read and cross-country ski.</p>
        <p>''We've grown up,'' Dr. Lynch said. ''Mature scientists in Antarctica take satisfaction from their work and don't need any high jinks. Antarctica has joined the world.''</p>
        <p>To me, Antarctica is a luminous cathedral - a special gift to all of us that deepens the perspectives of its pilgrims even while threatening them with death. If joining the world should turn out to mean fast-food chains, mine tailings and oil-soaked penguins, then we shall have lost something precious. But if we can somehow preserve Antarctica as a sanctuary for the spirit as well as a laboratory for the world, mankind will be well served.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
