<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Notable Books of the Year</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19901216T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="405603"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DE163CF931A35751C1A966958260" item-length="12886" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Notable Books of the Year</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This list has been selected from books reviewed since the Christmas issue of December 1989. It suggests only high points in the main fields of reader interest, and it does not include the titles chosen by the editors of The Book Review as the Best Books of 1990. Books are arranged alphabetically under subject headings. Quoted comments are from The Book Review.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This list has been selected from books reviewed since the Christmas issue of December 1989. It suggests only high points in the main fields of reader interest, and it does not include the titles chosen by the editors of The Book Review as the Best Books of 1990. Books are arranged alphabetically under subject headings. Quoted comments are from The Book Review.</p>
        <p>Autobiography and Biography</p>
        <p>AGAINST THE GRAIN: An Autobiography. By Boris Yeltsin. (Summit, $19.95.) This provocative book gives voice to the Russian-style populism and antiparty insurgency of its author, the most visible leader of the opposition to Mikhail S. Gorbachev.</p>
        <p>AMELIA EARHART: A Biography. By Doris L. Rich. (Smithsonian Institution, $19.95.) THE SOUND OF WINGS: The Life of Amelia Earhart. By Mary S. Lovell. (St. Martin's, $22.95.) Two biographies of the famous American pilot (and feminist) who vanished in the South Pacific in 1937. The authors agree on the important facts; Ms. Lovell is more skeptical about her flying skills than Ms. Rich, and thinks better of her husband and publicist, G. P. Putnam.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN CASSANDRA: The Life of Dorothy Thompson. By Peter Kurth. (Little, Brown, $24.95.) A skillful exploration of the life and personality of the formidable foreign correspondent.</p>
        <p>AS I SAW IT. By Dean Rusk as told to Richard Rusk. (Norton, $29.95.) A joint memoir, written with his son, presents the once inscrutable and remote former Secretary of State as eloquent, funny, moving, devilish and even earthy.</p>
        <p>AS THOUSANDS CHEER: The Life of Irving Berlin. By Laurence Bergreen. (Viking, $24.95.) A vivid and impressive portrait of the phenomenon who was part songwriter and part industry, set against the panorama of 80 years of American show business.</p>
        <p>BECOMING A POET: Elizabeth Bishop With Marianne Moore and Robert Lowell. By David Kalstone. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $22.50.) The fullest account so far of Bishop's life, David Kalstone's presentation approaches her creative activity through her close friendships with two other major poets.</p>
        <p>BENEDICT ARNOLD: Patriot and Traitor. By Willard Sterne Randall. (Morrow, $27.95.) This industriously researched biography turns up much evidence that Arnold, though brave and talented, shouldn't have been trusted in the first place.</p>
        <p>BORIS PASTERNAK: A Literary Biography. Volume One: 1890-1928. By Christopher Barnes. (Cambridge University, $69.50.) A painstakingly researched, elegantly produced book that renders the full texture of Pasternak's insecure, displaced existence.</p>
        <p>THE BOY-MAN: The Life of Lord Baden-Powell. By Tim Jeal. (Morrow, $24.95.) A monumental (670 pages) biography of the founder of Scouting, doing full justice to the complexities of the man and the contradictions in the movement he fathered.</p>
        <p>CAPTAIN SIR RICHARD FRANCIS BURTON: The Secret Agent Who Made the Pilgrimage to Mecca, Discovered the Kama Sutra, and Brought the Arabian Nights to the West. By Edward Rice. (Scribners, $35.) This life of the 19th-century explorer and sage is a first-class account of a strange and remarkable career.</p>
        <p>THE COLONEL: The Life and Wars of Henry Stimson, 1867-1950. By Godfrey Hodgson. (Knopf, $24.95.) A lucid, penetrating biography of the statesman, a pragmatic idealist who served Presidents from Theodore Roosevelt to Harry S. Truman.</p>
        <p>C. S. LEWIS: A Biography. By A. N. Wilson. (Norton, $22.50.) A skilled novelist and biographer (of Tolstoy) brilliantly and sympathetically demythologizes one of the most tendentiously written-about British authors of the 20th century.</p>
        <p>DADDY, WE HARDLY KNEW YOU. By Germaine Greer. (Knopf, $19.95.) Ms. Greer's enormous digressions and rambles are as entertaining as the principal action in this account of her quest to learn the origins of her own father, a man who, she finds, never knew his birth name or parents and lied about what little he knew.</p>
        <p>DANGEROUS CAPABILITIES: Paul Nitze and the Cold War. By David Callahan. (Edward Burlingame/HarperCollins, $24.95.) An industriously researched life of Mr. Nitze as the ultimate insider's insider, a systematic international pessimist who served under six Presidents, starting with Franklin D. Roosevelt.</p>
        <p>DARKNESS VISIBLE: A Memoir of Madness. By William Styron. (Random House, $15.95.) A short, intensely described account of the depression that struck Mr. Styron in 1985 and of his agonized recovery from what he calls "a howling tempest in the brain."</p>
        <p>DE GAULLE: The Rebel, 1890-1944. By Jean Lacouture. (Norton, $29.95.) The biographer of Ho Chi Minh and Andre Malraux wins again with the first volume of his splendid life of Charles de Gaulle, which takes destiny's favorite Frenchman from his birth to his triumphant entry into Paris in August 1944.</p>
        <p>DIARY OF AN EROTIC LIFE. By Frank Wedekind. (Blackwell, $24.95.) This sharply observed, outspoken diary was meant by the playwright both as a sourcebook for plays and as autotherapy.</p>
        <p>THE DIARY OF H. L. MENCKEN. Edited by Charles A. Fecher. (Knopf, $30.) The good Mencken -- a great writer, editor and friend -- and the bad Mencken -- anti-Semite, racist and crank -- revealed in a compulsively readable diary, kept from 1930 to 1948.</p>
        <p>THE EARLY ARRIVAL OF DREAMS: A Year in China. By Rosemary Mahoney. (Fawcett Columbine, $18.95.) A memoir by a teacher that indicts the works of the Chinese establishment all the more effectively because of its tenderness and generosity.</p>
        <p>ETCHINGS IN AN HOURGLASS. By Kate Simon. (HarperCollins, $19.95.) The third and last of Kate Simon's autobiographical books dips at anecdotal hazard into the places and events -- a lot of them sexual -- of a gallant, independent and hard-won life.</p>
        <p>EVERY GOOD-BYE AIN'T GONE: Family Portraits and Personal Escapades. By Itabari Njeri. (Times Books/Random House, $17.95.) An impassioned, skillful, frankly subjective attempt to explore and expose the depth of a black American family heritage.</p>
        <p>FREEDOM IN EXILE: The Autobiography of the Dalai Lama. (Cornelia &amp; Michael Bessie/HarperCollins, $22.95.) Forthrightly political and spiritual, the 14th Dalai Lama's reflective account argues for nonviolence, environmentalism and a free Tibet.</p>
        <p>GUILTY OF EVERYTHING: The Autobiography of Herbert Huncke. (Paragon House, $19.95.) The very survival of this prototypical beatnik and hipster to age 75 is amazing, and so is his record of horrific misadventures and unlikely acquaintances.</p>
        <p>A HIGHER KIND OF LOYALTY: A Memoir by China's Foremost Journalist. By Liu Binyan. (Pantheon, $22.95.) Repeatedly Mr. Liu wrote the truth; repeatedly he was punished for it, but never gave up faith in the party until Tiananmen Square. Strange and sad.</p>
        <p>HOLDING ON TO THE AIR: An Autobiography. By Suzanne Farrell with Toni Bentley. (Summit, $19.95.) The great ballerina's generous and unpretentious memoir shows us first a girl coping with conspicuous success, then a young woman bewildered by George Balanchine's affections, finally a triumphant maturity.</p>
        <p>A HOLE IN THE WORLD: An American Boyhood. by Richard Rhodes. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $19.95.) Mr. Rhodes's own passage through abuse and deprivation to redemption: a harrowing tale.</p>
        <p>THE HOUSE OF BARRYMORE. By Margot Peters. (Knopf, $29.95.) An excellent history of the prominent American theatrical family, considerable warts and all. For better or worse, the Barrymores have found their chronicler.</p>
        <p>HOW I BECAME HETTIE JONES. By Hettie Jones. (Dutton, $18.95.) The memoir of a young Jewish woman of the Beat Generation, who loved -- and lost -- the poet and black nationalist LeRoi Jones, is a valuable social document.</p>
        <p>IN ALL HIS GLORY. The Life of William S. Paley: The Legendary Tycoon and His Brilliant Circle. By Sally Bedell Smith. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $29.95.) Ms. Smith's thorough reporting displays both the greatness and the smallness of the generous, energetic but insecure and sometimes untrustworthy genius who created CBS.</p>
        <p>THE LABYRINTH OF EXILE: A Life of Theodor Herzl. By Ernst Pawel. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $30.) Zionism's founder subtly rendered in the round, with both his grandeur and his pettiness.</p>
        <p>A LIFE ON THE ROAD. By Charles Kuralt. (Putnam, $19.95.) A professional memoir by a gifted man who has delighted television viewers by exploiting a permanent stranger's sense of place.</p>
        <p>LOVE AND OTHER INFECTIOUS DISEASES: A Memoir. By Molly Haskell. (Morrow, $18.95.) A film critic's psychological journey through the terrifying sickness and near death of her husband, Andrew Sarris, also a distinguished film critic.</p>
        <p>LUCIUS D. CLAY: An American Life. By Jean Edward Smith. (Holt, $35.) A masterly biography of the brilliant political general who headed the American occupation of Germany after World War II, presided over the Berlin airlift and created West Germany.</p>
        <p>MEANS OF ASCENT: The Years of Lyndon Johnson. By Robert A. Caro. (Knopf, $24.95.) The second volume of a projected four, Mr. Caro's account of Johnson's life from 1941 to 1948 -- especially the "stolen election" that put him in the Senate -- is the work of an indefatigable researcher and master narrator.</p>
        <p>MEMOIRS. By Andrei Sakharov. (Knopf, $29.95.) Not so much a reflection on his life as an annotated record of it, this account tells how an essentially shy and securely privileged Soviet scholar became an unbreakable witness for intellectual freedom.</p>
        <p>MIDSTREAM. By Le Anne Schreiber. (Viking, $18.95.) A dauntless and moving memoir by a former Times editor who became a freelance writer while her mother died cruelly of cancer.</p>
        <p>RANDALL JARRELL: A Literary Life. By William H. Pritchard. (Michael di Capua/Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $25.) One of the most literary lives ever lived, Jarrell's was short on event but plentiful in wit, pathos and brilliance, as this careful biography shows.</p>
        <p>REBUILDING THE HOUSE. By Laurie Graham. (Viking, $17.95.) An affecting record of life reconstructed after the death of the elder partner in a remarkably happy transgenerational marriage.</p>
        <p>RICHARD NIXON AND HIS AMERICA. By Herbert S. Parmet. (Little, Brown, $24.95.) A thorough and thoughtful biography of both the 37th President and the society in which he came to power.</p>
        <p>RIVER OF TRAPS: A Village Life. By William deBuys and Alex Harris. (University of New Mexico, $19.95.) A man's life in a unique American culture, that of the</p>
        <p>Hispanos</p>
        <p>of northern New Mexico, honestly rendered by a writer and a photographer.</p>
        <p>ROBERT GRAVES: The Years With Laura, 1926-1940. By Richard Perceval Graves. (Viking, $24.95.) An authoritative and lively account, by his nephew, of Graves's voluntary surrender of his life and work to the obscure American poet Laura Riding.</p>
        <p>SLIM: Memories of a Rich and Imperfect Life. By Slim Keith with Annette Tapert. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $22.95.) A high-powered, experienced wife (of a film director, an impresario, a British banker) tells what fun charm, brains and beauty were to have.</p>
        <p>STALIN'S APOLOGIST: Walter Duranty, The New York Times's Man in Moscow. By S. J. Taylor. (Oxford University, $24.95.) A beautifully researched life of the high-living, cynical journalist who helped cover up Stalin's atrocities in the 1930's.</p>
        <p>TAKING HEART. By A. C. Greene. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $18.95.) A veteran essayist and commentator examines the experiences of the first patient in a new heart-transplant center -- himself.</p>
        <p>THEODORE DREISER: An American Journey 1908-1945. By Richard Lingeman. (Putnam, $39.95.) The second volume of Mr. Lingeman's massive biography documents the most troubled life led by any important modern American writer.</p>
        <p>THE TIME OF MY LIFE. By Denis Healey. (Norton, $29.95.) A large, literate, witty man, Mr. Healey turns his experiences in British ministries into a wise and informative memoir.</p>
        <p>VAN GOGH: His Life and His Art. By David Sweetman. (Crown, $30.) An engaging biography, published in the centenary year of the artist's death, that undoes some of the obscuring myths about van Gogh and illuminates the social and artistic world he lived in.</p>
        <p>WHAT I SAW AT THE REVOLUTION: A Political Life in the Reagan Era. By Peggy Noonan. (Random House, $19.95.) Ronald Reagan's speechwriter, an articulate true believer in her President's greatness, transforms what she beheld in Washington into fine, sometimes brusque and rough-cut social comedy.</p>
        <p>WHAT WE HAD. By James Chace. (Summit, $17.95.) This memoir of childhood and youth by a former editor of Foreign Affairs and The Times Book Review focuses lyrically on a town (Fall River, Mass.) and a family both in decline in the 1930's and 40's.</p>
        <p>WRESTLING WITH THE ANGEL: A Memoir of My Triumph Over Illness. By Max Lerner. (Norton, $18.95.) The experiences of a New York intellectual, now in his 80's, with three mortal diseases, which he has so far beaten with luck, pluck and modern medicine.  Children</p>
        <p>ANTARCTICA. Written and illustrated by Helen Cowcher. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $13.95.) The message of this visually dazzling book is clear: penguins have natural predators, and man, though different from the others, is part of that continuum. (Ages 5 to 8)</p>
        <p>BASEBALL IN APRIL: And Other Stories. By Gary Soto. (Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, $14.95.) These short stories deal sensitively with Mexican-American boys and girls becoming teen-agers in contemporary California neighborhoods. (Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>BEACH BALL. Written and illustrated by Peter Sis. (Greenwillow, $12.95.) Mary goes running after a beach ball and on the sand encounters concepts like color, number and shape. The intricate illustrations are ingenious and appealing to older children and Waldo fans. (Ages 2 to 5)</p>
        <p>THE BUCK STOPS HERE: The Presidents of the United States. Written and illustrated by Alice Provensen. (HarperCollins, $17.95.) A craftily designed, lavishly illustrated, panoramic introduction to the history of the American Presidency, subtly subversive in the amount of information it can imaginatively convey. (All ages)</p>
        <p>THE FOSSIL FACTORY: A Kid's Guide to Digging Up Dinosaurs, Exploring Evolution, and Finding Fossils. By Niles, Douglas and Gregory Eldredge. Illustrated by True Kelley and Steve Lindblom. (Addison-Wesley, Paper, $8.95.) There is much more than meets the eye in this clearly written, cheerily illustrated paperback that gently introduces some of the great discoveries in astrophysics, plate tectonics, natural selection and evolution, among other subjects. Even the appendixes are useful. (Ages 7 to 12)</p>
        <p>GALIMOTO. By Karen Lynn Williams. Illustrated by Catherine Stock. (Lothrop, Lee &amp; Shepard, $13.95.) A little boy in a village on the shores of Lake Malawi spends a day making a galimoto -- a toy car -- from various wires he gathers. The watercolor art broadens the scope of this engaging story. (Ages 5 to 9)</p>
        <p>JACK. By A. M. Homes. (Macmillan, $13.95.) Jack is a likable guy, a good kid caught in circumstances too much for him. His parents have separated; his spacey mother ducks reality; his father's roommate, Bob, turns out to be his lover. By the end of the book, Jack has grown convincingly. (Ages 14 and up)</p>
        <p>JULY. Written and illustrated by James Stevenson. (Greenwillow, $12.95.) These childhood recollections incorporate soft-spoken pictures, touched with amusing grace and completely in harmony with the story they serve. (Ages 5 and up)</p>
        <p>TEHANU: The Last Book of Earthsea. By Ursula K. LeGuin. (Jean Karl/Atheneum, $15.95.) This sequel to the prize-winning Earthsea fantasy trilogy explores the necessary and life-giving contributions of female magic, which is sometimes disguised as domesticity. There are dragons, of course, but also a poignant consideration of aging, among other adult themes. (Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>WAR BOY: A Country Childhood. Written and illustrated by Michael Foreman. (Arcade Publishing, $16.95.) The author grew up during World War II in Pakefield, an English town not far from German air bases, and one of his earliest memories is of a bomb coming through the roof. The prose is square-cut, almost clinical; the illustrations show us what is truly remembered. (Ages 8 and up)  Crime</p>
        <p>BONES AND SILENCE. By Reginald Hill. (Delacorte, $17.95.) The 10th entry in an outstanding procedural series set in Yorkshire. No other genre author writes with such understanding of silently unhappy women as does Mr. Hill in his tender portraits.</p>
        <p>BREAK AND ENTER. By Colin Harrison. (Crown, $17.95.) In this intensely felt first novel, Mr. Harrison heroically balances the philosophical drama of a man's crisis of faith with the puzzle-narrative of a legal whodunit.</p>
        <p>DARK OBSESSION: A True Story of Incest and Justice. By Shelley Sessions with Peter Meyer. (Putnam, $21.95.) The finely detailed and thoroughly shocking narrative, both personal and social, of a Texas teen-ager who found all too little family or institutional support in trying to escape from an incestuous step father.</p>
        <p>DEVICES AND DESIRES. By P. D. James. (Knopf, $19.95.) This absorbing novel, the 11th by the British writer, places the detective Adam Dalgliesh on the trail of a serial killer.</p>
        <p>DEVIL IN A BLUE DRESS. By Walter Mosley. (Norton, $18.95.) Easy Rawlins is a black World War II veteran who turns private eye in a jazzy novel that takes place in the Los Angeles of 1948. Mr. Mosley writes in a talking-blues style that is its own kind of music.</p>
        <p>AN EASY THING. By Paco Ignacio Taibo 2d. (Viking, $16.95.) Mr. Taibo composes a dense and disquieting picture of pervasive political chaos and social cynicism in a novel about a moody Mexico City gumshoe.</p>
        <p>THE END OF LIEUTENANT BORUVKA. By Josef Skvorecky. (Norton, $18.95.) Five stories, camouflaged as police thrillers, about a good man's melancholy trajectory through the corrupt and corrupting world of post-Dubcek, pre-Havel Prague.</p>
        <p>A FAINT COLD FEAR. By Robert Daley. (Little, Brown, $19.95.) A New York City police official takes on an international drug cartel in an intelligent, engaging novel that is popular entertainment of a high order.</p>
        <p>GALLOWGLASS. By Barbara Vine. (Harmony, $19.95.) Miss Vine's most penetrating foray yet into the dark mysteries of the heart's obsessions, examining love in many guises, chiefly pathological.</p>
        <p>GET SHORTY. By Elmore Leonard. (Delacorte, $18.95.) In Mr. Leonard's new punchy thriller, a crook from Miami changes his life -- or reveals it -- when he goes to Hollywood, where life isn't life unless it's the basis of a major motion picture.</p>
        <p>GROOTKA. By Jon A. Jackson. (Foul Play/Countryman, $19.95.) A dark and moody police procedural featuring a scrappy Detroit detective named Fang Mulheisen. Mr. Jackson stands right up there with the best chroniclers of urban crime.</p>
        <p>A MORNING FOR FLAMINGOS. By James Lee Burke. (Little, Brown, $18.95.) Lush descriptions and the idiosyncratic freshness of the characters' language mark this novel about a Cajun detective who sets up a sting operation for the Feds.</p>
        <p>MURPHY'S FAULT. By Steven Womack. (Thomas Dunne/St. Martin's, $17.95.) New Orleans is the setting for this tough and articulate first novel about greedy politicians and their dirty deals.</p>
        <p>NEMESIS. By Rosamond Smith. (William Abrahams/Dutton, $18.95.) Joyce Carol Oates's third mesmerizing Rosamond Smith mystery concerns a homosexual rape, the murder of a mediocre composer (but much worse man) and its solution by a pianist.</p>
        <p>OCTOPUS: The Long Reach of the International Sicilian Mafia. By Claire Sterling. (Norton, $19.95.) Ms. Sterling's Palermo-based bosses are credited with the creation of a multinational empire whose principal target has long been the United States.</p>
        <p>SKELETON-IN-WAITING. By Peter Dickinson. (Pantheon, $16.95.) Spunky, clever Princess Louise is on the case in the author's second nifty thriller about an imaginary British royal family.</p>
        <p>STILL AMONG THE LIVING. By Zachary Klein. (HarperCollins, $18.95.) Matthew Jacob, a private eye from Boston with a fondness for illegal substances, makes his debut in a novel that offers rich characterizations.</p>
        <p>THE WESTIES: Inside the Hell's Kitchen Irish Mob. By T. J. English. (Putnam, $21.95.) The last incarnation and, apparently, final collapse of Manhattan's long-running West Side gang under the twin assaults of Federal crime fighters and gentrification.</p>
        <p>Current Affairs and Social Commentary</p>
        <p>ALMOST A REVOLUTION. By Shen Tong with Marianne Yen. (Houghton Mifflin, $19.95.) An earnest account of the making of an activist of the democracy movement and an insider's record of the day-to-day events of the spring of 1989 and the June crackdown.</p>
        <p>BARBARIANS AT THE GATE: The Fall of RJR Nabisco. By Bryan Burrough and John Helyar. (HarperCollins, $22.95.) A vivid and compelling account of the 1988 sale of RJR Nabisco for $25 billion.</p>
        <p>BEIRUT FRAGMENTS: A War Memoir. By Jean Said Makdisi. (Persea, $19.95.) A woman who stuck with her city in the worst of times speaks eloquently against the indifference that has written off Beirut as just a specially nasty foreign place.</p>
        <p>BIRTH POWER: The Case for Surrogacy. By Carmel Shalev. (Yale University, $19.95.) A liberal feminist lawyer argues forcibly that women should have the legal right to sell their reproductive services (and the obligation to fulfill their contracts).</p>
        <p>BURNING DOWN THE HOUSE: How Greed, Deceit, and Bitter Revenge Destroyed E. F. Hutton. By James Sterngold. (Summit, $19.95.) The corruption and ruin of an old-line firm, chronicled by a reporter who covered the scandal for The New York Times.</p>
        <p>THE BURNING SEASON: The Murder of Chico Mendes and the Fight for the Amazon Rain Forest. By Andrew Revkin. (Houghton Mifflin, $19.95.) Mr. Revkin explores the life and death of a Brazilian rubber tapper and union leader within the wider context of the ecological threat posed by the clearing of the forests.</p>
        <p>THE COMING GLOBAL BOOM: How to Benefit Now From Tomorrow's Dynamic World Economy. By Charles R. Morris. (Bantam, $19.95.) An entrepreneur and former banker argues ingeniously that boom is right around the corner, and that scary things like Japan and deficits are either neutral or good for us.</p>
        <p>THE CONTENT OF OUR CHARACTER: A New Vision of Race in America. By Shelby Steele. (St. Martin's, $15.95.) Mr. Steele, a professor of English in California, argues from his own experience that many blacks are suffering from "race fatigue" and ought to rid themselves of self-identification as victims.</p>
        <p>CUBA: A Journey. By Jacobo Timerman. Translated by Toby Talbot. (Knopf, $18.95.) The author's fierce, intelligent account of a visit to Cuba in 1987 portrays an island in shambles, a nation suffocated and demoralized after three decades of revolution.</p>
        <p>DEVIL'S NIGHT: And Other True Tales of Detroit. By Ze'ev Chafets. (Random House, $19.95.) Detroit as now it is, a fallen city trying to climb back again, captured in vignettes and interviews by a suburban Detroiter who later immigrated to Israel.</p>
        <p>DISTURBING THE PEACE: A Conversation With Karel Hvizdala. By Vaclav Havel. (Knopf, $19.95.) Autobiography, political philosophy, history and esthetics, all displaying the qualities that projected the author into the presidency of Czechoslovakia.</p>
        <p>DIVORCING THE DICTATOR: America's Bungled Affair With Noriega. By Frederick Kempe. (Putnam, $24.95.) OUR MAN IN PANAMA: How General Noriega Used the United States -- and Made Millions in Drugs and Arms. By John Dinges. (Random House, $21.95.) Much in these two accounts by professional journalists has been known to our Government all along but kept secret. Both books are excellent guides through the undergrowth of America's affair with the Panamanian dictator.</p>
        <p>THE END OF THE LINE: The Failure of Communism in the Soviet Union and China. By Christopher S. Wren. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $22.95.) Anecdote, analysis and lots of life in both countries, delivered by a correspondent of The New York Times.</p>
        <p>THE EXPERIENCE OF PLACE. By Tony Hiss. (Knopf, $19.95.) This unusual and fascinating book recommends a consciously intensified use of our underlying awareness of what surrounds us to make us comprehend more fully who we are and where.</p>
        <p>FADE OUT: The Calamitous Final Days of MGM. By Peter Bart. (Morrow, $19.95.) How a corporate raider bought a going movie company and bled it dry; a cautionary tale of the 1980's.</p>
        <p>THE FALL OF PAN AM 103: Inside the Lockerbie Investigation. By Steven Emerson and Brian Duffy. (Putnam, $21.95.) Two professional journalists have constructed a surpassing account of the 1988 bombing, rich both in drama and in anecdotal details.</p>
        <p>FLASHBACKS: On Returning to Vietnam. By Morley Safer. (Random House, $18.95.) A postwar reinterpretation of the country by a CBS correspondent whose reporting on the war was among the best broadcast journalism of the 1960's.</p>
        <p>FRUIT TRAMPS: A Family of Migrant Farmworkers. By Herman LeRoy Emmet. (University of New Mexico, Cloth, $45; Paper, $24.95.) In this study of a migrant family, words and pictures echo and drive each other to portray a life of deprivation and triumph.</p>
        <p>GORBACHEV: Heretic in the Kremlin. By Dusko Doder and Louise Branson. (Viking, $24.95.) A narrative interpretation that does not pretend to yield a final reading of the Soviet leader but provides a guide to the roller-coaster volatility of the last five years.</p>
        <p>GRATITUDE: Reflections on What We Owe to Our Country. By William F. Buckley Jr. (Random House, $16.95.) Mr. Buckley proposes legislation summoning young Americans to 12 months of somewhat voluntary low-paid, low-grade public employment.</p>
        <p>INTIFADA: The Palestinian Uprising -- Israel's Third Front. By Ze'ev Schiff and Ehud Ya'ari. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $22.95.) A reporters' book that focuses on long-term trends and inquires what is distinctive or continuous about the Palestinian uprising.</p>
        <p>JUSTICE NOT VENGEANCE. By Simon Wiesenthal. (Grove Weidenfeld, $22.50.) Did Josef Mengele really drown in Brazil in 1979, or may the physician-murderer of Auschwitz still be alive? The man who brought Adolf Eichmann to judgment reflects on this and other cases from a life spent tracking Nazis.</p>
        <p>A LAW UNTO ITSELF: Power, Politics, and the IRS. By David Burnham. (Random House, $22.50.) An absorbing, critical, well-argued inquiry into our tax agency, by a former Times reporter.</p>
        <p>LOOKING FOR A SHIP. By John McPhee. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $18.95.) The usual -- that is to say, terrific -- McPhee treatment, in which the author surrenders to his subject and conquers it; in this case, the merchant marine of the United States.</p>
        <p>A MIRACLE, A UNIVERSE: Settling Accounts With Torturers. By Lawrence Weschler. (Pantheon, $22.95.) A disturbing account of the uneasy compromises between new civilian governments and the brutal military regimes they succeeded in Latin America.</p>
        <p>ON THE LAW OF NATIONS. By Daniel Patrick Moynihan. (Harvard University, $22.50.) After a convincing demonstration that past American leaders have honored the ideals of international law, the Senator from New York argues that recent Presidents are content just to throw America's weight around.</p>
        <p>ONE, BY ONE, BY ONE: Facing the Holocaust. By Judith Miller. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $21.95.) A correspondent for The Times examines the ways five European countries and the United States have distorted and manipulated the memory of the Holocaust.</p>
        <p>AN OPEN ADOPTION. By Lincoln Caplan. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $17.95.) Part research paper, part thriller, this case study broadens to examine a form of placement in which biological and adoptive parents are well known to one another.</p>
        <p>OUTRAGE: The Story Behind the Tawana Brawley Hoax. By Robert D. McFadden, Ralph Blumenthal, M. A. Farber, E. R. Shipp, Charles Strum and Craig Wolff. (Bantam, $21.95.) The tale, meticulously recounted by six reporters and editors of The New York Times, of a racially divisive hoax -- the purported rape of a young black woman by white men in a village north of New York.</p>
        <p>PLEDGING ALLEGIANCE: The Last Campaign of the Cold War. By Sidney Blumenthal. (HarperCollins, $22.95.) This absorbing history of the 1988 Presidential election exposes a political process that is vacuous and out of touch with the major questions.</p>
        <p>THE POLITICS OF RICH AND POOR: Wealth and the American Electorate in the Reagan Aftermath. By Kevin Phillips. (Random House, $19.95.) The redistribution of wealth toward the rich in the last 20 years was a Republican policy objective, not just an accident, Mr. Phillips contends, and a populist reaction is likely.</p>
        <p>THE PRIVATIZATION DECISION: Public Ends, Private Means. By John D. Donahue. (Basic Books, $22.95.) What government activities should be contracted out? This thoughtful book shuns global answers and explores how to examine individual cases.</p>
        <p>SADDAM HUSSEIN AND THE CRISIS IN THE GULF. By Judith Miller and Laurie Mylroie. (Times Books/Random House, paper, $5.95.) A scary, persuasive reading of the Iraqi leader's career, by a New York Times correspondent and a Harvard scholar.</p>
        <p>SLOW BURN: The Rise and Bitter Fall of American Intelligence in Vietnam. By Orrin DeForest and David Chanoff. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $19.95.) Mr. DeForest, the principal author, is an angry C.I.A. veteran, offering a sad tale of obduracy and incompetence.</p>
        <p>SMALL VICTORIES: The Real World of a Teacher, Her Students, and Their High School. By Samuel G. Freedman. (HarperCollins, $22.95.) In a sad account of social neglect and failure, a former New York Times reporter spends a year at a battered inner-city high school and chronicles the heroic and often fruitless efforts of students and teachers to make learning possible.</p>
        <p>SOVIET WOMEN: Walking the Tightrope. By Francine du Plessix Gray. (Doubleday, $19.95.) Brilliant, sympathetic portraits of overworked, frustrated women whose men have neither the authority of patriarchs nor the utility of househusbands.</p>
        <p>TOO GOOD TO BE TRUE: The Outlandish Story of Wedtech. By James Traub. (Doubleday, $21.95.) This account of a Bronx-based scam that cost taxpayers and investors about $300 million is elegant, funny and frequently exciting -- though its subject, the total failure of a corruptible system, isn't even slightly amusing.</p>
        <p>TRIBES WITH FLAGS: A Dangerous Passage Through the Chaos of the Middle East. By Charles Glass. (Atlantic Monthly, $22.95.) An unfunny thing happened to this ABC correspondent in Beirut: he got kidnapped. But he escaped, and his story, despite its basic sadness, is entertaining, often even cheerful.</p>
        <p>THE UNDESERVING POOR: From the War on Poverty to the War on Welfare. By Michael B. Katz. (Pantheon, Cloth, $22.95; Paper, $14.95.) A searching, unsettling history of Government policies toward poor people, with provocative solutions for what to do next.</p>
        <p>WHAT LISA KNEW: The Truth and Lies of the Steinberg Case. By Joyce Johnson. (Putnam, $22.95.) A painful, fascinating effort by a skilled novelist to both narrate and understand (but not to excuse) the events and personalities that led to the horrendous child-abuse case of Lisa Steinberg, dead at 6 in November 1987 in New York.</p>
        <p>THE WORST YEARS OF OUR LIVES: Irreverent Notes From a Decade of Greed. By Barbara Ehrenreich. (Pantheon, $19.95.) Fifty essays -- elegant, trenchant, angry and funny -- that sum up the author's view of the 80's and aim to make us think (and wince). Essays, Criticism and Letters</p>
        <p>THE BOY WHO WOULD BE A HELICOPTER. By Vivian Gussin Paley. (Harvard University, $19.95.) An original essay on the practice of teaching young children, using their own stories as a vehicle of instruction, by a University of Chicago master teacher.</p>
        <p>CARNAL ACTS: Essays. By Nancy Mairs. (HarperCollins, $19.95.) The author, who has multiple sclerosis, looks her disability straight in the eye, learning who she is and what has formed her.</p>
        <p>FIVE O'CLOCK ANGEL: Letters of Tennessee Williams to Maria St. Just, 1948-1982. (Knopf, $24.95.) Williams's letters to the Russian-born Englishwoman Maria St. Just reveal a cheerful, tender, civilized man far different from what has become the drugged, drunken, despondent received version of the playwright.</p>
        <p>FRANCOIS TRUFFAUT: CORRESPONDENCE 1945-1984. Edited by Gilles Jacob and Claude de Givray. (Noonday/Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, Cloth, $50; Paper, $19.95.) A hefty, well-annotated collection of the great French director's almost compulsive correspondence -- often joking, always self-revealing.</p>
        <p>HENRY JAMES AND EDITH WHARTON. Letters: 1900-1915. Edited by Lyall H. Powers. (Scribners, $29.95.) The delightful record of a friendship between two very high literary pinnacles.</p>
        <p>LETTERS OF KATHERINE ANNE PORTER. Edited by Isabel Bayley. (Atlantic Monthly, $29.95.) Letters of astonishing clarity, keenness and vigor showing the author of "Pale Horse, Pale Rider" as an astute critic of life and a solid help to her friends.</p>
        <p>LETTERS TO FREYA: 1939-1945. By Helmuth James von Moltke. Edited by Beate Ruhm von Oppen. (Knopf, $24.95.) Moving and eloquent letters to his wife by a German count, a Nazi resister who was executed by the Reich in 1945.</p>
        <p>LYDIA AND MAYNARD: The Letters of Lydia Lopokova and John Maynard Keynes. Edited by Polly Hill and Richard Keynes. (Scribners, $24.95.) Out of the tangled thickets of Bloomsbury come these tender and dazzling love letters between the commanding economist and the Ballets Russes dancer.</p>
        <p>NOTES OF A HANGING JUDGE: Essays and Reviews, 1979-1989. By Stanley Crouch. (Oxford University, $22.95.) A bold and pitiless critic focuses his wrath chiefly on other African-American intellectuals and spokesmen whom he finds short on seriousness.</p>
        <p>A PRESENT OF THINGS PAST: Selected Essays. By Theodore Draper. (Hill &amp; Wang, $25.) Informed, argumentative observations by the hardest-headed of liberals, taking on cold-war bungling, American Communism and journalistic ethics.</p>
        <p>RACE AND HISTORY: Selected Essays, 1938-1988. By John Hope Franklin. (Louisiana State University, $29.95.) A collection of essays that provides both a meditation on history and a record of its author's extraordinary life as a black man and as a historian.</p>
        <p>SEXUAL PERSONAE: Art and Decadence From Nefertiti to Emily Dickinson. By Camille Paglia. (Yale University, $35.) A critical study of sexuality in Western art that is also a scorched-earth attack on the underlying assumptions of liberalism and feminism.</p>
        <p>SOME FREAKS. By David Mamet. (Viking, $16.95.) Reminiscences and ruminations from left to right and back by a considerable playwright who is happy to exhibit his inconsistencies. Fiction</p>
        <p>ADULT ENTERTAINMENT. By John Metcalf. (St. Martin's, $15.95.) Two novellas and three short stories whose heroes long for lust but instead get wives, children, bills and crushed hopes; the truth, according to this Canadian writer, is simply no fun.</p>
        <p>ADVANCE, RETREAT: Selected Short Stories. By Richard Rive. (St. Martin's, $16.95.) Humane, observant stories from three decades by the late South African writer, one of the first to explore the meaning of mixed race in a rigid, dualistic society.</p>
        <p>AFTERLIFE. By Paul Monette. (Crown, $19.95.) A gallant, painful novel that concerns three "AIDS widowers" trying to reconstruct lives tenuously held in the wake of their lovers' deaths.</p>
        <p>AGE OF IRON. By J. M. Coetzee. (Random House, $18.95.) Mr. Coetzee's superb new novel lays bare the effects of apartheid on the psyches of both the oppressor and the oppressed.</p>
        <p>ANIMAL DREAMS. By Barbara Kingsolver. (HarperCollins, $21.95.) Social and political issues crowd around the narrator of this novel, but her commitment to saving her hometown manages to integrate them all into a plausible hopefulness.</p>
        <p>AT THE GATES OF THE ANIMAL KINGDOM. By Amy Hempel. (Knopf, $17.95.) Tiny stories and lots of them, bringing an almost miraculous exactitude of observation and execution to bear on men and women stuck in various poses of comedy and loss.</p>
        <p>BABY OF THE FAMILY. By Tina McElroy Ansa. (Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, $18.95.) This genial first novel renders the life of a black Georgia family of the 1950's in rich detail; but humdrum it's not, for the protagonist is a little girl who talks with ghosts.</p>
        <p>BARKING MAN: And Other Stories. By Madison Smartt Bell. (Ticknor &amp; Fields, $19.95.) In a shifty, dangerous world, Mr. Bell's humane and mature stories require -- and get -- frequent small acts of heroism from their characters, even against heavy odds.</p>
        <p>BECAUSE IT IS BITTER, AND BECAUSE IT IS MY HEART. By Joyce Carol Oates. (William Abrahams/Dutton, $19.95.) That heart is dark, ignorant and isolated for the</p>
        <p>arriviste</p>
        <p>heroine of Ms. Oates's novel, who lives with responsibility for a homicide.</p>
        <p>BLUE TAXIS: Stories About Africa. By Eileen Drew. (Milkweed, Paper, $9.95.) The narrators of these deft, direct tales are mostly expatriate Americans whose ambivalent relationships to third-world surroundings make political problems deeply personal.</p>
        <p>BODY. By Harry Crews. (Poseidon, $18.95.) Muscle, nerve, fervor and suspense are amply displayed (so is skin) as Mr. Crews's hungry heroine campaigns to win a major bodybuilding contest.</p>
        <p>BOHIN MANOR. By Tadeusz Konwicki. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $19.95.) This beautiful, grave novel connects the 19th and 20th centuries, the historic point of view and the personal voice.</p>
        <p>THE BOMB. By Makoto Oda. (Kodansha, $18.95.) This unsettling novel concerns a cast of everyday people, some living in Hiroshima, others at White Sands, N.M., during World War II.</p>
        <p>THE BOOK OF EVIDENCE. By John Banville. (Scribners, $17.95.) In this persuasive novel we meet a first-person narrator who is a murderer and an existential philosopher of exceptional depravity.</p>
        <p>THE BURDEN OF PROOF. By Scott Turow. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $22.95.) A lawyer investigates his wife's mysterious death -- a purported suicide -- even as he defends his wheeler-dealer brother-in-law from Federal authorities.</p>
        <p>THE CARNAL PRAYER MAT. By Li Yu. (Available Press/Ballantine, paper, $8.95.) The first complete English version of a Chinese erotic classic of the 17th century, fiercely comic and satirical, currently prohibited in the country of origin.</p>
        <p>CHEKHOV'S SISTER. By W. D. Wetherell. (Little, Brown, $17.95.) Mr. Wetherell's elegant, subtle novel, which takes place in Yalta in 1941, is about people who refuse to be humiliated or become losers.</p>
        <p>THE CLONING OF JOANNA MAY. By Fay Weldon. (Viking, $18.95.) After the protagonist of this energetic, intelligent satirical fantasy learns that her domineering husband had her cloned 30 years ago, all five Joannas band together to readjust their lives.</p>
        <p>COLLECTED STORIES OF WALLACE STEGNER. (Random House, $21.95.) This gathering yields an overview of the author's progress and that of his medium: big, wholehearted tales that proceed with a characteristic sauntering ease.</p>
        <p>DECEPTION. By Philip Roth. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $18.95.) A swift, elegant, disturbing novel, composed of fragments of talk (much of it about sex) between a woman and a man named Philip, whose relation to the real-life Philip Roth is as problematical as ever.</p>
        <p>DOGEATERS. By Jessica Hagedorn. (Pantheon, $19.95.) A fast, frequently hair-raising first novel, full of images and fantasies reflecting the author's Philippine background, that maps the ruin at the heart of Philippine society in the last four decades.</p>
        <p>EAST IS EAST. By T. Coraghessan Boyle. (Viking, $19.95.) An absorbing tragedy, full of laughter to the end, about a Japanese seaman who leads a life of unintentional crime in America.</p>
        <p>ENTERED FROM THE SUN. By George Garrett. (Doubleday, $19.95.) Christopher Marlowe suffers terminal violence in this tale of Elizabethan intrigue, betrayal, ambition, murder and the like, which ends the cycle begun by "Death of the Fox" (1971).</p>
        <p>FAMILY PICTURES. By Sue Miller. (HarperCollins, $19.95.) A virtuoso realistic novel about the family and the perspectives within it, spacious and encompassing, that explores what it means to make a home, live at home and learn what home is.</p>
        <p>FERRIS BEACH. By Jill McCorkle. (Algonquin Books of Chapel Hill, $18.95.) Ms. McCorkle's ambitious novel (her fourth) concerns the coming of age of a North Carolina teen-ager who falls in love with the illusory glamour of faraway Ferris Beach.</p>
        <p>THE FIREMAN'S WIFE: And Other Stories. By Richard Bausch. (Linden/Simon &amp; Schuster, $18.95.) Thinking people living ordinary lives, the characters in Mr. Bausch's impressive second collection of stories seek redemption through understanding.</p>
        <p>FIRST HUBBY. By Roy Blount Jr. (Villard, $18.95.) A novel of official and unofficial Washington in 1993, narrated by Guy Fox, husband of the first female President and, like Mr. Blount, a reconstructed Southerner and light-heavyweight humorist.</p>
        <p>THE FOLKS THAT LIVE ON THE HILL. By Kingsley Amis. (Summit, $18.95.) The comic novelist serves up a cast of assorted suburban Londoners in various shades of distress, with much of the noisy fun softened by a note of rueful melancholy.</p>
        <p>FLOATING IN MY MOTHER'S PALM. By Ursula Hegi. (Poseidon, $17.95.) A deft, convincing little memoirlike novel about a girl growing up in Dusseldorf in the 1950's, a child's phantasmagoria of love versus loneliness, wholeness versus amputation.</p>
        <p>THE FUGITIVE. By Pramoedya Ananta Toer. (Morrow, $16.95.) Written while its Indonesian author was imprisoned at the end of World War II, this suspenseful novel of his country's occupation by the Japanese weaves a web of motivation, character and emotion.</p>
        <p>THE FULL CATASTROPHE. By David Carkeet. (Linden/Simon &amp; Schuster, $18.95.) With humor and insight, Mr. Carkeet's fourth novel addresses the commonest of social diseases -- a failing marriage -- with the least likely of therapies: a live-in linguist.</p>
        <p>GOODNIGHT! By Abram Tertz (Andrei Sinyavsky). (Viking, $22.95.) A novel in the form of a chatty memoir whose charm lies more in details than exposition, even if the details concern the pre-Gorbachev bad old days of the author-narrator's imprisonment.</p>
        <p>THE HEALER. By Aharon Appelfeld. (Grove Weidenfeld, $16.95.) Mr. Appelfeld's eighth novel to be translated into English takes place in the Carpathians before World War II; it concerns a disease that won't be healed and a salvation that can't be achieved.</p>
        <p>HEMINGWAY'S SUITCASE. By MacDonald Harris. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $18.95.) Big chunks of previously unknown writing by Hemingway may have shown up in the hands of a vanity-press novelist in this exhilarating fiction about writing fiction.</p>
        <p>HELL-BENT MEN AND THEIR CITIES. By Susan Dodd. (Viking, $17.95.) Short stories, intelligent, sympathetic and sometimes satirical, whose brave though unheroic late-20th-century characters endure while keeping one another's spirits up.</p>
        <p>HIS LITTLE WOMEN. By Judith Rossner. (Summit, $19.95.) Ms. Rossner's eighth book of fiction takes on -- always with energy and humor -- Hollywood, multiple marriages, the effect of divorce on children, cosmetic surgery, Playboy and Ms. magazine.</p>
        <p>HOCUS POCUS. By Kurt Vonnegut. (Putnam, $21.95.) Mr. Vonnegut's most topical, realistic novel to date presents the first-person narrative of Eugene Debs Hartke, a Vietnam veteran who loses a teaching job for being too pessimistic and finds another at a state prison run for profit by a Japanese corporation.</p>
        <p>HOLLYWOOD: A Novel of America in the 1920s. By Gore Vidal. (Random House, $19.95.) The latest wonderfully literate installment in Mr. Vidal's docudramatic revision of American history and politics features a movie star with a mission: to persuade producers to make anti-German World War I movies.</p>
        <p>HOMEBOY. By Seth Morgan. (Random House, $19.95.) Savagely comic and often brilliant, Mr. Morgan's first novel conveys a relentless, hellish vision of a San Francisco nether world of drugs and hustlers, thieves and exotic pimps.</p>
        <p>HOT FUDGE. By Richard Spilman. (Poseidon, $17.95.) An impressive collection of short stories, written with precision and compassion, about Middle Americans for whom keeping a low profile has the authority of a chivalric code.</p>
        <p>IN A FATHER'S PLACE. By Christopher Tilghman. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $18.95.) The author's first book contains seven short stories, clear and charged with feeling, set in various places, rich enough in significant detail to do the work of novels.</p>
        <p>THE INDIAN LAWYER. By James Welch. (Norton, $19.95.) The fourth novel by the author of "Fools Crow" focuses on a young Indian attorney and the path he navigates between the reservation and "the real world"; his most mature and readable book.</p>
        <p>THE INNOCENT. By Ian McEwan. (Doubleday, $18.95.) A hair-raising thriller whose effects are produced by an acute rendering of the ordinary mind and of the violence and horror that can erupt from what that mind does not know about itself.</p>
        <p>IN PRAISE OF THE STEPMOTHER. By Mario Vargas Llosa. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $18.95.) An erotic tale of familial hanky-panky in which acts of foreplay are described fully but chastely, erogenous zones are poeticized and art hovers over all.</p>
        <p>KILLING MISTER WATSON. By Peter Matthiessen. (Random House, $21.95.) A fierce, fascinating novel based on the life and death of a buccaneer businessman shot to death in Florida in 1910.</p>
        <p>THE KING. By Donald Barthelme. (Edward Burlingame/HarperCollins, $16.95.) The author, who died last year, left us one more wild, parodic metafiction; in this one, King Arthur meets World War II.</p>
        <p>THE KNIGHT, DEATH AND THE DEVIL. By Ella Leffland. (Morrow, $22.95.) This vigorous novel about Hermann Goring, Hitler's baroque, enigmatic No. 2 Nazi, gives a credible sense of why Nazism succeeded in inflaming so many imaginations.</p>
        <p>LANTERN SLIDES. By Edna O'Brien. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $18.95.) This fine collection of stories, little tragedies of passion, stupidity or stubbornness, continues the quest for origins and explanations that has concerned Ms. O'Brien's fiction for decades.</p>
        <p>THE LAST STATION: A Novel of Tolstoy's Last Year. By Jay Parini. (Holt, $22.95.) Mr. Parini conjures up a familiar cast, according more respect than usual to the hopes, fears, torments and motives of the all-too-human people who drove the old man to distraction.</p>
        <p>LEWIS PERCY. By Anita Brookner. (Pantheon, $18.95.) Ms. Brookner concentrates her mature novelist's intelligence on an innocent, well-meaning man who gets beat up in the sexual wars.</p>
        <p>LIES OF SILENCE. By Brian Moore. (Nan A. Talese/Doubleday, $18.95.) The 16th novel of this quietly controlled, unassuming, intelligent, spiritually alert writer turns an ugly incident in Northern Ireland into an agonizing, provocative ethical quandary.</p>
        <p>LIKE LIFE. By Lorrie Moore. (Knopf, $18.95.) Her characters are not a happy lot, but the author's witty and wry observations prevent these stories from being grim or maudlin.</p>
        <p>LUCY. By Jamaica Kincaid. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $16.95.) This first-person novel about a young Caribbean woman in America renders a spare, somewhat numbed account of a first year abroad in which much is left behind and nowhere is quite arrived at.</p>
        <p>LYING TOGETHER. By D. M. Thomas. (Viking, $17.95.) The final novel of the author's "Russian Nights" quintet purports to be an improvisation by characters from the other four; the engaging, witty result grapples with big issues like meaning and truth.</p>
        <p>MARY REILLY. By Valerie Martin. (Doubleday, $18.95.) Stevenson's story of Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde from the unexpected viewpoint of a housemaid, a woman fierce with love, loyalty and the will to figure out what's going on between good and evil.</p>
        <p>ME AND MY BABY VIEW THE ECLIPSE. By Lee Smith. (Putnam, $18.95.) Powerful short stories of small-town life and the passage of time in the American South, full of striving, jealousy and pettiness but also of transcendent generosity and devotion.</p>
        <p>THE MESSAGE TO THE PLANET. By Iris Murdoch. (Viking, $22.95.) Miss Murdoch's 24th novel treats men and women seriously through a kind of high philosophical clowning, starring a charismatic philosopher exposed to huge overdoses of real life.</p>
        <p>THE MUSIC OF CHANCE. by Paul Auster. (Viking, $18.95.) A tour de force of eccentricity and obsessionalism, this half-picaresque novel concerns a fireman who meets many strange strangers.</p>
        <p>THE MUSIC ROOM. By Dennis McFarland. (Houghton Mifflin, $18.95.) The themes struck in Mr. McFarland's generous, hopeful and stylistically bold first novel include history and continuity, independence and separation, as its 29-year-old hero searches past and present for secrets of identity.</p>
        <p>MY HARD BARGAIN: Stories. By Walter Kirn. (Knopf, $18.95.) Smooth, agreeable, conversational stories whose conventional backgrounds serve to set off a shimmer of modern loopiness.</p>
        <p>NATURAL SELECTION. By Frederick Barthelme. (Viking, $18.95.) Mr. Barthelme's fourth fast, fresh novel examines the marriage of Peter, a born suburban faultfinder, and his wife, Lily, whose shopping lists he has been correcting for 15 years.</p>
        <p>THE NEUMILLER STORIES. By Larry Woiwode. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $18.95.) Utterly direct but sometimes painfully difficult in their emotional discriminations, most of these stories are the original versions of material later incorporated into the author's fine 1975 novel of Great Plains life, "Beyond the Bedroom Wall."</p>
        <p>ORDINARY MONEY. By Louis B. Jones. (Viking, $18.95.) A wacky, satirical first novel of life among the relatively disadvantaged of Marin County, California, who are saddled with responsibility for a truckload of counterfeit money (except it may be real).</p>
        <p>OTHER WOMEN'S CHILDREN. By Perri Klass. (Random House, $19.95.) Dr. Amelia Stern, the protagonist of Dr. Klass's fine novel, struggles profoundly and plausibly to balance her duties as a pediatrician and as a wife and mother.</p>
        <p>PALACE WALK. By Naguib Mahfouz. (Doubleday, $22.95.) Now available in English, the first volume of "The Cairo Trilogy," reputed to be the masterpiece of the Egyptian novelist and 1988 Nobel laureate, nobly supports that reputation.</p>
        <p>PASSING ON. By Penelope Lively. (Grove Weidenfeld, $17.95.) Tough and shrewd, precise and understated, Ms. Lively's eighth novel renders a family's painful efforts to sort out and overcome the emotional legacy of a truly awful mother.</p>
        <p>THE PAST IS ANOTHER COUNTRY. By Lois Battle. (Viking, $19.95.) A well-told and satisfying tale of a brilliantly successful former convent girl's return to her roots, which in this case are fastened deep in Western Australia.</p>
        <p>THE PEREZ FAMILY. By Christine Bell. (Norton, $19.95.) A loud, gaudy, sentimental, enthusiastic heartbreaker of a novel about Cuban immigrants making new lives in an enchanted Miami.</p>
        <p>PHILADELPHIA FIRE. By John Edgar Wideman. (Holt, $18.95.) First hinted at in his collection of stories, "Fever" (1989), this is a passionate, angry and formally fascinating novel of urban disintegration based on the 1985 police bombing of a Philadelphia row house by frustrated police.</p>
        <p>PICTURING WILL. By Ann Beattie. (Random House, $18.95.) Complex points of view unfold to yield the shock of enlightenment in Ms. Beattie's fourth novel, a lyrical, deeply affecting story about a little boy and the people who love him, or should.</p>
        <p>PINTO AND SONS. By Leslie Epstein. (Houghton Mifflin, $19.95.) A fantastic epic of 19th-century technology, in which the hero, a Hungarian Jew, wastes much effort trying to improve the world.</p>
        <p>A PLACE I'VE NEVER BEEN. By David Leavitt. (Viking, $18.95.) A fine collection of deft short stories about highly individualized love triangles, complicated by gender permutations.</p>
        <p>THE QUINCUNX. By Charles Palliser. (Ballantine, $25.) Can you imagine a gigantic (788 pages) imitation of Dickens, abounding in wickedness, full of descriptive power, replete with plot and gratifyingly difficult to put down? Mr. Palliser did!</p>
        <p>REACHING TIN RIVER. By Thea Astley. (Putnam, $19.95.) A vivid novel about growing up in great big Australia; at its heart is an eerie, hypnotic, sentimental excursion across that brown land.</p>
        <p>RESTORATION: A Novel of Seventeenth-Century England. By Rose Tremain. (Viking, $19.95.) Ms. Tremain's fine sixth novel restores the good name of historical fiction as it propels its insecure hero through hassles high and low in Charles II's England.</p>
        <p>SECRET ANNIVERSARIES. By Scott Spencer. (Knopf, $19.95.) A convincing</p>
        <p>Bildungsroman</p>
        <p>whose heroine's soul is formed, in public and private, by historical events from the 30's to the 60's.</p>
        <p>SEVENTH HEAVEN. By Alice Hoffman. (Putnam, $19.95.) Life on Hemlock Street is conventional, orderly and very 1950's in this bustling novel, except that 8-year-old Billy Silk is clairvoyant.</p>
        <p>SHIRA. By S. Y. Agnon. (Schocken, $24.95.) For more than 20 years the Israeli Nobel laureate worked on this unfinished novel, whose protagonist is a German-born scholar and whose theme is art's search for a vision of tragedy when real horror is unbearably vast.</p>
        <p>SILVER LIGHT. By David Thomson. (Knopf, $19.95.) Mr. Thomson's third novel presents America's wild West from the Civil War to the 1950's, writ very large and loony in handsome prose, with loads of real, imaginary and intermediate characters.</p>
        <p>SOLOMON GURSKY WAS HERE. By Mordecai Richler. (Knopf, $19.95.) Mr. Richler's ninth and most complex novel chronicles, with frequent and intense indignation, the generations of the convoluted, manic Gursky family through Canadian history.</p>
        <p>A STONE OF THE HEART. By Tom Grimes. (Four Walls Eight Windows, $15.95.) The afflictions of adolescence are rendered in unique and universal terms in this first novel, set in Queens in 1961, about a 14-year-old boy who idolizes Roger Maris.</p>
        <p>THE SUITCASE. By Sergei Dovlatov. (Grove Weidenfeld, $16.95.) Sergei Dovlatov, who died in August at 48, wrote this collection of autobiographical fictions -- each recalling the unlikely origin of a piece of clothing brought from the Soviet Union -- in a wholly Russian voice but a straightforward American tone.</p>
        <p>SWEET TALK. By Stephanie Vaughn. (Random House, $16.95.) Ms. Vaughn's fine first story collection offers harrowing situations made alternately funny and sad by lively, believable characters.</p>
        <p>A TENURED PROFESSOR. By John Kenneth Galbraith. (Houghton Mifflin, $19.95.) A liberal economist learns to quantify investor irrationality and makes millions until conservatives cut him down in Mr. Galbraith's rollicking spoof of free-market ideology.</p>
        <p>THAT TIME IN MALOMBA. By James Hamilton-Paterson. (Soho Press, $18.95.) A brilliant religious satire with elements of E. F. Benson and Evelyn Waugh, set in a Far East teeming with gurus, guerrillas, imams, fakirs, mullahs, rabbis and tourists.</p>
        <p>TITMUSS REGAINED. By John Mortimer. (Viking, $19.95.) Mr. Mortimer's splendid classical comedy of political manners in an English village paints all participants as greedy ninnies, most notably the title character, a politically prominent twerp.</p>
        <p>TO ALL APPEARANCES A LADY. By Marilyn Bowering. (Viking, $18.95.) Melodramatic and proud of it, this vigorous historical novel tells of a modern identity quest and late-Victorian adventures in the Far East and British Columbia.</p>
        <p>THE TONGUES OF ANGELS. By Reynolds Price. (Atheneum, $17.95.) The narrator of this chastely visionary novel looks back 34 years to examine his responsibility, perhaps, for a boy's death.</p>
        <p>A TRAIL OF HEART'S BLOOD WHEREVER WE GO. By Robert Olmstead. (Random House, $19.95.) The plot of this deft and peculiar novel goes round and round, but at the middle are the citizens -- especially the dead ones -- of Inverawe, N.H.</p>
        <p>THE WILD COLONIAL BOY. By James Hynes. (Atheneum, $18.95.) Brian Donovan, the American protagonist of Mr. Hynes's sharp-eyed and convincing first novel, finds himself swiftly involved with an I.R.A. dispute and a young American woman backpacker.</p>
        <p>WILDLIFE. By Richard Ford. (Atlantic Monthly, $18.95.) Mr. Ford's fourth novel, which concerns a 16-year-old boy, his parents and his mother's casual lover, holds at its heart a nostalgia for the true perfection of the way things used to be, before ruin set in.</p>
        <p>THE WOMAN LIT BY FIREFLIES. By Jim Harrison. (Seymour Lawrence/ Houghton Mifflin, $19.95.) A collection of three novellas whose energetic "interior" storytelling emphasizes character and subtext over plot and immediacy.</p>
        <p>THE WORLD OF NAGARAJ. By R. K. Narayan. (Viking, $18.95.) In his mid-80's and still at the top of his form, Mr. Narayan returns to his imaginary Mysore with a comic novel about some universal truths, among them the importance of personality and family.</p>
        <p>VINELAND. By Thomas Pynchon. (Little, Brown, $19.95.) The passions of the 1960's continue to govern the lives of members of a California community.</p>
        <p>YOU DON'T LOVE YOURSELF. By Nathalie Sarraute. (Braziller, $17.95.) The nonagenarian doyenne of the</p>
        <p>nouveau roman</p>
        <p>offers a novel in the form of an anonymous dialogue on the theme of self-hatred, with interior voices in lieu of characters. History</p>
        <p>COMING OUT UNDER FIRE: The History of Gay Men and Women in World War Two. By Allan Berube. (Free Press, $22.95.) This deeply researched account shows that the military and perhaps a million homosexuals often coped with each other fairly well.</p>
        <p>ENCYCLOPEDIA OF THE HOLOCAUST. Edited by Israel Gutman. (Macmillan, four volumes, $440.) An extraordinarily detailed and complete account of the extermination of almost six million Jews by the Nazis.</p>
        <p>EVERY SPY A PRINCE: The Complete History of Israel's Intelligence Community. By Dan Raviv and Yossi Melman. (Houghton Mifflin, $24.95.) A fascinating account of an intelligence establishment to which nearly supernatural powers are often attributed, but which makes mistakes like all the others.</p>
        <p>FORGED IN BATTLE: The Civil War Alliance of Black Soldiers and White Officers. By Joseph T. Glatthaar. (Free Press, $24.95.) The absorbing story, more social than military, of the revolution through which 180,000 blacks fought for the Union in the Civil War.</p>
        <p>A HISTORY OF SOUTH AFRICA. By Leonard Thompson. (Yale University, $29.95.) An admirably objective one-volume history of that rich but unfortunate land that offers some grounds to hope that compromise and reconciliation may indeed prevail.</p>
        <p>THE HOLOCAUST: The Fate of European Jewry, 1932-1945. By Leni Yahil. (Oxford University, $35.) A work of synthesis rather than documentary scholarship, this popular survey aims to cover all aspects of the subject, including its political context.</p>
        <p>THE JEWS IN AMERICA. Four Centuries of an Uneasy Encounter: A History. By Arthur Hertzberg. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $22.95.) A broadly familiar story that rises to the superb in its account of the last 60 years or so, but is pessimistic about the future, foreseeing an end to Jewish history unless a spiritual revival supervenes.</p>
        <p>THE POLK CONSPIRACY: Murder and Cover-Up in the Case of CBS News Correspondent George Polk. By Kati Marton. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $22.95.) Who killed George Polk, 34, and left his body in Salonika Bay in 1948? This angry book offers a plausible theory and a supporting view of Greek politics after World War II.</p>
        <p>RED VICTORY: A History of the Russian Civil War. By W. Bruce Lincoln. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $24.95.) Between 1919 and 1921 the Soviet state was created out of chaos by armed force, this timely and thorough account by a university historian reminds us.</p>
        <p>ROAD TO DIVORCE: England, 1530-1987. By Lawrence Stone. (Oxford University, $29.95.) A distinguished historian traces the evolution of English marriage law and moral values that led from the Reformation to our own breathlessly divorcing century.</p>
        <p>THE SECOND WORLD WAR. By John Keegan. (Viking, $29.95.) THE TIMES ATLAS OF THE SECOND WORLD WAR. Edited by John Keegan. (HarperCollins, $50.) A bold but balanced one-volume military history and a superbly produced and edited historical atlas that has no equivalent in its field.</p>
        <p>STALIN IN POWER: The Revolution From Above, 1928-1941. By Robert C. Tucker. (Norton, $29.95.) This painstaking study, 15 years in the making, documents Stalin's part in the rise of Hitler and presents a psychological thesis: Stalin's paranoia arose from his projection of his own character traits onto others.</p>
        <p>STALIN: The Glasnost Revelations. By Walter Laqueur. (Robert Stewart/Scribners, $24.95.) Mr. Laqueur's third book on the Soviet Union in three years mixes old knowledge with glasnost-era discoveries, including startling anecdotes recently revealed.</p>
        <p>TOKYO RISING: The City Since the Great Earthquake. By Edward Seidensticker. (Knopf, $24.95.) An informal and contentious history of the Japanese capital from 1923 to the present, often anecdotal, equally often painstakingly thorough.</p>
        <p>AN UNCERTAIN HOUR: The French, the Germans, the Jews, the Klaus Barbie Trial, and the City of Lyon, 1940-1945. By Ted Morgan. (Arbor House/Morrow, $21.95.) An eloquent book of personal and public history by a French-born American journalist out to understand the contradictions of his former country.</p>
        <p>VOICES OF FREEDOM: An Oral History of the Civil Rights Movement From the 1950s Through the 1980s. By Henry Hampton and Steve Fayer with Sarah Flynn. (Bantam, $25.95.) An intimate survey sprung from the "Eyes on the Prize" television series. Poetry</p>
        <p>ABOVE THE RIVER: The Complete Poems. By James Wright. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $27.95.) Lucidity, precision, poise, intelligence and the rigors of a craft that liberated imagination were the poetic values James Wright cherished, and his best poems, with their grace and intelligence, remain among the finest examples of midcentury American lyric.</p>
        <p>ARARAT. By Louise Gluck. (Ecco, $17.95.) There is nothing relaxed about the white-knuckle language of these poems, which give a family history with objectivity, compassion and regret, and with wit more mordant than trenchant. No American poet writes better than Louise Gluck; perhaps none can lead us so deeply into our own natures.</p>
        <p>THE AUGUST SLEEPWALKER. By Bei Dao. Translated by Bonnie S. McDougall. (New Directions, Cloth, $16.95; Paper, $8.95.) Bei Dao, the guiding voice of the stillborn "Democracy Movement" in China in the late 1970's, uses words as if he were fighting for his life with them. Living in a nightmare of cruelty and dreaming of normality, he has forged a language that speaks to all of us in astonishing, beautiful poems.</p>
        <p>THE NIGHT PARADE. By Edward Hirsch. (Knopf, $18.95.) Emotional richness combined with a precision of language and metaphor make the best of these poems wonderful to read. Some seem to have forced themselves into being; silence was no longer possible.</p>
        <p>SELECTED POEMS, 1966-1987. By Seamus Heaney. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $20.) Seamus Heaney's patch is Ireland, with its turmoil and mutilated native culture, and no poet has taken his role more seriously or defined his responsibility with greater care. The great heart and humanity of the man ring through the decades of his splendid poetry.</p>
        <p>THE TONGUES WE SPEAK: New and Selected Poems. By Patricia Goedicke. (Milkweed, $9.95.) This volume spans 25 years of the work of a poet who is always aware of the political state of the world and of history. Her strengths are sincerity, memorable rhythms and great emotional power.</p>
        <p>THE TRANSPARENT MAN. By Anthony Hecht. (Knopf, $18.95.) COLLECTED EARLIER POEMS. By Anthony Hecht. (Knopf, $22.95.) No poet can write more beautifully when he wants to, but Anthony Hecht is also our only poet who can horrify. He achieves most in the intensity of lyric, but always he speaks like a biblical patriarch, and his elegant speech is a brilliant counterirritant to the contemporary wastage of our language.</p>
        <p>THE WANT BONE. By Robert Pinsky. (Ecco, $17.95.) Jazzlike improvisations and brooding civility mark these poems about the overlapping metaphysics of Christianity and Judaism, about history as invisible presence, about the shaping drives and powers we turn into the artifacts of culture. It is Mr. Pinsky's riskiest and most imaginative book. Popular Culture</p>
        <p>AFRICAN CANVAS: The Art of West African Women. By Margaret Courtney-Clarke. (Rizzoli, $60.) A stunning photographic study that celebrates the timeless but vulnerable arts of everyday.</p>
        <p>CLEOPATRA: Histories, Dreams and Distortions. By Lucy Hughes-Hallett. (HarperCollins, $27.50.) The author's feminist thesis -- and who can deny it? -- is that Cleopatra's image has been manipulated from the beginning by men with axes to grind. Her research is both thorough and interesting and her writing sharp.</p>
        <p>THE DAME IN THE KIMONO: Hollywood, Censorship, and the Production Code From the 1920s to the 1960s. By Leonard J. Leff and Jerold L. Simmons. (Grove Weidenfeld, $22.50.) What couldn't happen on screen: a virtual negative history of sex in America.</p>
        <p>ENCHANTED DRAWINGS: The History of Animation. By Charles Solomon. (Knopf, $75.) An ambitious, sprawling illustrated account of the evolution of animated movies, packed with tales of warring studios, greedy producers and great artists.</p>
        <p>THE GREAT GOOD PLACE. By Ray Oldenburg. (Paragon House, $19.95.) A good society has places for people to hang out -- taverns, cafes, barbershops -- and Mr. Oldenburg, a sociologist, investigates what's become of ours and how to get them back.</p>
        <p>JEAN HOWARD'S HOLLYWOOD: A Photo Memoir. With photographs by Jean Howard and text by James Watters. (Abrams, $39.95.) Herself one of Hollywood's most beautiful and privileged people, Jean Howard snapped her shutter with a social historian's eye, capturing the great at play in the 1940's and 50's.</p>
        <p>LOVE FOR SALE: The Words and Pictures of Barbara Kruger. By Kate Linker. (Abrams, $29.95.) Socially and politically conscious photomontages in an unmistakable signature style, thoughtfully clarified and interpreted by Ms. Linker's text.</p>
        <p>THE MAN WHO SHOT GARBO: The Hollywood Photographs of Clarence Sinclair Bull. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $40.) Greta Garbo and other gods and goddesses, luminously rendered by the head of the M-G-M stills department from 1924 to 1961; 183 portraits in all.</p>
        <p>THE MISSING REEL: The Untold Story of the Lost Inventor of Motion Pictures. By Christopher Rawlence. (Atheneum, $19.95.) An argument for the priority of a Frenchman whose movie camera preceded Edison's and who disappeared in 1890.</p>
        <p>OUR NEW YORK. Text by Alfred Kazin. Photographs by David Finn. (HarperCollins, $35.) A delightful collaboration on the New York landscape and its meaning by two wise old Brooklyn hands.</p>
        <p>THE RUNAWAY BRIDE: Hollywood Romantic Comedy of the 1930's. By Elizabeth Kendall. (Knopf, $24.95.) A comprehensive evocation of the screwball comedy -- its silliness, its acknowledgment of social disorder, its emphasis on witty talk.</p>
        <p>SATURDAY NIGHT. By Susan Orlean. (Knopf, $19.95.) Eight hours in the hebdomadal cycle of American culture, sharply observed by a journalist with a gift for hanging around while paying attention.</p>
        <p>THE SPIRIT OF FOLK ART: The Girard Collection at the Museum of International Folk Art. By Henry Glassie. Color photographs by Michael Monteaux. (Abrams, $60.) With 154 splendid color pages, this rather ambitious illustrated essay celebrates a collection (located in Santa Fe, N.M.) that richly deserves it.</p>
        <p>STONE ALONE: The Story of a Rock 'n' Roll Band. By Bill Wyman with Ray Coleman. (Viking, $22.95.) A lively and detailed narrative, spiced with score-settling, of the origin and ascent to fame of the Rolling Stones, by the group's bassist.</p>
        <p>WRITERS IN HOLLYWOOD: 1915-1951. By Ian Hamilton. (Edward Burlingame/HarperCollins, $25.) An ably researched and entertaining account of the literati who condescended to, and profited from, the movie industry during its infant and golden years. Religion</p>
        <p>THE BOOK OF J. Translated by David Rosenberg. Interpreted by Harold Bloom. (Grove Weidenfeld, $21.95.) A rugged modern version of the J narrative, the oldest layer of the Pentateuch, with an interpretation of the author and her -- yes, her -- intentions.</p>
        <p>THE CATHOLIC MYTH: The Behavior and Beliefs of American Catholics. By Andrew M. Greeley. (Scribners, $21.95.) The priest, novelist, sociologist and maverick argues, with cogent figures, that Roman Catholics are better educated and richer than Protestants and more liberal on political issues.</p>
        <p>MAKING SAINTS: How the Catholic Church Determines Who Becomes a Saint, Who Doesn't, and Why. By Kenneth L. Woodward. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $24.95.) The religion editor of Newsweek explains the political factors that influence which potential saints are selected for official canonization.</p>
        <p>NO TURNING BACK: Two Nuns' Battle With the Vatican Over Women's Right to Choose. By Barbara Ferraro and Patricia Hussey with Jane O'Reilly. (Poseidon, $19.95.) An intriguing case history with a point of view, by two women who took on the hierarchy of the Roman Catholic Church and refused to give in.</p>
        <p>THE SPIRITUAL LIFE OF CHILDREN. By Robert Coles. (Peter Davison/Houghton Mifflin, $22.95.) This latest volume in a distinguished series of children's oral history focuses on the subjects' religious beliefs; the result is a remarkable book.</p>
        <p>UNDER GOD: Religion and American Politics. By Garry Wills. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $24.95.) Struck by the prominence of religion in American politics and the incapacity of journalists and academics to deal with it, Mr. Wills thoughtfully examines some pertinent and permanent themes in this continuing relationship. Science Fiction</p>
        <p>HYPERION. By Dan Simmons. (Foundation/ Doubleday, Cloth, $18.95; Paper, $8.95; Spectra/Bantam, Paper, $4.95.) THE FALL OF HYPERION. By Dan Simmons. (Foundation/Doubleday, Cloth, $18.95; Paper, $8.95.) Combined, these two make up a thousand-page novel; both are generously conceived and stylistically sure-handed works.</p>
        <p>THE DIVIDE. By Robert Charles Wilson. (Foundation/Doubleday, $19.95.) This literate thriller is a superbly crafted novel of character and a thoughtful exploration of what it might feel like to be a superman.</p>
        <p>RAMA II. By Arthur C. Clarke and Gentry Lee. (Spectra/Bantam, $18.95.) The sequel to Mr. Clarke's famous novel "Rendezvous With Rama" -- about a vast alien spaceship that seems oblivious to humanity's best efforts to make an impression -- is just as gripping in this second encounter.</p>
        <p>LENS OF THE WORLD. By R. A. MacAvoy. (Morrow, $18.95). Ms. MacAvoy has written a fantasy novel with all the conceptual rigor of good science fiction. Genre-mixing is only one of the narrative strategies she uses to draw readers into the tale of Nazhuret, an engaging orphan who has only his wits to help him as he sets out to discover his identity.</p>
        <p>QUEEN OF ANGELS. By Greg Bear. (Warner, $19.95.) A novel about the nature of consciousness that manages to be both entertaining and thought-provoking. A famous poet who murders eight of his young disciples, a policewoman who colors her skin black for cosmetic reasons and a scientist who invents a mind probe that can make psychotherapy an exact science are among the characters in this complex book that succeeds on virtually every level. Science, Medicine and Psychology</p>
        <p>ALTERED LOVES: Mothers and Daughters During Adolescence. By Terri Apter. (St. Martin's, $24.95.) An analysis of 65 mother-daughter pairs in Britain and the United States blows away some old misconceptions -- including the belief that adolescents achieve identity through rebellion, turmoil and separation.</p>
        <p>THE CHANGING ATMOSPHERE: A Global Challenge. By John Firor. (Yale University, $19.95.) A scientist at the National Center for Atmospheric Research explains the interrelationship of current environmental issues and the combined threat they present to life on earth.</p>
        <p>DISAPPEARING THROUGH THE SKYLIGHT: Culture and Technology in the Twentieth Century. By O. B. Hardison Jr. (Viking, $22.95.) A polymathic scholar and social critic's optimistic synthesis of future technology and consciousness.</p>
        <p>FINAL ANALYSIS: The Making and Unmaking of a Psychoanalyst. By Jeffrey Moussaieff Masson. (Addison-Wesley, $18.95.) The author's account of how disillusionment and disbelief made him "the Antichrist in the church of psychoanalysis."</p>
        <p>FIRE &amp; ICE: The Greenhouse Effect, Ozone Depletion, and Nuclear Winter. By David E. Fisher. (HarperCollins, $19.95.) THE NEXT ONE HUNDRED YEARS: Shaping the Fate of Our Living Earth. By Jonathan Weiner. (Bantam, $19.95.) There is, both authors assure us, a scientific consensus about global warming: it's coming. But something can be done, they believe, and these studies passionately and credibly urge attention to a threatening future that many of us seem to have despaired of in advance.</p>
        <p>FLOW: The Psychology of Optimal Experience. By Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi. (HarperCollins, $21.95.) "Flow," according to the author, a professor of psychology at the University of Chicago, is a learnable state of consciousness that comes with rightly interpreting what we are doing and what is happening to us.</p>
        <p>THE LIFE AND DEATH OF A DRUID PRINCE: The Story of Lindow Man, an Archaeological Sensation. By Anne Ross and Don Robins. (Summit, $19.95.) A fascinating argument, even if fetched a bit far, about a 2,000-year-old corpse found in England in 1984.</p>
        <p>MARS BECKONS: The Mysteries, the Challenges, the Expectations of Our Next Great Adventure in Space. By John Noble Wilford. (Knopf, $24.95.) What shall we do about Mars? A science correspondent of The Times examines our relationship with Mars so far and weighs the issues and options for the future.</p>
        <p>PILTDOWN: A Scientific Forgery. By Frank Spencer. (National History Museum/ Oxford University, $24.95.) Who invented Piltdown Man back in 1912? Mr. Spencer's studious compilation of the evidence points to a suspect -- and a motive.</p>
        <p>THE SPACE TELESCOPE: A Study of NASA, Science, Technology, and Politics. By Robert W. Smith. (Cambridge University, $39.50.) A big book about big science, focused on the history of space technology and the development of the Hubble Space Telescope.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGICAL RISK. By H. W. Lewis. (Norton, $22.95.) A valuable, clearly written appraisal of what's risky -- and not risky -- about technology, written by a physicist specializing in risk assessment and management.</p>
        <p>WHAT KIND OF LIFE: The Limits of Medical Progress. By Daniel Callahan. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $19.95.) An ethical philosopher's tough-minded look at the debate about medical costs and society's resources, arguing for rules that would give far higher priorities to prevention than to high-cost care in marginal cases. Spies &amp; Thrillers</p>
        <p>BLOOD TIDE. By Robert F. Jones. (Atlantic Monthly, $19.95.) Double revenge is the motif of this exciting thriller about a father and daughter who set out in a boat for the Philippines. The writing is superior.</p>
        <p>THE BLUE GATE OF BABYLON. By Paul Pickering. (Random House, $18.95.) This blackly humorous espionage novel is about a young British diplomat in West Berlin who likes women too much for his own good.</p>
        <p>BROTHERHOOD OF THE TOMB. By Daniel Easterman. (Doubleday, $19.95.) A frightening, action-packed book that involves the Vatican, a former C.I.A. man and a brotherhood established not long after the death of Christ.</p>
        <p>THE RUNNING TARGET. By Gerald Seymour. (Morrow, $19.95.) A top deskman at British intelligence is kidnapped by Iranians in this scary and searing book.</p>
        <p>SOVIET SOURCES. By Robert Cullen. (Atlantic Monthly, $19.95.) In the immediate future, an American journalist in the Soviet Union is set up by the K.G.B. The author has been a correspondent in Moscow, and every word he writes carries authority.</p>
        <p>UNDER SIEGE. By Stephen Coonts. (Pocket Books, $19.95.) Colombian drug lords declare war against the United States and send killer squads to Washington. This is escape reading at its best. Sports</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: The People's Game. By Harold Seymour. (Oxford University, $24.95.) The third volume in Mr. Seymour's history of baseball broadly details the game outside so-called Organized Baseball and its capture by designing institutions.</p>
        <p>DAMNED YANKEES: A No-Holds-Barred Account of Life With "Boss" Steinbrenner. By Bill Madden and Moss Klein. (Warner, $19.95.) A well-told account of the decline and fall of the New York Yankees at the hands of the team's principal owner.</p>
        <p>KAREEM. By Kareem Abdul-Jabbar with Mignon McCarthy. (Random House, $18.95.) A memoir in the form of a diary, combining this amazing player's last season as a Los Angeles Laker with autobiographical recollections, mostly magnanimous.</p>
        <p>MEN AT WORK: The Craft of Baseball. By George F. Will. (Macmillan, $19.95.) An elegant analysis of what baseball players actually do, investigated by the conservative columnist with love and curiosity but without sentimentality or mythologizing. Travel, Nature and Adventure</p>
        <p>THE ANTS. By Bert Holldobler and Edward O. Wilson. (Belknap/Harvard University, $65.) Two distinguished, articulate biologists reveal everything we didn't know we wanted to know about ants.</p>
        <p>PLAYING WITH WATER: Passion and Solitude on a Philippine Island. By James Hamilton-Paterson. (New Amsterdam Books, Cloth, $19.95; Paper, $11.95.) A truly remarkable lyrical meditation on sea, sunlight and the analysis of consciousness.</p>
        <p>SONORAN DESERT SUMMER. By John Alcock. (University of Arizona, $19.95.) A handsome, thoughtful record of nature observation and conceptual ecology in a very hard place to live.</p>
        <p>TIGERS: The Secret Life. By Valmik Thapar. Photographs by Fateh Singh Rathore. (Rodale, $35.) An education in tigerology and a hopeful assessment of their future as wild animals, even under India's population pressures. The photographs are gorgeous.</p>
        <p>A YEAR IN PROVENCE. By Peter Mayle. (Knopf, $19.95.) When the author, his wife and their dogs leave London for a sojourn in sunny Provence they encounter year-round surprises -- icy mistrals, unwelcome visitors, burst pipes and village rustics.</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 16, 1990, Sunday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error in the listing of notable books of the year in The New York Times Book Review on Dec. 2, three entries were omitted. These are the missing entries:</p>
        <p>CONSTANCIA AND OTHER STORIES FOR VIRGINS. By Carlos Fuentes. Translated by Thomas Christensen. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $19.95. ) Five bizarre short stories by the Mexican writer, whose authority is absolute and who is peremptory in leaving his readers to their own devices, trusting them not to be dolts.</p>
        <p>THE GENERAL IN HIS LABYRINTH. By Gabriel Garcia Marquez.  Translated by Edith Grossman. (Knopf, $19.95.) The Latin American novelist chooses Simon Bolivar as the hero of his new novel; the result is a fascinating literary tour de force, a moving tribute to an extraordinary man and a sad commentary on the ruthlessness of the political process.</p>
        <p>THE RUSSIAN REVOLUTION. By Richard Pipes. (Knopf, $40.) A massive, intellectually challenging history of Russia's national convulsion by the Baird Professor of History at Harvard, superbly and at times trenchantly written.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 16, 1990, Sunday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error in the listing of notable books of the year in The New York Times Book Review on Dec. 2, three entries were omitted. These are the missing entries:</p>
        <p>CONSTANCIA AND OTHER STORIES FOR VIRGINS. By Carlos Fuentes. Translated by Thomas Christensen. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $19.95. ) Five bizarre short stories by the Mexican writer, whose authority is absolute and who is peremptory in leaving his readers to their own devices, trusting them not to be dolts.</p>
        <p>THE GENERAL IN HIS LABYRINTH. By Gabriel Garcia Marquez.  Translated by Edith Grossman. (Knopf, $19.95.) The Latin American novelist chooses Simon Bolivar as the hero of his new novel; the result is a fascinating literary tour de force, a moving tribute to an extraordinary man and a sad commentary on the ruthlessness of the political process.</p>
        <p>THE RUSSIAN REVOLUTION. By Richard Pipes. (Knopf, $40.) A massive, intellectually challenging history of Russia's national convulsion by the Baird Professor of History at Harvard, superbly and at times trenchantly written.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
