<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Earth Day Isn't Getting Any Easier</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="346109"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="FORUM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH DAY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MOORE, PETER D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HENNESSY, EDWARD L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMON, JULIAN (PROF)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWN, LESTER R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DC123FF931A15757C0A966958260" item-length="1083" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Earth Day Isn't Getting Any Easier</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The 20th anniversary of Earth Day is being marked around the world. Here are four views on its significance.</p>
        <p>Peter D. Moore</p>
        <p>Mr. Moore is managing partner in Inferential Focus, a market research and forecasting firm in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The 20th anniversary of Earth Day is being marked around the world. Here are four views on its significance.</p>
        <p>Peter D. Moore</p>
        <p>Mr. Moore is managing partner in Inferential Focus, a market research and forecasting firm in New York.</p>
        <p>The 20th anniversary of Earth Day is being marked around the world. Here are four views on its significance.</p>
        <p>Peter D. Moore</p>
        <p>Mr. Moore is managing partner in Inferential Focus, a market research and forecasting firm in New York.</p>
        <p>On the surface, Earth Day is about clean air, clean water and a safer environment. But underneath, the motivation for this effort comes from a fundamental shift in society's values from short-term, leveraged exploitation to long-term control and protection. This shift is driven by people who have been disillusioned by the ineffectiveness of big government and big business in dealing with the problems confronting society. Their new mood is evidenced by a desire for participation, not delegation, effective action, not talk, and a willingness to accept responsibility for what is happening to our environment now.</p>
        <p>This new mood recently energized Harlem residents, led by local clergy, to paint over billboards with messages they felt exploited the youth in their community. Again it was seen in Tacoma, Wash., where a judge refused to accept a settlement between the city and the Pennwalt Corporation over a 75,000-gallon chemical leak into Puget Sound until the chief executive himself appeared in court. The judge said: ''I think the public is entitled to know who is responsible.''</p>
        <p>Environmentalists have been active ever since Earth Day 1970, but only recently has their message gained popular momentum. They have not changed; the listeners have changed, and the listeners' new perspective gives shape to the new ''environment'' in which business and political leaders must act.</p>
        <p>Edward L. Hennessy</p>
        <p>Mr. Hennessy is chairman of Allied-Signal.</p>
        <p>America's environment has improved markedly in the 20 years since the first Earth Day. Spurred by the growth in environmental concerns during the 1970's, government and industry made major strides in improving air and water quality, controlling hazardous wastes and addressing the most visible ecological abuses.</p>
        <p>Still, many environmental problems remain unsolved. And we face new, more pervasive concerns. The connection between ozone depletion and chlorofluorocarbons, for example, was not discovered until 1974, and the thinning of the ozone layer over the Antarctic was not observed until 1985. Allied-Signal Inc. and other CFC manufacturers have responded by phasing out CFC's and by spending hundreds of millions on research and development of safe substitutes. In the next 20 years, however, we must do more than just respond to clear and present dangers. We must create a generation of environmentally knowledgeable leaders who understand that all of our actions have environmental consequences.</p>
        <p>How can we do this? Tufts University has taken an innovative first step. Financed by Allied-Signal, the Tufts Environmental Literacy Institute will help faculties across the country integrate environmental issues into courses ranging from the liberal arts to engineering science.</p>
        <p>Equipped with a broader understanding of environmental problems, our future leaders will be better prepared to strike a balance between preserving the earth's resources and extending the benefits of new technology to the world.</p>
        <p>Julian Simon</p>
        <p>Mr. Simon is professor of business administration at the University of Maryland and author of ''The Economic Consequences of Immigration.''</p>
        <p>Earth Day is a costly fraud and not a trivial one at that. All these doomsayers are wasting a terrible amount of our resources and it is very bad for everyone's morale. Young people are being told that they cannot flex their muscles, that they cannot do great things because it might hurt someone else.</p>
        <p>But the scientific data compiled by the government show that the quality of the environment has been steadily improving. The air is more breathable, the water more drinkable, and we don't have the scarcities doomsayers predicted.</p>
        <p>There are many biologists who say that social scientists like myself just do not understand science. But the fact is these scientists ignore all of the evidence of history that says that things are getting better. They ignore the fact that there is more abundance, less starvation and that people are living longer. But when these scientists are confronted with these facts, they say this time the future will be different and things will get worse.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists say affluence causes the deterioration of the environment. And, while it is true that very poor people do not produce much trash, affluence is what cleans up the environment. This is true in part because the affluent can afford better services, but also because waste and pollution present opportunities. Economists like myself think that the economic system is responsive: every shortage is an opportunity for someone to fill a need.</p>
        <p>Lester R. Brown</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown is president of Worldwatch Institute, an environmental policy and research group.</p>
        <p>Each year in our ''State of the World'' report we - in effect - give the earth an annual physical. The results are not reassuring. Each year the earth's forests shrink, the deserts expand, cropland loses precious topsoil and the protective ozone layer thins. The concentration of greenhouse gases in the atmosphere continues to rise and the number of plant and animal species diminishes.</p>
        <p>The challenge facing humanity in the 90's is to reverse the environmental degradation of the planet before it leads to economic decline of the sort seen in parts of Africa. Meeting this challenge requires more than fine-tuning; it will take a fundamental restructuring of the global economy.</p>
        <p>Stabilizing climate means phasing out fossil fuels, replacing them with renewable sources of energy like hydropower, geothermal generating plants, solar-thermal power plants, wind-electric turbines and photovoltaic cells. It means designing a transport system that will be powered largely by solar-generated electricity, and perhaps hydrogen fuel, rather than gasoline. It means replacing garbage collection with recycling industries. Most of all, it requires greatly increased efficiency.</p>
        <p>Enterprising corporations will look at the blueprint of an environmentally sustainable global economy and design a corporate plan that helps make it a reality. Some farsighted corporations will move rapidly and capitalize on the new needs. Others will resist change and lose out. Corporate environmentalism is more than good public relations. It is a matter of economic survival.</p>
        <p>FORUM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
