<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lessons</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="332526"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="EDUCATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SCOTTSDALE (ARIZ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISKE, EDWARD B</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">EDUCATION PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona/Scottsdale</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D6123DF934A35750C0A966958260" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lessons</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Edward B. Fiske</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FISKE, EDWARD B</byline>
      <dateline>SCOTTSDALE, Ariz.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Steve Richardson and his fellow sixth graders at the Yavapai Elementary School recently became curious about the political changes in East Germany. So they went to a computer and tapped into a satellite network linking schools in North America, Europe and the Middle East.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Steve Richardson and his fellow sixth graders at the Yavapai Elementary School recently became curious about the political changes in East Germany. So they went to a computer and tapped into a satellite network linking schools in North America, Europe and the Middle East.</p>
        <p>Steve Richardson and his fellow sixth graders at the Yavapai Elementary School recently became curious about the political changes in East Germany. So they went to a computer and tapped into a satellite network linking schools in North America, Europe and the Middle East.</p>
        <p>Back came a message from students at Luitpold High School in Munich describing the excitement of West Germany's young people. ''Imagine, the younger generation in East and West have never had a chance so far to see their neighbors and to get to know their way of life,'' the German students' message said.</p>
        <p>To Steve and his friends, checking out the views of students 5,800 miles away comes as naturally as a trip to the school library did to previous generations of students. ''You find out what is happening right now,'' he said. ''And besides, we like to hear what kids have to say.''</p>
        <p>The incident is a sign that a long overdue change in the way schools view computers is finally beginning to occur. Machines that only a few years ago were viewed as objects to study or as glitzy replacements for teachers are coming to be seen as tools that can permeate virtually every aspect of school life, from brain-tickling to budgeting.</p>
        <p>When computers appeared on the scene, most schools responded by instituting courses in computer literacy. That was equivalent to educators in the mid-16th century offering courses in pencil literacy.</p>
        <p>Then computers came to be seen as extensions of teachers. Better software enabled students to work on their own, usually on relatively low-level skills like basic arithmetic or grammar. Teachers discovered that word processing, which lets students edit their work without having to retype it, was a big help in teaching writing.</p>
        <p>That was all very well, but, as Mark Share, coordinator of educational technology for the Scottsdale public schools, pointed out, it still fell short of seeing computers as ''tools in the hands of students, teachers and administrators.''</p>
        <p>Aided by $6 million from a bond issue, the 23 Scottsdale schools now have 2,600 computers, mostly Apples and Macintoshes, for 20,000 students, one of the richest ratios in the country.</p>
        <p>At appropriate ages, students are taught three basic skills - word processing, using spreadsheets and building and manipulating data bases. Three-year-olds in the preschool program draw and learn colors by moving their fingers across computer screens; high school students learn how to build computer-controlled robots. Math teachers use them to teach problem-solving and science teachers simulate frog dissections. Computer games incorporate geography lessons. Students can even take portable computers home.</p>
        <p>At Yavapai Elementary School, students use the Apple Global Education Network to exchange information on their respective environments with a school on Martha's Vineyard. They are also collecting water samples to help a student in Chicago study acid rain.</p>
        <p>''For the first time we can really take the information needs of students seriously,'' said Judy Voran, head librarian at Chaparral High School.</p>
        <p>It is by now commonplace to assert that tomorrow's information society will put a premium not only on what people know but on how well they can analyze large amounts of new information. On this score, computers are a natural.</p>
        <p>''Anyone can take a problem and find an answer,'' Mr. Share said. ''The hard thing is to figure out the right question. You might be looking at a lot of data on American Presidents and then ask yourself: Why did so many come from Virginia? Then you can start to find out why.''</p>
        <p>When computers are used to help make students independent thinkers, the teacher takes on a new role. ''The teacher as source of all information has died,'' said Vicki L. Durbin, the principal of Yavapai. ''They're becoming project managers.''</p>
        <p>In Scottsdale, computers are also hastening the trend toward giving individual schools more authority over their own budgets.</p>
        <p>Even in Scottsdale, the concept of computers as tools for transforming all aspects of school life is still in its infancy, and many problems lie ahead. For example, Ms. Durbin noted that popular standardized reading and math tests do not measure the sophisticated skills her teachers hope to develop by means of the new technology.</p>
        <p>''There's nothing in our media center that will help us on the Iowa Test of Basic Skills,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The same can be said of some of the tidbits that students discover from their high-tech globetrotting. ''An Eskimo kid told us that they like to chew on whale fat mixed with seal oil,'' Steve Richardson said. ''Yuck!''  EDUCATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
