<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Once Considered a Sure Thing, California's Environmental Package Falters</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="384473"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFERENDUMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">REINHOLD, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DC133CF935A2575AC0A966958260" item-length="1500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Once Considered a Sure Thing, California's Environmental Package Falters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT REINHOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REINHOLD, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Sept. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: When first proposed, a sweeping California ballot measure that promised a ''bold and comprehensive'' plan to protect the environment seemed a sure winner that could deliver a powerful national message about the public's determination to fight pollution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: When first proposed, a sweeping California ballot measure that promised a ''bold and comprehensive'' plan to protect the environment seemed a sure winner that could deliver a powerful national message about the public's determination to fight pollution.</p>
        <p>When first proposed, a sweeping California ballot measure that promised a ''bold and comprehensive'' plan to protect the environment seemed a sure winner that could deliver a powerful national message about the public's determination to fight pollution.</p>
        <p>But seven weeks before the election, the initiative appears to be in trouble. And environmentalists fear it may prove that voters' willingness to convert noble, abstract notions about the environment into concrete actions may be limited by the potential cost.</p>
        <p>''A recession is coming,'' one backer said. ''People get scared when they hear it's going to cost billions of dollars. Until recently I would have said it would pass handily. Now, it just might lose.''</p>
        <p>The Nov. 6 vote may offer the first public test of the domestic political consequences of the turmoil in the Middle East, which has sharpened public awareness of the trade-offs between energy production and environmental protection, a balancing act that is nowhere more pointed than in automobile-dependent California.</p>
        <p>While the initiative still leads in the polls, it has been battered in recent days by reports - vigorously disputed by its backers - that it would cost billions of dollars to local governments and the state and that it would depress agriculture and other industries. The legislative analyst for the City of Los Angeles, for example, estimated that the city's Department of Water and Power would have to spend more than $6 billion just to reduce carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>Opponents Focus on Tom Hayden</p>
        <p>An advertising campaign financed by chemical and allied agricultural interests has portrayed the initiative as an effort that tries to do too much and promotes the political ambitions of Assemblyman Tom Hayden, the chairman of the steering committee leading the effort to pass it. While Mr. Hayden, of Santa Monica, has long since moved into the Democratic liberal mainstream, the commercials attempt to exploit the public's lingering perception of him from his youthful days as an opponent of the Vietnam War. Those opposing the initiative call it the Hayden Initiative.</p>
        <p>The environmental leadership, which calls the measure Big Green, is worried. ''We're on the line,'' said Robert K. Hattoy, regional representative of the Sierra Club here. ''If Big Green loses, it will look like the movement cannot translate the rhetoric of Earth Day into the reality of Election Day.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hayden says this will not happen. ''A tremendous amount of money is flowing from the chemical companies to create a fictional campaign, but we will win in the end,'' he said. But doubts are growing. The campaign is using the same Hollywood hoopla environmentalists used successfully four years ago to pass an initiative to label foods and products containing toxins. On Thursday night, celebrities, including Bette Midler, Robin Williams, Cher, Olivia Newton-John and Meryl Streep, sang, danced and preached for clean air and water, nearly filling the 6,166-seat outdoor Greek Theater in Hollywood and raising about $600,000.</p>
        <p>'Other Side Is Much Smarter'</p>
        <p>''They're blindly going through campaigns of the past,'' said one disaffected backer, who spoke on the condition that he not be identified. ''The other side is much smarter. There is a feeling Big Green goes too far and voters do not want to pay a lot of money. There is no groundswell of support.'' A California Poll, an independent, nonpartisan statewide survey taken by the Field Institute Aug. 17-27, found voters favoring the measure by 58-26, but the margin was 49 percent to 35 percent among those who were familiar with it. The poll, with a margin of error of plus or minus five percentage points, also found that 16 percent were undecided. A recent Los Angeles Times poll found support had slipped to 44 percent in favor and 42 percent against; the poll's margin of error was three percentage points.</p>
        <p>Political experts say this is ominous because the opposition has not begun its main television advertising assault. The measure is popular in the Los Angeles and San Francisco areas, but not in the politically pivotal San Joaquin Valley, the huge agricultural region, because of fears that curbs on pesticides could injure the economy.</p>
        <p>Could Influence Governor's Race</p>
        <p>For that reason, the measure could play a key role in the governor's race between Dianne Feinstein, the Democrat, and Senator Pete Wilson, the Republican. Ms. Feinstein has endorsed it, hurting her in agricultural areas; Mr. Wilson has not. Jim Costa of Fresno, chairman of the Democratic caucus in the state Assembly, said: ''I told her that if it's a close race and she loses, the reason will be that she did poorly in the San Joaquin Valley because she supported Big Green.''</p>
        <p>On the ballot as Proposition 128 and formally known as the Environmental Protection Act of 1990, the measure runs 39 pages and nearly 16,000 words. It would substantially rewrite California environmental law, imposing standards far more stringent than Federal law, including these:</p>
        <p>* All pesticides and herbicides known to cause cancer and reproductive harm would be phased out and the sale of imported produce containing residues of those substances would be banned unless they presented ''no significant risk'' to health.</p>
        <p>* Emission of ''any gases which may contribute, directly or indirectly, to global warming,'' including carbon dioxide, would be reduced by 40 percent by the year 2010.</p>
        <p>* Manufacture of chlorofluorocarbons would be phased out to protect the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>* A $300 million bond fund would be created to buy ancient redwood forests, limit clear cutting of timber and require developers to plant trees.</p>
        <p>* All oil and gas drilling in state-controlled coastal waters would be prohibited and a $500 million oil-spill response fund created.</p>
        <p>* $40 million a year would be provided for ''applied research'' on alternatives to pesticides in agriculture and other topics.</p>
        <p>It would also create an elected state Environmental Advocate, with authority to enforce environmental laws, independent of the governor and attorney general. Reportedly, Mr. Hayden wants this job, but he has not acknowledged that. Proponents say the new post is necessary because the Legislature, Governor and Federal Government have been unwilling to take adequate measures to protect the environment. The measure was originally mounted to bolster the gubernatorial campaign of Attorney General John K. Van de Kamp, who opposed Ms. Feinstein in the Democratic primary. It cobbles together several disparate approaches to environmental protection that backers said the Legislature and Governor were unwilling to pass.</p>
        <p>'A Multipurpose Creature'</p>
        <p>Critics call the initiative a poorly drawn law. John P. Dwyer, a professor of law at the University of California at Berkeley, likened it to ''a frenzied scientist's recombinant DNA experiment'' that had spliced unrelated changes into a ''multipurpose creature.''</p>
        <p>Debate focuses mainly on the cost and Mr. Hayden's role.</p>
        <p>Frederick Cannon, senior economist at the Bank of America in San Francisco, told a symposium at Berkeley's Graduate School of Public Policy about 10 days ago that while the measure would not cause a recession, its impact would be ''substantial'' with ''major dislocations'' for certain industries, particularly farming. He added that the costliest provisions would be the ''greenhouse'' gas reductions.</p>
        <p>The nonpartisan Legislative Analyst's Office in Sacramento estimates direct costs to state and local governments at up to $2.6 billion over the next 20 years. An analysis commissioned by opponents of the initiative said it would increase energy prices by $10 billion to $15 billion a year, raise electric rates by at least 20 percent by the year 2000, and cause the loss of 500,000 to 2 million jobs in manufacturing and construction. The opponents have refused to release the details of how these conclusions were reached.</p>
        <p>Backers angrily dismissed such figures as scare tactics and are preparing their own economic analysis. ''These are simple-minded economic assessments based on the notion that we are capped out on energy savings,'' said Ralph C. Cavanagh of the Natural Resources Defense Council. ''There are large opportunities to save more by saving rather than producing energy.'' He argued that renewable energy sources including geothermal, solar and wind power would get a substantial boost from the initiative.</p>
        <p>The measure faces further political difficulties because the ballot will contain three other measures related to the environment. One of them, called Careful and mounted by the California Farm Bureau Federation and the Western Growers Association, would set less restrictive rules on pesticides. The two others offer competing plans on logging by environmentalists and timber companies.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot of confusion. All four sound good. People don't know how to vote to be good environmentalists,'' said Mr. Hattoy of the Sierra Club.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
