<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What a Sea of Stories Taught Me</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="393857"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FORD, RICHARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D9153FF932A15753C1A966958260" item-length="2710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What a Sea of Stories Taught Me</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD FORD; Richard Ford's most recent book is the novel ''Wildlife.''</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FORD, RICHARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Having spent a good part of the last year and a quarter at the task of reading for an annual best-story collection, I've begun to feel like the Professor Irwin Corey of the short story - the world's greatest living authority over a discipline that doesn't exactly exist, a professorship of nothing, tenured in the university without walls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Having spent a good part of the last year and a quarter at the task of reading for an annual best-story collection, I've begun to feel like the Professor Irwin Corey of the short story - the world's greatest living authority over a discipline that doesn't exactly exist, a professorship of nothing, tenured in the university without walls.</p>
        <p>Having spent a good part of the last year and a quarter at the task of reading for an annual best-story collection, I've begun to feel like the Professor Irwin Corey of the short story - the world's greatest living authority over a discipline that doesn't exactly exist, a professorship of nothing, tenured in the university without walls.</p>
        <p>When I began this enterprise I had a lot of ''ideas'' stored up concerning the short story, ideas that, like the concept of the short story itself, have somewhat faded in importance, leaving me in nothing more than a spirit of complaint, out of which I would love to tell you what my year's been like as a way of comforting myself for spending it so extravagantly. I had it in mind to settle some hash, to set straight varieties of wrongheadedness, to burst a few bubbles, step right in the middle of debates over embarrassing gibberish like minimalism and post-modernism. I meant to steal marches against retro-regionalism, pooh-pooh the fictitious short-story renaissance and the purported watering down of the story writers' gene pool by insidious writing programs. Like Keats, I suppose I felt I had a few axioms. And using them I meant to strike blows that would free writers everywhere - globally, as it were - to write what they damn well please, the best they can, and to like me for letting them.</p>
        <p>I don't know what got into me. I don't know whom I thought I was addressing or kidding or, unlike Keats, who I thought I was.</p>
        <p>A warming chestnut snugged into the heart of many anthology introductions is the complaint that a virtual cornucopia of wonderful stories - far too many for one slender volume - made final choices nearly impossible. This was not precisely my experience. There were perhaps five more very good stories than the 20 I wound up with at the end of my considerations. And I did not enjoy having to appraise these in seemingly relative, pseudocompetitive terms. I would have preferred giving each story a chance at its own absolute excellence, a habit that served me well through most of my reading.</p>
        <p>But there was something to learn from this great sea of stories. So much of the reading for this volume was of stories I didn't want to reprint, stories that didn't seem good enough, that my strongest feeling of contact is and has been with that group of stories and their writers. Unarguably, writing short stories - a minor contribution to the saga of mankind - is something most people can't do very well. I don't know why. Maybe it's harder than it looks, and wonderful stories do seem like little miracles.</p>
        <p>Over the years, people have been gracious enough to point out that I've written some unexcellent stories myself, and if that's true I hope to God I never write another one. But I know it's all right if I can't, and others sometimes don't. No one should care - least of all me - if a hundred writing programs graduate a thousand people every year, all of whom can write a semicompetent but rarely interesting version of what they mean to be a short story, or if oldsters write them by the carload, or if in California story writing is thought of as a branch of psychotherapy or crisis intervention.</p>
        <p>That's fine. We're not talking about global warming or toxic waste here. It's a victimless crime if the ''less gifted'' thrive and have fun. Art's that way - free. And you couldn't stop people anyway, just as you can't stop scores of magazines, large and small, famous and obscure, from publishing all that not-so-good writing, then turning their editors loose upon the world to sit on panels and brag about how good it all is. You won't get any hand wringing or defenses of the form out of me. The form's most persuasive defender - insofar as it needs any - is simply good work. And that's sufficient encouragement to those of us who write stories, and a pleasure to the remaining few who don't write them but merely like to read.</p>
        <p>Form, though, persists as a bothersome if finally treatable obsession in conversations about writing short stories. Disputes over form, slurring naturally enough into more self-devoted disputes about content and execution (the three being inseparable from birth), are the source of all the magical/minimal/classical/neorealist quacking that has become the feed call for so many suppressed intellectual appetites, as well as the subject of many, many, many tiresome essays and special issues and symposiums in countless magazines and universities - all best forgotten.</p>
        <p>Away from the shifting requirements of the writing I do myself, I don't really have much of a definition of the short-story form, and don't feel I need one. ''Short'' still seems somehow inevitable, though I'm pretty lenient about that. You can find plenty of primers and handbooks to tell you what a short story is and isn't, but in these months of reading I never once dismissed a piece of writing as not being properly a short story when it claimed it was one. I have, on the other hand, been inclined to dismiss stories that were not interesting - no matter that they conformed to the strictest formal restraints, had their mimetic ducks in swank rows, offered a peripeteia, a denouement and closed down tighter than banks at their earned endings.</p>
        <p>To me, it's a relief to observe how many disparate pieces of writing can be persuasively called short stories, how formally underdefined the short story still is in the minds and hands of writers. And even if the most excellent of recent stories do not represent formal variety as gaily as they might have 20 or so years ago, when John Cheever and Ann Beattie and John Updike and Joyce Carol Oates and Ray Carver were publishing toe to toe with Ron Sukenick and Donald Barthelme, Barry Hannah and George Chambers - the days of the ''anti-story'' and the early Fiction Collective and Fiction magazine and when, I guess, the short story was dead and didn't know it - my rules are the same as then: liberal to a fault, and submissive to any consciousness of form that inspires invention and discovery. What we want from stories is to have eternal passion revealed in that heart where, before, all seemed known and discovered. But to write that way, you're always going to be out there on your own - out, as Browning wrote, on the dangerous edge of things.</p>
        <p>What's interesting, of course, is what's interesting - if only for seeming less subservient to prescription and rule. Recently, on a flight back home to New Orleans, a man seated next to me began to take notice of the fact that I was reading. I was reading, not surprisingly, from a stack of short stories, my digits jammed in my ears for semiquiet, my brows beetled, concentrating as fiercely as ever it's possible when jammed into something like a big airborne aluminum storm drain filled, in this case, with Mardi Gras revelers. (Such is the cultural context of the American short story.) After several minutes of intermittent fixity upon me, during which my seatmate tried and finally succeeded in getting my attention loosed from my pleasure, he and I began a brief dialogue in which I tried to explain that I was reading short stories, that I had already read many of them but still had more to go, that there was this book to be published . . . and on in that vein we talked. Biff was his name, like the chummy old Alan Hale Jr. character on television, whom he in some ways resembled.</p>
        <p>When Biff had digested all my info, he looked at me somewhat gravely. He was a large, rough-skinned man in his 60's who'd sold jewelry items to the trade and had sold them for 40 years all over America, but who had done enough reading so that reading mattered to him. ''But wait, now, Dick,'' he said to me (though there wasn't a chance I could go anywhere). ''You're reading all these short stories. . . .'' He eyed my stack. ''But what're your criteria here? You know what I'm talking about? What's good and what's not good? That's always been a pretty damn subjective area to me.'' He nodded. And, well. Yes, of course. That's true. I began immediately then, as we commenced our long descent toward Lake Ponchartrain and the city that care forgot, to enunciate my criteria for him - the ones I felt were good ones and that I believed I was using. Nothing so narrow as to violate my instincts, yet nothing so wide as to make me seem vulgarly indiscriminate - the thing no one wants to be. Certainly he was serious enough that a good, crackling, stand-up answer was needed.</p>
        <p>''Well, Biff, since you asked, I'm looking for stories that will be axes for the frozen sea within us.'' That would've done the trick. Or, ''I'm hunting for stories that'll add to the stock of available reality, Biff. Or at least something to supply the satisfactions of belief in their measure and their style.'' Any of these would've done fine and been as true as true can be.</p>
        <p>But the fact is I didn't say those things. I maundered something about good stories being ''different,'' that the idea of a ''story'' was somewhat arbitrary, that you couldn't predict what would make a story good and that the precise vocabulary of one's standards often lay buried beneath impulse and taste (though, of course, I'd always been envious of people who could flash theirs like a police badge).</p>
        <p>It wasn't very good, what I said. My criteria seemed to stay pretty damn subjective, not to mention fuzzy about first principles, and soon this polite, interested man began admiring the approaching city out my window - at first just a stitch on the horizon, but rising by seconds more and more clearly into focus. We didn't talk much after that, and in a bit we didn't talk at all.</p>
        <p>People think of standards - criteria - as being clear rules against which random experience is measured, thereby helping randomness to seem less vexing and oppressive, like a foul line in baseball or the manual of arms or the rules of admiralty. And in general I don't believe the idea of standards is bad as long as they stay as supple as the experience to be measured. It certainly seems reasonable that I be able to address coherently the question of what's an excellent short story and what's a less than excellent one - and, more, that I believe in what I think is good, and that I believe something is good, and that I can lay it down in terms a nonwriter, a ''layman,'' can appreciate. Indeed, even to recognize a laity, with a corresponding set-apart priesthood of writer-readers, is at least dubious and threatens to make little princes of obscurity of those of us who are ostensibly in the know.</p>
        <p>Literary critics, in the palmy days before deconstruction, used to circle relentlessly the very issue of what's good, using a variety of august terminologies - all meant, I suppose, in part to keep their own little voids filled. What's a classic? What has gusto? Magnitude? What's sublime? What will last? - issues now largely lumped into the care of book reviewers, with few others knowing quite how to be interested.</p>
        <p>A couple of years ago, a dean at Northwestern University wrote to me soliciting my opinion (free of charge) about the creative work of a young colleague, a novelist I didn't know but whose work I liked. What the dean wanted to hear from me was: would this young man's work be read by later generations? Like Hemingway, I suppose he meant. Or Moliere, maybe. Or Chaucer. In any case, this seemed to be the going rate and standard for tenure at Northwestern, and apparently how good was measured. (Melville would never have been kept on there.) Most writers I know and whose work I admire want to write something that later generations will read and be redeemed by; they want, as my friend Barry Hannah says, to shoot for the stars in all that they write. But we all know there are no promises about that. No formulas. Adherence to the old? Adherence to the new? It's impossible to know if work will last, and slightly fatuous even to wonder, since we ourselves won't last, and literature may not either, though we all hope it does.</p>
        <p>After a day or so, I wrote to the dean and told him that while I certainly liked the writing in question, what I would do if I had his job would be to forget about permanence and later generations. Just read the work, I told him, then figure out if it's good according to what you think good is, and live with the consequences. Most writers wouldn't want it any other way.</p>
        <p>Good stories perform what wonders they do using wise standards all their own, discovered in the private vicissitudes of the act of writing. Some will essay to provide that ax for the frozen sea within us and to do so gracefully. Others will accept nothing but to reflect the connection between bliss and bale and be less than suave about it. Some will simply want to amuse us in a good cause. Don't get me wrong. I have my rules, for my stories. And with them I'm as despotic as I please. I want to write only characters who have the incalculability of life, stories with Wordsworthian purpose and powerful feelings. For me there are many fewer ways than Frank O'Connor's famous ''dozens'' to express verisimilitude - one, maybe one and a half. Max. My economies are drastic. I want endings (not stoppings) that close like supernovas and leave you gasping. But, hey. That's just me and my work. What kind of guy would I be, what kind of judge, if I insisted everybody do that? How much more difficult for Flannery O'Connor or Raymond Carver or Donald Barthelme if only one standard ruled our days?</p>
        <p>Early last winter, an editor from a large metropolitan newspaper called to ask if I would review a volume of short stories. The writer was someone whose stories I'd admired, and I wanted to read this new book, wanted to like everything about it. But in the course of our conversation I said that if I read the book and didn't like it I wouldn't write about it at all, since I had no wish to complain about my colleague's work in public.</p>
        <p>''Maybe I'd be all wrong,'' I said. ''I'd hate to drive readers away from a good book I was wrong about.''</p>
        <p>''But don't you want to uphold high literary standards?'' the editor said.</p>
        <p>''Sure,'' I said. ''But not at somebody else's expense. Anyway, I write stories myself. I have a way to hold up standards if I'm able at all.''</p>
        <p>''Yes. Well,'' this person answered in a peckish tone, discernible from miles and miles away, ''aren't you lucky?''</p>
        <p>''Yes, I suppose I am,'' I said. ''Though it's odd. That's not exactly how I feel.''</p>
        <p>But you can see what I'm getting at. Writing short stories and choosing 20 good ones are different businesses. Right brain, left brain, maybe. Who knows? So, finally, we get to the back of the garage, the nuts and bolts. There are not a lot of wonderful short stories published in America year to year, and partly in view of that rarity I chose only the best I could find, with no attempt to distribute evenly the number of men to women, the number of small magazines to large ones; I made no attempt to include some percentage of gay writers or Chicanos or African-Americans or Jews. I have not tried to encourage younger writers or discourage Southerners, West Coast writers, dyslexics, New-Agers, Christians or Viet vets.</p>
        <p>There were not many funny stories in the 250 I saw. I regret that and hope I wasn't driven by large numbers to confuse soberness with seriousness, as Edmund Wilson was said never to have done. I would hate more than I'd hate a faulty judgment to be a man who was thought of as hard to tickle.</p>
        <p>And with that said, I've reached the feeling that must regularly come only to authors of introductions to anthologies - a class of humans best represented by Professor Corey, the genial academic gentleman I began with - a feeling of having filled a much-needed void using the entirety of my passions and faculties. I fondly remember what the professor, when asked if he favored Brownian movement over the second movement of Beethoven's Fifth Symphony, was heard to remark - and this after only a moment's consideration, far less time than it's taken for you to read this essay - ''Why, yes!'' he said, smiling grandly. ''Yes, yes, yes, indeed. I couldn't agree more.'' No fool he.</p>
        <p>Adapted from the introduction to ''Best American Short Stories of 1990,'' to be published next month by Houghton Mifflin.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
