<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSH'S CABINET: WHO'S UP, WHO'S DOWN</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="337668"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CABINETS AND SUB-CABINETS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DF103DF936A15750C0A966958260" item-length="6401" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSH'S CABINET: WHO'S UP, WHO'S DOWN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire: William Safire is a columnist for The Times.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: At the first informal meeting of the Bush Cabinet, in Blair House a week before the Inauguration, George Bush pulled a handwritten list out of his pocket and read what he called ''The Marching Orders.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: At the first informal meeting of the Bush Cabinet, in Blair House a week before the Inauguration, George Bush pulled a handwritten list out of his pocket and read what he called ''The Marching Orders.''</p>
        <p>At the first informal meeting of the Bush Cabinet, in Blair House a week before the Inauguration, George Bush pulled a handwritten list out of his pocket and read what he called ''The Marching Orders.''</p>
        <p>''Think big. * Challenge the system. * Adhere to the highest ethical standards. * Be on the record as much as possible. * Be frank. * Fight hard for your position. * When I make a call, we move as a team. * Work with Congress. * Represent the United States with dignity.''</p>
        <p>Commerce Secretary Robert Mosbacher obtained a copy of that unassailably virtuous list of nine commandments and had it printed, framed and distributed to his 15 colleagues in the Cabinet. Some thought that smacked of apple polishing, but boosterism has never been a vice at Commerce.</p>
        <p>Bush's marching orders, written to be revealed, indicate how the President wants his Administration to be seen: bold, ethical, open, decorous. As his towering popularity shows, much of Mr. Bush's message is coming across. But at least one of those commandments, as we shall see, rings false.</p>
        <p>What kind of Cabinet did he want and what has he been getting? In the second quarter of his term, the time is ripe for preliminary judgments - not only about the individuals trusted with what Mr. Bush likes to call his stewardship, but about how they interact with the White House and each other in managing the country.</p>
        <p>In recent years, when Presidents enter office, they begin by declaring for ''Cabinet government.'' No yes-men for them; no palace guard centralizing power and isolating the President; on the contrary, we are all assured, the department heads will be given real responsibility to run their own shows.</p>
        <p>This assertion is made because every President is determined to avoid the mistakes in style as well as operation made by recent predecessors. Johnson and Carter are adjudged too much the detail men, micromanaging every facet of government from the Oval Office, undermining Cabinet responsibility; Nixon, after duly announcing an Eisenhower-style Cabinet government, saw the need to ''challenge the system'' and pulled the power inside, to the point of making sure his Cabinet members could not get through the staff guardians. Reagan started a revolution and turned it over to his Cabinet generals, refusing to intervene in titanic Cabinet struggles between State and Defense.</p>
        <p>The Bush management style is a reaction to the detached, decentralized Reagan style. Mr. Bush likes the expression ''hands-on,'' which in politics signifies involvement of the President in details of issues; he demonstrates his hands-onedness by exposing himself frequently to the media's pop quizzes (leaving the press corps gasping for fresh questions), but he has not drawn most Cabinet power inside the White House, as Johnson, Nixon and Carter did. Mr. Bush, the longtime insider, the close observer of past mistakes, is striving for that happy medium - neither too involved nor too remote. To achieve that light hands-on touch, he tries to avoid both dominating his ''team'' and letting it manipulate or define him.</p>
        <p>To exercise central policy control, the Bush Cabinet system relies on a White House chief of staff, John Sununu, who has strong policy views, and is no mere coordinator; he is backed up by an encyclopedic budget director, who adds a pinch of deviousness to his crunching of the numbers. To diffuse administrative responsibility, Mr. Bush permits a too-harmonious Cabinet to exercise more operational independence than is customary. In this way, an accessible President hopes to maintain hands-on policy and hands-off details.</p>
        <p>Is it working? In most cases, the Bush approach, Marching Orders and all, has produced one big happy family in power: rarely does a Cabinet exude such unanimity and eschew back-stabbing. ''You can have two basic problems with a Cabinet member,'' says a White House staff member. ''His Own Agenda is bad, because then you get an ideological split and the team comes apart. Even worse is Clientitis, when the Cabinet member forgets he works for the President and becomes a captive of his agency. So far, we haven't had a bad case of either.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, the absence of creative tension has generated little excitement or innovation: no stewing, all stewarding. ''All the action is in Moscow and Berlin, not here,'' says Lyn Nofziger, the appeal-freed Reagan aide I ran into on a street near the White House. ''What happened to all those fun ideological wars we used to have?'' Some skirmishing goes on, as we shall see, but as a result of the Bush emphasis on calm seas, internal order and at least the appearance of unanimity (Order Seven: ''When I make a call, we move as a team''), we miss the Rooseveltian turbulence that often leads to original thinking.</p>
        <p>Some Bush appointees are making it; a couple are dominant; others are falling sadly behind; a few are happy surprises. Here is one pundit's assessment of the standing - the internal and external perception of clout - of the 16 department heads who sit at the table with the President when the Bush Cabinet meets every third week.</p>
        <p>The standards I use to judge who's up and who's down do not include ideological purity or pristine moderation; to determine who is and is not a ''player,'' I have tried to suppress the urge to anoint as successes those who agree with me or answer my calls. It's George Bush's Cabinet, not mine.</p>
        <p>The criteria used here are: management skill, intelligence or savvy, ability to make the President look good, force of personality, originality and, most important, heft - the mysterious political weight derived from intellect, experience and character that causes colleagues and outsiders to take a public official seriously.</p>
        <p>Take them clockwise from the President, as they sit around the long oval Cabinet table:</p>
        <p>Dick Cheney</p>
        <p>Secretary of Defense.</p>
        <p>Cheney sits to the President's left, the traditional spot for the Secretary of Defense. Universally liked, respected for his intelligence and civility, the former House Republican whip is a Secretary of Defense truly on the defensive.</p>
        <p>Trying to hold the line on budget-cutting by calling attention to the continuing Soviet arms threat, he was ''Bakerized'' - cut off at the knees by someone other than the Secretary of State, but with James Baker's connivance. The instrument used to reduce Dick Cheney's influence was the Director of Central Intelligence, William Webster, who told Congress that even the overthrow of Gorbachev would be unlikely to restore the Soviet threat. Mr. Baker had seen and approved the C.I.A. testimony; the Secretary of Defense was blindsided by it and could only mumble that the rosy C.I.A. assessment was ''unhelpful.'' Mr. Bush later told a news conference that C.I.A. and Defense views were not drastically different - which all the more dramatized the split.</p>
        <p>Cheney is the foot-dragger in the stampede to disarm. Immersed in judicious budget-cutting, he is in a constant hard-line fallback position: he never seems to catch up with the latest bidding on reductions. As a result, the soft-spoken Cheney is slighted by doves, who think his department is an anachronism standing in the way of their peace dividend, and put down by hawks, who complain that he has been lukewarm on the Strategic Defense Initiative, too deferential to the dovish Joint Chiefs, and that he has not come up with a more mobile military strategy to cope with medium-sized threats worldwide.</p>
        <p>Although not a member of Bush's inner circle, Cheney has a small strike force within the bureaucracy that prevents total dominance by Baker's State Department. His Under Secretary for Policy, Paul Wolfowitz, is a foreign service officer who knows the international ropes and was chosen by the President to be part of the small group negotiating at the Malta summit. With Henry Rowen, an economist, among the first to predict intolerable strains on the Soviet arms budget, Defense now has an imposing internal think tank. It draws up ''guidance'' to combat Soviet troublemaking in the third world while striving mightily not to sound bellicose, which is like trying to design a quiet noisemaker.</p>
        <p>Cheney is fighting a rear-guard action, which rarely makes for a heroic posture statement, and in the final few weeks' infighting over the defense budget, he was abroad. When a disconcerting story broke about a ''blockade'' of Colombia by an aircraft carrier, the national security inner circle - Baker, Sununu and Brent Scowcroft, the national security adviser - jumped all over Cheney in a private meeting as if the derisive media play had been his fault; this indicated to status-watchers that Cheney's nose was pressed against the pane of power.</p>
        <p>Even when being snubbed in the Philippines by President Aquino, however, Chaney has the undoubted respect of George Bush. His seat at the left hand of the President automatically makes him a player, but in today's Puzzle Palace, he offers solidity when nimbleness is required.</p>
        <p>Robert A. Mosbacher</p>
        <p>Secretary of Commerce.</p>
        <p>Washington's social daggers were out for Georgette Mosbacher, the glamourous, global cosmetics executive. However, the hard-driving businesswoman proved neither Reagan-era glitzy nor Bush-era gray: she decorated her spacious new home in record time to be able to handle dinner parties reaching beyond the usual fuddy-duddies and enlivened by the presence of other successful women. If any members of the Bush Cabinet have a salon, it is the Mosbachers, who provide a needed bridge to the news media and the Congress.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Mosbacher was accompanied to Washington by her likable husband, Robert, Mr. Bush's Texas friend since 1958 and former chief fund-raiser. Hard-liners feared he would be swallowed up by the let's-do-business-with-the-Soviets crowd at the 15th Street Statistics Mausoleum, also known as the Commerce Department. Sure enough, Mosbacher has been touting fiber-optic sales to the Soviet Union over the objections of the Pentagon. But within the Cabinet, he disagreed with the budget director Richard Darman on a way to help American firms become more competitive and came out on top; as a result, the President has called for legislation loosening antitrust restrictions on joint production by United States firms. He has been losing points to Carla Hills, the United States Trade Representative, on confronting Japan on its trade barriers, and he lost a key turf battle to her about handling trade negotiations with Moscow. But Mosbacher is a loyalist with deep roots in the Bush campaigns; though a player only on occasion, he's a power kibbitzer.</p>
        <p>Samuel K. Skinner</p>
        <p>Secretary of Transportation.</p>
        <p>Only Veterans Affairs is more junior at the Cabinet table; Transportation is considered far out in the wings of the Washington power scene. Along comes this obscure Illinois prosecutor, the only Cabinet choice to have no entry in ''Who's Who in America.'' Fast on his feet and ready to jump into any sort of crisis, Sam Skinner turns out to be the first Transportation Secretary to be a player. He stepped gingerly into the Eastern Airlines strike, but descended on Alaska with enthusiasm to show the Bush flag in overseeing the Valdez oil spill. He discombobulated Wall Street takeover types by wagging a finger about leveraged buyouts of air carriers, and - taking on free-traders Nicholas Brady at Treasury and Michael Boskin of the Council of Economic Advisers - jawboned away at substantial foreign investments in United States airlines.</p>
        <p>Spirited activism counts. With hardly any bureaucratic or political or personal base, with little money to back up forceful statements of goals, and despite suspicion that he is a liberal at heart, Skinner is viewed as a Cabinet comer who might be chosen to rescue the Justice Department.</p>
        <p>Richard G. Darman</p>
        <p>Director of the Office of Management and Budget.</p>
        <p>This man suffers from the Dr. Fell Syndrome: few public servants of such extensive experience and wide-ranging interests and keen mind generate such mistrust. (''I do not love thee, Dr. Fell, the reason why I cannot tell. . . .'') Right-wingers remember him as Elliot Richardson's protege, a closet moderate, and later as Jim Baker's protege, a closet pragmatist; Dick Darman's political breeding was suspiciously centrist. Liberals see him as a man whose sensitivity, brains and suffer-no-fools temperament should have inclined him their way; they thus create an apostate who understands their motivations too well, and who sugarcoats parsimony with efficiency.</p>
        <p>He's nobody's protege now. Darman has made himself indispensible to the Bush mode of Cabinet operation, and delights in taking on the Cabinet members (except Baker and Brady) one by one, like a champ inviting all challengers at a county fair. He batters them into his overall policy-budget shape; when seriously challenged, as he was on funding by the drug czar William Bennett (a player, but not a Cabinet member), Darman goes one-on-one before Referee John Sununu, who adjudicates and cuts a deal. Rarely if ever is a Cabinet member humiliated and forced to appeal to the President.</p>
        <p>Known as a hardball player, Darman can lob in a soft pitch (Darman likes metaphors): to curry favor with Senator John Glenn, whose committee oversees O.M.B., Darman adopted Glenn's proposal to expand the Cabinet to accommodate the Environmental Protection Agency. ''What did it cost?'' asks a Darman fan. ''Three limousines and a plaque on the back of a chair. And someday, with a Democrat in the White House, they'll lump together Energy, Interior and Environment again.''</p>
        <p>Smart; ambitious; political inner circle; of the three Richards in the Cabinet, he is the only one not to insist on being called Dick. Richard Darman is a man to keep your eye on, in more ways than one.</p>
        <p>THE SEAT AT THE END OF THE TABLE TO THEJU President's left belongs to John H. Sununu, chief of staff, not a Cabinet member. Though he and Darman are the President's main conduit to the department heads, the reader will have to learn of his activities through his impact on the others, or elsewhere; 16 subjects is all I can handle here.</p>
        <p>Edward J. Derwinski</p>
        <p>Secretary of Veterans Affairs.</p>
        <p>This agency was elevated to the Cabinet by Ronald Reagan, professed foe of bureaucracy, in an exercise in patriotic window dressing - the new Secretary's presence in the Cabinet was a sop to the veterans' lobby.</p>
        <p>Derwinski refused to change the signs at the Veterans Administration, whose bureaucrats wanted new signs as befits their higher status; that was satisfying, if ostentatious, frugality. As veterans age, needs will shift from acute to extended care; Derwinski is considered a refreshing heretic in seeking to rationalize the future benefit structure.</p>
        <p>Accordingly, Ed Derwinski has proven to be more of an asset than a table-crowder. A veteran Congressman with good Polish connections, he brings political common sense to Cabinet discussions. Though not a player, Derwinski unexpectedly speaks up and is good to have on your side.</p>
        <p>Jack F. Kemp</p>
        <p>Secretary of Housing and Urban Development.</p>
        <p>He calls himself a ''bleeding-heart conservative,'' and that oxymoron sums up the unique Kemp role in the Bush Administration: the apostle of free enterprise who is the ambassador to the poor. As Senator Robert Taft showed generations ago, only a politician of tax-cut purity with conservative credentials could put across a program like Kemp's openhanded ''Project Hope'' - Federal support for low-income home ownership.</p>
        <p>Another anomaly: this man of the legislature was given what suddenly became the biggest administrative challenge of any of the Bush Cabinet - cleaning up the mess left when the Reagan White House (J. Baker, chief of staff, lest we forget) permitted ''Silent Sam'' Pierce's shrinking agency to be used as a political play-(Continued on Page 63) ground and influence-peddler's candy store. Kemp, steering between the Scylla of a cover-up and the Charybdis of a witch hunt, tightened controls, guided passage of corrective legislation and restored the agency's integrity without prejudging the hapless Pierce. Kemp said the mismanaged agency had been ''drifting for decades,'' which may have caused Carla Hills, a former H.U.D. Secretary, to blink.</p>
        <p>Kemp, who was the popular Republican choice to be Bush's running mate, was given an obscure post and found himself in the limelight. Though his primary interest has always been foreign affairs and economics, he plunged into the world of affordable housing with characteristic enthusiasm, pushing H.U.D.'s envelope, making himself a kind of Secretary of Family without treading on toes. ''It's amazing how he wraps Bush into everything he does and says,'' an aide to Governor Sununu notes admiringly. Kemp takes on Brady about interest rates with good humor, and seems to have an alliance with Darman, who needs some lines to the right.</p>
        <p>Unlike most Cabinet members, the former professional quarterback is an unabashed intellectual. Kemp has made a determined effort to reach out to black Americans, and his sincerity is not discounted as political. Though not an insider, Kemp's enthusiasm and savvy have made him a player.</p>
        <p>Clayton K. Yeutter</p>
        <p>Agriculture</p>
        <p>Yeutter (the first syllable is pronounced as in ''Yipes!'') is likely to preside over a reduction in farm supports, especially to wealthy farmers, which should earn him high marks with most of the media and big-city members of Congress, but the former boss of the Chicago Mercantile Exchange comes on too strong.</p>
        <p>Senators Dole, Leahy and Lugar are meeting in the Cabinet Room with the President and his Agriculture Secretary. With his stentorian voice, Yeutter goes on and on in what seems to some participants his usual condescending way. Noting this, Mr. Bush makes a circling motion with his hand, which Yeutter ignores. Finally, the President says gently, ''I think that probably covers it, Clayton.'' ''Oh no, Mr. President,'' says his Agriculture Secretary, ''I have more.'' And he booms on.</p>
        <p>His Commodity Credit Corporation's loan guarantees are coming under Congressional scrutiny and his two-minute encomia to the President at Cabinet meetings strike some Cabinet officials as unnecessary apple-polishing. To become a player, Yeutter would have to go up against Bob Dole's Kansas agriculture protectionism, and the President is not likely to let him do that.</p>
        <p>Nicholas F. Brady</p>
        <p>Treasury</p>
        <p>In an office energized by activists like Alexander Hamilton and John Connally, Nick Brady seems passive. A nice and profoundly unexciting man, he has been clumsy at Congressional hearings and a guaranteed ratings loser on interview shows. In Cabinet meetings, he says little (in contrast to the hyperarticulate Dick Darman, who is said to want his job). Handicapped by a reading disability, recently recovered from an operation on an arthritic hip and not temperamentally suited to the take-charge role that Treasury activists admire in their leaders, Brady has raised diffidence to an art form.</p>
        <p>However, he is to George Bush what Harry Hopkins was to F.D.R. - a modest friend who wants only to serve, and a trustworthy repository of confidences. The more Brady tells his colleagues he was never really as close as reputed to the Bushes, the more they recall that this Yalie was the only one authorized to speak for the candidate on his Presidential plans from 1984 to 1988.</p>
        <p>He is a white-shoe old shoe, able to walk across the street to the President's office whenever so inclined, and likely to be in the room in a domestic crisis after all but a few have been dismissed. Does he use this influence to advance his ideas? On lowering the capital gains tax, on reducing third-world debt and on paying for the savings-and-loan debacle, yes; on Wall Street reform and double taxation of dividends, no.</p>
        <p>He is like a counselor to the inner circle, not driving policy; in the crunch, Brady is to Darman what Scowcroft is to Baker. In the economic Quadriad, he shows little imagination and swings little weight. His power comes from his personal closeness to the President, who digs his diffidence and relies on his judgment, and from strong appointees in the Treasury subcabinet.</p>
        <p>Like the economy, Brady is in a mature phase of prosperity but not in a period of strong growth; in a downturn that would call for a dynamic economic spokesman, he would be a candidate for a major ambassadorship.</p>
        <p>WE ARE NOW HALFWAY AROUNDJU the cabinet table, at the Vice Presidential chair, opposite the President. The Vice President sits with the Cabinet, but as an elected official is not of it. Dan Quayle is far more internally effective than he is perceived outside; he saved important elements of our space program from Darman's budget knife, and received an unprecedented early choice by the President as the 1992 running mate. His cool crisis management of an attempted coup in the Philippines earned him respect inside the National Security Council. Still, he must find a way to gain gravitas: the unfair charge is still ''his face does not look lived in.'' Time and campaigning will put lines on his face, and welts on his back. He's not in the Bush loop as tightly as Baker, Darman or Sununu, but Quayle must be ranked as a player.</p>
        <p>Dick Thornburgh</p>
        <p>Atty Gen</p>
        <p>Nobody's press is worse than Dick Thornburgh's. He ranks somewhere down around former Attorneys General John Mitchell, William Saxbe and Ed Meese in the estimation of those who cover him because he is obsessed with leaks and has isolated himself behind a palace guard of Pennsylvania cronies; worse, his blunders on several nominations for assistants made him gun-shy to political fire from the right.</p>
        <p>That was not how it was supposed to be. On paper, Thornburgh was a fine appointment, coming in after Meese and held over by Bush. A former Criminal Division chief and a popular Governor of Pennsylvania, this man had all the credentials; nobody in the Cabinet has fallen farther faster.</p>
        <p>Too much political sensitivity is bad politics. A few months ago, I tried to get an answer out of Justice on a drug policy matter and gave up when nobody would call back - but weeks later, when I called the Austrian Embassy to ask if the Attorney General had toasted Kurt Waldheim at a dinner there, a Thornburgh press aide was on the phone within a half-hour. (The A. G. had toasted only ''Austria's leaders,'' according to a nervous Embassy source.) The emphasis within Justice now is on fixing the A.G.'s flaking image, hardly a sign of strength. When both Oregon senators asked for his help in getting a judgeship for a jurist under unfair fire from antipornographers, Thornburgh was fearful of antagonizing the far right; it was the tough-minded Sununu, not worried about flak from the right, who delivered.</p>
        <p>To counter the widespread wonderment at the failure of the holdover Attorney General to get on top of his job, Sununu, the chief of staff, insists Thornburgh is getting bad press because he is doing the dirty work to get good results.</p>
        <p>True, Thornburgh invited fire by circumventing his publicity-hungry Office of Professional Responsibility in one leak-plugging case. Sununu's defense, however, does not stand up: the criticism comes from all sides. As one loyal Republican puts it in wonderment, ''He's not that good to have such a bad press.''</p>
        <p>Losers are shunned. Thornburgh confidently announced he would accompany the President to the Cartagena drug summit, but when the list was put out by the White House, the Attorney General's name was not included. The significance of the President's rebuff was not lost on Thornburgh's Cabinet colleagues.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth H. Dole</p>
        <p>Labor</p>
        <p>For the first year, she went into a kind of hibernation. ''That office was like a bunker during Ray Donovan's time'' recalls a labor skate about the Reagan Labor Secretary; ''then it was opened up by Bill Brock and Ann McLaughlin, and the doors were closed again with Liddy Dole.'' She brought in her political team and the department bureaucracy brooded; the word was out that her appointment was to cool off Bob Dole, the Senate majority leader defeated for the presidential nomination. The derogation increased when, in the Eastern Airlines strike, Mr. Bush designated Transportation Secretary Sam Skinner to be Administration spokesman.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Dole showed little interest in women in the workforce and did not take the lead in child care; occupational safety became her cause, and she quadrupled the fines levied against employers. That pleased the A.F.L.-C.I.O., which wanted her to intervene in the Pittston coal strike. When she finally did, by appointing as mediator William Usery, a great old pro, she broke a Reagan precedent of nonintervention and received good press. However, the settlement has drawn the Labor Department into the thicket of the financing of health care, the implications of which even the alert Darman has not yet grasped.</p>
        <p>Her talent is also her drawback: she is a fungible appointee, liked by Congress, available to serve in whatever field whenever a woman with political savvy who makes a good speech is needed. In the past, some Republican Labor Secretaries, from James Mitchell to George Shultz, have used intellect and presence to make themselves powers in the Cabinet, but Mrs. Dole has no such pretensions. She is a soldier, not a player.</p>
        <p>Adm. James Watkins</p>
        <p>Sec Energy</p>
        <p>He may be the least known of the surprisingly strong Cabinet members because he is (a) colorless, as befits a nuclear engineer who came up under Hyman Rickover's thumb, and (b)involved in the details of his department. One senator explained it this way: ''Half the Energy Department is devoted to secret atomic stuff, and he's the first I can remember to understand the national security end of that job.'' Other senators agree that Watkins is a helpful witness, particularly since some previous Secretaries didn't know why our nuclear facilities were falling apart.</p>
        <p>He worried many conservatives at first by saying he was ''aghast'' at the deterioration of the nuclear weapons stock; ''aghast'' is almost as liberal a codeword as ''appalled.'' But Watkins turned out to be crisp and confident, announcing recently he would make public studies of the environmental impact of modernizing our nuclear weapons plants.</p>
        <p>Although he is presiding over a slide into an unprecedented reliance on overseas oil, Watkins gets high marks from his colleagues for ''taking his duty seriously.'' Rank him with Kemp, Skinner and Hills as members of the Unexpectedly Influential Quartet.</p>
        <p>Carla A. Hills</p>
        <p>Trade Rep</p>
        <p>''Bob Mosbacher and I do not disagree on anything,'' she has insisted publicly, a reading of reality that will come as a surprise to the Japanese, who see her as having a far tougher approach to trade than the Commerce Secretary.</p>
        <p>Washington expected the old Carla Hills: a quiet Secretary of H.U.D. in the Ford Administration, a respectably serious woman lawyer. It got the new Carla Hills, a more confident, energetic Cabinet member and a negotiator ready to assert strongly the United States' interest into removing trade barriers. She is not well known nationally because the very mention of GATT causes eyes to glaze over -''Uruguay Round'' beats warm milk as a terrific soporific - but Mrs. Hills gave Mr. Bush a card to play at his Malta summit by supporting observer status for the Soviet Union at the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade. ''How are they ever going to learn if they can't watch?'' she asked, later attributing that sensible quote to the President.</p>
        <p>One of the rare power struggles then took place within the Bush Cabinet. Commerce, a cumbersome 35,000 person agency, fully expected to handle the new trade treaty with the Soviet Union, as it did during the Nixon detente. Mr. Mosbacher claimed special expertise in working with the Russians on removing nonstrategic trade sanctions. But the President ruled against his Texas chum and turned to the tougher-minded Mrs. Hills. The T.R. group - only 135 people - was jubilant, but Mrs. Hills took pains to deny a turf victory; Mosbacher gulped and took defeat graciously. That was typical; a person who sits in the Cabinet room says, ''Look - you either win the argument or you're shamed into shutting up.''</p>
        <p>How does Hills manage to expand her job? Merit evidently counts</p>
        <p>Lauro F. Cavazos</p>
        <p>Sec of Ed</p>
        <p>If the Cabinet were a solar system, Cavazos would be Pluto. The holdover from the waning Reagan years is considered, even by many educators, to be the captive of the National Education Association, and White House aides see him as the classic case of clientitis. At the ''education summit'' of the nation's governors, the former anatomy professor showed no muscle; Roger Porter, the President's domestic-policy man, kept the national role exhortative rather than financially supportive. The Education Secretary, with little personality or known philosophy and grumpy about the press, was paid no attention.</p>
        <p>As Interior Secretary Manuel Lujan Jr. gains from comparison with a predecessor, Cavazos suffers from succeeding Bill Bennett, now the drug czar: as Bennett was, and is, involved, confrontational and colorful, Cavazos is aloof, ameliorating and dull. White House aides are now working on a plan to resuscitate the Education Secretary; if this fails, an early departure can be expected.</p>
        <p>Dr. Louis W. Sullivan</p>
        <p>Secretary of Health and Human Services.</p>
        <p>Here is a man whose life is being saved by smoking. For over a year, he was a minor embarrassment to the Administration - from stumbling at his confirmation hearings over the abortion issue, to displaying a naivete about the politics of catastrophic insurance that saw his position publicly contradicted by the decisive Darman.</p>
        <p>But Sullivan was a longtime friend of Barbara Bush; he came across as a man of intelligence, dignity and political loyalty in a job that chews up stronger executives; and he was the only black in the Cabinet at a time when the previous Cabinet black, Samuel Pierce of H.U.D., was coming under heavy investigation. In these circumstances, few wanted to criticize the former medical school president as being overwhelmed by the scope of the department and not being a ''player.''</p>
        <p>Along came R. J. Reynolds with a cigarette aimed at sales to blacks. Dr. Sullivan was the natural one to object, and his pop at this sitting duck was magnified on national television; overnight, he was the hero to the lionizers of former Surgeon General C. Everett Koop. When the tobacco company backed off, the nonplayer won a pot at last; in a further stroke of fortune, another media plan for ''targeting,'' or selling to, young women was leaked, and Sullivan was able to squeeze the same grapes again. The position did not cost the Government a nickel and Dr. Sullivan has been rehabilitated. He is still not a player but he is no longer an embarrassment.</p>
        <p>Will he ever be able to manage the monster of Medicare cost and quality, or put his own stamp on a staff that was chosen for him? ''You have to be careful when you ask somebody to clean out the cobwebs here at H.H.S.,'' says a longtime bureaucrat, ''it's the cobwebs that hold the place together.''</p>
        <p>Manuel Lujan Jr.</p>
        <p>Sec Interior.</p>
        <p>If Cavazos were Pluto in this solar system, Manny Lujan would be Uranus, one planet closer in, seldom seen and trying to make it into the Outer Circle.</p>
        <p>Lujan is a twofer: both a Western politician (New Mexico) and an Hispanic-American. The compliment usually left-handed him is: ''He's not Jim Watt.'' As expected, he plumps for offshore oil development but tries hard to avoid offending environmentalists. Mr. Bush has decided that the restraint on William Reilly, E.P.A. director and the in-house conservationist, will be in the more capable hands of John Sununu.</p>
        <p>President Bush seeks to avoid the customary bloodletting between conservationists and developers by taking the combativeness out of Interior (which supports offshore oil development) and giving Cabinet status to Reilly's E.P.A. (which is all-out for conservation). In this way, each constituency will have its advocate at the table, but with teamwork-minded Lujan and Reilly, the jousting will be gentlemanly.</p>
        <p>When the President was to give a speech at a conference concerned with global warming, Reilly submitted a draft speech that was eviscerated by Sununu, who decried ''a little tendency by some of the faceless bureaucrats on the environmental side to try and create a policy in this country that cuts off our use of coal, oil and natural gas.'' That's the sort of rhetoric we would expect from the Interior Secretary. Not in the Bush Cabinet; the voice occasionally heard is the voice of Lujan, but the hand is the hand of Sununu.</p>
        <p>James A. Baker 3d</p>
        <p>Sec State.</p>
        <p>Baker, the most enigmatic member of the Cabinet, occupies the traditional seat of honor to the President's right.</p>
        <p>Highly regarded as President Reagan's chief of staff, he was considered only an average Treasury Secretary. Originally called Joe Cool and Mr. Smoothie, he recently stepped out of character to tell a prayer breakfast how deeply religious he has become, which charitable souls took at face value and which cynics - asking, ''How many k's in this Jim Baker?'' - saw as an effort to win religious-right support. With a reputation for icy competence, he stunned Washington by lying unnecessarily on national television to conceal the first trip of Presidential envoys to Beijing after the Tienanmen Square massacre; he admitted later he should have ''no-commented.''</p>
        <p>In Moscow, he won points by adroitly parrying hostile questioning by Soviet legislators, but lost points by ineptly ad-libbing about Germany's ''continued membership in or association with NATO'' -as if to open the way out of NATO and toward neutrality. He soon disavowed the errant phrase, but foreign ministers are not supposed to make such mistakes.</p>
        <p>Baker operates within a closed circle at State, dealing with his portable cartridge of loyal campaign-to-government aides, to the consternation of foreign-service officers who mistakenly thought the appointment of their own Lawrence Eagleburger as deputy would provide a bridge of access.</p>
        <p>However, Eagleburger's route to the President's ear is not through his boss, Baker, but through his longtime fellow-toiler in the Kissinger vineyards, Brent Scowcroft, the national security adviser. Jim Baker has succeeded in dominating the team called ''Scowgleburger.'' At Cabinet meetings, Scowcroft, who like all aides except Sununu sits against the wall, is more a trusted counselor than a central operator, more genuine adviser than player at the power table. That suits the President and delights the Secretary of State. Baker likes to exercise his power through others. To put the chill of a possible loss of aid into the Israelis, the Secretary of State induced Bob Dole, the Senate majority leader, to suggest taking aid from Israel and Egypt and giving it to Eastern Europe; Baker then publicly agreed with Dole's trial balloon. In the same way, Baker watched as the C.I.A. chief, Webster, took the wind out of the Defense Secretary's sails (as described in the section on Cheney so long ago) in the halls of Congress, supposedly Cheney's turf. Baker used the occasion of reviewing a speech by Robert Gates, Scowcroft's deputy at the National Security Council, to slap down the hard-liners within the Administration who are not convinced that the Soviet threat has ended; by forcing Gates to cancel his speech, Baker signaled what the policy was and who was in total command.</p>
        <p>Longtime closeness to Mr. Bush also gives him the high-level bureaucratic security that comes only when nobody doubts you have the Presidential ear. Baker is to Bush as Darman is to Baker: the aide and protege is now almost on his own, but is driven to deference by age and habit and position in the pecking order. Baker, who ranged the whole political world as Reagan chief of staff, now works in a circumscribed foreign-affairs domain, but his dominance of the N.S.C. staff is tempered by the President's abiding interest in his area.</p>
        <p>A President with Bush's foreign experience is always ''his own'' Secretary of State; according to journalistic confidants of Mr. Baker, of whom I am not one, the President's decision to send emissaries to Beijing after the massacre went against the Secretary's advice. (This leak of a Baker background manipulation will be denied now, but confirmed in memoirs in a few years.) Perhaps that's why Baker enjoys traveling. Overseas, spin-doctoring a planeload of reporters, the man identified obliquely as ''a senior official traveling on the Secretary's plane'' is the boss.</p>
        <p>HOW DOES THIS CABINET WORKJU as a group? Certain strains are built in, as in State and Defense, but the age of clashes between Shultz and Weinberger is gone; Baker has established his dominance over Cheney. Some ideology is discussed - Kemp and Brady will disagree about tax cuts and growth - but this is generally a pack of moderates.</p>
        <p>Where's a potential President among these Bush appointees? Richard Nixon used to say that every Cabinet needed one future president in it, pointing disconcertingly to Coolidge's cabinet with Commerce Secretary Herbert Hoover (Nixon thought John Connally was to be his 1976 successor). Jim Baker probably harbors Oval Office hopes, but he cannot become Bush's V.P. (both men are from the same state, and the Constitution requires a ticket from different states); Baker lost his only bid for elective office in Texas; in 1994, a Democratic Senate seat opens up, but Lloyd Bentsen will be no pushover. Dick Thornburgh, a successful Governor, seemed possible a year ago but no longer; Jack Kemp is finding constituencies hitherto unknown to Republicans, is seasoning as an administrator and may emerge in 1996 at age 60.</p>
        <p>Is this a ''strong'' Cabinet? If you take that to mean a Ministry of All the Talents, as in Lord Grenville's era almost two centuries ago, no; says one of the Bush loyalists candidly, ''Surprising we're doing so well, given the lineup.''</p>
        <p>If you mean, ''Is this a Cabinet that carries out the President's philosophy?'' the answer is that its members, with a few exceptions, carry out his pragmatism, embody his prudence, and follow all the marching orders save the first: to ''Think big.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
