<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lifestyle;   Portable Shade Is Big on the Beach</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="373878"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEACHES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUNBURN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SKIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UMBRELLAS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JONES BEACH STATE PARK</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARRON, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Sunburn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sunburn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DE1E3CF936A3575BC0A966958260" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lifestyle;   Portable Shade Is Big on the Beach</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BARRON, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The days when the ''Doonesbury'' comic strip lampooned tanning contests with day-to-day coverage of the ''George Hamilton Pro-Am Celebrity Cocoa Butter Open'' seem to be over. So are the days of ''Let the Sunshine In,'' which may or may not be why some beaches now look like variegated mushroom fields of umbrellas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The days when the ''Doonesbury'' comic strip lampooned tanning contests with day-to-day coverage of the ''George Hamilton Pro-Am Celebrity Cocoa Butter Open'' seem to be over. So are the days of ''Let the Sunshine In,'' which may or may not be why some beaches now look like variegated mushroom fields of umbrellas.</p>
        <p>The days when the ''Doonesbury'' comic strip lampooned tanning contests with day-to-day coverage of the ''George Hamilton Pro-Am Celebrity Cocoa Butter Open'' seem to be over. So are the days of ''Let the Sunshine In,'' which may or may not be why some beaches now look like variegated mushroom fields of umbrellas.</p>
        <p>People who once thought nothing of acquiring lobsterlike coloring are crowding beneath umbrellas. ''The only thing better is sun block with an S.P.F. of about a zillion,'' said a pale-faced woman at Pennsylvania Station in New York on Friday morning, lugging a beach umbrella and waiting for a train to the Hamptons.</p>
        <p>These are not just flimsy parasols. They are big, and getting bigger.</p>
        <p>One wholesaler, the Ivy Mar Company of Central Islip, L.I., is so confident that the trend is toward larger umbrellas that it plans to introduce an 84-inch model next season.</p>
        <p>''The bigger the umbrella, the more protection from the sun,'' said the company's sales manager, Glenn DeBaere. ''It's our gut feeling that's what people want.''</p>
        <p>Orders on the Rise</p>
        <p>For now, the company offers a 48-inch nylon umbrella that can be clamped onto a beach chair ($4.99 at retail stores) and a 72-incher with a pole that pokes into the sand ($17.99). Mr. DeBaere estimated that orders were up 25 percent from last year, largely, he said, because of concern about too much sun.</p>
        <p>For retailers, beach umbrellas have been near sellouts this season. At the Fortunoff department store in Westbury, L.I., Beth Siegel, the vice president of sales promotion, said, ''Umbrellas have been real stars in this year's outdoor furniture sales.''</p>
        <p>But the best sellers of all, she said, have been see-through patio umbrellas. They are made of a new translucent fabric that is said to screen out harmful ultraviolet rays. Whether people can lug the umbrellas to the beach is another matter. ''This is an eight-and-a-half-foot umbrella,'' Ms. Siegel said. ''It's not what you would call easily portable. It needs a base. It's really for the backyard.'' Who's Counting? Zip Jack Industries in Elmsford, N.Y., makes easier-to-carry beach umbrellas using the ray-blocking material. Manny Dubinsky, the president of Zip Jack and a veteran of decades in the umbrella business, said the big ones had made a transition from outdoor cafes to beaches.</p>
        <p>But statistics are hard to come by. The umbrella industry's trade group went out of business several years ago, and the Suntanning Association for Education in Frederick, Md., said it had no data on umbrellas.</p>
        <p>''Our expertise is in indoor tanning, as opposed to outdoor,'' said Joyce Burdette, the executive director. ''I can make the general statement that people are more cautious than they used to be and getting their ultraviolet exposure in moderation, as opposed to just going out and spending hours and hours in the sun and getting all red.''</p>
        <p>On beaches on eastern Long Island last week, some people under umbrellas insisted that the sun was hotter than it used to be. The ozone layer is being depleted, they said, and weather patterns are changing. Everyone was wearing suntan lotion and knew the S.P.F., or sun protection factor.</p>
        <p>Looking pale, but protected by S.P.F. 29, Paul Croser of Westhampton, L.I., arrived at a beach near his home with a book and a small patio umbrella tucked beneath his arm. The book was nice, he said. The umbrella was a necessity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Croser, 31 years old, who works nights, said he wanted to be outdoors but was concerned about the sun. ''I know exposure isn't good as far as the long-range chance of getting skin cancer,'' he said. ''Short term, I have to worry about blisters.'' Robert and Amalia Molineaux of Floral Park, L.I., sat in the sun at the Westhampton beach wearing S.P.F. 4. But their 8-month-old son was playing beneath a $17.99 Ivy Mar umbrella they had bought at a drugstore on the way to the beach.</p>
        <p>Mr. Molineaux, an advertising consultant who never used to give much thought to solar overexposure, said he was convinced that the sun was hotter than when he was a child. ''If I can notice that much of a change in my lifetime,'' he said, ''that's really scary.''</p>
        <p>Half a mile down the beach, Debra Wilcox, a 30-year-old horse trainer from Westhampton, was packing up her umbrella. ''Ever since I realized the sun was so bad I've wanted to stay out of it,'' she said.</p>
        <p>And the view from the lifeguard's chair? Joseph W. Dooley Sr. has been looking down on overexposed sunbathers and so-so swimmers at the Smith Point Park on Fire Island since 1948. There are umbrellas these days, he said, but the really big news is that suntan lotion now comes with an S.P.F. of 45.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
