<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critics Say Draft Report on Climate Shift Ignores Urgency of Problem</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="358152"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEAT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDA143AF931A35755C0A966958260" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critics Say Draft Report on Climate Shift Ignores Urgency of Problem</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A draft report by an American-led policy group of the United Nations has proposed international measures to cope with global warming caused by pollution, but it calls for no specific goals or timetables for action.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A draft report by an American-led policy group of the United Nations has proposed international measures to cope with global warming caused by pollution, but it calls for no specific goals or timetables for action.</p>
        <p>A draft report by an American-led policy group of the United Nations has proposed international measures to cope with global warming caused by pollution, but it calls for no specific goals or timetables for action.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists and some European diplomats who have seen a summary of the report, which was prepared by American officials, complained that its recommendations did not reflect the urgency evident in a report on scientific knowledge about global warming.</p>
        <p>That report, prepared by a British-led panel and released last week by another United Nations panel, , found that unless the emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases that are trapping heat from the sun are immediately cut by more than 60 percent, global temperatures would rise sharply in the next century with unforeseeable consequences for humans.</p>
        <p>The draft policy report by the American-led panel calls for a general international treaty to address global warming, but none of the signers would be obligated to take specific action. Other recommendations are to use energy more efficiently, to strengthen existing institutions that could address the climate change issue, and to accumulate more information on scientific, technical and economic implications of the problem. #3 Panels Examine Problem Three United Nations-sponsored working groups are gathering information to help nations decide what to do about global warming. The British-led panel completed its report last week. A Soviet-led group studying potential effects of global warming is still working on its report. The American-led group was assigned to examine strategies for dealing with the problem.</p>
        <p>The information provided by the three groups is intended to form the basis of further international action to deal with the problem. An international conference will be held in Geneva this November to plan the next steps.</p>
        <p>The policy group's recommendations generally parallel the Bush Administration's approach to the problem. The Administration wants to delay specific international action, like mandatory reduction of carbon dioxide and other pollutants, and to focus on more study of the scientific and economic implications of the shift in climate.</p>
        <p>European governments are expected to press for a stronger report when the members of the American-led working group meet in Geneva next week to prepare its final report, said an official in the Netherlands Embassy here.</p>
        <p>The official said Western European governments were concerned that the policy summary prepared by the United States put more emphasis on uncertainties than was warranted by the findings of subcommittees that did the research for the report. But he said that his government could not comment officially on the report because it was still in draft form. #2 Panels at Odds Daniel Lashof, a global warming expert for the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental group, said ''there is a real disconnect'' between the recommendations of the science panel and the draft report by the working group on policy responses. He said the science panel ''made a strong statement about the science and the need for at least a 60 percent reduction in carbon dioxide, while the policy group did not even analyze the policy measures needed to reach that reduction.''</p>
        <p>Frederick M. Bernthal, deputy director of the National Science Foundation and chairman of the policy working group, did not respond to several telephone calls over the last two days.</p>
        <p>The draft report on policy options was prepared by the Response Strategies Working Group, one of three working groups that make up the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, which was created in 1988 by the United Nations Environmental Program and the World Meteorological Organization, another United Nations organization.</p>
        <p>The response strategies working group identified a number of measures that it said would be ''particularly important and feasible in the short term.''</p>
        <p>It suggested the development of a ''framework convention,'' or general treaty on climate change, without specifying any particular obligations or deadlines for reducing the pollution that is accumulating in the atmosphere and trapping radiation from the sun in a phenomenon known as the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>It proposed carrying out measures that ''are already economically and socially justifiable in their own right and which also provide benefits from a climate change standpoint.'' Such measures would include increased energy efficiency and improved use of forests and other natural resources.</p>
        <p>It urged increased research into scientific, technical and economic uncertainties about the magnitude, time and regional effects of global warming; potential policies to lessen its impact, and measures to adjust to a warmer earth when and if that happens. it Unlike the Bush Administration, several Western European countries have concluded that enough is known about the potential dangers to warrant substantial countermeasures, including stabilizing and reducing emissions of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
