<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>California Pushing the Limits With Environmental Plan</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="347600"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFERENDUMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PESTICIDES AND PESTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OFFSHORE EXPLORATION AND INSTALLATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">REINHOLD, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reserves (Natural Resources)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DE1039F934A15757C0A966958260" item-length="1122" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>California Pushing the Limits With Environmental Plan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT REINHOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REINHOLD, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, April 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The stage was set today for one of the toughest national political battles of 1990, drawing the environmental movement directly into hardball politics over a measure that would impose on California the most sweeping controls in the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The stage was set today for one of the toughest national political battles of 1990, drawing the environmental movement directly into hardball politics over a measure that would impose on California the most sweeping controls in the country.</p>
        <p>The stage was set today for one of the toughest national political battles of 1990, drawing the environmental movement directly into hardball politics over a measure that would impose on California the most sweeping controls in the country.</p>
        <p>A coalition of environmental groups turned in 800,000 signatures, more than enough to place a voter-initiated referendum on the November ballot.</p>
        <p>The initiative would, among other things, ban 19 cancer-causing pesticides still in wide use, drastically reduce emission of artificial gases that trap and retain heat from the sun, curtail clearing of forests, ban offshore oil drilling except in national emergencies and create an elected state environmental advocate to enforce the law.</p>
        <p>The measure has stirred nationwide unease among agricultural, chemical, logging and other interests, who are mounting a multimillion-dollar campaign to defeat it and to pass competing initiatives to override it lest the other states follow California's lead. But given the mounting public concern about the environment, the Big Green initiative, as its backers have named it, is considered likely to pass.</p>
        <p>Votes Are Involved</p>
        <p>''There's no way we can lose,'' the initiative's campaign manager, Bob Mulholland, said today. ''This is a done deal. We can't lose unless there's an earthquake that stops California.''</p>
        <p>Much more than the environment is at stake. The measure has been deeply enmeshed in the race for Governor as candidates have jockeyed for the powerful environmental vote.</p>
        <p>The measure was endorsed early on by State Attorney General John K. Van de Kamp, who faces the former Mayor of San Francisco, Dianne Feinstein, in the Democratic primary on June 5. After months of hesitation, Mrs. Feinstein, who had feared losing support in the agricultural Central Valley, endorsed the measure on Sunday, Earth Day.</p>
        <p>That leaves the certain Republican nominee, Senator Pete Wilson, a moderate with a pro-environment record, in the position of seeming to be against something widely perceived as akin to motherhood. He says he opposes the measure because it takes environmental authority away from the Governor.</p>
        <p>Critics of the measure say it would grievously injure the state's billion-dollar agriculture, aerospace and electronics industries, cause food prices to rise nationally and bring substantial increases in gasoline taxes, electricity rates and unemployment. They have tried to tarnish it by tagging it the ''Hayden initiative'' after Assemblyman Tom Hayden, the Democrat from Santa Monica who largely wrote the measure and who has a long association with radical and liberal causes.</p>
        <p>Interest in New Post</p>
        <p>Mr. Hayden is thought to be interested in running for the post of environmental advocate.</p>
        <p>The measure, the California Environmental Protection Act of 1990, touches on food safety, global warming from pollution, oceans, beaches and forests. Environmentalists say it is necessary to go directly to the voters because the California Legislature is so beholden to special interests that legislative remedies are impossible.</p>
        <p>The measure includes these major elements:</p>
        <p>* All pesticides judged by the state to cause cancer or reproductive damage are phased out in foods by 1996. Food produced out-of-state is banned from sale if even the slightest residue of such chemicals is detected.</p>
        <p>* Allowable residues of other pesticides are reduced to levels considered safe for children. Exposure of farmworkers to pesticides would be reduced to the lowest achievable levels.</p>
        <p>* Emissions of carbon dioxide, believed to add to global warming, are reduced by 20 percent by the year 2000 and 40 percent by 2010.</p>
        <p>* Steps to cut the emission of chlorofluorocarbons and other industrial chemicals believed to damage the earth's protective ozone layer. By 1995, the sale of cars using these chemicals in air conditioners is banned.</p>
        <p>* Oil drilling within three miles of the coast is forbidden unless the President declares a national emergency.</p>
        <p>* Creation of an oil-spill prevention plan, including a $500 million prevention and cleanup fund established with a fee of 25 cents a barrel paid by companies moving oil through California waters.</p>
        <p>* New controls on public sewage discharges and stricter health standards for beach waters and seafood.</p>
        <p>Although the measures do not address all of California's environmental problems, Albert H. Meyerhoff of the Natural Resources Defense Council said they represented the most comprehensive environmental law ever proposed.</p>
        <p>''It will not by itself save the planet,'' Mr. Meyerhoff said. ''It will save this corner of it.''</p>
        <p>Proponents say they expect to spend as much as $3 million to pass it.</p>
        <p>To fight the measure, the California Chamber of Commerce and the pesticide industry are mounting a campaign that opponents assert will cost $16 million. They have employed the political consulting firm Woodward &amp; McDowell of Burlingame, Calif. Jack S. McDowell, a partner in the firm, said the initiative was scientifically flawed in that it ignores the possibility that chemical residues at extremely low levels may not be hazardous to health.</p>
        <p>According to a preliminary study for industry by Spectrum Economics Inc. of San Francisco, the initiative would have devastating economic consequences for the state. The study said it would increase gasoline prices by 25 to 50 cents a gallon, raise electricity rates by more than 20 percent, force food processors, supermarkets, restaurants and shippers to spend millions of dollars to replace refrigeration units, cost one million jobs by the year 2000 and put California businesses at a competitive disadvantage.</p>
        <p>Competing Measure on the Way</p>
        <p>Food growers and processors have also joined to fight the initiative by forming Californians for Responsible Food Laws. They are gathering signatures for a competing measure, which they call the Consumer Pesticide Enforcement Act for Food, Water, and Worker Safety. That measure would double the amount of testing of fresh fruits and vegetables and establish a fund to find means of reducing pesticide use, but that sets less stringent standards.</p>
        <p>Lee Stitzenberger, campaign director of the growers' measure, said the approach was ''driven by science'' to establish safe risk levels for pesticide use. If the growers' measure gets more votes than the environmental initiative, it will override the pesticide provisions addressed in ''Big Green.''</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the Wilson campaign said that while Mr. Wilson approved of many parts of the environmentalists' measure, he thought environmental responsibility should remain with the Governor. But critics maintain that Mr. Wilson is beholden to the state's agricultural and chemical interests.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
