<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. VIEW PREVAILS AT CLIMATE PARLEY</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="399083"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMONS, MARLISE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DB153CF93BA35752C1A966958260" item-length="883" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. VIEW PREVAILS AT CLIMATE PARLEY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMONS, MARLISE</byline>
      <dateline>GENEVA, Nov. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>United States negotiators today turned aside an effort to set specific targets for wealthy countries to reduce emissions of carbon dioxide, which is widely expected to cause a dangerous heating of the global atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Instead, the 135 nations represented at the World Climate Conference ending here today adopted a declaration that urges countries to set targets, national programs or strategies to limit so-called greenhouse gases like carbon dioxide, but avoided further details.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>United States negotiators today turned aside an effort to set specific targets for wealthy countries to reduce emissions of carbon dioxide, which is widely expected to cause a dangerous heating of the global atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Instead, the 135 nations represented at the World Climate Conference ending here today adopted a declaration that urges countries to set targets, national programs or strategies to limit so-called greenhouse gases like carbon dioxide, but avoided further details.</p>
        <p>Such gases are known to trap heat in the atmosphere, and their concentrations are growing. Many scientists expect that this will cause the global climate to warm substantially, but they disagree whether this has yet been demonstrated.</p>
        <p>Despite pleas from scientists and politicians at the conference, two of the world's largest producers of the gas, the United States and the Soviet Union, refused to commit themselves now to cutting their output of carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>But the 10-day conference had other, immediate effects: it galvanized rich nations besides the United States into pledging cutbacks in their own carbon dioxide production, thereby putting new pressure on Washington.</p>
        <p>The pledges will mean higher costs in the near future for cars, heat and electricity, and a rush to produce more efficient machines and appliances. Japan, Canada, Australia and New Zealand and 18 European nations have announced such plans to cut back carbon dioxide.  New Environmental Market</p>
        <p>The gathering also served to confirm that industries in the world's two strongest economies have been reading the trends correctly: companies in Japan and Germany are already racing to produce technology to match environmental concerns. Politicians and industry representatives from both nations said environmental policies are creating enormous new economic opportunities.</p>
        <p>The Geneva meeting, held under the auspices of the World Meteorological Organization and the United Nations Environment Program, is a stage in the work toward a global convention on addressing climate change.</p>
        <p>Although formal negotiations for the treaty do not begin in Washington until Febrruary, some industrial nations pushed here for strong language with specific targets applying to rich countries, who jointly account for 75 percent of the world's carbon dioxide, most of them by burning fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>The United States succeeded in watering down key portions of the 30-point document adopted by consensus today. United States negotiators led an effort to include wording that emphasized the scientific uncertainties surrounding global warming and that evaded a commitment to channel new technology to protect the environment at almost no cost to poor nations.</p>
        <p>The United States supporters most in evidence were oil exporters like Saudi Arabia, Venezuela and the Soviet Union, who like Washington argued that not enough was known to act now on climate change. Western negotiators had expected no pledges from the Soviet Union, the largest producer of carbon dioxide after the United States; its inefficient industries and economy would be unable to afford the investment in cutting back pollution.  China Opposes Cutbacks</p>
        <p>China, another large polluter, said it could make no cutbacks because that would mean it could not industrialize. "We need not cut back because our per capita emissions are very low," said a delegate. "An American uses 18 times more energy than a Chinese."</p>
        <p>John Knauss, director of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, who led the United States delegation, said Washington had refused to set targets because "it does not believe in them," adding: "It's as simple as that. We are not prepared to guarantee our projections."</p>
        <p>European governments agree that by raising taxes and using energy more efficiently they can cut back or reverse close to 20 percent of their carbon dioxide emissions over the next 10 years without impairing economic growth. Japan and other nations concur. But they concede that cuts beyond this target will become more difficult.</p>
        <p>American officials here, however, questioned the European targets, which they characterized as political goals not easy to put into effect. European officials at the conference argued that the European Community's common strategy to cut pollution was prepared not just by environmental ministers, but also with energy ministers.</p>
        <p>In Italy, Germany, the Netherlands and Great Britain, parliaments have already approved the program to cut carbon emissions. The agreement reached by European Community countries last week is binding, and all members are expected to submit their by the end of this year.</p>
        <p>The intense haggling over the conference declaration, which lasted more than five days, has given a glimpse of how difficult it will be to reach an international accord on global warming. Many developing nations here fought against language that committed them to curbing population growth. Nations with tropical forests insisted on complete sovereignty.</p>
        <p>As experts here last week debated scenarios of a world 50 years from now, delegates from African and Asian countries said they were frustrated because, they said, more study should be focused on dealing with extreme climate variations causing floods and droughts today.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
