<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE U.S: STILL ON ITS FEET</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="343611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BESCHLOSS, MICHAEL R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NYE, JOSEPH S JR</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BOUND TO LEAD (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DD1E3AF936A25757C0A966958260" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE U.S: STILL ON ITS FEET</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL R. BESCHLOSS; Michael R. Beschloss is the author of ''Kennedy and Roosevelt: The Uneasy Alliance'' and ''Mayday: Eisenhower, Khrushchev and the U-2 Affair.''</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BESCHLOSS, MICHAEL R</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>BOUND TO LEAD</p>
        <p>The Changing Nature of American Power.</p>
        <p>By Joseph S. Nye Jr.</p>
        <p>307 pp. New York: Basic Books. $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>BOUND TO LEAD</p>
        <p>The Changing Nature of American Power.</p>
        <p>By Joseph S. Nye Jr.</p>
        <p>307 pp. New York: Basic Books. $19.95.</p>
        <p>BOUND TO LEAD</p>
        <p>The Changing Nature of American Power.</p>
        <p>By Joseph S. Nye Jr.</p>
        <p>307 pp. New York: Basic Books. $19.95.</p>
        <p>No postwar Presidential candidate has ever been defeated for railing against the country's decline. In 1960, John F. Kennedy declared, ''This nation in 1965 will still be the greatest, but will it still be the most powerful? . . . We are falling behind - behind in our schedules, behind in our needs, behind the Russians in our rate of progress.'' In 1970, President Richard Nixon warned against America's becoming a ''pitiful, helpless giant'' and a ''second-rate power.'' In 1980, Ronald Reagan ran for President under the slogan ''Let's Make America Great Again.''</p>
        <p>Each of these assertions turned out to have its irony. After campaigning on the need to restore United States nuclear superiority, Kennedy, as President, not only discovered that the nation had never lost its predominance, but moved toward the view that world peace would be better served by strategic parity with the Soviet Union. Mr. Nixon was the first postwar President to concede in public that the United States lived in a multipolar world. And the cost of Mr. Reagan's military buildup was the vast budget deficit that undermines American economic influence today.</p>
        <p>The Harvard political scientist Samuel P. Huntington has observed that the public discussion of American decline often provides ''better indications of American psychology than of American power.'' Allowing this debate to be trivialized and distorted by emotion ill serves the nation's leaders, especially those who are the gravest offenders. This is why Joseph S. Nye Jr.'s corrective, ''Bound to Lead,'' is welcome.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nye, the Ford Foundation Professor of International Security at Harvard, differs with Paul Kennedy's contention in ''The Rise and Fall of the Great Powers'' that the United States shows the symptoms of imperial exhaustion, like Philip II's Spain and Nicholas II's Russia. Mr. Nye allows that since the end of World War II, the American share of global product has slipped from roughly one-third to roughly one-fifth. But he calls this a ''return to normal'' from an artificial dominance over countries that had been invaded and bombed and needed to rebuild. He adds that the figure has remained stable since the early 1970's. Arguing against the thesis of military overcommitment, he notes that the ratio of the United States' defense burden to its share of world product is actually lower now than in the 1950's.</p>
        <p>Among the countries of the world, he writes, only the United States is predominant in all of the traditional arsenals of power - territory and population, military might, economic vitality, technology. The country profits as well from less tangible resources, such as the international appeal of its culture and language; its attractiveness and openness to immigrants, foreign students and investors; its influence as a part of multinational institutions and alliances.</p>
        <p>Are there any immediate challengers? Not the Soviet Union, with its economic, technological, political and ideological afflictions. Not China, with its unpredictable politics and still-backward economy. Not Japan, unless a very different political leadership is allowed to divert that country's immense technological and economic power into the building of a world-class military force. Not Europe, unless the one-market economic system that is to be established in 1992 leads to the much more difficult achievement of political integration. (Germany's movement toward reunification occurred too late for Mr. Nye to consider it as a separate case, but presumably that development has not caused him to alter his overall conclusions.) The end of the cold war, the spread of technology, rising nationalism in weak states and other fundamental changes are reshuffling the cards of world power. Not surprisingly, Mr. Nye proposes that the United States exercise leadership by restoring its domestic economic strength, preserving the ideal of an open world economy (without harming long-term American interests), helping to devise a new global balance of military power and making greater use of multinational organizations to overcome international problems like drugs, AIDS and global warming.</p>
        <p>Displaying the sensible use of history that informs his book, Mr. Nye notes the cautionary lesson of the 19th century and the 1930's: ''If the strongest state does not lead, the prospects for instability increase.'' But the United States may be unable to mobilize its resources fully in order to provide that leadership. Mr. Nye cites the disappointing recent record of American productivity, savings, education, research and development. He also laments the diffusion of domestic political power - reflected in the weakness of political parties and the strength of interest groups, among other elements. Such factors make more difficult the coherent and expeditious decision making that would help to maximize the nation's influence in the world.</p>
        <p>This places the burden on whoever is President to have the courage and political skill to lead - to warn Congress and the people against protectionism, sharp restrictions on immigration and foreign aid, and other measures that would reduce American global power.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nye is not indifferent to who is President. He has in the past provided foreign policy advice to Democratic candidates, including Michael S. Dukakis in the 1988 campaign. If a Democrat reaches the White House in the not-too-distant future, Mr. Nye may well be at his side, urging the prescriptions outlined in this volume.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
