<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Conferees Back Stiff Curbs on Chemical Emissions</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="392672"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAZARDOUS AND TOXIC SUBSTANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DC143BF93BA25753C1A966958260" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Conferees Back Stiff Curbs on Chemical Emissions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Leaders of the House-Senate conference committee that is rewriting the Clean Air Act moved a step closer to a final package today when they agreed on new requirements for reducing emissions of toxic chemicals from chemical plants, coke ovens, incinerators and other industrial polluters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Leaders of the House-Senate conference committee that is rewriting the Clean Air Act moved a step closer to a final package today when they agreed on new requirements for reducing emissions of toxic chemicals from chemical plants, coke ovens, incinerators and other industrial polluters.</p>
        <p>Leaders of the House-Senate conference committee that is rewriting the Clean Air Act moved a step closer to a final package today when they agreed on new requirements for reducing emissions of toxic chemicals from chemical plants, coke ovens, incinerators and other industrial polluters.</p>
        <p>The latest action means that rules for controlling acid rain and reducing air pollution in national parks are the only important issues that remain unresolved by the conferees.</p>
        <p>The agreement announced today calls for an array of mechanical and technical actions that industrial plants and some private businesses, like dry cleaners, must take to reduce emissions of toxic chemicals that the Government contends cause cancer. The provisions are intended to result in a 90 percent reduction of pollution from 189 substances by the turn of the century, said staff members working on the legislation.</p>
        <p>Durenberger Hails Move</p>
        <p>''It's a major step,'' said Senator Dave Durenberger, Republican of Minnesota, one of the conferees. ''It's the first time we've dealt with cancer-causing chemicals.''</p>
        <p>The agreement to control emissions of toxic substances would broaden the authority of the Environmental Protection Agency to regulate thousands of businesses and hundreds of pollutants that have never before come under Government restrictions.</p>
        <p>Roughly 12,000 incinerators in the nation, for instance, will be required to control emissions of the pollutants that the Government considers most hazardous.</p>
        <p>Paint shops, machining businesses and other small industrial plants that use some 30 toxic solvents will be required to change materials or install equipment to control emissions.</p>
        <p>One of the most difficult obstacles the conferees overcame was regulating toxic chemicals emitted in the baking of coal into coke for making steel. The agreement today will require 30 steel plants around the country to install modern pollution control equipment and take other actions to upgrade coke ovens by 1998 to reduce toxic emissions to levels attained by the best new coke ovens.</p>
        <p>No New Curbs on Mercury</p>
        <p>But the conferees bowed to pressure from the nation's electric utility industry and took no action to require additional controls on emissions of mercury and other toxic chemicals from coal-burning power plants in the Great Lakes region. Emissions of mercury produced by the burning of coal from electric power plants have been identified in several scientific studies as a primary cause of water pollution and contamination in fish in the Great Lakes and throughout the upper Middle West.</p>
        <p>Representative Gerry Sikorski, Democrat of Minnesota, proposed more stringent regulation of toxic emissions from all industrial plants in the Great Lakes region, but the conferees exempted power plants from the stricter regulation. They decided to direct the Environmental Protection Agency to conduct another study of toxic pollution of the Great Lakes to determine whether additional regulation of power plants is necessary.</p>
        <p>One novel section of the agreement calls for a new independent safety agency to be established to investigate chemical accidents. Such a new Chemical Safety Board, modeled after the National Transportation Safety Board, which investigates transportation accidents, will have teams of inspectors ready to be dispatched to the scene of chemical accidents to determine their causes. In addition, the E.P.A. will require industrial plants to prepare formal safety reviews that are available to the public. The E.P.A. will also be authorized to set new safety standards at chemical plants and other industries where bulk amounts of toxic chemicals are used.</p>
        <p>''Hundreds of people have died in the past decade in chemical accidents and this bill will go a long way to stopping those accidents,'' said David D. Doniger, a senior lawyer in Washington for the Natural Resources Defense Council, a national environmental group based in New York.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
