<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Robots Transform Coal Mining</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="324605"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROBOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRODUCTIVITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINES AND MINING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Productivity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Machinery and Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DE173DF93BA35751C0A966958260" item-length="1369" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Robots Transform Coal Mining</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>WANA, W.Va.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The four-inch carbide-steel claws of a screaming yellow robot tore relentlessly at the coal seam 1,000 feet below the surface, digging enough in 30 seconds to meet the electric needs of a typical suburban house for a year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The four-inch carbide-steel claws of a screaming yellow robot tore relentlessly at the coal seam 1,000 feet below the surface, digging enough in 30 seconds to meet the electric needs of a typical suburban house for a year.</p>
        <p>The four-inch carbide-steel claws of a screaming yellow robot tore relentlessly at the coal seam 1,000 feet below the surface, digging enough in 30 seconds to meet the electric needs of a typical suburban house for a year.</p>
        <p>The robot's human master, old enough to remember when miners used picks and shovels and loaded coal into carts drawn by dogs, strolled beside, periodically pushing buttons on support equipment.</p>
        <p>Coal mining, an unglamorous business known mostly for accidents and bitter strikes, is going high tech, and the resulting productivity gains are important for a nation that is using up its other fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>The country's deposits of coal are expected to last more than a century, while oil reserves will last only 10 years at current rates of production, assuming no more oil is found. Gas reserves are also more limited than coal supplies. As oil and gas are used up, finding and extracting them become more expensive; by contrast, because of technical advances like the robot, the cost of digging coal is falling. Thus, over the long term, the price gap between coal and oil and gas will probably grow, and coal could become an even more important energy resource.</p>
        <p>A New Mining Method</p>
        <p>The robot here, in the Consolidation Coal Company's Blacksville No. 2 mine, 700 to 1,400 feet under the Mason-Dixon line, is perhaps the most advanced in the country. It is but one recent improvement in a highly automated technique called longwall mining, in which coal is removed not by tunneling like a worm through an apple, leaving more of the target than is removed, but by methodically shuttling back and forth across the width of the deposit and devouring nearly everything.</p>
        <p>Longwall mining has been around for decades but mine operators have recently made the technique far more efficient. The method can now extract about 75 percent of the available coal, compared with 50 percent for conventional mining, which is done largely with machines that dig tunnels. Moreover, the coal can be recovered far more inexpensively.</p>
        <p>While coal has been hailed as the nation's energy savior since the 1973 Arab oil embargo, the cost of oil has not risen enough to make coal a good substitute beyond the power plant, where it is burned to produce electricity. Cutting the cost of coal production is a small step toward wider use. When costs justify it, coal can even substitute for gasoline.</p>
        <p>Extensive Deposits</p>
        <p>Already, coal is the nation's biggest indigenous energy source, and its role has been growing. It supplied more than 23.4 percent of all energy consumed in this country, up from 17.5 percent in 1973, the year of the first oil shock, and 19.1 percent in 1979. And it accounted for nearly one-third of all energy produced in this country last year, up from 22.5 percent in 1973. It is the main fuel used to make electricity, providing about 56 percent, and is also the nation's largest energy export by far.</p>
        <p>But increased production of coal also raises intense environmental questions. The issues range from the speculative - like the extent of global warming caused by the burning of carbon-rich fuels like coal - to the spooky, like the collapse of land as robot miners pass beneath. The Government is spending more than $5 billion to find cleaner ways to use coal, and the coal companies have tried harder to ameliorate the effects of the collapse, called ''subsidence.''</p>
        <p>Longwall mining is used wherever coal is present in thick, level seams deep under the ground. (Shallow deposits are often exploited by strip mining, in which the surface layers are scraped away and the coal is excavated from an open pit.) Embracing new technologies and sometimes developing technology on its own, Consolidation Coal, a subsidiary of E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company, last year mined 55 million tons with 9,500 employees. Fifteen years earlier it took 23,000 workers to mine 55 million tons. A big part of the change was installing 22 longwall machines like the robot here.</p>
        <p>Despite the loss of employment, the United Mine Workers union generally favors longwall mines. ''Back in the 1950's, John L. Lewis said it would be far better to have highly productive oprations that were able to pay our folks good wages and benefits than to have 600,000 shovelers living in poverty,'' said John Duray, a spokesman for the union.</p>
        <p>Called Safer</p>
        <p>Union officials say longwall mines are also inherently safer in their design, and the mines that can afford them are generally the bigger, better-managed ones.</p>
        <p>Consol, as the company that operates this mine is known, is by far the biggest longwall operator.</p>
        <p>In the longwall system at Blacksville 2, miners dig a tunnel the height of the coal seam, and in it they set up a row of floor-to-ceiling steel brackets to hold up the rock and soil above. Sheltered by the shields, the miners install a robot that runs back and forth on a track across the 750-foot-long wall of coal on the open side of the bracket. On each pass, a wheel 4 feet in diameter, studded with claws, chews up the coal in a space extending 3 feet high and 30 inches in front of it. The coal falls to a conveyor belt. At the end of the wall, the robot miner, called a shearer, reverses direction and makes a pass just below the first.</p>
        <p>When the shearer has finished its second pass, devouring almost all of the six-foot height of the coal seam here, it moves 30 inches forward and starts again. Then, in a sequence worthy of a grade-B science fiction film, each of the 153 steel shields in the row takes it turn stepping forward into the space that the shearer just opened, to be in position for the shearer's next pass. As they step forward, the earth behind them collapses.</p>
        <p>The longwall moves forward 17 to 20 feet per eight-hour shift, two or three shifts a day, until it has covered about a mile, over many months. Then, in a few hours, the equipment is moved to another track 750 feet long, and starts work again.</p>
        <p>Fierce Competition</p>
        <p>The process can help coal companies achieve enormous efficiencies. Competition among coal producers is vicious, and executives at Consol say they plan to meet it by increasing productivity 3 to 6 percent annually.</p>
        <p>Setting up a modern mine can cost $100 million, and the chance of making a killing is very small. Unlike the price of oil, the price of coal has been fairly stable since the early 80's and is not likely to go anywhere soon; when inflation is taken into account, the price of coal is down by 44 percent since 1975.</p>
        <p>The price varies according to the sulfur content and energy content of the coal. In September, the amount of coal required to make a kilowatt-hour of electricity cost only 54 percent as much as the oil needed for the same job, according to the National Coal Association.</p>
        <p>Blacksville has two of Consol's 20 longwall machines. There are only about 100 longwall systems running in the 2,000 underground coal mines in the United States, but they produce about one-third the coal that comes from such mines, and some experts think that figure will rise to more than half by the end of the 90's.</p>
        <p>About a third of the nation's coal comes from surface mining, mostly in the West. The other third comes from underground mines that use older technologies, either because their owners cannot afford longwall machines or because the coal deposits are unsuitable for them.</p>
        <p>Further Refinements</p>
        <p>Engineers are now working on additional refinements to longwall mining. For example, operators of the Blacksville 2 mine hope that even pushing the buttons to make the 153 shields step forward - now done by a human - will soon be taken over by the robot's computer brain.</p>
        <p>Workers at this mine do not believe that this refinement will cut payrolls further because someone will be needed to watch the robots. At other mines, however, the prospect of installing a longwall machine brings dread because of the layoffs that will come with it.</p>
        <p>High-tech changes are taking place at the surface, too. In a small factory at the mouth of the mine, the coal is washed in water and other liquids, removing some of the sulfur; it is then dried, crushed and sorted by size. Sometimes it is blended with coal from other mines.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
