<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Complete Return on Investment</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="337401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="FORUM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CORPORATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INVESTMENT STRATEGIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENSON, GELVIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DD1E3BF936A15750C0A966958260" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Complete Return on Investment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GELVIN STEVENSON; Gelvin Stevenson, an economist, is a consultant to the Interfaith Center on Corporate Responsibility in New York.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENSON, GELVIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Behind every tract of rain forest that is cleared, every factory that is shuttered and locked and every oil-clogged beach lies an investment decision. These decisions may have paid big dividends to shareholders and other investors - they may have made certain individuals wealthier - but they also have harmed the economy, society and environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Behind every tract of rain forest that is cleared, every factory that is shuttered and locked and every oil-clogged beach lies an investment decision. These decisions may have paid big dividends to shareholders and other investors - they may have made certain individuals wealthier - but they also have harmed the economy, society and environment.</p>
        <p>Behind every tract of rain forest that is cleared, every factory that is shuttered and locked and every oil-clogged beach lies an investment decision. These decisions may have paid big dividends to shareholders and other investors - they may have made certain individuals wealthier - but they also have harmed the economy, society and environment.</p>
        <p>Traditionally, individuals and corporations have evaluated their investments only according to the financial return to the investor. But if we are to create a decent and sustainable world, we must develop a way to evaluate investments and measure their complete return. The complete return on an investment includes not only the immediate financial reward, but also the financial and physical consequences to other people, the environment and society.</p>
        <p>For some investments, ones that pollute the environment or destroy neighborhoods, the complete return can be very low or even negative. Such investments attack the economic and moral foundations of society, even though they may pay handsome dividends to individual investors. The greater their number, the wider their effect.</p>
        <p>With environmental and social crises worsening, it is imperative that society shift more of its investments toward activities with high complete returns. This is not to argue for inefficiency or corporate suicide, but for a higher level of social consciousness. Indeed, such a shift is a major goal of the burgeoning movement for socially responsible investing - in the securities of public and private companies, and in the projects of nonprofit organizations.</p>
        <p>The movement is growing. Already, $450 billion in pension funds, endowments and foundations is subjected to screening that limits investments to socially responsible companies. In addition, many investors are taking more direct routes to influencing corporate behavior, including persuasion, proxy fights and product boycotts.</p>
        <p>A growing number of religious investors, funds, foundations and individuals are also investing in nonprofit, community-based organizations that provide high complete returns but low financial returns. These organizations are doing good, but are not enriching their investors very fast. The Creative Investment Program of the Presbyterian Church Foundation, for example, is the largest of the 50 or so religious investment programs and has more than $8 million to invest. Together, these religious foundations have committed more than $30 million to nonprofit institutions that serve human needs. These foundations make safe loans, at below-market interest rates, to organizations that attempt to achieve positive social goals.</p>
        <p>When I was working at the Presbyterian Church Foundation, helping them invest their money, one of my favorite projects was the purchase of the loans of five neighborhood housing service partnerships around the country. These purchases allowed the housing organizations to make new loans to residents who were otherwise considered ''nonbankable.''</p>
        <p>A typical home improvement loan from the neighborhood partnership went to a disabled man and his 87-year-old mother who lived on Social Security in Richland Center, Wis. They borrowed from the partnership to replace their water heater, repair their leaky roof and insulate their home. The total return to the Presbyterian Foundation for supporting this organization was only 4.5 percent - about the rate of inflation. But the complete return was much higher. Another aspect of socially responsible investing is to inject capital directly into emerging companies that have a social purpose. While risky, such investments may even provide a high financial return. One company I am working with is developing pollution control products while another is developing alternatives to cooling systems that deplete the ozone layer. The return to society that these companies offer - if they are successful - makes investing in them worth the risk.</p>
        <p>Even though social investing is growing, the allure of quick profits and a high rate of return - no matter what the social cost - remains. But we have a choice. We can we reject investments that damage the environment and the social fabric of our country voluntarily, or we can have these investments limited by legal means. Either way, we have no choice but to limit investments that pay poor social returns. Nothing less is at stake than the decency of our society, the vitality of our economy and the ability of our planet to sustain life.</p>
        <p>FORUM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
