<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Perrier Plans Return With A New Voice</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="338923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOTTLED WATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECALLS AND BANS OF PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SOURCE PERRIER SA</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">RINEY, HAL, &amp; PARTNERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WARING &amp; LAROSA INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROTHENBERG, RANDALL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ADVERTISING (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900329T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DA103CF93AA15750C0A966958260" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Perrier Plans Return With A New Voice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Randall Rothenberg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROTHENBERG, RANDALL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: REBOUNDING from its recall of 72 million green bottles of fizzy water from American restaurants and supermarkets, the Perrier Group of America yesterday announced that it was transferring the domestic advertising responsibility for Perrier water from Hal Riney &amp; Partners in San Francisco to Waring &amp; LaRosa in New</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: REBOUNDING from its recall of 72 million green bottles of fizzy water from American restaurants and supermarkets, the Perrier Group of America yesterday announced that it was transferring the domestic advertising responsibility for Perrier water from Hal Riney &amp; Partners in San Francisco to Waring &amp; LaRosa in New</p>
        <p>REBOUNDING from its recall of 72 million green bottles of fizzy water from American restaurants and supermarkets, the Perrier Group of America yesterday announced that it was transferring the domestic advertising responsibility for Perrier water from Hal Riney &amp; Partners in San Francisco to Waring &amp; LaRosa in New York.</p>
        <p>Perrier water, which was recalled worldwide last month after trace amounts of benzene were found in some bottles, is set to return to the American market in a wave that will roll across the United States from late April through the end of May, said Jane Lazgin, a spokeswoman for the Perrier Group in Greenwich, Conn.</p>
        <p>Perrier executives said the decision to shift Perrier water from Riney was not the result of any dissatisfaction with the agency, nor was it directly related to the recall. ''More than getting us out of a jam, it's to give us a fresh start,'' Ms. Lazgin said.</p>
        <p>Since the recall, the company has been running newspaper and radio advertisements prepared by Burson-Marsteller, the giant public relations company and an expert in crisis management. The company plans to delay the introduction of new brand advertising from Waring &amp; LaRosa until July, when stores are expected to be fully stocked, Ms. Lazgin said. That campaign will replace the work done by Riney, whose award-winning television commercials featured dreamy scenes of the French countryside accompanied by Hal Riney's throaty narration, which concluded with the statements ''It's perfect. It's Perrier.''</p>
        <p>Several weeks ago, the Riney agency lost the account of another Perrier Group brand, Poland Spring water, to Lord Einstein O'Neill &amp; Partners. Nonetheless, Mr. Riney said yesterday that the loss of the $8 million to $10 million Perrier account was ''a surprise to me.'' Two weeks ago, at the annual meeting of the American Association of Advertising Agencies, he delivered a humorous speech in which he asked the rhetorical question ''Are you still drinking Perrier?'' and answered with a confident ''Yes.''</p>
        <p>His agency is retaining responsibility for advertising four other bottled water brands marketed by Perrier: Arrowhead, Calistoga, Ozarka and Zephyr Hills. Billings for these accounts should total between $8 million and $10 million.</p>
        <p>Several top creative people have left Riney during the last several weeks. What is more, the agency's competitors have been spreading stories that Mr. Riney is trying to sell his shop and that his own time is dominated by work creating advertising for the General Motors Corporation's forthcoming Saturn automobile.</p>
        <p>Mr. Riney has repeatedly disputed these accounts, pointing out that his creative people are coveted by other agencies because of the work they have done for him, and that he has hired reputable talent to share the burden of the Saturn account.</p>
        <p>For Waring &amp; LaRosa, the value of the Perrier account is as symbolic as it is financial. The agency helped popularize the beverage in the United States with advertising that ran between 1981 and 1987. Its early print and television ads used the slogan ''Earth's first soft drink'' and featured the artist R. O. Blechman's lovably fragile characters with large noses and grape-shaped bodies.</p>
        <p>Perrier removed its account from Waring when the agency's former owner, BBDO, took on the account of its rival French mineral water Vittel. Waring executives bought their agency back in late 1988, and the agency has been slowly rebuilding a client roster that withered away during its years under BBDO and that agency's parent company, the Omnicom Group.</p>
        <p>Because of Perrier's quick response to the contamination, most beverage industry analysts have said its market dominance is not seriously imperiled. The company controlled almost 24 percent of the $2.17 billion domestic bottled water market in 1988 and 57 percent of the market for premium imported bottled water, according to the Beverage Marketing Association.</p>
        <p>On Feb. 9, the company, a unit of Source Perrier S.A. in Paris, recalled its entire stock of the bubbling water from 750,000 North American outlets, after the traces of the chemical solvent benzene were found. Several days later, the company recalled its entire stock from bistros and groceries worldwide, a total of 160 million bottles.</p>
        <p>An investigation found that the presence of the benzene, which in large doses has been shown to cause cancer in laboratory animals, resulted from the company's failure to monitor its buildup in the processing equipment. Benzene is naturally present, in minuscule amounts, in the carbon dioxide used to recarbonate Perrier.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
