<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN DEFENSE OF NUCLEAR POWER.    YES IT IS CLEAN - AND NOT A SOURCE FOR WEAPONRY</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="316619"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILSON, RICHARD (PROF)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DB133CF937A25752C0A966958260" item-length="323" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN DEFENSE OF NUCLEAR POWER.    YES IT IS CLEAN - AND NOT A SOURCE FOR WEAPONRY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your correspondents, Claudine Schneider and Jim Weiss, made some inaccurate statements in their letters (''Tainted Bait,'' Dec. 31). These errors presumably colored their views. It is indeed correct that nuclear power plants, such as the present commercial plants which contain uranium 238, produce plutonium. After a difficult chemical separation, the pure chemical element plutonium can be made. However, the fuel is left a long time in the reactor, and plutonium 240 is produced as well as plutonium 239, which cannot separated chemically. This makes a bomb difficult to make and unreliable because of pre-ignition. To the best of my knowledge, no country has a bomb made from this spent fuel.</p>
        <p>Representative Schneider does not seem to have noticed that many utility companies are proposing advanced gas turbines for their electricity generation, using natural gas or gas made from coal or other biomass. The facilities needed for producing gas are small and simple; in the past, capitalist enterprises built them without help. One may anticipate that if and when the cost is once again competitive this will be done again.</p>
        <p>I agree with Mr. Weiss that environmental degradation is not a neccessary consequence of man's existence, if we add the adjective ''major'' to degradation. It is for this reason that many scientists prefer nuclear energy to most other ways of producing energy. Setting aside such rare accidents as Chernobyl, where radiation levels will be back to normal in less than a century, the increase in radiation has been small - less than 1 percent at the boundary of a typical nuclear facility. By contrast, increases in the concentration of carbon dioxide, sulphates, nitrates and particulates from other energy uses are greater; so also are the fractions of land covered with concrete.</p>
        <p>RICHARD WILSON</p>
        <p>MALLINCKRODT PROFESSOR OF PHYSICS</p>
        <p>HARVARD UNIVERSITY</p>
        <p>CAMBRIDGE, MASS., JAN. 1</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
