<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business Diary/July 8-13</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="368357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">SUMMARY</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D7143CF936A25754C0A966958260" item-length="1818" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business Diary/July 8-13</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Allen R. Myerson</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>INTERNATIIONAL</p>
        <p>The Best Little Summit in Texas</p>
        <p>A summit conference meant to celebrate the triumph of free-market economics became a demonstration of laissez-faire diplomacy as well. For every country and cause, the final communique had a clause. As the conference in Houston ended, West Germany came away with the right to unilaterally aid the Soviet Union, Japan the right to aid China.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>INTERNATIIONAL</p>
        <p>The Best Little Summit in Texas</p>
        <p>A summit conference meant to celebrate the triumph of free-market economics became a demonstration of laissez-faire diplomacy as well. For every country and cause, the final communique had a clause. As the conference in Houston ended, West Germany came away with the right to unilaterally aid the Soviet Union, Japan the right to aid China.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIIONAL</p>
        <p>The Best Little Summit in Texas</p>
        <p>A summit conference meant to celebrate the triumph of free-market economics became a demonstration of laissez-faire diplomacy as well. For every country and cause, the final communique had a clause. As the conference in Houston ended, West Germany came away with the right to unilaterally aid the Soviet Union, Japan the right to aid China. The United States avoided taking a strong stance against global warming, while the European nations beat back American demands for a commitment to end agricultural subsidies. Instead of unanimity, the leaders of the West's seven major industrial powers settled for chumminess. President Bush tried to loosen up his guests with rodeo and barbecue, even as some Houstonians fumed that their art museum better reflected their worldly sophistication.</p>
        <p>Promises, Promises</p>
        <p>On one summit issue, President Bush got downright vehement. He demanded an end to agricultural subsidies. The United States showers its own farmers with aid and protection, but not nearly as much as Japan or Western Europe do. Administration officials said that subsidies keep food exports from America and the third world out of major markets. The President won no specific timetables or commitments from other leaders, just a general promise to roll back protectionist subsidies.</p>
        <p>Helping the East Go On-Line</p>
        <p>First the computer conferences, then maybe the computer sales. Western sellers are rushing to meet the Eastern bloc's potential buyers at one computer show after another. From last Tuesday through today the International Data Group has held its first PC World Forum/Moscow. Last month, the International Computer Club held its first International Computer Forum in Moscow. Set for early fall are the Softool U.S.S.R. conference in Moscow and the Edventure East-West High-Tech Forum in Budapest. The conference come as the West eases its technology export rules. But computer vendors still face unconvertible currencies, clogged distribution channels, scant office space - and doubts about whether the person who signs a deal today will have authority to live up to it tomorrow. ''I'm trying to first tell everybody how tough it is,'' said Esther Dyson, publisher of the Release 1.0 newsletter and sponsor of the Budapest conference. ''Then, if you still want to do it anyway, more power to you.''</p>
        <p>COMPANIES</p>
        <p>Defending the Family Honor</p>
        <p>It was a trying week for a President attempting to distance himself from the savings and loan debacle. He defended his son, Neil, against accusations that he violated conflict of interest rules as a director of the Silverado Banking, Savings and Loan Association in Denver. ''I have confidence in the honor and integrity of my son,'' President Bush said, while pledging to stay out of the case. Federal regulators are considering whether to file a $200 million lawsuit against Neil Bush and other directors to recover some of the Government's losses in Silverado's failure. The regulators released documents last week showing that loans Neil Bush voted to approve for a business partner cost the Government at least $45 million when they went bad. Democrats tried to force the Justice Department to appoint a special prosecutor, bringing protests from Republicans.</p>
        <p>*</p>
        <p>A Senate panel opened hearings into what Senator Howard M. Metzenbaum, an Ohio Democrat, called ''the worst case we have found'' of abuses in the savings and loan bailout program. An Arizona insurance executive with a history of legal and regulatory problems garnered promises of $1.85 billion in Federal subsidies to buy 15 failed savings and loans. The executive, James M. Fail, consolidated them into Bluebonnet Savings, which, with the Government aid, became the most profitable large savings and loan in the nation last year. Mr. Fail received help in securing the funds from Robert J. Thompson, an aide to George Bush when he was vice president.</p>
        <p>*</p>
        <p>The Senate approved a bill to provide $162 million to clean up the savings and loan industry and increase maximum penalties to life imprisonment.</p>
        <p>Taken for Granite</p>
        <p>Fly the friendly floors: American Airlines plans to charge its La Guardia Airport passengers an extra dollar a ticket for the privilege of treading imported granite floor tiles. Passengers on flights from Newark, New Orleans, West Palm Beach, Fla., and Fort Myers, Fla., will pay as much as $4 more for each ticket as well, reflecting what American calls ''excessive charges'' at these airports. At La Guardia, American objects to the use of granite tiles in the main terminal areas. American says the tiles are at least four times as expensive as the porcelain tiles the airline installs in its own terminal areas. While some consumer groups griped about the charges, analysts politely applauded. Julius Malduits of Salomon Brothers said airlines should be able to recoup added costs, whether at the airport terminals or at the fuel pumps. ''How's this any different from the fuel surcharges?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>The Brademas Touch</p>
        <p>If they had the millions, John Brademas had the lintels, with space for their names. And so, under his nine-year tenure as president of New York University, he lined up donors for the Tisch Hospital, the (Leonard N.) Stern School of Business and the Alexander S. Onassis Center for Hellenic Studies, named after Aristotle's son. His board of trustees, with Laurence A. Tisch of CBS as chairman, was stocked with Alan C. Greenberg of Bear, Stearns; Lewis L. Glucksman of Smith Barney; Thomas S. Murphy of Capital Cities/ABC; Milton J. Petrie of Petrie Stores, Lewis Rudin, the builder; Mr. Stern, of the Hartz Group; Martin Lipton, the lawyer, and Ann G. Getty. After raising $800 million in all, Dr. Brademas said last week that he will step down in December 1991.</p>
        <p>Chi-Chi Shopping</p>
        <p>With other tony New York retailers closing down, is there room for a new French arrival to open up? Galeries Lafayette of Paris plans to put its first American store in the Trump Tower space vacated by Bonwit Teller. But New York's appetite for Euro-glitz is slumping along with its economy. And Au Printemps S.A., Galeries Lafayette's Paris rival, closed its only United States department store, in Denver, last year. New York City's morale did improve last week with the Democratic Party's decision to hold its 1992 national convention there. But Galeries Lafayette will need to attract plenty of shoppers long before the conventioneers hit town.</p>
        <p>Adding Insult to Injury</p>
        <p>It was bad enough for John A. Mulheren Jr. to be convicted last week on four felony counts of conspiracy and securities fraud. But worse, he was convicted even after the lead witness against him, Ivan F. Boesky, confessed to keeping millions of dollars in ill-gotten profits, bribing fellow prisoners to do his laundry and deducting half his $100 million fine from his taxes. Mr. Mulheren, a former trader, was accused of conspiring with Mr. Boesky to manipulate the price of Gulf and Western Industries stock. A Federal judge declared a mistrial on 26 other charges when the jury deadlocked.</p>
        <p>In Brief</p>
        <p>A Federal judge took steps on Monday to consolidate hundreds of thousands of asbestos cases in an attempt to control legal costs. He also froze spending by a trust that the Manville Corporation set up to handle the claims.</p>
        <p>*</p>
        <p>Sears, Roebuck and Company said it expected sharply lower second-quarter earnings because of unanticipated losses in in its Allstate Insurance unit and weak sales in its stores. Eastern Airlines said Friday that it had entered merger talks with Northwest Airlines. Eastern also predicted 1990 losses greater than the projected $330 million.</p>
        <p>*</p>
        <p>Robert W. Kearns was awarded more than $5 million in his suit against the Ford Motor Company for infringing on his patent for intermittent windshield wipers.</p>
        <p>*</p>
        <p>Who says the leveraged-buyout boom is over? Kohlberg, Kravis, Roberts &amp; Company agreed last week to the sale of Motel 6 to Accor S.A. of France for $1.3 billion. Kohlberg, Kravis and its investors will earn five times their original $125 million investment.</p>
        <p>*</p>
        <p>The GTE Corporation intends to acquire the Contel Corporation in a stock swap worth $6 billion. GTE would become the nation's second-largest mobile telephone operator.</p>
        <p>*</p>
        <p>The United Parcel Service plans to convert its 2,700 delivery trucks in Los Angeles to run on cleaner natural gas.</p>
        <p>THE ECONOMY</p>
        <p>Loosening the Credit Reins</p>
        <p>It's as if Alan Greenspan got turned down for a loan himself. For months, business people have been complaining about tight bank credit, but the Federal Reserve chairman said he saw a problem in real estate only. Last Thursday, Mr. Greenspan announced that banks had indeed become too unwilling to lend, so the Fed was ready to compensate by easing interest rates. The very next day, market analysts saw signs that the Fed was pushing rates down. The markets rallied, with the Dow climbing above 3,000 for the first time, before closing at 2,980.20, up 75.25 for the week. Mr. Greenspan believes the economy is strong enough to resist a recession, analysts noted. ''The easing we got today seems to have been a special, once-and-for-all response to the banks' tightening,'' said Lawrence Krohn, an economist at Shearson Lehman Hutton.</p>
        <p>In Brief Truth in performing: New York and New Jersey are considering laws to require notices on concert tickets and advertising when a performance will be less than live. Many rock stars gyrate and lip-synch their way through programs of canned music that have all the spontaneity of political conventions.</p>
        <p>*</p>
        <p>Regulators ordered the nation's largest banks last Wednesday to write off 20 percent of their loans to Brazil and raise their write-offs for Argentina's debt from 40 to 60 percent.</p>
        <p>Inflation Takes a Hike</p>
        <p>No sooner does the Fed begin lowering interest rates than the inflation report takes a jump. While the producer price index rose just two-tenths of 1 percent in June, the core rate, excluding volatile food and energy prices, increased six-tenths of 1 percent. The jump in the core rate was twice what many economists expected. And evidence last week that oil producers were arranging to limit output might reverse recent declines in energy prices. Some economists said Friday's price report was nothing to worry about after several months of low inflation; for the first half year, wholesale prices still increased at an annual rate of only 3.7 percent. But other economists questioned whether higher prices will limit the Fed's flexibility. ''We do have an inflation risk,'' said Stephen S. Roach, the senior economist at Morgan Stanley. ''It will not go away, and most definitely not with the Fed adopting an easier policy.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
