<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Television;   2 Shows Aim Young and Younger</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="371404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FOX TELEVISION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">GLORY DAYS (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MOLLOY (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DA1531F936A15754C0A966958260" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Television;   2 Shows Aim Young and Younger</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN J. O'CONNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In its never-ending quest for the fountain of youthful audiences, Fox Broadcasting tonight is offering the first episodes of ''Glory Days,'' whose heroes are four post-high school chums heading in different directions, and ''Molloy,'' all about a frisky actress just turned 13. Neither offers an occasion to break out the soda pop.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In its never-ending quest for the fountain of youthful audiences, Fox Broadcasting tonight is offering the first episodes of ''Glory Days,'' whose heroes are four post-high school chums heading in different directions, and ''Molloy,'' all about a frisky actress just turned 13. Neither offers an occasion to break out the soda pop.</p>
        <p>In its never-ending quest for the fountain of youthful audiences, Fox Broadcasting tonight is offering the first episodes of ''Glory Days,'' whose heroes are four post-high school chums heading in different directions, and ''Molloy,'' all about a frisky actress just turned 13. Neither offers an occasion to break out the soda pop.</p>
        <p>''Glory Days'' comes from the factory of Patrick Hasburgh, creator of Fox's ''21 Jump Street,'' the show that brought us Johnny Depp and, in a spinoff called ''Booker,'' Richard Grieco. This is the television school of young male pinups. The new show combines the action elements of those series with the rites-of-passage musings of the movie ''Diner.'' Every so often, ''Glory Days'' pauses to allow one of the guys to hoist a can of beer and solemnly say, ''Here's to our youth.''</p>
        <p>Although these fellows may have grown up together, they really have very little in common. That's a core problem. Walker Lovejoy (Brad Pitt) is the local football star who, failing to make the college team, returns home to become - what else? - a journalist. His boss is Sheila Jackson (Beth Broderick), a newspaper editor who storms into her office shouting things like: ''Damn it, people, we are in the news business. I'm surrounded by midgets here.'' Walker may be inexperienced, but his cool lop-sided grin augurs well for a great career.</p>
        <p>Walker's best friend is Dave Rutecki (Spike Alexander), a rookie cop whose eagerness sometimes makes him act, as his superior puts it, ''a freakin' storm trooper.'' When Dave shoots a supermarket robber, Walker submits an eyewitness story to Ms. Jackson, who then proceeds to rewrite the piece and give it a sensational play (''Rookie Cop Kills Father of Four''). Dave is furious with Walker. ''All I wanted to be was a cop,'' he cries, adding jealously, ''You got the football scholarship, the girls and the great hair.'' Priorities, priorities.</p>
        <p>The other members of the group are Dominic Fopiano (Evan Mirand), amiably getting involved with college and fraternities, and Peter (T-Bone) Trigg, the totally unfocused son of hippie parents. T-Bone is never at a loss for an aphorism: ''Women are like pizza - the older they get, the easier they are to pick up.'' Or, ''Love is something men invented to get girls to take their clothes off.''</p>
        <p>Speaking of girls, Walker is crushed when he finds his former girlfriend sharing a mountain cabin with her art-history teacher. Rushing away with a tear in his eye, Walker mutters bitterly, ''Hope he gives you a good grade.'' Later she will beg for forgiveness, explaining that ''I just wanted to be more grownup,'' but Walker will have none of that. Now he listens to Ms. Jackson, who gives him helpful tips on being a sharp reporter: ''Sometimes you have to bend the truth, just enough to sell a newspaper.'' Her clincher: ''Ambiguity: it's the most important word in journalism.''</p>
        <p>As the episode ends, Walker has reconciled with Dave, and the two friends warmly embrace as the telephone, presumably with the spurned girlfriend at the other end, continues to ring unanswered. Ambiguity has its uses, too, evidently, in television rituals of male bonding.</p>
        <p>In ''Molloy,'' Mayin Bialik is Molloy Martin, a precocious youngster who, after the death of her mother in New York, has moved in with her father and his new family in Beverly Hills. In no time at all, it seems, she has snagged a job appearing on a children's program at the local public television station. A New Yorker to the bone, Molloy is commited to innumerable social and environmental causes. Her new family is pure California, preoccupied with bikini waxes, body rubs and scalp massages. ''Molloy'' has the courage of its stereotypes.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bialik, who appeared in the Bette Midler movie ''Beaches,'' looks a bit like Barbra Streisand auditioning for the Margaret Hamilton role in ''The Wizard of Oz.'' There's no denying she's energetic. That's helpful, because ''Molloy'' and its cliches will need all the energy it can get. Very nearly walking off with the show is Molloy's older step-sister, Courtney, played to a bubble-head fare-thee-well by Jennifer Aniston.</p>
        <p>Did Molloy mention the greenhouse effect? ''Get real,'' says Courtney, ''I don't talk to gardeners.'' And what really makes people happy? ''New shoes usually do a lot,'' she confides. On one level, ''Molloy'' asks what is important, and what is frivolous? This sitcom is all too eager to endorse the frivolous.</p>
        <p>Glory Days</p>
        <p>Executive producer, Patrick Hasburgh; producer, Mark Ovitz; co-producers, Justis Greene and Jodi Rothe; associate producer, Skip Schoolnik; Patrick Hasburgh Productions Inc. for Fox Television. Today on Fox at 8 P.M.</p>
        <p>Walker Lovejoy . . . Brad Pitt</p>
        <p>Dave Rutecki . . . Spike Alexander</p>
        <p>Peter Trigg . . . Nicholas Kallsen</p>
        <p>Dominic Fopiano . . . Evan Mirand</p>
        <p>Sheila Jackson . . . Beth Broderick</p>
        <p>Victor Krantz . . . Robert Costanzo</p>
        <p>Molloy</p>
        <p>Executive producers, Lee Rich, Grant Rosenberg, Stu Kreisman, Chris Cluess; produced by Andy Selig; created by George Beckerman; creative consultant, Lee Madux; story editors, Dottie Archibald, Carrie Honigblum, Renee Phillips; Lee Rich Productions in association with Warner Brothers Television. Today on Fox at 9 P.M.</p>
        <p>Molloy Martin . . . Mayim Bialik</p>
        <p>Paul Martin . . . Kevin Scannell</p>
        <p>Lynn Walker-Martin . . . Pamela Brull</p>
        <p>Courtney Walker . . . Jennifer Aniston</p>
        <p>Jason Walker . . . Luke Edwards</p>
        <p>Sara Peters . . . Ashley Maw</p>
        <p>Lewis D'Uncann Jackson . . . Bumper Robinson</p>
        <p>Simon Lansbury . . . I. M. Hobson</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
