<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Special Effects Take on Special Meaning on TV</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="399873"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SILVER, EDWARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D6133FF932A25752C1A966958260" item-length="1817" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Special Effects Take on Special Meaning on TV</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD SILVER; Edward Silver is a Los Angeles writer who often reports on the entertainment industry.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SILVER, EDWARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF EARTHQUAKE-THEMED EPICS can be called a genre, "The Big One: The Great Los Angeles Earthquake," a $9.5 million, four-hour mini-series that NBC will broadcast tonight and tomorrow at 9, is bringing that genre to television. Like the 1936 feature film "San Francisco," starring Jeanette MacDonald and Clark Cable, and Irwin Allen's visceral 1974 "Earthquake," which won an Oscar for its special effects, "The Big One" relies on an assortment of time-tested special-effects techniques to foster the suspension of disbelief.</p>
        <p>Craftsmen build miniature skyscrapers and rig them to crumble on cue. Artists paint mattes -- essentially trompe-l'oeil backgrounds -- to mimic scenery. During the height of the tumult, a battering ram jolts an artificial floor beneath the actors. Seismic tremors have been simulated the same way in Hollywood since the silents, down to the deft slap to the camera.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF EARTHQUAKE-THEMED EPICS can be called a genre, "The Big One: The Great Los Angeles Earthquake," a $9.5 million, four-hour mini-series that NBC will broadcast tonight and tomorrow at 9, is bringing that genre to television. Like the 1936 feature film "San Francisco," starring Jeanette MacDonald and Clark Cable, and Irwin Allen's visceral 1974 "Earthquake," which won an Oscar for its special effects, "The Big One" relies on an assortment of time-tested special-effects techniques to foster the suspension of disbelief.</p>
        <p>Craftsmen build miniature skyscrapers and rig them to crumble on cue. Artists paint mattes -- essentially trompe-l'oeil backgrounds -- to mimic scenery. During the height of the tumult, a battering ram jolts an artificial floor beneath the actors. Seismic tremors have been simulated the same way in Hollywood since the silents, down to the deft slap to the camera.</p>
        <p>By contrast, the creators of "After the Warming," a two-hour ecological documentary to be shown in prime time on the Public Broadcasting Service on Nov. 21, developed their own computer programs and image-processing techniques to invigorate a subject often examined with a dry, didactic tone. In their hands, the conventional science "doc" -- in this case, a looking back, from the year 2050, on how nations could have prevented the so-called greenhouse effect from laying waste to the planet Earth -- has been repackaged into a form of historical science fiction.</p>
        <p>In the process, the production provides a glimpse of how special-effects techniques may alter the look and feel of television over the next decade.</p>
        <p>Special effects have long been the province of theatrically released films and TV commercials, which routinely invest lavish amounts of time and money on what often results in mere seconds of final footage. But in the face of growing competition from visually stunning theatrical releases, such as "Total Recall," "Raiders of the Lost Ark" and "The Abyss," along with the abundance of choices on the TV dial, television producers are reaching for effects to turbo-charge their programming and to create fresh ways of telling stories. A tall order, considering the time and budgetary constraints of the medium, as well as the relatively small size of the screen. In response, TV fantasists have evolved a style of enhancement rather than overkill, what one effects designer calls "putting the sizzle on the steak."</p>
        <p>The new interest in visual trickery rests on a dazzling spectrum of technologies. Digital editing, in which filmed images are transformed into a mathematically based electronic signal, makes the combining of photographic elements a swifter and highly malleable process. Video is treated as a canvas upon which a cluster of painterly overlays are applied. Robotic "motion-control" camera work creates an interplay among disparate sequences (later collated in the editing room), so that, for example, the starship Enterprise can bear down on an enemy craft with precision or an actor can interact with himself, like identical twins, in a single scene.</p>
        <p>Though directors must still adhere to old-fashioned principles on the set -- if they want to shoot an explosion, they have to blow something up -- some observers are predicting the advent of the "digital set," in which computer-generated imagery (called CGI within the industry) is integrated with all levels of production. And although feature films have already made extensive use of this technology, CGI may become even more prevalent in television, because the tube's lower resolution requires a smaller investment of computer time. As this technology becomes less costly -- and more versatile -- television is fast learning to put it to use.</p>
        <p>"The nature of effects in TV is changing," says Maury Rosenfeld, a Los Angeles graphics designer for television. "Conventional animation, models, miniatures can't pull it off anymore. The audience has trained eyes."</p>
        <p>There are times, however, when an artisan's ingenuity makes his menagerie of black boxes almost superfluous. "In one paragraph," recalls Rob Legato, visual effects co-director of the syndicated series "Star Trek: The Next Generation," "the script said to accelerate to 10 times warp speed and go to the edge of the universe. Now what is</p>
        <p>that</p>
        <p>supposed to look like?"</p>
        <p>Mr. Legato would be the one to decide. Working on a weekly series -- one generally acknowledged as the leader in TV effects -- he didn't have a few months to park the problem with George Lucas's Industrial Light and Magic, the premier special-effects house for the film industry. Instead, the patterns made by Christmas-tree lights reflecting off wet dime-store Mylar, photographed through filters and tinted with murky gels, became the "Star Trek" edge of the universe.</p>
        <p>Yet in this day of synthetic imagery, couldn't a high-powered computer have rendered the unfathomable locale?</p>
        <p>"We could have," says Mr. Legato, "but $10 doesn't buy a lot of computer design time. Ten dollars buys a lot of Mylar."</p>
        <p>Jeff Sagansky, president of CBS Entertainment, was quick to say yes to "The Flash," a series on Thursday evenings at 8:30. "I was looking for something that would make some noise," Mr. Sagansky said recently. "Movies have been very successful in exploiting special effects with super heroes, and that attracts a large part of the audience we want to reach." "The Flash" is a production of Warner Brothers, the studio that put "Batman" on the big screen. "It's hard for TV to compete," Mr. Sagansky added. "But the producers convinced me the effects would be doable week in and week out."</p>
        <p>"The Flash" is based on a decades-old comic-book series chronicling the adventures of a crime-fighter endowed with super speed. Hourlong episodes typically cost $1.5 million, a good chunk of which goes into a highly detailed, skewed-noir look.</p>
        <p>The show's signature effect, the blurred figure of its hero in motion, is designed and executed in post production. Creating the sequence usually involves combining multiple speeded up images of the Flash (played by John Wesley Shipp) with electronically generated color and background footage.</p>
        <p>Integrating the streaked image with live action can get complex. In last week's episode, the Flash stole a rack of pool cues from an evil-doer's hands at super speed, one by one. The 10 seconds or so of finished footage involved the Flash filmed alone grabbing cues against a screen invisible to the camera. His figure was then electronically blurred, traced and isolated on an editing console, and precisely lined up to interact with his adversary -- who was moving at normal speed.</p>
        <p>Had the sequence been crafted for a theatrical release, filmed frames would likely have had to be colored or animated manually, with each composite of images built individually and developed overnight in a lab. That process typically requires days or weeks. Because "The Flash" is edited on digital video, a highly manipulable medium, the sequence took only 90 minutes.</p>
        <p>To some, the visual effects in "The Flash" are simply eye candy. But Danny Bilson, co-creator of the show, says, "We aren't trying to make a spectacle of him. It's all about exploring a character. Sometimes we just have him washing his dog at super speed. We've got him moving so fast in one episode, he goes into the future."</p>
        <p>The producers of NBC's "Lifestories" use special effects to educate their audience about the human body. Shown Sunday evenings at 8, each hourlong episode brings a different medical condition under observation by means of drama embellished by documentary-style graphics. One week the abdomen of a golfer is "opened" by computer simulation to reveal the progress of his colon cancer. In another episode, a simple clock graphic in the corner of the screen counts the vital minutes following a coronary. The "Lifestories"approach to medical programming is facilitated by the show's tool kit of visual effects.</p>
        <p>Though the effects are handmaidens to stories that inform as well as entertain, "doing something different," as Jeff Bleckner, the show's co-executive producer, puts it, is a strategic response to the shrinking of the networks' share of viewers.</p>
        <p>"This is what's changing TV," he says. "It is being forced to create programming that will hold people's attention while they're holding their remote control."</p>
        <p>"Maniac Mansion," a facetiously macabre Family Channel sitcom reminiscent of "The Addams Family" from the mid-60's, may also be trying to do that. The Addams family's Uncle Fester boasted a shaved head and a bell-ringer's robe; "Maniac Mansion" offers John Hemphill as Harry the Fly, a swattable germ-carrier with a wisecracking human head.  Putting an actor into a costume is hardly new, although "Mansion's" use of a digital editing console to reduce and animate Mr. Hemphill's image is a formidable ploy.</p>
        <p>When a half-human fly buzzes through a living room or the Flash moves fast enough to be catapulted into the future, the special effect begins with a physical object in front of a camera. With computer-generated imagery, however, television itself may be catapulted into a new realm of creativity. Indeed, eventually CGI "will be capable of imaging anything that can be imagined," says Peter Sorensen, a Los Angeles computer-graphics consultant.</p>
        <p>"After the Warming," the forthcoming PBS documentary, is structured around a high-tech conceit. Speaking from within a computer-generated "virtual reality chamber" in the year 2050, James Burke, the show's writer and host, recounts the crisis of global warming that arrived at the end of the 20th century and the subsequent communal process of global repair. The chamber, appearing as a latticework of light beams into which Mr. Burke's image is inserted in the editing room, "generates" and provides passage to five continents of actual locations, where the story is told.</p>
        <p>Rather than inspire awe, the graphics simply set the stage. "Our graphics form part of an environment appropriate to a global management agency of 2050," Mr. Burke explained in a telephone conversation from London. "People are so accustomed to standard documentary techniques that unless we place them in an entirely new context, such as the chamber, they would not suspend disbelief. Yet if we overplayed them, the credibility of that context would dissolve."</p>
        <p>It may be a few years before Mr. Burke can step into a CGI re-creation of an Amazon embankment from his synthetic latticework chamber. The clumpy texture of soil, the irregular grace of birds in flight, the subtle expressions of the human face -- these are still out of reach. On the other hand, the California Institute of Technology has developed a program that simulates fur -- not only the geometry of every individual strand of hair but its sheen as well -- for CGI teddy bears. Software for soulful eyes can't be too far off.  TELEVISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
