<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ocean Loudspeakers To Sound Off for Data On Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="398605"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOUND</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEAT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MUNK, WALTER (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Heard Island and McDonald Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sound</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DF1E3CF935A35752C1A966958260" item-length="1371" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ocean Loudspeakers To Sound Off for Data On Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BY sending pulses of underwater sound around the world through all five of its ocean basins, scientists hope to settle the question of whether the predicted "greenhouse" effect has begun to warm the planet.</p>
        <p>The experiment, described by an organizer in a recent lecture, is scheduled to begin in January. It will exploit the fact that the speed of sound in water depends on the water's temperature: the warmer the water, the faster sound propagates through it. Any significant change in the speed at which sound traverses several thousand miles of seawater would mean a change in the average temperature of the water through which the sound passed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BY sending pulses of underwater sound around the world through all five of its ocean basins, scientists hope to settle the question of whether the predicted "greenhouse" effect has begun to warm the planet.</p>
        <p>The experiment, described by an organizer in a recent lecture, is scheduled to begin in January. It will exploit the fact that the speed of sound in water depends on the water's temperature: the warmer the water, the faster sound propagates through it. Any significant change in the speed at which sound traverses several thousand miles of seawater would mean a change in the average temperature of the water through which the sound passed.</p>
        <p>Although scientists agree on the theory of greenhouse warming, which holds that various gases like carbon dioxide trap heat in the atmosphere, debate continues as to whether the increases in these gases have actually begun to warm the global climate. They hope to settle the question with measurements.</p>
        <p>Climatologists believe that the atmosphere and oceans are climatically coupled, with each influencing the other's temperature. Any long-term warming of the atmosphere would therefore be associated with a warming of the oceans.  Signals From the Deep</p>
        <p>Dr. Walter Munk of the Scripps Institution of Oceanography in La Jolla, Calif., is a leading organizer of the speed-of-sound experiment, which is supported by eight nations as well as the National Academy of Sciences, the Office of Naval Research, the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration and various university research groups.</p>
        <p>In the trial about to begin, a small ship will anchor near Heard Island, a remote Australian possession in the southern Indian Ocean. An underwater loudspeaker will be lowered to a depth of about 820 feet, and for nine days, the speaker will broadcast signals consisting of very low notes transmitted at high volume.</p>
        <p>Dr. Munk said in an interview that Heard Island was selected because of its location. From there, direct paths extend through each of the world's five oceans, and sound conducted along these paths should be audible to acoustic sensors placed thousands of miles away.</p>
        <p>Underwater microphones will be installed at Australia's Mawson Station in Antarctica, near Bermuda and San Francisco, and along the coasts of South Africa, India, Australia, New Zealand and Canada. Scientists cannot predict how loud the signal will be when it reaches any of these points, but they believe it will be audible to sensitive equipment.</p>
        <p>The distances between Heard Island and the various microphones are all known precisely, so that careful measurement of the time an acoustic signal takes to reach a sensor will permit calculation of the average speed of sound over the course. Altering Speed of Sound</p>
        <p>The speed of sound in water is roughly one mile per second, but it is altered by temperature, salinity, the direction and speed of currents, and the degree to which water is compressed at increasing depths. But temperature is the largest factor affecting the speed of sound over long distances, Dr. Munk said.</p>
        <p>If predictions of global warming are correct and the temperature of the oceans is rising as expected, sound will travel significantly faster each year over the 11,200-mile distance from Heard Island to San Francisco. Dr. Munk estimates that travel time for sound covering this route should be reduced by as much as one-quarter of a second each year.</p>
        <p>He and his colleagues intend to send a signal around the world using a pulse of sound that starts out no louder than that of a jet airliner taking off. To transmit this relatively modest noise over thousands of miles, the group will exploit a "sound axis," a layer of ocean water extending through all the world's oceans. This layer acts as a conduit for sound, in somewhat the way the rubber tube of a stethoscope transmits faint noises from a patient's chest to a doctor's ear.</p>
        <p>The sound signal, which will be broadcast at frequencies from 50 to 70 hertz (near the lower limit of human hearing), will emanate from a special loudspeaker placed at the depth of the sound axis at that point in the ocean -- 820 feet. The conduit's depth varies in different parts of the world, exceeding 3,000 feet in places. To send or receive sound through the conduit, the microphone or transmitter must be positioned within the waveguide.</p>
        <p>Dr. Peter F. Worcester, a research oceanographer at Scripps, explained that the sound axis is a form of waveguide -- a space that confines sound between two natural boundaries, thereby preventing it from dissipating upward or downward. The upper boundary of this conduit is called a thermocline, a division between ocean layers above which the water is relatively warm and below which it is much cooler.</p>
        <p>The lower boundary of the waveguide is another natural division resulting from compression of the water at increasing depths. Below this boundary, the high degree of compression begins to increase the speed of sound significantly. Journey Across the World</p>
        <p>The waveguide thus consists of a world-girdling layer of water in which sound travels relatively slowly; both above it and below it the speed of sound is higher. Because of these discontinuities above and below the oceanic layer, sound propagating through it tends to stay within the natural waveguide.</p>
        <p>The sound from the Heard Island loudspeaker will start out at an intensity of 209 decibels. By comparison, the noise of a jet airliner taking off is about 270 decibels. But while the sound of a jet engine transmitted through air fades out in a few tens of miles, a sound transmitted through an oceanic waveguide can travel to the other side of the world.</p>
        <p>Much fainter sounds than that of Dr. Munk's loudspeaker propagate over large distances through the oceanic waveguide, and some naturalists believe that deep-diving marine mammals, including Wedell seals and whales, may use the sound guide as a channel for acoustic communication and for tracking prey.</p>
        <p>"Some environmental groups are concerned that an underwater signal might disturb the behavior of these animals, perhaps disrupting migratory patterns," Dr. Munk said. "We are naturally concerned and are investigating all possible environmental problems, but we believe that our experiment will not cause problems."</p>
        <p>Because of their remarkable ability to conduct sound, oceans are extremely noisy, a fact that complicates the detection and tracking of hostile submarines. The faint noises of submarines are often masked by much louder oceanic noises, especially those caused by cracking and shifting ice in Arctic and Antarctic waters.</p>
        <p>But sounds produced by human beings have significantly increased ocean noise in recent decades. One source of noise is the use of explosives to send pulses of sound into the ocean floor, thereby producing echoes permitting the mapping of sedimentary layers.</p>
        <p>One critic of these and other noises produced by humans is Dr. Arthur A. Myrberg Jr., a marine biologist at the University of Miami.</p>
        <p>"Such noise," he wrote in a recent report, "when added to the oceans' own inherent noise levels, could well create difficulties for those animals that use the acoustical channel for communication and interception."</p>
        <p>The acoustical channel to which he referred is the same one the Heard Island experiment will use.</p>
        <p>Endangered bowhead whales avoid the noise of ocean drilling in the Beaufort Sea, Dr. Myrberg said, and migrating California gray whales avoid areas high in industrial noise.</p>
        <p>Dr. Munk believes that some fears by environmentalists greatly overestimate the hazards to marine wildlife, but that in any case, the Heard Island experiment will proceed cautiously.</p>
        <p>Dr. Munk said that the purpose of the January experiment, lasting nine days, will be merely to determine the feasibility of a full-scale experiment that would continue for 10 years.  "There have been estimates that it would take 100 years of measurements of the atmosphere to achieve 95 percent certainty that the greenhouse effect is, or is not, operating," he said. Measurements of ocean temperature change should yield the same degree of certainty in 10 years.</p>
        <p>"Surely, that is information the world needs," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
