<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Focus Shifts to Rules on Cleaner Air For Car, Chemical and Steel Makers</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="394863"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="THE STRUGGLE IN CONGRESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STEEL AND IRON</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC UTILITIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FEDER, BARNABY J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEVIN, DORON P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HICKS, JONATHAN P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steel and Iron</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DF133CF937A15753C1A966958260" item-length="1465" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Focus Shifts to Rules on Cleaner Air For Car, Chemical and Steel Makers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">The following article was reported and written by Barnaby J. Feder, Doron
 P. Levin and Jonathan P. Hicks.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>No consumer's wallet will go untouched by the Clean Air Act amendments expected to be enacted within days following compromises in the Senate and House.</p>
        <p>Much of the burden will fall initially on several industries that have long expected tighter controls on air pollution, including auto makers, steel producers, the chemical industry and public utilities. How quickly consumers pay for the changes these industries will be asked to make will depend in part on the state of the economy. If the nation tumbles into a recession, as some economists expect, business will have a harder time passing on the costs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>No consumer's wallet will go untouched by the Clean Air Act amendments expected to be enacted within days following compromises in the Senate and House.</p>
        <p>Much of the burden will fall initially on several industries that have long expected tighter controls on air pollution, including auto makers, steel producers, the chemical industry and public utilities. How quickly consumers pay for the changes these industries will be asked to make will depend in part on the state of the economy. If the nation tumbles into a recession, as some economists expect, business will have a harder time passing on the costs.</p>
        <p>In the long run, the bill could cost consumers as much as $50 billion, said David Hale, chief economist for Kemper Financial Services in Chicago. "It will begin to add to the inflation rate in a small way as early as next year," he added.  Worst-Case Scenarios</p>
        <p>Industry executives have tried to envision worst-case scenarios for the impact of the new amendments. Indeed, such theorizing was used to lobby against some of the far-reaching proposals favored by environmental groups. Now that the first round of the battle is over, the conflict will shift to the Environmental Protection Agency, which is charged with drafting regulations putting into effect most of the changes. In the meantime, many executives say, it is hard to make really useful projections without knowing what the E.P.A. intends to do.</p>
        <p>But some things are already clear. Coal-burning utilities will bear the brunt of the changes aimed at curbing acid rain. It is widely assumed that the state public utility boards, which set electricity rates, will have no objection to passing the costs for scrubbing equipment on to consumers as soon as it is installed, especially in states like Ohio and Kentucky, where the equipment will allow utilities to continue to use locally mined coal. Utility executives say that the companies with the most work to do might have to seek rate increases of more than 15 percent to cover their costs.  Technical Incapability Feared</p>
        <p>The goals set for auto makers are equally clear, but industry spokesmen are not as sure that their companies are technically capable of meeting those scheduled to take effect in the late 1990's. The steel industry asserts that it, too, may bump up against technology limits.</p>
        <p>There is one crucial difference between the two industries that leaves steelmakers feeling especially burdened. The laws about cars will be incorporated in the product, affecting all auto makers at home and abroad that hope to sell vehicles in the United States. The laws affecting steel relate to the steelmaking process, which will add to the cost of American steel but have no impact on foreign companies that export steel to the United States.</p>
        <p>Steelmakers might use this difference to argue for tariff barriers, import quotas or other protection from foreign competition in order to make it easier to pass on to consumers the costs of meeting the air pollution laws.</p>
        <p>Chemical makers point out that the big industries affected by the new amendments, including their own, tend to be heavy users of electricity. Thus, they will pay both for the costs of new controls on their toxic products and for the higher cost of energy from utilities that pay for scrubbers and other equipment to reduce acid rain.</p>
        <p>Following is a closer look at how three major industries are reacting to the new amendments:</p>
        <p>Autos</p>
        <p>The provisions affecting auto makers are among the most specific in the clean air agreement. They identify key pollutants emitted at the tailpipe and set targets for reducing them.</p>
        <p>The first round of reductions begins in 1994 and, according to the Chrysler Corporation, will cost several hundred dollars a car. They include a requirement that non-methane hydrocarbon emissions be reduced in phases by 1997 to 0.25 gram a mile from 0.41 gram and nitrogen oxide emissions be cut to 0.4 gram from one gram.</p>
        <p>The targets will be halved again between the turn of the century and 2004. Auto makers say that meeting those goals, or even those for 1997, may be more than they can cope with technologically at a reasonable price. "We don't know how to meet the provisions that begin in the late 1990's," said a Chrysler spokesman.</p>
        <p>The General Motors Corporation also served notice that it had doubts about the technological feasibility of the longer-range requirements.</p>
        <p>Challenge for Toyota</p>
        <p>The Toyota Motor Corporation, Japan's largest car maker, said that meeting the requirements would be a challenge and might be possible only by building cars that got poorer gasoline mileage. The Ford Motor Company said that one positive side of the compromise was that it took into account some of the industry's worries about the timetables set for various changes.</p>
        <p>The changes should not only lower tailpipe emissions but lead to more durable pollution control equipment on cars. Auto makers will be required to certify that the equipment will be effective for 10 years or 100,000 miles, double the current standards.</p>
        <p>Auto makers also would be compelled to build 150,000 vehicles annually starting in 1996 for an experimental fleet that will operate under stricter California clean air guidelines. That number would rise to 300,000 in 1998.</p>
        <p>Starting in 1994, auto makers would be required to install dashboard gauges that tell whether emission control equipment is working properly.</p>
        <p>"In rough numbers, cars at the end of this process will pollute one-sixth as much as they do now," said Robert Liberatore, Chrysler's executive director of government policy, summing up the overall impact.</p>
        <p>Chemicals</p>
        <p>Chemical manufacturers and trade groups that represent them said yesterday that the compromise clean air legislation offered little relief from requirements they consider expensive and difficult to put into effect.</p>
        <p>"It will lead to continued progress in cleaning our nation's air," said Robert A. Roland, president of the Chemical Manufacturers Association, a Washington-based trade group. "The bad news is that this continued progress won't come without a very high price. In fact, the price Americans will pay will be far more than it should be."</p>
        <p>Some chemical executives harbor concerns that the requirements that companies use the best available control technology will not be flexible enough to accommodate the wide range of chemicals and processes for dealing with them.</p>
        <p>Six-Year Extension Hailed</p>
        <p>Still, some chemical companies hailed provisions in the compromise legislation that would give chemical manufacturers six more years to comply with new emission standards if they reduced their toxic emissions by 90 percent from their 1987 level ahead of the 1994 deadline. (Even a reduction of 90 percent would not meet the new standards.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Roland said the cost of putting the legislation into effect would be "somewhere around $40 billion to $50 billion a year, and that will be on top of the $32 billion a year we already spend as a nation on cleaning our air."  Steel</p>
        <p>The American steel industry, which found previous versions of the clean air legislation unpalatable, has been far more amenable to the amendments as completed by the House and Senate conference committee.</p>
        <p>Steelmakers were disturbed by a requirement, in earlier versions, that they eliminate virtually all emissions from coke ovens by the year 2020 and in the meantime adopt the best available emissions reduction technology by 1995. Coke ovens are the furnaces that convert coal to coke in making steel.</p>
        <p>Steel industry officials contended that meeting the 1995 deadline would cost the industry about $5 billion, which they said they could ill afford.</p>
        <p>Under the House and Senate compromise measure, the industry does not have to adopt the best available technology to reduce emissions leakage in coke ovens until 2020 and in the meantime must reduce emissions gradually under guidelines to be formulated by the E.P.A.  More Stringent Standards</p>
        <p>The industry will have to meet progressively more stringent standards in 1993, 1995, 1998 and 2010. But the compromise no longer mandates that virtually all emissions be eliminated by 2020.</p>
        <p>David M. Anderson, general manager of environmental affairs at the Bethlehem Steel Corporation, said yesterday that the extension until 2020 was crucial to the American steel industry's competitive position. "Without the extension, the legislation could have shut down two-thirds of domestic coke ovens by 2003," he added.</p>
        <p>But Milton Deaner, president of the American Iron and Steel Institute, the industry trade group, complained that the clean air compromise still created far more stringent requirements for the steel industry than for other industrial groups.</p>
        <p>THE STRUGGLE IN CONGRESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
