<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reviving Nuclear Power From Its Coma</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="401753"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDD123BF93BA25752C1A966958260" item-length="467" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reviving Nuclear Power From Its Coma</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nuclear power has been comatose in the United States for more than a decade. The last nuclear plant order was placed in 1978, the year before the accident at Three Mile Island terrified the public and sent chills up the spines of utility executives who suddenly realized how easily a multibillion-dollar plant might be wiped out.</p>
        <p>But now, in an effort to revive itself, the nuclear power industry has issued a "strategic plan" designed to encourage the ordering of new plants by the mid-1990's, with the first to start operating by the turn of the century. The plan is both optimistic and limited but well worth pursuing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nuclear power has been comatose in the United States for more than a decade. The last nuclear plant order was placed in 1978, the year before the accident at Three Mile Island terrified the public and sent chills up the spines of utility executives who suddenly realized how easily a multibillion-dollar plant might be wiped out.</p>
        <p>But now, in an effort to revive itself, the nuclear power industry has issued a "strategic plan" designed to encourage the ordering of new plants by the mid-1990's, with the first to start operating by the turn of the century. The plan is both optimistic and limited but well worth pursuing.</p>
        <p>The need for the nuclear power option has been growing with every new woe that strikes fossil fuels. Coal, the chief source of electricity, will rise in cost and unacceptability as the new Clean Air Act clamps down. And the Persian Gulf crisis has underscored the vulnerability of oil supplies. Although most electric utilities have largely weaned themselves from foreign oil, some 6 percent of the electricity in this country is still generated by burning oil -- and the amount is rising. Judicious use of nuclear plants could halt that trend.</p>
        <p>More important in the long run, the threat of global warming, while far from proven, casts an ever-darker shadow over the prospects for burning coal, oil or natural gas. All such fossil fuels emit carbon dioxide, a "greenhouse gas" which traps heat in the atmosphere and might eventually cause a disastrous rise in global temperatures. Nuclear power plants emit no carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Thus the plan issued last week by a committee of nuclear and utility executives is a welcome step toward keeping the nuclear option available. The plan envisages using new types of reactors -- now being built abroad with participation by American companies -- that are evolutionary improvements over existing light-water reactors. These are supposedly 10 times safer, but still fall far short of the "inherently safe" designs sought by nuclear critics.</p>
        <p>The plan also calls for standardized nuclear plants, to improve the predictability of costs and building schedules and to reduce the regulatory burden imposed by custom-built plants. And it proposes streamlining the regulatory process and making it easier for new plants to obtain funding.</p>
        <p>Most of the steps seem reasonable and many are already under way. But the plan focuses primarily on procedural or institutional changes. It does not solve the more important substantive issues that have turned the public away from nuclear power. Until the industry shows that its plants can be operated with a near-perfect safety record, that radioactive waste can be disposed of and that financial risks can be brought under control, nuclear power in this country will continue to languish.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
