<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seabrook Nuclear Plant Doesn't Deserve License</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="336372"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MASSACHUSETTS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW HAMPSHIRE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SEABROOK NUCLEAR POWER PLANT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUKAKIS, MICHAEL S (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD81730F933A15750C0A966958260" item-length="529" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seabrook Nuclear Plant Doesn't Deserve License</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>''Clean Power's Strange Enemies'' (editorial, March 12) charges that the opposition of Massachusetts to the Seabrook nuclear plant in New Hampshire has cost the plant an extra $2 billion and hinders our country's efforts to control global warming. You have long criticized Gov. Mario M. Cuomo's opposition to the Shoreham, L.I., plant, so it is not surprising that you now turn to Seabrook.</p>
        <p>I have been a strong opponent of the Seabrook plant, but not because I have ''exaggerated the dangers of nuclear power.'' I am not an opponent of nuclear power, nor do I exaggerate anything about it. We have a nuclear plant in Rowe, Mass., with an excellent record. What I have done is fight the licensing of the Seabrook plant because I believe there is no way to protect Massachusetts citizens who live nearby if there is a major accident.</p>
        <p>Seabrook, N.H., has the largest summer beach population within four miles of any nuclear plant area. There are only two, two-lane roads leading from the plant. There are inadequate shelters. I have a responsibility to protect people who live in the six Massachusetts towns in the Seabrook evacuation planning zone.</p>
        <p>Because we have found no safe way to evacuate people in case of accident, this plant poses a major threat to our health and safety, and I cannot in good conscience support it.</p>
        <p>You say I am at least partly to blame that Seabrook is so expensive and that my ''unrepentant'' office says the investors knew the risks they were taking. We raised evacuation safety issues with the Nuclear Regulatory Commission 16 years ago before construction began. It was the N.R.C., not my office, that said investors knew the risks they were taking and that the concerns of Massachusetts would be heard in court later. If the N.R.C. had addressed safety then, everyone would have saved time and money. My office has never, ever, been cavalier about the costs of the Seabrook plant, in part, because they will affect New England consumers.</p>
        <p>After having followed the prescribed evacuation planning for several years, Massachusetts decided there was no plan that could protect the public adequately and thereafter refused to participate in the process. In contrast, the N.R.C. continually changed the rules, ignored its own process and pushed ahead to license this plant. Seabrook is not in compliance with licensing regulations. If it had been, it would have been licensed years ago.</p>
        <p>Seabrook is also not the answer to the global warming problem. It may not create much carbon dioxide during operation, but it does create tons of high-level radioactive waste that will remain toxic for 240,000 years. Keeping Seabrook shut will prevent a serious, long-term, public health and safety problem for New England. It makes far greater sense to spend our precious dollars on energy efficiency and renewable resources that do not harm the environment and can substantially reduce global warming.</p>
        <p>Finally, you also say that we should keep the nuclear option open. I agree. There may be safe sources of nuclear energy. But Seabrook isn't one of them.</p>
        <p>MICHAEL S. DUKAKIS</p>
        <p>Governor of Massachusetts</p>
        <p>Boston, March 15, 1990</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
