<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEW YORK WANTS CLEANEST AIR ACT</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="385997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DE123BF930A1575AC0A966958260" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEW YORK WANTS CLEANEST AIR ACT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: New York City officials, faced with continuing violations of Federal smog and carbon monoxide standards, are pressing for adoption of the strongest anti-pollution measures Congress is considering as it tries to agree on amendments to the Clean Air Act.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: New York City officials, faced with continuing violations of Federal smog and carbon monoxide standards, are pressing for adoption of the strongest anti-pollution measures Congress is considering as it tries to agree on amendments to the Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>New York City officials, faced with continuing violations of Federal smog and carbon monoxide standards, are pressing for adoption of the strongest anti-pollution measures Congress is considering as it tries to agree on amendments to the Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>The 142 House and 7 Senate conferees met all summer in Washington to resolve differences between the revisions to the act that were passed by each house this spring. The 20-year-old Clean Air Act has not been revised since 1977.</p>
        <p>Both bills would require major changes by businesses, particularly in the most polluted cities like New York, which will ultimately cost everyone more money. The Bush Administration estimated recently that the total economic cost would be at least $35 billion a year.</p>
        <p>Congressional conferees have reached the part of the 700-page bill that addresses motor vehicles, the source of much of New York City's air pollution. Decisions in the next few days about tailpipe-emission controls and clean-burning fuels will heavily influence when and if New Yorkers will be able to breathe healthy air.</p>
        <p>Expensive Ozone Control</p>
        <p>The conferees have already agreed to the House version of provisions to reduce smog from industrial sources. The House bill, supported by New York officials because it requires greater regulation of industrial sources, allows the city 17 more years to attain the Federal ozone standard.</p>
        <p>The industrial-smog provisions would have far-reaching effects in the New York area. Even small businesses like dry cleaners and bakeries would have to install expensive ozone-control devices. Vehicle-control measures like car-pooling and high-occupancy vehicle lanes would most likely have to be ordered in an effort to reduce or slow the growth of traffic.</p>
        <p>Ozone, the primary component of smog, is formed when hydrocarbons and oxides of nitrogen mix in the atmosphere in sunlight. Almost half the hydrocarbon emissions in New York come from mobile sources like cars and trucks; the rest come from sources like industrial plants, gasoline stations and paints and hairspray. Ninety percent of carbon monoxide emissions come from motor vehicles.</p>
        <p>In recent letters to members of the New York State Congressional delegation and influential Senators and Representatives, Mayor David N. Dinkins and the city's Environmental Protection Commissioner, Albert F. Appleton, said they sought the strongest possible Federal air pollution program, especially for motor vehicles.</p>
        <p>Fought by Auto and Oil Concerns</p>
        <p>''We need a tough, comprehensive mobile-source program with the strictest standards for tailpipe emissions,'' Mr. Appleton wrote. ''We need aggressive alternative fuel vehicles by bus operators, fleet operators and taxis, and mandatory use of reformulated gasoline and oxygenated fuel.''</p>
        <p>But New York is unlikely to get all that it wants in the motor vehicle and fuels section of the clean-air bill. For one thing, it has asked for measures that are not in either bill. And the automobile and oil industries have fought hard in the House and Senate to limit what they will have to do to comply with the act. Congressional staff members said last week that those industries were pressing conferees to further weaken the provisions, particularly rules for reformulated gasoline and clean-fuel vehicles for fleets.</p>
        <p>Both issues are important to New York. Widespread use of specially blended gasoline, which produces emissions that cause less buildup in the ozone layer, could give the city 20 percent of the reductions it needs to meet Federal smog standards without a big increase in the cost of fuel, environmental groups say.</p>
        <p>Dinkins Pledges Cleaner Fleets</p>
        <p>Irrespective of Federal mandates, the Dinkins administration has committed itself to buying more vehicles for city fleets that run on cleaner-burning fuels like natural gas. In general, the city views fleets - groups of private or government vehicles that can be centrally fueled - as important to air quality because they represent a high percentage of midtown traffic. But conferees are discussing limiting the categories of vehicles, like heavy-duty trucks, that would be required to convert to cleaner-burning fuels, Congressional staff members said.</p>
        <p>Also, the House bill calls for a pilot program in California, where pollution is most severe, mandating the sale of thousands of individually owned cars that run on cleaner-burning fuels. New York has asked to join the program.</p>
        <p>There are doubts about the conferees' ability to complete discussions before adjournment, scheduled for early October, but there is a chance they will return for a session after the November elections.</p>
        <p>Besides motor vehicles and fuels, the conferees still have to deal with the contentious issues of hazardous air emissions and acid rain. It took them the entire summer to get this far, in part because the crisis in the Middle East and the nation's budget problems are dominating legislators' attention.</p>
        <p>But powerful legislators like Representative John D. Dingell, Democrat of Michigan and chairman of the House Energy and Commerce Committee, say they want a bill this year. Mr. Dingell, who has helped block clean-air legislation in past years, said in Washington last week that he was ''strongly committed'' to a House-Senate accord as soon as possible.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists have said the Senate bill has stronger rules on motor vehicle emissions and the House measure is tougher on urban smog.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
