<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="332666"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDC173FF934A35750C0A966958260" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>Mitsubishi and Daimler-Benz are negotiating a plan of ''intensive cooperation'' in automobile technology, aerospace, microelectronics and a number of service industries. It may prove to be one of the most far-reaching industrial linkups ever and could pose an enormous competitive challenge for the U.S.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>Mitsubishi and Daimler-Benz are negotiating a plan of ''intensive cooperation'' in automobile technology, aerospace, microelectronics and a number of service industries. It may prove to be one of the most far-reaching industrial linkups ever and could pose an enormous competitive challenge for the U.S.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>Mitsubishi and Daimler-Benz are negotiating a plan of ''intensive cooperation'' in automobile technology, aerospace, microelectronics and a number of service industries. It may prove to be one of the most far-reaching industrial linkups ever and could pose an enormous competitive challenge for the U.S. [Page A1.]  The talks between the giant industrial groups are an attempt by both companies to position themselves before the European Community forms a single, borderless market by the end of 1992, analysts said. [D5.]</p>
        <p>The Soviet Parliament approved a property law giving private citizens the right to own small-scale factories and other businesses for the first time since the 1920's. [A1.]</p>
        <p>THE ECONOMY</p>
        <p>Orders received by the nation's factories fell in January at the steepest rate in 15 years, the Commerce Department said, reflecting a slump in the nation's manufacturing sector. [D1.]</p>
        <p>The Postal Service proposed an increase in all classes of mail that would raise a first-class stamp to 30 cents. [A16.]</p>
        <p>COMPANIES</p>
        <p>Some restrictions on A.T.&amp;T. should be removed, the F.C.C. chairman said, because enough competition exists. [D1.]</p>
        <p>Perrier is returning - today in France and by early April in America. A big marketing challenge lies ahead. [D1.]</p>
        <p>The Commerce Department is reworking proposed rules that would ease restrictions on exports of high-performance computers, agency officials said. [D2.]</p>
        <p>De Beers Consolidated Mines will split itself in two and base one of the newly formed companies in Switzerland. [D4.]</p>
        <p>Time Warner announced a joint venture with the Soviet film industry to build movie theaters in Moscow and Leningrad [D8] . The company will also start the country's first children's book club, offering a monthly selection of reading. [D17.]</p>
        <p>The Sunday Correspondent, seen as a likely casualty in Britain's ''quality'' Sunday newspaper war, announced new financing and a new shareholder. [D20.]</p>
        <p>Centaur Partners, in its effort to control National Intergroup, made two proposals that will ease its way. [D4.]</p>
        <p>BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY</p>
        <p>Sports cars and automatic transmissions have never mixed well. Porsche hopes to change all that. [D6.]</p>
        <p>A robot that can vacuum office buildings without assistance has been developed by a Canadian inventor. [D6.]</p>
        <p>MARKETS</p>
        <p>A decline in bond yields helped push stocks higher, with the Dow industrials advancing 27.25 points, to 2,676.80. Volume on the New York Stock Exchange remained relatively light. [D8.]</p>
        <p>Prices of Treasury notes and bonds rose in thin trading, as many dealers who sold on Monday became buyers. [D14.]</p>
        <p>The dollar closed mostly higher in domestic trading after falling overseas in the absence of any major developments to move the foreign exchange markets. [D15.]</p>
        <p>Most livestock and meat futures rose strongly on the Chicago Merc, helped by short-term demand and favorable shipping weather. Soybeans soared, grains were mixed and coffee fell. [D15.]</p>
        <p>TODAY'S COLUMNS</p>
        <p>''New'' Coke will get a new name and will take on Pepsi, Coca-Cola confirmed. Randall Rothenberg: Advertising. [D1.]</p>
        <p>Cutting ''greenhouse effect'' gases in the U.S. just 20 percent would cost trillions of dollars, two economists say, but that's not the really bad news. Peter Passell: Economic Scene. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Investors have abandoned stocks of many debt-laden companies, but this may have left some good buys. Market Place. [D8.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
