<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TOO MANY, TOO RICH, TOO WASTEFUL</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="339797"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BEAN, FRANK D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">EHRLICH, PAUL R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">EHRLICH, ANNE H</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">POPULATION EXPLOSION, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D6103FF932A35757C0A966958260" item-length="1035" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TOO MANY, TOO RICH, TOO WASTEFUL</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK D. BEAN; Frank D. Bean is director of the Population Studies Center at the Urban Institute in Washington and teaches sociology at the University of Texas, Austin.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BEAN, FRANK D</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>THE POPULATION EXPLOSION</p>
        <p>By Paul R. Ehrlich and Anne H. Ehrlich.</p>
        <p>320 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $18.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>THE POPULATION EXPLOSION</p>
        <p>By Paul R. Ehrlich and Anne H. Ehrlich.</p>
        <p>320 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $18.95.</p>
        <p>THE POPULATION EXPLOSION</p>
        <p>By Paul R. Ehrlich and Anne H. Ehrlich.</p>
        <p>320 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $18.95.</p>
        <p>At the end of World War II there were about 2.4 billion people in the world. Now there are 5.3 billion. If current rates of growth (about 1.7 percent annually) continue, nearly a billion more people will be sharing the planet by the year 2000. In ''The Population Explosion,'' Paul R. Ehrlich, the Bing Professor of Population Studies at Stanford University, and Anne H. Ehrlich, a senior research associate in biological sciences at Stanford, advance the neo-Malthusian thesis that we are rushing headlong toward disaster because of overpopulation. Our numbers are too large in relation to the ecosystem, they argue, and unless interventionist policies are adopted, the global population will soon be subjected to natural forces (perhaps massive increases in death rates) that will bring it back into balance.</p>
        <p>The Ehrlichs find evidence for concern in such examples of environmental degradation and resource exhaustion as global warming, acid rain, topsoil erosion, ground water depletion, destruction of the ozone layer, desertification and deforestation. By environmental standards, wealthier countries are at least as guilty of overpopulation as are poorer countries because, although their populations may be smaller and growing less rapidly, they consume more resources per capita, and they rely on more disruptive technologies. They are more likely, for example, to get about in automobiles than on bicycles.</p>
        <p>Environmental degradation is a serious problem. The exhaustion of nonrenewable resources, though the evidence is less clear-cut, may be equally serious. Certainly, the facts on balance seem to indicate that both are worsening. Less obvious, however, is what causes these problems.</p>
        <p>We can point to three factors: population, level of affluence and technology - that is, the number of people, how much they consume and the degree to which their consumption generates environmental degradation. Since the publication of the Ehrlichs' ''Population Bomb'' two decades ago, a debate has raged over which of these factors is most important. Then as now, the Ehrlichs emphasized population, although in this new book they are careful not to neglect the roles played by affluence and technology. Others, most notably Barry Commoner, have argued that technology is paramount, especially in developed countries like the United States. From a policy perspective, this dispute may be comparatively less important than identifying which of the factors can be most easily and rapidly changed.</p>
        <p>The contribution of this book is to call attention to the importance of the population factor. The Ehrlichs' background in population biology has sensitized them to the fact that overpopulation may lead to system failure even if it is not the initial cause of pollution or resource exhaustion.</p>
        <p>But the Ehrlichs may be criticized both for overstating their case and for underestimating the capacity of human institutions and technologies to change. What is the likelihood that institutional and technological adaptation will occur fast enough to deal with current and prospective problems? It is not easy to know the answer. The experience of the past 20 years is mixed. On the one hand, we have witnessed the results of the green revolution in agriculture and improvements in air quality following the imposition of automotive emission standards. On the other hand, we have seen the discovery of ozone depletion, deforestation and acid rain as major environmental problems.</p>
        <p>The continued dangers of environmental degradation suggest that it would be prudent to address the population factor, especially since we have evidence that most of the world's women want to have fewer children than they are at present likely to have. Yet even if replacement-level birth rates were to be reached this year (an impossible goal), the present age structure of the world's population would keep it growing for another 50 to 60 years, something demographers call ''population momentum.'' Given this and the likely continuation of adverse technological effects, it is not merely prudent but imperative that we confront population issues, and do so now. Even though this readable and interesting book occasionally presents its message in overly dramatic terms, it is the Ehrlichs' most effective statement of these conclusions yet.</p>
        <p>AS MEXICO GOES, SO GO WE</p>
        <p>Americans must find a way to integrate migration policy with a comprehensive population policy. This is especially important because net immigration now makes up something on the order of 25 percent of the growth of the American population. If a national goal of ending and then reversing population growth is established, as it should be, then it will be important to decide how much of the input side of our population equation is to be made up by natural births, and how much by net immigration.</p>
        <p>This is a particularly vexing problem because of our traditional welcoming attitude toward immigrants. . . . If the United States is going to avoid even more serious problems of overpopulation, its people are inevitably trapped in a zero-sum game; every immigrant admitted must be compensated for by a birth forgone. This will require either a further lowering of American birthrates (which are already low enough to bring an end to natural increase eventually) or much more attention to the problems of restricting immigration in the future. Booming populations in desperately poor nations are bound to make the comparatively affluent United States a target for ever more migrants.</p>
        <p>Much of the attention to immigration questions in the United States is focused around the flow of immigrants from Mexico. . . . The border is too long, the ties across it are too tight, and the difference in average wages is too great for a ''Great Wall'' policy to succeed. The only way that the tide is likely to be stemmed is through creative policies that simultaneously help Mexico to control its own population and substantially improve the standard of living of Mexicans within their homeland.</p>
        <p>From ''The Population Explosion.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
