<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>House, 401-21, Votes to Widen Clean Air Curbs</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="356072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERKE, RICHARD L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DINGELL, JOHN D (REPR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DC1638F937A15756C0A966958260" item-length="1359" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>House, 401-21, Votes to Widen Clean Air Curbs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERKE, RICHARD L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The House of Representatives late tonight overwhelmingly approved the first major overhaul of environmental laws in 13 years, rebuffing warnings from the White House that some provisions were ''unnecessarily costly.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The House of Representatives late tonight overwhelmingly approved the first major overhaul of environmental laws in 13 years, rebuffing warnings from the White House that some provisions were ''unnecessarily costly.''</p>
        <p>The House of Representatives late tonight overwhelmingly approved the first major overhaul of environmental laws in 13 years, rebuffing warnings from the White House that some provisions were ''unnecessarily costly.''</p>
        <p>Before the 401-to-21 vote, lawmakers resolved several lingering items, passing provisions for a program to assist workers whose jobs would be affected by the measure, a pilot program requiring the sales of alternative-fuel cars in Southern California, and expanded warranties for emission-control equipment.</p>
        <p>Representative John D. Dingell, the chairman of the Energy and Commerce Committee, whose decision to compromise on many elements of the legislation cleared the way for passage, said after the vote that the bill was ''a good piece of legislation'' but that it would take a toll on the public.</p>
        <p>''Everybody is going to find out that clean air is not free,'' said the Michigan Democrat. ''There are enormous costs in terms of jobs.''</p>
        <p>Estimates of $20 Billion a Year</p>
        <p>The bill, which by some estimates would cost industry $20 billion a year, would greatly strengthen the Clean Air Act of 1970, with broad new air quality standards, curbs on automobile emissions, requirements for the sale of cleaner-burning fuels and a program to cut emissions that cause acid rain. Representatives from industry and environmental groups say neither the House nor the Senate version of the legislation is particularly stronger than the other, although there are some differences in specific provisions. The Senate version was approved last month.</p>
        <p>Despite earlier warnings that he would recommend a veto of amendments that the House approved today, John H. Sununu, the White House chief of staff, said he would urge Mr. Bush to support the package.</p>
        <p>'A Lot of Fine Tuning'</p>
        <p>Mr. Sununu said that while he preferred elements of the version passed by the Senate, he was optimistic that provisions opposed by the Administration would be deleted when the measure goes to a House-Senate conference.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot of fine-tuning that has to be done,'' Mr. Sununu said in an interview. ''On the principles of the bill, most of what is coming out is consistent with the President's approach. Our recommendation is to proceed to the Senate and House conference.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dingell, commenting on the bill's prospects in negotiations between the chambers, said: ''You're going to see a very interesting conference where the results are difficult to predict.''</p>
        <p>Environmentalists Welcome Bill</p>
        <p>Environmental groups welcomed passage of the bill tonight, but they were restrained in their comments.</p>
        <p>''If the conferees choose the best parts of the two bills, they can fashion a good law and the nation will benefit,'' said Richard E. Ayres, chairman of the National Clean Air Coalition, which represents several organizations supporting stronger environmental laws. ''If, on the other hand, they choose the weakest portions of the two bills, the result will delay unacceptably the pollution control needed to protect public health.''</p>
        <p>Industry groups said they would press for many changes when the legislation goes to conference.</p>
        <p>Thomas R. Kuhn, president of the Edison Electric Institute, which represents electric companies, said tonight, ''Although specific compromises were reached which address some of our concerns, issues are still pending which could increase the five to seven billion-dollar price tag for electric consumers.''</p>
        <p>While it took six weeks of floor fights in the Senate to pass the bill, the House acted quickly, resolving most of the disputes in private negotiations. The measure was not introduced in the House until Monday.</p>
        <p>Debate Was Heated</p>
        <p>After a heated debate that focused not on the environment but on economics, the House rebuffed pressure from the White House and from industry, passing a measure that would provide $250 million in unemployment and retraining benefits for workers who lose their jobs because of the law.</p>
        <p>The amendment, sponsored by Representative Bob Wise, Democrat of West Virginia, was approved in a vote of 274 to 146, although a broader assistance program proposed by Senator Robert C. Byrd, Democrat of West Virginia, failed by one vote in the Senate. The measure was intended to help an estimated 5,000 coal miners who could lose their jobs because of the tougher acid rain provisions in the House bill.</p>
        <p>''We've taken care of industry's interests, we've taken care of the environmental interests,'' Mr. Wise said. ''And it's time to take care of the people's interests.''</p>
        <p>The workers' compensation amendment was of particular concern to Administration officials. In a letter Tuesday to House Speaker Thomas S. Foley, Mr. Sununu and William K. Reilly, administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, warned that the provision ''would open a multibillion-dollar deficit-increasing door that may never be closed.'' The two men raised their concerns in a meeting this morning with House Republicans.</p>
        <p>But in the interview later in the day, Mr. Sununu backed off from suggestions that the amendment would prompt a Presidential veto.</p>
        <p>Approval on Warranties</p>
        <p>The House also approved an amendment that would lengthen the warranties that parts and vehicle manufacturers must provide for emission-control equipment. Under the provision, the manufacturer, rather than the car buyer, is liable for many of the repairs of pollution-control equipment. A similar provision is contained in the Senate bill.</p>
        <p>''This amendment insures that neither consumers nor the environment gets stuck with the bill for faulty equipment and that independent garages get a fair break,'' said Representative Gerry Sikorski, a Minnesota Democrat and a chief sponsor of the amendment.</p>
        <p>A potentially serious jurisdictional dispute was averted when the House rejected an amendment by Representative Dan Rostenkowski, Democrat of Illinois and chairman of the Ways and Means Committee, that would have deleted user fees and tariffs from many of the bill's provisions. Mr. Rostenkowski had contended that the provisions were taxes and should have come under his committee's authority.</p>
        <p>Another point of contention that was resolved earlier today and passed by a wide margin was an amendment that would reduce production of chlorofluorocarbons and other chemicals that destroy the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Final Point of Contention</p>
        <p>It was not until late tonight, in a deal brokered by Speaker Foley, that an agreement was reached on the last point of contention that was the subject of vigorous negotiations throughout the day: The deal diluted a requirement co-authored by Representative Henry A. Waxman, Democrat of California, that automobile manufacturers each year produce a million vehicles that burn a cleaner fuel, beginning in the middle 1990's in the nation's most polluted cities.</p>
        <p>The Waxman plan was opposed by Representative Dingell, who is a staunch ally of the automobile industry. And, although a clean-fuel vehicle provision was contained in the Administration's original clean air proposal, Mr. Sununu said the House plan went too far in dictating certain types of fuels that would have to be used by the cars.</p>
        <p>Specifically, in the agreement reached tonight, the amendment would strike the requirement that a million clean-fuel vehicles be produced each year and instead establish a pilot program under which 150,000 cars that use alternative fuel would have to be sold in Southern California in 1994. The number would increase to 300,000 new cars a year beginning in 1997.</p>
        <p>After the vote tonight, Mr. Waxman cited the clean-vehicle measure as perhaps the most significant in the legislation. ''It is a foot in the door,'' he said. ''California will lead the way. I think the rest of the country will be following our example.''</p>
        <p>Despite Mr. Waxman's optimism, the Clean Air Working Group, a coalition of business and trade associations, expressed serious reservations about the overall legislation. ''The air quality debate in Congress is ignoring the simple guideline that new legislation be both effective and affordable,'' said William D. Fay, administrator of the organization.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
