<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LICENSE IS GRANTED TO NUCLEAR PLANT IN NEW HAMPSHIRE</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="331095"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW HAMPSHIRE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MASSACHUSETTS</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NUCLEAR REGULATORY COMMISSION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SEABROOK NUCLEAR POWER PLANT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUNUNU, JOHN H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900302T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDE103BF931A35750C0A966958260" item-length="1286" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LICENSE IS GRANTED TO NUCLEAR PLANT IN NEW HAMPSHIRE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>BETHESDA, Md., March 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Nuclear Regulatory Commission voted today to give an operating license to the Seabrook nuclear reactor, the New Hampshire plant that many experts consider the most fought-over nuclear project in America.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Nuclear Regulatory Commission voted today to give an operating license to the Seabrook nuclear reactor, the New Hampshire plant that many experts consider the most fought-over nuclear project in America.</p>
        <p>The Nuclear Regulatory Commission voted today to give an operating license to the Seabrook nuclear reactor, the New Hampshire plant that many experts consider the most fought-over nuclear project in America.</p>
        <p>Opponents, including officials in the neighboring state of Massachusetts, say they plan to appeal the decision in court almost immediately, but some acknowledged that full-power operation is likely by summer.</p>
        <p>The commission's 3-to-0 vote was a victory for the position of John H. Sununu, the White House chief of staff who, as Governor of New Hampshire, pushed hard for completion and licensing of the plant.</p>
        <p>Companies and Careers Affected</p>
        <p>The start-up of Seabrook is 11 years behind schedule and the cost, $6.45 billion, is now 12 times the original estimate.</p>
        <p>On its tortuous road to completion, the plant created the first bankruptcy of an investor-owned electric utility since the Depression, the Public Service Company of New Hampshire, and is widely credited with ending the career of a New Hampshire Governor, Meldrim Thompson Jr., who favored the plant, and helping pick a Democratic Presidential nominee, Gov. Michael S. Dukakis of Massachusetts, whose fight against the plant as Governor won him votes in the New Hampshire Presidential primary.</p>
        <p>More than 3,000 people have been arrested over the years trying to block construction, in a salt marsh in the coastal town of Seabrook. And millions of consumers in all six New England states, along with thousands of shareholders of the 16 companies that have had a hand in building the plant, have felt its effects.</p>
        <p>The vote today, conducted under heavy security, was expected and generated no debate among the commissioners. The three members who voted to grant the license were the chairman, Kenneth M. Carr, Thomas M. Roberts and Kenneth C. Rogers. The two other commissioners, Forrest J. Remick and James R. Curtiss, excused themselves from voting.</p>
        <p>Although several questions remain about the adequacy of plans to evacuate the area within 10 miles of Seabrook in case of an emergency, Mr. Carr said before the brief meeting this morning, ''We believe the license should be issued and that the plant can be operated safely.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Carr was booed by a dozen Seabrook opponents who wore gas masks and anti-contamination coveralls of the type worn by nuclear workers and carried signs reading, ''Radiation equals death.''</p>
        <p>After the vote, about 50 protesters gathered in Seabrook outside the plant gates and shouted, ''It's not over until it's over.'' By late afternoon the group had swelled to about 125, and more than 30 protesters had been arrested for blocking traffic and trespassing, The Associated Press reported.</p>
        <p>Touting of Benefits</p>
        <p>Even before the vote, Seabrook's supporters and opponents distributed statements of reaction. Harold B. Finger, president of the U.S. Council for Energy Awareness, a group that campaigns for nuclear power, said, ''There's no question that as time goes on even the people who opposed Seabrook will recognize its benefits to their region and their way of life. It will light the homes and run the factories of New England while emitting no greenhouse gases and while displacing 11 million barrels of oil every year.''</p>
        <p>But Senator Edward M. Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts, said the vote was ''the culmination of a long line of irresponsible 'public-be-damned' decisions by the N.R.C. He called the commission ''a rogue agency that lives by its own set of pro-industry rules.''</p>
        <p>The Senator noted that before the plant was licensed the commission changed its rules to allow consideration of emergency plans written by utilities instead of public officials. Massachusetts had refused to submit plans for its six towns within 10 miles of the plant, deciding after the Chernobyl accident in the Soviet Union that planning would be futile.</p>
        <p>Bleak Outlook on Appeals</p>
        <p>The commissioners authorized the staff to issue a license on March 8, but said that if appeals were filed in Federal court the staff should wait until March 15, to give the court time to act.</p>
        <p>While many opponents are optimistic about the appeal, Michael Mariotte, of the Nuclear Information and Resource Service, an anti-nuclear group, said, ''The history of these appeals has not been good.''</p>
        <p>Representative Peter H. Kostmayer, Democrat of Pennsylvania, announced that the House Interior Subcommittee on General Oversight and Investigations would hold a hearing on March 30 to investigate the commission's decision today.</p>
        <p>Even Seabrook's supporters say the plant's travails helped destroy the domestic nuclear industry.</p>
        <p>''What happened to us in building the plant is indicative of why no one will ever do it again, without drastic changes in the regulatory system and in financing,'' said Richard H. Bornemann, a vice president of the United Illuminating Company, of New Haven, the largest surviving builder of Seabrook.</p>
        <p>Years of Litigation</p>
        <p>Public Service decided in January 1972 to build twin reactors at Seabrook, at a cost of $973 million. Two years later Massachusetts began legal action to block construction, arguing that emergency evacuation would be impossible.</p>
        <p>That issue was to be the last, and most expensive snag. A year after the 1979 nuclear accident at Three Mile Island in Pennsylvania, after work was under way at Seabrook, the N.R.C. instituted stricter rules that required states and towns to submit plans for sheltering and evacuating the people within 10 miles of a plant, before the reactor could be licensed.</p>
        <p>Work on those plans for Seabrook proceeded until spring 1986, when the Chernobyl accident prompted Governor Dukakis to delay submitting plans for Massachusetts towns. He finally declined to submit any plans.</p>
        <p>Many towns in both Massachusetts and New Hampshire favored trying to block the plant by boycotting evacuation planning. But in New Hampshire, Governor Sununu had the state step in to submit the plans, over the towns' objections. He had previously spoken vigorously in favor of Seabrook, and favored amending a New Hampshire law that denied Public Service any money for the plant until it was finished. Later, after Mr. Sununu had become chief of staff, President Bush signed an executive order authorizing Federal preparation of such plans.</p>
        <p>Seabrook's builders wrote the evacuation plans for Massachusetts, and the N.R.C. changed its rules to accept those plans.</p>
        <p>Only 4 Left in Pipeline</p>
        <p>Assuming that appeals fail, Seabrook would be the 110th commercial reactor in this country. Only four are in the pipeline. On Feb. 8, Comanche Peak 1, in Somervell County, Tex., received a test license, like the one Seabrook received last year, and Comanche Peak 2 and Watts Bar 1 and 2, in Spring City, Tenn., are under construction. The Shoreham reactor, on Long Island, is finished but under an agreement with New York State, will never operate. All the plants ordered since 1974 have been canceled.</p>
        <p>Before today, the license most recently issued last August was for the Philadelphia Electric Company's Limerick 2 plant, near Pottstown, Pa.; the reactor entered commercial operation this January.</p>
        <p>In their planned appeals to the United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia, the opponents say they will argue that Seabrook should not operate because a licensing appeals board within the N.R.C. found four flaws in the emergency evacuation plan. One is that while an emergency could require that tens of thousands of people on nearby beaches take shelter from fallout there is no plan for sheltering them.</p>
        <p>But a panel of administrative law judges hearing the license application said Seabrook should be licensed anyway, and the N.R.C. agreed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
