<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Life-Cycle Studies: Imperfect Science</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="385786"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="CONSUMER'S WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TELLUS INSTITUTE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MEIER, BARRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHAPIRO, KAREN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CONSUMER'S WORLD PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D81138F931A1575AC0A966958260" item-length="1087" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Life-Cycle Studies: Imperfect Science</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARRY MEIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MEIER, BARRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Scientists are struggling to devise a way to help consumers, regulators and others choose among competing products, like those made from paper or plastic, based on their environmental impact. But researchers say that despite a spate of studies that make such comparisons, a valid method is not likely to be found for years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Scientists are struggling to devise a way to help consumers, regulators and others choose among competing products, like those made from paper or plastic, based on their environmental impact. But researchers say that despite a spate of studies that make such comparisons, a valid method is not likely to be found for years.</p>
        <p>Scientists are struggling to devise a way to help consumers, regulators and others choose among competing products, like those made from paper or plastic, based on their environmental impact. But researchers say that despite a spate of studies that make such comparisons, a valid method is not likely to be found for years.</p>
        <p>''Right now, it is impossible to make these kinds of decisions for 95 percent of the products out there,'' said Dr. Allen Hershkowitz, a senior scientist at the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental advocacy group in New York. And Rodney Parrish, an aquatic biologist at the Federal Environmental Protection Agency, said: ''It is certainly a goal, and it can be done in the future. But to use what is being done now as the basis for policy making would be misleading.''</p>
        <p>At issue is an increasingly popular research technique known as ''product life cycle'' analysis. Such a review tries to measure the environmental impact of a product on a ''cradle to grave'' basis. It looks at, among other things, the resources used to make the product, the pollutants released during that process and the problems asssociated with the product's disposal.</p>
        <p>Weighing the Pros and Cons</p>
        <p>Some researchers have suggested that by conducting studies of an aluminum can and a glass bottle, for example, it is possible to accurately compare their relative environmental impact. Recently, life-cycle studies have been used by marketers seeking to promote or defend consumer products. Some examples: studies that compare plastic bags with paper ones, disposable diapers with re-usable and metal plumbing pipes with their plastic competitors.</p>
        <p>Concern about the sudden outpouring of life-cycle studies led the Society of Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry, a professional group, to hold a meeting last month to review the scientific status of these findings. The group concluded that the current studies are inadequate because, among other things, they fail to use standardized methods, may be based on flawed assumptions or inaccurate data and do not fully portray a product's environmental effects.</p>
        <p>''In the guise of a complete science, a very partial product is being used to draw conclusions that are not warranted,'' said Richard Denison, a senior scientist at the Environmental Defense Fund, an advocacy group in Washington.</p>
        <p>Consider a recent study for the Council for Solid Waste Solutions, a plastics industry trade group, that compares the environmental impact of plastic shopping bags with paper ones. The study, conducted by Franklin Associates Ltd., environmental consultants in Prairie Village, Kan., found that plastic bags were environmentally superior to paper ones because they produce 74 to 80 percent less solid waste.</p>
        <p>But Robert Hunt, a vice president of Franklin Associates, acknowledged that the study did not fully analyze the relative environmental impact of the materials. ''The study addresses the issue of volume,'' he said, ''but it doesn't address the issue of how long it takes things to degrade.''</p>
        <p>One effort to advance the study of life-cycle analysis is going on at the Tellus Institute, a nonprofit research group in Boston. There, scientists working under contact to the New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection and other agencies are conducting an extensive analysis of various packaging materials, including steel, glass, aluminum, plastic and paper.</p>
        <p>The study, which will be completed next year, will be provide data for New Jersey regulators to determine whether they should discourage the use of certain packaging materials because of the pollution problems they create.</p>
        <p>To date, most life-cycle studies have simply listed the types of pollutants produced during a product's life span. But the Tellus study is among the first to attempt to analyze the impact of those pollutants on human health, said Karen Shapiro, an environmental scientist working on the study. That distinction is critical, Ms. Shapiro and others said, because while one packaging material may produce less pollution by weight than a competing material, the chemicals released may be far more toxic.</p>
        <p>Some researchers are skeptical that such a system can be developed. Mr. Hunt of Franklin Associates said that publicly available data on the types and amount of pollution produced at manufacturing plants are often incomplete. And Ms. Shapiro acknowledges that while the Tellus study seeks to weigh a pollutant's effect on human health, it does not account for its effect on environmental problems like acid rain or the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>''We recognize that this is not a complete picture, but the trade-off is that we can't keep studying this issue forever,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Researchers also say the controversy over life-cycle studies need not paralyze consumers. They continue to urge the public to use recycled products. They also point out that gauging the relative impact of similar products within the same category - household paints, for example - is far simpler than resolving more complex questions like the benefits of plastic versus paper.</p>
        <p>'Where Our Understanding Ends'</p>
        <p>''This is all very simple if you are trying to decide between a recycled paper cup and an unrecycled paper cup, but that's about where our understanding ends,'' said Mr. Denison at the Environmental Defense Fund.</p>
        <p>The Federal Environmental Protection Agency is now paying for research aimed at developing methods for life-cycle studies, a task that various experts estimate will take two to five years.</p>
        <p>But until that issue is resolved, at least two scientists who work for groups represented on the executive committee of Green Seal, a private, nonprofit group in Washington, are questioning just how far the labeling program can go. The reason: the lack of a scientifically defendable methodology.</p>
        <p>''There are some easy targets off the bat,'' Mr. Denison said, ''but we are many years away from being able to make complex decisions effectively.'' And Dr. Hershkowitz of the Natural Resources Defense Council said, ''We're not convinced we can sign off on any green labels right now.''</p>
        <p>Norman Dean, the president of Green Seal, said his group hopes to skirt the debate over life-cycle studies by first tackling relatively simple product categories like household paints and toilet paper. ''Our attitude,'' he said, ''is that admittedly this approach is in its infancy and as part of our program we will assess not only products but also research methods as they develop.''  CONSUMER'S WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
