<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Start Converting Shoreham to Gas</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="393848"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND OPINION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SHOREHAM (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND LIGHTING CO (LILCO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TWOMEY, THOMAS A JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D9143FF932A15753C1A966958260" item-length="1214" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Start Converting Shoreham to Gas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS A. TWOMEY Jr.Thomas Twomey Jr., a member of the Long Island Power Authority, headed the committee that recommended converting Shoreham to gas.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TWOMEY, THOMAS A JR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE final debate over the fate of Shoreham is about to begin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE final debate over the fate of Shoreham is about to begin.</p>
        <p>THE final debate over the fate of Shoreham is about to begin.</p>
        <p>The Long Island Power Authority, created by Gov. Mario M. Cuomo and the State Legislature, has released a report that concluded that converting Shoreham to a natural-gas plant is technically, economically and environmentally viable. The study determined that a conversion could provide an economical power supply for Long Island.</p>
        <p>The analysis was favorably received by the trustees of the authority, many of whom have long opposed the operation of Shoreham as a nuclear plant. By a unanimous vote, the trustees authorized the hiring of a project manager and other technical experts to help decide whether or not to proceed with the conversion by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>Long Island officials, once divided over the fate of Shoreham, seem united in support of the conversion. Suffolk County Executive Patrick G. Halpin and Representatives George Hochbrueckner, Thomas J. Downey and Robert J. Mrazek all issued statements supporting the conversion.</p>
        <p>Leaders of Long Island's business community, who in the past have been advocates of the Shoreham Nuclear Power Station, have also expressed support for the conversion proposal.</p>
        <p>So who is opposed to the idea? The Bush Administration is accelerating its efforts to reopen the Shoreham as a nuclear plant. Energy Secretary James D. Watkins recently urged the Federal Nuclear Regulatory Commission to deny the Long Island Lighting Company the right to transfer the plant to the Long Island Power Authority for decommissioning.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department argues that Shoreham should operate a nuclear plant to reduce Long Island's dependence on oil imported from the Middle East.</p>
        <p>But Lilco's oil doesn't come from the Arab nations. The vast majority of it comes from Venezuela. And by converting Shoreham to domestic and Canadian natural gas, we will reduce our dependence on oil even from South America, and we will do that with a clean, safe and abundant energy supply.</p>
        <p>Natural gas does not deplete the ozone level, does not create acid rain, and adds very little to the greenhouse effect. It does not create a costly ash or radioactive-waste disposal problem. With natural gas, there is no decontamination problem at the end of the useful life of the plant, saving ratepayers millions of dollars. And our grandchildren will not be paying for the storage of nuclear waste created by the electricity we use today.</p>
        <p>Best of all, there is an abundance of this clean fuel in America and Canada. Pipelines already exist, carrying natural gas to Connecticut from the Southwest.</p>
        <p>The Federal Government seems about to approve an application by the Iroquois transmission system for a new pipeline from Canada down to Connecticut and then across Long Island Sound to Commack. It would connect Connecticut with the pipeline from the Southwest, thereby flooding Long Island with large quantities of natural gas never before available.</p>
        <p>By using Shoreham as a natural gas plant, substantial savings to the ratepayer can be achieved. The non-nuclear Shoreham equipment, including transformers, switches, cooling systems and the turbine, can be harnessed in a conversion.</p>
        <p>By using this equipment, a conversion to a 900-megawatt plant would cost approximately $550 million. To build a plant of the same size at a new site without using the existing Shoreham equipment would cost about $960 million. In addition to this 80 percent increase in cost, there would be the difficulty of finding a suitable site on Long Island for such a plant.</p>
        <p>But even if a gas-fired plant is technically feasible and environmentally sound, does Long Island need one? Given its projected load growth and its current resource plan, Lilco expects to meet all of its obligations, including its reserve requirement, through the year 2005 without a converted Shoreham.</p>
        <p>However, included in Lilco's plan are upstate sources of energy that would be more expensive than the electricity from a converted Shoreham.</p>
        <p>By converting Shoreham, we would have available a cheaper energy source. And because the power would be generated on Long Island rather than imported through cables from upstate, it could prove to be more reliable. The conversion could be designed to permit Long Island to put into early retirement some of Lilco's current oil-fired plants, which use oil imported from Venezuela, thereby reducing the amount of imported oil consumed for electrical power.</p>
        <p>The savings from a converted Shoreham would be increased by an aggressive energy-conservation program. The power authority estimates that Long Islanders can save 12 percent of their electrical consumption by installing energy-saving devices and better refrigerators, freezers, lighting fixtures, furnaces and hot-water heaters.</p>
        <p>Utilities in other states have assisted in paying the cost of such new equipment, producing lower electricity bills for their customers while producing profits for their shareholders. Lilco's efforts to date have focused only on reducing peak load, rather than on reducing the annual use of electricity.</p>
        <p>Once Lilco commences a true energy-conservation program, the power authority estimates, it will save about 500 megawatts annually by the year 2000. This is about the total projected output of Shoreham.</p>
        <p>The combination of an effective energy-conservation program plus the conversion of Shoreham to natural gas would produce a cohesive energy plan critical for Long Island's economic well-being.</p>
        <p>Before the planning for the conversion of Shoreham can commence in earnest, however, the Bush Administration must withdraw its opposition to Governor Cuomo's Settlement Agreement to close Shoreham. The contracts have been ''signed, sealed and delivered,'' so no matter how long the Administration obstructs the transaction, Shoreham will never be operated as a nuclear plant unless, of course, Congress declares war and directs the Federal Government to nationalize Shoreham with many others for our national defense.</p>
        <p>Any attempt to reopen Shoreham would result in another decade of litigation, with no progress in developing a cohesive energy policy for Long Island. Meanwhile, the Administration, with its ultraclose ties to the nuclear industry, is costing Long Island about $8 million for each month they delay approving the transfer of the plant to the power authority.</p>
        <p>Much of this is the cost of maintaining employment at Shoreham, which is no longer needed. That is about $100 million a year. That money could be better spent on a truly effective energy-conservation plan or even the Shoreham conversion. Instead, it is being wasted.</p>
        <p>If Long Island commits itself to a strong and meaningful program of residential and commercial energy conservation and at the same time pursues the conversion of Shoreham, Long Island's energy future will soon be secure. There will be plenty of energy for healthy growth. We will be far less reliant on overseas sources of oil. Best of all we will have saved millions of dollars in energy bills for ourselves and our grandchildren.</p>
        <p>After years of confusion and struggle over Shoreham, Long Island now has a rare opportunity to forge a cohesive energy policy. How tragic it would be if the opportunity were lost because of misguided and shortsighted Federal intervention.</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND OPINION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
