<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="346653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DE143BF937A15757C0A966958260" item-length="1317" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-15</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-15</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-15</p>
        <p>Terms for a single German currency were proposed by Bonn, which bowed to East German demands by offering to convert the East German currency into West German marks at a rate that is very generous to East German workers and households.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>The only oil refinery in Lithuania shut down, its reserves exhausted by a fuel embargo imposed by the Kremlin in the hope of weakening the republic's spirit of independence.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Lithuania action by Bush expected</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Special direct flights to Saudi Arabia will be chartered by the Soviet Union for Soviet Muslims making the pilgrimage to Mecca this year, Moscow announced.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Soviet experts say their economy is worse</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Russians denied refuge in own land</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>An audience of Solidarity members sharply questioned the architect of Poland's transition to a free-market economy. The Finance Minister rejected calls for Government intervention to ease the hardships caused by his plan.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>More hostages could be released. Iran and its Lebanese Shiite Muslim allies signaled their willingness to keep pushing for the release of American hostages if the U.S. responds with reciprocal moves.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A weak ex-hostage arrives in West</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>For the captors, less in common now with Iran?</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Iraq is trying to develop a test site outside of its territory for firing new long-range missiles, Bush Administration officials believe. They have asked Mauritania about intelligence reports that it might permit Iraq to build a missile test range there.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>The leaders of the Christian churches in Israel and the occupied territories announced that they would close all their shrines for a day to protest the Israeli Government's support for a new Jewish settlement in the Christian quarter of the Old City.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Several people were killed in Nepal when angry crowds, frustrated by what they regarded as the slow pace of change, attacked several men in police uniforms.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Work stoppages in Nicaragua have paralyzed dozens of key services and industries just days before the country's first democratic transfer of power. Opposition leaders describe the moves as a Sandinista-led attempt to raise costs and create chaos.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>U.S. agents in Mexico are on alert</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Tone is mild at U.N. session for Third World aid</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Lima journal: New racial politics in Peru</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>National</p>
        <p>A16-21, B5-6</p>
        <p>A major shift in oil leasing policy has been proposed by the Interior Department to open the way to increased exploration and drilling in coastal waters. The new policy is designed to break a political deadlock.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The national Clean Water Act of 1972 has spun a web of arguments, legal questions, claims and counterclaims that has entangled farmers, environmentalists and Federal agencies over the definition of ''wetlands.''</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Beverly Hills journal: The stars come out for Earth Day</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>A guru who says she speaks for God, Elizabeth Clare Prophet, had predicted the likely outbreak of nuclear war but instead got a court order against her bomb shelter in Montana's mountains.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>A Harvard Law School professor, the first black to be given tenure there, said he has requested a leave of absence without pay until Harvard appoints a tenured black woman to its faculty.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>American University president quit under pressure</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>A law ordering a detailed study of crimes motivated by racial, ethnic or sexual prejudice was signed by President Bush. His audience included the first gay rights advocates invited to a White House ceremony.</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>A Minnesota Supreme Court decision that exempted an Amish group from compliance with a highway safety law was set aside by the U.S. Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Republicans favoring abortion rights are forming a political action committee to mount a three-year drive to change the party's platform and its firm anti-abortion position.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>A cut in Social Security taxes? Four months after Senator Daniel P. Moynihan of New York suggested a cut, his Democratic colleagues on the Senate Budget Committee are being prodded to finally take a stand.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>About 45 defeated House candidates from 20 states gathered in Washington not to ponder what might have been, but to advance a more ambitious agenda: changing a political system that they say is stacked against challengers.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>84 hurt as Amtrak train runs off track in Iowa</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Regional</p>
        <p>B1-5</p>
        <p>Crimes against teachers are rising in New York City's public schools, and they are being committed by ever younger students, statistics show. Such crimes increased by 25 percent in the first term of the school year.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Gina Feliciano told her story in court. The 18-year-old who has been at the center of the Bensonhurst murder case testified against her two neighbors who are charged with killing Yusuf K. Hawkins.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>2 men start jail terms in Howard Beach case</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>Police officers in Teaneck, N.J., said they felt as if they had already been judged and that the town had not supported them after the fatal shooting of a 16-year-old on April 10.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Officer charged in death of suspect in Brooklyn</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Residents of the Bronx are uneasy about how the borough might be portrayed in the coming film ''The Bonfire of the Vanities,'' based on the novel by Tom Wolfe.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>3 found slain in Bronx house, a baby unhurt</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>A $2 billion environmental bond act, the largest in New York State's history, will be presented to voters this fall, Gov. Mario M. Cuomo and legislative leaders announced in Albany.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Environmental protesters tie up Wall Street</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>Grass isn't greener after Earth Day</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Science Times</p>
        <p>What do clouds mean for global warming? Science closes in</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>After Three Mile Island cleanup, science learns many lessons</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Who really knows medical science, Ph.D.'s or M.D.'s?</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Hypertension among blacks the focus of intriguing research</p>
        <p>C3</p>
        <p>With heather going from hills, Britain raises alarm</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>The Cincinnati obscenity case</p>
        <p>C15</p>
        <p>Mel Powell's Pulitzer Prize</p>
        <p>C15</p>
        <p>Music: Kiri Te Kanawa</p>
        <p>C14</p>
        <p>Art: On loan to Poland</p>
        <p>C15</p>
        <p>Word and Image: Mordecai Richler's new novel</p>
        <p>C17</p>
        <p>Fashion</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>Sports</p>
        <p>Baseball: Miller settles in center for Mets</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>Winfield regaining form</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>Basketball: Oakley back on roster</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Columns: Berkow on taunting in college basketball</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Football: Juniors give draft its glitter</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Hockey: Capitals rout Rangers</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Ciccarelli sidelined</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Bruins closing in on sweep</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>Obituaries</p>
        <p>D22-23</p>
        <p>Paulette Goddard, film actress</p>
        <p>D22</p>
        <p>At the funeral for Raplph Abernathy, anger is eased</p>
        <p>D23</p>
        <p>Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Slouching in Jerusalem</p>
        <p>Finally, end home pork</p>
        <p>Don't blame Japan</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Anthony Lewis: Paying for murder</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Flora Lewis: Hold people power</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Joseph Papp, John E. Frohnmayer: On the N.E.A.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Ronald Fraser: What is a peace dividend?</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Roderick MacFarquhar: Canute's message to Gorbachev</p>
        <p>A23</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
