<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Cosmos And Those No-Hitters</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="365547"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAWKINS, ANDY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERKOW, IRA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Ira Berkow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DB143EF930A35754C0A966958260" item-length="809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Cosmos And Those No-Hitters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ira Berkow</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERKOW, IRA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: It's hard to bleed too profusely for Andy Hawkins of the Yankees because of the losing no-hitter he pitched Sunday when you know the story of Denny Pickett - I think it was Denny Pickett. It might have been Ronnie Madden, or Ernie Kumerow or Marco Dallesandro, but I'm pretty sure it was Denny Pickett.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: It's hard to bleed too profusely for Andy Hawkins of the Yankees because of the losing no-hitter he pitched Sunday when you know the story of Denny Pickett - I think it was Denny Pickett. It might have been Ronnie Madden, or Ernie Kumerow or Marco Dallesandro, but I'm pretty sure it was Denny Pickett.</p>
        <p>It's hard to bleed too profusely for Andy Hawkins of the Yankees because of the losing no-hitter he pitched Sunday when you know the story of Denny Pickett - I think it was Denny Pickett. It might have been Ronnie Madden, or Ernie Kumerow or Marco Dallesandro, but I'm pretty sure it was Denny Pickett. Denny was a left-handed pitcher in the Thillens Little League in Chicago many years ago, and about the size of a cork in a wine bottle. The biggest thing about him was his hat. And Denny hurled a no-hitter, too, one day, and lost.</p>
        <p>I don't remember the score - my team was playing the next game - except that he was way behind early, like 17-12 after two innings. It was one of those kinds of games. Denny might have been a little wild to begin with - Hawkins, remember, also walked two guys in that fateful eighth when the White Sox scored four runs, the only runs in the game - and the defense behind the pint-sized but plucky Pickett might have been a little fickle, in the manner of the Yankees' ball hawks, who committed three killer errors in the eighth.</p>
        <p>While others may have been nonplussed at Denny's situation, he was simply plussed, and kept pumping his heat, despite, as in Hawkins's case, batted balls bouncing off numerous teammates in the field.</p>
        <p>I retain the impression that Pickett never chastised his fielders from under the long bill of his cap, and I was moved when I read Hawkins's response to the rookie Jim Leyritz, who dropped a fly ball in the wind in left field with two out to allow in the White Sox' first three and deciding runs. Hawkins returned to the dugout after the eighth inning and consoled Leyritz. ''It's a tough wind,'' he told him.</p>
        <p>One is heartened by Hawkins, who only three weeks ago was told by the Yankees to pack his bags and get out of town. Oh yes, and leave his pinstriped knickers behind. He couldn't retire a batter. But as the gods would have it, another Yankee pitcher hurt his elbow, and Hawkins was asked to stay on, like an office temp.</p>
        <p>A no-hitter, meanwhile, is perceived as a remarkable thing. For those handful of innings, the toiler is a master, a virtually invincible practitioner. The verb that usually accompanies a story about a no-hitter is ''baffles.'' Somewhere in my memory, or mind's eye, I see a headline from 1958 that reads, ''Bunning Baffles BoSox.''</p>
        <p>In other words, the Red Sox couldn't figure out a way to get a hit off Jim Bunning of Detroit. This happened on July 20 of that year, as the Tigers won, 3-0. Bo Belinsky baffled Baltimore in 1962, and Bobo Holloman of the Browns did likewise, in his first major league start, against the A's, in 1953. (Bobo, by the way, was bye-bye from the major leagues by the next season, no longer a baffling-type operative.) But unless a pitcher is striking out everybody - and that has never been the case in the major leagues; Hawkins, for example, had just three K's - then batters are hitting the ball and some luck is involved when balls don't locate holes between the fielders that they generally do.</p>
        <p>In just three days, however, an abundance of luck and skill combined, and three no-hitters were turned out, two coming on the same day, Friday, thrown by Dave Stewart of the A's and Fernando Valenzuela of the Dodgers. And there were two others in the month of June, by Randy Johnson of the Mariners and Nolan Ryan of the Rangers.</p>
        <p>Suddenly a no-hitter seems an everyday occurrence, as common as bedroom slippers. Hawkins's game makes it six no-hitters so far this season, and, with still half a season to play, the 1917 record of seven seems within easy reach.</p>
        <p>Why so many no-hitters now? Some wonder if it's because of an abbreviated spring training after the lockout, or because the hitters are getting softer and the pitchers nastier, or, simply, because of the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>The view here is that it's an aberration, a quirk in the cosmos. After all, the three other times there were six or more no-hitters in a season were spread out over three decades, in the years 1908, 1917 and 1969. It is as likely as it is unlikely that there will be a seventh no-hitter this season.</p>
        <p>When Johnny Vander Meer, for one, pitched his two consecutive no-hitters in 1938, the only time this has happened, there wasn't another no-hitter thrown during that season.</p>
        <p>When Hippo Vaughn of the Cubs and Fred Toney of the Reds fashioned nine-inning no-hitters against each other in 1917 (with the Reds winning, 1-0, on a hit in the 10th), theirs were the only no-hitters in the National League that season.</p>
        <p>When Harvey Haddix in 1959 pitched his memorable 12-inning perfect game, and lost to the Braves in the 13th inning, it was the only no-hitter thrown that year.</p>
        <p>Andy Hawkins, too, threw a no-hit gem, and lost, and so is added to that rare pantheon, one peopled with the likes of Harvey and Hippo and little Denny Pickett.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
