<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The True Cost of Energy;   Pay It: For Security, the Economy and the Air</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="377723"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESERVES (NATURAL RESOURCES)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STRATEGIC PETROLEUM RESERVE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALES TAX</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reserves (Natural Resources)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DE1238F93AA2575BC0A966958260" item-length="668" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The True Cost of Energy;   Pay It: For Security, the Economy and the Air</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Saddam Hussein's plunder of Kuwait only dramatizes something Americans have long known from the bottom of their gas tanks: Oil dependency breeds vulnerability.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Saddam Hussein's plunder of Kuwait only dramatizes something Americans have long known from the bottom of their gas tanks: Oil dependency breeds vulnerability.</p>
        <p>Saddam Hussein's plunder of Kuwait only dramatizes something Americans have long known from the bottom of their gas tanks: Oil dependency breeds vulnerability.</p>
        <p>One way or another, the Iraq crisis will end. But the vulnerability won't - unless America creates a national energy policy. That's no sanctimonious abstraction; it's a practical need. A sound energy policy would encourage domestic suppliers, insulate the economy against foreign manipulation, protect the environment and raise revenue. Congress could do it all in a stroke, by increasing energy taxes.</p>
        <p>President Bush has followed the Reagan energy policy: reliance on deregulated markets to guide consumers and producers, and the Strategic Petroleum Reserve to offset supply disruptions. These are sensible principles. Deregulation has raised energy prices and cut use. And the reserve has warded off panic buying.</p>
        <p>Yet the Reagan-Bush hands-off approach is not enough. Americans account for 2 percent of the world's population but consume an astounding 25 percent of the world's oil. Much of this consumption is wasted because low market prices take insufficient account of real costs.</p>
        <p>One is national security. Every extra barrel consumed makes the U.S. that much more vulnerable to oil cartel cutbacks. The price Americans pay for imported oil covers none of the likely costs of future supply interruptions brought on by such dependence. Likewise, energy use fouls air and water and contributes to global warming. Yet consumers pay for none of this damage.</p>
        <p>The Best Way to Pay</p>
        <p>For all these reasons, consumers aren't paying the full costs of energy. The most effective way to do that is higher energy taxes. They would right the balance - and also avoid the need for a lot of micro-managing by Congress. Americans would switch to fuel-efficient cars without elaborate regulations; alternative fuels could become competitive without massive subsidies.</p>
        <p>Congress would still have to decide which energy taxes to raise, and by how much. Each tax has a different regional and environmental consequence. Though there are few studies to guide the decisions, a tax that would add between 25 and 50 cents to the price of a gallon of gasoline would make a good start.</p>
        <p>Debate over the pros and cons of various options must not overshadow the underlying principle: Americans are paying too little for energy.</p>
        <p>Fill the Reserve</p>
        <p>The Strategic Petroleum Reserve provides another pillar of energy policy. Large buffer stocks can offset temporary supply disruptions - and radically change oil exporters' calculations. These goals would be better served by expanding the reserve to 1 billion barrels from 600 million.</p>
        <p>Its operating procedures also need revision. The reserve can be opened only by a Presidential declaration of an emergency. There are promising proposals to open it on an ongoing basis, subject to a fee that would allow Government to replace withdrawn supply at a profit. These proposals deserve serious review, before the next crisis.</p>
        <p>Revive Nuclear Energy</p>
        <p>It's a Federal responsibility also to promote new sources of energy. There is a relatively low-cost, non-polluting form of it, which gives France 70 percent of its electricity, Japan 30 percent but the U.S. only 18 percent: nuclear. One attractive option would be to join with our allies in designing a nuclear reactor so safe that all reasonable unease would be allayed.</p>
        <p>The Iraq crisis has generated new oratory about energy independence. A tax that would take national security and the environment into account would mean only a moderate increase in the price of energy. But to achieve energy independence would require a draconian leap that would stifle the economy and cost millions of Americans their jobs. To press for energy independence for its own sake would be economically suicidal.</p>
        <p>A wise energy policy must strike a balance between reduced dependence and an induced depression. The starting point is this proposition: Energy taxes must rise.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
