<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="361528"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DD1231F935A25755C0A966958260" item-length="1310" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>2-5</p>
        <p>The United States will support a fund intended to help developing countries phase out chemicals that are destroying the earth's ozone layer, the White House said, reversing its earlier opposition to the international fund.</p>
        <p>Page 1</p>
        <p>Nicaragua's army would be reduced by one-third under an order issued by President Violeta Barrios de Chamorro.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>2-5</p>
        <p>The United States will support a fund intended to help developing countries phase out chemicals that are destroying the earth's ozone layer, the White House said, reversing its earlier opposition to the international fund.</p>
        <p>Page 1</p>
        <p>Nicaragua's army would be reduced by one-third under an order issued by President Violeta Barrios de Chamorro.</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>2-5</p>
        <p>The United States will support a fund intended to help developing countries phase out chemicals that are destroying the earth's ozone layer, the White House said, reversing its earlier opposition to the international fund.</p>
        <p>Page 1</p>
        <p>Nicaragua's army would be reduced by one-third under an order issued by President Violeta Barrios de Chamorro. The army is the biggest in Central America and the most powerful political weapon in the arsenal of the opposition Sandinista Front.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Israeli arms passed through Antigua before making their way to Colombian drug traffickers, according to an investigation that has shaken the five-decade political dominion of Antigua's Prime Minister, Vere C. Bird.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>Chances seem dim on Canadian pact</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>Liberia's President attacked the U.S. for not assisting the Liberian Government in its six-month civil war with rebel forces. He described Liberia as Washington's ''oldest ally on the African continent.''</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>Romanians took stock of the damage caused by the whirlwind of violence and lawlessness that swept Bucharest in the last two days. Even as miners began to pull out of the city, more cases of attacks were reported. A broad political chasm in Bulgaria separates supporters of the renamed Communist Party and backers of its anti-Communist opposition. The country's first multiparty parliamentary elections in more than four decades will end on Sunday.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Moscow journal: A ''white market'' - a commodities exchange that would provide a convenient trading place to speed and organize supply and demand - has been given approval by the city government.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Economic sanctions against Iraq should be resisted, a senior Bush Administration official urged Congress. But he strongly criticized the Iraqi Government for its human rights record and foreign policies.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>Iranian accord with Amoco lifts a barrier to U.S. trade</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>National</p>
        <p>6-9, 22</p>
        <p>President Bush vetoed a bill that would have relaxed restrictions on partisan political activity by Federal workers. The White House said Mr. Bush would also veto legislation mandating unpaid leave for workers facing a family emergency.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>A compromise on civil rights? The Bush Administration has intensified efforts to reach a compromise with Congress on civil rights legislation, in part to avoid a divisive debate during the visit of Nelson Mandela.</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>The Hispanic work force is growing at a rapid pace in California, which may create social and economic problems unless more is done to absorb the workers into the state's economy, a growing number of Californians believe.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>A flash flood struck an Ohio town. Torrential thunderstorms sent flood waters surging through a valley and into the Ohio River town of Shadyside Thursday night, killing several people and leaving dozens missing and dozens more homeless.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Efforts to protect a barrier reef near Southern Florida are proving difficult. Scientists and reef rangers believe reducing the impact of humans on the reef might give the coral a better chance for regrowth.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>The fire on a Norwegian supertanker in the Gulf of Mexico was extinguished and the flow of oil was stopped. Scientists later sprayed natural bacteria across a patch of floating oil in a test of a novel method for controlling oil pollution.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Violence erupted in Detroit as basketball fans spontaneously celebrated the Detroit Pistons' league championship. In the wake of the team's victory, eight people were killed and scores were injured by gunfire, stabbings and fighting.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Dave Durenberger returned home to the warm embrace of Minnesota Republicans and, with the sort of emotion that had once been rare in his public life as a U.S. Senator, asked their forgiveness.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Executive charged with selling ''Star Wars'' data</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Head of Brandeis quits after troubled tenure</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Regional</p>
        <p>23-26</p>
        <p>The widow of a young aspiring actor who was stabbed to death nine years ago outside an East Village restaurant by the jailhouse author Jack Henry Abbott was awarded $7.575 million in damages by a Manhattan jury.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Donald J. Trump missed a payment. The developer failed to pay about $73 million that he owed to banks and bondholders, but bankers said substantial progress was made on a deal to provide new loans to keep the Trump empire afloat.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>''Junk bonds'' for Trump's Castle plummet</p>
        <p>29</p>
        <p>Nelson Mandela's visit to New York is proving again just how hard it is for Mayor Dinkins to hold together the tiles of the city that he never tires of calling a gorgeous mosaic.</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>Nine murders were committed in New York City in a nine-hour period beginning Thursday afternoon. Even in a year when murders are occurring at a record pace, it was an abnormally bloody time.</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>Fare-beating reached record levels in New York City's subway system in May. People are vaulting over turnstiles, passing through gates illegally, putting less than the full fare in token collection boxes and stealing millions of dollars worth of tokens.</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>Brooklyn's representative renamed to school board</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>Name-calling in State Senate</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>Clerics at odds on excommunication for abortion</p>
        <p>26</p>
        <p>Suspicious fires in Copake, N.Y., have struck buildings from barns to businesses, rocking the rural town in Columbia County and creating an atmosphere of fear, anxiety and anger.</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>Gov. Jim Florio went on the radio in a campaign to win the hearts and minds of middle-class voters in New Jersey, as political pressures mounted for a crucial vote in the Legislature next week.</p>
        <p>24</p>
        <p>Lobster dealer guilty in insurance plot</p>
        <p>24</p>
        <p>Passenger drives bus from Delaware to New York</p>
        <p>24</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>A second illuminated manuscript from the hoard of medieval treasures stolen from the German town of Quedlinburg in the closing days of World War II has just been sold to a West German art dealer.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Eakins's ''Swimming Hole'' to stay in Texas</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>Joyce typescript in Texas</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>Film: Laurel with and without Hardy</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>Dance: Four works by Robbins</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>Book: ''Lion Mountain''</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>Consumer's World</p>
        <p>46</p>
        <p>More autos will have air bags</p>
        <p>New generation of childproof caps</p>
        <p>Coping with finding a nursing home</p>
        <p>A gadget to pull out ticks</p>
        <p>Guidepost</p>
        <p>Obituaries</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>Guy Paulin, Parisian fashion designer</p>
        <p>Joe Wright, arrested as member of Wilmington 10</p>
        <p>William Casey, theology professor and Jesuit educator</p>
        <p>Sports</p>
        <p>Baseball: Mets win</p>
        <p>41</p>
        <p>Jays beat Yanks</p>
        <p>43</p>
        <p>Athletics beat White Sox</p>
        <p>43</p>
        <p>Basketball: Pistons in special class</p>
        <p>41</p>
        <p>Column: Anderson on Ballesteros</p>
        <p>41</p>
        <p>Golf: Tim Simpson leads at Open</p>
        <p>41</p>
        <p>Two lead in L.P.G.A.</p>
        <p>42</p>
        <p>Soccer: U.S. team not down at loss to Italy</p>
        <p>42</p>
        <p>Czechoslovaks advance</p>
        <p>42</p>
        <p>Sports People</p>
        <p>42</p>
        <p>Track and Field: Lewis wins 100</p>
        <p>44</p>
        <p>Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>20</p>
        <p>A boost for both countries</p>
        <p>Now, the Thornburgh mess</p>
        <p>Who's afraid of foreign ideas?</p>
        <p>Holtzman haste</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>20</p>
        <p>Flora Lewis: NATO a la Francaise</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>Russell Baker: Probably needed rewiring</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>Milton Viorst: Keep the P.L.O. talks alive</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>Roberta S. Altman: Mrs. Jennings, don't rush</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>Ronald Takaki: The harmful myth of Asian superiority</p>
        <p>21</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
