<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Those Cursed Lips</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="370047"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="OBSERVER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BAKER, RUSSELL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D81639F932A15754C0A966958260" item-length="717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Those Cursed Lips</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Russell Baker</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BAKER, RUSSELL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Dr. Liverworth, as the world's foremost authority on lips, will you clarify the situation for me?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Dr. Liverworth, as the world's foremost authority on lips, will you clarify the situation for me?</p>
        <p>Dr. Liverworth, as the world's foremost authority on lips, will you clarify the situation for me?</p>
        <p>Answer: Read my lips.</p>
        <p>Q. They are saying yes?</p>
        <p>A. They are saying precisely what my ghostwriter wants them to say.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you mean to say that you, Dr. Liverworth, world's foremost authority, are merely a ghostwriter's mouthpiece?</p>
        <p>A. In the old days I used to say a few words of my own, but the polls showed they were sometimes the words a lot of people didn't want to hear. My consultants now insist I speak only the words of somebody else.</p>
        <p>Q. Is that ''somebody else'' the famous Peggy Noonan?</p>
        <p>A. Are you joking? Peggy ghosts for the finest Presidential timber and takes home best-seller bucks. I can't afford quality like that on the money a foremost-lips authority makes.</p>
        <p>Q. Speaking of Presidential timber, when acid rain and real-estate development finally succeed in destroying the great deciduous forests of North America, will we have to import our Presidents from Japan?</p>
        <p>A. My specialty is lips, not wood. I merely point out that the miniature trees the Japanese call ''bonsai'' would produce Presidents so tiny they could easily be sucked into White House air-conditioning vents and lost for days, since the roar of the fans would make it very hard to hear the cries of anguish from their tiny lips.</p>
        <p>Q. Speaking of cries of anguish, why are the Congressional Republicans making such agonized sounds?</p>
        <p>A. Congressional Republicans have been out of power for almost all of the past 60 years. Agonized sound is the natural utterance of such wretched souls.</p>
        <p>Q. But why do they now direct this natural utterance at their own President?</p>
        <p>A. Because they are maddened by what they have read on his lips recently. What they are reading are the words ''new taxes.'' They fear he has hired a ghostwriter who doesn't understand the importance of writing ''no'' before ''new taxes.''</p>
        <p>Q. They think America would be better off bankrupt than taxed again and again?</p>
        <p>A. National bankruptcy doesn't alarm them as much as fear that the President's new ghostwriter might get a lot of Congressional Republicans wiped out in the fall elections. They want voters who read the President's lips between now and Election Day to find the same beloved old words put there by his 1988 ghostwriter: ''no new taxes.''</p>
        <p>Q. Why are Congressional Republicans unhappy about being wiped out in the election? Republicans are always saying government is a menace to the country and Congress is a terrible outfit. Shouldn't they be delighted to sever their connections with such awful institutions?</p>
        <p>A. Of course not.</p>
        <p>Q. Why?</p>
        <p>A. Because, one, the Capitol has one of the world's best year-round air-conditioning systems. Two, dreadful though Congress is, its members legally collect millions of dollars from ''political action committees.'' Three, Washington is a far more interesting place to live than most places Republicans come from. Shall I go on?</p>
        <p>Q. Aren't you going to add that, terrible though it is being a member of Congress, a few patriotic Republicans have to do it to prevent Democrats from subjecting the country to the horrors of government?</p>
        <p>A. I am an authority on reading lips. That doesn't mean I believe everything lips say.</p>
        <p>Q. Why did Mr. Bush in 1988 promise not to raise taxes?</p>
        <p>A. Why not? Promising not to raise taxes is perfectly normal in a Presidential campaign. Voters expect the promise and expect it to be broken after the election. President Bush's mistake wasn't in making the usual promise, it was in framing it in two three-word belch lines that made a dramatic sound bite. ''Read my lips'' and ''no new taxes'' were ghostwriter triumphs. Unforgettable, regrettably.</p>
        <p>Q. What's wrong with that?</p>
        <p>A. It's dumb to make campaign promises that are not forgettable.</p>
        <p>Q. Are you calling President Bush dumb?</p>
        <p>A. Not at all. It was his campaign that was dumb. Its entire intellectual content was summarized with, ''Read my lips.'' This dumbness occurs because modern Presidential campaigns have to be built on dumb themes which can be easily absorbed by dumb people like you.</p>
        <p>Q. I beg your pardon! Are you aware that I never miss an installment of ''Entertainment Tonight''?</p>
        <p>A. Sorry, but my ghostwriter is turning me off. He wants to call Peggy Noonan.</p>
        <p>OBSERVER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
