<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Curbing U.S. Oil Appetite: Why It's So Hard</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="385083"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DF163BF93AA2575AC0A966958260" item-length="1366" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Curbing U.S. Oil Appetite: Why It's So Hard</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Oil, like ice cream or french fries, is something Americans enjoy but would be better off consuming less of. But it is also very hard to get away from, for engineering reasons as well as historical and economic ones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Oil, like ice cream or french fries, is something Americans enjoy but would be better off consuming less of. But it is also very hard to get away from, for engineering reasons as well as historical and economic ones.</p>
        <p>Oil, like ice cream or french fries, is something Americans enjoy but would be better off consuming less of. But it is also very hard to get away from, for engineering reasons as well as historical and economic ones.</p>
        <p>The biggest obstacle is that no other fuel holds so much energy in such a small, light package, least of all the readily available substitutes of coal or electricity. What is more, 80 years into the automobile era, everything is built around gasoline, an investment of billions in refineries, tanker trucks and gasoline stations.</p>
        <p>And even at the modestly elevated price now, few of the alternatives approach being economically competitive with oil. That is particularly important because many Americans have come to feel almost as if they have a constitutional right to low-priced gasoline and do not see much point in paying higher taxes or higher prices for substitutes.</p>
        <p>The addiction to oil is worse for the United States than for any other country. The American economy is the biggest and its thirst for oil the greatest. And per capita oil consumption in the United States is more than double that of France, Britain and Japan.</p>
        <p>The main reason for the difference is the automobile. Of the 17.3 million barrels of oil used each day last year, 10.9 million, or 62.7 percent, went into transportation, most of it for gasoline. In a recent study, Lee Schipper, an energy analyst at Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory, calculated that Americans used about 350 gallons of gasoline per person in 1987, compared with 150 gallons in West Germany.</p>
        <p>Higher fuel efficiency would help; if the average American car were as fuel-efficient as the average German car, American consumption would have been about 75 gallons lower, he calculated. But about another 75 gallons of difference resulted because Americans travel more miles. Still another reason for greater gasoline use is that this country has more cars per 1,000 population. Americans traveled more than 11,000 miles by car that year, on average, while West Germans drove 5,000 miles. Americans, in a bigger country, tend to drive farther to work and play.</p>
        <p>Drawbacks of Other Fuels</p>
        <p>Candidates for a new transportation fuel abound, but they all have strong disadvantages.</p>
        <p>Foremost are the technical reasons. No fuel, natural or synthetic, carries so much energy around in such a small package. A gallon of gasoline, which weighs about 7 pounds, has as much energy as 11 pounds of coal, and coal, as a solid, is more difficult to handle. Coal can yield a liquid fuel, methanol, but that has only about half the energy of gasoline per gallon. (Also working against this solution is that more than conventional gasoline, methanol from coal introduces gases that are thought to promote climate change. Also, burning methanol from any source produces formaldehyde and other pollutants.) A pound of natural gas will take a car about as far as a pound of gasoline, but the natural gas takes up much more space: The energy in one gallon of gasoline would require, at atmospheric pressure, a container of gas in a cube nearly 5 feet on each side. The natural gas can be squeezed into a far smaller volume, but that requires a very heavy tank.</p>
        <p>And the amount of natural gas needed would be vast. For households that heat the structure, cook and heat water with natural gas, for example, converting the family car to natural gas would more than double their energy demand. If millions of vehicles were converted, more wells would have to be drilled and many more transmission pipelines built.</p>
        <p>As for electricity, it is abundant because it can be made from coal, but the space problem is even worse than for natural gas. If the amount of energy stored in 12 gallons of gasoline were instead stored in lead-acid batteries like the ones typically used for cranking and ignition in cars, the battery would weigh nearly a ton and a half, about as much as a small car.</p>
        <p>Historical Momentum</p>
        <p>Providing nearly 100 billion gallons of gasoline a year has created a momentum that would be difficult for any competing fuel to overcome. ''It takes mucho, mucho billions, not only to develop and produce a fuel, but to produce an infrastructure,'' said Daniel Yergin, president of Cambridge Energy Research Associates of Cambridge, Mass. ''Gasoline won the struggle for automotive fuel at the turn of the century, and everything has been invested in that ever since.'' Mr. Yergin said that gasoline was once viewed as a useless byproduct of kerosene, which was used for home heating, and was therefore readily available when cars first appeared.</p>
        <p>Cars at the turn of the century ran on everything from electricity to ''town gas,'' which was produced by heating coal at central stations, mostly for lighting streets and homes and for cooking. A variety of petroleum products including naphtha were also tried. Some Stanley Steamers ran on kerosene.</p>
        <p>''At the very beginning of the auto industry, they didn't know what cars were going to run on,'' said James A. Wren, the chairman of the Society of Automotive Engineers history group. Alcohol was so popular, he said, that in France grape growers feared there would be nothing left for drinking.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wren traces the dominance of gasoline to nearly simultaneous developments: the Spindletop gusher, the large oil find in Texas that pushed oil prices below 5 cents a barrel, and Oldsmobile's open two-seater runabouts, called the Curved Dash Olds, which ran on gasoline. At that point, in 1901, ''you had a mass-produced car and a cheap fuel.''</p>
        <p>The range of options is larger now in a technological sense but not in an economic sense. Theodore Eck, the chief economist at Amoco, estimated that liquid vehicle fuel made from this country's most abundant hydrocarbon, coal, would not compete until oil prices reached $40 to $50 a barrel.</p>
        <p>Turning to Unconventional Oil</p>
        <p>Another possibility is ordinary gasoline made from abundant but unconventional oil, as from tar sands or shale, which generally requires mining rock and cooking it to make the oil come out. Chevron this spring estimated that such oils would be competitive with a world price of $25 to $40 a barrel in 1990 dollars. But while oil has jumped past $30 a barrel in recent weeks, oil executives say that because of the long lead times and heavy capital investments, it must be obvious to investors that the price will stay there. Today, that is like betting on Saddam Hussein's job tenure.</p>
        <p>Some fuels are available today at a price lower than gasoline's, but they entail other costs. A kilowatt-hour of electricity, for example, will propel a van about two miles, and the national average cost is about 8 cents, which is equivalent to gasoline at 80 cents a gallon in a 20-mile-per-gallon vehicle. And utilities say they could sell power for much less in off-peak hours, for drivers who charged their batteries at night. But because of the current state of battery technology, the vehicle itself would be uncompetitive.</p>
        <p>Other Costs Involved</p>
        <p>Some utilities will sell natural gas for vehicle use at a price equivalent to 70 cents a gallon of gasoline. But switching fuels means developing a vehicle engine that runs on something else, which could cost hundreds of millions of dollars, and providing a network of fueling stations.</p>
        <p>Amoco, which recently began selling natural gas at two stations as an experiment, puts the cost of adding a natural gas pump at about $250,000 per station. With environmental regulations governing underground storage tanks, costs for other kinds of fuels would also be high. And the United States has about 200,000 places that sell gasoline; a substantial fraction of them would have to offer a different kind of fuel before most Americans would buy it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eck at Amoco said that if Detroit would build cars that could switch from gasoline to natural gas, ''we could build the fueling stations a lot faster than they could build the cars.'' Sold in volume, he said, a car equipped to burn natural gas as well as gasoline would cost as little as $300 extra.</p>
        <p>But the auto makers show little enthusiasm for heavy new investments for a product for which the public is not clamoring.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
