<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ozone Hole Reopens Over Antarctica</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19901026T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="390508"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL OCEANIC AND ATMOSPHERIC ADMINISTRATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED9133EF931A25753C1A966958260" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ozone Hole Reopens Over Antarctica</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A gaping hole in earth's protective ozone layer has again opened over Antarctica, and scientists reported yesterday that the depletion of ozone there seemed to be nearly as severe as it was in the worst previous years, 1987 and 1989.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A gaping hole in earth's protective ozone layer has again opened over Antarctica, and scientists reported yesterday that the depletion of ozone there seemed to be nearly as severe as it was in the worst previous years, 1987 and 1989.</p>
        <p>A gaping hole in earth's protective ozone layer has again opened over Antarctica, and scientists reported yesterday that the depletion of ozone there seemed to be nearly as severe as it was in the worst previous years, 1987 and 1989.</p>
        <p>This is the first time a severe Antarctic ozone hole has developed in two successive years, according to the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration and the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.</p>
        <p>Scientists worry about such holes because they imply increasing health hazards throughout the world. Ordinarily, a layer of ozone in the stratosphere prevents a dangerous form of ultraviolet radiation from the sun from reaching the earth.</p>
        <p>But in recent years, synthetic chemicals called chlorofluorocarbons released into the air by various human activities have reached the stratosphere, where they break apart and destroy ozone. As a result, increasing amounts of dangerous radiation reach the ground, prompting fears of an epidemic of skin cancer and cataracts, and damage to crops, notably soybeans.</p>
        <p>Extent Is Unknown</p>
        <p>The exact geographic extent and overall depletion of ozone in this year's hole have not yet been determined, but Dr. David J. Hofmann, an aeronomist at the University of Wisconsin, said that balloon-borne instruments have found no ozone at all in a layer of atmosphere between 9.3 and 10.8 miles above the Antarctic continent. But above this level some ozone appears to remain, he said.</p>
        <p>Aeronomists are not yet sure whether this trace of high-altitude ozone extends over the whole continent, but if it does, this year's ozone depletion may be somewhat less severe than that of 1987, the worst year on record.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mark Schoeberl of NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center said the minimum value of the ozone shield over Antarctica this year fell to 123 Dobson units on Oct. 4. Dobson units are a measure of the ability of the atmosphere to absorb certain wavelengths of light, especially in the ultraviolet range. When the ozone layer was intact, normal readings above Antarctica reached 500 Dobson units. In 1987 and 1989 they fell to about 115.</p>
        <p>''An Antarctic ozone hole in 1990 comes as a surprise to some scientists,'' Dr. Schoeberl said.</p>
        <p>Monitored Since 1979</p>
        <p>Seasonal Antarctic ozone depletion has been monitored since 1979 using NASA's Total Ozone Mapping Spectrometer, an instrument carried by the Nimbus-7 satellite. Its measurements are supplemented by ground-based instruments that measure the intensity of ultraviolet radiation reaching the ground, and by high-altitude balloons launched from Antarctica by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</p>
        <p>Each time the ozone hole has occurred since its first appearance in 1987, it has appeared in late August -early spring in the Southern Hemisphere - and dispersed in early October. Many scientists believed that the holes occur in odd-numbered years but are apt to be less severe or nonexistent in even-numbered years.</p>
        <p>An exception was Dr. James K. Angel of Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Air Resources Laboratory in Silver Spring, Md., who published a paper predicting that this year's hole would be severe. Dr. Hofmann said yesterday that this year's hole appears to confirm Dr. Angel's prediction and the theory underlying it.</p>
        <p>Dr. Angel said in a telephone interview that while most investigators based their predictions about the Antarctic ozone hole on calculations derived from wind patterns in the stratosphere, his own calculations were based more on temperature patterns in the stratosphere. In June through August, the temperature of the stratosphere was higher than normal, and so were temperatures at the surface. This coincidence, Dr. Angel said, led to his unorthodox prediction of an ozone hole this year, published last month in the journal Geophysical Research Papers.</p>
        <p>World Accord on a Halt</p>
        <p>Seasonal ozone depletion over Antarctica - and a less severe depletion in the high Arctic - concern scientists because they imply a thinning of the ozone layer throughout the world. Worried leaders of most of the world's governments have agreed that chlorofluorocarbon production and use must be halted, but even if the phasing-out of these chemicals proceeds on schedule, the ozone layer will remain severely depleted well into the next century.</p>
        <p>On June 29, senior government leaders from more than 90 nations agreed in London to hasten the halt in global production and use of chlorofluorocarbons. Joining the agreement were China and India, which had previously declined to curb the chemicals. Their change followed agreement by the United States and other Western nations to contribute to an international fund intended to relieve the economic burden imposed on the third world by a ban.</p>
        <p>Chlorofluorocarbons have many important applications, especially as refrigerant gases in refrigerators and air conditioners, and as foaming agents in insulating plastic materials.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 26, 1990, Friday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>An article on Oct. 12 about the ozone "hole" over Antarctica misstated an affiliation of Dr. David J. Hofmann. He is a faculty member, on leave, at the University of Wyoming, not the University of Wisconsin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 26, 1990, Friday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>An article on Oct. 12 about the ozone "hole" over Antarctica misstated an affiliation of Dr. David J. Hofmann. He is a faculty member, on leave, at the University of Wyoming, not the University of Wisconsin.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
