<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="340582"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED61139F937A35757C0A966958260" item-length="1277" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-13</p>
        <p>A delegation of Lithuanians conferred with President Gorbachev's closest political ally amid signs that both sides want to end the impasse created after the Baltic republic declared its independence last month.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: Foreign Minister Eduard A.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-13</p>
        <p>A delegation of Lithuanians conferred with President Gorbachev's closest political ally amid signs that both sides want to end the impasse created after the Baltic republic declared its independence last month.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: Foreign Minister Eduard A.</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-13</p>
        <p>A delegation of Lithuanians conferred with President Gorbachev's closest political ally amid signs that both sides want to end the impasse created after the Baltic republic declared its independence last month.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: Foreign Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze arrived in Washington for meetings with President Bush and Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d, and Administration officials said he faces some tough talk on Lithuania this week.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Nothing but nice things to say of Gorbachev</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>U.S. urged to emphasize economic strength</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>East Germany's sluggish work ethic is causing West German businesses to rethink how much they will benefit from reunification.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>East German parties aiming for a cabinet by April 15  A8</p>
        <p>Bulgaria adopts election laws and names leader</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>American and Japanese officials said they had reached a basic agreement to allow foreign producers to compete for the satellite business of the Japanese Government and its public-sector entities.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>China has made new demands on the U.S. in discussing terms for the release of the dissident Fang Lizhi, American officials said. Mr. Fang is living in the American Embassy in Beijing.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Chinese protest leader escapes to the West</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>34 killed in bomb blast at Hindu rite in Punjab</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>News analysis: The Iraqi leader, Saddam Hussein, who has locked horns anew with Israel and with the Western powers that tacitly supported his war against Iran, is casting himself as the Arab world's defender.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Israel puts a satellite in orbit a day after threat by Iraqis</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Lebanon's currency hits all-time low</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>A group of alienated young Britons who feel passed over by the Thatcher era seem to have found a target for their anger and despair in an unpopular new Government tax.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>The South African Government began deploying army troops in Natal's strife-torn black townships as Nelson Mandela and some other black leaders voiced misgivings but not outright objections over the move.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Rehoboth journal: Fearful tribe raises flag of freedom</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>House approves special aid for Nicaragua and Panama</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Central American leaders call for demobilization of contras</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Cubans parade hardware to jam TV Marti</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>National</p>
        <p>A14-23, B5</p>
        <p>A compromise clean air bill was passed by the Senate by a vote of 89 to 11. Following a decade of legislative stalemate, the bill is intended to reduce acid rain, urban smog and toxic chemicals in the air.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The salvagers of a sunken ship thought that their dream of fabulous riches had come true last summer. But now, several insurance companies are trying to prove they own a big piece of that dream.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The vulnerability of technology to intruders operating beyond American borders and laws came into question as three Australians were charged with tampering with computers in the United States and Australia.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The residents of Ponca City, Okla., an oil-refinery city, counted their sorrows as well as their riches after reaching one of the largest settlements ever recorded in a lawsuit over environmental contamination.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Concern abates as oil in river passes Pittsburgh</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Vermont leader will not run again</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>A tough stance on the death penalty has become a central focus of campaigns across the country. Candidates are vowing that they would be more vigorous than their opponents in applying the death penalty.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>The ''Stealth'' fighter plane was hampered by pilot error and missed a critical target on its first combat mission in Panama, Pentagon officials said as they provided the first public pictures of the aircraft.</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>The judge in the Iran-contra trial of John M. Poindexter angrily ordered the jury sequestered during its deliberations after two jurors reported contacts with the press.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>New AIDS experiments stir hope and wariness</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Study shows that antiviral drug aids children with Chicken Pox</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>U.N.L.V. journal: Campus put on the map by a team</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Regional</p>
        <p>B1-4</p>
        <p>New York State's highest court ruled that the state must pay welfare recipients a monthly shelter allowance that bears ''a reasonable relation'' to the cost of their housing.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Cuomo and G.O.P. sketching accord on an income-tax cut</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Revenue steps proposed to balance Connecticut's budget</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Imelda Marcos's rackeetering trial began in a Federal courthouse in Manhattan with raucous and contentious opening statements by the prosecution and defense.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Robert Golub was found guilty of second-degree murder in the death of 13-year-old Kelly Ann Tinyes, a year after the girl's battered and mutilated body was found in a sleeping bag in his family's basement in Valley Stream.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Music played as police found bodies in 1971</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>The owner of the building that housed the Happy Land Social Club surrendered on a year-old arrest warrant as the Dinkins administration said it would padlock 38 social clubs operating illegally.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Schools Chancellor Fernandez is moving to require all public schools in New York City to prepare budgets for public scrutiny and is setting tougher standards for hiring district business managers.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Voting-machines lobbyist says official sought a bribe</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Liquor and cigarette advertisements aimed at blacks are being whitewashed in Harlem by the pastor of the Abyssinian Baptist Church, and advertising companies are putting up public service ads in their place.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Twin sisters accused of bilking blind man</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>The Living Section</p>
        <p>Food</p>
        <p>At the family table, a tale of freedom</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Wine Talk</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Imagine! A seder without gefilte fish</p>
        <p>C6</p>
        <p>Living</p>
        <p>From Calvin Klein, winning simplicity</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Diary</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>The stress of being an author and married to Salman Rushdie</p>
        <p>C17</p>
        <p>From nobody to somebody in art</p>
        <p>C17</p>
        <p>Met Opera names summer arts presenter</p>
        <p>C14</p>
        <p>Theater: Soviet company's ''King Lear''</p>
        <p>C17</p>
        <p>Music: Bach sung in concert, not church</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>Word and Image: Biography of Beauvoir</p>
        <p>C21</p>
        <p>Book Notes</p>
        <p>C21</p>
        <p>Dispute over PEN gala</p>
        <p>C22</p>
        <p>Sports</p>
        <p>Baseball: Mattingly wants new deal</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Basketball: Knicks top Cavaliers</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>College rules changes</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>Column: Berkow on Runnin' Rebels' victory</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Hockey: Islanders hope LaFontaine stays healthy</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Gartner sparks Ranger offense</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Devils' playoff spot is no surprise this time</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>Education</p>
        <p>Lessons</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>In U.S. school spending, the question is how much</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>Obituaries</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Arthur A. Houghton Jr., ex-president of Steuben Glass</p>
        <p>Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Radical reforms in Moscow</p>
        <p>Relief for the AIDS disaster</p>
        <p>Topics: Savage and racism</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Russell Baker: Paralyzing polls</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Garrison Keillor: Thanks for attacking the N.E.A.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>John J. Shanahan and Thomas S. DeLuca Jr.: Home pork</p>
        <p>A25</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
