<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Revived U.N. Needs Lively Leaders</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="386338"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">URQUHART, BRIAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D8173BF937A1575AC0A966958260" item-length="843" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Revived U.N. Needs Lively Leaders</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Brian Urquhart; Brian Urquhart, scholar-in-residence at the Ford Foundation, was U.N. Under Secretary General for Special Political Affairs.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">URQUHART, BRIAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In the aftermath of the cold war, a resurgence of ethnic and nationalistic drives and a reshaping of the patterns of power and influence have greatly increased the importance of the United Nations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In the aftermath of the cold war, a resurgence of ethnic and nationalistic drives and a reshaping of the patterns of power and influence have greatly increased the importance of the United Nations.</p>
        <p>In the aftermath of the cold war, a resurgence of ethnic and nationalistic drives and a reshaping of the patterns of power and influence have greatly increased the importance of the United Nations.</p>
        <p>The turbulent world of 1990 bears little resemblance to the world of 1945, when the world organization was set up. The way in which the U.N. system does business will therefore need to be changed. Foremost, we need to reconsider how its leaders are selected at such a demanding time.</p>
        <p>In its primary field, the maintenance of international peace and security, the world organization has already begun to function more effectively - in Afghanistan, the Iran-Iraq war, Namibia, Central America and Cambodia. The current crisis over Iraq's annexation of Kuwait is testing the authority of a Security Council that is no longer split by two veto-wielding superpowers. The current crisis is also the first full-scale test of collective security through the U.N.</p>
        <p>It used to be said that serious questions of international peace and security were beyond the capacity of the U.N., and that its main practical usefulness therefore lay in the economic and social field. It now looks as if that always questionable judgment is being stood on its head.</p>
        <p>Today the U.N. faces two main tasks: to combine peacekeeping, peacemaking and collective action into a reliable international system; and to deal with the great problems of global interdependence. The first of these tasks is now beginning to look rather more straightforward than the second, which depends to a great extent on leadership.</p>
        <p>The Secretary General is now recognized as an indispensable figure in the maintenance of peace and the resolution of conflict. Javier Perez de Cuellar, has been performing with great skill in this field. However, his place and his authority in the second broad task of the U.N. - global socioeconomic issues - are still far from clear.</p>
        <p>The U.N. system consists of a central political organization and a galaxy of specialized agencies and programs. The system was designed in 1945 for a world in which problems were comfortably divided into specialized compartments. It is now clear that the global problems and emergencies of our time demand a different approach and, in all probability, a different sort of leadership.</p>
        <p>The Secretary General is only first among equals of the heads of the U.N.'s 30 autonomous agencies: W.H.O., Unesco, Unicef and others. He does not have the authority either to coordinate their work or to demand the vigorous intellectual analysis of great problems that should animate the activities of the U.N. system.</p>
        <p>To manage vast problems such as global warming, refugees, overpopulation, environmental damage and the eradication of hunger and disease requires both the bringing together of divergent interests and the generation of ideas large and practical enough to work. Such ideas, if they are to be effective, must also be presented powerfully and persuasively to the public.</p>
        <p>Until now, the process of selecting senior officials of the U.N. system has been haphazard at best. It is surprising, therefore, that the results, on the whole, have been as good as they have. But change is urgently needed, as emerged clearly in a recent study, ''A World in Need of Leadership: Tomorrow's United Nations.'' Without the paralyzing constrictions of the cold war, a greatly improved process is possible.</p>
        <p>First, the Secretary General and the other executive leaders should serve only a single, seven-year term. They would thus have time to undertake important initiatives. They would be better able to resist political pressures from member governments. There would be less risk of exhaustion or staleness, and the search for the best leaders would not be sidetracked by constant reappointments.</p>
        <p>Second, governments must institute a systematic worldwide search for the best possible candidates, including men and women equally. (Until now, no woman has been seriously considered for the post of Secretary General. Of the 136 executive heads of specialized agencies and programs appointed since 1946, only one has been a woman.) Third, member governments should, in selecting future leaders, give far greater attention to the nature of the jobs to be done and the qualifications needed to do them.</p>
        <p>Fourth, the practice of individuals campaigning for the Secretary Generalship and other leadership posts should cease. At present this practice confuses and destabilizes an already defective selection process.</p>
        <p>The appointed leaders of international organizations are, of course, only a part of the leadership necessary to chart a course for the next century. To achieve results they must work with national and non-governmental leaders.</p>
        <p>But if the governments and the people of the world are to get what they expect and need from international organizations, they must be more attentive to the selection of leaders. Given the high stakes - the very survival of humanity in reasonable conditions - it is time to make the international system work.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
