<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="367187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DA153DF933A25754C0A966958260" item-length="590" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>The Houston Summit</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>The Houston Summit</p>
        <p>The Houston Summit</p>
        <p>Senior Soviet officials appealed for Western economic aid, but while the seven leading Western industrial powers met in Houston to debate whether to help President Mikhail S. Gorbachev, liberals and conservatives in his party differed sharply over what kind of aid to seek, and with what kind of conditions. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>An intractable dispute over farm subsidies erupted among the Group of Seven leaders, threatening to disrupt the unity of the three-day meeting. [A1.]  European officials accused the U.S. of frustrating their efforts to reach a new accord to combat global warming. [A10.]</p>
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>A heavily subsidized Texas savings institution made up of 15 failed institutions earned huge profits. But Bluebonnet Savings made only four new loans in 1989, a Senate panel was told. [A1.]</p>
        <p>A patient does not have property rights over body tissues that may be used to develop new drugs or medicines, a California Supreme Court ruled. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Americans took out $3.9 billion more in consumer credit than they paid off in May, the Government said. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Companies</p>
        <p>A Federal judge took the first steps toward consolidating hundreds of thousands of asbestos cases from around the nation into one large class-action suit. [D1.]</p>
        <p>Galeries Lafayette will specialize in women's clothes made in Europe in its new American store in Trump Tower in Manhattan. [D1.]  The 25-year lease that Donald J. Trump signed with Galeries Lafayette is worth $50 million to $65 million and will improve his financial picture, bankers said. [D5.]</p>
        <p>Mobil Oil has agreed to spend what is expected to be tens of million of dollars to clean up a hazardous pool of oil that has been seeping under the streets of Brooklyn for more than 30 years. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Texas Instruments asked a court to rule that five chip makers must obtain licenses to continue using a technique for gluing semiconductor components to their bases that Texas Instruments said is based on a method it patented in 1977. [D1.]</p>
        <p>The employee buyout group of UAL has enlisted the tentative financial support of five major banks, according to United's unions and bank officials. [D4.]</p>
        <p>Contract talks between Eastern and the pilots' union reached an impasse and a 30-day cooling period begins today. [D4.]</p>
        <p>Mitsubishi Trust and Banking is forming a 50-50 joint venture with the Chicago Research and Trading Group to give clients worldwide an opportunity to deal in futures and options. [D7.]</p>
        <p>Markets</p>
        <p>Two traders of the Chicago Mercantile Exchange were convicted of cheating customers. A third was acquitted. [D1.]</p>
        <p>Stocks seesawed in persistent computer-assisted buying and selling programs before advancing slightly in light trading. The Dow ended the day at 2,914.11, up 9.16. [D8.]</p>
        <p>Prices of Treasury securities fell and interest rates rose in slow trading. [D15.]</p>
        <p>The dollar finished mixed in light domestic trading. [D16.]  Cotton futures prices fell on the New York Cotton Exchange. [D16.]</p>
        <p>Today's Columns</p>
        <p>The cost of electricity will be higher in the second half of the 1990's, says William W. Berry, chairman of Dominion Resources. Talking Business. [D2.]</p>
        <p>When a tanker's oil hits the water these days, huge sums are spent on cleanup. But there are no pure plays in oil-spill cleanup companies. Market Place. [D8.]</p>
        <p>Advertising at trade publications has been virtually flat during the last several years. Kim Foltz: Advertising. [D19.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
