<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business Diary/November 11-16</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="402091"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D81130F93BA25752C1A966958260" item-length="1646" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business Diary/November 11-16</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Allen R. Myerson</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>COMPANIES A New Claim on Drexel</p>
        <p>The Government's claim for $11 billion from Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc. reads like an indictment of organized crime: Drexel plundered failed savings and loans "through bribery, coercion, extortion, fraud and other illegal means." The market for Drexel's "junk bonds" depended on the savings and loans, the Government said, and the collapse of dozens of these institutions can largely be blamed on Drexel. Drexel, still kicking, suggested that the Government is asking for so much because its New York law firm, Cravath, Swaine &amp; Moore, will share in the money recovered. Thomas D. Barr, the Cravath partner handling the Government's case, knows plenty about fighting Federal charges himself. He defeated a 13-year antitrust effort to break up the International Business Machines Corporation. But even he can't recover $11 billion. Drexel's estate is worth only about $3 billion, with other claimants swarming. Major Surgery at First Boston</p>
        <p>Another wounded veteran of the takeover battles of the 1980's is pulling through with intensive care. CS Holding Inc., the parent of Credit Suisse, the ambitious Swiss bank, gained control of CS First Boston last week by pouring in $300 million. First Boston underwent two other delicate, expensive operations: First, CS Holding removed from the First Boston portfolio hundreds of millions of dollars in weak loans. Then came a major amputation, with First Boston dismissing nearly all senior executives in real estate. The only major American investment bank to come under foreign control, First Boston is just the latest to require emergency resuscitation. Samuel G. Liss, a securities industry analyst at Salomon Brothers, said, "The difficulties that began with the demise of Drexel, which intensified the scrutiny of brokerage firm balance sheets, forced the hands of CS First Boston, Kidder Peabody and Shearson." General Electric has had to invest hundreds of millions in Kidder, and American Express had to buy full ownership of Shearson Lehman. On Wall Street, as elsewhere, health care costs are rising out of control. Sad Days for Freedom Bank</p>
        <p>It only had assets of $101.9 million. But Freedom National Bank of New York was often the first place black business people turned for a loan. Freedom was founded in 1964 by investors, among them Jackie Robinson, who wanted to promote Harlem's redevelopment. By the late 80's, overly ambitious goals mired the bank in bad loans. Federal regulators took it over as private rescue efforts failed. On Tuesday morning, Freedom opened its doors to pay off depositors who had been lining up on West 125th Street since 4 A.M. But a larger black-owned institution still thrives justdown the street: Carver Federal Savings Bank, with more than twice the assets, a healthy financial base and managers who know they can't afford as many mistakes as the bigger lenders downtown. Another Chance for Eastern</p>
        <p>Attracting more domestic business travelers helps, but Eastern Airlines's survival might depend on events in the Middle East. On Wednesday, a Federal bankruptcy judge gave Eastern $15 million from an escrow fund to keep flying. The creditors, who say that continued losses are draining their potential payoffs, clamored for the airline's liquidation. Martin R. Shugrue, the airline's trustee and manager, says that the offer of first-class seats for full-fare coach travelers gives the airline a chance of breaking even by March. "He's having some success," said Thomas Longman, an analyst at Bear Stearns. The judge's forebearance has reassured travelers, who are keeping their reservations. But Mr. Longman said that Mr. Shugrue's plans are based on 90-cents-a-gallon aviation fuel. The fuel rose from 58 cents in July to as much as $1.40 more recently, but sold for less than a dollar a gallon last week. Shaky Days at Pan Am</p>
        <p>The only United States airline that flies to Moscow is looking as harried and hungry as most Soviet consumers. The Pan Am Corporation sold its London routes last week to United Airlines for an urgently needed $400 million. United also agreed to guarantee $100 million worth of Pan Am tickets, so travelers would not be stranded if Pan Am folds. The airlines will coordinate their schedules and share their frequent-flier programs -- measures likely to feed passengers from United's domestic network onto Pan Am's international flights. The British and United States Governments have yet to approve the deal. But the airline's survival also depends on the price of fuel. Pan Am's fallback is a $450 million takeover offer from Trans World Airlines and its chairman, Carl C. Icahn. Donald Trump Pays His Dues</p>
        <p>Donald J. Trump agreed on Friday to carve up his interest in the Taj Mahal hotel and casino and serve his creditors as much as half. He missed a $47.3 million interest payment, forcing the Atlantic City hotel into a quick bankruptcy reorganization and losing some assets to creditors for the first time. A payment on Trump's Castle casino comes due next month. THE ECONOMY</p>
        <p>The President's Optimism</p>
        <p>The economy is really in trouble if even the President says it might be in a recession. Until recently, President Bush was able to find prosperity where most economists found decline. On Thursday, his tone changed, somewhat. "I am concerned about the slowdown," he said. "I worry about anybody that wants a job and doesn't have one." Not that the President has lost his ability to sound as upbeat as someone who has just thrown a half dozen ringers one after the other. His economic advisors gave him word that a recession is likely to be mild, he said, "six months at most." He must hope so, or else he could be the one in need of a job come January 1993. . The Inflationary Slope</p>
        <p>Higher energy prices are giving rise less to an inflationary spiral than a gradual slope. The cost of energy did raise the consumer price index six-tenths of 1 percent last month, but only three-tenths without food and energy -- the same pattern as the producer price numbers reported earlier. With a weak economy, said David M. Jones, chief economist at Aubrey G. Lanston &amp; Company, "we're not seeing the oil price shock being translated into a permanent acceleration in core inflation." Tarnish on the Bright Spot</p>
        <p>The weak dollar, an exporter's best friend, resulted in no increase in September shipments. Exports, which had been growing, fell 2.2. percent. "That takes care of the one bright spot in the economy," said Irwin L. Kellner, chief economist at Manufacturers Hanover. Some economists blamed weaker growth and reduced demand abroad, while others said that air cargo companies were too busy carrying military goods to the Middle East. The trade deficit fell 3.3 percent, to $9.4 billion, as imports also declined 2.4 percent. Dr. Kellner drew encouragement from oil imports that rose from in September despite the embargo against Iraq. "It shows there is plenty of oil," he said.  In Brief</p>
        <p>Most of last week's other figures confirmed the economists' consensus that the nation is entering a recession. Industrial production fell eight-tenths of 1 percent in October. Retail sales grew just one-tenth of 1 percent. The Federal Reserve apparently responded by pushing down interest rates.</p>
        <p>Oil prices fell $4.11 to $29.78 a barrel last week, as oil traders said that their fear of a a Middle East war had diminished. INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>Trade Talks in Jeopardy</p>
        <p>A dispute over European farm subsidies last week threatened the success of four years of trade talks. The Europeans reluctantly offered to cut their subsidies, down 15 percent since 1986, another 15 percent by 1996. Inadequate, said Carla A. Hills, the United States trade representative, as the Administration debated whether to stalk out of the negotiations. Her response helped convince the Dutch trade minister, Yvonne van Rooy, to speak of the 15 percent reduction as "not a final offer, but clearly an opening bid." Mrs. Thatcher's Challenge</p>
        <p>A "Europeanist" has arisen to challenge British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher's 11-year reign. Michael Heseltine, who quit her Cabinet in 1986, said on Wednesday that he would contest her leadership in a vote by Conservative members of Parliament on Tuesday. Mr. Heseltine sides with many business people but not Mrs. Thatcher in wanting Britain to take part in the European Community's drive towards economic union. A news service survey gave Mrs. Thatcher a clear edge. But the British public appears restive under high inflation and a headstrong leader. Japan's Quiet Green Movement</p>
        <p>Japanese corporations fear that their envirnomental efforts will be greeted with the sound of no hands clapping. Accused of single-minded dedication to efficiency and growth, some are pursuing recycling, conservation, beautification and rain-forest renewal. Semiconductor companies are working on ways to clean printed circuit boards without using chlorofluorocarbon gases that destroy the ozone layer. But the Japanese consider it defensive and immodest to boast of such efforts, reports the daily Nihon Keizai in an Asia Foundation translation. "Even within corporations, people look askance at environmental proselytizing," the newspaper said. "Action-team members risk accusations of grandstanding by colleagues for using recycled business cards." In Brief</p>
        <p>No longer will natty New Yorkers have to risk a shopping trip downtown. Barneys New York, with support from a Japanese partner, plans to open an 11-floor clothing store on upper Madison Avenue in 1992.</p>
        <p>Scali, McCabe, Sloves gave up the $40 million Volvo advertising account last week. A recent commercial demonstrating the car's ability to hold up under the onslaught of a monster pickup truck turned out to have been rigged.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>COMPANIES A New Claim on Drexel</p>
        <p>The Government's claim for $11 billion from Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc. reads like an indictment of organized crime: Drexel plundered failed savings and loans "through bribery, coercion, extortion, fraud and other illegal means." The market for Drexel's "junk bonds" depended on the savings and loans, the Government said, and the collapse of dozens of these institutions can largely be blamed on Drexel. Drexel, still kicking, suggested that the Government is asking for so much because its New York law firm, Cravath, Swaine &amp; Moore, will share in the money recovered. Thomas D. Barr, the Cravath partner handling the Government's case, knows plenty about fighting Federal charges himself. He defeated a 13-year antitrust effort to break up the International Business Machines Corporation. But even he can't recover $11 billion. Drexel's estate is worth only about $3 billion, with other claimants swarming. Major Surgery at First Boston</p>
        <p>Another wounded veteran of the takeover battles of the 1980's is pulling through with intensive care. CS Holding Inc., the parent of Credit Suisse, the ambitious Swiss bank, gained control of CS First Boston last week by pouring in $300 million. First Boston underwent two other delicate, expensive operations: First, CS Holding removed from the First Boston portfolio hundreds of millions of dollars in weak loans. Then came a major amputation, with First Boston dismissing nearly all senior executives in real estate. The only major American investment bank to come under foreign control, First Boston is just the latest to require emergency resuscitation. Samuel G. Liss, a securities industry analyst at Salomon Brothers, said, "The difficulties that began with the demise of Drexel, which intensified the scrutiny of brokerage firm balance sheets, forced the hands of CS First Boston, Kidder Peabody and Shearson." General Electric has had to invest hundreds of millions in Kidder, and American Express had to buy full ownership of Shearson Lehman. On Wall Street, as elsewhere, health care costs are rising out of control. Sad Days for Freedom Bank</p>
        <p>It only had assets of $101.9 million. But Freedom National Bank of New York was often the first place black business people turned for a loan. Freedom was founded in 1964 by investors, among them Jackie Robinson, who wanted to promote Harlem's redevelopment. By the late 80's, overly ambitious goals mired the bank in bad loans. Federal regulators took it over as private rescue efforts failed. On Tuesday morning, Freedom opened its doors to pay off depositors who had been lining up on West 125th Street since 4 A.M. But a larger black-owned institution still thrives justdown the street: Carver Federal Savings Bank, with more than twice the assets, a healthy financial base and managers who know they can't afford as many mistakes as the bigger lenders downtown. Another Chance for Eastern</p>
        <p>Attracting more domestic business travelers helps, but Eastern Airlines's survival might depend on events in the Middle East. On Wednesday, a Federal bankruptcy judge gave Eastern $15 million from an escrow fund to keep flying. The creditors, who say that continued losses are draining their potential payoffs, clamored for the airline's liquidation. Martin R. Shugrue, the airline's trustee and manager, says that the offer of first-class seats for full-fare coach travelers gives the airline a chance of breaking even by March. "He's having some success," said Thomas Longman, an analyst at Bear Stearns. The judge's forebearance has reassured travelers, who are keeping their reservations. But Mr. Longman said that Mr. Shugrue's plans are based on 90-cents-a-gallon aviation fuel. The fuel rose from 58 cents in July to as much as $1.40 more recently, but sold for less than a dollar a gallon last week. Shaky Days at Pan Am</p>
        <p>The only United States airline that flies to Moscow is looking as harried and hungry as most Soviet consumers. The Pan Am Corporation sold its London routes last week to United Airlines for an urgently needed $400 million. United also agreed to guarantee $100 million worth of Pan Am tickets, so travelers would not be stranded if Pan Am folds. The airlines will coordinate their schedules and share their frequent-flier programs -- measures likely to feed passengers from United's domestic network onto Pan Am's international flights. The British and United States Governments have yet to approve the deal. But the airline's survival also depends on the price of fuel. Pan Am's fallback is a $450 million takeover offer from Trans World Airlines and its chairman, Carl C. Icahn. Donald Trump Pays His Dues</p>
        <p>Donald J. Trump agreed on Friday to carve up his interest in the Taj Mahal hotel and casino and serve his creditors as much as half. He missed a $47.3 million interest payment, forcing the Atlantic City hotel into a quick bankruptcy reorganization and losing some assets to creditors for the first time. A payment on Trump's Castle casino comes due next month. THE ECONOMY</p>
        <p>The President's Optimism</p>
        <p>The economy is really in trouble if even the President says it might be in a recession. Until recently, President Bush was able to find prosperity where most economists found decline. On Thursday, his tone changed, somewhat. "I am concerned about the slowdown," he said. "I worry about anybody that wants a job and doesn't have one." Not that the President has lost his ability to sound as upbeat as someone who has just thrown a half dozen ringers one after the other. His economic advisors gave him word that a recession is likely to be mild, he said, "six months at most." He must hope so, or else he could be the one in need of a job come January 1993. . The Inflationary Slope</p>
        <p>Higher energy prices are giving rise less to an inflationary spiral than a gradual slope. The cost of energy did raise the consumer price index six-tenths of 1 percent last month, but only three-tenths without food and energy -- the same pattern as the producer price numbers reported earlier. With a weak economy, said David M. Jones, chief economist at Aubrey G. Lanston &amp; Company, "we're not seeing the oil price shock being translated into a permanent acceleration in core inflation." Tarnish on the Bright Spot</p>
        <p>The weak dollar, an exporter's best friend, resulted in no increase in September shipments. Exports, which had been growing, fell 2.2. percent. "That takes care of the one bright spot in the economy," said Irwin L. Kellner, chief economist at Manufacturers Hanover. Some economists blamed weaker growth and reduced demand abroad, while others said that air cargo companies were too busy carrying military goods to the Middle East. The trade deficit fell 3.3 percent, to $9.4 billion, as imports also declined 2.4 percent. Dr. Kellner drew encouragement from oil imports that rose from in September despite the embargo against Iraq. "It shows there is plenty of oil," he said.  In Brief</p>
        <p>Most of last week's other figures confirmed the economists' consensus that the nation is entering a recession. Industrial production fell eight-tenths of 1 percent in October. Retail sales grew just one-tenth of 1 percent. The Federal Reserve apparently responded by pushing down interest rates.</p>
        <p>Oil prices fell $4.11 to $29.78 a barrel last week, as oil traders said that their fear of a a Middle East war had diminished. INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>Trade Talks in Jeopardy</p>
        <p>A dispute over European farm subsidies last week threatened the success of four years of trade talks. The Europeans reluctantly offered to cut their subsidies, down 15 percent since 1986, another 15 percent by 1996. Inadequate, said Carla A. Hills, the United States trade representative, as the Administration debated whether to stalk out of the negotiations. Her response helped convince the Dutch trade minister, Yvonne van Rooy, to speak of the 15 percent reduction as "not a final offer, but clearly an opening bid." Mrs. Thatcher's Challenge</p>
        <p>A "Europeanist" has arisen to challenge British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher's 11-year reign. Michael Heseltine, who quit her Cabinet in 1986, said on Wednesday that he would contest her leadership in a vote by Conservative members of Parliament on Tuesday. Mr. Heseltine sides with many business people but not Mrs. Thatcher in wanting Britain to take part in the European Community's drive towards economic union. A news service survey gave Mrs. Thatcher a clear edge. But the British public appears restive under high inflation and a headstrong leader. Japan's Quiet Green Movement</p>
        <p>Japanese corporations fear that their envirnomental efforts will be greeted with the sound of no hands clapping. Accused of single-minded dedication to efficiency and growth, some are pursuing recycling, conservation, beautification and rain-forest renewal. Semiconductor companies are working on ways to clean printed circuit boards without using chlorofluorocarbon gases that destroy the ozone layer. But the Japanese consider it defensive and immodest to boast of such efforts, reports the daily Nihon Keizai in an Asia Foundation translation. "Even within corporations, people look askance at environmental proselytizing," the newspaper said. "Action-team members risk accusations of grandstanding by colleagues for using recycled business cards." In Brief</p>
        <p>No longer will natty New Yorkers have to risk a shopping trip downtown. Barneys New York, with support from a Japanese partner, plans to open an 11-floor clothing store on upper Madison Avenue in 1992.</p>
        <p>Scali, McCabe, Sloves gave up the $40 million Volvo advertising account last week. A recent commercial demonstrating the car's ability to hold up under the onslaught of a monster pickup truck turned out to have been rigged.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
