<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place;   Cleaning Up In Europe</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="358073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INVESTMENT STRATEGIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FUERBRINGER, JONATHAN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DB1F30F932A35755C0A966958260" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place;   Cleaning Up In Europe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jonathan Fuerbringer</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FUERBRINGER, JONATHAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ENVIRONMENTAL companies in Europe are looking attractive, as a result of dirty water, dirty air, acid rain, hazardous waste, sewage and little room for landfills.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ENVIRONMENTAL companies in Europe are looking attractive, as a result of dirty water, dirty air, acid rain, hazardous waste, sewage and little room for landfills.</p>
        <p>ENVIRONMENTAL companies in Europe are looking attractive, as a result of dirty water, dirty air, acid rain, hazardous waste, sewage and little room for landfills.</p>
        <p>One of the pluses, analysts and executives say, is the growing pressure for central regulation of the environment in a united Europe, which is likely to mean stricter and more uniform standards in different countries so that, for example, a business in France does not have an advantage over a company in Germany.</p>
        <p>But these analysts and executives warn that the environmental industry is still fragmented and immature. And they say that investment decisions must be made with caution and a long-term view. (Analysts of environmental stocks in the United States are also cautious now because the prices have already moved too high.) More important, European analysts say the euphoria over the profit potential should not spread to East Germany and the rest of Eastern Europe, where the environment has suffered severely under 40 years of Communist rule. Because of a lack of money, analysts and executives do not expect real environmental business to develop in Eastern Europe until at least the mid-1990's.</p>
        <p>''It's for the very brave,'' said David Owen, senior environmental analyst for Paribas Ltd. in London.</p>
        <p>But he also argues that the environment will have to be dealt with. He said the quality of water in Eastern Europe was now so bad that much of it could not be used in regular processing, as in chemical plants.</p>
        <p>Jerry Leitman, president of ABB Flakt Industrial Processes, the environmental company in the Swedish and Swiss industrial group of Asea Brown Boveri Inc., said the question is: Will ''these needs translate into demand and how soon will that happen?'' He added that ''there is definitely a shortage of money, especially for transnational solutions.''</p>
        <p>Jurgen Jung, director of strategic planning for RWE Entsorgung A.G., said, ''At the moment there is not a big environmental opportunity to earn money in these countries.'' He said the opportunity may be there in several years if the countries move toward market economies. But he said that RWE Entsorgung intended to concentrate its pollution efforts in East Germany. ''Because we have to earn money and we are a small company, we will not go into these countries,'' he said, referring to the rest of Eastern Europe.</p>
        <p>RWE Entsorgung, which specializes in incineration, sewage sludge treatment, and energy and resource recovery, is the waste management subsidiary of RWE, the West German power company that, as Mr. Owen said, is ''an environmental poacher turned gamekeeper.''</p>
        <p>On the environmental play in Europe, Mr. Owen favors companies that have the wherewithal in earnings elsewhere to wait out the fits and starts of environmental development, which he likens to a staircase. Up, with some new regulations, and then flat for a while before rising again. RWE, with electricity accounting for about 40 percent of sales; Asea Brown Boveri, the world's largest capital goods company, and Waste Management Inc., an American-based concern with a growing presence in Europe, fit this category.</p>
        <p>He is also interested in the small niche company. Over the next several years these will include the consulting firms and environmental services companies that will grow up with the newer and more complex environmental regulations. He also looks for companies that do special environmental work that larger concerns are not expected to be interested in.</p>
        <p>One of these companies is Powerscreen International P.L.C., which makes equipment used in recycling sewage and demolition waste. The company is based in Northern Ireland and Ireland, with operations also in South Wales and Pennsylvania. The Pennsylvania arm, Royer, makes machinery for soil and waste shredding and separation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Owen of Paribas also argues that investment in water treatment will be a major environmental opportunity in the 1990's. In his analysis, he said that the spending on water treatment would be far larger than expected because water quality is far below 1980 directives from the European Community. He said, for example, that in Italy 20 million people drink water that is below World Health Organization standards.</p>
        <p>In Britain alone, he notes that estimates for capital investment needed to bring water quality to the levels set by the European Community have leaped from several billion pounds, when the privatization of the water authorities was first considered in 1988, to an official $:24.6 billion. And he estimates the cost could be as high as $:36 billion.</p>
        <p>Among the companies that excite his interest in this area are Simon Engineering of Britian, which is involved in ground water decontamination and sewage treatment; KSB of West Germany, a manufacturer of water and fluid pumps and systems handling toxic effluents, and Compagnie Generale des Eaux of France, which does business in water and waste management and treatment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
