<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big What If: How a Hugo Might Hit L.I.</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="323934"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HURRICANES AND TROPICAL STORMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH CAROLINA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMITT, ERIC</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">HURRICANE HUGO</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD61031F935A35751C0A966958260" item-length="1084" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big What If: How a Hugo Might Hit L.I.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMITT, ERIC</byline>
      <dateline>LONG BEACH, L.I., Feb. 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Weather forecasting has never been a sure-bet science, and hurricanes are among nature's most fickle elements.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Weather forecasting has never been a sure-bet science, and hurricanes are among nature's most fickle elements.</p>
        <p>Weather forecasting has never been a sure-bet science, and hurricanes are among nature's most fickle elements.</p>
        <p>But computer models predicted Hurricane Hugo's swath of destruction so accurately last September that scientists now feel more confident in projecting storm damage and tidal surges in other areas. A team of scientists using a sophisticated computer model called Slosh and first-hand observations from storm-stricken South Carolina have a picture of what might happen to Long Island:</p>
        <p>If a storm the size of Hurricane Hugo hit New York's coast, Kennedy International Airport would be under 26 feet of water.</p>
        <p>A three-story wall of water with cresting waves whipped by 140-mile-per-hour winds would crush houses and high-rise apartments in this city of 35,000 people built on a barrier island.</p>
        <p>Boulders Hurled Like Pebbles</p>
        <p>Fire Island would be pushed 100 feet to 150 feet toward the mainland, stranding any surviving structures in the Atlantic Ocean.</p>
        <p>The research by the New York scientists is likely to help emergency planners prepare for future disasters. But coastal experts say the information is also sure to stoke a running debate about the wisdom of building on barrier islands, the shifting line of white beaches and tall dunes that stretches along and protects the East Coast.</p>
        <p>The lessons learned from Hugo already suggest that spending millions of dollars to build jetties, erect sea walls and replenish sand-starved beaches to protect oceanfront development may be futile in resisting nature's unceasing impulse to push the barrier islands toward the mainland. In Hugo's aftermath, scientists found that boulders from jetties were hurled like pebbles for two or three blocks, crushing buildings. The storm carved new inlets in thin barrier islands and shoved barrier beaches back as much as 150 feet toward the mainland. ''We're fooled into thinking that we can fix the position of beaches,'' said Peter J. R. Buttner, director of environmental management for the New York State Office of Parks, Recreation and Historic Preservation, who is head of an 11-member scientific advisory committee that sent experts to South Carolina. The committee's findings are certain to give new ammunition to opponents of development on barrier islands. The Long Island Regional Planning Board, for instance, recommended in December the gradual elimination of almost 5,000 homes and businesses on Fire Island that are vulnerable to erosion, and called for the return of the land to its natural state.</p>
        <p>Hurricane experts say the chances of a storm of Hugo's force - classified as category four with winds exceeding 131 miles per hour - striking this far north are slim. But ''it doesn't take a hurricane of Hugo's intensity to inflict the same kind of damage,'' said Bob Case, a hurricane specialist at the National Hurricane Center in Coral Gables, Fla.</p>
        <p>Older Long Islanders recall the hurricane of 1938, which killed 600 people as it ripped through eastern Long Island and New England. That hurricane's internal speed was less intense than Hugo's, but it was propelled up the Atlantic seaboard by stronger winds, making it just as deadly, Mr. Case said.</p>
        <p>'The Question is, When?'</p>
        <p>''You know one is coming,'' said Robert W. Johnson, a professor of ecology at Hofstra University, who is a member of the advisory committee. ''The question is, when?''</p>
        <p>The advisory committee, a branch of the New York State Disaster Preparedness Commission, has been studying coastal erosion on Jones Island, where Jones Beach State Park is, and the possible links between erosion, rising sea levels and the global warming trend.</p>
        <p>The research has focused on natural daily and seasonal processes that shape the barrier island, including tides and wind patterns. For the purposes of study, Hurricane Hugo was a coastal geologist's dream come true.</p>
        <p>The length and shape of South Carolina's 120-mile coast north of Charleston closely resembles New York's shoreline from Coney Island to Montauk, offering scientists here a rare opportunity to analyze a monster hurricane's devastating force on a similar coastal profile.</p>
        <p>'A Great Laboratory'</p>
        <p>''Hugo is a great laboratory in which to study how a barrier system behaves,'' said Mr. Buttner.</p>
        <p>Within a week after Hugo hit South Carolina, the committee dispatched a two-member ground team and a two-member air team to survey the damage and any coastal changes. Using a four-wheel drive vehicle, the two geologists on the ground measured sand movements, inland water levels, new inlets and the effects of jetties and sea walls.</p>
        <p>The air team, including Mr. Buttner, flying in a plane 200 feet above the shoreline, took more than 1,600 photographs.</p>
        <p>The committee then incorporated information from a computer program called Slosh, or Sea, Lake and Overland Surge from Hurricane. The program was developed by the National Hurricane Center and the Army Corps of Engineers. The model includes a topographical profile of all coastal areas in the country, so to predict a hurricane's tidal surge at any given place, scientists plug in measurements like the hurricane's wind speed, the storm's forward speed and the radius of the hurricane eye.</p>
        <p>Wiping Out Freeport and Merrick</p>
        <p>The storm surge, the amount of additional water that builds on top of a normal tide during a hurricane, is what causes much of the flooding. Combining values from the model with their own measurements, the scientists developed a map of the New York metropolitan area that projects storm surges from a Hugo-class storm. Because the New York coast is more densely populated than the South Carolina shore where Hugo hit, the damage here would be much greater, scientists said.</p>
        <p>''A storm that size would basically wipe out Freeport, Merrick, Bellmore, Wantagh'' and many other villages along the Island's South Shore, where the model predicts 10 to 15 feet of flooding, Mr. Buttner said.</p>
        <p>The Hudson River would rise more than 28 feet at the George Washington Bridge crossing and would be certain to flood Manhattan and New Jersey, the model indicates.</p>
        <p>The advisory committee does not make disaster-management policy, but its findings are likely to be used by emergency planners to study evacuation procedures, recovery operations and structural designs and requirements for buildings.</p>
        <p>''Once this research is completed, it will significantly improve our response capabilities,'' said Anthony J. Germano, deputy director of the New York State Emergency Management Office.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
