<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ambitious Air Pollution Bill Sent to White House</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="396038"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="THE STRUGGLE IN CONGRESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D8153BF93BA15753C1A966958260" item-length="1325" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ambitious Air Pollution Bill Sent to White House</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Senate granted final Congressional approval today to the 1990 Clean Air Act, a measure that transforms the 20-year-old original law from a path-breaking but narrow statute into an ambitious plan to cut contamination from every sizable source of air pollution in the nation.</p>
        <p>The Senate vote, 89 to 10, means the legislation now goes to the White House, which has indicated that President Bush will sign it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Senate granted final Congressional approval today to the 1990 Clean Air Act, a measure that transforms the 20-year-old original law from a path-breaking but narrow statute into an ambitious plan to cut contamination from every sizable source of air pollution in the nation.</p>
        <p>The Senate vote, 89 to 10, means the legislation now goes to the White House, which has indicated that President Bush will sign it.</p>
        <p>Almost everyone who negotiated the final accord agreed that the new legislation is one of the exceptional achievements in the current session of Congress and the most inclusive environmental statute ever approved by Congress. It is the first to tackle an immense environmental problem with equally broad legislation. The first Clean Air Act in 1970 was written on 41 pages; the 1990 act may take up more than 700 pages.</p>
        <p>"I'm convinced that people will look back at the 101st Congress and say, 'God bless them,' " said Representative Gerry Sikorski, a Minnesota Democrat who played a major role in developing provisions to end acid rain and to limit air pollution from toxic substances. "I'm not so sure they'll look back at the tax and budget fights. I know they'll remember the clean air legislation."  New Ways of Cutting Pollution</p>
        <p>Lawmakers said the measure offers imaginative and, in some cases, experimental provisions to reduce environmental contamination, like economic incentives to polluters that are aimed at gaining greater cooperation from companies.</p>
        <p>The legislation will serve as a model for updating in the 1990's the other 1970's-era statutes that form the foundation of the nation's environmental program, the lawmakers said.</p>
        <p>The largest economic incentives are in a provision on acid rain. The provision sets an overall annual level of emissions of sulfur dioxide from power plants, of 8.9 million tons, by the year 2000. That level is less than the half the current emissions. The measure sets a specific emissions limit on 111 utilities in 22 states. Under this plan, if a utility reduces emissions below the required level, it can sell the difference as a credit to new power plants or plants that are planning expansions. Those plants have to buy the credits to win permission from the Government to emit all their pollution.</p>
        <p>The lawmakers said they believe they can meet their goal of cutting emissions of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide by 12 million to 14 million tons annually. The pollution credits will help offset the cost of installing equipment in power plants in the those states.</p>
        <p>For instance, a power plant in Ohio, required to release no more than 30,000 tons of sulfur dioxide a year by the year 2000, has the option to install equipment that would reduce its emissions to 20,000 tons. That plant could then sell the 10,000-ton difference as a pollution credit to a new plant in Utah. The Utah plant, which expects to produce 10,000 tons of sulfur dioxide each year, would have to buy the 10,000-ton allowance to operate. The incentive, then, for both buyer and seller is to reduce their emissions as low as possible.</p>
        <p>The proposal for credits was developed by the Environmental Defense Fund, an environmental group based in New York and was included in the Clean Air legislation that President Bush submitted to Congress last year.</p>
        <p>It is a departure from the traditional environmental requirements, which commanded the environmental agency to develop new limits on pollutants and then required the agency to manage a program to enforce the new controls. Lawmakers hope the new approach will lead to more cooperation from utilities and decrease the burdens on the environmental agency, which has been criticized by Congress for failing to manage or enforce the nation's environmental law aggressively.</p>
        <p>"This approach cut the cost of achieving substantial reduction in acid rain pollution in half and made it possible for the President, Congress and environmental groups to negotiate a strong Clean Air bill after 13 years of gridlock," said William J. Roberts, legislative director in Washington for the Environmental Defense Fund.  Specifics in Legislation</p>
        <p>The legislation is also more precise in specifying the limits on pollution for industries and businesses and in setting timetables for meeting those limits. No other environmental statute is as precise. The agreement requires oil companies to develop new types of gasoline that burn more cleanly by 1995 and names nine cities, including New York, where the only gasoline available for sale will be the new fuel. Cities are required to reduce concentrations of ozone, a principal component of smog, to a level considered safe, and the act includes penalties if cities miss the deadlines.</p>
        <p>By writing the specific requirements into the legislation, lawmakers reduced the role the environmental agency would play in developing standards. The original Clean Air Act gave the agency such broad discretion to develop new rules and to enforce them that the effectiveness of the old law was severely limited, particularly in controlling toxic pollution from factories.</p>
        <p>The original law called on the environmental agency to identify chemicals that were toxic and to set limits on the amounts of these chemicals factories could release into the air. In 20 years, the agency completed work on just seven compounds.</p>
        <p>"We have to be more direct and more clear in environmental legislation than we were in the past," said Representative Henry A. Waxman, the California Democrat who was one of the most influential negotiators on the measure. "We wanted to minimize the number of things we could leave to the E.P.A.'s discretion because we've seen that the E.P.A. became more interested in protecting polluters than the environment."</p>
        <p>Mr. Waxman and other lawmakers were cautious about predicting the success of the new approach. The Environmental Protection Agency is still charged with writing hundreds of new rules and with enforcing many provisions. Environmental leaders noted that hidden within the bill were waivers and exemptions that would reduce its effectiveness.</p>
        <p>And industrial executives said they were concerned whether they could meet the new guidelines and about the cost of putting the plan into effect. Various estimates have put the annual bill at $20 billion to $50 billion. Under the best of circumstances, Mr. Waxman said, the nation will not begin to breathe significantly cleaner air until after the turn of the century.  Bridging Differences</p>
        <p>The agreement was possible, lawmakers said, because a formula was discovered to bridge the political divisions caused by an environmental threat that has multiple causes, crosses state boundaries and thus puts powerful groups and entire regions at odds.</p>
        <p>The most important factor in the new formula, they said, was the overwhelming public concern about the deterioration of the environment and broad popular support for measures to stem that decline, even if those measures resulted in higher costs for cars, electricity and consumer goods.</p>
        <p>"The equalizing factor that is unique to the environmental movement is that the American public has said overwhelmingly that they want the environment cleaned up, be it water or air, hazardous wastes or nuclear contamination," said Representative Mike Synar, a Democrat of Oklahoma. Earlier this year, Mr. Synar helped to establish the coalition between environmentalists and industrial leaders that led to agreements on reducing urban smog and toxic air pollution.</p>
        <p>A final factor in reaching political compromises, said environmental leaders and industrial executives, is that much more is known about the causes and effects of pollution. And lawmakers, especially House members elected in the mid-1970's and early 1980's are now experts in understanding environmental problems and in developing solutions. Many have also achieved enough prominence and seniority to defend their proposals.</p>
        <p>THE STRUGGLE IN CONGRESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
