<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="344351"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D7103AF934A25757C0A966958260" item-length="1338" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-19</p>
        <p>Lithuania is prepared to compromise on some of the independence measures that drove Moscow to threaten severe economic sanctions against the republic, the Lithuanian Prime Minister said.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-19</p>
        <p>Lithuania is prepared to compromise on some of the independence measures that drove Moscow to threaten severe economic sanctions against the republic, the Lithuanian Prime Minister said.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A2-19</p>
        <p>Lithuania is prepared to compromise on some of the independence measures that drove Moscow to threaten severe economic sanctions against the republic, the Lithuanian Prime Minister said.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>Insurgency swept into Moscow. Long-suffering dissidents finally took control of the Moscow City Council - and of the broken, demoralized city.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Sculptor to honor Siberia's victims</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Czechoslovakia's sense of harmony after the ''velvet revolution'' that toppled Communist rule last November has turned into discord in the Moravian capital of Brno.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>The U.S. should not rejoin Unesco, the Bush Administration has decided. A State Department report says that the U.N. organization wastes money, is poorly managed and has not taken a firm stand in defense of freedom of the press.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Blocked funds put U.S. role in Seville world fair in doubt</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Vancouver is fighting the AIDS virus by issuing clean needles to drug addicts who want them. The program just marked its first anniversary and drew praise in an article in The Canadian Journal of Public Health.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Ortega warns of snag on contras</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Llosa announces he will remain in race in Peru</p>
        <p>A2</p>
        <p>Nepal's first multiparty government in 30 years will be formed. King Birendra invited the national opposition, including Communist leaders, to form the new government.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Malaysia is turning away boat people from Vietnam with increasing frequency, despite continued protests from the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees, diplomats and international relief workers say.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>News analysis: India's accusations that Pakistan is trying to provoke another war over Kashmir are diverting attention from the inability of Prime Minister V. P. Singh's Government to stem resurgent tides of secessionism.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Sanctions against South Africa should continue, Nelson Mandela said. His call took on special meaning in Britain, where Prime Minister Thatcher advocates a relaxing of sanctions and has taken steps to do so.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Ethiopian Government seen as fighting to survive</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Lusaka journal: All about what's going on in Zambia, slyly told</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A20-22, B8-10</p>
        <p>The environment is at the forefront of American politics. Officials are finding themselves forced to recast their public postures on hazardous waste, acid rain and the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Barrels of plutonium-laced material stored at the Rocky Flats nuclear weapons plant actually contain wastes subject to regulation by Colorado and are being stored illegally, a Federal judge has ruled.</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>The battle against aircraft noise is being won by neighbors of airports around the country whose complaints were once often shunted aside by government officials and airlines.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>The shortage of affordable shelter for millions of needy people is putting enormous pressure on the nation's already overburdened public housing system and giving a new edge to an old policy debate.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The final appeal of a retarded man who, as a teen-ager, murdered a state trooper was turned down by the Supreme Court. By lifting its stay of execution, the Court will allow Louisiana to execute the prisoner.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Supreme Court lets stand a ban on school dance</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Convict suspected as drug figure flees Texas jail</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>A strike by teachers in Oklahoma shut nearly a quarter of the school districts. More than 18,000 teachers are protesting the Legislature's failure to pass an education bill that would have included pay raises.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Scores of transcendental meditators have moved their companies to Fairfield, Iowa, or begun new ones there. And they have brought with them prosperity and growth to an isolated patch of America's heartland.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Cincinnati arts center denies obscenity charges</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Washington Talk: Rewriting a budget (and its rules?)</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>REGIONAL</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Mayor Dinkins will not be able to vote as a member of the Board of Estimate on the renewal of two cable television franchises in Manhattan, the Conflicts of Interest Board ruled.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Two men Mayor Dinkins depends on, Norman Steisel and Bill Lynch, have developed a steady relationship, comfortably sharing power and the Mayor's confidence.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>The School of Library Service at Columbia University, the oldest and one of the most prestigious library schools in the nation, may close at the end of the academic year.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>7 Days has ceased publishing. Started two years ago with great fanfare, the magazine became popular with New York trendsetters, but it could not generate advertising support.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>The leader of a group of white youths ''boasted that he would 'blow the heads off the nigger bastards' '' hours before Yusuf K. Hawkins was shot to death, a prosecutor asserted in his opening statement in the Bensonhurst murder trial.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>The teen-ager killed by a policeman in Teaneck, N.J., last Tuesday was buried after a funeral service marked by muted anger amid themes of reconciliation and reform.</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>An alarming number of teen-agers and even children as young as 6 are riding outside elevators as they sweep up and down the shafts of high-rise housing projects.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Cuomo says budget is close, but legislators are less sure</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Daily News stops checkoffs</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Broadway producer pleads guilty to defrauding investors</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Animal-rights advocate agrees to year in jail in bomb plot</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Judge urged to allow more tests without answers disclosed</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DIGEST</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES</p>
        <p>In a restricted diet, tantalizing clues to longevity</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>The anguish of a heart valve's failure haunts the developer</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Ancient paintings in the Amazon, but how ancient?</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Medical detectives track down an elusive odor disorder</p>
        <p>C3</p>
        <p>Can a nice green lawn be hazardous to your health?</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Search for brown dwarfs in space heats up</p>
        <p>C6</p>
        <p>Personal Computers</p>
        <p>C7</p>
        <p>Peripherals</p>
        <p>C8</p>
        <p>Science Watch</p>
        <p>C9</p>
        <p>Science Q&amp;A</p>
        <p>C11</p>
        <p>ARTS/ENTERTAINMENT</p>
        <p>Chinese loyalty and dissent in art</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>Alice Munro writes of home</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>Theater: ''The Piano Lesson''</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>Music: Classical Band and Grande Bande</p>
        <p>C14</p>
        <p>Exploring the trombone</p>
        <p>C15</p>
        <p>Chamber Music Society</p>
        <p>C16</p>
        <p>Dance: By and for students</p>
        <p>C20</p>
        <p>Word and Image</p>
        <p>2 novellas by Natalia Ginzburg</p>
        <p>C17</p>
        <p>Migrant workers' plight, on TV</p>
        <p>C18</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B13</p>
        <p>Tokyo, where fashion is an art</p>
        <p>Patterns</p>
        <p>By Design</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>Baseball: Mets clobber Cubs</p>
        <p>D21</p>
        <p>Coach gets Yanks back to basics</p>
        <p>D25</p>
        <p>Brewers rout Red Sox, 18-0</p>
        <p>D25</p>
        <p>Basketball: Knicks win</p>
        <p>D21</p>
        <p>N.B.A. Notebook</p>
        <p>D25</p>
        <p>Columns: Anderson on Don King</p>
        <p>D21</p>
        <p>On Horse Racing</p>
        <p>D23</p>
        <p>Hockey: Rangers plan strategy</p>
        <p>D24</p>
        <p>Devils' hopes unravel</p>
        <p>D24</p>
        <p>Lacrosse: Notebook</p>
        <p>D23</p>
        <p>Marathon: Bordin and Mota win in Boston</p>
        <p>D21</p>
        <p>SportsPeople</p>
        <p>D23</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B12</p>
        <p>Marco A. Robles, former President of Panama</p>
        <p>Raymond Parker, abstract artist</p>
        <p>EDITORIALS/LETTERS/OP-ED</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>America, arrogant trade cop</p>
        <p>China policy, twice tainted</p>
        <p>Her face kept secrets</p>
        <p>Lost lesson of mental health</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Anthony Lewis: Verdict on Reagan</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Flora Lewis: The last war in Europe</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Victor Danilenko: Vilnius - its own worst enemy</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Humphrey Taylor: U.S. health care - built for waste</p>
        <p>A25</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
