<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Campus Life: U.C., Irvine; Chemist Links Global Warming To Methane Leaks</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="53" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="399615"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHANE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATURE (JOURNAL)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROLAND, F SHERWOOD (PROF)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DD1238F932A25752C1A966958260" item-length="703" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Campus Life: U.C., Irvine; Chemist Links Global Warming To Methane Leaks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>IRVINE, Calif.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Once called "the man who saw the end of the world" and "the man who knew too much," F. Sherwood Roland, a chemist from the University of California at Irvine, is again drawing attention with his most recent studies on methane and its contribution to global warming, or the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>Professor Roland, who first made headlines in the mid-1970's with his discovery that chlorofluorocarbons in aerosol spray cans contribute to the destruction of the earth's protective ozone layer in the atmosphere, suggested in last month's issue of the British science journal Nature that global warming might be slowed by reducing worldwide methane emissions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Once called "the man who saw the end of the world" and "the man who knew too much," F. Sherwood Roland, a chemist from the University of California at Irvine, is again drawing attention with his most recent studies on methane and its contribution to global warming, or the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>Professor Roland, who first made headlines in the mid-1970's with his discovery that chlorofluorocarbons in aerosol spray cans contribute to the destruction of the earth's protective ozone layer in the atmosphere, suggested in last month's issue of the British science journal Nature that global warming might be slowed by reducing worldwide methane emissions.</p>
        <p>His study found, for example, that natural gas pipes in Eastern European cities are leaking huge amounts of methane. Repairing the leaks, he concluded, would help slow global warming by reducing the excess methane that is not broken down in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>"There are lots of studies on methane of one form or another," Professor Roland said in an interview in his office, a small cluttered room whose walls are festooned with opera posters. "We're the only ones doing regular measurements that will give us a global assay."</p>
        <p>Samples From the Pacific</p>
        <p>His 20-member research team has been collecting air samples from throughout the Pacific since 1983 every three months in an effort to monitor the levels of methane in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Professor Roland's findings come at a time of rising concern about the health of the earth's atmosphere. He has already gone to New York and Washington for meetings concerning global warming and other atmospheric issues and will be going to Paris and Tokyo in the next few weeks.</p>
        <p>"There's enough interest in atmospheric science and enough concern about the problems," Professor Roland said. "that there are both scientific meetings on a global basis."</p>
        <p>The still sluggish response of the political community to the problem, however, does not surprise him. "After a certain point," he said, "you realize that the time scale for political action is measured in units of 5 or 10 years, not tomorrow."  In Center of Debate</p>
        <p>When he and his assistant, Mario Molina, discovered in 1973 that chlorofluorocarbons were eating away at the earth's protective ozone layer, the scientific community was thrown into fiery debate that lasted several years.</p>
        <p>It was not until the National Academy of Science in Washington published a report in 1985 acknowledging the dangers of chlorofluorocarbons that the research findings were accepted. The subsequent discovery of a hole in the ozone layer prompted further concern about the effects of these chemicals on the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Though Professor Roland says he tries not to get involved in the political aspects of science, he noted that scientists are obliged to alert the public to a health danger.</p>
        <p>"I feel that what one has is a responsibility to say what it is you found out," he said. He said that since there are two sides to every issue, "it's perfectly reasonable to say what you would do if the decision were up to you."  A Favorite Among Students</p>
        <p>Professor Roland, a tall and rangy 63-year-old who has been here for 26 years, has a gruff voice that belies a gentle demeanor and an easygoing manner that has made him a favorite among students.</p>
        <p>"He is very supportive," said Melinda Sargent, a research assistant from Westminster, Calif., who is working toward her Ph.D. in atmospheric chemistry. "He's very good at directing you."</p>
        <p>Tim Gilpin, a graduate student from La Jolla, Calif., who has been involved in chlorofluorocarbons and methane research for seven years said: "Dr. Roland really allows you the freedom to learn a lot. He gives you credit that you have a mind and you can think."</p>
        <p>Despite his accomplishments, Professor Roland said that being well-known has a price. He is often criticized by nonscientists for research whose effects they neither see nor understand.  "One of the things it tells you," he said, "is how much we are in need of better science education in this country, because the knowledge of science is so thin, on average, that it is difficult to separate out what is good science from what is nonsense."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
