<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="367722"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDC1430F931A25754C0A966958260" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>The Houston Summit</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>The Houston Summit</p>
        <p>The Houston Summit</p>
        <p>Negotiation and compromise were necessary on every key issue at the 16th meeting of the seven ranking Western powers, from aid to the Soviet Union to the environment, from relations with China to agricultural subsidies. News Analysis. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>The Group of Seven wrapped up their three-day meeting by proclaiming their united goal of fostering worldwide prosperity, but they hardly resolved the three main economic issues that had divided them at the outset. [A14.]  Excerpts from the Economic Declaration issued by the Group of Seven. [A15.]</p>
        <p>Leaders at the summit conference declined to adopt a West German proposal to set limits on the emissions of gases that contribute to global warming. Instead, they opted for an experimental program involving Brazil. [A14.]</p>
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>President Bush defended his son Neil, who has been charged with violating conflict of interest rules in a Denver savings case. The remarks came as the Senate approved measures to toughen penalties for those found guilty of savings and loan fraud. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Neil Bush charged that Federal regulators had acted ''with vengeance'' against him and accused them of concealing evidence that he said would exonerate him of their accusations. [D6.]</p>
        <p>A former savings and loan executive was indicted on 17 counts for his actions at the Sunbelt Savings Association. Edwin T. McBirney 3d was the 79th person charged as a result of savings and loan investigations by the Dallas Bank Fraud Task Force. [D1.]</p>
        <p>The Federal Government is ignoring scientific and technical data that could potentially be one of its most valuable weapons in the battle for high-technology international competitiveness, the Congressional Office of Technology Assessment reports. [D2.]</p>
        <p>The National Advisory Committee on Semiconductors is expected to issue a report today stating that the U.S. electronics industry is in danger. [D1.]</p>
        <p>Markets</p>
        <p>The Treasury informed the credit markets that bids at a particular price level would be limited to a maximum of 35 percent of the total amount of securities to be sold. The annoucement turned the auction of $8 billion worth of new seven-year Treasury notes into a protest vote. [D1.]  Yields were down on tax-exempt and taxable money market funds. [D7.]</p>
        <p>A key Senator offered a potential compromise in the vigorous debate over the Administration's proposal for changes in the regulation of stock index futures. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Stocks advanced sharply in heavy trading, with the Dow rising 41.83, to 2,932.67. [D8.]</p>
        <p>The dollar rebounded but dealers predicted that the currency would resume its downward course shortly. [D15.]  Prices of copper futures leaped to their highest levels in two months. [D15.]</p>
        <p>Companies</p>
        <p>The nation's largest banks were told to write off as a loss 20 percent of their loans to Brazil and increase their write-offs of loans to Argentina to 60 percent, from 40 percent, bankers said. [D1.]</p>
        <p>CBS reported a 16 percent rise in net income. [D1.]</p>
        <p>DeSoto plans to sell most of the company's operations. [D4.]</p>
        <p>Today's Columns</p>
        <p>Many Kay Jewelers bondholders are upset by what they regard as the sheer brazenness of Ratners Group's proposed offer of 75 cents on the dollar for their securities. Talking Deals. [D2.]</p>
        <p>The legal view of where investors' disputes with brokers can be arbitrated is becoming increasingly muddled. Market Place. [D8.]</p>
        <p>J. Walter Thompson has found an unusual way to come up with new advertising campaigns: it lets the research and account management departments do the job. Kim Foltz: Advertising. [D17.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
