<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Carbon Dioxide Warming Is Good for the Planet</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="351119"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D7153AF934A35756C0A966958260" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Carbon Dioxide Warming Is Good for the Planet</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Senator Al Gore Jr. tells us in an Earth Day article (''To Skeptics on Global Warming,'' Op-Ed, April 22) that the most compelling evidence for carbon dioxide-induced global warming is the close correlation in Antarctic ice-core data between carbon dioxide and temperature over the last 160,000 years. Scrutiny of the data, however, makes it clear that the scientific evidence does not support his contention.</p>
        <p>We need first to realize the chicken-and-egg nature of the ice-core data. Which comes first: changes in atmospheric carbon dioxide concentration or changes in temperature?</p>
        <p>The scientists who performed the original analyses on the ice core noted that changes in atmospheric carbon dioxide cannot be demonstrated to precede changes in air temperature when going from glacial to interglacial conditions. But in going from interglacial to glacial conditions, changes in air temperature always occur first, followed by changes in atmospheric carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Hence, changes in carbon dioxide concentration cannot be claimed to be the cause of changes in air temperature because the appropriate sequence of events (temperature changes following carbon dioxide change) is not only never present in the data, but it is actually violated in half of the record.</p>
        <p>How is it that Senator Gore's ''most compelling evidence'' is so readily refuted? The only reasonable answer is that his basic premise is wrong: the earth just doesn't respond to carbon dioxide as the computer models say it does. And that should surprise no one. To make a valid prediction about the real world, for example, it is necessary to account for every real-world process of significance to earth's climate system; even the models' creators do not claim such knowledge or expertise. Consequently, to base sweeping social changes on imperfect predictive tools is unwise and contrary to mainstream scientific thinking.</p>
        <p>I would agree, however, that as we debate and formulate policy in this area, we must bear in mind that our actions will affect not only our generation, but also generations to come. We owe it to our children and our children's children to investigate all aspects of carbon dioxide and global change. And when we do so, we find a wealth of beneficial effects from atmospheric carbon dioxide enrichment.</p>
        <p>First, more carbon dioxide in the air increases the productivity of nearly all plants. It also reduces the rate at which water is lost to the atmosphere through individual plant leaves, greatly increasing the efficiency with which plants use water in producing organic matter. Plants of the future will be able to grow in areas that have been too dry for them.</p>
        <p>Greater vegetative cover will mean less soil erosion. Greater plant productivity will also return more organic matter to the soil, increasing its fertility. With more organic matter in the soil, earthworm populations should be greatly augmented, further improving the fertility, structure, aeration and drainage of natural and agricultural soils. Larger and more vigorous populations of other soil organisms will also accelerate weathering and the creation of new soil, as well as increase the rate at which plants extract nitrogen from the atmosphere and use it as a fertilizer.</p>
        <p>All of these good things will happen because there has generally been more carbon dioxide in the air than there is now, except for the geologically brief period of the ice ages. Consequently, plants are much better adapted to living under such conditions; that's why botanists and other plant scientists refer to the rising carbon dioxide content of earth's atmosphere as atmospheric carbon dioxide enrichment and aerial carbon dioxide fertilization. It's one of the best things that could happen to the planet.</p>
        <p>So let's tell both sides. The facts demand it. Reason dictates it. Earth deserves it.</p>
        <p>SHERWOOD B. IDSO</p>
        <p>Research Physicist, Dept. of Agriculture</p>
        <p>Water Conservation Laboratory</p>
        <p>Phoenix, April 24, 1990</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
