<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>We Can't Take More of This 'Reagan Boom'</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="323531"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANDERSON, MARTIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEONTIEFF, WASSILY (PROF)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DC1130F937A35751C0A966958260" item-length="422" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>We Can't Take More of This 'Reagan Boom'</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Martin Anderson's exultant celebration ''The Reagan Boom - Greatest Ever'' (Op-Ed, Jan. 17) cannot be left to stand without rebuttal.</p>
        <p>True, the long recovery from the deep depression that brought President Reagan to power carried this country to the high point of the usual cyclical wave characterized by a low rate of unemployment and a high gross national product. It is most likely that wholesale tax cuts inaugurated by Mr. Reagan have made the level of the G.N.P., as measured by the Government statisticians, several billion dollars higher than it would otherwise have been. But at what a cost!</p>
        <p>Drastic cuts in public spending (except for military purposes) left the physical infrastructure of this country in ruin. City streets and transportation facilities, water supply and sewage systems, particularly in large metropolitan areas, are collapsing; the once glorious interstate highways are crumbling, and cramped airports are incapable of handling the rapidly increasing traffic. Despite the valiant effort of the underfinanced, underpowered Environmental Protection Agency, our lakes, rivers and forests are succumbing to deadly acid rain.</p>
        <p>What is even worse, the intellectual, cultural and social infrastructure of the country has suffered even more during this greater-than-ever boom than its physical counterpart. Primary and secondary schooling have been so weakened that a whole generation of boys and girls can hardly read, write or count, while the soaring price of higher education (which, in contrast to the United States, is free in most other advanced countries) makes it impossible for many young people to take advantage of it.</p>
        <p>No wonder the competitiveness of the United States is rapidly declining; many of our high technology industries are losing one battle after another in the struggle for their share of the foreign and even their own domestic market. At the same time, the rich are getting richer, and the poor are getting homeless.</p>
        <p>Let us hope that contrary to Mr. Anderson's expectations the ''Reagan boom'' will not continue in its present form for four or eight more years. If it does, the United States will find itself entering the 21st century as the richest country (in total value of stocks and bonds traded on the stock exchanges), but culturally and socially less advanced than other developed countries.</p>
        <p>WASSILY LEONTIEF</p>
        <p>New York, Jan. 19, 1990</p>
        <p>The writer, professor of economics at New York University, won the Nobel Prize for economics in 1973.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
