<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Each Country's Agenda at the Economic Summit Meeting</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="366974"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D9143BF93AA35754C0A966958260" item-length="598" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Each Country's Agenda at the Economic Summit Meeting</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: UNITED STATES</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: UNITED STATES</p>
        <p>UNITED STATES</p>
        <p>A key aim of the Americans will be to persuade industrial parnters, especially the Europeans, to phase out trade-distorting farm subsidies and import quotas. The agricultural dispute threatens to scuttle the four-year-old Uruguay Round of negotiations to liberalize the world trading system under the 97-nation General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade. The Bush Administration will oppose giving direct financial aid to Moscow, until there is geniune evidence of economic change in the Soviet union. The United States will also resist efforts to set a timetable for reducing emissionsof carbon dioxide and other gases.</p>
        <p>JAPAN</p>
        <p>The Japanese will push for a resumption of loans and aid to China. Tokyo argues that continuing the economic sanctions against Beijing, which came after the massacre of striking students around Tiananmen Square last year, will only make the Chinese leadership increasingly isolated. Japan opposes direct aid to Moscow, because of the long-running territorial issue of four northern islands, which the Soviets have occupied since the last days of World War II. Tokyo will also try to resist dropping import curbs that protect its rice farmers.</p>
        <p>WEST GERMANY</p>
        <p>Financial support to the Soviet Union is at the top of the German agenda. It is pushing for a Western aid package for the faltering Soviet economy of up to $20 billion. Bonn hopes financial aid to the Soviets will ease Moscow's qualms about German political unification. On the environment, Bonn will press for curbs on emission sof carbon dioxide and other gases, along the lines of its commitment to reduce carbon dioxide emissions some 25 percent by 2005.</p>
        <p>FRANCE</p>
        <p>The French, like the Germans, will push for emergency aid to the Soviet Union. The Mitterrand Government is also seeking support from its industrial partners to offer debtr relief for a broad range of developing nations. The French will resist the American push to lower subsidies and import curbs that protect European farmers. And France will seek a new commitment on the environment urging reductions in emissions of carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>BRITAIN</p>
        <p>The British expect the drive for a Western pledge of financial aid for the Soviet Union to be the key issue. Like the Americans, the British will resist. Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher believes the West should first offer Moscow economic and technical advice on how to build a market economy before it gives President Mikhail S. Gorbachev money. Mrs. Thatcher has been somehwat subdued in international gatherings recently, partly because of her lagging popular support and economic difficulties at home, where inflation and interest rates are high.</p>
        <p>ITALY</p>
        <p>Italy is concerned that financing developing nations will suffer in the rush to help Eastern Europe. The Italians, like the French, will push for a commitment to new financing arrangements for less-developed nations, especially so-called middle-income developing countries. Rome does support aid for the Soviet Union, especially since Rome's trade ties with Moscow are expanding.</p>
        <p>CANADA</p>
        <p>On the key issue of assistance to the Soviet Union, Canada shares the cautious stance of the United States, Japan and Britain. Prime Minister Brian Mulroney will use the summit meeting to try to assure his industrial partners that the recent consitutional crisis over the status of Quebec will not cripple Canada and that its economy remains sound and attractive to foreign investment. Canada also supports the American initiative to deal with the farm-subsidy issue in an effort to further open up world trade.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
