<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Camera</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="86" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Pastimes Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="405405"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PHOTOGRAPHY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHRISTMAS GIFTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRUNDBERG, ANDY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DB1138F931A35751C1A966958260" item-length="751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Camera</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andy Grundberg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GRUNDBERG, ANDY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Family and friends often are at a loss when it comes to buying gifts for photographers or would-be photographers. Cameras and lenses are expensive, and we're likely to be picky about which ones we want. So unless you want to drag the potential recipient and your checkbook to the camera-store counter, accessories may be a better choice.</p>
        <p>Here are a few accessory gift suggestions, out of a waiting cast of hundreds:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Family and friends often are at a loss when it comes to buying gifts for photographers or would-be photographers. Cameras and lenses are expensive, and we're likely to be picky about which ones we want. So unless you want to drag the potential recipient and your checkbook to the camera-store counter, accessories may be a better choice.</p>
        <p>Here are a few accessory gift suggestions, out of a waiting cast of hundreds:</p>
        <p>Print albums. I don't know about you, but I am always getting to the end of those plastic pages that hold my treasured snapshots. Since almost everybody shoots print film these days, almost everybody needs a place to put them. What if your favorite photographer shoots slides? Try a slide file or projector tray instead. Whatever organizer you buy, it will be better than the proverbial shoebox. Estimated cost: About $20 or more if you want a leather binding.</p>
        <p>Cleaning equipment. A can of compressed air (Dust Off or other brand) may seem a mundane gift, but the experienced photographer knows that it has endless uses. The newer types have propellants that don't hurt the ozone layer, which makes using them guilt-free. To spice i up the gift, include a packet of lens-cleaning tissue or one of the new long-lasting cloth wipes constructed of synthetic miracle fabric. Estimated cost: Under $10 for a modicum of air and a reuseable nozzle.</p>
        <p>A belt bag. Chances are even casual snapshooters have a camera bag, but how many carry one around while taking pictures? Still, those odds and ends like filters and film have to go somewhere. A little pouch that slides onto a belt is one solution: it's out of the way, doesn't weigh much, and holds just the right amount of accessories. If you can't find one in a camera store, try a camping or outdoor store instead. Estimated cost: $10 to $20.</p>
        <p>Polarizing filter. The quickest way to improve anyone's landscape photography is to give them a polarizer, which can deepen blue skies and heighten color saturation by eliminating reflections (but only when the sun is shining). Caution: some metering systems that use only a part of the light coming through the lens require a special version called a double polarizer; otherwise the meter will not read accurately. Be sure to peek at the camera's instruction book to see if it needs one of these. Also, match the filter size to the diameter of the photographer's favorite lens. Estimated cost: About $50 for a standard polarizer; over $100 for the double kind.</p>
        <p>A table-top tripod. These small gizmos rarely get used on table tops. I carry mine on trips, whenever the thought of lugging my full-size tripod seems onerous. These tripods fold to fit into a camera bag, but their tiny legs let you hold the camera steady in a pinch -- on top of car hoods, against fence posts, you name it. Estimated cost: $20 to $40.</p>
        <p>Teleconverters. Teleconverters do degrade lens performance and make it harder to see through the viewfinder. But they are small and they are indispensible when your mate's longest lens is not long enough. Moderate magnification -- 1.4 to 2 power -- is preferable, as are fully coated lenses. Metering and focusing mechanisms should be accommodated, and in the best of all possible worlds, the converter and lens should be matched by the manufacturer. SLRs only, please. Estimated cost: $100 to $200 for a decent, basic one; more for exotic lenses.</p>
        <p>A lens hood. Manufacturers of cameras and lenses really should include hoods as standard equipment for their lenses, but some expect to make more money selling them separately. If the photographer next to you doesn't have one, chances are the pictures he takes are full of flare and other bad effects. Lens hoods are specific to particular focal lengths; don't buy one loose out of a mark-down barrel. Estimated cost: $10 to $30.</p>
        <p>Film: Now here's something every photographer needs. Choose either a "brick" (20 rolls) of your photographer's favorite film, or stuff a few boxes of a premium emulsion in the stocking. Some of the fancy newcomers in the film arena include Kodak Ektar 25, Fuji's Reala print film and Velvia slide film, and Agfa's highly rated black-and-white emulsion, Agfapan Professional APX 100. Estimated cost: A few dollars for a single roll; up to $100 for a 20-roll package.</p>
        <p>Finally, once the gifts have been opened and you have a happy photographer on your hands, grab the camera and take his or her picture. Even photographers like to see themselves in pictures occasionally.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
