<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Strategy That Beats Shocking Fuel Bills</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="54" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="320735"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="CONSUMER'S WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEATING FUEL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CONSUMER'S WORLD PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DE1F3BF934A15752C0A966958260" item-length="1306" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Strategy That Beats Shocking Fuel Bills</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Millions of homeowners who shivered through the record cold spell of December are shuddering in January at a related problem: December's fuel bill. It is too late, of course, to do anything about the cost of heating last month, but future bills can be spread out or reduced, experts say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Millions of homeowners who shivered through the record cold spell of December are shuddering in January at a related problem: December's fuel bill. It is too late, of course, to do anything about the cost of heating last month, but future bills can be spread out or reduced, experts say.</p>
        <p>Millions of homeowners who shivered through the record cold spell of December are shuddering in January at a related problem: December's fuel bill. It is too late, of course, to do anything about the cost of heating last month, but future bills can be spread out or reduced, experts say.</p>
        <p>Anyone who pays a heating bill was hit with extra costs in December because the weather was 30 percent colder than a normal December in most of the East. But homeowners with the biggest problem are those who use oil.</p>
        <p>Oil prices, which have always fluctuated with the season at the retail level, have been especially variable this winter, rising by almost 50 percent in the cold weather. So a homeowner who might have expected to use 200 gallons in December at $1 a gallon instead may have used 260 gallons and paid $1.40, for a total cost increase of 80 percent.</p>
        <p>In contrast, natural gas prices do not vary seasonally for residential users. They do vary seasonally for industrial customers or utilities that choose to buy on the or short-term market, but even utilities that play this ''spot'' market generally get only part of their supplies that way, so the impact on them is muted.</p>
        <p>Gas prices vary from utility to utility. The Consolidated Edison Company of New York, which has among the highest gas prices in the country, is now selling gas at a price per cubic foot equivalent to $1.04 a gallon for heating oil, which is higher than home oil started the season but well below where it is now.</p>
        <p>Heat Now, Pay Later</p>
        <p>The simplest way for consumers to avoid a high December fuel bill is to pay part of it at some other time of the year. Most gas utilities and full-service fuel oil dealers will make this possible with a budget payment plan. Plans differ in important ways, but in most cases the utilities estimate what the consumer's annual bill will be, based on past use and weather expectations, and divide it by 10, or 11 or 12. The customer then pays in equal monthly installments.</p>
        <p>For fuel suppliers, which have year-round expenses, the advantage of this system is that it matches their revenue more closely to costs. The plans can also amount to an interest-free loan from the consumer to the company if the customer begins paying in July for services he will not start using until October or November.</p>
        <p>''There isn't any state law that would require them to pay interest,'' said Richard Kessel, the chairman of the New York State Consumer Protection Board.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, if the heating company will allow customers to start the plan at the beginning of the heating season, the opposite is true: the company will be providing an interest-free loan to the consumer.</p>
        <p>In either case, these balanced billing plans, or budget billing, as they are sometimes known, are not for everyone, Mr. Kessel said. They are most advantageous for ''consumers who are on a really tight budget,'' he added.</p>
        <p>If the budget plan begins in July and the worst of the heating season is not until January or February, the plan can be seen as a kind of layaway plan.</p>
        <p>All balanced billing plans include a provision for an adjustment in the last month to cover overpayments or underpayments. Thus, Mr. Kessel noted, a budget plan does not protect against unexpected price increases.</p>
        <p>Beware of Mid-Season Change</p>
        <p>Mr. Kessel cautions customers considering a budget plan to beware of a provision that allows for an adjustment in their payment at mid-season. This could destroy any advantage they might realize from the plan.</p>
        <p>Schenck Fuels of East Hampton, L.I., offers a budget plan, and Richard B. Herrlin, the company president, said that in some years it can be a good deal for the company, but that this year it is an especially good deal for customers. That is because demand was so high and oil so expensive this year that the 20 percent of his customers on the budget plan have run up big charges, but they will not have to pay any more than they usually do until their monthly rates undergo annual recalculation and adjustment in July. Mr. Herrlin said he assumes the rest of the winter will be essentially normal.</p>
        <p>At this point, after a very cold December but a normal November and warm January, heating requirements in the New York City area are running about 7 percent higher than last year and about 5 percent higher than a normal winter, the National Weather Service's figures show.</p>
        <p>Most heating oil dealers offer to start customers on a budget plan only in summer, so they can establish a credit balance before the cold weather sets in. Some gas utilities, including Consolidated Edison, will allow customers to join at any time of year.</p>
        <p>If homeowners are paying far in advance of using the product, by starting their cycle in the middle of summer, for example, the budget plan can raise their costs, because their money is in the hands of the utility or oil dealer and earning the consumer no interest.</p>
        <p>Only Real Saving: Cut Demand</p>
        <p>Ultimately, budget plans do not reduce the cost of the fuel used; at best they are neutral. For consumers to realize a real reduction in costs, they must cut their demand for fuel by improving insulation in attics, walls and around windows, by improving their heating systems or both. Free information on insulation is available by telephone from the Conservation and Renewable Energy Inquiry and Referral Service, at 800-523-2929. In Alaska and Hawaii the number is 800-223-3071.</p>
        <p>In an oil heating system, one method of improvement is to change the burner. Mr. Herrlin of Schenck Fuels said many older oil furnaces are able to effectively use less than two-thirds of the energy available in a gallon of fuel oil, while new ones recover 85 percent. Thus a new furnace can make three gallons do the work that previously required four.</p>
        <p>A new furnace can cost $2,000, but a smaller step toward efficiency, a $400 replacement burner for an existing furnace, can cut fuel needs and reduce a consumer's vulnerability to price shocks.</p>
        <p>If an old oil furnace is to be replaced, consumers should consider a gas furnace, which is available with efficiency as high as oil or higher. If the building does not already have gas service, for cooking or hot water, installing a gas line can be expensive. Consolidated Edison will extend a line 100 feet and build the first 100 feet of service line free. But suburban houses often require more than 100 feet of service line.</p>
        <p>Investments in energy efficiency that seem to be no more than break-even propositions at today's energy prices may look like shrewd investments in years to come. The consensus of experts, for the first time in several years, is that over the next few years oil and gas prices are going up.</p>
        <p>Did Insulating Do Any Good?</p>
        <p>Are the conservation improvements you have made in the past helping you this particularly cold winter?</p>
        <p>You can find out if you have old fuel bills, a pencil, a pocket calculator and a local newspaper.</p>
        <p>The newspaper probably lists a figure in its weather report for ''degree-days,'' a measure of heating requirements. It is the difference between the average temperature for a day and 65 degrees. If a day's mean temperature is 15 degrees, then the heating requirement is 50 degree-days.</p>
        <p>The easiest measure of heating efficiency is gallons of oil or cubic feet of natural gas per degree-day. If your area has accumulated 2,700 degree-days this season, and you have used 500 gallons of oil, then you used .185 gallons for each degree-day. No matter what the year-to-year difference is in the weather, you can calculate, using old bills, how this compares with years past.</p>
        <p>To determine degree-days for a year ago, natural gas customers can calculate from the temperature averages listed on their bills. Oil users can probably obtain degree-day figures from the library or their dealers.</p>
        <p>CONSUMER'S WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
