<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Drive Mounted for Environment Vote</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="390575"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFERENDUMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">REINHOLD, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DA1531F931A25753C1A966958260" item-length="1039" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Drive Mounted for Environment Vote</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT REINHOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REINHOLD, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Oct. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Amid signs that a far-reaching environmental measure on the California ballot is faltering, three national leaders of the environmental movement declared today that the state faced an environmental crisis. They announced the start of a door-to-door drive for the measure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Amid signs that a far-reaching environmental measure on the California ballot is faltering, three national leaders of the environmental movement declared today that the state faced an environmental crisis. They announced the start of a door-to-door drive for the measure.</p>
        <p>Amid signs that a far-reaching environmental measure on the California ballot is faltering, three national leaders of the environmental movement declared today that the state faced an environmental crisis. They announced the start of a door-to-door drive for the measure.</p>
        <p>They charged that eight oil and chemical companies that have contributed nearly $3 million to an advertising campaign to kill the voter-initiated measure were among the worst polluters in California and the nation. The measure would impose the strictest environmental controls in the country, banning many common pesticides and requiring drastic reductions in carbon dioxide emissions, among many other things.</p>
        <p>While none of the environmental leaders would concede the measure, which they call Big Green, was in trouble, many in the movement fear a loss would seriously slow the national political momentum for ecological causes. The vote is shaping up as a major test of whether the public's general desire for a cleaner environment is matched by willingness to pay for it.</p>
        <p>Opponents Tell of Job Loss</p>
        <p>Industry groups have mounted a withering advertising drive against it, charging that the measure tries to do too much and will raise water and power rates and cost jobs in manufacturing and agriculture. While there have been no recent statewide polls on the measure, political experts believe its once huge margin of support has eroded substantially in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>''Much is at stake in this fight, both for California and the entire nation,'' John Adams of New York, president of the Natural Resources Defense Council, said at a news conference at the Sierra Club's headquarters in San Francisco. ''Big Green is perhaps our best chance to translate the shift in public consciousness about the environment into political change.''</p>
        <p>He was joined by Jay Hair, president of the 5.8-million-member National Wildlife Federation, from Washington, and Michael L. Fisher, executive director of the Sierra Club, which has 200,000 members in California. Absent from the conference, and a similar one in Los Angeles, was Assemblyman Tom Hayden of Santa Monica, chairman of the steering committee running the campaign. Opponents have tagged the measure ''the Hayden initiative'' in the hope that voters will tend to oppose it if it is linked to the former anti-Vietnam War leader. #750,000 Members Alterted Expecting to be greatly outspent, the environmental leadership said it was mounting a statewide effort to get out the ''green'' vote with the help 750,000 members of environmental groups. The Sierra Club said it would call on its 11 chapters to man telephone banks, hand out leaflets at shopping centers, movie lines and street fairs and participate in local debates.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the natural resources council released a report stating that the fast-growing state faced alarming environmental degradation. ''California's environment and quality of life are in serious peril from the combined and continuous pollution of our air, drinking water, food supply, rivers, lakes and coastline,'' said the report, compiled by council staff members. It asserted that 227 million pounds of chemical pollutants are released annually in California.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview, Mr. Adams said that a direct voter measure was the only way to tackle these problems because ''special interests'' had thwarted efforts to pass laws in Congress and the State Legislature.</p>
        <p>The environmental leaders said major contributors to the campaign to defeat Proposition 128, as it appears on the ballot, are makers of pesiticides and other toxic chemicals. They said the Monsanto Company, which has contributed $405,000, is the sole manufacturer of the pesticide alachlor. They said alachlor was ''a probable human carcinogen'' that had contaminated ground and surface water in the Midwest. E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company, which has given $365,000, released 1,084,000 pounds of toxic chemicals in California in 1988, they said.</p>
        <p>The other six companies the environmentalists said had paid for the advertising were the Chevron Corporation, Dow Elanco Inc, Rhone-Poulenc S.A., Ciba-Geigy International AG, ICI Americas and ARCO and its sister company, the ARCO ChemicalCompany.</p>
        <p>Don Schrack, the spokesman for the chemical-industry backed group called ''No on 128,'' said the backers of the referendum had made a strategic decision to avoid discussing its lack of merit.</p>
        <p>The measure, which runs nearly 30,000 words, would substantially rewrite California environmental law, cobbling together an array of loosely connected laws. Among other things, it would phase out pesticides - just how many is at issue - that cause cancer or birth defects, strictly limit discharges of pollutants into coastal waters and phase out chemicals believed to deplete the earth's protective ozone layer. It would create an elected ''environmental advocate'' with special legal powers and require a state plan to cut carbon dioxide emissions by 20 percent by the year 2000 and 40 percent by 2010, adjusted for population growth as necessary.</p>
        <p>Study Cites High Costs</p>
        <p>Critics maintain the law is grounded in no reliable science and asks voters to impose huge costs on local governments and businesses. The critics also contend the measure would even undermine American competitiveness in international trade by establishing different food standards for the huge California market.</p>
        <p>According to a study by DRI/McGraw-Hill a Boston-based economic consulting concern, complying with the carbon dioxide provision would raise gasoline and diesel fuel taxes by 50 cents a gallon, require an investment of up to $50 billion to build high-speed trains between major cities, increase the use of nuclear power and slow California economic growth to about 65 percent of the national average from 150 percent.</p>
        <p>''Clearly these numbers generate a great deal of concern,'' said Victor F. Weisser, president of the California Council for Environmental and Economic Balance, a coalition of industry and labor groups that commissioned the study. The council has not taken a formal position on the proposition.</p>
        <p>Backers of the referendum say claims of huge costs are overblown.dEli Lilly(Dow Elanco)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
