<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>But We Close Our Eyes</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="328235"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="ABROAD AT HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, ANTHONY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">OP-ED</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DB163CF933A15751C0A966958260" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>But We Close Our Eyes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anthony Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, ANTHONY</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: From the Soviet Union to South Africa, societies are confronting their fundamental problems. Immobilism is giving way to change. There has never been a time in the world like this, we say to each other.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: From the Soviet Union to South Africa, societies are confronting their fundamental problems. Immobilism is giving way to change. There has never been a time in the world like this, we say to each other.</p>
        <p>From the Soviet Union to South Africa, societies are confronting their fundamental problems. Immobilism is giving way to change. There has never been a time in the world like this, we say to each other.</p>
        <p>But one great country is not confronting its problems. It is avoiding them, refusing to risk the uncertainty of change. That country is the United States.</p>
        <p>America's problems are no secret. Commissions have reported on them, Presidents talked, commentators thundered. But doing something -something meaningful - is another matter. That would take courage, and cost money.</p>
        <p>Education is an example. We have become an ill-educated society. Our working population is at a growing disadvantage with the well-schooled people of Japan and other East Asian societies, or of Germany or France.</p>
        <p>In our major cities public education is a disaster: starved for funds, mismanaged by bureaucracies. Middle-class families, unlike their counterparts in most places abroad, send their children to private schools. Huge numbers of Americans are functional illiterates.</p>
        <p>In his 1988 campaign George Bush said he would be the ''education President.'' His budget last month, discounted for inflation, actually proposed less spending than the previous year for education.</p>
        <p>Health is another profound problem. It cuts across lines of class and region, affecting the middle class and the poor, cities and rural areas.</p>
        <p>The United States is one of only two industrialized countries that have no national system of health insurance for the entire population. (The other is South Africa.) Most Americans have private insurance - but at ever-higher rates, burdening them and their employers. Medical care for the uninsured is provided, inadequately and at heavy cost, by local hospitals.</p>
        <p>Infant mortality is higher in this country than in some less affluent societies. A recent study in Chicago hospitals showed large numbers of children, up to age 5, who had not had the measles immunization that all should have had by 12 to 15 months.</p>
        <p>New York City's great teaching hospitals, once well endowed, are in severe financial difficulty now because governments compensate them so badly for the care they give poor patients. The hospitals are overwhelmed, their doctors unable to function properly. And the crisis is not going to be limited to New York.</p>
        <p>Then there is homelessness, a largely though not entirely urban problem. How many of us, middle-aged or older, ever thought we would walk down an American street as we would Calcutta, indifferent to desperation because we are so hardened to it?</p>
        <p>A host of economic problems menaces our position in the world: slow growth in productivity, inadequate investment and saving, a tax structure and cultural milieu that encourage business to think of the short term instead of the long. Again, there is no sign of a serious effort to address the dangers.</p>
        <p>Finally there is the most profound problem of all, the environment. George Bush said he would be the ''environment President,'' too. His record in office is a particularly graphic example of the current American habit of talking about problems without doing anything that would be really difficult.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has taken a more caring position on the environment than President Reagan. He picked a genuine conservationist, William K. Reilly, to head the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>But on a succession of tough issues Mr. Reilly has been overruled. When he drafted a Bush speech on the greenhouse effect and global warming, the speech was toned down and those very phrases eliminated. The President did not call for international action, as the State Department as well as the E.P.A. had proposed.</p>
        <p>The President promised a strong policy to protect wetlands. But after weeks of delay, the Administration issued wetlands rules that gave way on key points to developers.</p>
        <p>The White House chief of staff, John Sununu, has been blamed in the press for those and other retreats on the environment. But of course Mr. Sununu does what his boss wants.</p>
        <p>On all the hard issues Mr. Bush is doing fine in the polls by talking but not acting. The public is hardly in a daring mood these days, and doing something always offends someone. But leadership requires more than the attitude of the Victorian verse:</p>
        <p>Mother, may I go out to swim?</p>
        <p>Yes, my darling daughter;</p>
        <p>Hang your clothes on a hickory limb,</p>
        <p>But don't go near the water.</p>
        <p>ABROAD AT HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
