<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Triple Play;   The Rich Nations Get Richer. And Then?</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="365191"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HOUSTON (TEX)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ITALY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ITALY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SILK, LEONARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Houston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DF103DF932A35754C0A966958260" item-length="1604" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Triple Play;   The Rich Nations Get Richer. And Then?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEONARD SILK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SILK, LEONARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The currencies and economies of the two Germanys become one today, solidifying the German role as leader of a bloc of European states that are themselves rushing toward economic union and a closer political federation. And next week, the leaders of the seven strongest industrial democracies - the United States, Japan, Germany, France, Britain, Italy and Canada - gather in Houston for an economic summit meeting to survey the problems and opportunities of a world changed in subtle and not-so-subtle ways.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The currencies and economies of the two Germanys become one today, solidifying the German role as leader of a bloc of European states that are themselves rushing toward economic union and a closer political federation. And next week, the leaders of the seven strongest industrial democracies - the United States, Japan, Germany, France, Britain, Italy and Canada - gather in Houston for an economic summit meeting to survey the problems and opportunities of a world changed in subtle and not-so-subtle ways.</p>
        <p>The currencies and economies of the two Germanys become one today, solidifying the German role as leader of a bloc of European states that are themselves rushing toward economic union and a closer political federation. And next week, the leaders of the seven strongest industrial democracies - the United States, Japan, Germany, France, Britain, Italy and Canada - gather in Houston for an economic summit meeting to survey the problems and opportunities of a world changed in subtle and not-so-subtle ways. It is a world they helped make but never expected to see so soon.</p>
        <p>In this world, the Communist threat has collapsed, leaving the Big Three of the world economy - the United States, Japan and Europe -richer and more powerful than ever. But there is an overriding economic issue: how to hold the Western nations together now that they have won.</p>
        <p>With the cold war ending, a hot peace among the victors is breaking out as the industrial world, once dominated by the United States, becomes tripolar. In coming decades, the strains and conflicts among Western Europe, Japan and the United States could become chronic.</p>
        <p>These conflicts are already evident in a host of issues: how to break remaining barriers to trade that threaten to split the industrial world into regional trading blocs; how to integrate Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union into the global economic system; how to deal with a polluted environment and ward off the danger of global warming; how to fight the international drug trade; how to stimulate sufficient savings to meet the explosion of demand for capital all over the world, and how to redress the imbalances among the rich industrial countries and the debt-ridden countries of the third world.</p>
        <p>And, although it may take years to realize its benefits fully, the peace dividend - resources no longer needed for wars hot or cold - should make the capitalist democracies still stronger by enabling them to exploit more completely their basic advantage: the ability to capitalize on the individual talents and drives of their people and businesses to innovate, invest and thus grow richer.</p>
        <p>The peace dividend promises to be greatest for the United States, simply because it has been carrying the heaviest military burdens of the West. Partly because of those burdens, the United States has slipped from being the world's largest creditor nation to becoming its largest debtor, and has lost ground in world markets to Germany and Japan, its two strongest allies - and former enemies.</p>
        <p>In 1989, the United States ran a deficit of $106 billion in its balance of trade and payments - a total roughly matched by the $57.2 billion surplus of Japan and the $52.8 billion surplus of the Federal Republic of Germany. The outlook for 1990 is for an even greater disequilibrium in trade deficits and surpluses.</p>
        <p>But this disequilibrium is by no means due only to the differences in military burdens. The United States's large budget deficits and low savings rate have worsened its trade deficits and made it increasingly dependent on an inflow of foreign capital to finance its rising debt and its economic growth, which has now slowed to a crawl.</p>
        <p>The most startling economic event of the last week, President Bush's call for an increase in tax revenues, was triggered by the worsening budget deficit outlook and the need to break the deadlock with Congress; Mr. Bush himself acknowledged these heightened pressures for a new look at taxes, saying, ''Like Abraham Lincoln said, I'll think anew.' '' But, as his chief aide for the Houston summit, Under Secretary of State Richard T. McCormack, stressed in an interview, Mr. Bush's decision to act on taxes was also linked to America's weakened external position and its strained relations with Japan. The Japaneseclaimed some credit for persuading Mr. Bush that he simply had to take tougher fiscal action if the American trade deficit were to be cut.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides say many other factors were involved in his decision, including his sense of economic stewardship for the nation's welfare and his belief that the United States had better get its act together and hustle lest it see the heels of its Japanese and European competitors as they race ahead into the future.</p>
        <p>The United States still has the world's biggest economy, with a gross national product of more than $5 trillion compared to Japan's $2.8 trillion and a unified Germany's $1.5 trillion. But much of the total G.N.P. gap is due to population differences, with the United States numbering 249 million compared to Japan's 123 million and one Germany's 78 million. The 12 nations of the European Community number some 325 million, not counting the 16 million East Germans who joined the Western economy today, or other people in Eastern Europe who may join up fairly soon.</p>
        <p>At present exchange rates, per capita gross national product of the United States is a bit less than Japan's, but ahead of unified Germany, now weighted down by the newly incorporated East Germans. But the West Germans will be investing scores of billions in the East, and productivity there should catch up fast.</p>
        <p>The outlook for the American position versus the other two has been worsened by a disparity among their investment rates; the United States's rate of gross investment has been running at about 15 percent, West Germany's at 20 percent and Japan's at 32 percent. In addition, the levels and quality of education and labor skills, as well as the intensity of research and development, will also play vital roles in the outcome of the growing rivalry among the major industrial countries. A United States running huge budget deficits is hard pressed to deal with its domestic problems or lead internationally.</p>
        <p>And, without fear of the Soviets to hold them together, the United States, Japan and Germany could spin out of their common orbit, pulling other countries into North American, Pacific and European blocs. So, as Robert Hormats, an investment banker who served as a top Presidential adviser at earlier economic summits, puts it, ''The cardinal job of the Houston summit is to keep centrifugal forces from pulling the allies apart.''</p>
        <p>Hopes that those centrifugal forces can be resisted were raised by the announcement last week that the United States and Japan had agreed on a trade pact designed to discourage excess spending in the United States and stimulate foreign business in Japan. But doubts about whether the accord will be enforced persisted in Congress. The possibility remains that the Big Three of the economic world could still become inward-looking zones, focusing their trade and investment among countries in their own backyards and fighting each other for advantages elsewhere - in the third world, the Middle East and the present and former Communist countries.</p>
        <p>Differences Over Gorbachev</p>
        <p>That last issue has surfaced in advance of the Houston summit meeting. Chancellor Helmut Kohl of West Germany has been pushing for a much stronger Western effort to support President Mikhail S. Gorbachev's efforts to save the Soviet economy from an even worse collapse. But the United States, with its budgetary problems, has been arguing that a large aid effort for the Soviet Union at this point would pour money down the drain and would even be counterproductive, because it might enable Mr. Gorbachev to avoid pressing for the reforms that are crucial if foreign aid is to accomplish anything.</p>
        <p>The same issue emerged last week at the European Community's summit conference in Dublin, where Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher of Britain proposed that a team of economic experts prepare a report on what aid the Soviet Union needs and how best to make it effective. Proponents of quick help for the Soviets believe that if the West waits for reforms to come before it helps, the aid will be too late, and an important opportunity for furthering Soviet democracy will have been lost. The Houston summit meeting is likely to reverberate with intense discussion of this issue.</p>
        <p>But the Soviet issue, important as it is, does not pose the most dangerous threat to relations among the industrial democracies; the most serious danger is that of conflict over trade. The immediate threat is of a collapse of the current round of international trade negotiations, known as the Uruguay Round. These are aimed at knocking down barriers to trade in copyrights, patents and other intellectual property, agricultural products, and financial and other services, areas crucial to binding the modern world together.</p>
        <p>A collapse or failure of these talks would result if there were no breakthrough on agriculture. The Europeans, heading for unity and needing popular support in coming elections, are shrinking from taking on their own farm interests. The Americans say that if the Europeans don't yield on cutting barriers to trade in farm products, then nothing can be done to get the support of either the United States or third world countries on other issues. The United States intends to hang very tough on the agricultural issue.</p>
        <p>Thus the rich industrial powers are at a crossroad on the extent to which they will work together or split. The decisions they are making now in the trade talks, the summit discussions and the continuing deliberations over the military and economic future of Europe could set patterns for decades to come - whether nations will become more closely intertwined or divide into competing regions, and how fast the world economy will grow or regress. Ultimately, these patterns could affect the well-being of all people, rich and poor, in all countries.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
