<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Slimmer Peabody Attracts Suitors</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="354648"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDUSTRY PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRODUCTION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PEABODY HOLDING CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMAX INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HANSON PLC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HICKS, JONATHAN P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDE1331F93AA25756C0A966958260" item-length="962" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Slimmer Peabody Attracts Suitors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HICKS, JONATHAN P</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A few years ago, the Peabody Holding Company was among the nation's least efficient producers of coal. But the St. Louis company, the nation's largest coal producer, has since reduced its production costs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A few years ago, the Peabody Holding Company was among the nation's least efficient producers of coal. But the St. Louis company, the nation's largest coal producer, has since reduced its production costs.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, the Peabody Holding Company was among the nation's least efficient producers of coal. But the St. Louis company, the nation's largest coal producer, has since reduced its production costs.</p>
        <p>The turnaround and Peabody's vast reserves of low-sulfur coal - favored over coal with higher sulfur content because of environmental concerns - have made the company a desirable property.</p>
        <p>Amax Inc. and Hanson P.L.C. recently had a bidding skirmish for the company. On May 11, Amax offered $1.25 billion for Peabody, only to be quickly outbid by Hanson, which already holds a 45 percent stake in Peabody. The other 55 percent is held by the Newmont Mining Corporation.</p>
        <p>Bidding for the Newmont Stake</p>
        <p>Newmont Mining had agreed in March to sell that stake to Hanson for $715 million. But after the Amax bid, Hanson, the British conglomerate, raised the offer to $725.6 million. Amax said yesterday that it would not try to top the Hanson bid, but bidding for Peabody remains open until June 25. Amax, a mining and metals company with large reserves of low-sulfur coal, had offered to pay Newmont $718 million for its Peabody stake and $532 million for the Hanson holding.</p>
        <p>Officials from both Amax and Newmont Mining said they expected other bids for Peabody to emerge. Robert H. Quenon, who is president of Peabody Coal and president and chief executive of Peabody Holding, declined to be interviewed for this article.</p>
        <p>''They have completely turned themselves around at Peabody,'' said Marc D. Cohen, a coal analyst with Kidder, Peabody &amp; Company. ''They have made some dramatic changes in their cost structure and they have closed unprofitable operations.''</p>
        <p>Demand for low-sulfur coal is expected to rise over the next decade because of proposed regulations aimed at reducing acid rain. To meet proposed restrictions on sulfur emissions, electric utilities, which use about four-fifths of the nation's coal production, are expected to switch from high-sulfur coal to the cleaner-burning low-sulfur coal.</p>
        <p>Unlike most of its competitors, which operate solely in one region of the country, Peobody operates coal mines throughout the United States. About one-third of Peabody's 8.2 billion tons in reserves is low-sulfur coal. It has large reserves of high-sulfur coal in the Midwest, however.</p>
        <p>''This is a good time to be in the coal business,'' said Joel Price, an analyst with the Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette Securities Corporation, ''especially if you have the kind of low-sulfur coal reserves that Peabody has. But they still have the problem of the Midwestern high-sulfur coal to deal with.''</p>
        <p>Peabody, which produces 9 percent of the coal mined in the United States, produced 86.7 million tons of coal in 1989, according to the National Coal Association. That output places it far ahead of its next-largest rivals, the Consolidation Coal Company, with 1989 production of 52.5 million tons, and Amax Coal Industries, which produced 38.1 million tons last year.</p>
        <p>Efforts to Improve Efficiency</p>
        <p>Despite its size, Peabody has been less profitable than many of its competitors because its plants are less efficient, analysts say. The privately held company reported net income of $102 million last year, down from $104 million in 1988, but significantly higher than the $74 million in 1987.</p>
        <p>As a result, Peabody has benefited less than its competitors from the rebound in coal, but it has narrowed the gap. Peabody now produces 32.9 tons of coal per worker each day, compared with 22.1 tons in 1985.</p>
        <p>Analysts said increased spending for modernization last year and this year should lift its bottom line and position it for the trend toward low-sulfur coal. Peabody spent $129 million last year on capital improvements, a 36 percent increase over the 1988 level. The company has purchased continuous miners, machines that haul coal from within mines in a steady stream rather than by the truckload, and has also improved the equipment it uses to treat the mined coal.</p>
        <p>Cutbacks in Employees</p>
        <p>The program has already cut the company's costs. Peabody reduced its work force to 11,000 employees, from more than 13,000 three years ago. It now makes a profit of about $3 on a ton of coal, analysts say, an improvement over an estimated $2.25 a ton a year ago. Its current profit is still below the $4 to $5 a ton realized by competitors like the Du Pont Company and Mapco Inc.</p>
        <p>Peabody has also reduced its long-term debt to $498 million, from $565 million in 1988 and $635 million in 1987.</p>
        <p>Under Hanson's March purchase agreement, Newmont can accept bids for Peabody from other parties, as long as the bidder agrees to make an offer for the entire company. But the agreement stipulates that Hanson has the opportunity to outbid any offer.</p>
        <p>Hanson Ready to Fight</p>
        <p>Sir Gordon White, chairman of Hanson's operations in the United States, is ready to fight for control of Peabody. ''Anyone who wants to bid against us for Peabody is going to find it difficult,'' he said. ''It's going to have to be a very attractive price because we really do want Peabody.''</p>
        <p>Sir Gordon said that Hanson's interest in the American coal producer stems from the view that demand for coal will be strong in the coming years. ''In the United States today, over half the electricity produced comes from coal, and it is far more abundant than petroleum,'' he said. ''This is a source of energy upon which America can rely well into the future.''</p>
        <p>Coal is not a terribly cyclical business, and therefore Peabody is viewed as a tool for enhancing cash flow. Although the use of coal in such metallurgical applications as fueling coke ovens for the steel plants appears to be waning, coal analysts say that demand from utilities will continue to increase.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
