<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>93 NATIONS MOVE TO BAN CHEMICALS THAT HARM OZONE</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="364772"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONDON (ENG)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REILLY, WILLIAM K (ADMR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DD173BF933A05755C0A966958260" item-length="973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>93 NATIONS MOVE TO BAN CHEMICALS THAT HARM OZONE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, June 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In a landmark agreement, most of the world's nations vowed today that by the end of the century they would halt the production of chemicals that destroy the atmosphere's protective ozone layer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In a landmark agreement, most of the world's nations vowed today that by the end of the century they would halt the production of chemicals that destroy the atmosphere's protective ozone layer.</p>
        <p>In a landmark agreement, most of the world's nations vowed today that by the end of the century they would halt the production of chemicals that destroy the atmosphere's protective ozone layer.</p>
        <p>The agreement followed a last-minute concession by Washington. The United States agreed to provide technological help to poor nations in phasing out the production and use of chlorofluorocarbons, which have been found to deplete the ozone shield.</p>
        <p>Ninety-three nations approved the agreement, which went far beyond a 1987 treaty that called for a 50 percent reduction in the production of the chemicals by 1998. Fifty-seven nations had previously acceded to that agreement.</p>
        <p>'A Triumph of Reason'</p>
        <p>The latest accord was described by William K. Reilly, administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, as the most significant international agreement ever reached on the protection of the environment.</p>
        <p>Chris Patten, Britain's Environment Secretary and the presiding officer at the meeting, called the agreement ''a triumph of reason.''</p>
        <p>Ozone is a form of oxygen in the stratosphere that shields the earth from dangerous solar ultraviolet radiation. An alarming thinning of the ozone layer in recent years has been caused by pollution, scientists believe, chiefly in the form of chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>Danger of Skin Cancer</p>
        <p>These have been used since their invention in 1930 as refrigerants, plastic foam-blowing gases, solvents and propellants, and scientists are now developing substitutes for them. These chemicals are used in refrigerators, all types of air conditioners, foam packing and upholstery, dry cleaning and other products.</p>
        <p>Scientists say that as more ultraviolet radiation penetrates the atmosphere, it is likely to cause an epidemic of skin cancer and cataracts, as well as damage to agriculture. Two nations, China and India, which had refused to accede to the 1987 treaty, the Montreal Protocol, were satisfied by the latest agreement. Their delegation leaders plan to recommend ratification.</p>
        <p>Besides banning the production and use in new products of the five main types of dangerous chemicals, the new agreement calls for a ban by the end of the century of three fire-extinguishing chemicals called halons.</p>
        <p>Two other chlorine-based chemicals used as solvents and cleaning agents, methyl chloroform and carbon tetrachloride, are to be sharply restricted. The participants agreed to reduce methyl chloroform production by 70 percent by the year 2000 and by 100 percent in 2005. Production of carbon tetrachloride is to be reduced 85 percent by 1995 and 100 percent by 2000.</p>
        <p>Aerosol cans with chlorofluorocarbons, no longer manufactured in the United States and Western Europe, are still made in some of the other countries that joined in today's agreement.</p>
        <p>The agreement reached today, in line with the Montreal Protocol, gives the poor nations a 10-year grace period to give up chlorofluorocarbons, requiring them to halt production before the year 2010 rather than 2000.</p>
        <p>The agreement creates a new international body with a 14-member executive committee. It will administer a new fund that will be used to help poor countries make the transition to technologies free of chlorofluorocarbons. Rotating members of the executive committee, each serving three-year terms, will always include seven industrial and seven poor nations.</p>
        <p>Makeup of New Panel</p>
        <p>Initially, the committee will consist of Canada, West Germany, Finland, the Netherlands, Japan, the United States, the Soviet Union, Brazil, Egypt, Ghana, Jordan, Malaysia, Mexico and Venezuala, with Finland as chairman for the first year.</p>
        <p>The fund will total $240 million for the first three years. The United States has agreed to contribute $40 million to $60 million of this.</p>
        <p>''This should be seen as part of a pattern of very generous support the United States is prepared to extend to developing nations acceding to the agreement,'' Mr. Reilly said.</p>
        <p>Haggling over details of the fund and a related issue, the demand by poorer countries for a transfer of technology from industrial nations, preceded the agreement.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mostafa K. Tolba of Egypt, executive director of the United Nations Environment Program and chairman of the talks, said he found the deliberations the most taxing of his career.</p>
        <p>In the course of the meeting, heads of delegation from India, Malaysia and several other poorer nations accused the United States of ''economic imperialism'' in pressing the third world to give up chlorofluorocarbons without guaranteeing compensatory technical and financial assistance.</p>
        <p>Reproaching India</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly, annoyed by particularly barbed criticism from India, told a reporter at this morning that ''there is only one real problem here, and that problem is India.''</p>
        <p>Among other things, Maneka Gandhi, head of the Indian delegation, accused American businesses of purposely selling technology based on chlorofluorocarbons to third world countries, including India. A spokesman for the American delegation denied that any such sales had taken place.</p>
        <p>A fundamental remaining difference between the United States and many poorer nations is related to precedents, although this issue did not prevent today's agreement.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Gandhi and other delegates regard the ozone conference as a precursor to many agreements on protection of the environment. Procedures and financing mechanisms now established should apply to future agreements on global warming and other problems, she said.</p>
        <p>The American delegation insisted, however, that the ozone agreement created no precedents for any future negotiations.</p>
        <p>A big obstacle to an agreement was cleared two weeks ago when the United States reversed its position and said it would support a new international fund to help poorer countries that agree to phase out chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
