<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The President Looks On the Bright Side, And It's in Europe</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="323280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="MODEST DREAMS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMS CONTROL AND LIMITATION AND DISARMAMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">APPLE, R W JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D8173AF937A35751C0A966958260" item-length="1042" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The President Looks On the Bright Side, And It's in Europe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R. W. APPLE Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">APPLE, R W JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IT is hard for most of the world to focus these days on anything other than Europe, as events there tumble forward, pell-mell, and last week President Bush proved to be no exception. Not only did he propose, in his first State of the Union address, radical new cuts in Soviet and American combat forces, but he also gave Mikhail S.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IT is hard for most of the world to focus these days on anything other than Europe, as events there tumble forward, pell-mell, and last week President Bush proved to be no exception. Not only did he propose, in his first State of the Union address, radical new cuts in Soviet and American combat forces, but he also gave Mikhail S.</p>
        <p>IT is hard for most of the world to focus these days on anything other than Europe, as events there tumble forward, pell-mell, and last week President Bush proved to be no exception. Not only did he propose, in his first State of the Union address, radical new cuts in Soviet and American combat forces, but he also gave Mikhail S. Gorbachev another salute, as he described it, for encouraging peaceful change in what used to be called the satellite states.</p>
        <p>That's what was new, so that's what made the news, even if it tended to emphasize again that the main action is elsewhere, despite Mr. Bush's bold assertion that ''America stands at the center of the widening circle of freedom.'' Washington is more and more aware that the President and the United States are secondary players in this drama that is transforming a continent, day by day and week by week.</p>
        <p>But the speech and the new Federal budget, which preceded it by two days, had other, subtler messages, which were all but lost in the shouting. At the end of his first year in the White House, Mr. Bush marked out some trails that he intends to follow.</p>
        <p>All in all, he showed a marked preference for foreign policy over domestic, to no one's surprise. This President, after all, held three major foreign-policy posts earlier in his career. What is more, the questions of foreign affairs are more tractable just now than the questions of domestic affairs, with the single, notable exception of China. Having barely escaped humiliation by Congress over his insistence on keeping close links to Beijing, Mr. Bush elected not to press the issue last week. He did not mention China once in reporting on the state of the union.</p>
        <p>Foreign policy is also relatively cheap. The prospect of reducing American troop strength in Europe to 225,000 (and if the Democrats and the eastern Europeans have their way, well below that) will eventually mean money saved, even if some of it will be spent on economic aid to Poland, Hungary, Czechoslovakia and the rest. And saving money is in with politicians of both parties.</p>
        <p>There were standing ovations Wednesday night when Mr. Bush called for an end to bigotry in the United States, and when he announced the troop cuts, and when he proclaimed his military triumph in Panama. But what really brought whoops of pleasure from the assembled Senators and Representatives, the Republicans and some Democrats, was the President's reiteration of his pledges not to raise taxes.</p>
        <p>Yet hewing to that policy, and also striving to reduce the deficits that he inherited from Ronald Reagan, leaves Mr. Bush with little room to maneuver.</p>
        <p>''The money is there,'' he said, in sharp contrast to his comment on taking office a year ago that ''we have more will than wallet.'' Clearly, he has been reading the poll-takers' findings as the nation enters an election year in which the Republicans hope to lay the groundwork for regaining control of Congress. The voters are worried about education and drugs and the environment, the polls say, so Mr. Bush offered increased funds for Head Start and more work on global warming and an intensified war on cocaine.</p>
        <p>There was something, in other words, for almost everyone. But there was no suggestion that national calamities lurked or that national sacrifices were needed; indeed, Mr. Bush seemed consciously to have avoided picking any one or two or three problems - the homeless, say, or competitiveness - as cause for warning.</p>
        <p>Most Presidents feel that they must act boldly, must innovate, in the first year or so of their terms, while they have a new mandate and their teams are full of the energy that Washington eventually saps from even the most vigorous.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush clearly does not intend to do that, at least in the domestic field. As in his invasion of Panama, and in his speech on Europe at NATO headquarters last summer, he showed in the troop-reduction plan the capacity to surprise those who have criticized him as too passive, but that capacity has been confined to foreign affairs.</p>
        <p>He sees a modest role for himself and the Government at a time when difficult problems - AIDS, the homeless, medical costs, industrial decline, poverty, child care - seem to need fresh and, some would argue, huge attention. Instead of stirring calls to the nation to follow him in solving problems, Mr. Bush asked grandfathers and grandmothers, fathers and mothers, to talk to the younger generation. The thousand points of light were back: ''We've got to step forward when there's trouble, lend a hand, be what I call a point of light to a stranger in need.'' It was all very nebulous.</p>
        <p>In a way, this budget and this State of the Union address represented a gamble. Clearly, Mr. Bush thinks the country is basically satisfied. Clearly, he believes that however many ills it sees, it believes that government is only a part, and probably only a very small part, of a solution. Clearly, he thinks that limited government action, combined with ample reassurances that he feels and cares, will prove politically adequate.</p>
        <p>Hence the plethora of symbolic actions of which he spoke - planting a billion trees, transforming the Environmental Protection Agency into a full-fledged department with a seat at the Cabinet table, asking Dr. Louis W. Sullivan, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, to ''review'' the already voluminous studies about how to get soaring medical-care costs under control.</p>
        <p>Hence, also, the evocative, emotional talk at the end about holding his 12th grandchild - ''the little guy'' - in his arms, and of the centrality of faith and family. If there had been pictures and music with it, it would have made a great campaign commercial.</p>
        <p>Which is, to be fair, what the State of the Union address has become in this age of television. Once, Congress was the principal audience, and the talk was technical, a presentation by a professional to professionals; that was what the Founding Fathers had in mind when they provided for periodic reports by Presidents. But now the ''target group,'' to use the language of marketing, is the whole country, and images and moods count, not numbers and analysis.</p>
        <p>And in 1990, as in 1988, the mood that George Bush seeks to project is nostalgic, warm, safe, steady.</p>
        <p>MODEST DREAMS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
