<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reviews/Dance; Rebecca Kelly's Decade of Growth</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="395784"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DANCING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">KELLY, REBECCA, DANCE CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KISSELGOFF, ANNA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D6123AF934A15753C1A966958260" item-length="568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reviews/Dance; Rebecca Kelly's Decade of Growth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KISSELGOFF, ANNA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rebecca Kelly and her husband, Craig Brashear, were young dancers in 1979 when they formed the Rebecca Kelly Dance Company. In that period, it was easier to admire their commitment and sincerity than Miss Kelly's somewhat bland choreography, for which the troupe was obviously an outlet.</p>
        <p>The distance Miss Kelly has traveled since that time was impressive on Thursday night when her company opened a short season (through tonight) at Gould Hall, 55 East 59th Street. The five pieces were full of ideas, and the best part was that they included movement ideas. In two trios, "Talata" and "Arbitra," Miss Kelly choreographs with boldness and imagination.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rebecca Kelly and her husband, Craig Brashear, were young dancers in 1979 when they formed the Rebecca Kelly Dance Company. In that period, it was easier to admire their commitment and sincerity than Miss Kelly's somewhat bland choreography, for which the troupe was obviously an outlet.</p>
        <p>The distance Miss Kelly has traveled since that time was impressive on Thursday night when her company opened a short season (through tonight) at Gould Hall, 55 East 59th Street. The five pieces were full of ideas, and the best part was that they included movement ideas. In two trios, "Talata" and "Arbitra," Miss Kelly choreographs with boldness and imagination.</p>
        <p>At all times, Miss Kelly knows how to bring out the unexpected in her dancers, among whom the highly talented Willie Hinton stands out for the juiciness with which he plunges into every dance phrase.</p>
        <p>Two of the group pieces have now-fashionable environmental themes. "Tear of the Clouds, 1989" is subtitled "Requiem for our forests dying from acid rain in the Northeastern United States." Mark Sadan photographed the male and female dancers, all discreetly topless, amid the woods and rocks of the Adirondacks, and his slides are projected on a scrim.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brashear, Angelique D'Addario, Christopher Hemmans, Mr. Hinton, Ted Thomas, Anina von Molnar and Beth Anne LaComb, in leotards behind this scrim, are abstracted versions of animal creatures and foliage. Harmony gives way to angular agony; splayed hands and tension are petrified in every body. An eclectic musical collage by the company gives way to the sounds of rain and wolves. The utter decay in the photos (the mud-smeared dancers lie amid barren trees) is echoed in a symbolic death by the performers onstage.</p>
        <p>Here, as in "Yellow Stone," the other "nature" piece, Miss Kelly had a fine idea that could have been enhanced by more dynamic variety. Mr. Sadan's slides on a backdrop of stones and watery fissures have a more remote relationship to three men in yellow shorts and two women. (The third, Hally Bellah, could not dance because of an injury.) But Mr. Hinton, delineating the curved shapes that Miss Kelly favors, stood out here while Mr. Hemmans was given a sudden air-patting gesture, all the more effective because it was so strange. Mr. Brashear, Miss D'Addario and Miss von Molnar completed the cast. The score was by Frank Loch.</p>
        <p>The same women and Miss LaComb were the marvelous odalisques in Turkish trousers who tumbled and revolved around one another in "Talata." (The word means trio in Arabic.) The piece is a delight, transforming conventional ballet movements like an arabesque penche or renverse into a flow full of rhythmic merriment. The whispered lyrics of George Wallace's "Mokambuku" give these sophisticated orientalisms a contemporary cool.</p>
        <p>In "Arbitra," in which Elliot Sokolov's score is superimposed over Villa-Lobos's well-known "Bachianas Brasileiras," Leslie Myers was stunningly impassioned in the love triangle completed by Mr. Brashear and the more restrained Miss D'Addario. Miss Kelly tinged the piece with flamenco hauteur but also managed cleverly to suggest high emotion through pure movement -- the onrush of one dancer to another and even a communal roll on the floor.</p>
        <p>In "Clarion," to Mr. Loch's music, the high points were Miss Kelly's way with lifts and partnering, evidence of how she is moving happily beyond convention.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
