<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cherry Blossom Time? Gone With March Wind</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="342224"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="SPRING JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREES AND SHRUBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARADES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON (DC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARRON, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DB1E3AF93AA35757C0A966958260" item-length="707" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cherry Blossom Time? Gone With March Wind</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BARRON, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: It rained on Dave C. Williams's parade. It also snowed and sleeted. Then the sun came out.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: It rained on Dave C. Williams's parade. It also snowed and sleeted. Then the sun came out.</p>
        <p>It rained on Dave C. Williams's parade. It also snowed and sleeted. Then the sun came out.</p>
        <p>The calendar said it was the right time for Washington's rite of spring, the Cherry Blossom Parade. But nature beat Mr. Williams and the other parade organizers to the finish line. The cherry blossoms peaked last month, with temperatures in the 80's.</p>
        <p>Hardly any pinkish petals remain on the trees around the Tidal Basin and the Jefferson Memorial. But the parade went on as scheduled Saturday despite down-coat weather that had an estimated 150,000 shivering spectators - half as many as expected - in layers of clothes that are usually deep in the closet by April.</p>
        <p>''It's the craziest year I can remember,'' said the radio and television interviewer Larry King, the grand marshal, in a wool sport jacket, a lined trench coat, another topcoat and a tarpaulin over his legs. ''Something's going on here.''</p>
        <p>Meteorologists say it has to do with the jet stream's mercurial flight plans. It has thrown people's rhythms out of sync far beyond cherry blossom country. ''Obviously, if it's snowing out and your weather is inclement,'' said George Hanley, a vice president at Brooks Brothers, ''you're not going to be thinking, 'Do I need a new poplin suit?' ''</p>
        <p>Clothes-buying is not the only warm-weather ritual put on hold. ''People are keeping their wardrobes in their closets because spring hasn't sprung,'' said William Seitz, executive director of the Neighborhood Cleaners Association, a trade group. He estimated that business was off 10 percent from last year. But Mimi Marenberg, who runs a valet service in a Manhattan apartment house, put the figure closer to 40 percent.</p>
        <p>''Anybody who depends on the weather to make a living this year, forget it,'' she said. ''No one's cleaning their leathers. No one's cleaning their suedes for the spring, and no one's doing any furs.They aren't even bringing anything in to be pressed.''</p>
        <p>The hot-then-cold spell brought out the daffodils at the Bayard Cutting Arboretum in Oakdale, L.I., and the azaleas at George Vanderbilt's estate in Asheville, N.C.</p>
        <p>It may have brought out creatures that land on a sting and a prayer. Joseph F. Sanzone, the superintendent of the Suffolk County Bureau of Vector Control on Long Island, said some early-hatching mosquitoes probably came to life in those warm days of March. But the cold that followed, he said, kept them from whizzing much beyond their ponds and streams.</p>
        <p>In Florida, the roller-coaster temperatures confused the orange trees as much as it did the cherry blossoms here. The citrus growers say they expect to ship only 39 million cartons, down from the 60 to 70 million they hoped for. They are worried that Brazilian juice may take up the slack.</p>
        <p>''We used to be the big supplier,'' said Richard Kinney, executive vice president of the Florida Citrus Packers Association. ''Once they establish a foothold, it's very difficult to get back on top. But you can't grow a tropical plant in 19-degree weather.''</p>
        <p>The cherry blossom festival is not the only spring celebration that was late this year. The pear blossoms are out in Medford, Ore., even though the festival is not until next week.</p>
        <p>In Denmark, S.C., the dogwood peaked a couple of weeks ago, the earliest ever, but the long-planned partying did not begin until Friday. And gardeners in Louisville worry that the dogwood there will be long gone by the time they get around to singing ''My Old Kentucky Home'' at the Kentucky Derby next month.</p>
        <p>The weird weather has ''wreaked havoc as far as the festival atmosphere,'' said Mr. Williams, the parade organizer here.</p>
        <p>In the blanketed Washington crowds on Saturday, the talk was not of global warming but of local warming, something to wish for when the high is 49 degrees. Drum majorettes' three-cornered hats had aerodynamic characteristics. So did Harry Higgins's lawn chair, which he brought from Gettysburg, Pa. A gust blew it off the curb.</p>
        <p>Eric Wagner of Burke, Va., was here because the opening game of his son's soccer season was canceled. ''Snow,'' he explained, adding that he had tried to tell his children snow was rare in April. ''I don't think they understand that,'' he said. ''It snowed three times in the last two weeks.''  SPRING JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
