<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE PEOPLE WHO GREASE THE WHEELS</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="World of New York Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="341911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT REALLY MAKES NEW YORK WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DC153DF93BA35757C0A966958260" item-length="3327" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE PEOPLE WHO GREASE THE WHEELS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY JAMES BARRON; James Barron is a reporter on the metropolitan staff of The New York Times.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: People often get overlooked in New York, especially the ones behind the scenes. Consider the 2,098 who tend to the ups and downs of 46 city-owned bridges; the 340 who collect coins from 64,000 parking meters; the 10 who inspect all 56,000 elevators; the 16 who put chlorine in the 73 city pools. The 128,000 who work in hospitals and the 32,400 who assist in doctors' and dentists' offices get little glory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: People often get overlooked in New York, especially the ones behind the scenes. Consider the 2,098 who tend to the ups and downs of 46 city-owned bridges; the 340 who collect coins from 64,000 parking meters; the 10 who inspect all 56,000 elevators; the 16 who put chlorine in the 73 city pools. The 128,000 who work in hospitals and the 32,400 who assist in doctors' and dentists' offices get little glory.</p>
        <p>People often get overlooked in New York, especially the ones behind the scenes. Consider the 2,098 who tend to the ups and downs of 46 city-owned bridges; the 340 who collect coins from 64,000 parking meters; the 10 who inspect all 56,000 elevators; the 16 who put chlorine in the 73 city pools. The 128,000 who work in hospitals and the 32,400 who assist in doctors' and dentists' offices get little glory. Broadway is famous, but not most of the 21,200 individual entertainers, musicians and producers who make shows happen. This city is so complicated and confusing that it can seem like a miracle when anything gets done. The credit often belongs to unheralded New Yorkers, like the ones profiled here, who keep things in sync.</p>
        <p>WILLIAM FREIER, TRAFFIC LIGHT TIMING ENGINEER</p>
        <p>William Freier sees red a lot. Also green and yellow. He is the man assigned by the City Department of Transportation to keep the 2,500 traffic lights in Manhattan synchronized. Computers now control the signals in the other boroughs, but in Manhattan, which has the most lights and the most complicated traffic patterns, the bugs haven't been worked out yet. So the lights are still governed the way they were half a century ago, by mechanical timers that whir and click like voiceless music boxes. Some timers are 40 or 50 years old (but Mr. Freier, 46, says the newer ones are usually the first to go).</p>
        <p>His daily rounds take him from street corner to street corner, where he tinkers with slow-turning ratchet wheels inside dark-green signal boxes. (Mistaking them for mailboxes, people occasionally ask Mr. Freier to deposit their letters. Politely he goes to the nearest real mailbox.) Of late, he has been shaving nine-tenths of a second off every green light in Manhattan. New Federal regulations that say there must be at least three full seconds of yellow between the green and the red. Of such imperceptible intervals his career is made.</p>
        <p>One afternoon recently, Mr. Freier was checking the lights on Columbus Avenue between 72d Street and 79th Street. At 77th Street, across from the American Museum of National History, the light was 8 seconds slow. The one at 76th Street was 5 seconds slow. So was the one at 75th Street. Methodically he brought them all up to speed. At 74th Street, the light was right on time, but at 73d Street - wouldn't you know it? - the light was 1 second fast. Mr. Frier got out his pliers, moved a pin the size of a paper clip, checked the timing on his stopwatch and drove off, without missing the light.</p>
        <p>FRANZ MOHR, PIANO TECHNICIAN</p>
        <p>''I play more in Carnegie Hall than anybody else,'' says Franz Mohr. ''But I have no audience.'' Seeing him alone on the stage hours before a concert, one might mistake him for a virtuoso improvising on a nine-foot grand. Instead, Mr. Mohr, the chief technician for Steinway &amp; Sons, is tuning it. He goes where the pianos go: when Rudolf Serkin takes a Steinway on tour, Mr. Mohr goes along, checking a key here, tightening a string there. But the first strings he loved were on a violin. A native of Duren, West Germany, he gave up playing when realized he would never be another Heifetz. He could not give up music, so he became an apprentice with the piano manufacturer Ibach &amp; Sons in 1950, at the age of 23. Twelve years later he moved to New York. He has been at Steinway's headquarters, a few steps from Carnegie Hall, ever since.</p>
        <p>The first time he tuned Arthur Rubinstein's piano, for a concert at Yale, Mr. Mohr did what anyone would do: he cleaned the keys. ''Young man,'' Mr. Rubinstein said as he stood in the wings with the audience already in their seats, ''you didn't know, but nobody ever cleans the keys for me. It makes them too slippery.'' The stickiest thing Mr. Mohr could find backstage was hair spray. ''I went pssst up, pssst down,'' he says. ''The audience laughed. But he loved it.''</p>
        <p>The only tuning Mr. Mohr regrets is one he did not do. The volcanic pianist Arturo Benedetti Michelangeli once practiced until 30 minutes before curtain time at Carnegie Hall, then turned to Mr. Mohr and declared: ''I give you 10 minutes.'' ''I cannot perform a miracle in 10 minutes,'' Mr. Mohr replied, and left. One reviewer's only complaint was that Michelangeli had to play an out-of-tune instrument.</p>
        <p>STEVEN THOMAS, NATIONAL WEATHER SERVICE FORECASTER</p>
        <p>Steven Thomas does not see himself as an F. Scott Fitzgerald or a Norman Mailer. ''I don't consider myself a good writer at all,'' he says. Sometimes he gets writer's block. But every day, thousands in the New York area hang on his every word. He writes weather forecasts. Mr. Thomas, 40, is the deputy-meteorologist-in-charge at the National Weather Service's Manhattan office. It is a room where the thick blue curtains are usually drawn tight.</p>
        <p>He says that when he hears a forecast on the radio, he almost never thinks, ''I wrote that'' - even though he did. Nor does it upset him that rich and famous television personalities recite what he writes, often without changing a word. ''If they can make the big bucks,'' says Mr. Thomas, who earns between $50,000 and $60,000 a year, ''more power to them.''</p>
        <p>Time to do the midday forecast. A cold front is speeding across Pennsylvania and there are broken clouds and west-to-southwest winds. ''The problem of the day is do we or do we not put snow in the forecast,'' he says. ''Once air comes through the higher elevations to New York City, it has a tendency to dry out, which means that just because it's snowing in Scranton or Allentown, it doesn't mean it's going to snow here.''</p>
        <p>He grabs a sheaf of maps and checks the temperature readings from Newark and Islip, L.I. He boots up a personal computer and rereads the forecast from the previous shift. After a peek through the curtains, he changes ''variable cloudiness'' to ''partly cloudy.''</p>
        <p>''What's the difference?'' he says. '' 'Variable cloudiness' is a term I don't like. Hard to define. And I like to say 'partly sunny' when I can because it's more optimistic. After four days of 'partly cloudy,' it just sounds more upbeat.''</p>
        <p>SANDRA LANE, SUBWAY TRAIN OPERATOR</p>
        <p>It is 7:30 a.m. Sea gulls are circling over still-drowsy commuters on the elevated platform at the Neptune Avenue subway station in Brooklyn. ''Usually if I come in slowly enough, somebody will say, 'There's a woman driving the train,' '' says Sandra Lane, wide awake in the driver's seat of the F train that is rumbling to a stop.</p>
        <p>Her day begins at 5:41 A.M., when her shiny eight-car train rolls out of the 179th Street terminal in Hillside, Queens. Forty stops and 104 minutes later, Ms. Lane pulls into the giant rail yard at Coney Island, the other end of the line. ''I like it here because there's a pool table in the crew room,'' she says.</p>
        <p>A conductor for two years before becoming a train operator in 1984, Ms. Lane has been spat upon (''by a three-piece Wall Street type'') and stopped by a frozen pumpkin (''It was on the tracks on the Williamsburg Bridge and activated the emergency brake''). She is getting tendinitis in her brake arm (''The body just starts falling apart, I guess''), but she can still drop a wicked side-pocket shot (''I get to take the men's masculinity away from them by winning'').</p>
        <p>Even though she lives in St. Albans, Queens, home is still Norristown, Pa., where she grew up. ''I don't want to be a New Yorker, no offense to New Yorkers,'' she says. ''This is just somewhere I ended up. I like small-town values. My 13-year-old daughter has a curfew.''</p>
        <p>Working in the subways was a career detour for Ms. Lane, 39. She has a master's degree in special education and a B.A. in Spanish literature and taught Head Start classes on the Lower East Side until budget cuts killed the program. The day she signed on with the Transit Authority, she beat her teaching salary by $6,000 a year.</p>
        <p>LINDA STARR, ASSISTANT DISTRICT ATTORNEY, BROOKLYN</p>
        <p>Linda Starr wants to talk to Mary, but her line is busy, has been all morning. Mary's husband is in jail, charged with stabbing her and beating her on five different occasions. Once she was pregnant. The assaults happened in their apartment, where most nights there was an argument. Now Mary wants the charges dropped. If Mary will not testify, Ms. Starr, the prosecutor, has no case.</p>
        <p>She has been dialing Mary's number for more than an hour, hoping to talk her into changing her mind about taking the stand against her husband. Finally a child answers. ''Go get mommy,'' Ms. Starr says. The child says no.</p>
        <p>Mary's case is like so many that Ms. Starr, 31, has handled since joining the Brooklyn District Attorney's office in 1985. ''In case after case,'' she says, ''the violence escalates, ending up with a death, usually hers. But you just can't say, 'Don't you know you're likely to end up dead?' ''</p>
        <p>The morning's scenario is not what Linda Starr had in mind when she majored in entomology at Ohio State. ''I always thought I'd do some science thing where you hang from trees in the jungle and track new species,'' she says. She enrolled at the University of Southern California Law School after working in a rape crisis center. ''I thought law school was the place you went to learn to change things.''</p>
        <p>An 11-year-old girl arrives for a pretrial interview. ''Do you like school?'' Ms. Starr begins. A 49-year-old man, a friend of the family, is accused of sodomizing this child and her 13-year-old sister. ''He said not to tell nobody because we'd get in trouble,'' the girl says.</p>
        <p>Ms. Starr has trouble leaving her work behind when she goes home. ''I worry all the time,'' she says, and refers to a stabbing case similar to Mary's in which a judge refused to jail the husband, leaving him free on bail for a month. ''The judge said to me, 'Look, if anything happens, the blood's on my hands.' I think that's a horrible thing to say.''</p>
        <p>PATRICK RYAN, PORT CAPTAIN</p>
        <p>The person with moment-to-moment responsibility for New York City's armada - seven Staten Island ferries, two prison barges and a vessel that carries the bodies to Potters Field - wastes no words: ''I hate boats. They're always breaking down.''</p>
        <p>Patrick Ryan, 37, port captain since 1987, spent 10 years as a deckhand, pilot and captain on the 6,000-passenger ferries to Staten Island, crossing the treacherous currents of the world's busiest shipping lanes. To him, the ferries are ''upside-down helicopters'' - they have no rudders, only adjustable propellers. The larger boats have some of the biggest engines General Motors has ever made, so powerful that it is easier to slam into the slip than slide in. ''You're going sideways faster than you're going forward,'' Ryan says, describing the docking maneuver. ''You know when you're half a mile off the slip if you're going to make it or not.''</p>
        <p>Captain Ryan was at the helm one morning in July 1986 when Juan J. Gonzalez, brandishing a sword he had bought in Times Square and the conviction that God had ordered him to use it, slashed 10 passengers and a deckhand. The captain wastes few words: ''I had to have one of the mates stand by the pilothouse door with an axe.''</p>
        <p>Now, in addition to occasional pilothouse duties, Captain Ryan buys the 12,000 gallons of oil that the ferries burn each day. He schedules repairs and Coast Guard inspections for the city's vessels. He pays the dry-cleaning bills of passengers whose coats are ruined by pigeons.</p>
        <p>And he worries about keeping up the ferry's 99 percent on-time record. One afternoon a passenger collapsed while the ferry John F. Kennedy was making the half-hour trip from lower Manhattan to Staten Island. ''This is terrible,'' said Captain Ryan, as he stood with the paramedics who boarded the vessel when it docked. ''This woman is having a heart attack and I'm thinking, 'Can this boat get out on time at 4:10?' ''</p>
        <p>HOWARD MILLER, SATELLITE MANAGER</p>
        <p>When Tom and Dan and Peter put on their trenchcoats and fly away to cover a summit conference like the one off Malta last year, Howard Miller sees to it that television viewers see them.</p>
        <p>As the general manager for the I.D.B. Communications Group, the 37-year-old Mr. Miller is a 90's-style Captain Video. His high-tech setup on Staten Island - 15 dish antennas that look like a forest of outsized mushrooms swiveling behind a 50-foot-high barricade - captures satellite signals and relays them to the networks in Manhattan. The giant wall cost $8 million and keeps out unwanted electronic signals that could make Tom look like Dan. Or like nothing at all.</p>
        <p>Each network has satellite equipment of its own to link it to affiliates and receive transmissions from anywhere in this country. But for global hookups when a major story breaks abroad, the networks turn to indepedent contractors like I.D.B. Communications. Mr. Miller's out-of-the-way electronic command post at the still-unfinished Staten Island Teleport - ''behind behind the scenes,'' as he describes it - is often the first place on earth to receive the news. When the Marines invaded Panama last December, Mr. Miller got the first glimpse.</p>
        <p>Not all the signals that go through Mr. Miller's control room are incoming. The Cable News Network's reports from New York first go to the Staten Island Teleport, where engineers beam them to CNN's headquarters in Atlanta. Some of the telephone calls to London made over MCI are routed through I.D.B. Communications and relayed to satellites. So is a sizable portion of the daily programming for the Voice of America, Radio Free Europe, CBS Radio and Westwood One.</p>
        <p>Some of the productions that he uplinks and downlinks never make it to the networks. But Howard Miller thinks satellite weddings, with the bride and groom in one place and their families on the other side of the planet, are out of this world.</p>
        <p>ADRIAN BENEPE, PARKS DIRECTOR OF ART AND ANTIQUITIES</p>
        <p>Bronze, marble, granite, stainless steel, zinc - if it's a statue, a monument or a memorial and it's in a city park, Adrian Benepe is its keeper. There are maybe 1,500 of them out there to wax, buff and restore, says Mr. Benepe; he's been counting them since he got this job at the end of 1987. The tallest is the 153-foot Prison Ship Martyrs' Monument, in Fort Greene Park in Brooklyn. The smallest is the St. Claire Pollack Memorial - four feet seven inches - in Riverside Park in Manhattan. It's an urn. The shiniest is the statue of Gen. William Tecumseh Sherman at the gateway to Central Park; regilding it last year cost $125,000.</p>
        <p>''When people meet me for the first time,'' says Mr. Benepe, ''they say, 'We expected someone with a long, gray beard and a tweed jacket.' '' At 33, the New York City Parks Department's director of art and antiquities still has the inquisitiveness and eagerness of the Central Park ranger he once was. Central Park means so much to him, in fact, that he got married there, in turn-of-the-century costume.</p>
        <p>Mr. Benepe's responsibilities include developing new memorials. Currently on the drawing board: one to Eleanor Roosevelt on Riverside Drive and one to Duke Ellington on Fifth Avenue. With his six-person restoration crew, he wages war on pigeons, graffiti, acid rain and exhaust fumes. The last two can reduce marble to powder and finely detailed bronze to pockmarked scrap.</p>
        <p>''You have to be a time traveler to do this job,'' Mr. Benepe says. ''You have to understand the 19th century and what was going on then and why something was put together the way it was. You have to come back to the present and say what the maintenance needs are and whether we can meet them. And then you have to travel into the future and say what this would look like in 20 years if we did nothing.''</p>
        <p>DON DURING, AIR TRAFFIC CONTROLLER</p>
        <p>Squinting through the tinted plate-glass windows with their postcard-perfect views of Manhattan, Don During has no time to reflect - not on what his colleagues faces last September, when a USAir jet skidded off the rain-slicked runway at La Guardia Airport, not on what he faced last week, yesterday or even an hour ago. Mr. During, 35, is an air traffic controller in the tower at La Guardia, where r a moment of reckoning occurs every 70 seconds.</p>
        <p>At this moments, five jets are lined up, awaiting takeoff clearance from Mr. During. And from somewhere over Shea Stadium, Pan American 531 - a shuttle flight from Boston - is callng in. As the chief choreographer in this aerial ballet, Mr. During clears the first of the lined-up jets and tells the Pan American pilot to make a turn.</p>
        <p>He stays cool despite the pressure, ''The test for controller is not knowledge,'' Mr. During says. ''They give you a piece of cardboard with lines on it, and you have to fold it up to makes a box.'' The key is an aptitude for spatial relations. Mr. During sometimes plays video games with his son, 6, and daughter, 4. ''This does take the same talent,'' he says, and shrugs.</p>
        <p>Mr. During was a United States military controller, first at a NATO base in England, then at Elgin Air Force Base in Florida. He got his first glimpse of La Guardia at 3 o'clock one mornng in 1981. It was hours before the Professional Air Traffic Controllers walked off their jobs, and Mr. During and other military controllers had been flown in to keep the airport running. Mr. During lived in a Holiday Inn for eight months. ''It got old real quick,'' he says.</p>
        <p>On the job, when his headset is crackling with chatter from pilots, Mr. During talks in a machine-gun monotone only slightly slower than an auctioneer's. ''Some days you go home and your mouth is worn out from talking so much,'' he says. ''Everything has to be done fast because of the speeds of the aircraft.'' He contrasts it to more leisurely forms of transportation. ''Driving a car,'' he says, ''you may make 20 decsions in a one-minute period, but it's so routine that you don't even think about it. Well, this you do think about.''</p>
        <p>JIM GATENS, HEAD TREASURER, TKTS</p>
        <p>''Sometimes I feel like General Custer in here,'' says Jim Gatens, who commands the ticket sellers in the TKTS booth in midtown Manhattan's Duffy Square. Mr. Gatens' quick-fingered troops are usually far outnumbered by customers calmoring for the half-price theater tickets they sell. It takes 30 minutesto get to the ticket windows if the line snakes as far south as West 46th Street. ''You have all the windows open,'' Mr.Gatens says, shaking his head, ''and it just doesn't get any shorter,'' On the inside, the pressure stays high. Often there are 50 Broadway and Off-Broadway listings on the TKTS boards. All the prices are different, so the math is tricky. But the grand totals are, well, grand: one Saturday last year, Mr. Gatens and his crew sold 11,000 seats, a new record and nealry double the normal number.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gatens, who has been with TKTS since it opened 17 years ago, takes part in endless behind-the-counter bantering and batering. He is a kind of futures trader, guessing which shows will sell and which will not, then ordering the right numbers from the theaters. The theaters are playing a similar game, trying to decide how many tickets to send to TKTS.</p>
        <p>One Wednesday morning, with a line of matineegoers at the windows, Mr. Gaten's telephone rings. It's the St. James Theater box office, offering 50 rear mezzanine seats. Mr. Gatens says yes. The Imperial Theater calls a moment later, promising 20 orchestra seats. Yes, again. Then a buy order: Mr. Gatens calls the 46th Street Theater. We're down to 20,'' Mr. Gatens says, cradling the telephone on his shoulder and feeding a stck of $20 bills into a counting machine. ''We're going to need some more.''</p>
        <p>At a window, a blind woman in a red coat wants two for ''Gypsy.'' Mr. Gatens slides the tickets through the slot. Sometimes a celebrity appears through the glass, ''A lot of the faces you know but can't remember the names,'' he says. Then there are the customers who cannot remember why they are in the line. One woman asked for a hot dog. Another wanted a subway token.</p>
        <p>WHAT REALLY MAKES NEW YORK WORK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
