<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Over E.P.A. Protest, White House Alters Wetland Agreement</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="324585"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WETLANDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AREA PLANNING AND RENEWAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REILLY, WILLIAM K (ADMR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUNUNU, JOHN H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wetlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDA1F3AF93BA35751C0A966958260" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Over E.P.A. Protest, White House Alters Wetland Agreement</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Over the objections of the Bush Administration's chief environmental official, the White House today altered a Federal agreement to protect the nation's wetlands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Over the objections of the Bush Administration's chief environmental official, the White House today altered a Federal agreement to protect the nation's wetlands.</p>
        <p>Over the objections of the Bush Administration's chief environmental official, the White House today altered a Federal agreement to protect the nation's wetlands.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said the changes were made despite the opposition of William K. Reilly, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, at the insistence of the White House chief of staff, John H. Sununu. Mr. Sununu has been increasingly intervening in the formulation of the Administration's environmental policy.</p>
        <p>Most recently, the officials said, Mr. Sununu's views helped shape a speech on global warming given by President Bush on Monday that disappointed some environmentalists because it did not call for action but called instead for further study.</p>
        <p>Essentially, the newly revised wetlands agreement permits exceptions to requirements that protect the land from development or require the replacement of any that is lost.</p>
        <p>Wetlands are swamps, marshes, bogs and other areas with a high proportion of water. They provide breeding grounds for fish and waterfowl and vital habitats for a variety of wildlife. They prevent floods by sopping up moisture and filter pollution from surface waters and recharge underground water supplies.</p>
        <p>The initial wetlands policy was contained in an agreement reached last November between the Environmental Protection Agency and the Army Corps of Engineers. The Administration today released a revised version of that agreement.</p>
        <p>Demands by Alaskan Officials</p>
        <p>The changes reflect, in part, the demands of Alaska, where officials saw the original wetlands agreement as inhibiting the development of oil and other resources over much of the state. Alaska is in large part tundra, which is technically wetland.</p>
        <p>The Transportation Department also objected to the original agreement, saying it could interfere with plans to build airports and roads.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sununu actively sided with Alaskan officials, and pressed his case with President Bush, On the other side, officials said, were Mr. Reilly and Robert Page, Assistant Army Secretary for civil works.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly declined to comment on whether he had personally protested to the President over the alteration of the agreement.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview this evening, he said only that ''the President's commitment to no net loss of wetlands is one he believes in quite strongly.''</p>
        <p>But some environmentalists said the revised agreement represented a substantial retreat from the no-net-loss policy first enunciated by Mr. Bush in the Presidential election campaign in 1988.</p>
        <p>While the Administration is still developing its overall policy regarding development in the wetlands, environmentalists and several officials within the E.P.A. said the revised agreement gives the Federal Government the flexibility to permit the destruction of wetlands that was not contained in the original agreement. They said the revised agreement establishes a principle that the loss of wetlands, without taking compensating measures, remains acceptable under certain circumstances.</p>
        <p>A Clarification, Officials Say</p>
        <p>Administration officials defending Mr. Bush said the agreement affected only about 20 percent of the nation's wetlands. They said the agreement was intended only to ''clarify'' current wetlands protection requirements of the Clean Water Act.</p>
        <p>The original agreement set forth a sequence of steps a developer had to follow to obtain a permit for filling or dredging a wetland. First, the least environmentally damaging alternative had to be chosen; second, if damage occurred it must be kept to a minimum, and, finally, if extensive damage was unavoidable, ''compensatory'' action, like restoring an existing wetland or creating a new artificial wetland, must be undertaken.</p>
        <p>The revised agreement keeps these requirements but then notes that they ''may not be practicable where there is a high proporition of land which is wetlands.''</p>
        <p>While this section was inserted to meet Alaska's objections, it does not limit its application to Alaska. ''This would permit damage to wetlands from the North Slope of Alaska to the Everglades,'' one E.P.A. official complained.</p>
        <p>Praise From Alaskan Senator</p>
        <p>The revisions also give the E.P.A. and the Army Corps of Engineers discretion to waive the requirements on a variety of grounds, including a determination that the wetland ought to be drained to prevent some other form of serious environmental harm.</p>
        <p>Senator Ted Stevens, Republican of Alaska, praised the changes, saying, ''The document now recognizes that conditions in Alaska are different and that there are circumstances under which wetlands can be developed without signfiicant environmental loss.''</p>
        <p>But Hope Babcock, general counsel for the National Audubon Society, said the revisions ''defeat the President's no-net-loss goal by relieving anyone from a clear legal obligation not to fill a wetland or to compensate for doing so.''</p>
        <p>Kathryn S. Fuller, president of the World Wildlife Fund and the Conservation Foundation, called the revised document ''a major retreat'' from efforts to conserve wetlands.</p>
        <p>Each year the nation is losing nearly 500,000 acres of wetlands a year to agriculture, industry and the spread of urban areas, Interior Department figures show. Fewer than 100 million acres of wetlands in the contiguous 48 states remain of the more than 250 million acres of wetlands that existed when the first Europeans arrived on this continent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
