<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Religions and Environment: Focus on a Worldly Concern</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="384720"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RELIGION AND CHURCHES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDMAN, ARI L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DALAI LAMA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDA103EF934A2575AC0A966958260" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Religions and Environment: Focus on a Worldly Concern</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ARI L. GOLDMAN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDMAN, ARI L</byline>
      <dateline>MIDDLEBURY, Vt., Sept. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Dalai Lama walked out of a steepled church today at the center of this New England college town, strode down a hill to an outdoor altar and broke bread with several hundred students and visitors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Dalai Lama walked out of a steepled church today at the center of this New England college town, strode down a hill to an outdoor altar and broke bread with several hundred students and visitors.</p>
        <p>The Dalai Lama walked out of a steepled church today at the center of this New England college town, strode down a hill to an outdoor altar and broke bread with several hundred students and visitors.</p>
        <p>The event was not a 1960's-style mass conversion by an Indian guru but a recognition in the 90's that the West could learn much from the East about reverence for the earth.</p>
        <p>The sharing of the bread came at the end of a four-day conference at Middlebury College about the relationship between religion and the environment. It was one of a growing number of such gatherings in recent years to bring together representatives of different faiths to talk about things once regarded as the domain of scientists: overpopulation, pollution, deforestation and the depletion of the ozone layer in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>'Red Warning Light'</p>
        <p>An alarm was sounded by the Dalai Lama, the spiritual and political leader of Tibetan Buddhists. ''Mother planet is showing us the red warning light,'' he said. '' 'Be careful,' she is saying. To take care of the planet is to take care of our own house.''</p>
        <p>Christian, Jewish, Muslim, Buddhist and American Indian theologians participated. And as in similar recent conferences, much of the blame for the ravaging of the earth was placed on what one speaker called the Judeo-Christian tradition.</p>
        <p>In the last year, the North American Conference on Religion and Ecology met in Washington and the Global Forum of Parliamentary and Religious Leaders met in Moscow to discuss similar environmental themes.</p>
        <p>Environmentalism has become part of the curriculum at major seminaries, including the Harvard Divinity School. And denominations as diverse as the Unitarians and the Southern Baptists are featuring the environmental crisis on the covers of their journals.</p>
        <p>The attraction of the conference here was the Dalai Lama, the recipient of the 1989 Nobel Peace Prize for his nonviolent struggle to gain independence for his homeland. Five thousand people crowded into the indoor hockey rink on this 2,000-student campus to hear him speak on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Some social scientists have held Western culture and religion as responsible for the environmental crisis on two accounts: They contend the culture is the major modern source of science and technology, and that it has upheld a theology that appears to make the exploitation of the earth legitimate.</p>
        <p>Audrey Shenandoah, an elder of the Onondaga tribe in upstate New York, used very different imagery in her presentation here. Ms. Shenandoah spoke of ''our mother earth'' and ''our brothers, the animals.''</p>
        <p>She said: ''Human beings are not superior to the rest of creation. If human beings were to drop out of the cycle of life, the earth would heal itself and go on. But if any of the other elements would drop out - air, water, animal life or plant life - human beings and the earth itself would end.''</p>
        <p>In the Onondaga tradition, she said, before a decision about the land is made, the implications must be considered for the lives of those who will live for seven generations.</p>
        <p>Seyyed Hossein Nasr, professor of Islamic studies at George Washington University, was more direct in his attack on the West. He said Islam upheld a reverence for the earth that was ''either forgotten or marginalized in religious thought in the West.''</p>
        <p>'Theology of Nature'</p>
        <p>''What would be called a theology of nature in Christian terms,'' he said, ''has never been forgotten in Islam, nor has the sacred view of the cosmos become totally replaced by the view based upon purely quantitative science, as has occurred in the West.''</p>
        <p>A Christian theologian, Sallie McFague, said the religious culture in the West often saw the earth as merely a way station for a better world to come. ''Christians have been brainwashed to think they belong somewhere else, namely heaven.'' Christianity focuses on human beings, she added, ''to the almost total neglect of other species.''</p>
        <p>But Dr. McFague, a professor of theology at Vanderbilt University in Nashville, said neither human beings nor God were diminished by the broad acceptance of the scientific theory that the universe began with an explosion of matter from which everything on earth evolved. ''In fact,'' she went on, ''both are enlarged.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Ismar Schorsch, who presented a Jewish perspective, preferred to retrieve largely forgotten Jewish traditions rather than reconstruct religious images. He said Judaism, ''at its best holds out a model for reining in the appetites'' of men and women.</p>
        <p>Dr. Schorsch, the chancellor of the Jewish Theological Seminary in Manhattan, called for a return to traditions like Sabbath rest, which bids man to put down his plow and give himself and the earth a rest.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
