<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Antarctica Sheds Ice and Scientists Wonder Why</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="376019"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, WALTER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DA1639F937A2575BC0A966958260" item-length="2041" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Antarctica Sheds Ice and Scientists Wonder Why</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER SULLIVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: SATELLITE monitoring shows that Antarctica has shed more than 11,000 of its 5 million square miles of ice since the 1970's, and scientists say further study is needed to determine whether the findings indicate that global warming is melting polar ice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: SATELLITE monitoring shows that Antarctica has shed more than 11,000 of its 5 million square miles of ice since the 1970's, and scientists say further study is needed to determine whether the findings indicate that global warming is melting polar ice.</p>
        <p>SATELLITE monitoring shows that Antarctica has shed more than 11,000 of its 5 million square miles of ice since the 1970's, and scientists say further study is needed to determine whether the findings indicate that global warming is melting polar ice.</p>
        <p>The new findings and other reported indicators of warming have led researchers to devise elaborate plans to map Antarctica's ice. Only half its coastline has been repeatedly recorded in satellite pictures so far.</p>
        <p>A meeting of experts organized early this year by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration in College Park, Md., recommended that a multidisciplinary research initiative be established to involve universities and Federal agencies in the study of changes in marine ice sheets, ice resting on land that is now below sea level.</p>
        <p>If global warming occurs, its effects will be most obvious at the poles, Dr. Richard S. Williams Jr. of the United States Geological Survey said in an interview. In the past, the comings and goings of polar ice have caused sea levels to fall and rise by hundreds of feet. A sea level rise of only a few feet could be catastrophic for coastal areas worldwide.</p>
        <p>Dr. Williams said the shedding of Antarctic ice might have begun ''hundreds of years ago.'' He said he doubted that it was part of a short-term cycle, but said he could not rule out global warming as the cause.</p>
        <p>Jane G. Ferrigno, who works with Dr. Williams, said at an international conference on the subject at the University of Alaska in Fairbanks in June, that in 1986 alone, more than 8,800 square miles of ice had floated into the Weddell Sea from the Larsen and Filchner ice shelves, layers of continental ice about 1,000 feet thick, that flowed off onto ocean water.</p>
        <p>''Recent apparent large-scale retreat or recession in several areas make it important to continue to monitor and evaluate the changes to determine if they are random, cyclic, or whether they are a signal of global climate change,'' she said.</p>
        <p>This loss of ice from the shelves did not substantially raise sea levels, she said, but could clear the way for rapid and massive shedding of ice resting on land, which would cause water levels to rise.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ferrigno said four other extensions of the continental ice had gone to sea in the last few years, as well. In 1987 more than 1,900 square miles from the Ross Ice Shelf ''calved,'' floating off to sea as a giant iceberg and disintegrated.</p>
        <p>Researchers studying corals have concluded that two periods of polar ice melting after the last ice age brought about extremely rapid sea level rises - up to 14 feet in a century. Last month, French scientists reported that evidence from African lakes suggested that rapid climate change coincided with the polar melting and filled the previously arid lakes, perhaps within decades.</p>
        <p>The Antarctic accounts for 91 percent of the earth's ice. Almost all the rest is over Greenland. Enough of this ice melted between the last two ice ages, 125,000 years ago, to raise global sea levels at least 20 feet above their present level. A study of sea-level rise published this month by the National Academy of Sciences, while noting that global sea levels have risen 300 feet in the last 18,000 years as ice sheets melted and taking into account the possibility of further polar ice melting, forecast a rise of roughly 1.5 to 3.5 feet in the next century.</p>
        <p>Participants at the NASA meeting said much of West Antarctica's marine ice sheet is vulnerable to collapse and dispersal into the oceans when sea water penetrates it, causing it to break into icebergs. The proposed multidisciplinary project, called Searise, would monitor the grounding line, the place where ice flowing off the continent becomes waterborne and the spot where the penetration of ocean under the marine ice sheets would occur. Because the land slopes downward at the new grounding line, the ice ''would find itself in deeper water, where the ice needs to be thicker to maintain contact with the bed,'' the Searise report said. In such a situation, it explained, ''the grounding line retreats faster and faster as the entire ice mass is dispersed toward its margin and into the ocean.''</p>
        <p>Possible Signs of Collapse</p>
        <p>Like water flowing off a continent, five ''streams'' of ice renewed by snowfall, up to 50 miles wide and 300 miles long, flow across the slow-moving West Antarctic ice sheet into the floating Ross Ice Shelf. These streams, which move half a mile a year, ''may be manifestations of collapse already under way,'' the NASA panel said.</p>
        <p>Specialists believe that if the Ross Shelf went to sea, no longer buttressing the inland ice, the ice might become ''unplugged'' and disperse. This might occur as well on the opposite side of West Antarctica if the Ronne and Filchner ice shelves went to sea, but only a small percentage of them has broken up in recent years.</p>
        <p>A contrary view, that the Antarctic ice may be growing, has been advanced by Dr. Charles R. Bentley of the University of Wisconsin at Madison. From measurements of snow accumulation and ice that broke off into the water, he has sought to estimate how much ice is being added to the ice sheet by snowfall and compare it with the loss by flow into the sea around the entire continent. From this he estimates that input exceeds output by 5 to 15 percent. He said global warming would produce even greater accumulation, since that would increase the humidity of air blowing from the sea, causing still more snow to fall.</p>
        <p>The accumulation that he estimates is already occurring would lower worldwide sea levels by one-tenth to four-tenths of an inch per year. But sea levels seem to be rising. This means the melting ice must be coming from elsewhere, possibly Greenland or mountain glaciers, he said in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>Melting Greenland Ice</p>
        <p>Dr. Roy M. Koerner of the Geological Survey of Canada has argued that the rise in sea level at the end of the next-to-last ice age to 20 feet above the present level was almost all caused by shedding of ice from Greenland. Samples from the bottoms of two holes drilled through the Greenland ice cap, he argues, show that the ice formed on bare land at the start of the most recent ice age, after all ice from the previous ice age had already vanished.</p>
        <p>He noted that so far, samples from the sea floor off Antarctica have not shown evidence that West Antarctica totally shed its ice after the next-to-last ice age.</p>
        <p>Evidence that polar ice disintegrated after the last ice age far more rapidly than had been supposed has been derived from corals on the island of Barbados by Dr. Richard G. Fairbanks of the Columbia University Lamont-Doherty Geological Observatory. He has reconstructed a record of sea levels over the past 18,000 years. This, he said in an interview, shows that 14,200 years ago, sea levels were rising at a rate of 14 feet per century.</p>
        <p>In a subsequent surge, 11,300 years ago, seas rose 12 feet per century. Whether the melting came from Antarctica or elsewhere is uncertain, he said. The rapid filling of widely separated lake beds in the African desert was reported in a recent issue of the journal Nature by French researchers who studied lake sediment.</p>
        <p>Participants in the NASA meeting acknowledged that ice is also flowing swiftly off Greenland. For example, Jakobshavn Glacier, the world's fastest, is flowing into the sea at the rate of 75 feet a day. They decided, however, that their first focus should be on the West Antarctic sheet because of its vulnerability. More offshore sampling could help determine its history, as well as drilling through it to see whether any ice from the previous ice age remains.</p>
        <p>Participants also noted that shedding of the Antarctic ice would have many little-recognized effects, changing ocean and air circulation probably as far north as the tropics. Such circulation is now strongly influenced by the violent winds that pour off the South Polar ice.</p>
        <p>Monitoring by Satellites</p>
        <p>NASA officials believe that satellites carrying laser altimeters will be able to spot lowering of the surface, if a collapse is occurring. The program assumes that satellites, as well as surface expeditions, will monitor changing ice volume, including flow down the glaciers and ice streams. Scientists from several countries are building radio-observing stations in Antarctica to provide highly precise reference points for such observations.</p>
        <p>By comparing radio signals from distant celestial objects like quasars, scientists at stations on land and on the ice can determine their locations to within a fraction of an inch. The Japanese have recently built such a station at Showa, their base in Enderby Land. The West Germans have started one near the Antarctic Peninsula. A Soviet station is projected, but the site is still uncertain.</p>
        <p>Dr. James Garwin of NASA, who is working on plans for satellite mapping of Mars as well as the height of the Antarctic ice, said a challenge would be to determine the satellite's orbit precisely enough to identify where its radar or laser beam is looking.</p>
        <p>Other efforts are already under way. Dr. Baerbel K. Lucchitta of the Geological Survey office in Flagstaff, Ariz., told the Fairbanks meeting of efforts to learn the extent to which Antarctica, through its many coastal glaciers, is dumping ice directly into the sea. The 25-nation Scientific Committee on Antarctic Research has begun a program to take duplicate photographs from space of glaciers recorded by satellite in the early 1970's.</p>
        <p>So far, she said, such repeated images of 15 glaciers have been recorded, showing rates of annual motion ranging from 328 feet to 1.4 miles. Because the flowing glaciers carry with them crevasse patterns, splits in the ice that are easily recognized in the images, their motions can be followed from year to year. The fastest are the Pine Island and Land Glaciers, both draining Marie Byrd Land.</p>
        <p>Robert A. Wharton Jr., of the Desert Research Institute in Reno, told of 10 years of observing ice thickness on Lake Hoare, a permanently ice-covered lake in southern Victoria Land, near McMurdo Sound. From 1979 to 1986, he said, it thinned from 18 feet to 11 feet, then stabilized.</p>
        <p>Above-Freezing Temperatures</p>
        <p>''An increase in mean annual temperature is the most plausible explanation,'' he said. He and his colleagues believe that peak summer temperatures have been above freezing ''for a progressively longer period of time each year since 1973.''</p>
        <p>Another temperature measurement was reported by Gary D. Clow and colleagues at the Geological Survey branch in Menlo Park, Calif. They studied the manner in which heat has propagated downward in permanently frozen ground, concluding that during the past century much of northern Alaska has warmed about 4 to 8 degrees Fahrenheit.</p>
        <p>Dr. Clow said a drill hole in the Taylor Dry Valley of Antarctica showed a rise of about two degrees in the past 15 years, but its link to warming was uncertain.</p>
        <p>The June 28 issue of Nature discussed evidence for Arctic ice thinning obtained by upward-looking sonar on two British submarines cruising under the ice. Earlier expeditions have found average thicknesses to be highly variable, ranging from 10 to 15 feet. The thinning from 1976 to 1987 was found to be substantial, but subject to so many factors that it could not be taken as evidence for climate change.</p>
        <p>There seems to be widespread, though not universal, agreement that the world has become warmer in recent decades. Philip D. Jones and Tom M. L. Wigley at the University of East Anglia in Britain have completed a 10-year analysis of available data. In the August issue of Scientific American they say: ''Our work shows conclusively that the world's climate, though highly variable over periods of a decade or less, has become generally warmer during the past century.''</p>
        <p>The effect, they say, has been less than that predicted from carbon dioxide and other gases added to the atmosphere by human activity. There is no proof that such an effect is occurring, they say, but they argue that this should not be used as an excuse for inaction.</p>
        <p>''The longer the world waits to act, the greater will be the climate change that future generations will have to endure,'' they warned.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
