<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cloth Diapers Don't Help the Environment</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="389667"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLASTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GERGLEY, LISA BELLINI</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DC1E3EF934A35753C1A966958260" item-length="433" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cloth Diapers Don't Help the Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In a recent letter to the New Jersey editor entitled ''A Cup of Coffee, an Idea on Recycling,''the author suggested that an appropriate environmental alternative to a plastic foam coffee cup is a ceramic mug and that a canvas or string grocery bag is better than a brown paper bag.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In a recent letter to the New Jersey editor entitled ''A Cup of Coffee, an Idea on Recycling,''the author suggested that an appropriate environmental alternative to a plastic foam coffee cup is a ceramic mug and that a canvas or string grocery bag is better than a brown paper bag.</p>
        <p>In a recent letter to the New Jersey editor entitled ''A Cup of Coffee, an Idea on Recycling,''the author suggested that an appropriate environmental alternative to a plastic foam coffee cup is a ceramic mug and that a canvas or string grocery bag is better than a brown paper bag.</p>
        <p>That's fine. The problem is in assuming that disposable diapers should be replaced by cloth diapers. If saving the environment is the concern, cloth diapers are a big mistake.</p>
        <p>Let's not forget about the greater amount of water pollution that cloth diapers can create and the higher amount of water they consume. Each child requires an extra 144 gallons of water to wash, rinse and rerinse his cloth diapers. Luckily New Jersey is not experiencing a water shortage this year, but what about states like California that are? Switching to cloth diapers would be a disaster. The Environmental Protection Agency said it would make matters worse.</p>
        <p>If a diaper service is used, cloth diapers can produce more air pollution and consume more energy. The delivery trucks use gasoline and pollute our air as they weave through traffic. In today's time of dual-career families, it is not realistic to assume that most people who use cloth diapers will wash their own.</p>
        <p>The fact that 90 percent of the disposable diaper is recyclable was left out. It is true that disposable diapers come from our trees, but at least that is a renewable energy resource; new trees are planted to replace those cut down. The energy used as gasoline for delivery trucks or the water used and polluted as a result of washing cloth diapers cannot be renewed.</p>
        <p>Let's not be quick to blame disposable diapers for our landfill problem either. According to an archeologist at the University of Arizona, diapers account for 1.8 percent of volume in landfills. On the other hand, paper and yard waste total about 60 percent of the landfill. If we recycled and composted those two items alone, we could reduce our garbage by more than half. Let's focus on the things we can do to make the biggest dent in the garbage glut.</p>
        <p>As a mother, I worry about a proposed bill in New Jersey, which I visit often, that would require all institutions like nursing homes, hospitals and day care centers to use cloth diapers. I would worry about my daughter's health in a day care center with children in cloth diapers. Cloth diapers leak more so there is a greater chance for the spread of infections. In addition, when I have my second child, I will be sure to choose a hospital that uses disposable diapers.</p>
        <p>LISA BELLINI GERGLEY</p>
        <p>Locust Volley, L.I.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
