<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Talking Business; with Ellis of Northeast Utilities;   The Lessons From Seabrook</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="332213"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ELLIS, WILLIAM B</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SEABROOK NUCLEAR POWER PLANT</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PUBLIC SERVICE CO OF NEW HAMPSHIRE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NORTHEAST UTILITIES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">TALKING BUSINESS (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900306T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DE153BF935A35750C0A966958260" item-length="864" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Talking Business; with Ellis of Northeast Utilities;   The Lessons From Seabrook</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Nuclear Regulatory Commission voted last week to give an operating license to the Seabrook nuclear plant after 20 years of controversy and protests and the bankruptcy of its major builder, the Public Service Company of New Hampshire, which owns 36 percent of the project. William B. Ellis is the chairman and chief executive of Northeast Utilities, based in Berlin, Conn., which owns a 4 percent share of Seabrook and is expected to complete the purchase of Public Service soon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Nuclear Regulatory Commission voted last week to give an operating license to the Seabrook nuclear plant after 20 years of controversy and protests and the bankruptcy of its major builder, the Public Service Company of New Hampshire, which owns 36 percent of the project. William B. Ellis is the chairman and chief executive of Northeast Utilities, based in Berlin, Conn., which owns a 4 percent share of Seabrook and is expected to complete the purchase of Public Service soon.</p>
        <p>The Nuclear Regulatory Commission voted last week to give an operating license to the Seabrook nuclear plant after 20 years of controversy and protests and the bankruptcy of its major builder, the Public Service Company of New Hampshire, which owns 36 percent of the project. William B. Ellis is the chairman and chief executive of Northeast Utilities, based in Berlin, Conn., which owns a 4 percent share of Seabrook and is expected to complete the purchase of Public Service soon.</p>
        <p>Q. What does Seabrook's operation mean to New England?</p>
        <p>A. The addition of that generating capacity is terribly important, because New England has already come very close to not having adequate capacity. Even though it's only 5 percent more, it provides a little breathing space; it carries us roughly two years.</p>
        <p>Q. Does the Seabrook saga - $6.5 billion, 20 years, one bankrupt utility - teach any lessons about the way generating capacity will be added in the future?</p>
        <p>A. The lesson is already palpable. We are more cautious, don't assume too much. We don't presume too much. We have had demonstrated to us in several states the gap between the assumptions that utilities made when they got these construction projects started and the way real life actually comes about, in the way plants are treated in rate-making. Those lessons affect utilities all over the country.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you build large power stations anymore?</p>
        <p>A. At Northeast, after having finished Millstone 3, we are in a situation where we don't have to build any more large power stations. I'm told by utility people who need more capacity that they are more cautious. They don't like the way it looks and they don't build capacity.</p>
        <p>Q. Does Seabrook push the utilities toward conservation?</p>
        <p>A. Not the Seabrook experience so much but the overall problem of building capacity. I do believe that has been a major driving force toward conservation. Utilities have discovered that it's not easy to build capacity, so you better try to reduce the need for new capacity. Also, they have discovered it is the public will. Public policy seems to be pointing in the direction of conservation, and getting along in this world requires you to have regulators that find you credible. That means to be a good conservationist.</p>
        <p>Q. What is Seabrook worth?</p>
        <p>A. If you were to measure it in terms of alternative energy sources, it probably is hard to recover in a direct economic sense as much as the $6.5 billion that it cost. But that may not be the best way of looking at it. For example, if global warming were to require that we don't burn any more fossil fuel, that plant will be worth more than $6.5 billion, depending on what you otherwise would find yourself doing in this world to avoid burning fossil fuel.</p>
        <p>Q. Is Seabrook a cautionary tale for utilities, that it is possible for a utility to go out of business by making the wrong choice in power generation?</p>
        <p>A. No. That oversimplifies it. It ignores the predominant factor in the Public Service bankruptcy; the state government passed an anti-construction-work-in-progress law. It reduced Public Service's options.</p>
        <p>Q. You mean the law that barred the company from charging customers for unfinished or canceled plants?</p>
        <p>A. Yes. Public Service could have concluded, as some companies did, that the power's too expensive, we don't want it. But the law made it impossible for them to do things that their analysis would have said they should do, because they would not be able to recover a dime of what they'd invested in the plant. That distortion complicates the question greatly. The choice would have been, either break the company or have a chance of continuing.</p>
        <p>This may be a little academic, but if an unnamed company with an unnamed project faced a decision where there's a 20 percent chance that they can continue the project and ultimately recover their cost, but a zero chance of recovering a dime if they choose to abandon it, it really drives them in a wrong directions, away from a decision that's in the public interest.</p>
        <p>Q. In fact, all the partners who went along with that unnamed company and unnamed project signed a do-or-die pact to finish the plant, didn't they?</p>
        <p>A. Well, they'd signed the pact long before death was a part of the deal. Any reasonable person at that time would have been very surprised at the time those signatures went down that death was in the cards.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you have any predictions for Seabrook 2, which was abandoned at 25 percent complete, or for nuclear power in New England?</p>
        <p>A. I have no predictions for Seabrook 2. It's not a subject that we discuss very much. It's rarely mentioned in my hearing.</p>
        <p>With regard to nuclear power, the facts of life, quite aside from Seabrook, are very powerful. Many features of a nuclear plant say, Don't do another one. Too much has to be done. Public attitudes and public opinion, and how those translate into governmental policy, would have to provide absolute assurances, that all the way from beginning construction to the end of the lifetime of that plant, there would be governmental support for nuclear power.</p>
        <p>What I have just done is give you the absolute mission impossible.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
