<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is Overpopulation Too Grim a Tale?</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="348292"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="CONNECTICUT OPINION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POPULATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D61F39F93AA15757C0A966958260" item-length="806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is Overpopulation Too Grim a Tale?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William A. Burley; William A. Burley, principal of the John Pettibone School in New Milford, is a member of the population committee of the Connecticut Sierra Club.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: NO problem facing the earth looms larger than the growth in the reproductive rate of the human species. Virtually all degradation of the environment, all exhaustion of natural resources and substantial human suffering can be attributed to the crushing effect of a population that is too numerous for our planet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: NO problem facing the earth looms larger than the growth in the reproductive rate of the human species. Virtually all degradation of the environment, all exhaustion of natural resources and substantial human suffering can be attributed to the crushing effect of a population that is too numerous for our planet.</p>
        <p>NO problem facing the earth looms larger than the growth in the reproductive rate of the human species. Virtually all degradation of the environment, all exhaustion of natural resources and substantial human suffering can be attributed to the crushing effect of a population that is too numerous for our planet.</p>
        <p>The belief among many cultures that children are the equivalent of wealth is a bankrupt social and economic theory. In the last decade of the 20th century, fewer children mean a better life and a healthier environment.</p>
        <p>Consider pollution. It is but one strand in a Gordian knot involving industry, demand for consumer goods, petrochemical use, energy consumption and waste disposal. It knows no national or geographic boundries. Human effluence despoils the beaches of Cannes as well as those of Niantic. The skies are fouled with noxious gasses that haunt us in the form of health-harming particulates, acid rain and ozone depletion.</p>
        <p>Increasing levels of atmospheric carbon dioxide contribute to global warming. Landfills spill over with toxic chemicals contaminating water supplies. Nuclear-waste stores are time bombs waiting to detonate.</p>
        <p>Like it or not, the nations of the northern hemisphere must assume most responsibility for worldwide pollution. To a large degree, third world people suffer the consequences of first world gluttony.</p>
        <p>What about the depletion of natural resources? All people shoulder some blame. The industrialized nations gobble more than their fair share of irreplaceable fossil fuels and mineral resources, but poorer nations, too, are guilty of clearcutting rain forests, overfishing the seas, stripping the hillsides for firewood and exhausting the soil. Perhaps the most valuable commodity of all, fresh water, is being reduced at an alarming rate. In short, the resources essential for sustaining life - food, clean water, energy, shelter and a safe environment - are in imminent peril of becoming eroded beyond repair.</p>
        <p>The number of humans is astonishing. World population stands at 5.3 billion in 1990, and will double to 10 billion in 40 years. The earth's population is growing by 90 million a year, the equivalent of the entire population of Mexico.</p>
        <p>Many nations, especially in Africa and Asia, are teetering on the edge of social collapse. Wholesale famine in these countries is probable in five years. Tens of millions will starve to death. The United States and other agriculturally rich nations will be unable to prevent starvation, since first world food-producing capabilities are stretched to the limits. In 1988 the United States had to import grain for the first time.</p>
        <p>This is grim stuff at any age, so how can it be appropriate to teach to children? How will they react to information about the portent of cataclysmic events?</p>
        <p>My experience is that children know something is fundamentally wrong with the world, and they are eager to listen to the message. They do not suffer undo emotional stress. For one thing, they know about pollution, recycling and conservation. They're involved with these activities when they attend Scout meetings or eat at McDonald's. The news is full of stories about toxic hazards, polluted water sources and medical wastes on beaches. They know about global warming and the destruction of the rain forests.</p>
        <p>What they don't know are the facts about the other side of the ecology equation, the burgeoning human population. And without a grasp of the details, their knowledge of conservation is only half an education.</p>
        <p>What are reasonable things to teach children about the population explosion? First, tell them the numbers, but equate the numbers with more concrete concepts. For example, the population of the United States is growing every year by 2.5 million people, roughly the number of people in Connecticut.</p>
        <p>Next, tie population growth to environmental issues. Discuss acid rain and global warming. Talk about the local landfill. Guide them to see that the earth cannot withstand mistreatment by hoards of people. And show them how the American life style is particularly damaging to the environment.</p>
        <p>Finally, offer suggestions about how they can become involved and make a difference. Discuss taking political action. Encourage them to write letters to state and Federal legislators asking that they sponsor a bill calling for a national policy on population reduction.</p>
        <p>Give them bibliographies of appropriate readings. Provide names and address of organizations working on conservation and population issues. And counsel them that they can make a difference, but they will face some difficult choices in their lives about family planning and consumer habits.</p>
        <p>Should we teach children about the population problem? The real question ought to be: can we afford not to educate our young about the realities of their future?</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT OPINION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
