<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Are You Your Planet's Keeper?</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Health; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="345850"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH DAY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WADE, NICHOLAS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NAAR, JON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COHEN, GARY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'CONNOR, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NULL, GARY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEGER, WILL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOWERMASTER, JON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HYNES, H PATRICIA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIFKIN, JEREMY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ERICKSON, BRAD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LYMAN, FRANCESCA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">DESIGN FOR A LIVABLE PLANET (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FIGHTING TOXICS (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CLEARER, CLEANER, SAFER, GREENER (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SAVING THE EARTH (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">EARTHRIGHT (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">GREEN LIFESTYLE HANDBOOK, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CALL TO ACTION (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE TRAP, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DD1F38F931A15757C0A966958260" item-length="1583" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Are You Your Planet's Keeper?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS WADE; Nicholas Wade is a member of the editorial board of The New York Times.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WADE, NICHOLAS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>DESIGN FOR A LIVABLE PLANET</p>
        <p>By Jon Nair</p>
        <p>FIGHTING TOXICS</p>
        <p>Edited by Gary Cohen and John O'Connor.</p>
        <p>CLEARER, CLEANER, SAFER, GREENER</p>
        <p>By Gary Null</p>
        <p>SAVING THE EARTH</p>
        <p>By Will Steger and Jon Bowermaster.</p>
        <p>EARTHRIGHT</p>
        <p>By H. Patricia Hynes.</p>
        <p>THE GREEN LIFESTYLE HANDBOOK</p>
        <p>Edited by Jeremy Rifkin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>DESIGN FOR A LIVABLE PLANET</p>
        <p>By Jon Nair</p>
        <p>FIGHTING TOXICS</p>
        <p>Edited by Gary Cohen and John O'Connor.</p>
        <p>CLEARER, CLEANER, SAFER, GREENER</p>
        <p>By Gary Null</p>
        <p>SAVING THE EARTH</p>
        <p>By Will Steger and Jon Bowermaster.</p>
        <p>EARTHRIGHT</p>
        <p>By H. Patricia Hynes.</p>
        <p>THE GREEN LIFESTYLE HANDBOOK</p>
        <p>Edited by Jeremy Rifkin.</p>
        <p>DESIGN FOR A LIVABLE PLANET</p>
        <p>By Jon Nair</p>
        <p>FIGHTING TOXICS</p>
        <p>Edited by Gary Cohen and John O'Connor.</p>
        <p>CLEARER, CLEANER, SAFER, GREENER</p>
        <p>By Gary Null</p>
        <p>SAVING THE EARTH</p>
        <p>By Will Steger and Jon Bowermaster.</p>
        <p>EARTHRIGHT</p>
        <p>By H. Patricia Hynes.</p>
        <p>THE GREEN LIFESTYLE HANDBOOK</p>
        <p>Edited by Jeremy Rifkin.</p>
        <p>CALL TO ACTION</p>
        <p>Edited by Brad Erikson.</p>
        <p>THE GREENHOUSE TRAP</p>
        <p>By Francesca Lyman.</p>
        <p>Boycott A.T.&amp;T. Donate your old tires to a playground. Buy shares in a recycling company. Save your used cans to hold nails. Boycott General Electric. Dose up on vitamins. Take a vacation in your own town. Boycott Weyerhaeuser. Don't buy hair spray, make your own from a boiled lemon.</p>
        <p>These prescriptions have a common purpose. Not, as you might suppose, to save pennies for your piggy bank, but to save the world from ecological disaster. They are culled from the parade of books with which the publishing industry is giving its lock-step salutation to April 22, the 20th anniversary of Earth Day.</p>
        <p>The prescriptions are of course quite dotty. Even if we all gummed up our hair with lemon juice spray, helped turn our local playground into a used-tire dump and took our vacations around it, leaving our nails at home in used tin cans, while praying for our recycling company to escape Chapter 11, but forbearing to call our broker on A.T.&amp;T., these hair-shirt exertions would leave the environment little better off. Still, one must admire the spirit that drives the recommendations for such complicated life styles.</p>
        <p>Earth Day 1970 marked the emergence of the environmental movement as a potent force in American politics. A cascade of landmark laws, including the Clean Air Act and the Clean Water Act, were soon passed. Earth, air and water are far cleaner as a result, even if still far from pristine. Any who doubt their deep debt to the environmental movement have only to travel to Eastern Europe, where for the past 40 years the environment has yielded to the production norms of central planners. The Danube is a sewer, the Vistula's waters too polluted even for industrial use, and a pall of choking soot and sulfur dioxide eats away at leaves and lungs from Saxony to Silesia. The United States once risked these excesses too, but then an open political system responded to citizens' protests.</p>
        <p>The environmental movement in the United States is broadly based and covers a wide political spectrum. Most of the works under review are handbooks for citizen action. They are written more to exhort the troops to battle than to offer dispassionate analysis. The general formula is to establish quickly that everyone is in imminent peril - from toxic waste dumps, indoor pollution, electromagnetic waves, the greenhouse effect or pesticides - then proceed to list possible remedies.</p>
        <p>The general fault is a lack of perspective. The writers give little or no space to the considerable improvements already made or under way.</p>
        <p>None attempt to establish priorities, grade the risks or compare them with accepted hazards in everyday life. The gloom and doom are surely self-defeating because most readers will soon be overwhelmed by the dangers on all sides and throw up their hands.</p>
        <p>Jon Naar, the author of DESIGN FOR A LIVABLE PLANET: HOW YOU CAN HELP CLEAN UP THE ENVIRONMENT (Harper &amp; Row, cloth, $25.95; paper, $12.95), presents his case clearly, with well-devised tables. He usefully lists ways to reduce energy use in the home. But he sometimes lapses into relentless exaggeration. In ''virtually any urban area you live in, the air you take in every five seconds almost certainly does not meet federal standards,'' proclaims the chapter on air pollution. It's true that 135 million Americans live in areas that fail one or more of the six Federal air quality standards. But the book doesn't mention that an area fails the smog standard if even one of its air quality monitors shows an excess pollutant for four hours per year. Obviously that does not mean, as the author seems to think, that every breath you take is polluted.</p>
        <p>FIGHTING TOXICS: A MANUAL FOR PROTECTING YOUR FAMILY, COMMUNITY, AND WORKPLACE, edited by Gary Cohen and John O'Connor (Island Press, cloth, $31.95; paper, $19.95), may be useful if you live near a toxic dump, as many people do. It has clear chapters on environmental law and citizens' rights. It is not so clear on quantifying the risk from toxic dumps. Given the witch's brew of poisonous chemicals contained in many dumps, the health of the surrounding populations is surprisingly untouched, at least on present evidence. But from the first sentence onward - ''uncontrolled toxic chemicals and wastes have reached crisis proportions'' - this book aims to alarm, not assuage.</p>
        <p>CLEARER, CLEANER, SAFER, GREENER: A BLUEPRINT FOR DETOXIFYING YOUR ENVIRONMENT by Gary Null (Villard, $18.95) deals with everything from the greenhouse effect to electromagnetic radiation. There's a lot of information, but essentially the book offers a ride through a house of horrors. ''American agriculture is teetering on the brink of disaster and getting more vulnerable every day. This is not meant to be an alarmist statement,'' Mr. Null remarks, ''but it is intended to get your attention.'' Now we are attending, what is the solution to all these daunting problems? Well, the environment of course is almost beyond saving, so the best you can do, Mr. Null explains, is to safeguard your own health - by eating more vitamins.</p>
        <p>SAVING THE EARTH: A CITIZEN'S GUIDE TO ENVIRONMENTAL ACTION by Will Steger and Jon Bowermaster (Knopf, paper, $19.95) is perhaps the best in this category. It is carefully written, with reasoned suggestions for action and informative diagrams. The authors prefer to build a case for their views rather than bludgeon the reader into submission. They even welcome economic growth: ''The key to saving the rain forests rests in helping Third World nations achieve sustainable development.''</p>
        <p>A large amount of mostly practical advice on pesticides, recycling, drinking water, and actions to avert ozone layer thinning and climate change is to be found in EARTHRIGHT by H. Patricia Hynes (Prima, cloth, $24.95; paper, $12.95).</p>
        <p>Those prepared to accept full responsibility for the earth's plight will learn in THE GREEN LIFESTYLE HANDBOOK, edited by Jeremy Rifkin (Holt, paper, $10.95), how their personal choices in everyday life impinge on the planet. Indeed, the authors write, every dollar spent in the supermarket ''is a vote for or against the environment.'' Correct living requires using cold water in the kitchen whenever possible, starting a compost heap and watering the lawn only at night. Consumption, the economists' measure of success, is this handbook's bugaboo, despite its focus on middle-class living. All of our raw materials - food, wood, minerals - it warns, ''are either grown on mechanized, chemical-intensive 'farms' or extracted from the earth by oil-guzzling machines. The result is irreversible topsoil erosion, deforestation, water pollution, and the release of billions of tons of carbon dioxide into the atmosphere.'' So should we abandon mining and farming? The authors of the handbook put up no resistance to the logical thrust of their principles - that humankind would do best to revert to the cave, or maybe the monastery.</p>
        <p>There is little analysis in CALL TO ACTION: HANDBOOK FOR ECOLOGY, PEACE, AND JUSTICE (Sierra Club, paper, $14.95). The editor, Brad Erickson, believes that a corporate conspiracy controls the Government and exploits both the environment and the poor so that the elite may grow rich. Naturally, ''we cannot trust politicians or lobbyists to halt the destruction of the Earth for us.'' Strangely, this book is sponsored by the Sierra Club, which maintains a powerful and effective lobbying arm.</p>
        <p>In a more serious category is THE GREENHOUSE TRAP: WHAT WE'RE DOING TO THE ATMOSPHERE AND HOW WE CAN SLOW GLOBAL WARMING by Francesca Lyman with Irving Mintzer, Kathleen Courrier and James MacKenzie (Beacon, cloth, $21.95; paper, $9.95), which offers a detailed but approachable analysis of a single issue. But is the globe really warming? Most climatologists believe there is utterly inadequate evidence that greenhouse-induced warming has yet begun - a point that might have received more emphasis in a book of this quality. The authors, from the World Resources Institute, also equivocate in discussing nuclear power, which, since it produces no greenhouse gases, should be considered by any serious prophet of greenhouse warming.</p>
        <p>All the books under review are earnest attempts to get people involved in protecting the environment. They therefore contribute to a noble and necessary cause. Even if some of their recommendations seem quixotic, there is surely value in getting people to think about how their patterns of consumption affect the environment.</p>
        <p>The danger of these books is their lack of discrimination. In portraying all environmental threats as equally and utterly hazardous, they overstate the case and, worse, fail to set priorities. The public is thus encouraged to waste money in abating catchy-sounding but lesser evils, such as toxic dumps or offshore sludge dumping, while ignoring more serious pollutants, such as radon in homes and chemical runoff from farms.</p>
        <p>Earth Day 1970 was the harbinger of stirring victories for cleaner air and water. These books offer little guide to the far more complex issues that lie beyond Earth Day 1990.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
