<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Women's Group Seeks Environmental Role</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="396066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED NATIONS CONFERENCE ON ENVIRONMENT AND DEVELOPMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOWE, MARVINE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDE133AF93BA15753C1A966958260" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Women's Group Seeks Environmental Role</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARVINE HOWE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOWE, MARVINE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Alarmed by the deteriorating health of the planet, women from around the world have come together to demand a bigger role in all levels of decision-making on the environment and development.</p>
        <p>In a four-day session that ended Monday, 50 women met at the United Nations Church Center to establish a worldwide network for bringing their agenda into the environmental debate. Their immediate goal is equal representation at the United Nations Conference on Environment and Development in Brazil in 1992.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Alarmed by the deteriorating health of the planet, women from around the world have come together to demand a bigger role in all levels of decision-making on the environment and development.</p>
        <p>In a four-day session that ended Monday, 50 women met at the United Nations Church Center to establish a worldwide network for bringing their agenda into the environmental debate. Their immediate goal is equal representation at the United Nations Conference on Environment and Development in Brazil in 1992.</p>
        <p>The international committee includes leading environmentalists like Vandana Shiva of India; Wangari Maathai of Kenya, a grass-roots organizer; Dr. Rosalie Bertell of Canada, an environmental health specialist, and radical environmentalists like Claire Greensfelder of the Earth Island Institute in California.</p>
        <p>Women have been "invisible in policy-making on environmental and development issues," said Bella Abzug, a founder of the Women's Foreign Policy Council, the meeting's sponsor. The participants put together a plan to mobilize their local constituencies and lay the groundwork for their own congress in Miami in November 1991, the Brazil conference in 1992 and other efforts over the next decade.  'A Real Learning Process'</p>
        <p>Although they came from diverse cultures in Latin America, Africa, Asia, Europe and North America, the women had little difficulty in reaching a general consensus on their basic goals, principles and plan of action. They differed mainly in style, with some of the more radical campaigners fiercely attacking governments viewed as anti-environmentalist.</p>
        <p>Libby Bassett, an American environmental consultant, said the congress did not become a regional debate or a struggle between the first world and the third. She described it as "a real learning process in which we worked out an alternative way of planning the planet."</p>
        <p>The plan of action sets these main goals:</p>
        <p>*Full participation by women in environment policy at all levels.</p>
        <p>*Freedom of choice in family planning.</p>
        <p>*Redefinition of development on the principle that investment must not destroy the environment.</p>
        <p>*Increased education and information on the environment and development.</p>
        <p>*Protection of natural systems.</p>
        <p>*Development of a code of earth ethics.</p>
        <p>The conference took health as its central theme, inspired by the work of Dr. Bertell, who heads the International Institute of Concern for Public Health, based in Toronto. For the last 12 years, Dr. Bertell has helped organize communities and individuals whose health is threatened by industrial and military pollution.</p>
        <p>"Everybody agrees that the environment is sick -- the Earth and air, water, forests -- and that what we want is a healthy, balanced environment," said Chodchoy Sophonpanich, president of the Thai Environmental and Community Development Association.  Keeping 'Systems in Balance'</p>
        <p>Maria Eugenia de Cotter, director of the Arias Foundation of Costa Rica, said that healthy development means "keeping the natural systems in balance, whether it be the human system or the ecological system."</p>
        <p>Tamar Eshel, a former member of the Israeli Parliament, said that up to now, women have been out of the environment policy process. She felt that this would change now, adding that her own government had asked her to report on the results of the meeting.</p>
        <p>Brief reports from the industrialized and developing world on the health of the environment were equally grim.</p>
        <p>"What we have today is maldevelopment, wealth and poverty," said Dr. Rosina Wiltshire of the Caribbean Conservation Association in Barbados. "This distorted concept of development will ultimately lead to the de struction of the planet."</p>
        <p>In Thailand, people either don't know or don't care about environment, Ms. Sophonpanich said. She stressed that many laws have not stopped deforestation, either at the hands of businessmen or villagers.  'The War of Resources'</p>
        <p>In India, economic development has not improved the quality of life, said Vanaja Ramprasad, a consultant on ecology. "New technologies have increased food production but the majority cannot afford to buy."</p>
        <p>"In Africa we have no choice; we know we're doing the wrong thing but what else can we do?" said Gertrude Mongella, a member of the Central Committee of Tanzania's governing party. She said impoverished women were among those who routinely exploit the environment, cutting down trees for firewood, growing tobacco, allowing overgrazing and using pesticides.</p>
        <p>"Even if there's a woman at the top, they can still destroy environment very thoroughly," said Bernadette Vallely of the Women's Environment Network in Britain. She pointed to a crisis in the country's health service, as well as acid rain, poverty and high levels of pollution.</p>
        <p>Concern over "the war of resources" was voiced by Perdita Huston, an American writer on women in development. Noting that most natural resources are found in the third world, particularly in the south, she warned that "the world is heading for a real south-north confrontation."</p>
        <p>But Ms. Maathai, founder of Kenya's Green Belt tree-planting movement, cautioned, "It's easy to accuse the north, but they have brothers in the south who make it possible to exploit our resources." She said that members of local power elites must be made aware of "threats to all forms of life, even the butterflies."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
