<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ACID RAIN REPORT CONFIRMS CONCERN</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="381954"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DA1438F935A3575AC0A966958260" item-length="861" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ACID RAIN REPORT CONFIRMS CONCERN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Nearing the end of a 10-year study, a preliminary Federal report today confirmed many scientists' concerns about the environmental damage caused by acid rain, but concluded that the problem is not of crisis proportions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Nearing the end of a 10-year study, a preliminary Federal report today confirmed many scientists' concerns about the environmental damage caused by acid rain, but concluded that the problem is not of crisis proportions.</p>
        <p>Major Conclusions</p>
        <p>In its final draft report, made public today, the study group found that scientific evidence ''clearly demonstrated'' these conclusions:</p>
        <p>* Aquatic life is being damaged by acid rain in about 10 percent of eastern lakes and streams. But much of the damage is probably caused when snow melts in the spring, pouring concentrated amounts of acid water into the streams.</p>
        <p>* Visibility is being reduced in the eastern United States and in some metropolitan areas of the West.</p>
        <p>* Acid rain is contributing to the erosion and corrosion of stone and metal structures.</p>
        <p>* Acid rain is reducing the ability of red spruce trees at high altitudes to withstand the stress caused by cold temperatures.</p>
        <p>The study group, made up of representatives from government agencies, also found evidence of a number of other effects, including the probability that the pollutants that cause acid rain may be causing respiratory illness and other health effects in humans.</p>
        <p>While the group found that ''the majority of North American forests are healthy,'' its computer projections also found that acid rain may produce nutrient deficiencies that would lead to forest decline in the decades ahead.It also found that acid rain may be contributing to the decline of sugar maples in some areas of eastern Canada, although the maple problem is related to ''localized soil nutrient deficiencies.''</p>
        <p>Key Sources of Emissions</p>
        <p>The report confirmed that emissions of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxides, many of them originating at coal-fired power plants in the Midwest, are, as scientists have long believed, the source of acid precipitation - acidic rain, snow, fog and dry particles. Ozone, a pollutant formed in the lower atmosphere when volatile chemicals from auto exhausts and other sources react with sunlight, also contributes to the damage attributed to acid rain, the report said.</p>
        <p>At a news briefing today, members of the study group said that the findings provide a firmer basis for policy making. But they conceded that the study, which cost $537 million to prepare, left a number of important questions unanswered, including the economic cost of acid rain damage.</p>
        <p>James R. Mahoney, director of the program, said that the findings were surrounded by ''considerable uncertainty.''</p>
        <p>But he also said that the work of the program ''significantly reduced the scientific uncertainties about acidic deposition processes and effects.'' ''Many, but not all, of the scientific consensus views reported in the early 1980's have been supported by more recent studies,'' he said, ''but the more extreme views in both directions expressed by some individual scientists and in some of the media have been rendered unlikely to be correct.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Mahoney said that energy conservation should be first of the list of permanent measures to be taken to resolve the long-term problem of acid rain.</p>
        <p>Reactions Are Mixed</p>
        <p>Industry groups said the report showed that damage from acid rain was less than feared and that there was no need to rush into expensive control measures.</p>
        <p>Thomas R. Kuhn, president of the Edison Electric Institute, an association of privately owned electric utilities, said, ''The most compelling results of the study point out that damage from acid rain is much less than we feared in the late 1970's and early 1980's.''</p>
        <p>Environmentalists said the report included little that was new and made little difference in terms of policy.</p>
        <p>David Hawkins, a lawyer and air pollution expert for the Natural Resources Defense Council, said that ''President Bush was wise not to wait'' for the report to formulate an acid rain proposal.</p>
        <p>''Little comes out of it that we didn't know before we started,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Among the unanswered questions, Mr. Hawkins said, are the long-term effects on forests and the details of health risks.</p>
        <p>''Our reaction is that this is a very expensive exercise in documenting the obvious,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The final report will be made public in the next few months after the public has a chance to comment on the draft.</p>
        <p>Eileen B. Claussen, the E.P.A. representative on the panel, said that while the report had not definitively cleared up all the issues, it underscored the need for the acid rain control legislation proposed by President Bush. That legislation would cut sulfur dioxide emissions by 10 million tons, nearly half of current levels.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
