<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene;   Global Warming: Look or Leap?</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="326580"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ECONOMIC ADVISERS, COUNCIL OF</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ECONOMIC SCENE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DF1730F937A25751C0A966958260" item-length="793" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene;   Global Warming: Look or Leap?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: FOR George Bush the candidate, global warming was hot stuff - not as critical to the nation's future, perhaps, as ending prison furloughs for murderers, but near the top of the list of issues that mattered to the quiche and Volvo crowd.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: FOR George Bush the candidate, global warming was hot stuff - not as critical to the nation's future, perhaps, as ending prison furloughs for murderers, but near the top of the list of issues that mattered to the quiche and Volvo crowd.</p>
        <p>FOR George Bush the candidate, global warming was hot stuff - not as critical to the nation's future, perhaps, as ending prison furloughs for murderers, but near the top of the list of issues that mattered to the quiche and Volvo crowd.</p>
        <p>For George Bush the President, global warming is another of the universe's great mysteries, worthy of careful study but not precipitous response. Indeed, in deference to those who believe the globe may even be cooling, Mr. Bush now discreetly refers to the issue of ''climate change.''</p>
        <p>This transformation has been widely reported as an ideological victory for John Sununu, the President's conservative guru. But it also represents a technocratic victory for President Bush's Council of Economic Advisers, and in particular for one council member, Richard Schmalensee, an expert on regulation from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. The council's annual report, published last week, offers the economist's case for looking a while longer before we leap.</p>
        <p>In a bow to Mr. Sununu, a former nuclear engineer, the report notes that computer forecasts of warming necessarily turn on primitive assumptions about atmospheric dynamics. It is even conceivable that the ''greenhouse effect,'' caused by the accumulation of atmospheric pollutants that trap solar energy, will be more than offset by cooling caused by increased cloud cover.</p>
        <p>But the council's views carry the most credibility on the council's own turf. The economic burden imposed by a temperature increase, the report says, may be relatively modest, while the costs of containing the greenhouse-effect pollutants over the next century may prove extraordinarily high. Increased summer temperatures could directly affect health. But while ''the average temperature differential between New York City and Atlanta is as large as the most extreme predictions of warming,'' the report notes, ''there is no evidence that Atlanta's warmer climate creates a greater health risk than New York's.''</p>
        <p>Higher temperatures are likely, however, to reduce overall agricultural productivity. According to the Department of Agriculture, the net costs worldwide of a doubling of carbon dioxide, the primary greenhouse gas, would run from $35 billion to $170 billion annually.</p>
        <p>That is a lot of money. But it amounts to just 1 percent of current world income. And as the council argues, it is in the same ball park as the costs of Government regulations that now distort food production and reduce its total value. To put it another way, freer markets in agriculture, the council suggests, could more than offset greenhouse-effect losses.</p>
        <p>On the other side of the ledger, controlling carbon dioxide emissions would be no small undertaking. There is no practical way to trap carbon emissions from smokestacks or tailpipes. And according to one study cited by the council, the energy conservation needed to reduce carbon dioxide output by 20 percent in the United States over the next 110 years would cost from $800 billion to $3.6 trillion.</p>
        <p>Nor, the council notes, would that titanic conservation effort be worth much if the rest of the world did not follow suit. Europeans and Japanese, who are less addicted to fossil fuels than Americans, may be ready to make the sacrifice. But developing countries, most notably China, are not about to slow industrialization to keep Boston cool or spare Iowa from drought.</p>
        <p>Is the council right to be so cautious? While it is hard to find an economist who believes the benefits of slowing global warming exceed the costs, many economically sophisticated environmentalists still believe many anti-greenhouse measures are worth it in any case.</p>
        <p>One class of extremely potent greenhouse gases, the chlorofluorocarbons (CFC's) used primarily in refrigerators and air-conditioners, are also responsible for most damage to the ozone layer. The United States is already committed to ending CFC production gradually to forestall a worldwide epidemic of skin cancer. Why not buy a little extra insurance against global warming, environmentalists argue, by accelerating the phase-out?</p>
        <p>Then there is the issue of energy conservation. Some forms of carbon-controlling conservation, almost everyone agrees, would be extremely expensive. But other measures - for example, efficiency improvements in home appliances and commercial lighting - would probably save more in electricity bills than they would cost in new equipment.</p>
        <p>The council accepts in principle the idea that some anti-warming initiatives could be justified on unrelated merits. The challenge for the Bush Administration will be to translate those principles into policy - to stop looking at global warming as a yes-or-no question and look for cheap ways to exploit the maybes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
