<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After a Near-Perfect Flight, Shuttle Is Readied for Return</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="390128"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCOVERY (SPACE SHUTTLE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE SHUTTLE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D91F3BF933A25753C1A966958260" item-length="521" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After a Near-Perfect Flight, Shuttle Is Readied for Return</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla., Oct. 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The five astronauts of the space shuttle Discovery prepared today to return to Earth on Wednesday, ending a four-day mission that is being hailed as one of the smoothest flights ever.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The five astronauts of the space shuttle Discovery prepared today to return to Earth on Wednesday, ending a four-day mission that is being hailed as one of the smoothest flights ever.</p>
        <p>The five astronauts of the space shuttle Discovery prepared today to return to Earth on Wednesday, ending a four-day mission that is being hailed as one of the smoothest flights ever.</p>
        <p>''This flight is probably as close to perfect as we are likely to get,'' Ron Dittemore, a flight director, said at a news conference today.</p>
        <p>From the time of liftoff on Saturday and the deployment of the Ulysses spacecraft on its solar research mission, officials said, the shuttle has given flight controllers nothing to worry about - no malfunctions, no leaks or worrisome instrument readings.</p>
        <p>The Discovery is scheduled to glide to a landing at Edwards Air Force Base in California at 9:57 A.M., Eastern daylight time. Weather at the desert base is expected to be favorable. #1.7 Million Miles Away The Ulysses spacecraft continued to speed away from Earth, bound for Jupiter and then into a wide-ranging orbit of the Sun. Officials said the craft is already 1.7 million miles from Earth, with all systems functioning normally.</p>
        <p>In their final day in orbit, the astronauts stowed their gear and conducted a test firing of the jet thrusters that the shuttle will depend on for orienting itself in the plunge through the atmosphere for the landing. No problems were encountered.</p>
        <p>Among the scientific and engineering experiments the astronauts worked on today was the operation of instruments for measuring Earth's damaged ozone layer in the upper atmosphere. The measurements were being recorded for analysis after the mission.</p>
        <p>The primary purpose is to compare data from the shuttle instruments with measurements by similar instruments on three weather satellites, which are the source of most studies of ozone degradation caused by chemical pollutants. Scientists hope the calibration tests will assure the most accurate measurements possible for the detection of ozone trends.</p>
        <p>The astronauts also operated an experiment to study how the genetic material in the cells of plant roots responds to the virtual absence of gravity in space flight. The experiment was developed by Dr. Abraham D. Krikorian, a biologist at the State University of New York at Stony Brook. One purpose is to learn how to grow crops for food on long-duration space missions.</p>
        <p>Fire Set in Cabin</p>
        <p>On Sunday, the crew deliberately started a fire in the shuttle cabin. The blaze was safely contained in a metal chamber, where paper was ignited and observed by cameras and other instruments. Scientists want to know how fast fire burns and how hot it gets in the spaceship environment.</p>
        <p>The studies are considered essential to improving the safety aboard shuttles and in designing the proposed Freedom space station. Astronauts had a close call last year on the shuttle Columbia when a facsimile machine short-circuited, sending sparks and smoke into the crew cabin.</p>
        <p>The astronauts aboard the Discovery are Capt. Richard N. Richard, the mission commander, and Capt. William M. Shepherd, both of the Navy; Lieut Col. Robert D. Cabana, the pilot, of the Marine Corps; Comdr. Bruce E. Melnick of the Coast Guard, and Maj. Thomas D. Akers of the Air Force.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
