<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Editorial Notebook;   Mr. Bush and America's Greens</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="368479"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">HOUSTON (TEX)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Houston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDD103FF936A25754C0A966958260" item-length="629" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Editorial Notebook;   Mr. Bush and America's Greens</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush's next summit meeting might well be a cozy little chat in the Oval Office with a handful of environmental leaders. There's much common ground between them. But one would never know that from the poisonous and sometimes silly rhetoric that filled the air during last week's economic summit meeting in</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush's next summit meeting might well be a cozy little chat in the Oval Office with a handful of environmental leaders. There's much common ground between them. But one would never know that from the poisonous and sometimes silly rhetoric that filled the air during last week's economic summit meeting in</p>
        <p>President Bush's next summit meeting might well be a cozy little chat in the Oval Office with a handful of environmental leaders. There's much common ground between them. But one would never know that from the poisonous and sometimes silly rhetoric that filled the air during last week's economic summit meeting in Houston.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists from seven nations descended on Texas like boll weevils to monitor their governments' actions. The Americans, in particular, had reason to be supremely disappointed at Mr. Bush's reluctance to embrace even a modest strategy for limiting emissions of carbon dioxide that could cause a catastrophic warming of the earth's climate.</p>
        <p>But they had no reason to engage in the hyperbole attributed to Jay Hair, the moderate president of the National Wildlife Federation. ''Bush's efforts at balance, compromise and consensus building,'' he cried, ''are killing the world.'' Not to be outdone in the bombast sweepstakes, the ever-competitive Mr. Bush retorted that he wasn't out to win ''brownie points'' with environmentalists. Nor would he be swayed by ''extremists,'' or seduced by ''radical positions'' that would ''throw a lot of American men and women out of jobs.''</p>
        <p>The childishness of all this is self-evident. It's hard to imagine President Bush waking up and saying, ''Barbara, let's go out and mess up the earth today''; equally hard to imagine Mr. Hair gleefully calculating the number of families he could impoverish by saving the spotted owl.</p>
        <p>What makes this backbiting dangerous is that it blocks serious discussion of very complex questions. Environmental issues are never easy; their solution is rarely cost-free. They require hard choices between environmental protections the voters obviously want and the economic growth many Americans are loath to abandon. And that requires a maximum of care and a minimum of cant. Mr. Bush has shown himself capable of both. His clean air bill, though greatly improved by the environmentalists, was patiently conceived.</p>
        <p>His recent decision to ban coastal drilling, taken after long study, was a sensible bow to the environmentalists who argued that the oil was not worth the risk. It was also a good example of the ''balance, compromise and consensus building'' that Mr. Hair finds so distasteful.</p>
        <p>Conversely, given an opportunity to strike a balance between jobs and nature in the spotted owl controversy, Mr. Bush responded with pained indifference, threatening to change the endangered species law that had dumped the problem on his desk in the first place.</p>
        <p>His vision on global warming seems even more cramped. Chancellor Helmut Kohl of West Germany asked the President to cut harmful emissions by 25 percent over the next 15 years. John Sununu, the White House chief of staff, screamed that any such plan would threaten America's sovereignty and plunge it into depression. This ignored the findings of tough-minded economists like Yale's William D. Nordhaus, who argues in the latest Economist that a 20 percent cut can be achieved at very little cost to annual economic growth.</p>
        <p>Even so, with Mr. Bush in the White House, America's greens at least have somebody to work with. That's more than they had before. Between 1980 and 1988 the White House was occupied by a man who wanted to drill everywhere, thought that acid rain was a figment of some crazed Canadian's imagination and blamed ''killer trees'' for global warming.</p>
        <p>The time ought to be ripe for sensible debate on the competing demands of the environment and energy. While perpetual dissatisfaction is the natural state of any self-respecting environmentalist, caterwauling doesn't help. Neither does a petulant President who keeps threatening to pick up his bat and ball and go home.</p>
        <p>ROBERT B. SEMPLE Jr.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
