<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>American Politics Loses Way As Polls Supplant Leadership</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Trouble With Politics: Running vs. Governing - First of four articles." name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="335828"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1984</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ORESKES, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MONDALE, WALTER F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DC153FF93BA25750C0A966958260" item-length="3705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>American Politics Loses Way As Polls Supplant Leadership</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL ORESKES, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ORESKES, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As America's democratic visions and values seem to triumph around the world, an unhappy consensus has emerged at home that domestic politics has become so shallow, mean and even meaningless that it is failing to produce the ideas and leadership needed to guide the United States in a rapidly changing world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As America's democratic visions and values seem to triumph around the world, an unhappy consensus has emerged at home that domestic politics has become so shallow, mean and even meaningless that it is failing to produce the ideas and leadership needed to guide the United States in a rapidly changing world.</p>
        <p>As America's democratic visions and values seem to triumph around the world, an unhappy consensus has emerged at home that domestic politics has become so shallow, mean and even meaningless that it is failing to produce the ideas and leadership needed to guide the United States in a rapidly changing world.</p>
        <p>''We've tended to trivialize issues to the point where meaningful debate has become almost impossible,'' Representative Mickey Edwards of Oklahoma, the chairman of the House Republican Policy Committee, said in a recent interview.</p>
        <p>Former Vice President Walter F. Mondale said, ''We've got a kind of politics of irrelevance, of obscurantism, that is more prevalent than in any time I can recall.'' Politicians think the problem has only deepened since his disastrous effort to talk about tax increases in the 1984 Presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>Crippling Superstructure</p>
        <p>This unhappiness about modern politics is more than mere nostalgia for some idyllic past that never was. Politicians in both parties say government is being crippled by a new superstructure of politics that makes ideas harder to discuss and exalts public opinion over leadership.</p>
        <p>This is a time when the two basic tenets of American government for nearly half a century -the New Deal and military containment of the Soviet Union - no longer hold, when the end of the Cold War has left struggling democracies across the once-Communist world and fundamental questions at home about the need for a military budget of $300 billion. But the American political system is unable even to define and debate critical questions, let alone resolve them.</p>
        <p>As the United States searches for leadership on problems from stagnant labor productivity to soaring health care costs, a Congressman is warned by his political consultant not to make a speech calling for a huge cut in the military budget because he would be moving ahead of public opinion. As use of foreign oil rises again, the political system has abandoned even discussion of nuclear power as an alternative to pollution-producing fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>In the past, when a President failed to seize the initiative, Congress often tried to. But now both ends of Pennsylvania Avenue seem immobilized by a politics of avoidance, where poll takers and advertising producers are more influential than economists or engineers.</p>
        <p>Four Chief Fears of Politicians</p>
        <p>Instead of responding to changes in the world, the officials elected to lead the nation say they live each day in fear of the four horsemen of modern politics: televised attacks by their opponents, intense personal scrutiny by the press, cynicism on the part of the public and the need to raise huge sums to buy television time to combat the attacks, scrutiny and cynicism.</p>
        <p>None of these problems is altogether new. But politicians say their combined impact, and particularly the force of television on both politics and on the culture in general, have reinforced each other to derail the wheels of Government.</p>
        <p>Representative David R. Obey, Democrat of Wisconsin, a veteran legislator respected in both parties as a student of the institutions of government, described the problem this way: ''When the main question in a member's mind every time he votes is, 'What kind of a 30-second spot are they going to make out of this vote?' then truly the ability of the political system to make complicated and tough decisions in the long-range interest of the United States is atomized.''</p>
        <p>Trivialization. Atomization. Paralysis. These words have become the descriptive vocabulary on which members of both parties draw to describe the state of politics and government in America. The Democrats blame President Bush for crippling budget talks with his campaign-driven ''read my lips'' tax policy. But John H. Sununu, who helped orchestrate Mr. Bush's 1988 campaign, is equally unhappy now as he sees from his post as White House chief of staff that ''sound bite'' politics has made lawmakers, as he put it, less ''willing to take innovative stands or distinct positions or stand on principle.''</p>
        <p>The political fear of tampering with benefits for the elderly, which many lawmakers feel is where the Government could save money, was revealed in a joke making the rounds of the Republican cloakroom on Capitol Hill after a proposal to eliminate the deficit by cutting Social Security cost-of-living increases, among other things. ''Social Security is the third rail of American politics,'' went the joke. ''Touch it and you die.''</p>
        <p>Representative Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri, the majority leader of the House and a 1988 Democratic Presidential candidate, tried last week to make a partisan issue out of what he said was President Bush's failure of leadership in foreign policy. The President, Mr. Gephardt said, is doing nothing to explain the changes in the world to the American people, who remain uncertain and confused.</p>
        <p>Democrats Face Position Troubles</p>
        <p>Many Republicans concede that Mr. Bush has offered what Kevin Phillips, the Republican analyst, describes as ''a follow-up Presidency,'' evidencing little creativity on either making foreign policy or solving social problems.</p>
        <p>But both Democrats and Republican agree with Mr. Phillips's conclusion that there has been, in his words, a larger political failure, a general ''cerebral atrophy'' among opinion leaders and an inability by the Democrats to state their positions in any way that forces the Republicans to respond.</p>
        <p>''Europe is about to establish a truly integrated trading system with major consequences for our own economy,'' a plaintive Mr. Obey said in a recent speech. ''Japanese industries are challenging America's for world economic leadership. Are not these challenges, along with the challenge of homelessness, rootlessness and second-rate educational performance sufficiently profound to demand a vigorous, honest and substantive debate between and within both parties about how they should be met? Is American politics so brain-dead that we are reduced to having political shysters manipulate symbols?''</p>
        <p>There was considerable uneasiness on Capitol Hill when the most eloquent statement of the nation's role in the post-Cold War world came not from one of the elected representatives of the American people, but from a playwright and former Communist political prisoner, Vaclav Havel. Addressing a joint session in his new job as President of Czechoslovakia, Mr. Havel put it this way:</p>
        <p>''As long as people are people, democracy in the full sense of the word will always be no more than an ideal. One may approach it as one would a horizon, in ways that may be better or worse, but it can never be fully attained.</p>
        <p>''In this sense you, too, are merely approaching democracy. You have thousands of problems of all kinds, as other countries do. But you have one great advantage: You have been approaching democracy uninterrupted for more than 200 years.''</p>
        <p>How would this thoughtful and subtle man fare in an election here?</p>
        <p>''How much money does he have?'' replied Representative Bill Thomas, a California Republican who is one of his party's most outspoken critics of the way politics are practiced in the United States. ''Which consultant does he have? And is he willing to shave his mustache? Issues are not the problem, son. We're talking image. If you've got $2 million I can guarantee it.''</p>
        <p>Cynicism by citizens toward politicians is hardly new. What is striking is the unanimity among the consumers and practitioners of politics, and how the practitioners, even as they bemoan the process they foster, are feeding the cynicism back to the consumers.</p>
        <p>One measure of the general concern is that more than a score of institutions, including groups like the Ford Foundation and the American Bar Association, have undertaken studies based on the belief that American democracy is not working the way it should.</p>
        <p>Range of Possible Improvements</p>
        <p>Across the country, in speeches, symposiums, reports, as well as scores of interviews, a wide range of possible improvements have been offered, from lowering the remaining voter registration barriers to giving candidates free television time.</p>
        <p>A group of present and former elected officials, including former Senators Barry Goldwater, the Arizona Republican, and William Proxmire, the Wisconsin Democrat, have organized what they call the Center for National Independence in Politics. Its purpose is to provide voters with impartial information on candidates and their positions on issues to counteract trivial or negative campaigns.</p>
        <p>No doubt some of the state of American politics is simply that the tides of history are running faster elsewhere. ''We are in a sorting-out period,'' said Representative Newt Gingrich of Georgia, the Republican whip, ''in which the Republicans and the conservative movement are trying to figure out what phase two is'' after President Ronald Reagan. As for the Democrats, he added, they ''are trying to figure out how they create a new start.''</p>
        <p>Sense of Alarm and Dismay</p>
        <p>There is also a view that the nation will again awake when confronted with some crisis. But among politicians working in the world of today, a sense of alarm, dismay and disgust pervades. Representative Dan Rostenkowski, the Illinois Democrat who is chairman of the Ways and Means Committee, says he was motivated by sheer frustration at the budget deficit deadlock when he proposed his plan of tax increases, spending cuts and spending freezes last week.</p>
        <p>The Administration hinted it might talk about taxes. But politics are so poisoned these days that Democrats responded as if invited for a walk on an ice-crusted lake.</p>
        <p>Such suspicions contribute to the sour mood in national politics. There is the liberal legislator who complains that even other Democrats fear that talking about deep military spending cuts will lead them to be labeled as weak; there is the conservative law clerk who says he is afraid to publish law review articles because they will be used to attack him later.</p>
        <p>The Republican Party chairman, Lee Atwater, widely regarded as a popularizer of slash-and-burn political tactics, says the real problem is a public attitude that can be summed up in three words: ''Bull permeates everything.''</p>
        <p>The System</p>
        <p>Bogged Down In Big Business</p>
        <p>The American system was not designed for effeciency, with its diffusion of power and its checks and balances. The question is, Has a new force been added that has overwhelmed the balancing mechanisms?</p>
        <p>Winning elections has become a business, a big business with professional associations and magazines, where volunteers have been replaced by computer-assisted polling, the pamphlet by the television spot. This has driven up the cost of politics sharply. More than half a billion dollars will be spent on races for the House and Senate this year, nearly a tenfold increase over 1974. The cost of running for governor, state legislature or even city council has also soared.</p>
        <p>A Republican consultant, Don Sipple, warns that Washington is now the seat of a ''political-industrial complex,'' a play on President Dwight D. Eisenhower's warning about the dangers of a ''military-industrial complex.''</p>
        <p>Political dialogue and decisions are made up of the actions, large and small, of thousands of independent political figures. The intimidating and expensive quality of modern politics has made each of them a little more cautious, politicans say. When each small decision to be careful instead of controversial is added together, they say, the sum total is a major impact on political debate.</p>
        <p>System Called Money-Driven</p>
        <p>''It tends to homogenize the process,'' said Mickey Kantor, a lawyer who has long been active in California and national Democratic Party politics. ''It tends to make it money-driven. It takes the ideology out of it. It stifles creativity and strong stands, all of which is not good for the country.''</p>
        <p>George J. Mitchell of Maine, the Senate majority leader, says the flow of campaign money ''tends to keep you locked in to your views.''</p>
        <p>On Capitol Hill, stories abound about how the professional techniques of modern politics discourage government action and even debate, or lead to ill-conceived action. ''When it comes to dealing with the budget,'' Robert Strauss, the former Democratic national chairman, said in Senate testimony last month, ''the political process has become somewhere between timid and irrelevant.''</p>
        <p>Representative Les AuCoin, Democrat of Oregon, offered an example of how the new breed of political professionals discourages debate. He said he drafted a speech in which he wanted to call for a 50 percent cut in the military budget to produce money for domestic needs. He sent the speech to a well-known political consultant with whom he talks frequently. The consultant wrote back that his reaction to the speech was very negative.</p>
        <p>''You should know you are way ahead of public opinion on this,'' the consultant wrote.</p>
        <p>'A Safer Middle Ground'</p>
        <p>Mr. AuCoin, who has not yet made the speech, said, ''He was urging me to a safer middle ground so I wouldn't run the risk of having my chin out too far.''</p>
        <p>The science of public opinion measuring is being misused, Mr. AuCoin said, ''to lock you in where you are today rather than to lead society to where you think you ought to be.''</p>
        <p>Public-opinion measurement has become a tool not only of modern politics but of government. Proponents of polling say this makes democracy more democratic. But the public is often not aware of the details of problems, said Senator James A. McClure, Republican of Idaho, and polls are measuring emotional response, not thought-out views.</p>
        <p>Harry Boyte, director of the Hubert H. Humphrey Institute of Public Affairs at the University of Minnesota, said: ''We have public opinion now, which is people's private reflexes. But we don't have public judgment. So everything is broken down into market segments. You have no public process.''</p>
        <p>Senator McClure said this is apparent in efforts to grapple with complex subjects like clean air legislation. ''If it causes 10 deaths in the next 700,000 years, we have to stop it,'' Mr. McClure said, characterizing the distorted debate on environmental pollution. ''That's not rational. It's not intelligent. But it responds to emotion.''</p>
        <p>It is becoming increasingly difficult to get Congress ''to make balanced judgment on good information,'' said Senator McClure, who is retiring after 25 years on Capitol Hill in frustration over what he calls the new breed of ''wet-finger politicians,'' who he said spend more time sampling the political winds than reading policy papers.</p>
        <p>The Public Attitude</p>
        <p>Involvement: Why Bother?</p>
        <p>One problem with the intense measuring of public opinion is finding out how sour it is, a disenchantment that can be traced to Vietnam and Watergate. In tracking the public mood and taking positions and packaging advertising based on that mood, politicians and their consultants are reinforcing the disenchantment. This cynicism has become a closed loop.</p>
        <p>No one defines this loop better than Mr. Atwater, who as chairman of the Republican party, is the nation's best-placed political consultant.</p>
        <p>He summed up, in an interview in his office at the Republican National Headquarters here, his view that the negativeness of current politics flows from a deeper discontent in the public mood this way:</p>
        <p>''First and foremost I would say that the public's attitude about politics is very much in concert with their attitude about all institutions. If you want to look at a solid trend for the last 15 or 20 years, it is that the American people are cynical and turned off about all the institutions, and politics is one. It's only one of them.</p>
        <p>''Bull permeates everything. In other words, my theory is that the American people think politics and politicians are full of baloney. They think the media and journalists are full of baloney. They think organized religion is full of baloney. They think big business is full of baloney. They think big labor is full of baloney. To single out politics is making a grave mistake in terms of understanding attitudes of Americans.''</p>
        <p>Institutions on Decline</p>
        <p>Peter Hart, a Democratic poll taker, said that the cynicism of the last 30 years has deepened into a disconnection of individuals from politics.</p>
        <p>The disconnection of the public can be seen as well, over the last three decades, in sharp declines in the sort of organizations that used to serve as intermediaries between the public and government - political parties, churches, labor unions - as well as in voting.</p>
        <p>Polls and on-the-street interviews frequently turn up sentiments like those expressed by Twila Martinez, a 38-year-old San Franciscan. Ms. Martinez, who says she has evolved into a Republican, summarizes her generation's view of government and politics this way: ''It seems like another world to me. It goes on, it functions, but I don't feel like it really directly affects us.''</p>
        <p>The TV Influence</p>
        <p>Lay It All Out In 30 Seconds</p>
        <p>Television was originally viewed as a democratizing force. It did help break down party machines and let candidates speak directly to the electorate.</p>
        <p>Now another result is becoming clear. ''The rise of electronic media has had an effect on draining content out of campaigns,'' said Arthur Schlesinger Jr., the historian.</p>
        <p>Senator John C. Danforth, a Republican of Missouri, said, ''It has locked candidates into ridiculous positions because only ridiculous positions can be compacted into 30-second commercials.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sununu said, ''Both life style and technology has forced politics for the most part to condense its message and therefore to sharpen its focus and therefore to lose, if you will, some of the supporting detail that was part of the system when people were campaigning with pamphlets.''</p>
        <p>It Is Harder to Be Heard</p>
        <p>To make things worse, it is increasingly hard to be heard over the clatter of other information and entertainment and this, politicians say, pushes them to speak more loudly and harshly.</p>
        <p>''I tell you what you do in a campaign,'' said Mr. Atwater, sitting at his conference table in an interview a few weeks before it was discovered that he had a benign tumor in his brain. ''You get a table like this every morning at seven o'clock and spend an hour and a half figuring out what you're going to do to get on the news that night - to get in the news hole. What stunt you can pull that will give you 14 seconds of news hole.''</p>
        <p>The decline of political parties as the controlling force in campaigns has led to the rise of a new power: the news media. News coverage, especially on television, has become so influential in politics and government that Mr. Atwater says it ''drives the system now.''</p>
        <p>Political consultants and politicians have little patience with journalists who complain about the lack of substance or the rise of personal attacks in politics. Even when politicians try to talk about issues, the press ignores them, assert politicians from Mr. Sununu to Senator Mitchell.</p>
        <p>Tone of News Darkens</p>
        <p>Thomas Patterson, professor of political science at the Maxwell School of Government, said the tone and content of news coverage of politics had darkened dramatically over the last 30 years. In the 1960 campaign, 60 percent of the coverage of the Presidential candidates in Time and Newsweek was favorable, a study by Professor Patterson found. In 1988, only 30 percent was favorable. The same trend could be found among newspapers and television.</p>
        <p>''Increasingly, the thread running through it is, 'There is something wrong with the campaign; there is something wrong with the candidate,' '' Professor Patterson said.</p>
        <p>The something wrong now includes subjects previously off limits. Many journalists defend their interest, saying private behavior can reveal public character. But Judith Lichtenberg, a professor at the University of Maryland, challenges this. ''The politics of character tend to drive out the politics of substance,'' she said in a paper for the Joan Shorenstein Barone Center on Press, Politics and Public Policy at Harvard.</p>
        <p>The Theodore White school of political reporting, with its focus behind the curtain of campaigns, innovative when he wrote the first ''Making of the President'' book in 1960, is now the norm. An old-style stenographic reporting of issue statements is viewed as intellectually uncritical by journalists, particularly the generation that lived through the official deceit of the Watergate scandals. But the politicians say the press, by its focus on mechanics and character, is as responsible as anyone for the negative and trivial quality of political discourse.</p>
        <p>''By lifting the curtain the media fosters the view that campaigns are simply a game and a deceitful game at that,'' said Gary Orren, a student of campaign coverage at Harvard's Kennedy School of Government.</p>
        <p>Mr. Orren said: ''I don't think it's any wonder that the public wasn't particularly troubled at all when the issues of the Bush Administration and the tone of the Bush Administration right after they were inagurated bore no resemblance to the issues and tone of the campaign waged in the fall. The public has learned that the campaign is a charade. They've been taught that.'' Surveying the political scene this year, there is every sign that the problems will only deepen in 1990. The tax issue is already becoming an indicator of the tolerance of candidates and the public for policy debate.</p>
        <p>In Texas, a state with deep fiscal problems, the primary election Tuesday was preceded by a campaign dominated by big money on the Republican side and by personal bashing and innuendo on the Democratic side. The closest thing to a policy debate was between the two candidates who each insisted they would execute more criminals.</p>
        <p>The only real discussion of the state's financial problems came as candidates tripped over each other to promise they would not support an income tax. The question to be answered in the 1990 elections, said Mr. Sipple, the Republican consultant, is ''Does the electorate still want to be lied to about taxes?''</p>
        <p>NEXT: The effect on the politicians.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
