<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CRIME</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="363320"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STASIO, MARILYN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARRISON, COLIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHOPEN, BERNARD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COOK, THOMAS H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRANT, LINDA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">IRVINE, ROBERT</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BREAK AND ENTER (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">DESERT LOOK, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NIGHT SECRETS (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BLIND TRUST (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">GONE TO GLORY (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED6163AF937A15755C0A966958260" item-length="1159" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CRIME</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARILYN STASIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STASIO, MARILYN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: You wouldn't want to be in Peter Scattergood's loafers, despite their snazzy shine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: You wouldn't want to be in Peter Scattergood's loafers, despite their snazzy shine.</p>
        <p>You wouldn't want to be in Peter Scattergood's loafers, despite their snazzy shine.</p>
        <p>The 31-year-old assistant district attorney has been handed a sensational double murder case involving the Mayor of Philadelphia in Colin Harrison's BREAK AND ENTER (Crown, $17.95), but the poor guy is too distraught to concentrate. His wife has just walked out; his mother has cancer; the brother of a soon-to-be-convicted murderer is muttering threats on his life; and he's up to his fancy razor cut in major bills. An earnest and intelligent man of Quaker upbringing (who loves his work because in court ''you were allowed to fight''), Scattergood struggles to build a just case against the probable killer of the Mayor's nephew and the young man's girlfriend. But in his guilt and panic over losing his wife, he behaves so recklessly as to betray both the law and his own moral principles.</p>
        <p>In this intensely felt first novel, Mr. Harrison heroically balances the philosophical drama of a man's crisis of faith with the puzzle-narrative of a legal whodunit. The author's style veers from the wild to the woolly, with occasional flashes of the amazing, as in the hero's appraisal of a veteran attorney's perfectionism as ''the by-product of a mind that worked like a man painting a white room white who never believes he has finished.'' The vitality of such thought and such language is often feverish, but never dull.</p>
        <p>*  *  *</p>
        <p>''Crazy people lived in this land,'' says the Nevada private eye Jack Ross in THE DESERT LOOK (Mysterious Press, $17.95). ''I felt right at home.'' Besides being crazy, the desert rats in Bernard Schopen's atmospheric mysteries always have wonderful, bizarre tales to share with a good listener like Ross. The detective gets an earful here when he sets out to investigate the death of his mother, a Las Vegas showgirl who 30 years earlier was killed in a barroom brawl after she supposedly heisted a bundle of casino money and fled into the desert. In trying to clear her name, Ross wanders from the fleshpots of Vegas to desolate camps in the desert, collecting narrative scraps of lies and half-truths from the kind of people you wouldn't trust to hold your watch while you wash your hands.</p>
        <p>Among these mesmerizing, if untrustworthy, yarn spinners are some wild, flashy women. But the author's heart and literary skills are quickened primarily by ''aging solitary males . . . trapped in a tangle of other lives and yet isolated, unattached.'' The ones with the vacant ''desert look.'' Even as the thread of Mr. Schopen's twisted generational saga keeps getting buried in the particles of his sandstorm prose, the voices of these haunted men carry a long way in the thin, dry air.</p>
        <p>*  *  *</p>
        <p>Women and their unfathomable ways have always intrigued Frank Clemons, a New York private eye who began brooding on the feminine mystique in Thomas H. Cook's ''Sacrificial Ground,'' when, as a detective with the Atlanta police, he became obsessed with a female murder victim. In NIGHT SECRETS (Putnam, $19.95), Clemons hasn't lost his Southern accent or his tendency to romanticize women as creatures of mystery.</p>
        <p>True, the detective doesn't seem all that carried away with his well-paying day job, tracking the nervous young wife of an affluent businessman. One can't really fault him on that. Despite her twitchy behavior, the woman is a pallid character, and only a hopeless romantic like Clemons would fail to see what monkey business she's up to. He is enthralled, however, by the woman on his night case, a mysterious gypsy who has been arrested for a savage murder she may not have committed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cook tries to draw us into Clemons's woozy state of mind with luscious descriptions of this enigmatic beauty and dark hints of her true mission on earth. But aside from her many baleful looks and hissed threats at the hero, the woman is no great shakes as a conversationalist and the level of their communication remains fairly primitive. As always, the author's gritty cityscape maintains its melancholy charm; but he has written elsewhere with truer feeling about the inhabitants of these lonely streets.</p>
        <p>*  *  *</p>
        <p>Catherine Sayler runs such a squeaky-clean private investigations operation in San Francisco that sexist slobs like Mike Hammer and Sam Spade probably wouldn't be allowed in the door, even if they wiped their feet. The heroine of Linda Grant's BLIND TRUST (Scribners, $18.95) avoids messy murders, specializing instead in white-collar crimes of industrial espionage or bank fraud - like the case she takes on here for a bank vice president who suspects that an absent underling is planning to fiddle with the computer system and make off with $5 million in cash.</p>
        <p>Catherine delegates the research to her quota-perfect staff - two women, a black man, two (female, part-time) college students, two (male, freelance) film makers and an Asian legal counselor - and heads for the missing executive's hometown of Modesto. Here she is joined by her boyfriend, an ideally supportive lover who also cooks. There are likewise no flies on Catherine. She takes her vitamins, teaches aikido and on a walk in the woods ponders the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>Despite the plausible procedures and decent fieldwork performed by Catherine and her busy little helpers, all this righteousness throws a dull wash on the characters and their profession. And then there's the dialogue. ''You three were in Vietnam together,'' Catherine says to some garage mechanics. ''It must have been pretty rough.'' Try that line on Sam Spade, he'd kick the door in.</p>
        <p>*  *  *</p>
        <p>The ironic title of Robert Irvine's GONE TO GLORY (Thomas Dunne/St. Martin's, $16.95), the third in an unusual series set in the territory that remains of Brigham Young's once vast Mormon empire, refers to an abandoned coal-mining town where a renegade sect of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints has taken refuge. A place of Stygian gloom, its homes reduced to charred rubble from sulfurous fires burning below the ground, this eerie sanctuary inspires the bleakest sort of humor from Moroni Traveler, a Salt Lake City sleuth pointedly named for an angel.</p>
        <p>''A man shouldn't go to Glory on an empty stomach,'' says he, on his way up a 9,000-foot mountain to find out why someone would kill for this bit of hell. Especially someone like old Pepper Dalton, a local sports legend who wants to sell his stake in Glory so that he can buy a moth-eaten baseball club and bring it back to . . . well, glory.</p>
        <p>Aged men like Pepper and his would-be team manager, Hap Kilgore, are a weakness with Mr. Irvine's detective, who lives with his father and maintains an abiding interest in the paternalistic church he has renounced but not shaken. ''You can't mess with religion,'' Traveler's dad warns him, ''not in this state.'' He doesn't listen, of course, this angelic cynic who is as fascinated with the dreams of old men as we are with him.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
