<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Putting the Heat on Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="391831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="CONNECTICUT Q&amp;A: MARY M. MUSHINSKY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIERDEN, ANDI</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MUSHINSKY, MARY M (REPR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DE1630F937A25753C1A966958260" item-length="1510" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Putting the Heat on Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDI RIERDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RIERDEN, ANDI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: CONNECTICUT has become the first state in the country to pass legislation aimed at reducing the possibility of a global warming. Scientists have predicted that increased concentrations of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere from fossil-fuel emissions may alter the earth's climate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: CONNECTICUT has become the first state in the country to pass legislation aimed at reducing the possibility of a global warming. Scientists have predicted that increased concentrations of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere from fossil-fuel emissions may alter the earth's climate.</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT has become the first state in the country to pass legislation aimed at reducing the possibility of a global warming. Scientists have predicted that increased concentrations of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere from fossil-fuel emissions may alter the earth's climate.</p>
        <p>If that occurs, says the law's sponsor, State Representative Mary M. Mushinsky, Democrat of Wallingford, warmer temperatures would cause sea levels in Connecticut to rise, harming the state's wetlands and private wells along the coast. Air pollution would increase, and plant and animal life would also be threatened, she said.</p>
        <p>''There's very little leadership at the Federal level which acknowledges that global warming is a problem,'' said Ms. Mushinsky. ''Therefore it's up to the states to take action.'' The law, which went into effect on Oct. 1, changes the building code to require more energy-efficient construction, requires government purchase of fuel-efficient cars and energy-efficient state housing, sets new requirements that must be met before electric heat can be used in homes, sets state mass-transit goals and requires the planting of trees to offset emissions.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mushinsky, co-chairwoman of the legislature's Environment Committee, has also helped to sponsor mandatory recycling laws. She received a bachelor's degree in biology from Southern Connecticut State University in 1973 and is working toward a master's in liberal studies from Wesleyan University.</p>
        <p>In an interview at her home, she discussed the new global-warming law. Here are some excerpts from the conversation:</p>
        <p>Q. How would global warming affect Connecticut?</p>
        <p>A. Global warming could result in a rise in sea level that could take away 20 percent of the wetlands bordering the shoreline. Saltwater would seep into the aquifers and subsequently the wells of people living along the shore. The overall trend is that the atmosphere is loading up with carbon dioxide, and inevitably that will cause the temperature to go up, resulting in hotter weather and an unusually high number of days over 90.</p>
        <p>We could lose some of our tree species, like hemlock and sugar maple, as well as a number of animal species, such as turtles and cold-weather birds. The worst-case scenario, if the radical temperature changes happen, is that we'd get the equivalent of a glacier air change in 50 years, instead of 12,000 to 20,000 years, which would make it impossible for some animals and plants in the state to adjust.</p>
        <p>Another prediction is an aggravation of our already bad smog problem. We're already in violation of the Federal Clean Air Act because of our levels of auto emissions. And if temperatures start rising, you'll have this cooking effect on the atmospheric heat with the carbon dioxide, which will increase the pollution.</p>
        <p>Q. What are the major contributors to this problem?</p>
        <p>A. Mainly fossil-fuel consumption. About 26 percent of our carbon dioxide is from electric power plants and another 38 percent is from auto emissions. The rest is from industries, coal and oil plants, residences and office buildings. But transportation is the big one, and that's why we've been going after them.</p>
        <p>Q. How does the legislation address the transportation problem?</p>
        <p>A. It sets up several goals to increase the passenger-vehicle occupancy rate to 1.2 persons per car by the year 2000 and requires that the Department of Transportation come up with a strategy by next session to increase passenger vehicle rates to 1.25 by the year 2010.</p>
        <p>It also aims to increase the use of public transportation, so that at least 10 percent of all trips between home and work occur in cars occupied by more than one person by the year 2000. Right now, that rate is about 7 percent.</p>
        <p>We're trying to push the D.O.T. to promote public transit. Our perception is that they pretty much go with the status quo. If there's an increase in cars on the road, then they'll build more roads. But what we want them to do is try to get more people to switch from one form of transportation to another.</p>
        <p>We also established an advisory and watchdog group called the Connecticut Public Transportation Commission, which, in addition to watching the D.O.T., will make recommendations on disincentives to free parking. For example, as a legislator I'm able to park free. But if I had to pay for it, I'd be more encouraged to car pool or take public transportation. The other thing that they are looking at is off-peak transit services and urban loop shuttles. Those are van buses that pick people up from bus or train stations, then go from office building to office building to drop them off.</p>
        <p>Q. Does the law address ways to decrease car-fuel consumption?</p>
        <p>A. It sets fuel-efficiency standards for state-purchased vehicles. By 1993, cars must have a 29-miles-per-gallon rating. By 1997, they must have at least a 38-miles-per-gallon-rating and by 2000, at least a 45-miles-per-gallon rating. We're also requiring that the state consider buying cars that use alternative fuels, like propane, that are stored in a separate gas tank in the car, allowing you to switch back and forth from one tank to the other.</p>
        <p>I'm trying to get other states to pass the same bill, because if I can get big guys like New York and California, then Detroit will change their cars. Because we are such a small state, we don't have a lot of influence in the marketplace. But if the states can group together and require higher emissions controls, then Detroit won't have any choice.</p>
        <p>We're telling Detroit that right now we'll buy American, but only a few that can achieve a 29-miles-per-gallon rating. But by the year 2000, we're going to be buying foreign cars unless they do some shuffling. The state's always had a 'Buy American' policy, but at some point, you've got to take a stand on energy conservation and national security. And if buying U.S. cars means more fuel consumption and more oil crises like the one in Kuwait, then it's time Detroit got the message.</p>
        <p>Q. What about cutbacks in energy consumption for heating and air-conditioning?</p>
        <p>A. The act discourages the use of electric heat in buildings that are not properly insulated or built. If the Department of Housing uses electric heat as the primary heating source in new construction, those units must meet the requirements of the electric utilities energy-conservation incentive program, which gives a special electric rate if they have super-insulated the house to make it efficient. A new or substantially renovated private residence may not use all-electric heat unless they have been audited for energy efficiency. If they go ahead and build an all-electric heat building and they flunk the audit, then they'll be subjected to higher electric rates.</p>
        <p>After 1994, the state must also come up with ways of decreasing fossil-fuel consumption by promoting conservation, solar and other alternative energy sources when designing new buildings.</p>
        <p>Q. Because they absorb carbon dioxide, trees are apparently helpful in alleviating global warming. How does the law address this?</p>
        <p>A. It authorizes the Environmental Protection Commissioner to require applicants for air-discharge permits to provide tree or turf-grass planting to offset carbon-dioxide emissions from the discharge source. The permits can require that the amount of trees planted is equal to the amount of carbon-dioxide output.</p>
        <p>Q. Does the law provide any other disincentives?</p>
        <p>A. We've taken away the municipalities' ability to give tax breaks for multilevel parking garages, unless the garage is a necessary component of the mass-transit system - that is, unless it's set up to operate at a train station or around some other public-transit system.</p>
        <p>Q. Are there any incentives for so-called telecommuting?</p>
        <p>A. The act requires the Office of Policy and Management to compile a report by next session that will recommend ways companies could ease the fuel-consumption problem by allowing their employees to drive to work, say, four out of five days. On the day they work at home, they could use their computer or telephone. That's not only good for fuel efficiency, it's also good for parents with small children at home.</p>
        <p>Q. Is solar energy feasible in this climate?</p>
        <p>A. It is for hot-water heating. But solar energy is still a ways off. Ironically, about two weeks before Kuwait was invaded, Arco sold all of its solar technology to Japan. They were the only big solar energy player in the United States. So 5 or 10 years from now, we're going to be buying solar-run cars from the Japanese.</p>
        <p>Q. Has Iraq's invasion of Kuwait sparked an interest in the global warming issue?</p>
        <p>A. Yes, it has. The silver lining in the Kuwait crisis is that global warming is being looked at again from the standpoint of fuel security, the Federal Government is again looking into ways to reduce our dependence on foreign fuel, and into auto efficiency. Last year, it was a dead issue. Whether or not he realizes it, Saddam Hussein is a friend of energy conservation, because he is forcing us to look at those issues again.</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT Q&amp;A: MARY M. MUSHINSKY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
