<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Arm Twisting in Capital Is Just Short of Physical</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="388924"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="THE BUDGET AGREEMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOBBYING AND LOBBYISTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">RASKY, SUSAN F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DD173BF936A35753C1A966958260" item-length="1162" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Arm Twisting in Capital Is Just Short of Physical</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN F. RASKY, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RASKY, SUSAN F</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Wednesday night, Representative Ralph Regula was undecided about how to vote on the bipartisan budget compromise. This morning, his mind was made up: He was adamantly opposed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Wednesday night, Representative Ralph Regula was undecided about how to vote on the bipartisan budget compromise. This morning, his mind was made up: He was adamantly opposed.</p>
        <p>Wednesday night, Representative Ralph Regula was undecided about how to vote on the bipartisan budget compromise. This morning, his mind was made up: He was adamantly opposed.</p>
        <p>In between, the Ohio Republican got a taste of the White House approach to winning friends and influencing people. Mr. Regula had planned to impress some constituents last night by taking them to the Presidential box at the Kennedy Center for a performance. The reservations had been confirmed by the White House and his guests told where to show up. Late Wednesday afternoon, he received a telephone call from the White House Congressional liaison office asking his position on the budget plan. ''Leaning against,'' he replied. The White House ordered his tickets canceled. The White House chief of staff, John H. Sununu, approved the order.</p>
        <p>Tales of such tactics abounded in the Capital today as both the White House and the Congressional leadership scrambled for enough votes to pass the budget agreement. Democratic leaders met endlessly to devise strategies to mollify unhappy liberals and soothe the feelings of angry committee chairmen who sense that their turf has been violated by Congressional leaders and White House officials.</p>
        <p>Hit Where It Hurts</p>
        <p>But it was White House officials who set the hard-ball tone in a journey to Capitol Hill on Monday to brief Republicans on the budget plan that was announced in the White House Rose Garden on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sununu told the lawmakers not to be surprised if President Bush visited the districts of those who voted against the agreement and ''pointed his finger at them and looked them in the eye'' and said they had deserted their President and their country in an hour of need, said Republicans staff members who attended the meeting.</p>
        <p>Representative Carl D. Pursell, a Michigan Republican, rose from the audience to challenge Mr. Sununu. ''You don't help yourself or your cause'' with such threats, he said. Representative Bill Goodling, a Pennsylvania Republican, told his colleagues, ''I know George Bush, and he would never do anything like that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sununu replied, ''George Bush is a much nicer guy than I am.'' Where's the Carrot?  Representative Raymond J. McGrath, a Republican of Nassau County in New York, said he had received calls from the Secretary of Health and Human Services, Louis W. Sullivan, and the Treasury Secretary, Nicholas F. Brady, and that the Administration's lobbying approach seemed to be ''all sticks and no carrots.''</p>
        <p>''Brady told me, 'It's too bad you can't be with the President,' and then he said, 'If you think this is bad for New York, wait until you see the next package.' ''</p>
        <p>At least one Republican seemed to get soft soap rather than hard ball. Representative Michael G. Oxley, an Ohio Republican, received a commitment from Mr. Sununu to back the lawmaker's efforts to relax acid rain provisions in the clean air legislation awaiting final approval by Congress. ''It's not often that a relatively junior member gets an opportunity to use a little leverage,'' Mr. Oxley said.</p>
        <p>The only incentive Democratic leaders could offer their rank-and-file members was a promise that Representative Dan Rostenkowski of Illinois, who heads the House Ways and Means Committee, would endeavor to improve matters. Mr. Rostenkowski, who had been threatening to oppose the plan, joined the backers today and pledged to Democrats at a private meeting that his panel would do some adjusting of the tax provisions and Medicare program cuts that liberals find so objectionable.</p>
        <p>Tinkering With the Package</p>
        <p>Mr. Rostenkowski called President Bush on Wednesday evening to explain that the tax portion of the budget deal surely didn't accomplish what Mr. Bush had intended it to. ''I told him I didn't work for two and a half years on tax reform to have it all disintegrate, and that the taxes they agreed to in the summit would just create new loopholes,'' he said in an interview. He said the President replied, ''Danny, I don't want people not to pay taxes.''</p>
        <p>Asked whether that meant he had the President's approval to alter the budget agreement in his committee, Mr. Rostenkowski replied: ''He didn't give me any length or breadth or width. We'll have to see when it's done whether he bucks or buckles.''</p>
        <p>Confusion predominated in the House throughout the day, as leaders in both parties counted votes and kept coming up short. Under the compromise, Democratic and Republican leaders have pledged that they would deliver a majority of their members to support it so that neither party could make an issue of the spending cuts and tax increases in the November elections. In the office of the House Republican leader, Robert H. Michel of Illinois, the scene was barely controlled chaos as rumors flew that Democratic leaders might be willing to make a side deal with rebellious liberals in their own party and come up with enough extra votes to pass the budget even if the Republicans were unable to deliver a majority of their party members.</p>
        <p>Since all of the negotiations on the package were conducted in private, lobbyists have not had their usual opportunities to buttonhole lawmakers. But today they were out in force, swarming outside the House chamber to catch members as they entered to cast votes on other legislation.</p>
        <p>Robert, Not Richard</p>
        <p>Administration lobbyists, communicating with each other and the White House on cellular telephones, nearly got trampled in the crush and finally took up positions on the steps of the Capitol to get a first crack at the lawmakers. Sometimes it was hard to keep all the players straight.</p>
        <p>Representative Robert G. Torricelli, a liberal Democrat from New Jersey, frequently found himself being mistaken for the White House Budget Director, Richard G. Darman. The two men have little in common politically, but they do share a striking physical resemblance.</p>
        <p>''Some Administration lobbyist who must not get to the White House too often called out, ''Hi Dick,' and an elevator operator told me I did a great job in the budget summit,'' he said. ''I wonder if this happens to Darman.''</p>
        <p>Confusion about what's in the budget plan is also a problem. Representative Gary Ackerman, a Queens Democrat, said he found himself arguing on Wednesday night with a angry constituent about the proposed cuts in Medicare. The constitutent happened to be his own 71-year-old Uncle Morris, who suggested that his nephew find a way to cut more from military spending so that the Medicare program could be spared.</p>
        <p>Heat From Uncle Morris</p>
        <p>''I said, 'Uncle Morris, we're only talking about $6 a month on your premium,' '' Mr. Ackerman said.</p>
        <p>Uncle Morris was not mollified. In the next breath, he suggested that the United States should take more forceful military action in the Persian Gulf.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'But Uncle Morris, if we do that, there goes the money for your Medicare,' '' the Congressman said.</p>
        <p>Uncle Morris was not convinced, Mr. Ackerman said.</p>
        <p>THE BUDGET AGREEMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
