<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Region: Connecticut and Westchester;   The Problem of 'Sick-Building Syndrome'</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="375438"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OFFICE BUILDINGS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINDOWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHARLES, ELEANOR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Windows</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDB1339F931A2575BC0A966958260" item-length="1066" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Region: Connecticut and Westchester;   The Problem of 'Sick-Building Syndrome'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR CHARLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHARLES, ELEANOR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: SICK-BUILDING SYNDROME, a disorder that medical and environmental professionals say is widespread, but largely unregulated, refers to vague illnesses reported by people who work in large office buildings where the windows are inoperable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: SICK-BUILDING SYNDROME, a disorder that medical and environmental professionals say is widespread, but largely unregulated, refers to vague illnesses reported by people who work in large office buildings where the windows are inoperable.</p>
        <p>SICK-BUILDING SYNDROME, a disorder that medical and environmental professionals say is widespread, but largely unregulated, refers to vague illnesses reported by people who work in large office buildings where the windows are inoperable.</p>
        <p>While there are regulations addressing the issue in New York State, California, Canada and elsewhere here and abroad, Connecticut has been slow to act on the matter.</p>
        <p>State Representative Carl Schiessl, a Windsor Democrat, said that a bill dealing with the issue had been returned to the House Public Health Committee in 1988. Last year, said Mr. Schiessl, who is vice chairman of the panel, it was not returned to the floor because of ''the tight fiscal situation.'' He said a stronger bill will be introduced in January.</p>
        <p>While sealed windows do not by themselves cause problems, they do cut off immediate relief from poor air circulation. On the list of complaints are throat and eye irritation, coughs, headaches, fatigue, nausea, confusion and irritability - all relieved on leaving the premises.</p>
        <p>Cost-cutting by building managers is part of the problem. With increasing frequency they are shutting down vents that admit outside air into the ventilating systems. It is cheaper to recycle indoor air at a given temperature than cool or heat air from outdoors, but it results in the recirculation of dirty air throughout the building. In addition, filters that should be changed frequently are left in place for years, and unemptied water in air-handling systems turns into bacteria-infested slime.</p>
        <p>Studies done by the Aetna Insurance Company, which monitors air quality in the buildings it insures, show that 30 to 40 percent of them have indoor air-quality problems. When they fail to comply with Aetna standards their policies are canceled. Clean buildings may qualify for a lower premiums.</p>
        <p>''Once we make an initial evaluation and assume the risk of insuring a building,'' said Christopher Wiernicki, who is the manager of Aetna's environmental health unit in Hartford, ''we continue to make routine visits to determine that nothing could cause people to be sick and then have a claim.''</p>
        <p>Under a state mandate, insurance companies are required to cover a certain percentage of high-risk buildings that have been unable to get insurance in the marketplace. ''The premiums are considerably more expensive, providing an incentive to clean up the building,'' said Mr. Wiernicki.</p>
        <p>His unit, which has more than 500 engineers and industrial hygienists, also responds to calls for buildings with environmental problems whether Aetna insures them or not. Charges are either included in the premium or billed separately. Several other insurance companies, including Travelers and the Hartford Insurance Group, and some industries like United Technologies maintain similar divisions.</p>
        <p>When the General Assembly convenes next January, the House Public Health Committee will present a bill based on recommendations in a report on sick-building syndrome by the state's Department of Health Services.</p>
        <p>The study notes that indoor air pollution can reach levels up to 10,000 times greater than those outdoors. Its recommendations include ventilation and building codes; standards for specific contaminants; public education programs; research projects and a formal indoor air pollution assessment and control program.</p>
        <p>''In the absence of state law, the decisions to correct such situations are made strictly on a marketing basis,'' said Colleen Sheriden, a vice president at Cushman &amp; Wakefield Realtors in Stamford.</p>
        <p>The presence of asbestos or radon, for example, turns off prospective buyers or renters of office buildings, a direct result of heightened public awareness.</p>
        <p>But recognition of more subtle contaminants is still in its infancy and building owners and managers, air-quality consulting firms, and even physicians who have treated people with sick building symptoms, are reluctant to identify polluted buildings.</p>
        <p>''The sociology is complicated,'' said John Yokum, head of TRC Environmental Consultants in East Hartford. ''You may be dealing with a malcontent.''</p>
        <p>Carbon dioxide exhaled by too many people in a room, copying machine chemicals, and formaldehyde gases emitted by carpeting and furniture are among the culprits. Retrofitting buildings to upgrade air quality is costly and real estate brokers say most buyers are unaware of the potential problems. So far, few appraisers lower the value of seriously contaminated buildings.</p>
        <p>When a problem does arise, it can cost from $1,000 to $10,000 in tests merely to identify the source.</p>
        <p>''We are dealing with a soup of contaminants,'' said Jim Heldenbrand, manager of standards for ASHRAE in Atlanta, the American Society of Heating, Refrigerating, and Air- Conditioning Engineers, which draws up legally unenforceable but commonly accepted standards for architects and engineers.</p>
        <p>''We recommend 20 cubic feet of air a minute per person,'' said Mr. Heldenbrand. The standard was raised from 15 cubic feet a year ago, and 5 cubic feet during the 70's when the energy crisis prompted the construction of ''tight'' buildings with inoperable windows.</p>
        <p>Many variations can skew a system, such as erecting extra partitions that cut off the flow of air; or a smoking lounge that requires 60 cubic feet of air per person - ''beyond the capacity of many ventilating systems,'' according to Mr. Heldenbrand.</p>
        <p>''Building-related illness is much more common than the average physician realizes,'' said Dr. Thomas Godar, a specialist in pulmonary medicine at St. Francis Hospital in Hartford. ''It's ordinarily ascribed to job-related stress, allergies, or the person is regarded as hysterical or a chronic complainer.'' Some of his patients obtain relief by changing jobs or taking inordinate numbers of sick days. Data on long-term effects have not yet been accumulated.</p>
        <p>For many years, the Federal Occupational Safety and Health Adminstration has been concerned with regulating heavy industry in terms of fire safety, mechanical hazards and direct exposure to toxic chemicals.</p>
        <p>''The American scene is changing from manufacturing to service oriented businesses,'' said Mr. Wiernicki, ''with a broader spectrum of men and women working in offices than did in factories. I think we will see increasing regulation of white-collar buildings in the next few years, just as we once did in factories.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
