<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scientists Confront An Alarming Mystery: The Vanishing Frog</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="328335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FROGS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AMPHIBIANS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLAKESLEE, SANDRA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amphibians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDB143FF933A15751C0A966958260" item-length="1430" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scientists Confront An Alarming Mystery: The Vanishing Frog</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANDRA BLAKESLEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BLAKESLEE, SANDRA</byline>
      <dateline>IRVINE, Calif., Feb. 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A panel of experts met here today to assess an alarming number of reports that amphibians are rapidly disappearing from many ponds, rivers, mountains and rain forests around the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A panel of experts met here today to assess an alarming number of reports that amphibians are rapidly disappearing from many ponds, rivers, mountains and rain forests around the world.</p>
        <p>A panel of experts met here today to assess an alarming number of reports that amphibians are rapidly disappearing from many ponds, rivers, mountains and rain forests around the world.</p>
        <p>Many species of frogs, toads and salamanders are ''crashing throughout North, Central and South America, Europe, Asia, Africa and Australia,'' said David Wake, a biology professor at the University of California at Berkeley who is the panel's chairman. ''They are disappearing from nature preserves, in the most pristine sites of Costa Rica, Brazil, Yosemite, Sequoia and Isle Royale National Parks. Meadows where frogs were as thick as flies are now silent.''</p>
        <p>The scientists emphasize that the evidence is by no means clear-cut. Some species of amphibians seem to be thriving in some parts of the world, said Dr. Harold J. Morowitz, a biology professor at George Mason University in Fairfax, Va. Counting frogs is a tricky business, he said, and reports of their demise could be completely wrong.</p>
        <p>To sort through the conflicting evidence, the National Research Council's biology board has convened the two-day meeting of 20 experts in amphibian ecology, physiology, tropical biology, population genetics, virology and statistics, held at the Beckman Center of the National Academies of Sciences and Engineering in Irvine. Participants plan to issue recommendations tomorrow on what should be done.</p>
        <p>'Everybody Has a Theory'</p>
        <p>Amphibian populations fluctuate wildly, said Dr. Henry Wilbur, a zoologist from Duke University who said he was invited to the meeting to play devil's advocate. But the evidence presented today, he said, ''sure makes it look like something real is going on in some places in the world.'' However, he said, ''I'd be surprised if we come up with a unitary cause for all the problems people are describing.''</p>
        <p>''Everybody has a theory to explain the local declines,'' said Dr. Wake. ''In Texas they say it's cattle egrets. In Connecticut it's the blasted raccoons. In Brazil they say it's the cold winters, and in British Columbia it's that paint plant across the lake.'' But declines could also be caused by global problems like acid rain, pesticides and air pollution, he said.</p>
        <p>''If frogs and salamanders are dying off in synchrony, there's a message there for us,'' said Dr. Wake in opening the meeting. Like canaries that die when exposed to odorless, poisonous gases deep in coal mines, he said, amphibians may be an ''indicator species'' for the poisons of industrialized society.</p>
        <p>The problem began coming into focus last September, at the first world herpetology congress in Canterbury, England. As scientists from 63 countries began to compare notes on declining amphibian populations in their own backyards, Dr. Wake said, ''we were shocked to discover the extent of the problem.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Wake said he had to cajole many scientists into admitting they could no longer find amphibians in their favorite field haunts. ''They blame themselves, saying maybe they need bifocals,'' he said. One reason they did not report the problem earlier, he went on, was that they were afraid a younger colleague or even a child would discover frogs that were reported to have vanished.</p>
        <p>Despite their surprise over the reported extent of amphibian decline, scientists at the meeting said it was no wonder that frogs are vulnerable. Because amphibians generally have two life stages, one in water and one on land, they come into contact with a wide variety of substances. Moreover, they literally breathe through their moist skins. Heavy metals and other contaminants in soil or water easily pass into their bodies. So do the chemical residues in the many creatures they eat.</p>
        <p>Amphibians' Rise and Fall</p>
        <p>Up to now, amphibians have been spectacularly successful in exploiting the ecological niche of temporary bodies of water, said Dr. Richard Wassersug, a tadpole expert from Dalhousie University in Halifax, Nova Scotia. ''When the ponds dry up,'' he said, ''the frogs hop out.''</p>
        <p>Amphibians have used this technique to spread themselves all over the world, from the Arctic Circle to deserts, from below sea level to 15,000-foot mountains, said Dr. Wassersug. Frogs can be the size of a dime or a basketball. Salamanders can be as short as matchsticks or as long as surfboards.</p>
        <p>At today's session, panelists heard a variety of reasons for the decline of amphibian populations, both local and global.</p>
        <p>The most obvious local reason is drought. Some species cannot survive more than three dry years in a row; others are more adaptable. Many reports of missing frogs were ascribed to bad weather, said Dr. Wake, but he added: ''These animals have been around for 70 million years. They survived what did in the dinosaurs. I don't think they'd check out because of a couple of cold winters or dry summers.''</p>
        <p>Another common explanation is competition from people. In Japan, rice paddies where amphibians flourish are giving way to golf courses. In the United States, frogs return to ponds only to find condominiums. In Hungary, salamanders are contaminated with effluent from factories. Frogs' eggs are particularly vulnerable, because they are fragile and because females lay so many of them in one place. Ten thousand frogs can be wiped out ''in a single predatory event,'' said Dr. Wassersug, like 11-year-olds playing catch with frogs' eggs.</p>
        <p>Pollution from copper mines seems to have wiped out the tara humara frog from Arizona, the panelists were told. And the celebrated jumping frog of Calaveras County, Calif., is extinct because those not eaten by gold miners in the 19th century were eaten by the Eastern bullfrogs that were brought West for food and hunting in the 20th.</p>
        <p>Edible Fish, Edible Tadpoles</p>
        <p>Another danger is the worldwide trend of stocking lakes and ponds with edible fish, said Dr. Roy McDiarmid, a herpetologist at the Smithsonian Institution's Natural History Museum in Washington. Fish eat tadpoles. Once the fish get around, he said, frog ponds become frogless.</p>
        <p>The real mystery is what might be killing frogs in pristine environments. Dr. David Bradford, who teaches environmental studies at the University of California at Los Angeles, said that in the 1970's he found ponds in the High Sierra with more than 800 adult yellow-legged frogs and 1,500 tadpoles. Last summer Dr. Bradford revisited 38 lakes, and the frogs ''were gone in all but one,'' he told the panelists.</p>
        <p>A leading cause of such declines may be acid rain and snow, said Dr. John Harte, a professor of energy and resources at Berkeley. He said a study on tiger salamanders in the Colorado Rockies had found that melting snow can release a pulse of acidity that damages salamander eggs. Tiger salamanders have declined by 65 percent over the last seven years in one area studied, he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bradford also raised the possibility of contamination from airborne pesticides. In the late 1960's, frogs in the High Sierra absorbed significant amounts of DDT that wafted into the mountains from crop spraying in the Central Valley of California. DDT has been banned in the United States but is still widely used in many countries, he said, and could be harming some amphibians in pristine places far from the source of the pollution.</p>
        <p>It was also suggested that increasing levels of ultraviolet light, admitted by the earth's deteriorating ozone layer, could damage frog eggs floating on the surface of ponds. When exposed to the damaging light at an early stage of development, the fertilized eggs fail to divide properly.</p>
        <p>Dr. Harte said that natural causes may also be involved. For example, the brilliantly colored golden toad has not been sighted in the Monte Verde reserve in Costa Rica since 1987. Glass frogs and rain frogs are also in decline. Just 50 miles away, said Dr. Harte, the Poas volcano is spewing sulfur dioxide and sulfates into the reserve.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wilbur, the devil's advocate, said recounts were needed in places where good population estimates were made in the past, followed by laboratory experiments to test the tolerance of tadpoles and frogs to increased acidity.</p>
        <p>He added that when possible, species that have succumbed to environmental pressures should be compared to species that are thriving. For example, tree frogs are alive and well in many parts of California where red- and yellow-legged frogs have vanished in California.</p>
        <p>''Something is going on in different parts of the world with different species and we don't know what,'' said Dr. Wilbur. ''Our hope is we can come up with some ideas, but don't expect solutions right away.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
