<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Ted Turner Saved the World</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="370476"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOODWILL GAMES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">TURNER, TED</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">VECSEY, GEORGE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DA113BF931A15754C0A966958260" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Ted Turner Saved the World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VECSEY, GEORGE</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: TED TURNER is a notorious film colorizer from way back. He is also responsible for those soporific Atlanta Braves broadcasts into defenseless homes and taverns all over this land.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: TED TURNER is a notorious film colorizer from way back. He is also responsible for those soporific Atlanta Braves broadcasts into defenseless homes and taverns all over this land.</p>
        <p>TED TURNER is a notorious film colorizer from way back. He is also responsible for those soporific Atlanta Braves broadcasts into defenseless homes and taverns all over this land.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the old scalawag has his redeeming qualities. For one thing, he has individually moved the doomsday clock a few ticks further away from midnight.</p>
        <p>This wobbly planet has become a better place since Cap'n Courageous mused out loud that it would neat to put on a summer sports jamboree between the U.S. and them pinko commies, as he has been known to call people from the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>Whatever Teddy wants, Teddy gets. In 1986, his very own television empire was filled with everything from rhythmic gymnastics to motorcycle soccer, emanating from the very epicenter of communism, Moscow.</p>
        <p>They called it the Goodwill Games. They still do, although this event has not exactly permeated the American consciousness.</p>
        <p>When a wandering scribe tells his friends that he is off to Seattle, they ask why. ''The Goodwill Games,'' he says. ''The what?'' people ask. ''You know, Ted Turner's thing.'' ''Oh, right.''</p>
        <p>Turner became the star of his own event in 1986 by wandering from contest to contest, from camera to camera, from notepad to notepad, pleading the cause of peace.</p>
        <p>He was like a tormented visionary straight out of Tolstoy or Dostoyevsky, urging the people of the earth to make volleyball, not war.</p>
        <p>''How much time we got?'' Turner asked in that honking voice of his.</p>
        <p>In his impassioned speeches, he linked peace and ecology, humanity and nature. He was better than anything that happened in the pole-vault pit or the water-polo pool.</p>
        <p>The Goodwill Games lost $26 million. Almost nobody watched. Despite that, Turner had an impact on the future of the globe.</p>
        <p>This was at a time when our own elected leader was still prattling on about the Soviet Union's being an ''evil empire,'' like something out of ''Star Wars.'' But Turner brought in a whole circus of athletes, journalists and tourists to take a look at a troubled society in ferment.</p>
        <p>Has anybody noticed that since Turner went to Moscow, political dissent has come to the Soviet Union, the Berlin Wall has come down, several Eastern Bloc nations have broken free, and Len Dykstra was given a chance to play every day?</p>
        <p>They did not give Turner the Nobel Peace Prize for all this, but there is still time. The Goodwill Games are back for another try, this time in the sun-baked city of Seattle. You read that correctly. Turner will surely turn this heat wave into a sermon on global warming.</p>
        <p>Seventeen days is a lot of air time, but no doubt they will try to make it sound exciting on television. Besides, it gives a lot of people, including a few thousand Soviet visitors, a chance to nibble on some crab, ride the ferry boats (whose foghorns sound vaguely like Ted Turner) and walk the hillsides of Seattle. And 17 days gives Turner the chance to remind people our work is not yet done.</p>
        <p>''The world is a lot less dangerous,'' Turner said the other day while being prodded by a journalist.</p>
        <p>''Who cares why? If the Goodwill Games had something to do with it, so much the better,'' he added. ''But you've had Pepsi-Cola here for a long time, and medical doctors, and Ted Hesburgh and John Denver.</p>
        <p>''The Soviet leadership feels I was friendly with them all along, but it's hard to ask me about what we accomplished.</p>
        <p>''I think big; I'm a big thinker, but there's no way I could have predicted what has happened.''</p>
        <p>Turner admits that these Goodwill Games will lose ''more than half'' of the $26 million they lost in 1986, but, he said, ''I look at it as investment spending.''</p>
        <p>Besides, Turner said, the battle is still not won.</p>
        <p>''Relations between the countries are better,'' he said, ''but we still have 30,000 missiles on hair trigger. They haven't got rid of a single missile in most places. They still haven't done much.</p>
        <p>''It's like a relationship with your wife,'' said Turner, who has been keeping company with Jane Fonda in recent days. ''You can't take it for granted.''</p>
        <p>This forum, this bully pulpit, may still be the major justification for the Goodwill Games, which have the artificial aura of a made-for-TV spectacular.</p>
        <p>Because of the U.S.-U.S.S.R. format, there is not enough money or attention to bring in many of the great athletes from other nations. The Olympics it is not.</p>
        <p>But Turner is stressing that ''ninety percent of the best athletes in the world are here,'' and he is saying that the track-and-field competition will be the best on American soil since the 1932 Summer Games.</p>
        <p>The 1984 Summer Games, remember, were tarnished because the Soviet Union and its pals did not show up, a tit for tat for the U.S. absence in Moscow in 1980.</p>
        <p>Those are now known as the bad old days. There have been no Olympic boycotts since Ted Turner went to Moscow. Think about it.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
