<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Two Democratic Leaders, Two Needed Victories</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="340047"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILD CARE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">TONER, ROBIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDD113DF931A35757C0A966958260" item-length="964" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Two Democratic Leaders, Two Needed Victories</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN TONER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TONER, ROBIN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: When the 1989 session of Congress ended last November, Democratic leaders said: Wait till next year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: When the 1989 session of Congress ended last November, Democratic leaders said: Wait till next year.</p>
        <p>When the 1989 session of Congress ended last November, Democratic leaders said: Wait till next year.</p>
        <p>Like coaches defending a less than stunning season, they described 1989 as a building year, when the new leadership teams in the House and Senate were still finding their footing and feeling their way. So there was a powerful sense of relief among Democrats last week when George J. Mitchell of Maine, the Senate majority leader, and Thomas S. Foley of Washington, the Speaker of the House, each won something.</p>
        <p>Last Thursday's votes on a critical clean air amendment in the Senate and the child care measure in the House were institutional and legislative victories for the Democratic leadership, which took office with huge expectations that they have struggled to meet.</p>
        <p>Perhaps equally important, the votes were signs of life in a Congress that has not exactly been a legislature on the march this year, despite the predictions of last fall. ''Something finally happened,'' said a Democratic strategist, who spoke on the condition of anonymity. ''Part of this is just the natural ebb and flow of the legislative calendar of Congress, but it came not a moment too soon.''</p>
        <p>Inside and Outside</p>
        <p>Legislative leadership is an inside and an outside game. The Democratic leaders proved something in the inside game last week by pushing through measures each had promised to produce, with some of the most difficult challenges coming from members of their own party. But many Democrats acknowledge that this Congress and this leadership have a long way to go in the outside game of public perceptions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitchell's victory came as he removed the last major obstacle to Senate passage of the Clean Air Act by defeating an amendment by Senator Robert C. Byrd of West Virginia that would have established a $500 million relief program for coal miners who lose their jobs because of acid rain controls. The vote was 50 to 49, with only 16 of the 50 coming from Democrats.</p>
        <p>It was a crucial test for Mr. Mitchell, both because it pitted him directly against Mr. Byrd, his predecessor in the job of majority leader, and because it was a serious threat to the compromise bill negotiated by the White House and Senate leaders.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitchell has made passage of clean air legislation a top priority; it has dominated the Senate for much of 1990, or ''what seemed like from here to eternity,'' as a House Democratic aide said. The bill still faces a tortuous road through the House after the Senate votes on it on Tuesday. But Mr. Mitchell can claim that his portion of the mission is well on its way, though he must share credit with the Bush Administration and Republican leaders.</p>
        <p>''I'm more confident than ever that we'll have a strong and fair new law this year,'' Mr. Mitchell said in an interview on Friday in which he gracefully played down the personal aspect of his struggle with Mr. Byrd.</p>
        <p>Foley vs. the Memory of Wright</p>
        <p>In the House, Mr. Foley set passage of child care legislation as a priority; the Senate had approved a child care bill last year, but the House was bogged down in the kind of internecine committee squabbling that gives unending ammunition to Congressional critics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Foley is widely respected in Congress. But since he succeeded the hard-driving Jim Wright of Texas, many have wondered whether his judicious, conciliatory style would be effective in the sprawling, quarrelsome House. His allies said his dogged pursuit of the child care legislation, which was passed Thursday over the threat of a Presidential veto, showed that his style could produce results, albeit slowly.</p>
        <p>''He's been able to adapt the Foley style to legislative accomplishments,'' a House Democratic strategist said. ''It does take a long time, simply because he's not one of these 'damn it, do it now' leaders. Maybe in the long run it will be more successful than Jim Wright's 'damn it, do it now.' ''</p>
        <p>Still, that aide and many other Democrats say the Democratic leaders are heading for what may be their most rigorous test: the budget, where the challenges of the inside and the outside game are intense. Inside, the leadership needs to deal with committees and elements of the Democratic caucus that can disagree intensely over taxing and spending; outside, it faces an election-year environment where every move can have campaign consequences.</p>
        <p>Still, It's Only April</p>
        <p>The effectiveness of this Congress and its leadership will be judged in the months ahead as they grapple with the appropriate level of military spending cuts, the proposal by Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan, Democrat of New York, to reduce Social Security taxes and the proposal by President Bush to cut the tax on capital gains. More broadly, the leadership will be tested by a White House that has shown an uncanny ability to checkmate Congressional Democrats on one issue after another.</p>
        <p>''No doubt about it, it's going to be the most difficult budget year we've had, maybe since 1981,'' said Representative Steny H. Hoyer of Maryland, the chairman of the House Democratic Caucus. He was referring to the first year of the Reagan Administration, when the White House and Congress squared off over huge spending and tax cuts. ''The money is tighter,'' he went on, ''the targets are lower, and the Moynihan proposal puts a lot of political heat in it.''</p>
        <p>Still, at week's end, the Democratic leadership in the House and the Senate were pointing to some legislative accomplishments, although the child care and clean air bills still have many hurdles to clear.</p>
        <p>''I think we are making significant progress toward objectives set out in the beginning of this Congress,'' Mr. Mitchell said, ''which will enable us to say, when it's over, that this was a productive and significant Congress.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
