<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fans of Rushing Rivers Gather</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="337922"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="ON YOUR OWN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RAFTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DF113DF935A15750C0A966958260" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fans of Rushing Rivers Gather</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: GLOBAL warming might melt glaciers and threaten the environment, but a different type of global warmth attracted a contingent of 75 Russians and participants from more than 30 other countries to take part in the Nantahala '90 Rally, a 12-day whitewater rafting event that ended today at the Nantahala Outdoor Center (N.O.C.) in western North</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: GLOBAL warming might melt glaciers and threaten the environment, but a different type of global warmth attracted a contingent of 75 Russians and participants from more than 30 other countries to take part in the Nantahala '90 Rally, a 12-day whitewater rafting event that ended today at the Nantahala Outdoor Center (N.O.C.) in western North</p>
        <p>GLOBAL warming might melt glaciers and threaten the environment, but a different type of global warmth attracted a contingent of 75 Russians and participants from more than 30 other countries to take part in the Nantahala '90 Rally, a 12-day whitewater rafting event that ended today at the Nantahala Outdoor Center (N.O.C.) in western North Carolina.</p>
        <p>''The rally is a place where folks who love rivers - who love running rivers - are drawn together,'' said Ellen Babers of the N.O.C., who is an open-canoe instructor and coordinator for the rally. ''World events have really contributed to the timeliness of the rally. We have Czechoslovaks, Poles, Indians; and the East and West Germans have united to compete as one team.''</p>
        <p>More than 300 participants, whose level of ability ranged from eager novice to champion, competed in raft and kayak slalom, river rescue, and a ''triathlon'' combining mountain bicycling, downriver rafting, and running. All told, the rafters ran rivers in North Carolina, Tennessee and Georgia.</p>
        <p>As much as the rally tested the participants' skills on the water, the fortnight had loftier objectives: ''to promote international peace, trust, friendship, and understanding by bringing outdoor enthusiasts from around the world together,'' according to Project RAFT (Russians and Americans for Teamwork) literature. Project RAFT is the event's California-based organizing body.</p>
        <p>''Even, maybe, two years ago, if somebody would tell me that, 'O.K., guy, you are supposed to raft in the middle of United States next month,' I would have thought it was a joke, and not a very clever one,'' said Ivan Maurakh, a member of the Russian team who served as interpreter for Project RAFT.</p>
        <p>Maurakh is also captain for the All World team, which consisted of one member from each participating country. This team, he said, is ''maybe the quintessence of the whole rally, because it goes far further toward our goal of international teamwork.''</p>
        <p>The Soviet Union has long been a land of rafting enthusiasts, but because the country has no whitewater-outfitting industry, the enthusiasts must build their rafts from whatever materials are available. The resulting ''plots,'' the Russian term for homemade craft, resemble small floating barges.</p>
        <p>Last year, Siberia was host for the Soviet Union's first full-fledged international rafting event, the Chuya Rally '89, which drew 300 entrants from 17 countries. The venture was a collaborative effort between the Siberian river explorer, Misha Kolchevnikov, and Project RAFT, founded by California river guides Jib Ellison and Mike Grant. The organizers moved this year's rally to the United States in hopes of gaining further international participation. They succeeded.</p>
        <p>''There were flags from all over the world,'' said a member of the Costa Rican squad, Fernando Esquivel, referring to the multinational representation in a St. Patrick's Day parade through the streets of Atlanta. The parade was an extra-curricular activity planned for the foreign competitors as they traveled from New York airports to North Carolina.</p>
        <p>''For many years, we had no idea what life was like in other countries,'' said Jaromir Laskot, the captain of the Czechoslovak team. ''We saw only the bad side of the coin. It is good that we can now see for ourselves.'' ''In the past, there was a lot of political prejudice,'' Esquivel said, alluding to tensions that until recently impeded cultural exchange and understanding among nations. ''But there is really no difference between us. We're all happy running the river.''  ON YOUR OWN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
