<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Grappling With the Cost Of Saving Earth's Ozone</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="368905"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GASES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DD1438F934A25754C0A966958260" item-length="1763" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Grappling With the Cost Of Saving Earth's Ozone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: AS scientists, engineers and manufacturers struggle to find substitutes for the ozone-destroying chemicals world governments have decided to ban, there are fears that the cost of replacing them might include environmental risks, as well as a financial burden for consumers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: AS scientists, engineers and manufacturers struggle to find substitutes for the ozone-destroying chemicals world governments have decided to ban, there are fears that the cost of replacing them might include environmental risks, as well as a financial burden for consumers.</p>
        <p>AS scientists, engineers and manufacturers struggle to find substitutes for the ozone-destroying chemicals world governments have decided to ban, there are fears that the cost of replacing them might include environmental risks, as well as a financial burden for consumers.</p>
        <p>Chemical and appliance makers say that technologies can be developed quickly to avoid use of ozone-destructive substances but that large uncertainties about the effect of the substitutions remain.</p>
        <p>Last month delegates of more than 90 governments met in London and agreed on a treaty to phase out the ozone-destroying chemicals, chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, by the end of the century. Even before the international agreement, the United States and most other industrial countries had taken steps to begin the change. But no simple substitutions for CFC's are in sight, and the reduction of risks posed by them may increase other risks, experts say.</p>
        <p>Some government and industrial experts assert that chemicals and technologies intended as replacements may contribute to global warming, although less so than the chemicals they replace. Many appliances and machines are expected to operate at lower efficiency and higher cost than before and are likely therefore to raise costs and consume more energy. No estimate of the global cost of replacing CFC-based technology has been made, but the Environmental Protection Agency estimated that the cost in the United States alone would be some $3 billion, mostly for replacing equipment made obsolete or unusable by the ban.</p>
        <p>The chlorofluorocarbon compounds, which are also known as Freons, consist of combinations of carbon, chlorine and fluorine atoms. They are extremely versatile chemicals used primarily as refrigerants in air-conditioners, freezers and refrigerators; as foaming agents in plastic and rubber insulation; as aerosol spray propellants, which are banned in the United States but still used in many other countries, and as cleaning solvents for microelectronic circuits.</p>
        <p>In the United States about one-third of the chlorofluorocarbonsproduced are used for refrigeration and the rest mostly for blowing plastic foams or as solvents. But throughout the developing world, where use has rapidly increased in recent years, almost all the production is used as refrigerants. Experts consider the problem of making chlorofluorocarbon-free refrigerating technology available to India and China, which together have nearly 40 percent of the world's population, particularly urgent.</p>
        <p>The chlorofluorocarbons in common use are nonflammable, nontoxic, stable, relatively easy to manufacture and ideally suited to the applications for which they were developed. The global market is currently about $1.8 billion a year, and in non-Communist countries alone, some two billion pounds of the chemicals are manufactured each year.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, these chemicals are so stable that once released into the atmosphere molecules can survive for more than a century, allowing them to drift intact into the stratosphere. At high altitude they are exposed to intense ultraviolet radiation that breaks the molecules apart, producing free chlorine atoms. These can destroy enormous amounts of ozone, a trace gas that shields the earth from the most dangerous form of ultraviolet radiation.</p>
        <p>The degradation of the stratospheric ozone layer, which became evident in the mid-1980's, may eventually let in radiation severe enough to cause an epidemic of skin cancer and cataracts and to reduce agricultural productivity seriously. Chlorofluorocarbons also trap radiant solar heat and contribute strongly to the heating of the atmosphere, or ''greenhouse'' effect.</p>
        <p>A Rare Agreement on All Sides</p>
        <p>Environmental lobbyists, Government agencies, chemical industries and appliance manufacturers are in rare agreement on one point: the chemicals must be eliminated from the environment as soon as possible.</p>
        <p>''CFC replacement must be completed whatever the cost,'' said Dr. William M. Eichbaum, vice president of the World Wildlife Fund. ''The developed world has shown that it can accommodate the change. But the developing world is entitled to the technical assistance it will receive under the London accord.''</p>
        <p>A spokesman for E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company, the world's largest manufacturer of chlorofluorocarbon products, said the company was among the first to recognize the health risks posed by ozone-destroying chemicals. Du Pont projects that conservation measures will reduce the use of chlorofluorocarbons by 30 percent by the year 2000 and that substitutes will be needed for the remainder. But in some applications, no substitutes have been invented, and in others, the projected substitutes are more costly, less efficient and more dangerous to use.</p>
        <p>Du Pont, which manufactures about one-fourth of the world's chlorofluorocarbons, expects to spend $1 billion in the next 10 years in developing substitutes, but such research represents only a minor part of the conversion cost.</p>
        <p>Dr. Leo E. Manzer, who directs replacement research for Du Pont, said equipment dependent on the chemicals is worth some $135 billion in the United States alone, equipment that must be modified or replaced. Some 5,000 American businesses with 700,000 workers produce chlorofluorocarbon-related goods and services valued at $28 billion a year.</p>
        <p>Finding a New Refrigerant</p>
        <p>All automobile air-conditioners and most home refrigerators contain CFC-12. It is among five chlorofluorocarbon compounds banned by the treaty.</p>
        <p>Du Pont, the Allied-Signal Corporation, the British-based company ICI and other major chemical manufacturers plan to market a compound called HFC-134a as a substitute for CFC-12, and Du Pont's new Corpus Christi, Tex., plant will begin manufacturing the substance by the end of this year. HFC-134a contains only carbon, hydrogen and fluorine but no chlorine; it therefore cannot destroy ozone.</p>
        <p>But simply draining the ozone-destroying CFC-12 from the compressor of an air-conditioner or refrigerator and replacing the fluid with the new HFC-134a does not work, engineers say. The compressor and sometimes the entire system must be redesigned to accommodate the new refrigerant.</p>
        <p>While HCF-134a is benign to the ozone layer, it increases the trapping of solar heat by the atmosphere. But HCF and other substitutes have been shown to have only about one-tenth the greenhouse warming effect of chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>Challenges Posed by New Rules</p>
        <p>Refrigeration engineers say new Government regulations have posed exceptional challenges. Heinz Jaster, a thermodynamics expert in the General Electric Company's research and development group, said: ''Under the law, the energy efficiency of most new home refrigerators must be improved about 30 percent by Jan. 1, 1992. But at the same time, we are now required to phase out the CFC refrigerants that make high energy efficiency possible.''</p>
        <p>Some problems could be avoided, experts say, if makers of refrigerators and air-conditioners were willing to use propane as a refrigerant. John Missenden, director of a research group at South Bank Polytechnic Institute in England, has noted that propane is a good refrigerant, is harmless to ozone and costs about one-sixtieth as much as HFC-134a. Its only important drawbacks are that it is flammable and a greenhouse contributor. Mr. Jaster acknowledges that propane could easily be adapted as a refrigerant, but that the fire and explosion hazard it would create would be intolerable.</p>
        <p>Some experts also worry that by getting rid of chlorofluorocarbons, industrial technologies will inadvertently degrade the environment in other ways.</p>
        <p>A study by Oak Ridge National Laboratory recently concluded that because substitutes would be less efficient as refrigerants and insulators, electricity use in the United States would increase by about 3 percent, increasing consumer costs significantly. Assuming that the electricity is produced mainly by burning fossil fuels, the carbon dioxide sent into the atmosphere will correspondingly increase. Carbon dioxide is a greenhouse gas believed by many scientists to cause climatic warming.</p>
        <p>Another problem is that one class of planned substitutes for chlorofluorocarbons to be used as foam-blowing agents and refrigerants, HCFC's, will damage the ozone layer, albeit at a decreased rate with an ozone-destroying potential about 5 percent that of CFC's. Greenpeace and several other environmental groups strongly objected to the London agreement, partly because it did not ban HCFC's but merely recommended that their use be phased out by 2040.</p>
        <p>Du Pont counters that a quick ban of them would have disastrous effects on refrigeration technology and would force developing nations to revert to the much more damaging chlorofluorocarbons. Moreover, Dr. Manzer reported in a July 6 article in the journal Science, eliminating HCFC's from insulating foam would create heat and cooling losses equivalent to that produced by several billion gallons of petroleum annually in the United States.</p>
        <p>Another major use of chlorofluorocarbon solvents is in the electronics industry, which needs especially efficient cleaning agents capable of penetrating the microscopic crevices in electronic chips. So far, although many companies have developed various solvent blends and water-based cleaners for microelectronic devices, no completely satisfactory substitute has been devised for CFC-113 solvent, a prohibited compound.</p>
        <p>The American Telephone and Telegraph Company has said that a partial solution is to manufacture electronic circuits that do not need cleaning. David Chittick, the company's vice president for environment and safety, reported in a newsletter that A.T.&amp;T. had developed a new type of rosin flux for its solder that leaves less residue that must be cleaned. The company has already reduced its consumption of chlorofluorocarbon solvents from 3.1 million pounds in 1986 to 2.3 million pounds last year. But ''80 percent of the solution comes fairly easy,'' Mr. Chittick said, ''and the last 20 percent gets very expensive and difficult to achieve.''</p>
        <p>Engineers at many companies are experimenting with blends of chemicals as substitute solvents, plastic foaming agents and refrigerants. They are also investigating entirely new mechanical systems, including refrigerators without conventional compressors.</p>
        <p>''There's no question that the world will learn to get along without CFC's,'' Dr. Manzer said. ''The questions that remain have to do with cost - the trade-off costs, as well as the money.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
