<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>1,082 Graduate at Princeton</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="360897"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="COMMENCEMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEGREES, ACADEMIC</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PRINCETON UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FITZGERALD, ELLA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DB1730F930A25755C0A966958260" item-length="260" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>1,082 Graduate at Princeton</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>PRINCETON, N.J., June 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Princeton University conferred 1,082 bachelor degrees and 571 advanced degrees at its 243d commencement today in front of Nassau Hall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Princeton University conferred 1,082 bachelor degrees and 571 advanced degrees at its 243d commencement today in front of Nassau Hall.</p>
        <p>Princeton University conferred 1,082 bachelor degrees and 571 advanced degrees at its 243d commencement today in front of Nassau Hall.</p>
        <p>The president of Princeton, Harold T. Shapiro, urged the class of 1990 not to let early failures stop them from trying to achieve. ''Let us not be paralyzed or demoralized by the tedious pace of progress,'' he said. ''Rather let our vision and hope be constantly refreshed by each successful step toward our ultimate objective.''</p>
        <p>The commencement followed a weekend of reunions at which Sally Frank, a member of the class of 1980, received an award from the Alumni Council for service to the university.</p>
        <p>In an 11-year legal battle against three of Princeton's 13 eating clubs that excluded women, she got one to halt the practice. The clubs serve as dining halls for most upperclass students.</p>
        <p>Six people were awarded honorary degrees. They are:</p>
        <p>ELLA FITZGERALD, the singer, for her achievement over six decades.</p>
        <p>MEG GREENFIELD, editorial page editor of The Washington Post, for writing that ''takes the nation's and the world's pulse.''</p>
        <p>DOROTHY HEIGHT, president of the National Council of Negro Women, for her work in civil rights.</p>
        <p>F. SHERWOOD ROWLAND, the Donald Bren Professor of Chemistry at the University of California at Irvine, for research into damage to the earth's ozone layer.</p>
        <p>ROBERT TUCKER, emeritus I.B.M. Professor in International Studies at Princeton, for his work in Soviet-American affairs.</p>
        <p>P. ROY VAGELOS, chief executive officer of Merck &amp; Company, for helping to conquer disease.</p>
        <p>COMMENCEMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
