<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Ebb and Flow Of Ancient Glaciers, Clues to Next Ice Age</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="317275"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GLACIERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE AGE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Glaciers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Age</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DE1038F935A25752C0A966958260" item-length="2163" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Ebb and Flow Of Ancient Glaciers, Clues to Next Ice Age</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE climatic history of the last half-million years is largely a history of ice and cold, punctuated every 100,000 years or so by brief, glorious intervals of unusual warmth called interglacials. If nature takes its course, scientists say, the current interglacial - the one in which human civilization developed - should begin to end within the next 2,000 years or sooner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE climatic history of the last half-million years is largely a history of ice and cold, punctuated every 100,000 years or so by brief, glorious intervals of unusual warmth called interglacials. If nature takes its course, scientists say, the current interglacial - the one in which human civilization developed - should begin to end within the next 2,000 years or sooner.</p>
        <p>THE climatic history of the last half-million years is largely a history of ice and cold, punctuated every 100,000 years or so by brief, glorious intervals of unusual warmth called interglacials. If nature takes its course, scientists say, the current interglacial - the one in which human civilization developed - should begin to end within the next 2,000 years or sooner. But nature may not take an unaltered course. Unprecedented concentrations of heat-trapping carbon dioxide in the atmosphere could extend the present interglacial by a millennium or more and transform it into a ''super-interglacial'' with average global temperatures higher than any seen in the last million years, say a number of scientists who study the advance and retreat of the great glaciers.</p>
        <p>Putting off the next ice age might seem an attractive prospect; in the depths of the last one, 18,000 years ago, global temperatures averaged almost 10 degrees colder than today's and much of North America was buried under ice averaging a mile thick. Some experts say, however, that such a delay carries its own risks and uncertainties. There has never been more carbon dioxide in the air than now, they say, and since the burning of fossil fuels is causing the concentration to rise with no end to the increase in sight, there is no reliable guide to the climatic changes and disruptions it might cause.</p>
        <p>''We're going outside what nature has experienced in the recent past,'' said Dr. Nicholas Shackleton of Cambridge University in England, who has long been in the forefront of research on the glacial periods. ''It's scary.''</p>
        <p>In the last decade or so, scientists have made great strides in understanding the causes and workings of the great glacial cycles. But how much the globe will warm up is a matter of intense argument, and some glaciologists who believe that a super-interglacial is on the way say it may not last long enough to delay the world's turn to a new ice age. How all this will play out is one of the major questions faced by the interrelated sciences of glaciology and climatology.</p>
        <p>The present interglacial is 10,000 to 13,000 years along, and scientists say that in at least the last half-million years, no interglacial has ever lasted longer than 12,000 years. Over the last few years, scientists have generally come to agree on what determines the timing of these warm cycles and of the long, uneven cold spells that culminate in full ice ages.</p>
        <p>The glacial cycles are set in motion by periodic wobbles in the Earth's rotation and changes in the tilt of its axis and the shape of its orbit, occurring over tens of thousands of years. The three overlapping cycles control the timing of global warming and cooling, and the long-term advance and retreat of the glaciers, by altering the angles and distances from which the Sun's energy strikes the Earth.</p>
        <p>The shortest cycle, which is repeated mainly in periods of 19,000 and 23,000 years, is that of the wobble in the Earth's rotation. The wobble, or precession, is much like that of a spinning top as it loses speed. In the second cycle, the tilt of the Earth's axis as it orbits the Sun varies from about 22 degrees to about 25 degrees over 41,000 years. In the longest cycle, the Earth's orbit stretches slightly from nearly circular to elliptical and back again every 100,000 years or so.</p>
        <p>To some degree, said Dr. John Imbrie of Brown University, a leading glaciologist, the two shorter cycles appear to exert a direct force on the climate, much as the Earth's movement about the Sun exerts a direct influence on the change of seasons. By itself the 100,000-year cycle does not appear strong enough to bring about direct alterations in the Earth's climate. But scientists believe it sets off complex and far-reaching changes in the ocean-atmosphere system that drives the climate.</p>
        <p>This astronomical theory of glaciation, as it is called, was first set forth in the 1920's by Milutin Milankovitch, a Yugoslav mathematician, but confirmed only in the 70's and 80's. Researchers did so by analyzing ocean sediment in which the glacial cycles were reflected in the remains of plankton-like animals that live at particular temperatures, and by studying the ancient distribution of isotopes of oxygen whose proportions vary with the temperature.</p>
        <p>The focus of research now is on understanding how all three cycles affect the workings of the dauntingly complex ocean-atmosphere system and how they will be affected by rising concentrations of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Ice ages and interglacials differ from each other in their duration and internal fluctuations, partly because the interaction of the three astronomical cycles is rarely the same. The ice ages cannot be forecast exactly; Dr. Imbrie said they have ''an average recurrence time.''</p>
        <p>Coming: Global Cooling</p>
        <p>Scientists calculate that in the normal course of the cycle, apart from any warming induced by humans, the present interglacial should give way within no more than 2,000 years to a gradual, uneven decline in global temperature that would bring moderate cold about 5,000 years from now and major ice ages about 23,000 and 60,000 years from now.</p>
        <p>The interplay of the cycles means that each glacial period follows an uneven course, with relatively colder periods interspersed with relatively warmer ones, but none of them as warm as an interglacial. Average global temperatures in the past have reached about 60 degrees at the peak of an interglacial, and declined to about 50 degrees in the depths of an ice age. Nor does cooling or warming happen at the same time everywhere in the world. In the most recent climatic cycle, the coldest point in the Northern Hemisphere came about 18,000 years ago, after which the climate rapidly warmed.</p>
        <p>Life persisted even in the depths of that last ice age. But ice buried much of Europe and North America, and locked up so much water that the global sea level fell by 350 feet, exposing broad stretches of the continental shelf. A band of dry, windswept tundra bordered the southern fringes of the glaciers, and summers south of that were shorter and cooler than now. In the Southern Hemisphere, small ice sheets covered parts of Australia, New Zealand and Argentina.</p>
        <p>Smaller fluctuations are superimposed on these grand swings of climate. In the present interglacial, for instance, a warming trend about 1,000 years ago, called the Medieval Maximum, enabled the Vikings to settle Greenland and vineyards to flourish in Britain. On the other hand, scientists say that about every 2,500 years, a ''little ice age'' cools the globe. In the most recent of these, lasting from the 15th century to the 19th, the average temperature in Europe was nearly 3 degrees lower than today and mountain glaciers advanced all over the world. Crops failed and villages starved in parts of Europe. The Hans Brinker story in Holland was set in this period, as was the ordeal of Washington's army at Valley Forge. In 1779-80, New York Harbor froze solid.</p>
        <p>Cold Times, Warm Intervals</p>
        <p>The cause of these little ice ages, which have about one-tenth the impact of a full ice age, is uncertain, although some scientists believe they may be related to variations in the Sun's energy output. Smaller climatic oscillations also take place on scales of a century or less, and even smaller ones last a few years. There were warm intervals in the last little ice age, for instance; and in the United States, the relatively warm 1930's gave way to the colder 50's, 60's and 70's, to be followed again by the warmer 80's. Some climatologists say an overall warming trend can be detected over the last century, but others dispute this.</p>
        <p>The causes of these shorter-term oscillations are poorly understood, said Dr. Imbrie. Scientists believe that among the factors involved are volcanic eruptions and the periodic back-and-forth shifts in the surface temperature of the equatorial Pacific Ocean that have become known as the El Nino-La Nina cycle.</p>
        <p>Climatologists and glaciologists are sure that both the oceans and atmospheric carbon dioxide figure strongly in the longer-term climatic shifts. One of the great discoveries of the last decade, said Dr. Imbrie, was the finding by French and Soviet scientists in 1987 that atmospheric carbon dioxide rose and fell in rough parallel with the ice-age cycle over the last 150,000 years, covering two interglacials. The scientists made their findings by analyzing core samples of Antarctic ice.</p>
        <p>Whether the carbon-dioxide fluctuation is a cause or an effect of warming and cooling is an unanswered question of the chicken-and-egg sort. ''One of the really fundamental problems to be solved is why the carbon dioxide changes, because that clearly is involved in this ice-age change,'' said Dr. Imbrie. ''Nature herself has been changing carbon dioxide substantially, and a Nobel Prize question is why that happens.''</p>
        <p>In one way or another, he and other scientists believe, the Milankovitch cycles probably influence the way the ocean circulates, setting in train a complex chain of climatic interactions, involving carbon dioxide, ice, air temperatures, clouds, vegetation patterns, dust, atmospheric methane and a host of other factors.</p>
        <p>Cycles and Currents</p>
        <p>Studies of ocean sediment indicate that in glacial times, carbon dioxide is transferred from the upper waters of the ocean to the depths, said Edward A. Boyle, a planetary scientist at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, in a paper at the American Geophysical Union in San Francisco last month. One consequence, he said in an interview, is that the ocean becomes more alkaline and draws more carbon dioxide from the atmosphere. Lower levels of carbon dioxide are associated with lower global temperatures. ''There is probably something about the Milankovitch cycles that alters the chemical redistribution within the ocean,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Milankovitch cycles may also cause the pattern of ocean currents to change abruptly, altering the global distribution of heat, say Wallace S. Broecker, a geochemist at the Lamont-Doherty Laboratory, and George H. Denton, a geologist at the University of Maine. They believe this sudden ''flip,'' in which the ocean-atmosphere system drastically reorganizes, sets off glacial periods and interglacials.</p>
        <p>Dr. Broecker and Dr. Denton say a global ''conveyor belt'' of ocean currents now carries warm air to the North Atlantic, warming the northern latitudes and preventing glaciers of ice-age scale from developing. Studies of the ancient climate seem to show that the conveyor belt ceases in glacial times, the scientists say. They believe that this is related to changes in the intensity of the seasons induced by the changes in the Earth's orbit and attitude.</p>
        <p>The pattern of ice ages over the last half-million years is that the ice advances over periods of 100,000 years and then recedes more rapidly, over 6,000 or 7,000 years. Dr. Broecker says the climate itself changes even more rapidly, and that the melting of the ice follows more slowly. ''A lot of things occur abruptly and more or less together,'' said Dr. Imbrie.</p>
        <p>The end of the interglacial and the beginning of of the gradual decline into ice-age cold may also come with relative suddenness, Dr. Broecker says. ''The way I would count this interglacial,'' he said, ''it's already 13,000 years along,'' and the onset of the decline is overdue. ''You can say we're approaching that precipice now,'' he added.</p>
        <p>A Major Uncertainty</p>
        <p>The effect of the expected global warming from carbon dioxide produced by humans remains a major uncertainty. Dr. Shackleton, of Cambridge University, said carbon dioxide levels are now higher than they were at the height of the last interglacial, more than 100,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>''There is clearly going to be more carbon dioxide in the atmosphere than there has been in any previous interglacial,'' he added. ''It will soon be way above any previous natural level, and it will disappear into the oceans on a time scale of 1,000 or 2,000 years.''</p>
        <p>Some say this means that the plunge into a new ice age could be delayed by a similar interval. The peak of the super-interglacial, Dr. Broecker said, would probably occur no later than the year 2200; after that would come a long, slow decline over centuries. But the timing is uncertain. James Hays, another leading glaciologist at Lamont-Doherty, said ''we could go through the whole greenhouse episode and come back to normal'' before the decline to the next ice age begins.</p>
        <p>An unusually high level of atmospheric carbon dioxide, Dr. Broecker said, might cause the ocean-atmosphere system to flip into a new superwarm state as easily as it can flip to a glacial state, with unforeseen and unprecedented consequences.</p>
        <p>''We're living in a system that can do strange things,'' he said. ''Small forcings have produced large things, and to say a priori that this gas can't produce large changes is just bloody insanity.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
