<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LEARNING TO DO WITHOUT EARTH</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="335922"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARANTO, GINA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAGAN, DORION</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BIOSPHERES: METAMORPHOSIS OF PLANET EARTH (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DF1030F93BA25750C0A966958260" item-length="429" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LEARNING TO DO WITHOUT EARTH</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINA MARANTO; Gina Maranto is a science journalist who has written on environmental issues and reported on the Biosphere II project.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARANTO, GINA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>BIOSPHERES</p>
        <p>Metamorphosis of Planet Earth.</p>
        <p>By Dorion Sagan.</p>
        <p>198 pp. New York.</p>
        <p>McGraw-Hill Publishing Company. $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>BIOSPHERES</p>
        <p>Metamorphosis of Planet Earth.</p>
        <p>By Dorion Sagan.</p>
        <p>198 pp. New York.</p>
        <p>McGraw-Hill Publishing Company. $19.95.</p>
        <p>BIOSPHERES</p>
        <p>Metamorphosis of Planet Earth.</p>
        <p>By Dorion Sagan.</p>
        <p>198 pp. New York.</p>
        <p>McGraw-Hill Publishing Company. $19.95.</p>
        <p>Expanding on the much-debated Gaia hypothesis of the British atmospheric chemist James Lovelock - which holds that the globe and life on it constitute a superorganism engaged in maintaining the conditions necessary to its own survival - Dorion Sagan in this slim volume puts forward his view that the Earth is in the process of re-creating itself. Mr. Sagan, who is the co-author, with the biologist Lynn Margulis, of ''Microcosmos,'' posits that human beings are '' 'genitals' . . . the planetary counterpart to reproductive organs,'' and that they have, primarily through the development of industrial technology, become ''incestuously involved'' with Mother Earth.</p>
        <p>In a bizarre act of reproduction, we, the planet's gonads, have begun to construct hermetically sealed, self-sustaining ecological enclosures. (The largest conceived to date is the two-acre Biosphere II, a building in the Arizona desert north of Tucson). These so-called biospheres constitute the first stages of the Earth's embryonic differentiation, says the author, and in the near future may prove the only havens for life on a fatally polluted planet.</p>
        <p>The leap from terrestrial biospheres to bases on Mars and beyond, Mr. Sagan imagines, is not great, and ''once life gets into space using recycling technology, it will. . . . snap off the earthly umbilical cord.'' At that point, he continues grandiloquently, ''our planetary parent . . . could be crushed like a sunflower seed with no threat of violence to life as a whole.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sagan claims to be writing science fact, not fiction; however, he provides little proof to support his contentions. At his best when describing natural phenomena and stumping for a new ecological ethos, he engages in mere fatuity when promulgating his progressivist, New Age argument (''The pen I use to write belongs not to me but to the Earth, to the Earth writing a note to itself''), and he verges continually on teleology (global warming, he writes, may be the planet's way of ''ridding itself of excess humanity''). In a particularly muddled passage, Mr. Sagan compares the environmental ravages of industrialization to both cancer and pregnancy.</p>
        <p>Throughout, ''Biospheres'' is devoid of socioeconomic analysis and lacking in humanity. Sadly absent from Mr. Sagan's biocentric and technophilic scenario is any consideration of the spiritual and esthetic dimensions of a future spent in artificial, climate controlled enclosures.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
