<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Congress: Much Accomplished, Much to be Done</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="374508"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D9103AF93BA3575BC0A966958260" item-length="1048" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Congress: Much Accomplished, Much to be Done</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>Airport Expansion - The House has authorized $17.7 billion in spending over the next two years to upgrade the nation's aviation system that includes letting airports levy a tax on roundtrip airline tickets of up to $12. The tax faces strong opposition in the Senate, which has not yet acted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>Airport Expansion - The House has authorized $17.7 billion in spending over the next two years to upgrade the nation's aviation system that includes letting airports levy a tax on roundtrip airline tickets of up to $12. The tax faces strong opposition in the Senate, which has not yet acted.</p>
        <p>Airport Expansion - The House has authorized $17.7 billion in spending over the next two years to upgrade the nation's aviation system that includes letting airports levy a tax on roundtrip airline tickets of up to $12. The tax faces strong opposition in the Senate, which has not yet acted.</p>
        <p>Civil Rights - Both houses have passed nearly identical bills that would overturn or modify recent Supreme Court decisions that limited the effect of Federal laws against job discrimination. The bills would also broaden laws permitting people to collect damages in bias cases. A conference committee will seek to resolve technical differences between the two versions. President Bush has threatened a veto, saying the legislation would lead to job quotas.</p>
        <p>Clean Air - Both houses have passed legislation that would revise and expand environmental laws for the first time in 13 years. The bills vary significantly in their prescriptions for acid rain, toxic pollutants, automobile emissions and urban smog. Conferees are now faced with the difficult task of reconciling the differences.</p>
        <p>Crime - The Senate bill would include a three-year ban on nine types of assault-style weapons, greater Federal assistance to law-enforcement agencies, an expansion from 23 to 34 in the number of Federal crimes that would warrant the death penalty and streamlined Federal court reviews of death sentences. The bill that the House Judiciary Committee has passed is in some instances less sweeping than the Senate-passed version and includes emphasis on alternatives to incarceration.</p>
        <p>Family Leave - Congress passed legislation that would have required businesses with 50 or more employees to grant workers up to three months of unpaid leave at the time of the birth or adoption of a child or when a member of their immediate family falls ill. President Bush vetoed the bill. The veto was sustained in the House.</p>
        <p>Farm Programs - Both Houses have approved nearly identical legislation that would set the country's farm policy over the next five years and would cost between $54 billion and $58 billion. The bills continue government subsidy and credit programs established in 1985, set productions goals for 13 basic commodities, set limits on pollution from farms and establish new provisions for growing and selling food products without toxic chemicals. Conferees will have to resolve the differences. The Bush Administration has threatened to veto the legislation because of the cost, and Congressional leaders seem to concede that some cost-trimming is required.</p>
        <p>Housing - Both houses have passed bills that would pledge significant amounts of new housing money (spending ceilings of approximately $28 billion), both to strengthen current programs and to create new ones. The bills propose new approaches to long-standing problems, emphasizing home ownership for the poor, offering increased money to nonprofit aid groups and making it easier to link social services to housing. Significant differences exist between the versions and could prove contentious when conferees meet to resolve them.</p>
        <p>The Disabled - Congress passed and President Bush signed a measure that would guarantee disabled Americans broadened employment opportunities and greater access to public accommodations and transit systems.</p>
        <p>Aids - Congress has voted to authorize $875 million next year to provide health care to people with AIDS in cities and states hardest hit by the epidemic. The Bush Administration did not support the bill, but the President is likely to sign it.</p>
        <p>Campaign Finance - Senate and House have each passed campaign finance bills. The Senate bill would bar contributions from political action committees to candidates running for Federal office and would establish a system of voluntary spending limits depending on the size of the state. The House version would limit House candidates to $275,000 in total contributions from political action committees for each election and would establish voluntary spending limit of $550,000 per House candidate for each election cycle. Conferees will seek to resolve the differences. President Bush has made clear that he is inclined to veto either version as offering too much protection to incumbents.</p>
        <p>Child Care - The House and Senate have passed different versions of the legislation. The Senate version would spend$10 billion over four years, starting in 1991, and increase tax credits for child care. The House version is estimated to cost $27 billion over the next five years, $18 billion of which would come in tax revenues that would be lost through expanding tax credits to famlies earning under $20,270 a year. Conferees from the House and Senate Labor Committees have worked out differences in the grant portion of the two bills. The most disputed part of the legislation is the provision for an earned income tax credit and this must still be resolved by the two finance committees.</p>
        <p>Oil Spill Liability - Congress has passed bills that would sharply increases shipping companies' liabilities for oil spills, create a $1 billion fund to pay for clean-up costs in excess of shippers' liabilities, allow states to impose unlimited liability under state laws, require that most tankers be equipped with double hulls over the next 20 years and establish and expand regional response strike teams that can be called upon after a major spill. The bill is awaiting the President's signature.</p>
        <p>Military - The Senate has approved a $289 billion military program bill that would cut $18 billion from President Bush's budget request of $307 billion for the fiscal year that begins Oct. 1. The bill would cut $1 billion from the President's request $4.7 for the Strategic Defense Initiative; recommend a troop cut of 100,00 0 in the coming fiscal year, with half of the reduction from forces in Europe, and leave intact the $4.6 billion budget request for two B-2 stealth bombers. The overall plan approved by the House Armed Services Committee would cost $283 billion. It would alot $2.9 billion for the anti-missile program, recommend a troop cut of 129,000 and halt production of the B-2. Negotiations on military programs are expected to be further complicated by the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
