<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cleaner Air, Almost</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="357221"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D71139F93BA15756C0A966958260" item-length="480" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cleaner Air, Almost</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: For years, Americans demanded cleaner air and Washington did nothing. Now that the House has joined the Senate in passing legislation, a major overhaul of the air pollution laws - little more than a distant dream one year ago - seems well within reach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: For years, Americans demanded cleaner air and Washington did nothing. Now that the House has joined the Senate in passing legislation, a major overhaul of the air pollution laws - little more than a distant dream one year ago - seems well within reach.</p>
        <p>For years, Americans demanded cleaner air and Washington did nothing. Now that the House has joined the Senate in passing legislation, a major overhaul of the air pollution laws - little more than a distant dream one year ago - seems well within reach.</p>
        <p>The struggle is not over. Important differences between the House and Senate must still be resolved. The White House is rightly unhappy with a dubious and potentially costly provision that would compensate workers who lose their jobs because of the legislation.</p>
        <p>Yet the recent history of the two bills is heartening. At each step of the way, old and bitter Congressional adversaries have shown a willingness to compose their differences. That same spirit can bring a compromise measure home.</p>
        <p>Last summer, in the first big down payment on his pledge to be America's ''environment President,'' Mr. Bush proposed to tackle three problems: acid rain, airborne toxic chemicals produced by industry, and urban smog.</p>
        <p>The House and Senate approaches on acid rain are nearly identical to Mr. Bush's. They would cut harmful sulfur dioxide emissions by 10 million tons by 2001 and cap emissions thereafter. And they contain an innovative pollution-trading system that would allow clean utilities to sell ''credits'' to dirty ones. On toxic gases, the bills actually strengthen the President's original plan to require industry to slash the emissions of 191 chemicals over 10 years.</p>
        <p>The question of how to deal with urban pollution has proved most difficult of all. Nearly half the nation's smog is caused by automobiles and trucks. When Mr. Bush proposed to cut these emissions through a combination of expensive pollution controls and alternative fuels, the oil and automobile industries cranked up a huge lobbying effort.</p>
        <p>The campaign flopped. The Senate and House made Mr. Bush's proposals on tailpipe emissions even tougher. They established new fuel standards that would compel the oil companies to produce cleaner-burning gasolines. And they would require auto makers to produce a modest number of cars capable of running on super-clean non-gasoline fuels like compressed natural gas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush originally asked for one million such cars annually by 1997. When industry protested that there might not be a market - especially if alternative fuels were not widely available - the White House dropped the idea. The House revived it in two ways: a pilot program under which 300,000 alternate-fuel cars would be sold in southern California by 1997, and a program for centrally fueled fleet vehicles like mail trucks. That's narrower than the original million-car mandate, but it's still a stunning innovation.</p>
        <p>The strength of Mr. Bush's original proposal and the two bills is that they challenge industry to develop new technologies. But there's a more immediate challenge: getting a bill to the President's desk this summer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
