<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST: SATURDAY, JUNE, 23, 1990</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="363147"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BUSINESS DIGEST (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">SUMMARY</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D9143CF930A15755C0A966958260" item-length="611" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST: SATURDAY, JUNE, 23, 1990</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>The Economy</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>President Bush entered the savings and loan fray and the political battle over his Administration's handling of the crisis by announcing a plan to send ''teams of razor-sharp prosecutors and auditors'' to speed hundreds of fraud investigations. [Page 1.]  Orders for ''big ticket'' durable goods jumped 3.9 percent in May, the Commerce Department reported. Analysts said it was further evidence that the economy's sluggish manufacturing sector might be bouncing back. [32.]  Personal spending was flat in May, the Government said, in a report pointing to growing caution among consumers. [32.]</p>
        <p>Companies</p>
        <p>Next week I.B.M. will introduce a new home computer line, trying again in an area where it suffered its most embarrassing defeat. In 1983 the computer giant made its first foray into the home market with the PCjr., an ill-starred effort that ended in early 1985 after the machine flopped with consumers. [31.]  Philip Morris plans to become the world's No. 2 coffee manufacturer and marketer by buying most of Jacobs Suchard, a Swiss coffee-and-candy giant, for $3.8 billion. [31.]  Du Pont said it would design four plants to produce refrigeration chemicals that do not endanger the earth's ozone layer, but said it was continuing to delay a commitment to produce another family of compounds that would have a different use. [31.]  Coniston Partners has run out of companies to raid. One of the best-known and most-feared corporate investors of the 1980's will dismantle its $700 million investment pool and return the money to its limited partners. [31.]  A major German bank is now Donald Trump's biggest obstacle in his quest for a $65 million loan package to rescue his empire, bankers said. Several Japanese banks have come around, they said, but Dresdner Bank is refusing. [33.]  At a time of rapidly growing demand for tests of environmental hazards, many commercial laboratories are producing misleading and inaccurate information. [48.]  Quaker Oats' sales and earnings for the year will be flat or ''slightly lower'' than last year, the chairman said, citing persistent softness in cereal and pet food. [33.]</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>The West German Government will guarantee a $3 billion bank credit for the Soviet Union in an effort to bolster the flagging Gorbachev reform program. It is the largest single credit the Soviet Union has ever received from Western banks. [1.]  At the U.N., Nelson Mandela pressed his call for continued economic sanctions to force change in South Africa. [8.]</p>
        <p>Markets</p>
        <p>Stocks tumbled late in the day as program traders moved in heavily, selling along a broad front. The Dow plunged 44.55, to 2,857.18, bringing the loss for the week to 78.71. [31.]  Prices of Treasury securities were slightly higher despite several seemingly negative currents swirling about the markets. [34.]  Activity in the currency markets centered on Canada's dollar, which fell against the U.S. dollar, as the deadline approached for Canada to approve a much-disputed constitutional accord. [39.]  Frozen pork belly futures fell the permitted daily limit of 2 cents a pound for the fifth time in the last seven sessions. [39.]</p>
        <p>Today's Columns</p>
        <p>When younger family members are involved in managing a business, their contribution has value for estate-tax purposes, a court has ruled. Your Money. [32.]  A method of evaluating a thoroughbred by computer has been patented. Drawing on the technology of jet-fighter simulators, the system analyzes a horse's gait and reproduces it in a mechanical, computer-driven steed. Patents. [32.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
