<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From the Folks Who Brought Us Winter</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="391883"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SACKS, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">VOLLMANN, WILLIAM T</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ICE-SHIRT, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D91F26E232BC4852DFB66F958A" item-length="1081" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From the Folks Who Brought Us Winter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID SACKS; David Sacks is at work on an encyclopedia of the ancient Greek world.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SACKS, DAVID</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>THE ICE-SHIRT</p>
        <p>By William T. Vollmann.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 415 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>THE ICE-SHIRT</p>
        <p>By William T. Vollmann.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 415 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $19.95.</p>
        <p>THE ICE-SHIRT</p>
        <p>By William T. Vollmann.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 415 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $19.95.</p>
        <p>Imagine a performance of Wagner's ''Ring'' cycle directed by Sam Peckinpah, with a new libretto by J. R. R. Tolkien and occasional music by Aaron Copland, and you'll be getting the feel of this ambitious, often enthralling novel about the Vikings' arrival in North America, in the blissful place they called Vinland, circa A.D. 1000. ''The Ice-Shirt'' contains notes and glossaries indicating that William T. Vollmann has drawn on medieval Norse sagas, legends of the Micmac Indians and Greenland Inuit, and his own travels along the North Atlantic seaboard. But his main source seems to be his powerful imagination, with which he imposes a unifying theme on this mass of material.</p>
        <p>''The Ice-Shirt'' is the first of seven projected novels about the changing American landscape and the relationship between pioneers and Native Americans. The story's melancholy prescience of doom, a feature borrowed from Norse literature, is well suited to this somber topic: without harping on modern-day racism or pollution, Mr. Vollmann clearly foreshadows them.</p>
        <p>The author of two prior books - a novel, ''You Bright and Risen Angels,'' and a collection, ''The Rainbow Stories'' - Mr. Vollmann has a busy, fabulist style that has been compared with Thomas Pynchon's; like Mr. Pynchon (whose most recent novel, set in modern California, is titled ''Vineland''), Mr. Vollmann plays on the question of America's loss of promise. ''The landscape around us,'' he writes sadly, ''is but a shadow of the landscape within us.'' His book is a stunning experiment, albeit not a completely successful one.</p>
        <p>Most historians now believe that the Vikings probably did sail here 500 years before Columbus. Norse-style ruins have been uncovered in Newfoundland, and there are two medieval Icelandic prose epics, the ''Graenlendinga Saga'' and ''Eirik's Saga,'' that describe the accidental discovery and brief colonization of Vinland the Good, a fertile, wooded coastline somewhere southwest of Greenland, possibly in present-day New England. Grapes and wheat grew wild there, the rivers teemed with salmon and, the ''Graenlendinga Saga'' says, ''there was never any frost all winter.'' The colonists encountered the native inhabitants, whom they bilked at trade. Then, after battles with these people and a bloody internal quarrel, the survivors sailed home to Greenland.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vollmann begins his version of this story with an expansive, entertaining account of the grisly feuds in Norway that sent refugees like Eirik the Red voyaging westward, first to Iceland, then to Greenland and beyond. The central conceit of ''The Ice-Shirt'' is that the white people brought frost with them to Vinland: they infected the New World with the insane greed and homicidal thirst for power that was rife in the Old World; and so Vinland eventually became snowbound in winter, like Scandinavia. (Symbolism aside, this fits with the fact that the North Atlantic climate grew colder during the later Middle Ages.) Moreover, the novel says, the pollution was deliberate. For Mr. Vollmann takes from the sagas a villainous secondary character - Freydis, Eirik's illegitimate daughter - and makes her into a central figure who comes west on a mission of evil, to ruin Vinland. In her jealous thirst for power, Freydis puts on the Ice-Shirt; that is, she makes a pact with the Devil. In Inuit folklore, Amortortak is a demon ''whose touch is death''; in Viking parlance, Blue-Shirt was a landmark mountain glacier in Greenland. The novel creates of these two a composite figure, who is cleverly tied into old Norse legends of Queen Hel in her realm of ice, and into American Indian stories of the cosmic Evil Twin. Mr. Vollmann's Amortortak is an international fiend, manifested as ice and cold. Although frost may not be the obvious associate of evil in these days of global warming, the reader soon falls into step and savors the interplay of symbols: ''You Icelanders,'' the ice demon declares, ''are all bonded to Me by virtue of your blue eyes.''</p>
        <p>Without apparent strain, the story interweaves numerous characters, sea voyages, murders and supernatural horrors, digressing with relish. The medieval cycle is broken up by chapters giving Mr. Vollmann's own impressions of certain relevant places, such as Iceland and Baffin Island. These modern interpolations work surprisingly well - for instance, the tensions between the Inuit and the ethnic Danes in present-day Greenland, as observed by the author, seem to descend in a straight line from the Vikings' exploitations of long ago.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vollmann has a knack for stringing a sentence with simple words in a way that transports the reader. King Gudrod, he writes, ''sat in his high-seat; he read the runes of his bench-boards; he stood up roaring, at which his house-carles rattled their spears with a gladsome shout. Soon thereafter he went a-Viking against the other Kings.'' But there are also some false notes, most of them deliberately supplied to jar the reader and point out a moral, as in this description of human sacrifice in a pagan grove: ''If the gods were delighted the dim white bodies vanished in the water, transubstantiated into heaven like the lucky inhabitants of Hiroshima.''</p>
        <p>The problems come at the end. Three quarters of the way through the book, the novelty of Mr. Vollmann's vision starts to wear off, yet he doesn't replace it - as we wish he would - by shooting the narrative toward a goal. The suspense created by Freydis's evil quest turns out to be somewhat false, and the story dissolves into a series of chapters that, however well written, don't bring the plot forward. There is a delightfully ghastly tour of hell, in the best epic tradition, followed by a battle scene between Vikings and Indians (taken from the ''Graenlendinga Saga'' and genuinely improved by the author's elaborations). Although this episode conveys the Indians' moral victory over the invaders, the frost comes to Vinland anyway - we're not sure how.</p>
        <p>And yet, despite these disappointments, ''The Ice-Shirt'' impresses mightily in its scope, its scene-painting and its enciphered social messages. We hate the Vikings' rapacity, yet Mr. Vollmann also lets us admire their bold aspirations. As he writes of the colonists in Greenland, ''It required a desperate distracted ambition to make anyone go there. But there are always to be found dreamers who will do anything.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
