<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Washington's Mood Worries Detroit</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="381415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSERVATION OF RESOURCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUEL EFFICIENCY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEVIN, DORON P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRYAN, RICHARD H (SEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D6103DF930A3575AC0A966958260" item-length="1523" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Washington's Mood Worries Detroit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DORON P. LEVIN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEVIN, DORON P</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Sept. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As fuel prices climb, a jittery auto industry is watching how lawmakers in Washington react.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As fuel prices climb, a jittery auto industry is watching how lawmakers in Washington react.</p>
        <p>Rising oil prices make passage of stricter fuel-economy standards more likely, although not inevitable, according to auto makers. The mere discussion of the idea worries them. For several years, American auto companies have relied heavily on the fat profit margins on full-size cars to buttress their dwindling earnings.</p>
        <p>''Any time people get emotional, you can get a knee-jerk reaction that isn't thought through,'' said Joel Pitcoff, a sales and marketing analyst for the Ford Motor Company.</p>
        <p>Japanese auto makers oppose the bill as well, but for a different reason. The bill proposes a gradual percentage increase in each company's fuel-mileage average. Since Japanese-made autos are already more fuel efficient than those of American companies, raising their fuel-economy levels by a set percentage would force them to attain a higher standard than their American competitors.</p>
        <p>The Persian Gulf crisis has also rekindled a longstanding public debate over who should bear the responsibility for reducing imports of oil.</p>
        <p>Conservation and environmental groups supporting the Senate bill, which is sponsored by Richard H. Bryan, a Nevada Democrat, favor tightening efficiency standards for cars, which they believe will force auto makers to develop various energy-saving technologies. Fuel conservation was being urged by these groups even before the Iraq crisis as a way to alleviate global warming.</p>
        <p>They point out that the current rules on fuel economy have not forced anyone to do without big or powerful cars, as some auto makers had predicted when the corporate-average fuel-economy standard was developed after the energy crisis in the early 1970's.</p>
        <p>Opposition From the Auto Makers</p>
        <p>The auto makers, with support from Administration officials, oppose a tighter Federal fuel-economy standard. Last month, Energy Secretary James D. Watkins introduced a ''short-term strategy'' for stabilizing oil markets by raising domestic production and encouraging conservation. He suggested that the Government should not bog down stabilization efforts by trying to revise the fuel-economy standard and other issues that are bound to involve lengthy debates.</p>
        <p>For their part, auto makers contend that further big gains in energy efficiency are not possible without limiting the selection of cars that Americans have grown accustomed to having.</p>
        <p>Yet, as long as gasoline remains relatively cheap and readily available, they argue, drivers will not buy highly efficient vehicles in great number. Indeed, fuel is now so cheap on a historical basis, when adjusted for inflation, that even the recent run-up in prices is not financially significant for most drivers, they say.</p>
        <p>''Fuel prices have gone up only 15 to 20 cents a gallon, and the principal effect of that on car buying is short term,'' said George Eads, chief economist for the General Motors Corporation.</p>
        <p>But analysts agree that much higher prices or a fuel shortage would sharply reduce sales of big cars.</p>
        <p>Auto makers argue that if the nation wants to be less reliant on foreign oil, lawmakers should pass some type of energy tax to raise the price of fuel, which would in turn stimulate consumer demand for fuel-efficient vehicles. The industry has no consensus on precisely what type of regulation it wants, but an energy tax is not likely to win wide support in Washington.</p>
        <p>The Chrysler Corporation and Ford support a tax specifically on gasoline, although Ford stipulates that the proceeds should be used to reduce the Federal budget deficit. G.M. has opposed a gasoline tax but favors a broader tax on all forms of energy. G.M. and Ford are both against increasing the corporate-average fuel- economy standard. Lee A. Iacocca, the chairman of Chrysler, is not, but he says an increase to 40 miles a gallon is too great.</p>
        <p>Auto executives dismiss the argument sometimes advanced by conservation groups that the auto makers possess energy-saving technology but refuse to put it on the market because of the high cost of doing so.</p>
        <p>''Everyone thinks there's something on the shelf we're withholding,'' said Edward Mertz, vice president in charge of G.M.'s Buick division. ''The problem is plain old physics. We would have to take cars out of production'' if fuel-efficiency requirements became too stringent.</p>
        <p>Two-Ton Buick Roadmaster</p>
        <p>Mr. Mertz was speaking on Tuesday in Novi, Mich., at the introduction of Buick's 1991 models. Among the new cars scheduled to appear in the coming year is the Buick Roadmaster, a two-ton behemoth that is bigger and heavier than most cars Buick has built in the last two decades.</p>
        <p>The average fuel efficiency of new domestic cars increased sharply between 1980 and 1988, but has declined slightly in the last two years as consumers have chosen bigger cars. To improve fuel efficiency without sacrificing power or comfort, auto makers say, they must overcome many technical hurdles caused by the potential fuel-efficiency, safety and clean-air regulations, which are costly and often conflict with one another.</p>
        <p>For example, safety devices like airbags are required by law but add weight and reduce fuel efficiency. Two-stroke engines generate more horsepower for their weight than four-stroke engines now in use in cars. But their emissions will not meet standards included in a proposed clean-air act now pending in Congress.</p>
        <p>Martin Zimmerman, Ford's chief economist, said the cost of meeting higher fuel-efficiency standards, clean-air rules and other Federal regulations at the same time would be much more expensive than if the standards were met separately.</p>
        <p>Not Enough Engineers</p>
        <p>Richard Donnelly, the head of G.M.'s engine division, said he could not find enough engineers and scientists with the necessary skills to work on the various regulatory projects.</p>
        <p>Still, many weapons remain in the industry's fuel-efficiency arsenal. G.M. says the average fuel efficiency of its cars has improved 130 percent since the mid-1970's, and Mr. Mertz of Buick believes the improvements will continue, albeit at a reduced pace, as engineers take pounds off various components by developing lighter materials.</p>
        <p>Thomas Kowaleski, a Chrysler spokesman, said the auto maker produces about 300,000 four-cylinder engines a year but could triple that number if the demand increased. ''We're working on projects like the two-stroke engine, but we want to make sure technology is perfected before we introduce it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''No one wants to have trouble merging on interstates,'' he said, referring to the problems that many cars had in the early 1970's when clean-air requirements led to engines that did not work well or provide much acceleration.</p>
        <p>Much of the theoretical basis for Senator Bryan's bill - which assumes that auto makers can come up with technical answers for problems of efficiency without radically changing how cars perform - comes from Deborah Bleviss, executive director of the International Institute for Energy Conservation.</p>
        <p>'No One Wonderful Technology'</p>
        <p>Ms. Bleviss, a physicist by training, argued in a book published in 1988 that technologies like two-stroke engines, lighter-weight materials, electronic engine controls and continously variable transmission - a high-efficiency replacement for automatic transmission - hold great promise.</p>
        <p>''There's no one wonderful technology'' that would enable auto makers to average 40 miles a gallon, she said. ''When Detroit says the two-stroke engine can't meet emissions requirements, you have to take that with a grain of salt. It's in Detroit's interest to say that.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Bleviss said a stringent fuel-economy standard must be accompanied by other laws to dampen demand for fuel, as well as by Government-sponsored research to help with the burden of developing new technologies. Rather than an energy tax, she said, she leaned toward auto registration fees on a sliding scale based on the vehicle, and sales taxes that provide an incentive for fuel efficiency.</p>
        <p>David Cole, a professor at the University of Michigan in charge of transportation studies, says auto makers would have trouble ''technically and financially'' in meeting a 40-mile-a-gallon standard.</p>
        <p>''With energy ridiculously cheap, there are still questions as to whether customers would accept vehicles that would satisfy this law,'' Mr. Cole said. ''They just might decide to get themselves new politicians.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
