<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tanker Blaze Out; Bacteria Test Begins</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="361523"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEGA BORG (TANKER)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TANKERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GULF OF MEXICO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">TEXAS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORWAY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tankers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DE1231F935A25755C0A966958260" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tanker Blaze Out; Bacteria Test Begins</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>GALVESTON, Tex., June 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: On a day of jubilance and optimism, firefighters today extinguished the fire on a Norwegian supertanker and stopped the flow of oil. Minutes later scientists sprayed natural bacteria across a 40-acre patch of floating oil in the first open-sea test of a novel method for controlling oil pollution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: On a day of jubilance and optimism, firefighters today extinguished the fire on a Norwegian supertanker and stopped the flow of oil. Minutes later scientists sprayed natural bacteria across a 40-acre patch of floating oil in the first open-sea test of a novel method for controlling oil pollution.</p>
        <p>On a day of jubilance and optimism, firefighters today extinguished the fire on a Norwegian supertanker and stopped the flow of oil. Minutes later scientists sprayed natural bacteria across a 40-acre patch of floating oil in the first open-sea test of a novel method for controlling oil pollution.</p>
        <p>The two events, which took place under brilliant skies and on rolling seas 57 miles south of here in the Gulf of Mexico, ended one of the worst shipping accidents in this region and may have opened a new era in overcoming toxic pollution.</p>
        <p>''This is a wonderful sight,'' said Garry Mauro, the Texas Land Commissioner, whose agency sponsored the test. ''Over here, we have an entirely new technology for cleaning up spills. Behind me, the fire is out. It's what we've been waiting for for a week.''</p>
        <p>An explosion rocked the 885-foot supertanker, the Mega Borg, at 11:30 P.M. on June 8, hours after she began transferring her 41-million-gallon cargo of light Angolan crude to a smaller ship. Almost three million gallons had been transferred when the blast ruptured some of the ship's cargo tanks, ignited an enormous fire and killed two sailors. Two more sailors, thought to have been in the engine room, are missing and presumed dead.</p>
        <p>Smoke Clears and Gushing Stops</p>
        <p>The ferocious fire, which burned for a week, had 100-foot flames and generated temperatures high enough to nearly melt the ship's steel superstructure. But at 10:10 A.M. today, the thick, black smoke that has hidden the stern of the tanker suddenly diminished. Oil stopped gushing into the sea, and fireboats backed away from the wreck and headed to their home ports.</p>
        <p>Coast Guard officials said that metal in the stern was still hot and that until it cooled, the fire would not officially be declared over.</p>
        <p>Three miles east of the ship, scientists from Alpha Environmental Inc., a biotechnology company in Austin, Tex., mixed 100 pounds of bacteria with seawater on the deck of a Coast Guard boat. At 12:10 P.M., pumps were turned on and a cream-colored stream of naturally occurring bacteria was sprayed on the oiled surface of the Gulf.</p>
        <p>The bacteria, collected from around the world by Dr. Carl H. Oppenheimer, a marine microbologist, have turned toxic petroleum compounds into water, carbon dioxide and harmless fatty acids in numerous tests in Texas and elsewhere since the mid-1970's. The results of the open-sea test will not be known for several days, said Dr. Oppenheimer, a co-founder of the five-year-old company. The 40-acre patch was marked with white bouys, and scientists will monitor the bacteria and collect data from a Texas A&amp;M University research vessel.</p>
        <p>Test May Change Methods</p>
        <p>If the test is successful, it could make obsolete the cleanup equipment and skimming boats like those that have been maneuvering behind the Mega Borg, state officials said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mauro said he was ready to use thousands of pounds of bacteria over the weekend if there was a strong indication that the microbes were doing their jobs.</p>
        <p>''We've had a chance to turn a disaster into an opportunity,'' he said as he stood aboard the Coast Guard boat.</p>
        <p>The notion of using bacteria to reduce pollution is far from new. Municipal sewage systems have used bacteria to break down wastes for more than a century. But in the 1980's, scientists began to consider applying microbes to reducing toxic chemical pollution.</p>
        <p>Bacteria Improved</p>
        <p>Bacteria are known to be capable of consuming the hydrogen and carbon molecules of petroleum and turning them into harmless substances. But the pace of the degradation is often slow.</p>
        <p>In the last few years scientists have vastly increased the microbes' rate of reproduction and thus their ability to consume petrochemicals.</p>
        <p>A small industry has grown around the technical advance. Industry executives estimate that up to 40 companies now produce bacteria in the United States for environmental applications and perhaps 300 more companies use bacteria and fertilizers for cleaning up industrial wastes.</p>
        <p>In Alaska, fertilizers made in France are being applied to rocky beaches to encourage the growth of bacteria to eat oil spilled from the supertanker Exxon Valdez, which went aground in March 1989. State officials said the technique, known as bioremediation, was used on 76 miles of beaches last year with modest success.</p>
        <p>Almost Perfect Conditions</p>
        <p>The Mega Borg disaster provided almost perfect conditions for testing the release of living bacteria. The Mega Borg lost at least 4.3 million gallons of her cargo, according to the latest Coast Guard estimate. Most was burned or evaporated from the warm Gulf waters.</p>
        <p>The 12,000 to 40,000 gallons of light crude oil left in the water should prove a ready source of food for the bacteria and the warm weather will enhance their growth, Dr. Oppenheimer said.</p>
        <p>If the bacteria work, they will leave behind nothing but clear water. But Dr. Croom and other experts cautioned that microbes work best when they are confined to small areas of pollution. The size of the oil slick, and its patchiness, could turn the experiment into a failure.</p>
        <p>The bacterial tests continue Saturday when Alpha Environmental will launch flotation booms to corral two much smaller patches of oil.</p>
        <p>''This is the beginning of a new concept to use natural degradation to remove some of our worldwide pollution,'' Dr. Oppenheimer said. ''This could be the start of something very important or all of us.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
