<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Revenues, Not Taxes</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="364332"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WICKER, TOM</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">GRAMM-RUDMAN-HOLLINGS ACT</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D61E3CF93BA15755C0A966958260" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Revenues, Not Taxes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Tom Wicker; A.M. Rosenthal is traveling.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WICKER, TOM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: If anything can, President Bush's flip-flop on taxes, plus two others on spotted owls and off-shore oil drilling, ought to bring his approval rating down from the unreal 70-plus percent he's been enjoying.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: If anything can, President Bush's flip-flop on taxes, plus two others on spotted owls and off-shore oil drilling, ought to bring his approval rating down from the unreal 70-plus percent he's been enjoying.</p>
        <p>If anything can, President Bush's flip-flop on taxes, plus two others on spotted owls and off-shore oil drilling, ought to bring his approval rating down from the unreal 70-plus percent he's been enjoying.</p>
        <p>But don't bank on it. That kind of popularity may be based less on issues than on a nice-guy exterior, a folks-next-door syntax and a motherly First Lady with a hometown hairdo.</p>
        <p>Still, since Mr. Bush just recently reversed himself on helping the third world protect the ozone layer, for him to take three more about-face steps in a single day suggests that the heat is making him uncomfortable in the kitchen.</p>
        <p>Partially reneging on spotted owls as an endangered species, while limiting the support Republicans have been giving to off-shore oil drilling, pleased neither side of either issue. When at the same time Mr. Bush abandoned his no-new-taxes pledge - the hard core of his 1988 campaign, and of his party's strategy in the Reagan-Bush years - he outraged Republicans running for office in 1990. They think he sabotaged their best issue to avoid a recession when he runs for re-election in 1992.</p>
        <p>Democrats, however, should temper their glee. On the tax issue, there may be method in Mr. Bush's alleged surrender.</p>
        <p>His list of things that need to be done to fight the deficit included code words for the capital gains tax break he lusts for. The easiest new revenues, however, would be obtained from higher sin taxes and other excises. If that's the final mix, the Democrats will have been conned into a tax benefit for the rich and a regressive tax increase for everybody else.</p>
        <p>The hit list also included ''entitlement and mandatory program reform.'' That parses out to some kind of limits on Social Security, retirement, health and other benefits for people who tend to vote Democratic. Is that a good swap in return for new taxes on many of the same people? And to pay down a deficit that does not clearly and immediately threaten them, if at all?</p>
        <p>Worse, and even if a new tax burden is spread equitably among rich and poor, Mr. Bush can and probably will campaign for Republican candidates next fall on the premise: ''Don't blame me. The spendthrift Democrats made me do it.''</p>
        <p>Worse still, maybe there's more truth than poetry in what some Republicans are counting on, that Mr. Bush only called for ''new tax revenues'' - not for new taxes. That leaves him what supple politicians A. M. Rosenthal is traveling. admire as ''wiggle room'' to back out of the arrangement if the Democrats are insistent on raising taxes he doesn't want to raise - say, on the incomes of the rich. He could, and probably would, then tell the electorate next fall: ''They tried to raise your taxes and I wouldn't stand for it.''</p>
        <p>He may even have been right the first time, that new taxes are not needed. There's no automatic link between the deficit and interest rates, despite cries to the contrary. A substantial reduction in the Federal deficit could be damaging to what is at best a tentative economy. And the Gramm-Rudman limit of $64 billion on a 1991 Federal deficit likely to be $160 billion can't be reached without disastrous recessionary effect.</p>
        <p>If the deficit is not reduced to that level, however, the foolish Gramm-Rudman law will mandate draconian budget cuts to reach it. The Republicans do not want to make such cuts in military expenditures; the Democrats are anxious to avoid them in non-military programs; and no one wants a recession.</p>
        <p>The threat of Gramm-Rudman, therefore, far more than the more touted threat of the deficit itself, is the major reason why negotiators for both parties want deficit reduction -even at the cost of higher taxes, and even though they concede that they'll still have to adjust the Gramm-Rudman limits upward.</p>
        <p>Why not repeal a bad law and be done with it, if its supposed disciplinary effect is going to be eased anyway? And does Ronald Reagan's deficit, which has been around for nearly a decade without producing the various catastrophes so often predicted, really demand a tax increase?</p>
        <p>A vitally needed public investment (an important form of savings) in education, research, the environment, roads, bridges, housing, renewable energy sources, etc., would serve far better purposes. In addition to meeting real needs, such investment would put thousands of idle Americans to work, including many now headed for the welfare rolls and/or the penitentiary. That in turn would produce the new tax revenues Mr. Bush finally admits are necessary -but without new taxes.</p>
        <p>IN THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
