<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Is Assailed at Geneva Talks For Backing Out of Ozone Plan</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="352150"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT (IBRD)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DA1F3DF933A25756C0A966958260" item-length="955" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Is Assailed at Geneva Talks For Backing Out of Ozone Plan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A White House decision to oppose financial aid for developing countries to phase out chemicals that are destroying the Earth's ozone layer was sharply criticized today at an international meeting in Geneva.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A White House decision to oppose financial aid for developing countries to phase out chemicals that are destroying the Earth's ozone layer was sharply criticized today at an international meeting in Geneva.</p>
        <p>A White House decision to oppose financial aid for developing countries to phase out chemicals that are destroying the Earth's ozone layer was sharply criticized today at an international meeting in Geneva.</p>
        <p>The Administration's policy decision on the international control of chlorofluorocarbons was made by Richard G. Darman, the Director of the Office of Management and Budget, and John H. Sununu, the White House chief of staff, over the opposition of the Environmental Protection Agency's Administrator, William K. Reilly, in preparation for the Geneva meeting.</p>
        <p>Roman Popadiuk, a White House deputy press secretary, said today that the Administration supported financial aid to developing countries to help them deal with the chemicals, but that such aid should come from money already available to the World Bank or other international lending institutions.</p>
        <p>'Mind-Boggling,' Norwegian Says</p>
        <p>Jan Thompson, director general of Norway's Environment Ministry, said it was ''mind-boggling'' and ''totally unacceptable'' that the United States should back down from an agreement made by industrial nations at a conference in March to provide a new fund for financial and technical assistance to stop using chlorofluorocarbons and other chemicals depleting the protective ozone in the upper atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Ozone in the upper atmosphere protects the Earth's surface from excessive ultraviolet radiation from the sun, which can cause skin cancer and cataracts, and damage crops and wildlife. An international consensus has been reached that virtually all chlorofluorocarbons and related chemicals that destroy atmospherical ozone should be eliminated by early in the next century.</p>
        <p>A member of the Brazilian delegation expressed strong disappointment with the United States position, saying that adherence of the developing nations to a treaty to end the use of the chemical substances ''depends on the political will of our partners in the developed world.''</p>
        <p>Chlorofluorocarbons are widely used as refrigerants and solvents, for insulation foam and in a variety of other products.</p>
        <p>Every speaker from other countries expressed surprise and dismay at the United States' stand, an American official at the Geneva meeting said.</p>
        <p>''This was a major embarrassment for the United States,'' the official said. Earlier Annoyance With U.S.  The criticism of the United States in Geneva recalled last month's White House conference on climate change here, which angered European delegates because it concentrated almost exclusively on the need for more research into the scientific and economic issues surrounding the issue of global warming.</p>
        <p>European officials said then that the focus of worldwide environmental efforts should now be on ways of coping with anticipated global warming and other climate changes in the next century.</p>
        <p>The White House has particularly annoyed Norway by refusing to let Mr. Reilly accept its invitation to attend a conference on the environment and economic development to be held in the city of Bergen next month, Administration officials said today.</p>
        <p>Darman Provokes Europeans</p>
        <p>The decision to oppose a new fund to help poor countries adhere to the ozone treaty follows a speech by Mr. Darman at Harvard University last week in which he assailed ''radical Greens'' for seeking to impose a system of ''global management'' to protect the environment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Darman said that the label ''environmentalist'' is ''a green mask under which different faces of politico-ideology can hide.'' It would be, he said, a ''regrettable irony,'' if just as American values have prevailed ''in the East-West struggle, they were to be lost in what some environmentalists like to term the struggle for ''global management.''</p>
        <p>The Geneva meeting today, at which about 50 nations were represented, is preparing for a conference in London next month called by the United Nations to strengthen the Montreal Protocol, a treaty that calls for a 50 percent reduction in the production and use of chlorofluorocarbons by 2000.</p>
        <p>Members of Congress, environmentalists, a spokesman for the industry, and some members of the Administration criticized the White House decision to oppose new money for the developing countries. They said that it could undermine efforts to strengthen the ozone treaty.</p>
        <p>Chemical Lobbyist's Argument</p>
        <p>Kevin J. Fay, executive director of an industry association that represents chlorofluorocarbon producers and users, said the industry strongly supports the fund. He noted that the United States' contribution to the $100 million fund would only be about $15 million or $20 million a year and could easily come out of the $5 billion in excise taxes that the Government is imposing on his industry over the next five years.</p>
        <p>Republican and Democratic Senators sent separate letters to President Bush today, expressing disappointment with the decision and urging him to change his mind. The Republican letter, initiated by Senator John H. Chafee of Rhode Island, said that the decision ''isolated the United States and put us in an untenable position.''</p>
        <p>David Doniger, who is observing the Geneva meeting as a lawyer for the Natural Resources Defense Council, said that the White House decision ''is a penny-pinching blunder that endangers consensus for a global phase-out of CFC's,'' shorthand for chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>India and China, two countries that have plans for greater use of the substances, have made it clear that they will not join the treaty to restrict or eliminate the use of the chemicals without substantial financial and technical assistance. India has also said that it would urge developing nations who have signed the Montreal Protocol to withdraw if there is no money.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
