<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Watkins Defends Policy on Warming</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="324970"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WATKINS, JAMES D (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUNUNU, JOHN H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D9173EF93AA35751C0A966958260" item-length="635" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Watkins Defends Policy on Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Energy Secretary James D. Watkins today offered a vigorous defense of the Bush Administration's policy on global warming, asserting that all top policy makers agreed on the President's approach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Energy Secretary James D. Watkins today offered a vigorous defense of the Bush Administration's policy on global warming, asserting that all top policy makers agreed on the President's approach.</p>
        <p>Energy Secretary James D. Watkins today offered a vigorous defense of the Bush Administration's policy on global warming, asserting that all top policy makers agreed on the President's approach.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists have charged that President Bush's speech to an international conference on climate change earlier this week had been softened by John H. Sununu, the White House chief of staff, over the objections of the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Watkins said today that the speech was written from an outline that the energy chief drew up with William K. Reilly, the head of the Environmental Protection Agency. A spokesman for the agency confirmed that this afternoon.</p>
        <p>An Administration official who followed the negotiations involved in preparing the speech said today that Mr. Reilly and Mr. Watkins were, in fact, in agreement, along with Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d and Dr. D. Allan Bromley, the President's science adviser. The official said those advisers fought a largely successful battle to keep Mr. Sununu from vitiating the text.</p>
        <p>Mr. Watkins denied there had been any disagreements. ''I don't know of any standoff, and I'm in the middle of it,'' he said to a group of reporters he called to his office. Mr. Reilly told a group of reporters from trade newsletters that the Bush speech had been ''fully responsive,'' and that those who were critical of it ''misgauged the moment and the reality of what negotiations are all about,'' said Luke Lester, a spokesman for the agency.</p>
        <p>Speech Viewed as Key Step</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly viewed the speech was a major step forward, because the President was the first head of state to address the group, the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, the spokesman said. The group was formed under the auspices of the United Nations Environmental Program and the World Meteorological Association.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Reilly also said, ''the President is calling the shots and he is concerned about both the environment and the economy.''</p>
        <p>The agency chiefs made their separate statements on the eve of a hearing to be held by the Department of Energy on warming of the of the earth due to atmospheric pollutants, much as heat is trapped in a greenhouse, and the role of science in energy problems.</p>
        <p>The hearing is part of a series organized by Mr. Watkins to develop a ''national energy strategy'' and will center on the role of the oceans in moderating global temperatures and absorbing carbon dioxide, a gas produced by combustion that is believed responsible for half of the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>Many environmentalists have called for moves to reduce carbon dioxide production. Mr. Watkins said today that ''it would be very precipitous, and totally unsupported, to set some kind of a limit right now.'' People with scientific backgrounds realize there are still too many uncertainties to undertake expensive control measures, he said. Non-scientists are simply becoming emotional on the topic, he said.</p>
        <p>More Research Money Sought</p>
        <p>Environmental groups have noted that the Energy Department has asked for more money for research, but has also proposed cutting conservation financing in half, to $212.6 million in the 1991 fiscal year from $411.5 million in the current year.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Watkins said the budget for conservation, which goes for such purposes as adding insulation to the houses of poor people, was being cut because the states were already failing to spend all the money available. Meanwhile, he said, his department and others, and researchers at Government laboratories, were making progress in energy conservation technologies and in learning about pollution and global climate issues, even as environmentalists complained that not enough was happening.</p>
        <p>''It's time to get the glass half full on this thing,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
