<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Perrier to Return to U.S. Early Next Month</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="332623"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOTTLED WATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BENZENE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PERRIER GROUP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAMIREZ, ANTHONY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDB103CF934A35750C0A966958260" item-length="886" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Perrier to Return to U.S. Early Next Month</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAMIREZ, ANTHONY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Pulled off the market because of a contamination scare, Perrier sparkling water is returning - today in France and by early April in America.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Pulled off the market because of a contamination scare, Perrier sparkling water is returning - today in France and by early April in America.</p>
        <p>Pulled off the market because of a contamination scare, Perrier sparkling water is returning - today in France and by early April in America.</p>
        <p>The marketing challenge for Perrier, the leader in the worldwide mineral water market, is to convince consumers of the validity of the pre-recall advertising slogan, ''It's pure. It's Perrier.'' To that end, the United States importer of Perrier said yesterday that the return of the bottles next month would be accompanied by a $25 million marketing campaign. In newspaper ads, Perrier will acknowledge the contamination troubles and declare that ''the problem has been fixed.'' But new Perrier radio ads will take a whimsical approach while the water is still scarce.</p>
        <p>Water imported for American supermarkets and restaurants will still appear in the familiar green pear-shaped bottles but will carry the designation ''nouvelle production.''</p>
        <p>Because Perrier is bottled at one source, in Vergeze in southern France, it will take months to refill the worldwide pipeline. Much of Western Europe will get Perrier in the next two weeks. But supplies will not reach Japan and the Far East until mid-April.</p>
        <p>Full redistribution in the United States will take 8 to 16 weeks. Time for bottling, loading, shipping, clearing customs, distribution and delivery by trucks varies for different cities. So while the East Coast will begin receiving new bottles in early April, the rest of the country will get them later. Recall Began in U.S.  Perrier was recalled on Feb. 9 in the United States and on Feb. 14 worldwide. Source Perrier, the Paris-based parent company, said world stocks of the mineral water totaled 160 million bottles and were worth $70 million. About 72 million bottles were in the United States.</p>
        <p>Perrier's troubles stemmed from a failure to monitor adequately a buildup of trace amounts of the chemical benzene in the spring's carbon dioxide gas used in processing Perrier. Benzene in extremely high doses is believed to cause cancer.</p>
        <p>Ronald V. Davis, president of Perrier Group of America, told reporters that company-commissioned surveys show that consumers have a high awareness of the benzene problem but that four out of five plan to buy Perrier when it is again available.</p>
        <p>'I Will Take It Back'</p>
        <p>In New York, Lutece, the French restaurant, has substituted Saratoga, a domestic sparkling water distributed by Evian Waters. Andre Soltner, owner and chef, said ''very few'' customers were asking for Perrier but added, ''When Perrier comes back, I will take it back.''</p>
        <p>In Berkeley, Chez Panisse reported a similar customer reaction. ''I haven't noticed any tragic responses,'' said Richard W. Mazzera, the business manager. While the restaurant has substituted Levissima, an Italian sparkling water, Chez Panisse will also take back Perrier.</p>
        <p>Last year, Perrier sold $119 million worth of Perrier in the United States. Mr. Davis expects to recover 80 percent of that business in 18 months. Perrier Group includes nine domestic brands, among them the best-selling Arrowhead brand, a still water like tap water. Total sales for all Perrier Group brands in the United States in 1989 were $640 million.</p>
        <p>The American marketing campaign comes at a time when competitors, especially No. 2 Evian Waters of America Inc., are trying to make inroads in Perrier's shelf space in supermarkets and convenience stores, where most bottled water is sold. Mr. Davis acknowledged that the Perrier brand lost about 50 percent of its shelf space during the recall. Perrier Group filled the remaining space with some of its domestic brands.</p>
        <p>'Definitely a Mistake'</p>
        <p>The first phase of the marketing campaign begins today with radio and print advertisements, including a full-page ad that appears on page A9 of today's New York Times, and is built around the slogan ''Perrier. Worth waiting for.'' The ads, in major newspapers nationwide, declare that ''for a product known for its purity,'' the benzene problem ''was definitely a mistake.''</p>
        <p>Perrier has also hired the Second City improvisational group for radio skits about a mythical Perrier News Network and its ''sightings'' of bottles as they appear around the country. In one such ad, a ''PNN'' announcer asks a restaurant manager whether happy customers are singing and dancing because Perrier is back. No, says the deadpan manager, they are standing around drinking Perrier, enjoying it ''just like before.''</p>
        <p>Hal Riney &amp; Partners, a San Francisco ad agency, is still developing a new campaign for Perrier.</p>
        <p>Monitoring Advanced</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Perrier Group of America made available to the press a hydrologist hired by the company. The hydrologist, Duncan M. Finlayson, a director for the Robertson Group P.L.C., an environmental consultant, said the charcoal filters that screen out naturally occurring impurities in carbon dioxide gas were now being monitored every two hours at the Vergeze plant, instead of weekly.</p>
        <p>Based on his company's inspection of records and procedures, Mr. Finlayson said, there was a ''supposition'' that the plant had produced benzene-contaminated water since last June.</p>
        <p>In discussing the minute amounts of benzene found in several bottles of Perrier, Mr. Finlayson said a person would get a larger dose of benzene from breathing fumes while filling the gas tank of a car.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
