<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Twist And Out</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="80" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="354887"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="WINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CORK</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PRIAL, FRANK J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cork</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D91738F933A15756C0A966958260" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Twist And Out</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK J. PRIAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PRIAL, FRANK J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE BIG CHAMPAGNE HOUSES IN FRANCE KEEP these fellows around for parties - heaven knows what they do the rest of the time - to saber the tops off bottles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE BIG CHAMPAGNE HOUSES IN FRANCE KEEP these fellows around for parties - heaven knows what they do the rest of the time - to saber the tops off bottles.</p>
        <p>THE BIG CHAMPAGNE HOUSES IN FRANCE KEEP these fellows around for parties - heaven knows what they do the rest of the time - to saber the tops off bottles.</p>
        <p>It has got something to do with the Russian cavalry - or maybe it was old Nelson Eddy movies. In any event, it's a messy way to get at the wine.</p>
        <p>And then there are Port tongs. You've probably never even seen Port tongs, much less used them. They look like something from a Torquemada collection, but the only thing they torture is the necks of Port bottles - Port bottles with uncooperative corks.</p>
        <p>Heated to a red glow and clamped around the bottle's neck, they snap it off neatly just below the cork, not even rippling the wine. Which is more than can be said about the melodramatic saber. It sends the top flying and slops the Champagne all over the place. It's amazing, the length to which some people will go to get a drink. Fortunately for the rest of us, there are easier ways. With a little patience, you can twist any Champagne cork out of the bottle. If you are impatient, there is a lovely little plastic-coated gadget called a Champagne Star that fits over the cork and does most of the work for you.</p>
        <p>If you are into old vintage Ports, by all means pick up some Port tongs. Younger bottles respond docilely to any good corkscrew or to the two-bladed Ah-So cork-puller that is sold in most liquor shops. The Ah-So - it's German, not Japanese - takes a little practice, but it's the ultimate weapon in the war on both soft, crumbly corks and corks that seem to have been set in place with Krazy Glue. The French for corkscrew is tire-bouchon, or cork-puller. It most accurately describes the Ah-So, which has no screw at all. Most corkscrews do have screws, including most French corkscrews. So much for precision in the French language.</p>
        <p>There are two types of screws used in corkscrews - the worm and the awl, which sounds as if it were the name of a London pub. The awl is the worst. It is a solid metal shaft with a helix edge, just like a screw used in wood or metal. In inexperienced hands, which means most of them - hands that is - the awl will rip up through the center of a well-fixed cork, leaving cork crumbs all over the table, most of the cork still in the bottle and egg on the opening party's face.</p>
        <p>A good example of the awl type is the double-arm corkscrew. The arms go up laterally as the awl twists in, then they are pulled down to their original position. Sometimes the cork comes out; sometimes it doesn't.</p>
        <p>A good example of the worm is the well-known Screwpull that employs a single but powerful Teflon-covered worm screw. Few corks can resist the Screw-pull, although the Teflon does wear off in time. The Screwpull people also offer a serious lever model. This is a fascinating gadget guaranteed to liven up the dullest dinner party. It's got the same Teflon-covered steel worm, but it's set on a two-armed apparatus that would intimidate any cork, though it is much simpler to operate than it looks. Its price - about $100 - makes it a relatively serious toy.</p>
        <p>The waiter's friend is the corkscrew most often seen in restaurants. It looks like a penknife and, in fact, often has a small knife blade to cut the lead foil cap away from the top of the bottle. Most waiter's friends have a decent worm screw and some even have a two-stage lever -the part that rests against the lip of the bottle - to accommodate short and long corks.</p>
        <p>The waiter's friend can be unfriendly at times. Some restaurants will not allow servers to set the bottle on the table to get needed leverage. It's painful, watching some servers who don't have enough arm strength to hold the bottle with one hand and extract the cork with the other.</p>
        <p>There were corks long before there were corkscrews; the Romans were said to have used corks. It was the advent of wine bottles to age wine that brought on the cork puller. Originally, enough cork was left outside the bottle to be pulled by hand - or, probably, by the teeth, a la John Wayne. It was just a stopper.</p>
        <p>Beginning in the 17th century, the cork was pushed far into the bottle, not just to keep the wine in but to preserve it. Enter the corkscrew, or bottle screw, as it was known for several centuries. Old prints of bewigged gentlemen opening their Port or claret show that the simplest corkscrews have changed very little over the last 250 years. Even our more elaborate gadgets, with screws and levers, are pretty much as they were a century ago.</p>
        <p>What seems to have been lost is a sense of humor. Some of the earliest twin-lever models were shaped like a woman's legs. A model dating from the Roaring 20's is a small statue of Representative Andrew Joseph Volstead, who was the author of the infamous Prohibition act.</p>
        <p>Inevitably, the corkscrew became a collector's item, and corkscrew fans banded together. One of the best known groups is the International Correspondents of Corkscrew Addicts, founded by, among others, Brother Timothy, for many years cellarmaster at the Christian Brothers Winery in California. Brother Timothy's corkscrews, known as the Christian Brothers collection, number some 1,500 items.</p>
        <p>Christie's and Sotheby's occasionally auction off corkscrews. Some rare items sell for $1,000 or more, but many interesting old cork pullers still can be found in the $200 to $300 range.</p>
        <p>The corkscrew has long held an irresistible attraction for the old-fashioned tinkerer, the basement inventor. Many of the bizarre results of this challenge have been patented and are, in fact, for sale. Most are the variations of the Archimedean principle of leverage, but some of the zanier examples use air or carbon dioxide pumped into the bottle through a hollow needle in the cork. So it's not at all strange that there are people who actually seek out the most useless corkscrews for their collections.</p>
        <p>WINE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
