<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="341307"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DF103FF935A35757C0A966958260" item-length="1361" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>A five-day summit meeting between President Bush and Mikhail S. Gorbachev will be held in Washington beginning on May 30, the White House and the Kremlin said.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>Soviet troops went on another foray in the Lithuanian capital while the Kremlin repeated that it would not hold formal talks with separatist leaders until the republic voided its declaration of independence.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Support for German unification has grown, but Americans seem uneasy about whether the change in Europe is permanent, according to the New York Times/CBS News Poll.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>East Germany's new Parliament held its inaugural session, but with the major parties still negotiating a coalition, no government was installed.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Bonn works on money plan amid protests in East</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Yugoslavia's first multiparty vote in 45 years will be held Sunday in the republic of Slovenia. No matter who wins, the tiny republic on the edge of the Alps is considered certain to signal its desire for independence.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Japanese barriers on trade will be reduced under an agreement reached by Washington and Tokyo. The Japanese steps range from cutting restrictions on large retail stores to altering real estate tax policies.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Aid to Cambodia and Vietnam by Eastern European countries may be reduced after the collapse of Euro-pean Communism and the withering of Comecon, the Eastern-bloc trading association.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>There is a sense of crisis in Nepal. The pro-democracy opposition is preparing for a general strike, and there is speculation that King Birendra, the all-powerful sovereign, might suspend Parliament.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>F. W. de Klerk and Nelson Mandela agreed to reschedule formal talks between the Government and the African National Congress on a political settlement on South Africa's future.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Israeli people want reform. Their voices are difficult to hear above the din of promises, threats and warnings that characterize the nation's politics, but their message is clear: they want electoral reform.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Gelbard, career envoy, reported favored for Managua post</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Nsanje journal: Will Malawi shut its door to refugees?</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>National</p>
        <p>A12-22</p>
        <p>The long climb in housing prices that has made home ownership all but a sure-fire investment may level off or decline during this decade, many experts think. That would alter consumer spending habits.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Pentagon spending reductions twice as great as those offered by President Bush have been proposed by two senior Republican Senators, William S. Cohen of Maine and John McCain of Arizona.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The nation's Roman Catholic bishops have engaged a public relations firm and a polling concern in Washington to conduct a nationwide campaign to persuade both Catholics and non-Catholics to oppose abortion.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Study finds little distress in women after abortion</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>An Alderman in Milwaukee has stunned and divided the city with his efforts to revive the Black Panthers and build a black militia that he says will take violent action if his demands for racial parity are not met.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>A hoax call to the Coast Guard may have cost the lives of two fishermen on a ship sinking off the coast of Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Boston University's John R. Silber is not a conventional candidate for the Democratic nomination for Governor of Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Washington Talk: If politics is broke, can talk fix it?</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>F.B.I. Director William S. Sessions was accused by members of Congress of tolerating what one lawmaker described as the ''living hell'' experienced by the bureau's black and Hispanic employees.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Newspaper editors hear self-criticism</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>The issue of controlling acid rain was tackled by the House Energy and Commerce Committee, which voted to recommend sweeping legislation to strengthen the Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Mercury may be banned from paint. Government regulators are alarmed at growing evidence of potential health dangers from the toxic metal, which is used in latex paint.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Monkey virus infects four, but none gets sick</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>A winged rocket is launched into orbit from a B-52 aircraft</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Regional</p>
        <p>B1-4</p>
        <p>An additional revenue shortfall of $105 million is faced by New York City for the fiscal year ending June 30, Mayor Dinkins said. He said he would seek $309 million more in higher taxes to balance the budget for next year.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>An income tax cut would be delayed under a tentative plan agreed on by Gov. Mario M. Cuomo and legislative leaders in Albany. The cut would be phased in over three years.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>The Port Authority dropped plans for a $1 increase in its bridge and tunnel tolls and a 25-cent fare increase on PATH trains later this year, the executive director of the bistate agency said.</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Dean of New School picked to head planning agency</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>The Hispanic community is rallying to pressure the Dinkins administration to avoid sweeping away social clubs that the community says serve vital cultural, economic and educational needs.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>An appraisal: The Trump Taj Mahal has been advertised as the eighth wonder of the world, but it will be that only to people who consider seeing 3,000 slot machines in a single room to be a greater experience than the pyramids.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Four turtles from under the streets of New York City</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Marcos role in investments is recounted by ex-banker</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Suspect in slaying had order to stay away</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>A doctor cites loss of memory in murder case</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Weekend</p>
        <p>Easter music</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Bushes see Michael Jackson</p>
        <p>C27</p>
        <p>Theater: On Stage</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>''Paradise for the Worried''</p>
        <p>C3</p>
        <p>Len Cariou in ''Mountain''</p>
        <p>C29</p>
        <p>Film: At the Movies</p>
        <p>C8</p>
        <p>''I Love You to Death''</p>
        <p>C8</p>
        <p>''Cry-Baby''</p>
        <p>C10</p>
        <p>''The Cook, the Thief, His Wife and Her Lover''</p>
        <p>C12</p>
        <p>''In the Spirit''</p>
        <p>C16</p>
        <p>Music: World tour via folk song</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>States drop record labeling bills</p>
        <p>C36</p>
        <p>Dance: Pilar Rioja</p>
        <p>C3</p>
        <p>Architecture: An elusive modernist</p>
        <p>C27</p>
        <p>Art: Brazilian at the Modern</p>
        <p>C31</p>
        <p>Auctions</p>
        <p>C31</p>
        <p>''Works on Paper'' at the Armory</p>
        <p>C31</p>
        <p>Restaurants</p>
        <p>C22</p>
        <p>Word and Image: TV Weekend</p>
        <p>C34</p>
        <p>Edith Wharton stories</p>
        <p>C36</p>
        <p>Sports</p>
        <p>Baseball: Righetti to close show</p>
        <p>A28</p>
        <p>Spira is arraigned</p>
        <p>A28</p>
        <p>Basketball: Oklahoma reinstates women's program</p>
        <p>A27</p>
        <p>Boxing: Ruddock in picture</p>
        <p>A27</p>
        <p>Column: Anderson on Masters</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Golf: Two Masters rookies lead</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Hockey: Rangers beat Islanders</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Devils fall in overtime</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Whalers edge Bruins</p>
        <p>A29</p>
        <p>Tennis: Capriati defeats Sanchez Vicario</p>
        <p>A28</p>
        <p>Law</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>At the Bar</p>
        <p>Leaps of science create quandaries on evidence</p>
        <p>Obituaries</p>
        <p>Edward E. Carlson, former chief executive of UAL Inc.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>S. Gershon Levi, an ex-president of a Rabbis' group</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Rafael Lorente de No, a researcher</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>A34</p>
        <p>Pretoria: not black and white</p>
        <p>Court rules for the homeless</p>
        <p>Protecting inept managers</p>
        <p>David C. Unger: Nationalism</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>A34</p>
        <p>William Safire: Our ''open doormat''</p>
        <p>A35</p>
        <p>Anthony Lewis: Hope, the beloved country</p>
        <p>A35</p>
        <p>Alice H. Amsden: An Asian plan for East Europe</p>
        <p>A35</p>
        <p>James T. Laney: Why tolerate campus bigots?</p>
        <p>A35</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
