<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Are We Doomed?</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="404012"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="ENVIRONMENTAL BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FIROR, JOHN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CHANGING ATMOSPHERE, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDD1531F936A15752C1A966958260" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Are We Doomed?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Malcolm W. Browne; Malcolm W. Browne is a science reporter for The New York Times.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE CHANGING ATMOSPHERE  A Global Challenge. By John Firor. 145 pp. New Haven: Yale University Press. $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE CHANGING ATMOSPHERE  A Global Challenge. By John Firor. 145 pp. New Haven: Yale University Press. $19.95.</p>
        <p>BY now most of us are aware that sinister forces are reshaping our habitat. As the human race burgeons (it has doubled in just 37 years), it is fouling the global nest at a horrifying rate. Already we are witnessing the death of forests and lakes, the dwindling of genetic diversity and the spread of cancer.</p>
        <p>These changes are not pleasant to acknowledge, and we cling to the straws offered by uncertainty. Since the scientists assessing the damage to our land, water and air constantly disagree with one another, we are permitted to hope that the Cassandras are simply wrong. Some commentators buttress this hope by reminding us that the earth is an astonishingly resilient place that has always managed to absorb the blows dealt by humans and nature.</p>
        <p>John Firor, a scientist who directs the Advanced Study Program at the National Center for Atmospheric Research, in Boulder, Colo., throws ice water on such cozy assumptions. Scientific debates about the atmosphere abound, he concedes, but they are mainly about how much and how soon the dreadful consequences of our profligacy will become manifest, not whether they will come about at all. In the space of a few dozen decades man has profoundly (and perhaps irreversibly) changed the terrestrial habitat, and the rate of change is now increasing almost beyond belief. It is folly, he writes, to use scientific quibbling over details of this cataclysm as a pretext for inaction.</p>
        <p>"The Changing Atmosphere" is about even larger human issues than air pollution. The thrust of Mr. Firor's argument is that none of the environmental issues now facing us can be considered in isolation; the danger that the warming of the atmosphere will melt polar ice and raise sea levels enough to destroy most of Bangladesh, he demonstrates, is directly related to the educational status of an African woman cooking a meal in an earthen pot over an open fire.</p>
        <p>Mr. Firor's book is persuasive because it is based more on evenhanded analysis than on advocacy. He does not assert, for example, that failure to correct our erring ways will bring certain doom; he merely suggests that inaction will limit human options in ways that will enormously complicate our survival. He suggests that even if most animal and plant species fall victim to the environmental changes we are bringing about, we will create new, more useful species, by genetic engineering or other means. And even if our chlorine-based pollutants eventually weaken nature's ozone shield so that ultraviolet radiation wipes out global soybean production and other crops, he says, substitutes can probably be developed.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Firor warns that if we decide to shoulder total responsibility for readapting the world to the changes we are imposing on it, we must complete our preparations before doing away with Mother Nature altogether. We must be ready with new systems of agriculture, industry, economy and society -- along with governments strong enough to make them work -- if we are not to face an agonizing period of transition.</p>
        <p>Most of "The Changing Atmosphere" is devoted to clear explanations (illustrated by simple graphs) of the relationships between acid rain, climate warming and stratospheric ozone depletion, as well as to their causes and effects. This book could serve as a primer for anyone confused by the wealth of technical information that has been published about these complex atmospheric phenomena.</p>
        <p>UNLIKE many books about the climate, though, this one focuses sharply on some of the social mainsprings of atmospheric change, notably the population explosion. The author repeats the familiar injunctions to wean ourselves from fossil fuels, develop alternative energy sources and use all our resources more efficiently. But he adds that "each problem discussed here, and indeed almost every global problem facing us today, is driven in the first instance and exacerbated by growth in the world's population."</p>
        <p>He argues that only by stemming population growth -- perhaps by raising the economic and educational standards of women in the third world and by providing incentives to raise smaller families -- will we be able to manage the complications caused by pollution and the depletion of resources.</p>
        <p>"The Changing Atmosphere" is about as agreeable as a dose of ipecac; the reader is left with a sense of astonishment that human intelligence could have permitted us to reach this predicament. But perhaps the era of complacency is ending and we have at last begun to think about saving ourselves.</p>
        <p>ENVIRONMENTAL BOOKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
