<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOREST SERVICE ABUSING ROLE, DISSIDENTS SAY</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="331871"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FOREST SERVICE, US</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">EGAN, TIMOTHY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROBERTSON, F DALE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DF1031F937A35750C0A966958260" item-length="1692" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOREST SERVICE ABUSING ROLE, DISSIDENTS SAY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY EGAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">EGAN, TIMOTHY</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, March 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Saying the Forest Service has abused millions of acres entrusted to it, supervisors and professionals in the service are rebelling against Federal policies that promote logging, mining and road-building in 191 million acres of public forests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Saying the Forest Service has abused millions of acres entrusted to it, supervisors and professionals in the service are rebelling against Federal policies that promote logging, mining and road-building in 191 million acres of public forests.</p>
        <p>Saying the Forest Service has abused millions of acres entrusted to it, supervisors and professionals in the service are rebelling against Federal policies that promote logging, mining and road-building in 191 million acres of public forests.</p>
        <p>The dispute could also determine how the country manages nearly half its clean water supply, its biggest and oldest trees, its largest wilderness areas, its most bountiful wildlife habitats and resources, which provide the most jobs in many Western communities.</p>
        <p>In the rush to sell Federal timber, the agency created by Theodore Roosevelt to manage the vanishing wilderness has lost sight of its original goal, say the supervisors of many national forests and hundreds of lower employees who have joined a dissident group in the service.</p>
        <p>The Leading Road-Builder</p>
        <p>They say the Forest Service has become the No. 1 road-builder, hacking more than 340,000 miles of logging roads in the woods in the last half-century, and that it is now spending more money on cutting down trees than for any other purpose.</p>
        <p>''We're managing our resources horribly,'' said Jeff DeBonis, a Eugene, Ore., forester who organized the Association of Forest Service Employees for Environmental Ethics in an attempt, he says, to change the service's direction. His group claims it has 1,500 service members out of a total of 38,000 employees.</p>
        <p>The protests are not unheeded. At the very top of the Forest Service, officials who were saying a decade ago that boards are more valuable than old trees have been replaced, Current appointees, the dissidents say, who believe century-old stands of trees have a value beyond lumber's value.</p>
        <p>F. Dale Robertson, chief of the service since 1987, said in an interview that the internal debate was good for the service. Reflecting a change in its direction and a shift in the public's view of forests toward more concern for the environment, the service's proposed budget for the fiscal year 1991 is ''better-rounded than we've ever had before,'' he said.</p>
        <p>President Bush has proposed that $175 million be spent on a tree-planting program to be supervised by the service. But critics say that merely planting new trees while another arm of the service is knocking down centuries-old trees will leave America's woodlands impoverished.</p>
        <p>Change in Society</p>
        <p>''There's a change going on in society, and the Forest Service can't just ignore that,'' Mr. Robertson said. ''We intend to be more environmentally responsible.''</p>
        <p>Many top agency officials from around the country applaud the philosophical changes, but they say more should be done to change programs and spending priorities to reflect the good stewardship values of the service.</p>
        <p>Its budget is established by the President and Congress, but the process of deciding how to spend the money begins with the philosophy and requests of the 156 forest supervisors.</p>
        <p>For example, Tom Kovalicky, supervisor of the 2.2 million-acre Nez Perce National Forest in Idaho, makes a request each year on how much money to spend on his forest. He has complained that his efforts to restore salmon and steelhead runs receive minimal financing, while the timber-cutting program, which he says harms those streams, receives the lion's share of the $14 million Nez Perce budget.</p>
        <p>'Troubling Times'</p>
        <p>''These are troubling times for many of us,'' Mr. Kovalicky and supervisors of national forests in Montana, Idaho and the Dakotas wrote three months ago in an open lettter to Mr. Robertson. ''Many people, internally as well as externally, believe the current emphasis of national forest programs does not reflect the land-stewardship values embodied in our forest plan.''</p>
        <p>Citing continuing logging programs in pristine areas and ''sagging'' public support for the service, the supervisors from the northern Rocky Mountain region who signed the letter wrote, ''We have become a dysfunctional Forest Service family.''</p>
        <p>Similar letters to Mr. Robertson came from supervisors of national forests throughout the West. He said this ''straight talk'' could help fashion for the agency a new conservationist role, which he said many have been seeking for a long time.</p>
        <p>Even with its enormous acreage, $3 billion annual budget and legion of rangers and biologists, the service has long operated in virtual anonymity. But now, driven by a revolt from within and criticism from outside, the agency is going through a major, and very public, transformation.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of good, dedicated people in the Forest Service, but there is also a lot of dead wood left over from 25 years of rape-pillage-and-plunder mentality,'' said Don Kern, a hydrologist with the Flathead National Forest in Montana. ''Unfortunately, many of those people are in key management positions.''</p>
        <p>Critics in Logging Industry</p>
        <p>Some leaders in the logging industry say the revolt in the Forest Service is fueled by environmental zealots.</p>
        <p>''They're rabble-rousers,'' said Troy Reinhart, a former service employee who is executive director of Douglas Timber Operators. The group represents Oregon companies that depend on public land for their wood supply.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robertson said he would prefer that the dissidents promote change by quietly working within the agency, but he said he is ''officially neutral'' about the group.</p>
        <p>Mr. DeBonis, founder of the group, resigned last week as a Federal timber sales planner after 12 years with the service because, he said, he wanted to stop supporting the timber policy and devote more time to the organization.</p>
        <p>Mr. DeBonis, who now publishes a quarterly newsletter, Inner Voices, started his campaign early last year, when he wrote a blistering letter to Mr. Robertson.</p>
        <p>A Letter of Protest</p>
        <p>''Our basic problem right now is that we are much too biased towards the resource-extraction industries, particularly the timber industry,'' Mr. DeBonis wrote to the chief. ''We support their narrowly focused, shortsighted agenda.''</p>
        <p>He also sent a computer memorandum to other employees reporting on a conference that singled out the Forest Service as being mainly responsible for severe logging of old-growth forests in the Pacific Northwest.</p>
        <p>After being reprimandeded for using the service's computer, Mr. DeBonis began organizing the dissident group on his own time, he said, by sending fliers to other Forest Service offices.</p>
        <p>His criticism that the Forest Service has become too much of an industry ally has been repeated by supervisors of some national forests, pointing to the increased logging on public lands.</p>
        <p>For most of the last five years, the share of the service's budget for wildlife and stewardship has been in steady decline, while more than a third has gone to the timber program.</p>
        <p>Rise in Logging on Public Land</p>
        <p>Before World War II, very little logging was done on national forest land. But as the last of the big trees disappeared from private land, attention turned to the reserves, set aside 100 years ago, as a source of the industry's wood supply. In the last three years, a record number of trees have been cut from the national forests, more than 12 billion board feet a year, or triple the number of a generation ago.</p>
        <p>In the Pacific Northwest, where almost half of all the logging on national forests is done, the Forest Service has cut the oldest and biggest trees first and replacedthem with new trees.</p>
        <p>In the early 1980's, John B. Crowell was the Assistant Secretary of Agriculture in charge of the national forests. Mr. Crowell said one of his main goals was to speed logging of the 3 million to 4 million acres of original forest left in the West. That policy is now under review, Mr. Robertson said.</p>
        <p>Since the mid-1980's, the last of the old growth has been cut at a pace of about 70,000 acres a year. Most national forests in the Northwest are now laced with roads and clearcuts. In the Gifford Pinchot National Forest in Washington (named for the service's founder) less than a tenth of the 1.1 million acres of the original forest remains as it was in Mr. Pinchot's time.</p>
        <p>''We are trading our forests in on European-style plantations that are really nothing more than economic tree farms,'' Chris Maser wrote in his book, ''Forest Primeval,'' published last year by Sierra Club Books. Mr. Maser is a former research scientist with the Interior Department.</p>
        <p>A Legacy in the Balance</p>
        <p>In the view of Mr. Maser and some top scientists in the Forest Service, the Government is wiping out the biological archives of the old forest, a legacy of several generations of plant life that may be needed as a hedge against disease, global warming and fires.</p>
        <p>''Our forest lands should be more than just agricultural lands with a slow-maturing crop,'' said Dr. Jerry Franklin, an ecologist with the Forest Service who is considered the Government's foremost expert on old-growth forests. He advocates keeping much of the remaining ancient forest of the West intact as a storehouse of information for future foresters.</p>
        <p>After years as an outside voice, Dr. Franklin's warnings are finding a home in the upper echelons of the Forest Service.</p>
        <p>''For the first time as an agency we are recognizing the importance of old growth on a national level,'' said Mr. Robertson, who noted that this new policy was influenced by the work of Dr. Franklin. ''Old-growth forests are an important ecosystem that we are just beginning to understand.''</p>
        <p>A BUDGET FOR FORESTS</p>
        <p>U.S. Forest Service budget for the fiscal year 1990.</p>
        <p>$921 million - Timber related activities (timber sales support, construction, reforestration, etc.)</p>
        <p>$551 million - Fire Fighting</p>
        <p>$363 million - Total payments to states</p>
        <p>$145 million - Research</p>
        <p>$139 million - Recreation</p>
        <p>$131 million - Misc.</p>
        <p>$104 million - State &amp; Private Forestry</p>
        <p>$ 96 million - Road Maintenance</p>
        <p>$ 88 million - Construction</p>
        <p>$ 71 million - Wildlife &amp; Fish</p>
        <p>$ 63 million - Land Acquisition</p>
        <p>$ 41 million - Soil, Water &amp; Air Management</p>
        <p>$ 24 million - Trail Maintenance</p>
        <p>$392 million - Other National Forest System Resources</p>
        <p>Source: U.S. Forest Service</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
