<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>West</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="398937"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="THE 1990 ELECTIONS: STATE BY STATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNORS (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION RESULTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILSON, PETE (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FEINSTEIN, DIANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DD1539F93BA35752C1A966958260" item-length="2147" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>West</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALASKA</p>
        <p>Running as an independent, Walter Hickel pulled away from a crowded field to establish an 8-percentage-point lead over his closest contender, Tony Knowles, the Democratic candidate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hickel, as a Republican, was Governor from 1966 to 1968.</p>
        <p>The other candidates scrambling to succeed the retiring Governor, Steve Cowper, had similar lengthy political records. Mr. Knowles was Mayor of Anchorage and Arliss Sturgulewski, the Republican candidate, spent 12 years in the State Senate.</p>
        <p>John S. Devens, the Democratic nominee for Alaska's sole seat in the House of Representatives, gave the Republican incumbent, Don Young, a tight race, but Mr. Young managed to overcome his opposition.</p>
        <p>And Senator Ted Stevens, a Republican, was one of the first Alaskan candidates in this election to raise his arms in victory, defeating Michael Beasley, a Democat.</p>
        <p>Marijuana is again illegal in Alaska -- voters passed a ballot measure that rescinds a law allowing private use of the drug. ARIZONA</p>
        <p>J. Fife Symington, a Republican developer, and Terry Goddard, a Democrat and former Mayor of Phoenix, ran a hot and very close race for Governor -- one that may not be over.</p>
        <p>Arizona law requires a majority vote, and it appeared yesterday that the number of write-in votes might keep both candidates below the 50-percent mark, requiring a run-off between the Republican and Democrat.</p>
        <p>With about 90 percent of the ballots counted yesterday, Mr. Symington led by 4,527 votes. But Karen Osborne, an assistant secretary of state, said there were thousands of uncounted write-in votes for other candidates.</p>
        <p>By a narrow margin, Arizonans rejected the designation of the Rev. Martin Luther King's birthday as a state holiday. The Democrats gained control of the State Senate, while Republicans run the lower house. CALIFORNIA</p>
        <p>Dianne Feinstein, the former Mayor of San Francisco, lost the governor's race to Senator Pete Wilson, a Republican who was once Mayor of San Diego.  [ Page B2. ]  As Governor, Mr. Wilson may appoint someone to fill his seat in the Senate until a special election is held in 1992.</p>
        <p>In an upset, veteran Congressman Charles Pashayan Jr., a Republican, was soundly defeated by the Democratic candidate, Calvin Dooley. But in two other tight races, the incumbents won: George E. Brown Jr., a Democrat, and Al McCandless, a Republican.</p>
        <p>Showing their anger with politicians, voters narrowly passed Proposition 140, which prevents state officeholders from serving for more than eight years; it also caps legislators' office expenses and eliminates their once-lucrative retirement benefits. Voters defeated a more moderate proposition to limit terms and also defeated Big Green, an environmental plan that might have cost billions of dollars.</p>
        <p>Democrats retained control of the Legislature, which will draw new Congressional districts as California gains several seats in the House. COLORADO</p>
        <p>Republicans successfully reshuffled several seats and retained control of them all. Following a plan used in other states, the party recruited a popular Representative, Hank Brown, to run for the Senate seat left open by the retirement of William L. Armstrong, a Republican. Mr. Brown defeated Josie Heath, a former Boulder County Commissioner.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown's run at the Senate left open his Fourth District seat. The Republican candidate, State Senator Wayne Allard, defeated State Representative Richard R. Bond.</p>
        <p>Incumbents in the state's remaining five districts all were re-elected, while Republicans retained control of the Legislature.</p>
        <p>The Governor, Roy Romer, never faced any serious competition and easily defeated the Republican candidate, John Andrews.</p>
        <p>Voters approved a ballot proposal to limit members of Congress from Colorado to 12 years in office, and state officials to no more than eight years, a law that legal scholars say may not withstand a constitutional challenge. HAWAII</p>
        <p>Democrats, who have dominated this island state's politics, swept all the major offices. Senator Daniel K. Akaka, appointed to fill the unexpired term of Spark M. Matsunaga, who died in April, handily defeated Representative Patricia Saiki, a Republican. The G.O.P. had seen this race as perhaps its best chance to pick up a seat in the Senate. They hoped Ms. Saiki, a Japanese-American, could win a significant percentage of Hawaiians of Japanese descent, a group that tradtionally favors Democrats. But Saiki campaign officials said yesterday that Mr. Akaka had maintained support among this group.</p>
        <p>Democrats won both races for the House, wiith State Senator Neil Abercrombie beating Mike Liu, leader of the Republicans in the State House, and former Representative Patsy Mink winning over former State Representative Andy Poepoe, a Republican.</p>
        <p>Gov. John Waihee, a Democrat, easily won re-election, and his party retained substantial majorities in the Legislature.  IDAHO</p>
        <p>The incumbent Governor, Cecil D. Andrus, a 59-year-old Democrat, defeated Roger Fairchild, a Republican and former majority leader of the State Senate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Andrus served as Governor from 1971 to 1977 and as President Jimmy Carter's Interior Secretary from 1977 to 1981 before becoming Governor again.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the year he vetoed what would have been a highly restrictive abortion law. For his part, Mr. Fairchild was a declared opponent of abortion before winning the Republican nomination.</p>
        <p>With Senator James A. McClure, a Republican, retiring, the race for his seat was between Representative Larry E. Craig, a Republican, and Ron Twilegar, a Democrat and former State Legislator. The victor was Mr. Craig. Larry LaRocco, a Democrat and stockbroker, won Mr. Craig's Congressional seat, defeating State Senator C. A. Smyser.</p>
        <p>The Republicans will continue to control the State Legislature. MONTANA</p>
        <p>Senator Max Baucus, a Democrat, easily won a third term against Lieut. Gov. Allen C. Kolstad, a Republican.</p>
        <p>Senator Baucus shunned the campaign complacency of his former colleague, John Melcher, who ignored his 1988 campaign until the summer and was defeated by a little-known Republican, Conrad Burns. Mr. Baucus spent more than a year barnstorming the state and raised more than $2 million in his campaign. Mr. Kolstad evoked criticism in the environmentally conscious state last July by calling threats of acid rain and global warming "scare tactics."</p>
        <p>Democrats won control of the Legislature.</p>
        <p>Representative Pat Williams, a six-term Democrat who was co-author of a compromise measure that continued Federal financing for the National Endowment for the Arts, overcame a challenge by Brad Johnson, a former state party official who is an aide to Representative Ron Marlenee, a Republican who won re-election in the Second District. Mr. Johnson accused Mr. Williams of supporting pornography.</p>
        <p>Reapportioning is expected to cost Montana one of its two House seats in 1992. NEVADA</p>
        <p>Bob Miller, a Democrat who became Acting Governor two years ago, easily won his first election to a full term as Nevada's chief executive.</p>
        <p>The 45-year-old Mr. Miller, also a former two-term district attorney from Las Vegas, replaced Richard H. Bryan, who was elected to the Senate in 1988. This time Mr. Miller easily defeated Jim Gallaway, a 50-year-old lawyer and former marine, who used his own considerable resources to finance much of his campaign. Mr. Gallaway stressed his "pro-business, anti-tax" stance and criticized the Governor for his anti-abortion position. Mr. Miller drew two-thirds of the vote.</p>
        <p>Democrats gained control of the State Senate and held onto the House as well.</p>
        <p>In the Second Congressional District, virtually the entire state outside the Las Vegas area, Barbara F. Vucanovich, the four-term Republican incumbent, easily defeated Jane Wisdom, a member of the State Assembly. NEW MEXICO</p>
        <p>With the incumbent Governor, Garrey Carruthers, ineligible to try for re-election, former Gov. Bruce King was the Democratic candidate for the post. In an energetic race, he beat former State Representative Frank Bond, the Republican candidate.</p>
        <p>The 66-year-old Mr. King, a rancher and businessman, was Governor from 1971 to 1974 and again from 1979 to 1982. In this year's campaign, he stressed education, the environment and economic development. To spur economic development, he called for steps to create more growth in the state's private business sector.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bond, a 47-year-old lawyer and rancher with land interests, also stressed economic policies, calling for various measures to promote diversfied development and create additonal jobs in the state.</p>
        <p>Senator Pete V. Domenici, a third-term Republican, crushed State Senator Tom R. Benavides, a Democrat. Mr. Domenici won almost three-quarters of the vote.</p>
        <p>The Democrats retained control of the Legislature.  OREGON</p>
        <p>Senator Mark O. Hatfield withstood a stiff challenge from Harry Lonsdale, a Democratic businessman, to win a fifth term in office.</p>
        <p>Secretary of State Barbara Roberts, a Democrat, will replace Neil Goldschmidt, the retiring Democratic Governor, after coasting to victory over Attorney General David Frohnmeyer, a Republican.</p>
        <p>In the Fifth District, Mike Kopetski, a Democrat, defeated Representative Denny Smith, a Republican. Mr. Kopetski fell just 707 votes short of Mr. Smith two years ago.</p>
        <p>But Democrats lost control of the State Assembly, thereby losing control of the redistricting process.</p>
        <p>A measure to give parents tax credits if they send children to private schools was defeated 2 to 1. So were attempts to toughen the state's recycling requirements, to shut down its sole nuclear power plant, and to regulate land use more closely. Two measures restricting abortions also failed. UTAH</p>
        <p>Representative Wayne Owens of Salt Lake City, who has been the only Democrat in Utah's delegation, defeated a challenge from Genevieve Atwood, a Republican who is a former State Representative.</p>
        <p>Another Democrat, Bill Orton, will join the delegation, in the Provo seat left open by Representative Howard C. Nielson, a Republican who is retiring. Mr. Orton, 42 years old, a tax lawyer and first-time candidate, won in what is often called the most Republican district in the nation. He emphasized his conservative ideology, supporting a balanced-budget amendment, a smaller Federal Government and anti-abortion laws.</p>
        <p>Mr. Orton's Republican opponent was former State Senator Karl Snow, a 60-year-old professor and administrator at Brigham Young University, who has been the subject of an investigation by The Provo Herald into his ownership of certain stocks and his business association with a convicted felon.</p>
        <p>The State Legislature remains Republican. WASHINGTON</p>
        <p>Representative Jolene Unsoeld, a freshman Democrat who was elected to Congress in 1988 by only 618 votes, defeated Bob Williams, a former State Representative, by 13,000 votes. Mrs. Unsoeld's narrow victory two years ago made her a premier target of Republicans in 1990. Mr. Williams accused Mrs. Unsoeld of being a typical "tax-and-spend liberal." She said Mr. Williams was anti-environment and conservative.</p>
        <p>In another contest, Representative John Miller, a conservative Republican in his third term representing the First Congressional District in northern Seattle, defeated Cynthia Sullivan, a member of the King County Council. She said Mr. Miller had neglected local problems, including traffic congestion, and voted wrong on environmental issues. But his endorsement by the Sierra Club and the League of Conservation Voters deflated that issue.</p>
        <p>Voters overwhelmingly rejected a sweeping environmental measure because, opponents said, they feared losing control over community issues. Voters in the Seattle-Tacoma area also rejected a proposed real estate tax increase to pay for the preservation of open land.</p>
        <p>Democrats retained control of the State House and were in a close race to take control of the Senate.  WYOMING</p>
        <p>Alan K. Simpson, the powerful Senate Republican Whip, easily won re-election against a political newcomer. He soundly defeated Kathy Helling, a 32-year-old sociology major at the University of Wyoming who challenged Mr. Simpson's positions on economic development and energy policy. The outcome reflected local polls that showed Mr. Simpson to be Wyoming's most popular statewide official.</p>
        <p>In Wyoming's sole Congressional district, Craig Thomas, the freshman Republican who replaced Dick Cheney when he was named Secretary of Defense, defeated Peter Maxfield, a Democratic lawyer and former dean of the University of Wyoming Law Schol.</p>
        <p>In the race for governor, Mike Sullivan, a popular Democrat, won re-election with a 2 to 1 ratio. His Republican opponent, Mary Mead, is a rancher and daughter of former Gov. Clifford P. Hansen.</p>
        <p>Republicans retain control of the Legislature.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALASKA</p>
        <p>Running as an independent, Walter Hickel pulled away from a crowded field to establish an 8-percentage-point lead over his closest contender, Tony Knowles, the Democratic candidate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hickel, as a Republican, was Governor from 1966 to 1968.</p>
        <p>The other candidates scrambling to succeed the retiring Governor, Steve Cowper, had similar lengthy political records. Mr. Knowles was Mayor of Anchorage and Arliss Sturgulewski, the Republican candidate, spent 12 years in the State Senate.</p>
        <p>John S. Devens, the Democratic nominee for Alaska's sole seat in the House of Representatives, gave the Republican incumbent, Don Young, a tight race, but Mr. Young managed to overcome his opposition.</p>
        <p>And Senator Ted Stevens, a Republican, was one of the first Alaskan candidates in this election to raise his arms in victory, defeating Michael Beasley, a Democat.</p>
        <p>Marijuana is again illegal in Alaska -- voters passed a ballot measure that rescinds a law allowing private use of the drug. ARIZONA</p>
        <p>J. Fife Symington, a Republican developer, and Terry Goddard, a Democrat and former Mayor of Phoenix, ran a hot and very close race for Governor -- one that may not be over.</p>
        <p>Arizona law requires a majority vote, and it appeared yesterday that the number of write-in votes might keep both candidates below the 50-percent mark, requiring a run-off between the Republican and Democrat.</p>
        <p>With about 90 percent of the ballots counted yesterday, Mr. Symington led by 4,527 votes. But Karen Osborne, an assistant secretary of state, said there were thousands of uncounted write-in votes for other candidates.</p>
        <p>By a narrow margin, Arizonans rejected the designation of the Rev. Martin Luther King's birthday as a state holiday. The Democrats gained control of the State Senate, while Republicans run the lower house. CALIFORNIA</p>
        <p>Dianne Feinstein, the former Mayor of San Francisco, lost the governor's race to Senator Pete Wilson, a Republican who was once Mayor of San Diego.  [ Page B2. ]  As Governor, Mr. Wilson may appoint someone to fill his seat in the Senate until a special election is held in 1992.</p>
        <p>In an upset, veteran Congressman Charles Pashayan Jr., a Republican, was soundly defeated by the Democratic candidate, Calvin Dooley. But in two other tight races, the incumbents won: George E. Brown Jr., a Democrat, and Al McCandless, a Republican.</p>
        <p>Showing their anger with politicians, voters narrowly passed Proposition 140, which prevents state officeholders from serving for more than eight years; it also caps legislators' office expenses and eliminates their once-lucrative retirement benefits. Voters defeated a more moderate proposition to limit terms and also defeated Big Green, an environmental plan that might have cost billions of dollars.</p>
        <p>Democrats retained control of the Legislature, which will draw new Congressional districts as California gains several seats in the House. COLORADO</p>
        <p>Republicans successfully reshuffled several seats and retained control of them all. Following a plan used in other states, the party recruited a popular Representative, Hank Brown, to run for the Senate seat left open by the retirement of William L. Armstrong, a Republican. Mr. Brown defeated Josie Heath, a former Boulder County Commissioner.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown's run at the Senate left open his Fourth District seat. The Republican candidate, State Senator Wayne Allard, defeated State Representative Richard R. Bond.</p>
        <p>Incumbents in the state's remaining five districts all were re-elected, while Republicans retained control of the Legislature.</p>
        <p>The Governor, Roy Romer, never faced any serious competition and easily defeated the Republican candidate, John Andrews.</p>
        <p>Voters approved a ballot proposal to limit members of Congress from Colorado to 12 years in office, and state officials to no more than eight years, a law that legal scholars say may not withstand a constitutional challenge. HAWAII</p>
        <p>Democrats, who have dominated this island state's politics, swept all the major offices. Senator Daniel K. Akaka, appointed to fill the unexpired term of Spark M. Matsunaga, who died in April, handily defeated Representative Patricia Saiki, a Republican. The G.O.P. had seen this race as perhaps its best chance to pick up a seat in the Senate. They hoped Ms. Saiki, a Japanese-American, could win a significant percentage of Hawaiians of Japanese descent, a group that tradtionally favors Democrats. But Saiki campaign officials said yesterday that Mr. Akaka had maintained support among this group.</p>
        <p>Democrats won both races for the House, wiith State Senator Neil Abercrombie beating Mike Liu, leader of the Republicans in the State House, and former Representative Patsy Mink winning over former State Representative Andy Poepoe, a Republican.</p>
        <p>Gov. John Waihee, a Democrat, easily won re-election, and his party retained substantial majorities in the Legislature.  IDAHO</p>
        <p>The incumbent Governor, Cecil D. Andrus, a 59-year-old Democrat, defeated Roger Fairchild, a Republican and former majority leader of the State Senate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Andrus served as Governor from 1971 to 1977 and as President Jimmy Carter's Interior Secretary from 1977 to 1981 before becoming Governor again.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the year he vetoed what would have been a highly restrictive abortion law. For his part, Mr. Fairchild was a declared opponent of abortion before winning the Republican nomination.</p>
        <p>With Senator James A. McClure, a Republican, retiring, the race for his seat was between Representative Larry E. Craig, a Republican, and Ron Twilegar, a Democrat and former State Legislator. The victor was Mr. Craig. Larry LaRocco, a Democrat and stockbroker, won Mr. Craig's Congressional seat, defeating State Senator C. A. Smyser.</p>
        <p>The Republicans will continue to control the State Legislature. MONTANA</p>
        <p>Senator Max Baucus, a Democrat, easily won a third term against Lieut. Gov. Allen C. Kolstad, a Republican.</p>
        <p>Senator Baucus shunned the campaign complacency of his former colleague, John Melcher, who ignored his 1988 campaign until the summer and was defeated by a little-known Republican, Conrad Burns. Mr. Baucus spent more than a year barnstorming the state and raised more than $2 million in his campaign. Mr. Kolstad evoked criticism in the environmentally conscious state last July by calling threats of acid rain and global warming "scare tactics."</p>
        <p>Democrats won control of the Legislature.</p>
        <p>Representative Pat Williams, a six-term Democrat who was co-author of a compromise measure that continued Federal financing for the National Endowment for the Arts, overcame a challenge by Brad Johnson, a former state party official who is an aide to Representative Ron Marlenee, a Republican who won re-election in the Second District. Mr. Johnson accused Mr. Williams of supporting pornography.</p>
        <p>Reapportioning is expected to cost Montana one of its two House seats in 1992. NEVADA</p>
        <p>Bob Miller, a Democrat who became Acting Governor two years ago, easily won his first election to a full term as Nevada's chief executive.</p>
        <p>The 45-year-old Mr. Miller, also a former two-term district attorney from Las Vegas, replaced Richard H. Bryan, who was elected to the Senate in 1988. This time Mr. Miller easily defeated Jim Gallaway, a 50-year-old lawyer and former marine, who used his own considerable resources to finance much of his campaign. Mr. Gallaway stressed his "pro-business, anti-tax" stance and criticized the Governor for his anti-abortion position. Mr. Miller drew two-thirds of the vote.</p>
        <p>Democrats gained control of the State Senate and held onto the House as well.</p>
        <p>In the Second Congressional District, virtually the entire state outside the Las Vegas area, Barbara F. Vucanovich, the four-term Republican incumbent, easily defeated Jane Wisdom, a member of the State Assembly. NEW MEXICO</p>
        <p>With the incumbent Governor, Garrey Carruthers, ineligible to try for re-election, former Gov. Bruce King was the Democratic candidate for the post. In an energetic race, he beat former State Representative Frank Bond, the Republican candidate.</p>
        <p>The 66-year-old Mr. King, a rancher and businessman, was Governor from 1971 to 1974 and again from 1979 to 1982. In this year's campaign, he stressed education, the environment and economic development. To spur economic development, he called for steps to create more growth in the state's private business sector.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bond, a 47-year-old lawyer and rancher with land interests, also stressed economic policies, calling for various measures to promote diversfied development and create additonal jobs in the state.</p>
        <p>Senator Pete V. Domenici, a third-term Republican, crushed State Senator Tom R. Benavides, a Democrat. Mr. Domenici won almost three-quarters of the vote.</p>
        <p>The Democrats retained control of the Legislature.  OREGON</p>
        <p>Senator Mark O. Hatfield withstood a stiff challenge from Harry Lonsdale, a Democratic businessman, to win a fifth term in office.</p>
        <p>Secretary of State Barbara Roberts, a Democrat, will replace Neil Goldschmidt, the retiring Democratic Governor, after coasting to victory over Attorney General David Frohnmeyer, a Republican.</p>
        <p>In the Fifth District, Mike Kopetski, a Democrat, defeated Representative Denny Smith, a Republican. Mr. Kopetski fell just 707 votes short of Mr. Smith two years ago.</p>
        <p>But Democrats lost control of the State Assembly, thereby losing control of the redistricting process.</p>
        <p>A measure to give parents tax credits if they send children to private schools was defeated 2 to 1. So were attempts to toughen the state's recycling requirements, to shut down its sole nuclear power plant, and to regulate land use more closely. Two measures restricting abortions also failed. UTAH</p>
        <p>Representative Wayne Owens of Salt Lake City, who has been the only Democrat in Utah's delegation, defeated a challenge from Genevieve Atwood, a Republican who is a former State Representative.</p>
        <p>Another Democrat, Bill Orton, will join the delegation, in the Provo seat left open by Representative Howard C. Nielson, a Republican who is retiring. Mr. Orton, 42 years old, a tax lawyer and first-time candidate, won in what is often called the most Republican district in the nation. He emphasized his conservative ideology, supporting a balanced-budget amendment, a smaller Federal Government and anti-abortion laws.</p>
        <p>Mr. Orton's Republican opponent was former State Senator Karl Snow, a 60-year-old professor and administrator at Brigham Young University, who has been the subject of an investigation by The Provo Herald into his ownership of certain stocks and his business association with a convicted felon.</p>
        <p>The State Legislature remains Republican. WASHINGTON</p>
        <p>Representative Jolene Unsoeld, a freshman Democrat who was elected to Congress in 1988 by only 618 votes, defeated Bob Williams, a former State Representative, by 13,000 votes. Mrs. Unsoeld's narrow victory two years ago made her a premier target of Republicans in 1990. Mr. Williams accused Mrs. Unsoeld of being a typical "tax-and-spend liberal." She said Mr. Williams was anti-environment and conservative.</p>
        <p>In another contest, Representative John Miller, a conservative Republican in his third term representing the First Congressional District in northern Seattle, defeated Cynthia Sullivan, a member of the King County Council. She said Mr. Miller had neglected local problems, including traffic congestion, and voted wrong on environmental issues. But his endorsement by the Sierra Club and the League of Conservation Voters deflated that issue.</p>
        <p>Voters overwhelmingly rejected a sweeping environmental measure because, opponents said, they feared losing control over community issues. Voters in the Seattle-Tacoma area also rejected a proposed real estate tax increase to pay for the preservation of open land.</p>
        <p>Democrats retained control of the State House and were in a close race to take control of the Senate.  WYOMING</p>
        <p>Alan K. Simpson, the powerful Senate Republican Whip, easily won re-election against a political newcomer. He soundly defeated Kathy Helling, a 32-year-old sociology major at the University of Wyoming who challenged Mr. Simpson's positions on economic development and energy policy. The outcome reflected local polls that showed Mr. Simpson to be Wyoming's most popular statewide official.</p>
        <p>In Wyoming's sole Congressional district, Craig Thomas, the freshman Republican who replaced Dick Cheney when he was named Secretary of Defense, defeated Peter Maxfield, a Democratic lawyer and former dean of the University of Wyoming Law Schol.</p>
        <p>In the race for governor, Mike Sullivan, a popular Democrat, won re-election with a 2 to 1 ratio. His Republican opponent, Mary Mead, is a rancher and daughter of former Gov. Clifford P. Hansen.</p>
        <p>Republicans retain control of the Legislature.</p>
        <p>THE 1990 ELECTIONS: STATE BY STATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
