<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Good Reasons To Protect Trees</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="407363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREES AND SHRUBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JESCVAGE-BERNARD, KARENB</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D81531F93AA35751C1A966958260" item-length="627" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Good Reasons To Protect Trees</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I would like to comment on "Updating a Tree Ordinance: Property Rights vs. Public Good"  [ Nov. 18 ] .</p>
        <p>My only criticism of the pro-tree arguments quoted in support of strengthening and expanding existing legislation is: they don't go far enough. I think there are many more reasons to protect public and private trees, which should be enumerated in any ordinance. Here are some of them:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I would like to comment on "Updating a Tree Ordinance: Property Rights vs. Public Good"  [ Nov. 18 ] .</p>
        <p>My only criticism of the pro-tree arguments quoted in support of strengthening and expanding existing legislation is: they don't go far enough. I think there are many more reasons to protect public and private trees, which should be enumerated in any ordinance. Here are some of them:</p>
        <p>Trees Make Money. A nationwide survey of realtors by American Mortgage Banking turned up these tree facts:</p>
        <p>*Buyers will pay up to 15 percent more for a treed lot than a clear-cut lot.</p>
        <p>*Home buyers will pay 8 to 10 percent more for a property landscaped with healthy shade trees -- and the higher the sales price, the more important trees are.</p>
        <p>*Homes with mature trees sell faster than homes without.</p>
        <p>These survey results make it clear that trees increase residential property values.</p>
        <p>Trees Save Money. Energy studies comparing homes on treed and untreed properties show how we can realize stupendous savings on our utility bills. Winter heating bills can be cut by as much as 33 percent if a thick windbreak of evergreens is planted to block incoming winter winds.</p>
        <p>In summer, a single tall, dense deciduous tree (like a sugar maple, oak or beech) planted on the southwest side of the house can cool the interior as effectively as four medium-sized air-conditioners running 24 hours a day. By carefully choosing and siting trees on our property, each of us could save money on our gas, oil and electric bills while decreasing our demand for dwindling fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>Trees Work Free. Besides trapping airborne pollutants before they reach our lungs, the leafy canopy of trees breaks the force of rain hitting the ground and thus prevents flash flooding and soil erosion (two environmental problems of special interest in steep and hilly Westchester County).</p>
        <p>By stopping erosion and flooding, trees keep silt from filling our ponds, lakes and reservoirs and also keep runoff from septic systems and storm sewers off our roads and out of our drinking and recreational water.</p>
        <p>Without trees to do this work, think what we would have to pay for protection, correction and control: the price for retaining walls, municipal sewers, sewage-treatment plants, water- and air-pollution control devices and dredging, drainage and flood-control projects staggers the imagination -- and it would all have to be from increased taxes.</p>
        <p>Trees Help Halt Global Warming. Now that we know how trees prevent the lethal build-up of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere, world attention is focused on saving the tropical rain forests. But how many of us think about America's lost rain forest? When the first European immigrants arrived 370 years ago, a belt of gigantic trees stretched from the Atlantic to the Mississippi.</p>
        <p>Two hundred and fifty years later, this temperate rain forest had been completely cut. Only now can we begin to see and assess the effects of this unintentional experiment on the planet's climate. Protecting existing enclaves of trees is not enough: we need to replant America's primal forest as much as possible, as fast as possible.</p>
        <p>Are our trees really invisible? In our yards, in our towns, in our world, trees are the lungs that take in carbon dioxide and breathe back oxygen, they are the heart that pumps water from the soil back to the sky, the liver that detoxifies poisons and pollutants put into the air and water, the kidneys that regulate the flow of water through the planet's system. And they do all this quietly, invisibly and tax free.</p>
        <p>These are some of the benefits our local officials might consider adding to the list of esthetic and historic amenities that trees provide for our towns. KAREN JESCVAGE-BERNARD Croton-on-Hudson</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
