<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Painting the Pentagon Green</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="366879"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">NUNN, SAM (SEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D71738F93AA35754C0A966958260" item-length="517" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Painting the Pentagon Green</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Senator Nunn has recently offered a plan to enlist the Pentagon's aid in saving the planet. Though the chairman of the Armed Services Committee's new interests may not be entirely unconnected to his old interest in safeguarding military spending, his ideas are worth considering on their merits. They open up potentially important areas for cooperation, and set off a number of alarm bells.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Senator Nunn has recently offered a plan to enlist the Pentagon's aid in saving the planet. Though the chairman of the Armed Services Committee's new interests may not be entirely unconnected to his old interest in safeguarding military spending, his ideas are worth considering on their merits. They open up potentially important areas for cooperation, and set off a number of alarm bells.</p>
        <p>Senator Nunn has recently offered a plan to enlist the Pentagon's aid in saving the planet. Though the chairman of the Armed Services Committee's new interests may not be entirely unconnected to his old interest in safeguarding military spending, his ideas are worth considering on their merits. They open up potentially important areas for cooperation, and set off a number of alarm bells.</p>
        <p>He suggests the Pentagon can help in gathering data about the environment, developing new energy technologies and inventing new techniques of environmental cleanup.</p>
        <p>Military ships, submarines, planes and satellites, for example, regularly visit inaccessible parts of the globe and could gather important data about pollution, the earth's climate and the possibility of global warming. Nuclear submarines habitually patrol beneath the Arctic icecap, the thinning of which would be an important indicator of the predicted greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>In addition, some spy satellites gather infrared data, which could perhaps also be used to monitor the earth's heat balance. Warships on routine patrols could measure the ocean temperature. Some of the best data on the protective ozone layer in the stratosphere already come from an adapted U-2 spy plane.</p>
        <p>Fitting these various military platforms with the appropriate sensors, if they don't carry them already, would not be too expensive. The question is whether publishing the data might compromise national security by revealing the patrolling areas of submarines and satellites' capabilities. Environmentalists may protest that it would be better to transfer these vital data-gathering missions directly to environmental agencies rather than have them done by the Pentagon on an ad hoc basis. But civilian agencies don't have the money or expertise to operate submarines or satellites, whereas the cost to the Pentagon of adding environmental duties to routine patrols and training missions could be negligible.</p>
        <p>The Defense Department also has much to contribute to the art of cleaning up toxic dumps. Many military bases are contaminated with chemical wastes, and the nuclear weapons production complex, run by the Energy Department, has copious problems of chemical and radioactive waste. If the Pentagon applied serious technical talent to cleaning up these sites, it might well develop cleanup techniques useful for civilian wastes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nunn wants to set up a Defense Environmental Research Council to explore all these initiatives with the Pentagon and Energy Department. This is a promising idea that deserves serious and open-minded consideration. It could benefit the Pentagon by giving budget support to help keep its military capabilities intact, while serving environmental ends as well. It could help environmental agencies by providing data and services that could be duplicated only at great expense.</p>
        <p>But these benefits are hypothetical. The Nunn proposal requires meshing a nascent environmental mission with a formidable bureaucracy. Officials in Washington will have to do much thinking and talking before marrying the lion and the lamb.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
