<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times;   Mankind as Aggressor In the War on the Planet</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="343470"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITGANG, HERBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COMMONER, BARRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOULD, JAY M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDMAN, BENJAMIN A</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MAKING PEACE WITH THE PLANET (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">DEADLY DECEIT (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">GREEN LIFE STYLE HANDBOOK, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DA1E3FF937A25757C0A966958260" item-length="926" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times;   Mankind as Aggressor In the War on the Planet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Herbert Mitgang</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MITGANG, HERBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>Making Peace With the Planet</p>
        <p>By Barry Commoner</p>
        <p>292 pages. Pantheon Books. $19.95.</p>
        <p>Deadly Deceit</p>
        <p>Low-Level Radiation, High-Level Cover-Up</p>
        <p>By Jay M. Gould and Benjamin A. Goldman</p>
        <p>222 pages. Four Walls Eight Windows. $19.95.</p>
        <p>The Green Life Style Handbook</p>
        <p>Edited by Jeremy Rifkin</p>
        <p>202 pages.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>Making Peace With the Planet</p>
        <p>By Barry Commoner</p>
        <p>292 pages. Pantheon Books. $19.95.</p>
        <p>Deadly Deceit</p>
        <p>Low-Level Radiation, High-Level Cover-Up</p>
        <p>By Jay M. Gould and Benjamin A. Goldman</p>
        <p>222 pages. Four Walls Eight Windows. $19.95.</p>
        <p>The Green Life Style Handbook</p>
        <p>Edited by Jeremy Rifkin</p>
        <p>202 pages.</p>
        <p>Making Peace With the Planet</p>
        <p>By Barry Commoner</p>
        <p>292 pages. Pantheon Books. $19.95.</p>
        <p>Deadly Deceit</p>
        <p>Low-Level Radiation, High-Level Cover-Up</p>
        <p>By Jay M. Gould and Benjamin A. Goldman</p>
        <p>222 pages. Four Walls Eight Windows. $19.95.</p>
        <p>The Green Life Style Handbook</p>
        <p>Edited by Jeremy Rifkin</p>
        <p>202 pages. Owl Book/Henry Holt. $10.95.</p>
        <p>Barry Commoner, a scientist who has helped make Americans aware that they live in a fragile environment, says mankind is on a collision course with its own planet. In ''Making Peace With the Planet,'' one of the major books timed to coincide with the 20th anniversary of the first Earth Day on April 22, he sounds the alarm in these words:</p>
        <p>''Clearly, we need to understand the interaction between our two worlds: the natural ecosphere, the thin global skin of air, water and soil and the plants and animals that live in it, and the man-made technosphere - powerful enough to deserve so grandiose a term. The technosphere has become sufficiently large and intense to alter the natural processes that govern the ecosphere. And in turn, the altered ecosphere threatens to flood our great cities, dry up our bountiful farms, contaminate our food and water and poison our bodies - catastrophically diminishing our ability to provide for basic human needs.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Commoner, who directs the Center for the Biology of Natural Systems at Queens College, says the human attack on the ecosphere has instigated an ecological counterattack. His book is a model of clarity even for the reader who knows little about science.</p>
        <p>The trouble with the American system of environmental regulation, he finds, is that it tries to control rather than prevent pollution. As a result, new faults develop that erode the regulatory process. For example, he says that if brewers were forbidden to put plastic nooses on six-packs and supermarkets were not allowed to wrap items in vinyl and then stuff everything into a plastic carrying bag, the petrochemical industry's toxic invasion of the biosphere would be pushed back and the cost of waste disposal reduced.</p>
        <p>Mr. Commoner does not restrict his thinking to his own laboratory. He sees liberalization in the Eastern bloc as an opportunity for nations to cooperate in saving an ecosphere that has no boundaries: ''Now that the people of the world have begun to understand that our survival depends equally on ending the war with nature and on ending the wars among themselves, the path to peace on both fronts becomes clear. To make peace with the planet, we must make peace among the peoples who live in it.''</p>
        <p>The urgency of the environmental battle is illustrated in ''Deadly Deceit,'' a frightening investigative book. It warns of the dangers of low-level radiation and asserts that health hazards are overlooked and routinely covered up. The authors, Jay M. Gould and Benjamin A. Goldman, experts in statistics and waste management, are directors of the Radiation and Public Health Project in New York City. Their supporting evidence is derived from industry and government records.</p>
        <p>''Deadly Deceit'' maintains that after radiation was released at the Savannah River nuclear weapons plant in South Carolina in 1970 and at the Three Mile Island power plant in Pennsylvania in 1979, some 50,000 to 100,000 deaths occurred that were related to the accidents. After 18 years of official concealment, the authors state, the Savannah River reactor-rod meltdowns were disclosed by Senator John Glenn, the Ohio Democrat. The book attributes large increases in infant deaths to birth defects caused by low-level radiation in those places. By contrast, they say, Wyoming and Montana, two states far from nuclear emissions, have among the lowest infant mortality rates in the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gould and Mr. Goldman contend that emissions of fission products from commercial reactors may have set off a cancer epidemic in Millstone, Conn., near New London. They say that many young people born in the peacetime nuclear age have sustained immune-system damage. ''Deadly Deceit'' maintain that local and state governments have been reluctant to make public low-level radiation statistics. It is these statistics that the authors have used to sound the tocsin in their powerful report.</p>
        <p>A more optimistic view can be found in ''The Green Life Style Handbook,'' a sort of do-it-yourself guide for people who want to get involved in environmental activities. For those who like to accumulate odd information, it is even fun to read. How many people know that about 4 percent of the solid waste in the United States is made up of disposable diapers?</p>
        <p>The book is edited by Jeremy Rifkin, the president of the Greenhouse Crisis Foundation in Washington, and is full of practical advice and noble intentions. It includes articles by experts who tell the reader about everything from products that are made without inflicting cruelty on animals to recycling paper for the office, from investing money in socially responsible companies to using the Freedom of Information Act to find out whether a corporation is polluting a hometown river.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rifkin's own contribution concentrates on the greenhouse effect, ozone depletion and acid rain. Similarly, Bill McKibben's recently published ''End of Nature,'' an eloquent book about global warming, the destruction of the rain forest and environmental pollution, called for Americans to live closer to nature in their personal lives. ''The Green Life Style Handbook'' tells how they can do so.Advance Publicationsd(Pantheon Books)Holtzbrinckd(Holt)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
