<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CONSUMER'S WORLD: Coping;   With Winter, in Advance</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="379297"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIRS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REPAIR SERVICES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WARDE, JOHN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CONSUMER'S WORLD PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Service Industries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDD123FF936A1575BC0A966958260" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CONSUMER'S WORLD: Coping;   With Winter, in Advance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN WARDE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WARDE, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The warm, dry weather that usually arrives in the Northeast around Labor Day, ending summer's fiercest heat and humidity, offers ideal conditions for sealing and preparing outdoor surfaces for fall and winter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The warm, dry weather that usually arrives in the Northeast around Labor Day, ending summer's fiercest heat and humidity, offers ideal conditions for sealing and preparing outdoor surfaces for fall and winter.</p>
        <p>The warm, dry weather that usually arrives in the Northeast around Labor Day, ending summer's fiercest heat and humidity, offers ideal conditions for sealing and preparing outdoor surfaces for fall and winter.</p>
        <p>If night temperatures remain above 50 degrees, that's the time for patching and resurfacing blacktop driveways. It improves their ability to repel moisture and withstand repeated freezes and thaws.</p>
        <p>But before the driveway is resurfaced, any damage should be repaired first with a pourable liquid crack-filler or with the latex kind, which can be applied with a caulking gun. Asphalt patching compound can be applied with a trowel. Then apply your blacktop driveway sealer, using a push broom and a squeegee.</p>
        <p>All of these items are available at hardware stores, home-care centers and many department stores. Most crack-fillers and patching compounds are comparable in quality; the best sealers are fortified with rubber to enhance adhesion and with other chemicals, to hasten drying.</p>
        <p>If your home has a flat roof, applying a layer of asphalt roof coating, a product similar to driveway sealer, will prolong its life by protecting the surface and filling small cracks.</p>
        <p>Roof coating should be applied every two or three years regardless of its rated lifespan. Two types of coating - black and metallic, each available in several grades - are manufactured. In the Northeast and other temperate areas, the black variety, which has more asphalt and therefore greater waterproofing, is usually a better choice than the metallic type; the metallic one contains aluminum and sacrifices some sealing ability for the sake of reflecting heat.</p>
        <p>For winter protection, applying or renewing caulking compound is important. The purpose of caulking is to seal gaps between nonmoving building materials like siding, both to prevent drafts and keep out moisture.</p>
        <p>Pure silicone caulking is generally considered best for versatility, elasticity and durability, but newer acrylic latex (sometimes containing silicone), polysulfide and ethylene copolymer caulking compounds are less expensive and usually as effective. (Consult product labels for specific advice.) Acrylic latex and ethylene copolymer caulking can be painted on.</p>
        <p>To seal between masonry and metal, choose butyl caulking; on masonry alone, polyurethane caulking.</p>
        <p>Caulking compound generally will not seal gaps that are wider or deeper than half an inch. The conventional method: First, plug most of the gap with oakum or with fiberglass insulation. Then apply caulking over the insulation. Polyurethane foam in aerosol cans can be used for big gaps.</p>
        <p>Most aerosol foam sealant contains chlorofluorocarbons that scientists say break down the atmosphere's ozone layer. One that does not contain chlorofluorcarbons is DAP Kwik Foam, made by a division of the USG Corporation. It is available at most home centers and hardware stores.</p>
        <p>Polyurethane foam can also be used to seal foundation cracks in basements, as part of a strategy to exclude radon from the home.</p>
        <p>To seal gaps around the moving parts of doors and windows, use weatherstripping. The most effective fits out of sight between the edges of the door, or between the window sash and the frame.</p>
        <p>The most durable is made of spring metal; it must be nailed in place with small brads that come with the weatherstripping. Weatherstripping made of plastic with adhesive backing is also available. It's easier to install, but may last only a few years.</p>
        <p>Easiest of all to install, but the least durable, are foam-rubber strips with adhesive backing. They must be attached indoors, usually to visible parts of window and door frames. Despite shortcomings, this is often the only weatherstripping suitable for casement windows.</p>
        <p>Rotted wood takes special attention. Of course, the best solution is new, sound wood, but this often requires skilled carpentry and may be too expensive or impractical.</p>
        <p>Instead, try treating rotten wood with a liquid hardener containing resins. Then, if necessary, restore missing areas with a companion epoxy or acrylic putty. Minwax High Performance Wood Hardener and High Performance Wood Filler are two such products that are suitable for small-scale patching. They are at home-care centers and hardware stores.</p>
        <p>For extensive restoration, especially on wood that bears a heavy load, consider LiquidWood and WoodEpox, available from the manufacturer, Abatron Inc., at 33 Center Drive, Gilberts, Ill. 60136 or by calling (312) 426-2200.</p>
        <p>Finally, deck, patio, sidewalk and other surfaces that must survive harsh weather should be coated with a clear penetrating seal. Thompson's and Cuprinol are popular brands of sealer for concrete, brick masonry and wood. They are easy to find and they are in compliance with air pollution regulations.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
