<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Minnow to Sturgeon, North American Fish Are in Peril</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="321884"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATERWAYS AND OTHER BODIES OF WATER</classifier>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ENDANGERED SPECIES ACT OF 1973</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waterways and Other Bodies of Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DB1230F933A05752C0A966958260" item-length="1244" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Minnow to Sturgeon, North American Fish Are in Peril</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ONE in three species or subspecies of native freshwater fish in North America is or may be threatened by the degradation of lakes, rivers and streams, scientists say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ONE in three species or subspecies of native freshwater fish in North America is or may be threatened by the degradation of lakes, rivers and streams, scientists say.</p>
        <p>ONE in three species or subspecies of native freshwater fish in North America is or may be threatened by the degradation of lakes, rivers and streams, scientists say.</p>
        <p>Fish in waterways all over the continent are being affected by urban, agricultural and industrial development, pollution and the introduction of competitive or predatory fish, the researchers say.</p>
        <p>And though governmental efforts like the Endangered Species Act have been successful in individual cases, they have been unable to solve the overall problem.</p>
        <p>There are about 1,000 species and subspecies of freshwater fish in the United States, Canada and Mexico. In a new report, the American Fisheries Society says 364 of them fit one of three categories: endangered, which means facing extinction in all or a significant portion of their ranges; threatened, meaning likely to become endangered in the near future; and of ''special concern,'' meaning that relatively minor disturbances to the environment could place them in danger.</p>
        <p>That is 113 more species and subspecies than were on the society's first list, compiled in 1979. It does not include the 40 species thought to have become extinct in this century.</p>
        <p>From Minnows to Sturgeon</p>
        <p>On the new list, published in the November-December issue of the journal Fisheries, are many types of fish throughout the continent, including all 50 states. They range from large to tiny, from obscure to well-known; the list includes species of minnows and killifish, the paddlefish, the Colorado squawfish and two-thirds of all species of North American sturgeon.</p>
        <p>Many kinds of game fish are also endangered or threatened, including sunfish, perch, catfish and 34 kinds of trout, but the report said that only 3 percent of all species on the list are threatened by recreational or commercial fishing.</p>
        <p>''The situation is more alarming than we expected,'' said Dr. Jack E. Williams, director of the society's endangered species committee. ''There has been a continuing downturn in the status of freshwater fish in North America. What is more alarming is that our report finds very few cases of success.''</p>
        <p>Since the Endangered Species Act was adopted in 1973, only four species of fish have recovered enough to be moved from the endangered to the threatened category. None has been removed from the list. In the same period, six species have become extinct and scores more have become endangered or threatened.</p>
        <p>Scientists and environmentalists predict that burgeoning human population and development will push many more species to the brink of extinction or over it. ''The rate of extinction will increase,'' said Dr. Williams, who is also fisheries director of the Bureau of Land Management. ''If we cannot reverse this trend, we will see large-scale species losses and large-scale system failures.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Peter B. Moyle, a fishery biologist at the University of California at Davis, said the list might be too conservative. ''We have lost a number of species,'' he said, ''but we are in danger of rapidly losing many more not on the list.''</p>
        <p>And Maitland Sharp, executive director of the Isaak Walton League, a conservation group, said the study showed that the Endangered Species Act was ''not doing an adequate job protecting these threatened and endangered species.'' He added that Congress and the Federal Fish and Wildlife Service might need to reassess the law.</p>
        <p>The Death of Habitats</p>
        <p>While there is seldom a single factor responsible for a species' decline or extinction, experts agreed that the most pervasive threat is destruction of delicate fish habitats. That destruction assumes many forms: the diversion of water for drinking and irrigation; industrial and agricultural development; sewage and chemical pollution, and the introduction of non-native species.</p>
        <p>A new and serious threat is the proliferation of acid rain. Some lakes and streams in the Northeast and Canada have become so acidic that fish can no longer live in them. In 100,000 lakes in Ontario and Quebec, wild stocks of the endangered aurora trout have been eradicated; half the range of the endangered Acadian whitefish of Nova Scotia has been destroyed.</p>
        <p>''Across southern Canada there has been a tremendous alteration of fishery habitats,'' said Charles Dauphine, coordinator of endangered species for the Canadian Wildlife Service in Ottawa. ''We are quite alarmed by the scale of the threat.''</p>
        <p>But scientists agree that the hardest hit regions are in the arid parts of the Southwestern United States and northern Mexico. The fisheries society says 62 percent of the imperiled species are in five American states - California, Nevada, Arizona, New Mexico and Texas - or in the Mexican states of Sonora, Chihuahua and Coahuila.</p>
        <p>''Every fish in the Southwest is endangered whether or not it is on the list because of the continued population growth in the region,'' said Phil Pister, a biologist for the California Department of Fish and Game who is secretary of the Desert Fishes Council. ''The situation is going to get nothing but worse.''</p>
        <p>The Colorado River once flowed 1,450 miles, from the Rocky Mountains to the Gulf of Mexico. Now not even a trickle often remains at the river's mouth, the water having been captured by large dams and diverted for thirsty crops and human populations.</p>
        <p>In Special Danger: Mexican Fish</p>
        <p>As a result, many fish species have disappeared from the Colorado and its tributaries. And many that survived the loss of habitat have been eliminated by the introduction of non-native fish like the largemouth bass, which prey on native species or compete with them for dwindling food supplies. Compounding the crisis, many species in the arid Southwest live in single small streams or springs, fragile aquatic ecosystems that are easily disrupted.</p>
        <p>Of the 113 species added to the American Fisheries Society's list since 1979, 56 are native to Mexico. The society says that many were added because improved techniques have identified more imperiled species, but that many others were included because growing population and pollution have devastated habitats.</p>
        <p>''Most of our fish in Mexico are in some sort of danger,'' said Dr. Salvador Contreras-Balderas, a co-author of the report who is a professor at the Autonomous University of Nuevo Leon in Monterrey, Mexico.</p>
        <p>''Strong regulations are now beginning to be enforced, but the situation will not get better,'' he said. He cited a lack of experts, ''a lack of economic resources, a lack of ecological conscience.''</p>
        <p>In the Yucatan, for example, many people dump trash and sewage into crevices and caverns, unwittingly destroying the fragile subterranean habitat of the dama blanca ciega, a tiny blind species that faces almost certain extinction.</p>
        <p>In the United States, scientists say, 30 Federal agencies and a plethora of state bodies have addressed the problem species by species instead of dealing with entire communities of fish and freshwater ecosystems. And many experts agree that efforts to halt the decline of freshwater species will meet resistance from political and economic interests.</p>
        <p>But Bob Herbst, executive director of Trout Unlimited, a sport fishing association, said something must be done to halt the decline of even small, obscure and seemingly unimportant species. ''Fish are barometers for the future of humans, like the canary in a coal mine,'' he said. ''Whether a fish species lives indicates the quality of the environment for man.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
