<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Personal Health</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="388713"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DIGESTIVE TRACT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DIET AND NUTRITION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRODY, JANE E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">HEALTH PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PERSONAL HEALTH (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Digestive Tract</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Digestive Tract</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DF1E31F937A35753C1A966958260" item-length="1171" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Personal Health</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jane E. Brody</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRODY, JANE E</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ''What do you do about the gas?'' has become the most frequent response to current dietary advice to eat more fruits and vegetables, beans and peas, bran and whole grains. Indeed, in this high-fiber era, flatulence may have supplanted excess stomach acid as America's primary digestive complaint and concern.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ''What do you do about the gas?'' has become the most frequent response to current dietary advice to eat more fruits and vegetables, beans and peas, bran and whole grains. Indeed, in this high-fiber era, flatulence may have supplanted excess stomach acid as America's primary digestive complaint and concern.</p>
        <p>''What do you do about the gas?'' has become the most frequent response to current dietary advice to eat more fruits and vegetables, beans and peas, bran and whole grains. Indeed, in this high-fiber era, flatulence may have supplanted excess stomach acid as America's primary digestive complaint and concern.</p>
        <p>Unlike bad breath, you don't need a best friend to tell you why you have become a social pariah. You could console yourself with the fact that everyone is in the same boat - at least everyone smart enough to eat the most healthful foods.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, flatulence is not like garlic, which, if eaten by all, cannot be detected by any. And judging from the social history of flatus (virtually every society has greeted it with disdain), it is unlikely ever to achieve social acceptability.</p>
        <p>Though an estimated 30 million Americans are chronically plagued by excess intestinal gas, very few seek medical assistance. Those who do consult a physician are usually told to avoid eating the infamous gas-producing foods.</p>
        <p>Elimination diets appear to benefit about half of extremely flatulent people, said Dr. Michael D. Levitt, an expert in gastrointestinal gas at the Veterans Affairs Medical Center in Minneapolis. But for some people this means eliminating most foods now promoted as important to reducing risks of developing heart disease, cancer and osteoporosis.</p>
        <p>Among the most common gas-inducing foods are milk and milk products, dried beans and peas, unfermented soybean foods, oat bran, cabbage, brussels sprouts, raw carrots, celery, onions, eggplant, bananas, apples, raisins, grapes, high-fiber cereals and white wheat products.</p>
        <p>New Remedies</p>
        <p>A few years ago an alternative to the elimination diet was offered in the form of activated charcoal, a treatment purported to be at least 2,000 years old. Studies showed that when charcoal capsules (Charcocaps by Requa, sold over the counter in pharmacies) were taken before and soon after a bean meal, intestinal gas produced was greatly reduced and the bean eaters reported fewer problems with bloating and flatulence.</p>
        <p>In these studies, charcoal was shown to be far more effective than simethicone, another popular over-the-counter gas chaser that can help to counter stomach gas but apparently does nothing for flatulence.</p>
        <p>Charcoal, however, is not a perfect solution. A lot must be taken - four large capsules before and four after eating a food like beans. For those who would need to use it several times a day, the product can be prohibitively expensive, since it sells for $4 to $6 for 36 capsules. Furthermore, charcoal does not discriminate in the compounds it blocks; it may also reduce intestinal absorption of needed drugs and mineral nutrients.</p>
        <p>But now there is more good news for the bean and broccoli lovers of the world. The producers of Lactaid, the enzyme product that makes milk digestible for people with lactose intolerance, have a new product: an enzyme that digests the gas-producing compounds in foods like beans, broccoli, cabbage, onions and eggplant.</p>
        <p>Studies sponsored by the manufacturer, anecdotal reports from scores of people who tried it on their own and personal experience strongly suggest that use of the product, aptly dubbed Beano, can greatly reduce the gaseous legacy of many vegetable foods. Wherefore Flatus?  Everyone has intestinal gas. It is produced by bacteria that live in the large intestine, or colon, when they metabolize compounds that reach there undigested.</p>
        <p>More than 99 percent of rectal gas is made up of odorless vapors - carbon dioxide, nitrogen, hydrogen, oxygen and methane. But it also has other chemicals so pungent that people can detect them at levels of one part in 100 million parts of air.</p>
        <p>Normal, healthy people eating ordinary foods release about a quart of rectal gas a day. But if a sensitive person eats an especially gaseous food, flatus production can soar.</p>
        <p>The culprit foods contain complex sugars called oligosaccharides that the human body is unable to digest. Instead of being broken down by intestinal enzymes, these sugars pass through to the colon where resident bacteria use them for food. Hydrogen and other gases are the byproducts of microbial digestion.</p>
        <p>Interestingly, some intestinal bacteria can consume the hydrogen that other bacteria produce, and the balance and relative efficiency of these two groups of bacteria in the bowels of different people may partly explain why some people release more gas than others.</p>
        <p>How the Enzyme Works</p>
        <p>Beano contains the sugar-digesting enzyme that people lack. It is called an alpha-galactosidase and it breaks apart the indigestible alpha-linked complex sugars that are the main source of trouble in legumes, cruciferous (cabbage-family) vegetables and many other vegetables, as well whole grains, bran and some seeds.</p>
        <p>The commercially produced enzyme, made by the fungus Aspergillus niger, is sold in liquid form. Its flavor resembles that of soy sauce, and it needs to be used only once with the first mouthful of the culprit food (cooled so as not to inactivate the enzyme by heat) or with some other cool food just before the gaseous food is consumed.</p>
        <p>From 3 to 10 drops per serving of a gaseous vegetable usually can prevent undue flatulence.</p>
        <p>The manufacturer cautions that Beano cannot get rid of all sources of flatus. There are soluble and insoluble fibers that people - but not intestinal bacteria - are unable to digest. Beano also has no effect on lactose, the milk sugar that causes flatulence and bloating in people with lactose intolerance.</p>
        <p>For the lactose problem, the enzyme lactase must be used before lactose-containing foods are consumed. Lactase is available in liquid and tablet forms as Lactaid and as milk digestant tablets produced by Natural Brand (sold in General Nutrition Center stores).</p>
        <p>Lactase in liquid form can be added to milk 24 hours ahead to allow it to predigest 70 to 99 percent of the lactose, depending upon how much of the enzyme is used. For more solid dairy products (like cottage cheese and ice cream) and for foods made with dairy products (like pancakes, soups and some breads), lactose tablets taken just before consuming the foods can aid in their digestion. The tablets are also handy when eating dairy products away from home.</p>
        <p>Lactase has been a remarkably successful product among milk lovers who are lactose-intolerant. Only time and wider experience will tell if alpha-galactosidase will be as successful in countering gas from beans and other plant foods. Its only drawback to date is the possibility that some sensitive people, particularly those allergic to molds or penicillin, may experience nausea or gastric upset when using the enzyme.</p>
        <p>If Beano is not available from local pharmacies, it can be bought by direct mail from Lactaid Inc., P.O. Box 111, Pleasantville, N.J. 08232, or by calling the toll-free number 800-257-8650, Monday through Friday between 8:30 A.M. and 5:30 P.M., Eastern time. A 75-serving vial of Beano sells for $8.95.</p>
        <p>HEALTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
