<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Frigid December, A Warm January, Alas</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="319992"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOMBS AND BOMB PLOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIE DETECTORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL RIGHTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ENTERPRISE (ALA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMOTHERS, RONALD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'FERRELL, ROBERT WAYNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D81F3DF936A15752C0A966958260" item-length="722" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Frigid December, A Warm January, Alas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM E. SCHMIDT, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Jan. 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: On the University of Chicago campus, ranks of ice sculptures carved for the school's annual Winter Festival are melting slowly into January's mud, and plans to build a giant snow house have been called off.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: On the University of Chicago campus, ranks of ice sculptures carved for the school's annual Winter Festival are melting slowly into January's mud, and plans to build a giant snow house have been called off.</p>
        <p>On the University of Chicago campus, ranks of ice sculptures carved for the school's annual Winter Festival are melting slowly into January's mud, and plans to build a giant snow house have been called off.</p>
        <p>''The festival is supposed to be our way of expressing joy in the midst of a grim, cold winter,'' Don Levine, a sociology professor who helped organize the festival, said Tuesday as drizzle fell on the snowless campus. ''Well, it may not be very cold, but it's still pretty grim, isn't it?''</p>
        <p>From the northern Plains, across the Midwest and into the East, a long interlude of unseasonably mild weather is wreaking havoc with the heart of winter.</p>
        <p>Although December saw record-setting low temperatures as far South as Florida, the National Weather Service says January is just the opposite. If present trends continue, this will be the mildest January in Chicago and other parts of the Upper Midwest since 1933. #13 Degrees Above Normal Level The average daily temperature so far in January has been 34.5 degrees, compared with a normal temperature for this time of year of 21.4 degrees.</p>
        <p>While that is good news for homeowners worrried about heating bills, nearly two weeks worth of daytime temperatures near 40 and above have ruined the plans of skiers, snowmobilers and other winter sport enthusiasts, and forced the organizers of the region's growing roster of winter festivals to rearrange events and, where possible, nature.</p>
        <p>At the St. Paul Winter Carnival in Minnesota, the nation's largest and oldest winter festival, more than 1,000 cubic yards of snow was imported by truck this week from a nearby ski resort so snow sculptors could go to work this weekend on the otherwise barren grounds of the State Capitol.</p>
        <p>''Seeing as people don't like to ski on grass, we've already canceled the cross country ski race,'' said Margie Simon, a spokeswoman for the carnival. And she said the snowshoe marathon would be just a regular running race this winter.</p>
        <p>The warm weather has also caused problems for a team of Soviet ice carvers, who traveled to the festival to carve a 60-foot-long, 18-foot-high firebird out of ice. Heavy tarpaulins have been placed on scaffolding surrounding the sculpture in an attempt to keep warm sun off the ice, which causes the ice to lose its transparency and turn a kind of milky white.</p>
        <p>In northwest Indiana, near Chicago, organizers of a winter carnival in La Porte County have called off this weekend's snowmobile race and warned ice fishermen to stay off some lakes. Just a few weeks ago, more than three feet of snow was on the ground, said Mark Kuta, an organizer of the race. ''And then the thermometer went up, and the snow went away, and now it feels like March outside,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dangers on Lakes</p>
        <p>The midwinter warming has also made ice on lakes treacherous. On one lake near St. Paul, a dozen automobiles have already fallen through the ice, and at least one snowmobile rider was killed when his machine broke through thin ice.</p>
        <p>James Wagner, a meteorologist with the Weather Service's Prediction Branch, described this winter's weather as ''strange,'' or at least difficult to predict. After December's cold, Mr. Wagner and his colleagues were calling for temperatures in January to be 10 to 15 degrees below normal.</p>
        <p>Instead of arctic fronts charging down from the North Pole, he said, the weather from Denver to Buffalo has been mostly dominated by an upper air system in the eastern Pacific Ocean, which has brought a westerly flow of relatively warm and damp air deep into the country.</p>
        <p>''Of course everyone wants to know if this is part of global warming, or the greenhouse effect,'' Mr. Wagner said, in response to a question about the unseasonably mild January. He said he thought this winter's odd weather had more to do with atmospheric variability, rather than some larger sustained trend.</p>
        <p>In fact, he said, if an average is taken of temperatures so far during December and January, they are still mostly on the cold side in most parts of the country.</p>
        <p>In Chicago, Don Morrison, a meteorologist with the local Weather Service office, said the weather in the next few days would become a bit cooler, with a possibility of wet snow on Thursday. But as for today, with temperatures near 50 and clear skies, Mr. Morrison said he was planning to play golf.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
