<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mitchell Set to Move a Clean Air Bill to Senate Floor</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="330554"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITCHELL, GEORGE J (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D6113FF93BA15751C0A966958260" item-length="715" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mitchell Set to Move a Clean Air Bill to Senate Floor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As bargaining on clean air legislation continued out of the public eye, the Senate majority leader, George J. Mitchell of Maine, insisted today that he would bring legislation back to the floor Thursday, with or without an agreement with the Bush Administration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As bargaining on clean air legislation continued out of the public eye, the Senate majority leader, George J. Mitchell of Maine, insisted today that he would bring legislation back to the floor Thursday, with or without an agreement with the Bush Administration.</p>
        <p>As bargaining on clean air legislation continued out of the public eye, the Senate majority leader, George J. Mitchell of Maine, insisted today that he would bring legislation back to the floor Thursday, with or without an agreement with the Bush Administration.</p>
        <p>In discussions over the last month, Senate leaders and Administration negotiators have reached agreement on many elements of legislation to strengthen the Clean Air Act of 1970. They include the difficult issues of how to control toxic chemicals sent into the air by industry and new requirements for cities that have not been able to reduce smog to levels mandated by law.</p>
        <p>As of today, however, the two sides have not been able to resolve differences on several other important issues, most of them having to do with how stringently to crack down on pollution from automobiles.</p>
        <p>Negotiations on Acid Rain</p>
        <p>Today the negotiators took on the still unresolved question of how the legislation would deal with acid rain, which is not a major source of contention between Senate leaders and the Administration but is an area of dispute among senators themselves. Both the legislation proposed by President Bush last year and the bill reported by the Senate Environment and Public Works Committee, now pending on the Senate floor. would require coal-burning power plants to make steep reductions in the pollution that causes acid rain.</p>
        <p>A number of Senators, particularly from the Midwest, where most of the plants are situated, are concerned about the impact the plan would have on their states' economies and are seeking changes.</p>
        <p>Senator Mitchell said today that he would introduce substitute legislation on Thursday to incorporate the negotiated changes. He did not say what he would do about those areas of the bill for which there was no agreement.</p>
        <p>While negotiators were unable to agree with the White House on how much to control automobile pollution, sources said Senator Mitchell had reached a compromise with Senator Carl Levin, Democrat of Michigan, that would reduce some concerns of Detroit's manufacturers.</p>
        <p>Cloture Move Possible</p>
        <p>For one thing, car makers would not be required to increase their vehicles' fuel efficiency substantially so as to reduce carbon-dioxide pollution. Carbon dioxide from burning fossil fuels is the most significant industrial gas now accumulating in the atmosphere, and many scientists believe this will lead to a substantial warming of the earth in the next century.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the Majority Leader said Senator Mitchell might introduce a petition on Thursday to limit debate and the number of amendments that may be offered to the bill. The petition for cloture needs 60 votes to be adopted.</p>
        <p>Senator Mitchell has repeatedly said that he has conducted the back-room negotiations because without them he would be unable to block or end a filibuster, particularly if it is supported by the White House.</p>
        <p>President Bush has said he would not accept the committee bill because it was too costly. Administration officials said the Senate bill would cost the country $41 billion a year by the year 2000, whereas the President's bill would cost $19 billion. Senate aides and enviromentalists say the Administration's cost estimates are based on incorrect assumptions and are grossly inflated.</p>
        <p>The disagreement over controlling automobile pollution is largely about a provision in the Senate bill that would require two rounds of reductions of tailpipe emissions of ozone and carbon monoxide. The Administration strongly objects to the second round of controls, scheduled to go into effect in 2003 under the Senate bill, on the ground that it would cost a huge sum and achieve only marginal improvement in air quality.</p>
        <p>The Senate leaders, joined by state air quality officials and environmentalists, maintain that the goal of clean air cannot be met in most cities without the second round of tailpipe controls, given the growing number of cars on the road and the steadily increasing number of miles driven by each car.</p>
        <p>The compromise on controlling toxic chemicals in the air removes one of the sorest points of contention between senators and the Administration, which said compliance with the Senate committee's provision would force many companies out of business.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
