<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Washington at Work;   Bush's Adviser on Domestic Policy: The Perfect Person to Win the Point</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="338805"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIDES AND EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOWD, MAUREEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PORTER, ROGER B (BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900329T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDB123DF93AA15750C0A966958260" item-length="1736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Washington at Work;   Bush's Adviser on Domestic Policy: The Perfect Person to Win the Point</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DOWD, MAUREEN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Roger Porter has a theory that you can learn a lot about people by watching them on the tennis court.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Roger Porter has a theory that you can learn a lot about people by watching them on the tennis court.</p>
        <p>Roger Porter has a theory that you can learn a lot about people by watching them on the tennis court.</p>
        <p>Take Mr. Porter himself, an expert player who often plays doubles with President Bush.</p>
        <p>The court strategy of the Assistant to the President for Economic and Domestic Policy is patient, steady, cerebral. He is scrupulous about line calls and he is willing to rally eight or nine times while he decides exactly which shot to set up for a put-away.</p>
        <p>''A lot of players play impatiently,'' he says, talking about tennis and about life. ''And it is not easy in tennis, unless you're much better than your opponent, to score a lot of outright winners. My point is to win the point, but not to do it in any particular time frame.''</p>
        <p>An Emphasis on Details</p>
        <p>Because of his amiable, meticulous and tenacious nature, Mr. Porter is regarded as the perfect person to run the domestic policy shop at a time when the President is focusing on the more heady foreign policy agenda, earmarking the first part of the peace dividend for aid to Panama and Nicaragua, while domestic policy is found more in details than in grand schemes.</p>
        <p>Some wags wonder what Mr. Porter does all day, arguing that Mr. Bush's domestic policy, as George J. Mitchell of Maine, the Senate majority leader, drily observes, ''is notable primarily for its absence.''</p>
        <p>This month Senator Mitchell noticed Mr. Porter's presence. The paradigm of the team player so celebrated in the Bush Adminstration, Mr. Porter was not very visible in his first year. He gained a higher profile as indefatigable point man for the Administration's Clean Air Act, winning from Mr. Mitchell a compromise measure that is tougher in some respects than the White House wanted but is still weaker than a Senate committee version - weaker enough that some of his colleagues think the majority leader is giving away too much.</p>
        <p>Domestic Approach Disputed</p>
        <p>Democrats hope the White House strategy is a vulnerability, that American anxiety about trying to make America work better at home and so compete better abroad will lead to dissatisfaction with the President's domestic approach.</p>
        <p>Mr. Porter argues that within the constraints of fiscal responsibility the President has advanced a bold domestic and economic agenda on clean air, child care, education, capital gains, and drugs and crime.</p>
        <p>''I do not agree with the notion that the President has failed to put forward dramatic initiatives,'' Mr. Porter said. ''Quite the contrary, his initiatives are dominating the agenda. He is also building bridges to governors, to Congress and to the country. His domestic policy is not dependent on heavy-handed Government mandates, but on market-oriented approaches. The rest of the world is now following our lead on this.''</p>
        <p>A Black Belt in White Paper</p>
        <p>Even in a city of policy wonks, Mr. Porter is an acknowledged black belt in white paper, a voluminous note-taker and voracious document-reader who spends long hours brokering complex programs with a host of bickering agencies and interest groups.</p>
        <p>''Policy is his bag,'' said Marlin Fitzwater, the White House spokesman. ''He's one of those guys who reads the Federal Register and notices the fine print. He can tell you how much carbon monoxide amounts to how much global warming.''</p>
        <p>Told that on the subject of policy he often utters pedantic sentences, Mr. Porter replies with self-deprecating humor, ''But I am a walking textbook, you know that.''</p>
        <p>Methodical? He is so methodical that he tears out the advertisements from news magazines before he reads them so that they can be stored in smaller stacks afterward.</p>
        <p>Hard-working? Mr. Porter, who eats warmed-over dinners when he gets home past 9 P.M. and who has been known to spend the night on his office couch, processes so much paper that he needs six in-boxes, occasionally using his closet as a seventh.</p>
        <p>Asleep at a Rock Concert</p>
        <p>On weekends and evenings he sometimes brings his three children into the office; his wife, Ann, says the brood has grown up helping him type memos. The hours sometimes catch up with him. He once took his son to a Michael Jackson concert and managed to sleep through it.</p>
        <p>Disciplined? Raised in a studious, ordered Mormon household, where his mother read books to the children at the dinner table and his father taught them the art of arranging books neatly in a bookcase, the 43-year-old Utah native does not drink, smoke, swear, guzzle coffee, leave messes or lose his temper.</p>
        <p>Mr. Porter says he never thought about rebelling as a teen-ager because he was ''too busy.'' His A average in high school and at Brigham Young University was marred by a handful of A-minuses, including one he says he didn't deserve in physics because the final exam was on the day President John F. Kennedy was assassinated and the teacher refused to postpone the exam.</p>
        <p>Mr. Porter, who started college at 16, took two years off to work in England as a Mormon missionary. ''My family gave me a legacy of an approach to life that is structured but not rigid,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Two Kinds of Advisers</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, who first met Mr. Porter in 1976 when President Gerald R. Ford asked him to join in a game of doubles, likes two kinds of advisers. His barbed wire side, developed in his years in Texas politics, likes realpolitik tough guys like Lee Atwater, the Republican national chairman, and John H. Sununu, the White House chief of staff. His more genteel side is attracted to moderate, progressive, noblesse oblige advisers like Mr. Porter and William K. Reilly, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>Asked to offer a list of public officials to call for a profile of his first year, Mr. Porter named as many Democrats as Republicans.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Porter says that even when her husband chides the children about chores, he sets up a gentle ''win-win situation,'' adding: ''If a room needs to be cleaned, he might offer to clean it with them. He operates very much from a base of trust.''</p>
        <p>In the days of sweeping influence exercised by predecessors in the domestic policy post like John D. Ehrlichman in the Nixon Administration and Stuart E. Eizenstat in the Carter Administration, gentle compromise was not a necessary building block for operations in that post. Nor is the office the petri dish for conservative ideological debate that it was in the Reagan years. Under Mr. Porter, the let's-cut-them-off-at-the-knees attitude that sometimes prevailed in the past has given way to a let-us-reason-together-without-spending-money attitude.</p>
        <p>Once the domestic policy office could dictate terms to the Office of Management and Budget. Now Richard G. Darman, Mr. Bush's budget director, as brainy and strong-willed as his close ally Mr. Sununu, dictates the terms to the domestic policy office.</p>
        <p>A Technician, Not a Strategist</p>
        <p>''Porter becomes less a principal and more a staffer for Sununu,'' said one White House insider. ''He's more a technician than a strategist.'' But in George Bush's White House, the likes of Mr. Porter and Mr. Reilly can be comfortable - even when others seem to be dominating their fields.</p>
        <p>''I do not sense a contest or competition there,'' Mr. Porter says of Mr. Darman, with whom he shared teaching duties a decade ago at Harvard's Kennedy School for courses like managing Federal policy development.</p>
        <p>Mr. Darman had the brazen dash in the classroom, Mr. Porter the quiet charm. Those who know both men say their talents are still complementary.</p>
        <p>Mr. Porter is skilled at taking the issue of the moment, finding out where everyone stands, clarifying and organizing their positions, and presenting them to the President in a fair way.</p>
        <p>''He was born to process,'' a colleague said of Mr. Porter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Darman has a rare ability for taking the issue of the moment and developing a strategy on how it will play three years hence.</p>
        <p>Complaints Over Bush Policy</p>
        <p>The Administration has astutely tried to co-opt some Democratic issues, like child care and the environment, but complaints are growing noisier that, on domestic policy, Mr. Bush speaks loudly but carries a small stick.</p>
        <p>The Administration's transportation policy, in which the budget office removed or changed references to Federal spending, ''crystallizes why this Administration's domestic agenda is devoid of policy,'' Senator Mitchell said. ''Essentially, the transportation policy is a catalogue of what's wrong in the country, trying to dump the responsibility off on states and local government. It's the opposite of Federal policy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Porter demurs. ''It is wrong to equate Federal leadership with Federal spending,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Porter played point for the Administration's at the February education summit conference, where the President and the governors agreed on objectives to improve results in education. But educators were dubious that the goals, including making American students the first in the world in mathematics and science by the turn of the century, could be achieved.</p>
        <p>Compromise on Clean Air Law</p>
        <p>As to the first revision of the nation's clean air laws since 1977, though environmentalists agree that Mr. Bush is more sensitive to their cause than Ronald Reagan was, they complain that the compromise catered too much to business interests.</p>
        <p>But Administration officials were surprised and thrilled that Mr. Porter pulled a compromise together. Even Democrats like Senator Michell, who day by day is forced to beat off challenges to the compromise by fellow Democrats, came away praising the domestic policy adviser as even-tempered, open-minded and candid.</p>
        <p>Mr. Porter says this patient style will work. ''As Gorbachev has learned, you can't turn around a country from the top,'' Mr. Porter said. ''It has to come from the bottom.''</p>
        <p>Roger Blaine Porter</p>
        <p>Assistant to the President for Economic and Domestic Policy</p>
        <p>Born: June 19, 1946</p>
        <p>Hometown: Provo, Utah</p>
        <p>Education: B.A. magna cum laude in history and political science from Brigham Young University, 1969. Rhodes Scholar. Woodrow Wilson Fellow. Bachelor of Philosophy, Oxford University, 1971. M.A. and Ph.D. in Government, Harvard University, 1978.</p>
        <p>Previous washington jobs: Special Assistant to the President, Ford Administration, 1974-77; Deputy Assistant to the President for Policy Development, Reagan Administration, 1981-85.</p>
        <p>Interests: History, classical music, basketball, tennis, travel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
