<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tiny Bubbles Explain the Babble of Undersea Noise</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="407762"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NOISE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DC1730F932A25751C1A966958260" item-length="2091" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tiny Bubbles Explain the Babble of Undersea Noise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>UNTIL recently, the blur of noise just beneath the surface of the sea seemed as meaningless as the roar of a conch shell held against the ear. But pioneers in a new branch of science are learning to make sense of the noise and from it to measure phenomena that shape global climate.</p>
        <p>The source of much of the noise permeating the ocean's surface layer has turned out to be underwater clouds of microscopic bubbles that act as miniature loudspeakers. Dr. Herman Medwin of the Naval Postgraduate School in Monterey, Calif., has dubbed them "screaming infant microbubbles."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>UNTIL recently, the blur of noise just beneath the surface of the sea seemed as meaningless as the roar of a conch shell held against the ear. But pioneers in a new branch of science are learning to make sense of the noise and from it to measure phenomena that shape global climate.</p>
        <p>The source of much of the noise permeating the ocean's surface layer has turned out to be underwater clouds of microscopic bubbles that act as miniature loudspeakers. Dr. Herman Medwin of the Naval Postgraduate School in Monterey, Calif., has dubbed them "screaming infant microbubbles."</p>
        <p>These and other previously unsuspected sources of oceanic sound are under intense study. Scientists hope they will provide measures of the oceans' rainfall, wind speeds, oceanic currents and the exchange of gases and heat between the oceans and the atmosphere. Such indicators are vital to understanding the dynamics of climate, including the global warming that some studies suggest may result from increasing amounts of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Acoustical oceanography, as the new science is called, was the subject of a special session held last month at a meeting of the Acoustical Society of America in San Diego. Reports presented at the meeting, which have riveted the attention of physicists, oceanographers and climatologists, focused on microbubbles.</p>
        <p>Microbubbles are measured in microns, or millionths of a meter. By comparison a human hair is about 100 microns thick. Microbubbles range in diameter from about 20 to 200 microns. These bubbles are created by breaking waves and by raindrops falling into the sea. Unlike larger bubbles, which quickly rise to the surface, microbubbles can remain virtually suspended in water at depths as great as 300 feet.</p>
        <p>Most microbubbles are too small to be seen except under a microscope, and their very existence was doubted by scientists until the mid-1960's. Many physicists believed that the gas trapped in such a small bubble would be so highly compressed that it would quickly dissolve in the surrounding water, causing the bubble to collapse.</p>
        <p>But investigators recently discovered that a microbubble's surface is an efficient scavenger, gathering up bacteria, organic matter and other dirt, which form a barrier through which gas does not quickly diffuse, Dr. Medwin said. A microbubble can therefore survive much longer than was previously believed.</p>
        <p>Another recent discovery was that microbubbles make noise -- much more noise than that caused by the patter of rain on the surface of water.</p>
        <p>When a raindrop hits the water, Dr. Medwin said, the impact makes a sound that lasts for about one thousandth of a second. The sound of many raindrop impacts blends together as a kind of hiss, or "white noise." But after a delay of 20 to 40 one-thousandths of a second, he said, the crater left by the impact in the water may form a microbubble. Infancy of Bubble</p>
        <p>The energy imparted to the gas in the tiny bubble causes it to pulse violently for up to one twenty-fifth of a second. The rate of pulsing during this "infancy" of the bubble ranges from 2,000 to 20,000 hertz (pulses per second), and the pulsation creates intense, high-pitched sound. (A sound of 20,000 hertz is at the extreme upper limit of human hearing.) When the "screaming infant microbubble" uses up the energy imparted by the impact, it becomes an "adult" microbubble and stops emitting sound.</p>
        <p>The high-pitched screech produced by a myriad of pulsating microbubbles might have attracted only academic interest but for the fact that the pitch of the sound is related to the size of the bubbles producing it: the larger the diameter of a bubble, the lower its pitch. When a bubble is formed by falling rain, moreover, its size is directly related to the size of the raindrop that produced it, as well as the angle at which the raindrop hit. Another useful discovery was that the intensity of sound at a given pitch is an index of the rate at which raindrops are hitting the water.</p>
        <p>From these relationships, Dr. Medwin and other acoustical oceanographers said, it is possible to infer air temperature above the ocean (which influences the size to which raindrops grow before falling to the surface).  Subtle changes in the spectrum of sound frequencies emitted by microbubbles result from changes in the angle at which raindrops hit water; drops that hit obliquely produce slightly different sounds from those that land vertically. By inferring the angle at which raindrops hit in a given shower, it is possible to estimate the wind speed that deflected the drops from vertical descent.</p>
        <p>The numbers and sizes of bubbles introduced into the ocean surface strongly affect the exchange of gases, and some estimates of mixing can be made when the numbers and types of raindrops striking the surface is known. In general, the greater the ratio of surface area to volume of the bubbles, the more gas is introduced into the ocean. Measure for Ocean Climate</p>
        <p>Many uncertainties remain to be settled in determining these relationships, he said, but in principle, microbubble sound should give oceanographers and climatologists a powerful new tool for measuring climatic conditions over vast areas of ocean.</p>
        <p>Rainfall, a particularly important factor in climate, is difficult to gauge at sea. On a ship, conventional rain-collecting devices are notoriously unreliable, partly because wind speeds and directions vary greatly, depending where on the ship the instrument is placed. In any case, there are far too few ships at sea to sample oceanic rain patterns adequately, and oceans cover most of the earth's surface.</p>
        <p>Oceanic rainfall is usually estimated from satellite photographs, which measure, among other things, the temperature of cloud tops, a factor related to the probability of rain beneath the clouds.</p>
        <p>"But satellite estimates have never been adequately validated by independent means," Dr. Medwin said. "Now, however, it may be possible to drop arrays of sonobuoys over large areas of ocean, recording the sounds of microbubbles and calculating rain and wind speeds from the sound." Sonobuoys, commonly used for detecting submerged submarines, are ocean buoys from which strings of hydrophones are suspended at different depths. Noises detected by the hydrophones are transmitted by radio to nearby aircraft.</p>
        <p>Proof that microbubbles produce most of the sound in water pelted by raindrops came last year in striking photographs made by the National Center for Physical Acoustics in University, Miss. Dr. Lawrence A. Crum, the center's director, and a postdoctoral student, Dr. Hugh C. Pumphrey, made high-speed photographs showing typical raindrops hitting water. As each photographic frame was exposed, a simultaneous tracing was recorded on the film, showing the frequency and intensity of sound in the water at that instant. Discovery Regarding Sound</p>
        <p>"What we discovered," Dr. Crum said, "was that a resonating microbubble produces most of the sound -- not the impact itself."</p>
        <p>Not all raindrops produce microbubbles, but when they do, the sequence of events is always about the same. First, the impact creates a hemispherical crater in the water's surface. Once the crater is fully formed, a ripple called a capillary wave moves down its walls to the bottom of the crater, where it converges and squeezes the crater wall into a nipple. An instant later, the nipple is pinched off by the ripple to form a microbubble, and this event initiates the "scream."</p>
        <p>High-pitched sound continues for a fraction of a second until the bubble's oscillations run out of energy, in somewhat the way a freely swinging pendulum slows to a halt.</p>
        <p>"When a raindrop hits a sidewalk, it makes a 'splat,' " Dr. Crum said. "But when it hits water, the sound is more like a 'plunk,' and the details of that plunk are what interest us. If we can use this new knowledge to remotely monitor rainfall over the oceans, it will be a tremendous advance for climatology."</p>
        <p>Microbubbles remain useful to oceanographers even when they have stopped making noise.</p>
        <p>Dr. David M. Farmer of the Canadian Government's Institute of Ocean Sciences in Sidney, British Columbia, is using clouds of bubbles to track ocean currents. Working in the water of Saanich Inlet, a glacial fjord north of Vancouver Island, he and his colleagues are using underwater sound transmitters tuned to the resonant frequencies of microbubbles to make the bubbles resonate and produce sound of their own. Broadcasting six different sound frequencies, the group can target a wide range of microbubbles and force them to resonate. The resonant sound is then tracked by directional hydrophones.</p>
        <p>"We've found that it is easy to track bubble clouds this way, and we can therefore study ocean surface currents in detail," Dr. Farmer said. In the past, oceanographers were forced to ignore surface circulation because it was too complex to be measured, he said.</p>
        <p>"But now that we can look at surface circulation we can get quantitative information about coupling -- the interaction of the atmosphere with the oceans -- a vital determinant of climate," Dr. Farmer said. "We can learn more about the exchange of gases and heat between the oceans and atmosphere, and begin to get more realistic approximations of global conditions." Effects of Wind</p>
        <p>One type of ocean circulation of special interest to oceanographers is caused by wind. Wind creates long, rotating "cells" of water that apparently move in corkscrew fashion through the surface layer of the ocean in the direction of the wind. These cells, named for the late physicist Irving Langmuir, who hypothesized their existence, are thought to be responsible for bringing plankton and other organisms to the surface, and atmospheric air to lower depths.</p>
        <p>Where two Langmuir cells lie next to each other and rotate in opposite directions, they seem to act as a pump bringing plankton and other biological material to the surface. As this dirt collects at the boundary between the rotating cells, it is concentrated in a narrow line on the surface, creating a long streak of relatively smooth water aligned with the wind. Such "sea streaks" had never been well explained until recent research revealed their nature.</p>
        <p>In the past, most acoustic research in oceans has been conducted by navies in connection with tracking or evading hostile submarines. Sensitive military techniques can detect very faint sounds emitted by a submarine, even when these signals are almost entirely masked by the background noise of the ocean. Naval research is much more concerned with the signal than the noise.</p>
        <p>"But one person's noise is another's signal," Dr. Farmer said, "and for us, it's the background that's important."</p>
        <p>Useful oceanic sound is not limited to the high frequencies caused by microbubbles. A background noise made up of many kinds of sound -- powerful but inaudibly low notes struck by storms and the thump of breakers, the boom of cracking ice, the rumble of submarine earthquakes -- suffuses the oceans, and scientists are beginning to make some sense of this background.</p>
        <p>Dr. William A. Kuperman of the Naval Research Laboratory in Washington compared oceanic background noise to the diffuse light that bathes a landscape on a cloudy day.</p>
        <p>"It's possible to use that diffuse light or sound to distinguish shapes," he said. "For example, we already know that the diffuse, low-frequency sound of the Pacific Ocean is different from that of the Atlantic. The difference may be caused by the greater steepness of continental shelves under the Pacific, against which surface waves are constantly banging. Our research is aimed at using the ocean as an acoustic lens, through which we hope to discern the shapes of objects as well as details of the ocean itself."  STORMS LEAVE THEIR TRACES IN BUBBLE CLOUDS Sounds that permeate the surface layer of ocean water are caused mainly by tiny, vibrating bubbles created by rain and waves. Their sounds contain clues that may allow scientists to monitor weather conditions in remote oceans. Such information could greatly improve forecasts of global climate. Microscopic bubbles help scientists track currents that form when wind churns surface waters of the ocean into corkscrew swirls called Langmuir cells. Bubbles about the thickness of ahuman hair capture organic material that prevents them from collapsing. Virtually suspended near the ocean surface, the resonating bubbles emit sound allowing scientists to track ocean currents.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
