<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ocean Waves Power a Generator</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="386671"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORWAY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISLAY (SCOTLAND)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">QUEENS UNIVERSITY (BELFAST)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN COMMUNITY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Scotland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D8103EF936A1575AC0A966958260" item-length="1613" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ocean Waves Power a Generator</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS</byline>
      <dateline>BELFAST, Northern Ireland</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ON a rocky headland bashed by the Atlantic Ocean, engineers are finishing a wave power installation that they hope will prove an important stepping stone toward much larger projects in the rush for renewable and clean energy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ON a rocky headland bashed by the Atlantic Ocean, engineers are finishing a wave power installation that they hope will prove an important stepping stone toward much larger projects in the rush for renewable and clean energy.</p>
        <p>ON a rocky headland bashed by the Atlantic Ocean, engineers are finishing a wave power installation that they hope will prove an important stepping stone toward much larger projects in the rush for renewable and clean energy.</p>
        <p>With a simple device in a wave-washed gully, they are tapping some of the immense energy stored in the swell of the ocean and converting it into electricity. They use waves to produce an airstream that drives a turbine. In the coming weeks, the turbine will be linked to a generator that will supply all the current needed by a small community.</p>
        <p>This small station is the simplest effective wave-power device created so far, its engineers say. Its team of engineers from Queens University in Belfast is part of the growing group of experts who argue that there are no inherent obstacles to harnessing the enormous energy potential of the sea.</p>
        <p>The pilot plant at Islay, an island on the west coast of Scotland, is expected to produce a modest average of 40 kilowatts a day, enough for the nearby little village, which now uses diesel fuel. But specialists say units of this size can already be multiplied for island communities or desalinization plants.</p>
        <p>Along the stormy west coast of Europe, several recent studies note, the ocean swell is so mighty and near constant that it could theoretically provide places like Ireland, Scotland and Portugal with more electricity than they need. In deeper offshore waters where waves can have five times as much power, some experts say, the yield could be far greater.</p>
        <p>Although small-scale experiments with wave energy have been going on for several decades, more ambitious projects for commercial quantities of energy have long lingered on the drawing board. Advocates argue that even when projects were technically and economically feasible, progress has been unnecessarily slow, because they have lacked political and financial support.</p>
        <p>But interest in wave power has warmed as the politics and pollution of oil and nuclear energy have become more troublesome. The Persian Gulf crisis, experts say, is now likely to increase support for all forms of renewable energy.</p>
        <p>In recent months, the European Community Commission has for the first time included wave power among alternative energy sources earmarked for research funds in 1991. Norway, Britain, India and Japan have also committed new funds.</p>
        <p>''Man has always been afraid of the power of the sea but I think we are now in the early stages of tapping it,'' said Trevor Whittaker, a naval architect who heads the wave power team at Belfast University.</p>
        <p>The new wave plant sits on a bleak promontory on Islay, a place that feels the full blast of the Atlantic breakers on most days of the the year. In the gully, the team set down a hollow concrete chamber, its front wall partly open to the sea. As a new wave arrives, usually about every 10 seconds, the rising water in the chamber pushes the air into a vent holding a turbine, which drives a generator.</p>
        <p>The receding wave and the dropping water level create a vacuum so that air is sucked back in and continues to drive the turbine. This is possible because Alan Wells, an engineer in Belfast, designed a rotor whose blades are lifted like the wings of an airplane by rising air so that it can spin independently of the direction of the air. American one-direction rotor works on a different principle, with blades pushed onward by air.</p>
        <p>''The technology is so simple, it's amazing a wave energy device was not invented years ago,'' said Stephen McIlwayne, a team member. He has spent many hours on Islay, timing and gauging the swell of the ocean, which inspires him to speak of wave energy on an epic scale.</p>
        <p>The Ocean as a Battery</p>
        <p>''You watch that tremendous power all the way down the coast, and it makes you think of the hundreds of megawatts that are being dashed on the shore and not being used,'' he said. ''The ocean is like a big battery, a huge collector and we can tap it in many places. It's just a matter of time.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Whittaker cautioned against too much short-term optimism because of the fate of some earlier plants. A Norwegian tower, which worked on a similar but more complicated principle, was unhinged from the rocks and destroyed in a storm in 1988. India planned for the world's largest wave power station in Madras by setting a series of turbines into a harbor wall. The project was canceled when waves proved not to be strong enough year round.</p>
        <p>Japan has experimented with devices powering buoys and light-houses. It is now finishing a breakwater for a fishing village that holds devices to produce 40 kilowatts a day. A Portuguese group wants to start a pilot project on the Azores.</p>
        <p>Dispute Over Salter Duck</p>
        <p>But in Britain a bitter dispute has erupted involving the most sophisticated device designed so far, the so-called Salter duck.</p>
        <p>Although Britain had moved faster in wave energy research than other nations, the Government cut off most funds in 1982, after an unfavorable report that presented wave energy as more costly than wind energy and instead recommended more work on wind.</p>
        <p>Stephen Salter, a professor of mechanical engineering at Edinburgh University, has fought the decision ever since. Dr. Salter invented the duck, a machine he said could generate large volumes of energy offshore.</p>
        <p>Dr. Salter charged that the negative report was prepared by experts from the British nuclear agency who strongly favored nuclear energy. He said they had a vested interest in distorting his data and cost estimates. The controversy grew as one consultant who worked on the report testified that his key conclusions were ''changed and even reversed'' against his will.</p>
        <p>The experts responsible for the report have denied that there was any conflict of interest and insisted that the duck was not cost effective. Other engineers have argued that the fight arose because the two sides used widely different assumptions for calculating costs.</p>
        <p>The controversy has become the subject of hearings in Parliament, and Britain's Department of Energy has now begun a new review of the viability of wave energy. Some oceanic engineers hope that this will lead to a new lease on life for Salter's duck.</p>
        <p>Tested in a large wave tank at the University of Edinburgh, the duck, a canister, generates electricity as it moves with the waves, nodding up and down on a spine. Dr. Salter, a robotics specialist, acknowledged that his device would be costly and that it might take years of work before it could go offshore. 2 Kinds of Wave Devices Although different countries are now researching a range of devices, Mr. Salter said there were still only two basic methods to make energy from waves: ''Either you use something rigidly fixed, which must resist every force the wave throws at it, like a boxer who has his head against the wall. Or you have a more complex device that dodges out of the way like the boxer who moves on his feet. The second is far more costly, but it will work in deep water and yield far more energy.''</p>
        <p>Installations using underwater concrete baffles to focus waves toward a narrow point on shore are another example of the fixed-device class, but they have not had great success so far.</p>
        <p>Many experts say they believe that wave power at best can provide only a small part of overall energy needs. Mr. Whittaker believes it is too early to make that judgement.</p>
        <p>''Technically there is enough energy along our coasts to power Britain,'' he said, ''but at this point to deliver 1,000 megawatts to the consumer, you need a wave power plant with machines spread out along 30 miles at some distance from each other, much like underwater fenceposts.''</p>
        <p>With currently available technology, wave power is useful only for small communities. Mr. Whittaker therefore sees the pilot plant on Islay only as a ''way to improve the credibility of wave power and then move on to larger projects.''</p>
        <p>Like other advocates, he argues that the ''technology is too young to judge it.'' He went on: ''You could not have asked the Wright brothers to design a jumbo. If we had looked at the early motorcar or the plane this way, we would have axed the industry.''</p>
        <p>'Waves Bend and Converge'</p>
        <p>Britain, with its large stretches of coast facing the open Atlantic, is now making a survey of wave energy resources along its shores. Other countries, including Ireland, France, Spain and Portugal, are considering making similar studies. Such research includes looking for ''hot spots'' along headlands and other places where waves concentrate. ''Waves bend and converge and focus much like light waves,'' said Mr. McIlwayne, ''so the topography creates places of greater intensity.''</p>
        <p>Other new water-powered projects include setting ranks of barriers to take advantage of changing tidal water levels in the estuaries of coastal rivers. France already has one such tidal energy plant in the mouth of the Rence. But further plans in western Europe have been opposed by environmentalists who say the large barriers would be too disruptive for natural life.</p>
        <p>Compared with solar and wind energy, Mr. Whittaker said, ''ocean waves are the most concentrated form of renewable energy we know, and it is continually created.'' He continued: ''Waves hitting us today could have been generated days ago somewhere else. The whole ocean acts as a collector of solar energy.''</p>
        <p>The Commission of the European Community will have more than $25 million available next year for research into alternative energy. ''We think wave energy has a strong potential and deserves some of those funds,'' said Philippe Bourdeau, the commission's director for environmental and energy research.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
