<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cheering a Flip-Flop</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="362698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WICKER, TOM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDA1031F932A15755C0A966958260" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cheering a Flip-Flop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Tom Wicker</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WICKER, TOM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: When a politician changes his position, he or she is usually derided for a ''flip-flop.'' But here are two cheers for President Bush's about-face decision to help poor countries stop using chemicals destructive to earth's vital ozone shield.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: When a politician changes his position, he or she is usually derided for a ''flip-flop.'' But here are two cheers for President Bush's about-face decision to help poor countries stop using chemicals destructive to earth's vital ozone shield.</p>
        <p>When a politician changes his position, he or she is usually derided for a ''flip-flop.'' But here are two cheers for President Bush's about-face decision to help poor countries stop using chemicals destructive to earth's vital ozone shield.</p>
        <p>A third cheer will be due when Mr. Bush flip-flops again and decides -as mounting evidence dictates - to take action now against global warming, the so-called ''greenhouse effect.'' Under counseling from his iron-fisted chief of staff, John Sununu, Mr. Bush is so far willing only to call for more study.</p>
        <p>That's like seeing Willie Horton at your front door, and asking him in to state his intentions before you call the cops.</p>
        <p>Also on Mr. Sununu's bad advice, the President had welshed on a U.S. pledge to put up $25 million of a fund to help poor nations pay for substitute chemicals more ''ozone-friendly'' -but more expensive - than the damaging chlorofluorocarbons they've agreed to phase out. Under strong international and domestic pressures - including some from within the Administration - Mr. Bush reversed himself and Mr. Sununu last week.</p>
        <p>That's not only an ozone-friendly flip-flop; it should also have profitable U.S. economic consequences. Nations like China and India, as they abandon chlorofluorocarbons, will need the substitutes - for instance, in China's home refrigeration program. Those countries alone have 40 percent of the world's population, and thus can offer a substantial market to U.S. manufacturers of chlorofluorocarbon substitutes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush still is virtually isolated in the world in his reluctance to do anything about global warming. Standing alone, of course, is not necessarily a reason to change; nor is Mr. Sununu wrong that there is scientific uncertainty about the climatic consequences of the steady increase in carbon dioxide in the atmosphere - an increase that is not in doubt.</p>
        <p>The White House has insisted on awaiting an exhaustive study by more than 300 experts on the climate brought together by the United Nations. Last month, however, an ''executive summary'' of the U.N. survey was published in London - and it largely discredited the Sununu-Bush do-nothing policy.</p>
        <p>With only a few dissenters, the panel concluded that if worldwide ''business as usual'' continues, the earth's global mean temperature could increase by 5.4 degrees Fahrenheit by the end of the next century. That would produce a global mean sea-level rise of 25 to 26 inches, with significant regional variations.</p>
        <p>That's still an informed prediction, not an absolute certainty, since mathematical models of the atmosphere can vary; but it was the most authoritative conclusion yet reached by a credible scientific body. It was good enough, moreover, for Prime Minister Thatcher, who promptly announced her decision to reduce the projected growth of Britain's carbon dioxide emissions, stabilizing them at 1990 levels by the year 2005.</p>
        <p>But just cutting the rise in emissions is too little, too late. The United Nations report called for a 60 percent immediate reduction in current greenhouse gas emissions, just to stabilize concentrations of those gases already in the atmosphere. Britain, moreover, emits only about 3 percent of carbon dioxide worldwide; the United States is responsible for about 25 percent.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, in an evenhanded article in next month's Scientific American, Robert M. White, a former chief of the U.S. Weather Bureau, suggests a rational list of high-priority, common-sense actions demanded by what is already known about global warming.</p>
        <p>Mr. White, now president of the National Academy of Engineering, concedes the ambiguities of atmospheric models and projections and the seriousness of some scientific reservations. He concludes, nevertheless, that ''a wise course'' would be ''one that recognized uncertainty but would not permit that uncertainty to forestall action.''</p>
        <p>He would begin with steps that also make sense ''for other economic and environmental reasons'' - first priority going to energy conservation and efficiency. A shift from coal and oil to natural gas would substantially reduce carbon dioxide emissions; a more drastic move to non-fossil energy sources would be of even greater benefit. Reforestation and forest preservation would help absorb greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Even such beginning steps will not be easily taken. Mr. White doubts that any policy course can do more than ''retard'' climate warming. And if even that much is to be accomplished, George Bush - or maybe only John Sununu - needs to do another flip-flop, soon.</p>
        <p>IN THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
