<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Technology;   The 'Concept Car' Pushes Change</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="364897"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARRAR, GEORGE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D9103BF932A35754C0A966958260" item-length="996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Technology;   The 'Concept Car' Pushes Change</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE HARRAR; George Harrar, a writer specializing in technology, is co-author of ''The Ultimate Entrepreneur.''</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HARRAR, GEORGE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: This month, the Ford Motor Company will introduce the 1991 Capri, a sporty new car to be built in Australia around a Japanese Mazda drive train. It will be aimed at the market made popular by Mazda's Miata. But unlike the Miata, which was conceived quietly at the company's design studios in California, the Capri began life in 1982 in full view as a ''concept car.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: This month, the Ford Motor Company will introduce the 1991 Capri, a sporty new car to be built in Australia around a Japanese Mazda drive train. It will be aimed at the market made popular by Mazda's Miata. But unlike the Miata, which was conceived quietly at the company's design studios in California, the Capri began life in 1982 in full view as a ''concept car.</p>
        <p>This month, the Ford Motor Company will introduce the 1991 Capri, a sporty new car to be built in Australia around a Japanese Mazda drive train. It will be aimed at the market made popular by Mazda's Miata. But unlike the Miata, which was conceived quietly at the company's design studios in California, the Capri began life in 1982 in full view as a ''concept car.'' Originally called the Barcetta, the Capri was desgined in Italy at Ford's Ghia studio around a Ford Fiesta drive train. The Barcetta was shown at auto shows around the world and reviewed by trade publications before the decision was ever made to manufacture it.</p>
        <p>Concept cars are futuristic design and engineering exercises that automakers around the world undertake to test and to show off new ideas. The flashiest make the covers of Motor Trend and Car and Driver, magazines aimed at automobile enthusiasts. On the auto show circuit, concept cars lend excitement to the more down-to-earth models on the platform next door, the ones actually available for purchase.</p>
        <p>A traditional goal of building concept cars, said Neil Walling, the Chrysler Corporation's director of advanced and international design, has been ''in barest terms, free advertising.'' But increasingly, automakers view concept cars as important ways of testing new technologies and styling concepts. For designers, said Jerry Hirshberg, head of Nissan Design International Inc. in Los Angeles, concept cars ''are a real good vehicle for demolishing preconceptions.''</p>
        <p>Numbers are difficult to come by because not all concept cars are completed or shown to the public. But the industry consensus is that car makers are building more of them - and more are also making it into production.</p>
        <p>''There is always an internal debate whether to show a car,'' said Don Runkle, vice president of the advanced engineering staff at the General Motors Corporation. ''Some say we shouldn't show anything except what is for sale.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, one major company - Honda - follows that strict policy of secrecy regarding experimental designs. Two years ago, G.M. adopted the policy that all concept cars shown to the public must be drivable, even if only in the most limited sense of a few miles per hour on a closed track.</p>
        <p>At Ford, engineers present 40 to 50 car ideas a year to top management, including about 10 highly speculative models. The public usually sees just five of them. According to Tom Scott, director of international design, Ford might spend $200,000 on a fiberglass body and up to $4 million for a fully engineered car. He sees these design exercises as a way to educate and condition top management to new ideas.</p>
        <p>Jim Wangers, president of Automotive Marketing Consultants, a firm that tests automobile performance, sees an additional purpose for building concept cars, particularly for a company like Chrysler, which faces ongoing questions about its financial future and management stability. ''A concept car,'' he said, ''is a way of confirming to the public that, by God, this company is involved in some high-tech advanced planning.''</p>
        <p>In 1992, Chrysler plans to begin limited production of the Viper R/T-10, a concept car to be priced in the upper $40,000 range. It will be built around an innovative 10-cylinder engine design on a low-slung sports-car body.</p>
        <p>In sheer numbers, G.M. beat the competition this year by rolling out 10 concept cars. Most spectacular is the CERV (corporate experimental research vehicle) III, the latest test machine to build on the Corvette's design. With 650 horsepower and a top speed of 225 m.p.h., the Cerv III is actually too powerful to ever reach dealer showrooms. But it does tackle a basic engineering question that may one day be incorporated into G.M.'s production models - how to marry sports-car performance with everyday drivability.</p>
        <p>The key word here is ''active.'' Active rear steering, which automatically makes adjustments for wind gusts. An active suspension system, which compensates for dips in the road. An active pedal pusher, which will push back on the brake to let the driver know that when the car is close to spinning its wheels.</p>
        <p>''We are learning,'' said Don Runkle, vice president of G.M.'s advanced engineering staff, ''how to integrate the many active control systems that are bound to end up in the vehicles of the 1990's.''</p>
        <p>Each concept car G.M. builds costs from $300,000 to $5 million, depending on whether the model is primarily a design shell or a full-fledged test of sophisticated engineering ideas. For the 10 cars introduced this year, G.M.'s total investment may reach $27 million - a sizable amount, but only a fraction of the $5.24 billion G.M. spends annually on research and development.</p>
        <p>Some show cars, or at least concepts, reappear periodically, testing and refining the same basic concepts, yet never make it to production. This is the case with G.M.'s family of electric vehicles.</p>
        <p>In 1964, responding to concerns about air quality, the company brought forth the Electrovair I, a battery-powered Chevrolet Corvair. G.M. followed up with the Electrovair II, which could run 40 to 80 miles before recharging, and the Electrovan for the truck market. By the end of the decade, Motor Trend magazine was asking on its cover, ''1969 - Year of the Electrics?''</p>
        <p>Entering 1990, the threat of global warming and a polluted environment sparked G.M. chairman Roger B. Smith to introduce in January, with much fanfare, something called the Impact.</p>
        <p>The Impact, the latest in a long line of electric concept cars, accelerates from 0 to 60 miles per hour in eight seconds and can reach 75 m.p.h. Yet as Mr. Runkle acknowledged, ''There still are significant issues related to batteries that need to be resolved. In 10 years, you could see some on the road.'' Then again, you may not. As Mr. Walling of Chrysler put it, the designers and engineers who build concept cars, testing their ideas, ''don't pay a great deal of attention to manufacturability.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
