<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Day To Save the Earth</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="345890"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="CONNECTICUT OPINION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH DAY</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDB103BF931A15757C0A966958260" item-length="669" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Day To Save the Earth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jacqueline Heneage; Jacqueline Heneage, First Selectman of Westport from 1973 to 1981, is project manager of the Housatonic Resources Recovery Authority in Brookfield.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: I WAS a 1970 Earth Day participant. But 20 years later, I feel that in many ways the earth movement has gone astray, and I am appalled at what the environmental activists are doing to many attempts to solve environmental problems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: I WAS a 1970 Earth Day participant. But 20 years later, I feel that in many ways the earth movement has gone astray, and I am appalled at what the environmental activists are doing to many attempts to solve environmental problems.</p>
        <p>I WAS a 1970 Earth Day participant. But 20 years later, I feel that in many ways the earth movement has gone astray, and I am appalled at what the environmental activists are doing to many attempts to solve environmental problems.</p>
        <p>Have I changed? Perhaps. But I think what is now impeding safe solutions to numerous environmental problems is the way many environmentalists have hardened their positions and refuse to accept that conditions, processes, technology and scientific evidence have changed.</p>
        <p>Since the original Earth Day, environmentalists deserve great credit for demanding that attention be paid. But now, when they continue to cause public agitation based on obsolete data and deny that technological changes have responded to their concerns, they damage efforts to provide responsible solutions to the problems they dentified.</p>
        <p>For example, the American Medical Association maintains that there is no convincing scientific evidence that dioxin poses a direct threat to human health. Several years ago, Barry Commoner, as a reputable scientist, called attention to dioxin and spoke against the disposal of solid waste by incineration, because dioxins spurted out the chimneys.</p>
        <p>Has he ever changed his position or played a leadership role in dispelling public fear, now that all the evidence shows that dioxin is a red herring when it comes to public health and that the modern waste-to-energy plant is so technically advanced that what comes out the chimney is generally cleaner than the air we normally breathe? If he has, he is still quoted by the environmental scaremongers who make sure the public remains misinformed.</p>
        <p>Consider Neil Seldman of the Institute for Local Self-Reliance. He employs a very well-organized and well-financed effort to discredit waste-to-energy plants, playing on people's fears for their health and their property values by using outdated pictures of obsolete incinerator plants belching smoke - and, of course, dioxins. He does this to promote his organization's position that all waste can be recycled, while refusing to recognize that the modern waste-to-energy plant is the best recycler of all. It can convert 76 percent of otherwise nonrecyclable waste into valuable steam or electricity, and another 3 percent to ferrous metal recovery. In addition, such plants extend the life of our remaining fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>While recycling appeals to many people and should be promoted, it is not the entire answer to waste disposal. Every responsible person recognizes that not everything can be recycled, nor will everyone fully participate in recycling. Being an ardent recycler should not mean that all other methods of waste disposal should be actively fought as unworthy or dangerous. Only zealots refuse to accept that other methods of waste disposal must go hand in hand with recycling, so that we can solve the entire solid-waste management problem. That is why we need some waste-to-energy plants. That is why we need some landfills.</p>
        <p>Why are their actions important, and why is their inability to change positions damaging? Because they can so easily destroy solutions to environmental problems by raising fears and taking advantage of our general ignorance of health risks.</p>
        <p>Most of us don't really understand or know how to weigh health risks. When where we are exposed to verified health risks, like alcohol and tobacco, we tend to discount them. Where the health risk is unknown and the exposure unclear, we tend to make a far greater fuss. Just use the word dioxin, and antennas shoot up. When people playing on others' fears and ignorance, many attempts at solving environmental problems become fiascos overnight.</p>
        <p>The fight over waste-to-energy plants is but one example of the failure to alter positions when industry has responded to concerns or where scientific evidence cannot support the claims. This failure shows how dogmatic environmentalists can be, and it hampers many attempts to use alternative techniques to address environmental headaches.</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT OPINION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
