<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Forces Seen as Backbone of New Bush Energy Policy</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="396090"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="THE STRUGGLE IN CONGRESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENERGY DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DB163DF93BA15753C1A966958260" item-length="1032" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Forces Seen as Backbone of New Bush Energy Policy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr., Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush Administration's long-awaited national energy strategy will include incentives for efficiency and for renewable fuels and other fresh Government iniatives, but it will continue the Reagan Administration's fundamental reliance on market forces, Energy Department and industry officials say.</p>
        <p>Planning for the strategy, begun at a time of what Energy Secretary James D. Watkins calls energy complacency, is heading toward completion with American troops in the Persian Gulf protecting Mideast oil fields. An interim report was published in April and some options were added in the aftermath of the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bush Administration's long-awaited national energy strategy will include incentives for efficiency and for renewable fuels and other fresh Government iniatives, but it will continue the Reagan Administration's fundamental reliance on market forces, Energy Department and industry officials say.</p>
        <p>Planning for the strategy, begun at a time of what Energy Secretary James D. Watkins calls energy complacency, is heading toward completion with American troops in the Persian Gulf protecting Mideast oil fields. An interim report was published in April and some options were added in the aftermath of the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait.</p>
        <p>The planning is far more comprehensive than the 1987 study on energy security that found, essentially, that low oil prices were helping to make the United States overly dependent on foreign oil.</p>
        <p>Linda G. Stuntz, the chief overseer of the project that is to put 65 or more options on President Bush's desk in early December, said last week that the free market, while essential, "was not in and of itself sufficient" to produce effective energy policy. Change in Tone of Report</p>
        <p>"It's not sufficient when you have Congress putting large tracts of the outer continental shelf off limits, when you have concerns about gas emissions that may substantially affect your ability to use fossil fuels," said Ms. Stuntz, the department's deputy under secretary for policy, planning and analysis.</p>
        <p>Initially, the strategy was to consist of recommendations, not just options for Presidential consideration. But that approach underestimated the politics of an elaborate process involving many agencies, including the Environmental Protection Agency and the Departments of Transportation, Interior and Housing and Urban Development. Most importantly, the White House chief of staff, John H. Sununu, is said to have insisted that the final shaping of policy be left to the President.</p>
        <p>Ms. Stuntz said that Mr. Bush, as a founder of an oil company, is capable of making the policy selection himself if provided the necessary information.</p>
        <p>While Bush policy makers insist that near-exclusive reliance on the market was overdone in the 1980's, they are not inclined to subsidize, mandate or otherwise promote energy sources and technologies that are uneconomic.</p>
        <p>As an example of one kind of initiative that is regarded favorably, Ms. Stuntz cited a proposal that would not only impose a tax on cars with very poor gasoline mileage, as at present, but would also encourage consumers, through rebates, to buy cars that get exceptionally good mileage.  Incentives for Consumers</p>
        <p>She said automobile companies were ordered, under penalty of fines, to produce fuel-efficient cars but "we don't really give consumers an incentive" to buy them.</p>
        <p>The report delves in detail into such questions as how big a rebate would be required to produce a certain volume of vehicle sales and what the effect would be on domestic and foreign automobile companies and jobs.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Scott Sklar, executive director of the Solar Energy Industries Association, said department analysts were willing to make allowances for the heavy capital investment required for renewable sources of energy like solar systems.</p>
        <p>"That's a major step forward," Mr. Sklar said. "Bush really does believe that all the options belong at the table."</p>
        <p>Pains have been taken to build the strategy from the ground up, with 18 public hearings, 448 witnesses and 22,000 pages of written submissions. But preliminary reaction from trade associations and others who have been able to review some of the proposals ranges from hope to outright disapproval.</p>
        <p>"There isn't any kind of guiding principle stated there," said Richard L. Lawson, a former Air Force general who heads of the National Coal Association, after seeing a substantial amount of the work. "There has to be something to provide rigor" to the exercise, he said, adding, "Until I have a statement of the problem, I don't know what to do with it."  Effort Called Balanced</p>
        <p>But Nicholas Bush of the Natural Gas Supply Association, an industry group, called the effort "extremely balanced" and said there is a reasonable chance for it to provide a solid "framework for doing something."</p>
        <p>The options quickly put forward as a result of the Iraqi invasion included simple measures like buying lower-octane gasoline and inflating tires to specification for better mileage as well as proposals to add tax credits for oil exploration and to expedite permits for natural gas pipeline projects.</p>
        <p>Indeed, much of the emphasis in the emerging strategy is on curbing demand and enhancing supply rather than injecting a fresh government presence.</p>
        <p>"I think what you can expect is a new effort to look at existing barriers that are blocking effective market operation," Ms. Stuntz said. "We're not done deregulating the energy business by a long shot. Nobody who's ever tried to build a facility or spent any time at the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission needs to be convinced of that." The commission has authority over various aspects of natural gas and over electricity at the wholesale level. Bigger Threat to Security</p>
        <p>The Iraqi invasion also complicated national security by making oil prices far more volatile than they have been historically. In recent weeks, the price of crude oil rose steeply, then plummeted, then rose again.</p>
        <p>Reducing the United States vulnerability to a volatile oil market, Secretary Watkins told a recent conference in London, "can most likely be achieved" through a combination of efficient oil production and consumption, by "greater fuel-switching, especially to plentiful and more geographically dispersed natural gas, and dedicated efforts to develop alternative transportation fuels."</p>
        <p>Ms. Stuntz says she remains optimistic that a coherent program can be adopted. Critics would be offered a trade of some hydropower initiative or access to the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge for, say, curbing electricity demand or more money for research into fuel alternative.</p>
        <p>"There is a core of people who appreciate that approach," she said. "They're willing to deal on that basis."</p>
        <p>THE STRUGGLE IN CONGRESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
