<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE HEAT IS ON</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="331493"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KANIGEL, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISHER, DAVID E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEINER, JONATHAN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FIRE &amp; ICE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEXT HUNDRED YEARS, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DB173BF937A35750C0A966958260" item-length="1207" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE HEAT IS ON</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">ROBERT KANIGEL; Robert Kanigel, the author of ''Apprentice to Genius: The Making of a Scientific Dynasty,'' is working on a biography of the Indian mathematical prodigy Srinivasa Ramanujan.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KANIGEL, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>FIRE &amp; ICE</p>
        <p>The Greenhouse Effect,</p>
        <p>Ozone Depletion, and Nuclear Winter.</p>
        <p>By David E. Fisher.</p>
        <p>232 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Harper &amp; Row. $19.95.</p>
        <p>THE NEXT ONE HUNDRED YEARS</p>
        <p>Shaping the Fate of Our Living Earth.</p>
        <p>By Jonathan Weiner.</p>
        <p>312 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Bantam Books. $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>FIRE &amp; ICE</p>
        <p>The Greenhouse Effect,</p>
        <p>Ozone Depletion, and Nuclear Winter.</p>
        <p>By David E. Fisher.</p>
        <p>232 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Harper &amp; Row. $19.95.</p>
        <p>THE NEXT ONE HUNDRED YEARS</p>
        <p>Shaping the Fate of Our Living Earth.</p>
        <p>By Jonathan Weiner.</p>
        <p>312 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Bantam Books. $19.95.</p>
        <p>FIRE &amp; ICE</p>
        <p>The Greenhouse Effect,</p>
        <p>Ozone Depletion, and Nuclear Winter.</p>
        <p>By David E. Fisher.</p>
        <p>232 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Harper &amp; Row. $19.95.</p>
        <p>THE NEXT ONE HUNDRED YEARS</p>
        <p>Shaping the Fate of Our Living Earth.</p>
        <p>By Jonathan Weiner.</p>
        <p>312 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Bantam Books. $19.95.</p>
        <p>In 1981, a team of British researchers at a frigid, wind-swept base in the Antarctic noticed a drop in stratospheric concentrations of ozone, a variant of ordinary oxygen that helps shield our planet from harmful ultraviolet rays. This was no slight, subtle falloff but a plunge. Couldn't be, the British at first thought. Maybe their instruments were off. After all, their findings flatly contradicted those reported by an American Nimbus satellite in orbit since 1978.</p>
        <p>The British, it turned out, were right, Nimbus wrong. By 1984, the concentration of ozone had dropped by 30 percent. There was an enormous, steadily growing ozone hole at the South Pole.</p>
        <p>Since the Nimbus scientists were looking for only a small slip in the standard ozone readings, they had programmed their computers to disregard as spurious departures from the norm of more than a few percent. In effect, they blinded themselves to the ozone hole, leaving to the British, down on the ground, the dubious pleasure of discovering it.</p>
        <p>This story can be read as a lesson in scientific fallibility: when it comes to the complex scientific issues besetting the planet, you'd best believe no one. Yet within the large context offered by David E. Fisher in ''Fire &amp; Ice'' and Jonathan Weiner in ''The Next One Hundred Years,'' the story can be seen to argue for quite a different conclusion. If, as both authors abundantly show, planetary science is so tricky, so excruciatingly dependent on the assumptions made in fashioning computer models, so riven with controversy, what does it mean when the scientific community does reach something like consensus?</p>
        <p>Such consensus, Mr. Fisher and Mr. Weiner assure us, exists: the greenhouse effect is real. The globe is warming. Humanity's hold upon the planet is threatened.</p>
        <p>In the greenhouse effect, methane, water vapor and particularly carbon dioxide collect in the atmosphere, forming a layer of insulation around the earth. If that layer thickens on account of the burning of fossil fuels and other factors, the earth holds on to more of the sun's heat. Result? A global warming.</p>
        <p>How much warming can we expect? Here consensus breaks down. With decisive political action and good luck, the temperature rise may be limited to, say, three degrees Fahrenheit - triple that of the heat waves of the 1980's - bringing with it mild climatic changes to which we could adjust without too much bother. But it's just as likely, many scientists feel, that there will be a rise of 10, 15 or 20 degrees - enough to melt the polar ice caps, raise sea levels, inundate low-lying lands from Bangladesh to New York, appreciably alter climate and cause economic and political chaos as the hungry and thirsty billions struggle to survive the disruption.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weiner and Mr. Fisher cover remarkably similar ground in their books. Both tell us how the greenhouse effect comes about; how it was first revealed through one scientist's methodical tracking of carbon dioxide levels; how clearing the Amazon rain forests contributes to it; why it is so difficult to predict accurately how much warming there will be, when it will begin and how fast it will happen; and how chlorofluorocarbons - like spray-can propellants and the Freon used in air conditioners - chew up the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fisher, a professor at the University of Miami and the author of ''Race on the Edge of Time'' and ''The Birth of the Earth,'' widens his focus enough to include the worldwide nuclear winter, which would likely follow any large-scale exchange of nuclear warheads. In this scenario, soot and smoke from a hundred ravaged cities would form an atmospheric blanket over the earth, chilling it and possibly extinguishing much of its life.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weiner, the author of ''Planet Earth,'' is the more leisurely of the two authors, more confident he's got your attention, more overtly literary. Some of his metaphors are unforgettable. As a way of showing that the stratosphere, unlike the lower atmosphere, doesn't easily rid itself of pollutants, he writes, ''It is like an eye without tears.''</p>
        <p>To illustrate how the greenhouse effect implies not just a warming of the atmosphere but a chilling higher up, he explains that if you wear a flimsy shirt in a snowstorm, snowflakes landing on it melt. But if you wear several heavy sweaters, snowflakes alighting on the outermost one, now insulated from the heat of your body, stay frozen. ''Earth,'' writes Mr. Weiner, ''is swinging through the chill of outer space, and the atmosphere is its only clothing. Adding greenhouse gases to the air is like pulling on more and more layers of wool.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fisher's talent is noisier, but no less effective in capturing the reader. Conversational, gently rambling, he is not above taking off on a startling digression to flesh out an idea. ''Living in this world,'' he writes, ''is something like watching an Alfred Hitchcock film: just when you think you've got the ending figured out, he - and nature - hit you with another shock. Remember Psycho?'' But ''in this case, the knife-wielding nut turns out to be a bacterium hiding from the air,'' which dwells in some termites, feasts on felled trees from the Amazon rain forest and churns out methane, a greenhouse gas.</p>
        <p>At another point, Mr. Fisher, borrowing a metaphor from the physicist Richard Feynman, compares the difficulty of understanding the planet to discovering the rules of chess by observing moves made in some small corner of the board.</p>
        <p>Mercifully, neither author succumbs to despair in writing about such a bleak subject. Both believe that humans can act sensibly and creatively to forestall their doom. Amsterdam, after all, lives under water, the North Sea held back by dikes. The oil shock of the early 1970's galvanized America into producing, and buying, fuel-efficient cars that have slowed the buildup of carbon dioxide. And in 1988, most nations of the world agreed to cut the use of ozone-eating chlorofluorocarbons by half within the next decade. The authors believe that similar actions, accelerated by the urgency of the crisis, could moderate the warming to come, and they offer their own laundry list of environmental prescriptions.</p>
        <p>Little of this is new; we have been living with global warming, the ozone hole and the prospect of a nuclear winter for some time now. They have become part of our public vocabulary. Indeed, that is just the problem both writers confront: their readers have been subject to so much in the way of journalistic pyrotechnics surrounding these issues, to such a tide of seemingly contradictory headlines, that no one knows what to believe anymore. Both authors struggle against the numbing effect of such confusion.</p>
        <p>And both succeed, with passion and credibility. You cannot read either of them and conclude anything but that, if the nations of the world fail to act, or fail to act soon enough, it will be not just our distant progeny who take the heat but our own children.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
