<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suspect in Record Highs: New Gauge</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="389980"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THERMOMETERS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">TUCSON (ARIZ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALBANY (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL WEATHER SERVICE</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona/Tucson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Albany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DB1738F93AA35753C1A966958260" item-length="865" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suspect in Record Highs: New Gauge</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: All sorts of explanations have been offered for record high temperatures across the country - the greenhouse effect, the growth of cities, even chance. But the National Weather Service is examining an additional theory: the thermometers were wrong.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: All sorts of explanations have been offered for record high temperatures across the country - the greenhouse effect, the growth of cities, even chance. But the National Weather Service is examining an additional theory: the thermometers were wrong.</p>
        <p>All sorts of explanations have been offered for record high temperatures across the country - the greenhouse effect, the growth of cities, even chance. But the National Weather Service is examining an additional theory: the thermometers were wrong.</p>
        <p>Over the three years that a new type of thermometer has been in use in Tucson, Ariz., it has on 15 occasions registered temperatures above the city's previous high of 111 degrees, and this summer it registered a record of 117 degrees. In Albany, where the Weather Service uses the same type of thermometer, independent forecasters say it often records temperatures 3 degrees higher than other gauges.</p>
        <p>The thermometer at issue is an electronic sensor, called the HO83, that the Weather Service is counting on to replace the traditional mercury and glass thermometers in 1,000 observing sites around the country. The $5,000 electronic gauge records instantaneous changes in temperatures and keeps track of its own observations, unlike a mercury thermometer, which needs an attendant to take hourly readings.</p>
        <p>A Design Flaw, Critics Say</p>
        <p>But critics say that although the new electronic thermometer is more convenient, it has a wide margin of error. Albany and Tucson are the only cities where independent forecasters have complained to the Weather Service, but the critics say the problem may be more widespread.</p>
        <p>What may be causing the exaggerated readings, these critics contend, is that the fan in the HO83 is not strong enough and that the thermometer is absorbing too much solar radiation. The combination means that the air the thermometer is measuring has been artificially heated.</p>
        <p>Enough questions have been raised about the HO83 that the Weather Service is conducting a study of the thermometer at its testing center in Sterling, Va.</p>
        <p>''It is well known if it doesn't have good aspiration, it doesn't read right,'' said Norm Hoffman, the Weather Service's manager for Northern California.</p>
        <p>Dr. Elbert W. Friday Jr., the director of National Weather Service, said a comprehensive study of the thermometer in Albany found no bias, while early evidence suggests that there could be some error in Tucson. He added, ''I haven't seen any evidence that there is a design flaw yet, but we're keeping an open mind. We are certainly doing an investigation, but it is not a big deal.''</p>
        <p>Thomas R. Karl, chief of global climate lab at the National Climatic Data Center in Asheville, N.C., who conducted preliminary studies of the new thermometers in Tucson and Albany, said he is concerned that the margin of error in the HO83 is so wide that scientists will not be able to determine whether the earth is getting warmer.</p>
        <p>''From a climatological standpoint the data is not measured at an appropriate level,'' Mr. Karl said. For aviation and general weather forecasts, the thermometer is adequate, he said.</p>
        <p>Temperature Taking Is Not Easy</p>
        <p>Taking a city's temperature is not as easy as it used to be. As new technologies take hold within the Weather Service and the growth of cities changes the conditions around traditional observation sites, meteorologists have had to experiment with methods that would insure the continuity of their temperature readings.</p>
        <p>Adding to the difficulties is the new thermometer. Weather Service officials are instructed to compare readings from the electronic thermometer against a mercury thermometer once a week to eliminate any errors.</p>
        <p>But while the adjustments are made each week, the electronic thermometer is only considered to be broken and sent for repairs when it differs by 2 degrees from the other thermometer. By comparison, a mercury thermometer, which tends to fluctuate less, typically has an error range of three-tenths of a degree.</p>
        <p>''Any time you decrease the error range you get an increase in cost,'' Dr. Friday said.</p>
        <p>As for the validity of records measured with a thermometer with that error range, Dr. Friday said, ''if there is a record of 3 degrees, you can count on it. If a record is set by half a degree or 1 degree, than it might be a little fuzzy.'' He said the observations of 8,000 volunteers, most of whom use mercury thermometers, should be used for detailed studies of the climate.</p>
        <p>The Weather Service owns about 250 of the devices. The agency is planning to buy at least 750 more units, made by the Technical Services Laboratory of Fort Walton Beach, Fla., as part of its modernization program in the next few years, said Gerald F. O'Brien, the Weather Service's chief of surface operations.</p>
        <p>Robert Gall, a meteorology professor at the University of Arizona in Tucson, prepared the documentation that led to the Weather Service studies.</p>
        <p>He compared the temperature readings from the Tucson office - before and after the new thermometer - to a nearby observation site. The comparison showed that the new thermometer inflated readings in a consistent pattern throughout the day. Early in the morning there was hardly any error, he said, while in the heat of the day the error rose to about 3 degrees.</p>
        <p>Tom Adler, the Weather Service official who conducted the tests at Tucson, said that maybe too much was being expected from Weather Service thermometers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
