<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When a Shipment of Plants Arrives</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="343769"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="GARDENING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FAUST, JOAN LEE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED81631F936A25757C0A966958260" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When a Shipment of Plants Arrives</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FAUST, JOAN LEE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: NURSERY orders that were mailed a few months back are now being filled. Cartons packed with live plants are arriving apace. The thing to do, of course, is open the cartons and plant the plants immediately? Right? Wrong. Opening the cartons as soon as possible is essential. The plants have been smothered for many days, and upon arrival, they will need to receive some air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: NURSERY orders that were mailed a few months back are now being filled. Cartons packed with live plants are arriving apace. The thing to do, of course, is open the cartons and plant the plants immediately? Right? Wrong. Opening the cartons as soon as possible is essential. The plants have been smothered for many days, and upon arrival, they will need to receive some air.</p>
        <p>NURSERY orders that were mailed a few months back are now being filled. Cartons packed with live plants are arriving apace. The thing to do, of course, is open the cartons and plant the plants immediately? Right? Wrong. Opening the cartons as soon as possible is essential. The plants have been smothered for many days, and upon arrival, they will need to receive some air. This deed is important, but planting immediately is not. It may even be a bit hasty.</p>
        <p>After opening the carton, check to see that the plants are upright. If they are not, put them upright, in their carton, but keep the carton in a cool, not sunny place.</p>
        <p>When the carton is opened, shake off the plastic peanuts from the plants or pick them out of the collar of foliage. They are extremely lightweight and easy to pick off. Although this packing material is made of plastic, many mail-order houses are now using peanuts made from environmentally sound plastic. The original peanuts were made with CFC's, the chlorofluorocarbons that ascend into the atmosphere and affect the earth's ozone layer.</p>
        <p>These peanuts can be saved and used for future packing needs. Some gardeners like to cut them into smaller pieces and use them as the bottom drainage layers for containers like tubs, planters and large pots. But since they never do biodegrade, these peanuts are there permanently. Be warned that they will turn up in potting mixtures, if the containers are dumped out and the potting mixture is reused.</p>
        <p>Next, check over the plants. Nurseries are learning to pack their plants extremely well. Some are shipped in pots, in a lightweight mixture with their collar of foliage safely encased in plastic wrap. Usually a piece of plastic is placed over the top of the potting mixture and secured with rubber bands.</p>
        <p>Remove this piece of protective plastic and feel if the potting mixture is moist. If it is not, then the plants should be watered. If the mixture is damp, leave it alone. It is probably well soaked through, and the roots do not need any more water for the moment.</p>
        <p>The mail-order nursery shipment will also include dormant plants wrapped tightly in squares of thin plastic. The plants are protected either in damp sphagnum moss or wood shavings. It is always a challenge for a gardener to find where the plastic wrap begins, where to start the unraveling. A red string tucked in by the nurseries that indicates ''Start here'' would help.</p>
        <p>These dormant, wrapped plants are the ones to be most concerned about when a shipment of plants arrives. The plants should be unwrapped as promptly as possible. If their packing material is damp, as it usually is, the roots should also be moist and in good condition. Quite often, the plants will not have tops - that is, they will be dormant, , and new growth will not occur until the plants are set in the ground and their roots settle in.</p>
        <p>To be sure that these plants survive, pot them up as promptly as possible. Have handy a few clean pots and a general potting mixture, even one used for starting seed is fine. This potting will give the plants time to recover from the shipment, establish themselves and maybe even start to grow.</p>
        <p>This shipment of plants needs to be set in a cool place, either in a garage or under the shelter of trees, for at least a few days. This outdoor time will give the plants time to recover from shipment before their next shock - planting.</p>
        <p>If a large order of woody plants - trees and shrubs - arrives, the best thing for these plants is either the potting, as described, or heeling them in a reserve area.</p>
        <p>This is done by digging a V-shaped trench with a spade or garden fork and placing the root area of the woody plants in it. Then shove the soil back in place, and the roots will be protected from drying out. The plants will be secure in this location for several days - or weeks - until they can be planted.</p>
        <p>Sometimes a shipment of plants arrives in rainy, cool weather, and it is impossible to get them into the ground. These measures will at least assure that the shipment will not be lost, and the plants will have a good chance for survival.</p>
        <p>Plants that arrive in pots can be put into the ground when holes are ready for them. Plants that arrive dormant can stay in their pots for a few days and be planted, when you are ready.</p>
        <p>One of the most important tasks about planting is to be sure that the new plants are watered in well.</p>
        <p>One nursery even goes so far as to use the term ''muddy the plants in.'' Soak the ground to be sure that the root area is wetted through, and the plants are well on their way to becoming established.</p>
        <p>GARDENING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
