<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Lone Cause Found to Account For Decline of Frog, Experts Say</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="328533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FROGS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AMPHIBIANS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLAKESLEE, SANDRA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amphibians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDA1131F932A15751C0A966958260" item-length="405" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Lone Cause Found to Account For Decline of Frog, Experts Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANDRA BLAKESLEE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BLAKESLEE, SANDRA</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Feb. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: There is convincing evidence that some species of frogs, toads and salamanders are rapidly declining in many parts of the world, a panel of experts concluded today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: There is convincing evidence that some species of frogs, toads and salamanders are rapidly declining in many parts of the world, a panel of experts concluded today.</p>
        <p>There is convincing evidence that some species of frogs, toads and salamanders are rapidly declining in many parts of the world, a panel of experts concluded today.</p>
        <p>But there is no evidence that the declines are caused by a single factor like acid rain or increased ultraviolet light, they said. Rather, the major cause for the disappearance of amphibians is widespread destruction of areas where animals live by human beings, they said.</p>
        <p>The panel of 22 experts was convened by the National Research Council, a nonprofit organization that advises the government on scientific matters. The biology board of the council, which is associated with the National Academy of Sciences, called on the experts to assess the question of declining amphibian populations in the wake of numerous anecdotal reports that frogs are disappearing.</p>
        <p>''There was a sense of emergency among many of the people at the meeting,'' said Dr. David Bradford who teaches environmental studies at the University of California at Los Angeles and is a member of the panel. ''Some of the species seem to be crashing right in front of us.''</p>
        <p>Ideal for Environment Study</p>
        <p>The panelists agreed that amphibians are ideal for studying the effects of water, air and soil pollution, since the animals spend their lives sampling all aspects of the environment. They also called for short-term studies to assess the problem before convening a larger meeting of scientists from around the world concerned with amphibians.</p>
        <p>The group drafted an emergency letter to the world's scientists, said Dr. Bradford, ''calling their attention to the immediacy of this problem.''</p>
        <p>The consensus of the meeting was that many amphibian species in the mountains of western North America are in decline, even in nature preserves where there is no apparent intrusion by human beings, the panelists said. Other regions, including the Northeastern United States, Canada and eastern Australia, have experienced the decline of several species in many sites but current data are fragmentary.</p>
        <p>Other regions, like the Southeastern United States, show little evidence of a general decline in amphibians, apart from what is clearly attributable to habitat destruction, the panel members concluded.</p>
        <p>In some places, they said, species are both declining and thriving. They hypothesized that some animals may be more sensitive than others to pollution or to subtle changes in habitat.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
