<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Study Says Apartheid Hurts the Environment</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="352911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (NON-US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH AFRICA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">WORLD WATCH INSTITUTE</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDB1F38F930A25756C0A966958260" item-length="402" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Study Says Apartheid Hurts the Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Apartheid has had a disastrous effect on South Africa's environment, an American report says.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Apartheid has had a disastrous effect on South Africa's environment, an American report says.</p>
        <p>Apartheid has had a disastrous effect on South Africa's environment, an American report says.</p>
        <p>The report, issued on Friday by the World Watch Institute, a Washington-based research group, says the policy of racial separation has worsened pollution by concentrating people in confined areas and by depressing wages. This has led to artificially cheap coal that ravages the land when it is mined and fouls the air where it is burned.</p>
        <p>The resettlement of blacks and extensive mining have resulted in the poisoning of much of the countryside, said the report, titled ''Apartheid's Environmental Toll.''</p>
        <p>The South African Embassy said it had no comment.</p>
        <p>''To finance the military superstructure that upholds minority rule, broad areas have been deeply scarred by reckless mining,'' the report said. ''Meanwhile, air pollution over the nation's coal region ranks with the worst in the world, partly because of an energy strategy that aims at minimizing dependence on anti-apartheid oil exporters.''</p>
        <p>The author of the study, Alan B. Durning, a senior researcher at WorldWatch, said half the black population has been forced to move to the 13 percent of the country the Government has designated as tribal homelands. Mr. Durning said the overcrowded lands have been stripped of their topsoil by overgrazing and farming, and that forests there are rapidly dwindling as trees are felled for fuel.</p>
        <p>Mines Are Not Controlled</p>
        <p>The Government, mindful of its reliance on mineral income, exempts the mining industry from environmental standards, Mr. Durning said.</p>
        <p>Coal-fired electrical plants lacking sulfur-removing scrubbers emit dark plumes of smoke across the coal-producing region, causing acid rain that threatens crops and the remaining forests in the northern states, the report said.</p>
        <p>''Parts of South Africa are an ecological wasteland, and most of it you will see in the homelands,'' said Pauline H. Baker, an expert on South Africa at the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, a Washington research center. ''You can see the haze that hangs over Soweto. It is pollution from the kerosene and coal-burning lamps.''</p>
        <p>The World Watch report noted that blacks crowded into the homelands and townships suffer the worst effects of the dirty air and contaminated water from mining excavation.</p>
        <p>An end to apartheid will not automatically bring an end to the environmental destruction, Mr. Durning said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
