<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Proposals for a U.S. Energy Policy: Some Possible, Most Not</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19900925T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="386488"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDB153CF937A1575AC0A966958260" item-length="3214" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Proposals for a U.S. Energy Policy: Some Possible, Most Not</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: From the day Ronald Reagan arrived in Washington until the day before Saddam Hussein's troops reached Kuwait City, energy policy was a fringe issue in the United States. Now, the deployment of American troops in the Persian Gulf to assure a steady flow of oil has left many policy makers wondering whether the United</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: From the day Ronald Reagan arrived in Washington until the day before Saddam Hussein's troops reached Kuwait City, energy policy was a fringe issue in the United States. Now, the deployment of American troops in the Persian Gulf to assure a steady flow of oil has left many policy makers wondering whether the United</p>
        <p>From the day Ronald Reagan arrived in Washington until the day before Saddam Hussein's troops reached Kuwait City, energy policy was a fringe issue in the United States. Now, the deployment of American troops in the Persian Gulf to assure a steady flow of oil has left many policy makers wondering whether the United States has options other than force to insure an adequate supply of energy.</p>
        <p>But many proposals - including driving at the speed limit, paying high taxes on gasoline, running cars on natural gas and bicycling to work - seem a radical departure from how Americans work and play and live and how they think about natural resources. Here are 10 frequently mentioned proposals and their prospects for adoption:</p>
        <p>1 Reduce Speed Limits And Enforce Them</p>
        <p>A car that gets 28 miles a gallon at 55 miles an hour gets about 21 miles a gal lon at 65 miles an hour, the Insurance Institute for High way Safety says.</p>
        <p>Driving more slowly would seem to benefit both individuals' pocketbooks and the nation's balance of payments and energy security, not to mention side effects like saving lives and reducing pollution. (Remember Earth Day?) But a few minutes on any Interstate highway demonstrates that when it comes to getting from point A to point B, most drivers agree that the proper speed is as fast as possible.</p>
        <p>In New York, where the speed limit is 55 miles an hour, a vacationer who toured 180 rural miles of the New York Thruway at 60 miles an hour last month was the slowest vehicle on his stretch of road. Even the proverbial milk wagon went faster.</p>
        <p>After the Arab oil embargo of 1973-74, when most people worried where their next tankful of gas was coming from and children on Halloween dressed up like OPEC ministers, Congress responded to the new national mood by imposing a national 55-mile-an-hour speed limit. Most people actually slowed down almost to that speed.</p>
        <p>But when gasoline once again became inexpensive, Washington responded by allowing the states to raise their speed limits to 65 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>Speed aside, encouraging drivers to keep their tires fully inflated, and providing air hoses at a time when fewer gas stations do, would also increase gas mileage considerably.</p>
        <p>PROSPECTS: No change unless a crisis mentality takes hold or law-enforcement officials deploy their troops to stop speeding.</p>
        <p>2 Insist on Cars With Better Mileage</p>
        <p>Six million bar rels of oil a day, out of total domestic consumption of 16 million, is used to provide fuel for cars and light trucks. Federal policy has already had a major impact on gas mileage; alarmed by the Arab oil embargo in 1973-74, Congress required car makers to raise the mileage of cars, step by step, until the average of all cars sold reached 27.5 miles a gallon.</p>
        <p>As new cars were built and old cars retired, the average efficiency of cars on the road in the United States has risen from 13.3 miles a gallon in 1973 to about 20 miles a gallon today, an improvement of 50 percent. Even if the Government does nothing more, average fuel economy will improve as new cars replace older ones.</p>
        <p>But the collapse of crude oil prices in 1986 pushed gasoline prices so low that car buyers stopped demanding the more efficient models. Between the 1988 and 1990 model years, buyers moved so heavily to bigger cars with bigger engines that average fuel economy declined by 3 percent. The average fuel economy of 1990 model-year cars is 27.8 miles a gallon, down from 28.6 two years ago. (On the other hand, cars do accelerate more quickly. The 1990 models, on average, go from 0 to 60 miles an hour in seven-tenths of a second less than it took the 1988's.) A bill in the Senate would raise the corporate average fuel economy standard by 40 percent by 2001, to about 40 miles a gallon. That would save nearly three million barrels a day when the new cars are fully phased in, according to the bill's supporters. This is a big number in relation to the seven million barrels a day currently being imported and far exceeds the 730,000 barrels a day that the United States had been getting from Iraq and Kuwait.</p>
        <p>Supporters say the Senate bill, sponsored by Richard H. Bryan, Democrat of Nevada, would stimulate the development of engine and transmission technologies, along with increased use of lightweight materials.</p>
        <p>But the auto makers say they used almost every trick they knew to double fuel efficiency from the mid-1970's to the mid-1980's. Nearly all cars made today have front-wheel drive instead of rear-wheel drive, and use fuel injectors instead of carburetors; all have been redesigned to cut wind drag. If substantial advances are to be made, the manufacturers say, it will have to be by making the cars smaller.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it's reasonable to hold that the most mobile society in the world can meet its personal and business transportation needs with a fleet of mini-compacts, subcompacts and compacts,'' said Thomas H. Hanna, president of the Motor Vehicle Manufacturers Association.</p>
        <p>''Sales, the only barometer of consumer preference, support this,'' he said. ''In 1989, cars rated at 50 miles per gallon or better accounted for less than 3 percent of U.S. sales.''</p>
        <p>But rather than making smaller cars, designers could increase mileage merely by cutting horsepower, forcing drivers to wait a second or two longer to go from 0 to 60. But that, Detroit says, does not sell cars.</p>
        <p>PROSPECTS: A law increasing mileage standards is likely to pass in some form.</p>
        <p>3 Substitute Pedals For Petroleum</p>
        <p>Half of all trips to work are estimated to be five miles or less. That is a com fortable bicycle ride for a healthy adult.</p>
        <p>But bicycles do not mix well with rain, snow, extreme heat, or the proper attire required by many companies. They also compete poorly for road space with automobiles, and in most places, local governments do not think they are important enough to warrant bicycle paths. Many employers provide parking for cars; fewer provide secure bicycle racks, or showers.</p>
        <p>Cycling already saves about 50,000 barrels of oil a day, said Charles Komanoff, an energy consultant and electricity expert in New York who is the president of Transportation Alternatives, a bicycle advocacy group. Part of the savings comes from the three million people who commute by bicycle; a larger part comes from people who cycle for pleasure, rather than going for a Sunday drive. Another part comes from trips by children who do not have to be ferried in cars, he said.</p>
        <p>If 10 percent of the work force shifted to bicycles for most of the year, from less than 3 percent now, the country could save an additional 25,000 barrels of oil a day, he calculates. Only 30 percent of car miles involve going to or from work, but bicycles could still substitute for part of the other 70 percent.</p>
        <p>The public is skeptical, and some interest groups go so far as to suggest that bicycling is almost un-American. One major chemical company, the Ethyl Corporation, seeking to build public support for a gasoline additive that it said would save oil, ran full-page newspaper ads showing photos of cyclists commuting in Beijing, with a caption that said some solutions to the energy problem were not practical here.</p>
        <p>PROSPECTS: Barring a dramatic change in personal habits and how people are required to dress for work, no change.</p>
        <p>4 Tax Gasoline At a Hefty Rate</p>
        <p>Most other indus trialized countries tax vehicle fuel by $1.50 to $3 a gallon; the average in this country, combining state, Federal and local taxes, is about 25 cents.</p>
        <p>Oil companies and car makers agree that recent decades have demonstrated that the most effective way to decrease consumption is to increase the price. The idea is hardly new. John B. Anderson, a former Representative from Illinois, built a Presidential campaign on the issue 10 years ago. The idea's appeal to voters, as measured by the Electoral College, was zero.</p>
        <p>Mr. Anderson, who now teaches law at Nova University Law School in Fort Lauderdale, Fla., said he believed such a tax was unlikely to prove any more popular now.</p>
        <p>And not everyone agrees that a higher tax would reduce fuel use. ''I don't think that consumption taxes do much except buy a bigger government,'' said Theodore Eck, the chief economist at the Amoco Corporation. Even with a 50-cent-a-gallon tax, he said, ''the incremental cost of driving a mile is low as heck,'' compared with fixed costs like the purchase price of the car and the insurance cost. ''Not too many people are going to hang it up and walk,'' he said.  The oil industry also argues that the tax would fall more heavily on poor people, who can least afford it and who often drive the oldest, thirstiest cars.</p>
        <p>To encourage national policy goals, Americans like tax breaks, not tax increases. Raising the tax on beer and liquor to keep up with inflation has been difficult in recent years. And gasoline is one of the few consumer products more popular than beer.</p>
        <p>PROSPECTS: Fair to poor.</p>
        <p>5 Use Natural Gas To Power Vehicles</p>
        <p>North America is largely self-suffi cient in natural gas, and major gas utili ties are offering to sell it for vehicle use at the equiva lent of 70 cents a gallon. Burned in a car or truck, natural gas produces far lower levels of soot and the chemicals that cause smog and acid rain than gasoline does. (Methanol and ethanol, two other alternative fuels, are more expensive than gasoline and offer less of an environmental advantage over gasoline.) Thousands of gasoline stations sit astride pipes that carry natural gas to homes, factories and other businesses. Natural gas does not require new refineries. Cars would have to be built with different fuel tanks, or have the tanks added, but existing gasoline engines will run acceptably without major modifications, and with relatively modest changes, a gasoline engine can be converted to run well on natural gas.</p>
        <p>In the San Francisco area, Pacific Gas and Electric says that of the seven million vehicles in its service territory, 500,000, which account for one-quarter of the area's fuel use, would be obvious candidates for an easy switch to natural gas. These are almost all fleet vehicles, from buses and delivery trucks to the vans of plumbers and electricians, that could or already do refuel at a central point.</p>
        <p>Pacific Gas and Electric, with two other big California utilities and others in Texas, recently signed a deal with General Motors to produce 1,000 three-quarter-ton pickup trucks powered solely by natural gas. They are to be sold and serviced through regular G.M. dealers in 1991. But progress has been slow, even in California, with its severe air pollution problems. ''We face a public acceptance obstacle,'' said Norman L. Bryan, vice president of Pacific Gas and Electric. The public dislikes the idea of a gaseous fuel, he said, even though natural gas appears to have technical advantages over gasoline. For one thing, if it leaks, it dissipates rather than forming a puddle, he pointed out. Explosion is a possibility with any flammable substance, but the ignition temperature of natural gas is 400 degrees higher than gasoline's.</p>
        <p>Natural gas is also hampered by a public perception, accurate 10 years ago when Government price regulations depressed drilling, that the supply is limited. This is a self-fulfilling perception, because fears about supply have held down demand for gas and therefore its price, removing an incentive for exploration. Experts point out that prospectors are drilling deeper and deeper, and the deeper the well, the more likely that what is found is natural gas. The size of the inventory in this continent is uncertain but seems likely to be substantial.</p>
        <p>Natural gas in vehicles also requires bulky canisters, which cut down cargo space in cars. And some bridges and tunnels deny access to vehicles carrying bottled gas.</p>
        <p>PROSPECTS: Natural gas will cease to be unusual in fleet vehicles. But it may be be many years before most drivers are interested in exploring this option.</p>
        <p>6 Tax Imported Oil To Spur U.S. Drilling</p>
        <p>American oil pro duction is declining 5 or 6 percent a year, because even now prices are too low to stimulate drilling, and drillers are not sure how long the current higher price will last. In many cases, even the current prices do not justify keeping open wells that produce only small amounts.</p>
        <p>Since 1986, when Saudi Arabia entered a price war with other OPEC producers and the price of a barrel dropped below $10, production in this country has declined by 2.3 million barrels a day, or about a quarter.</p>
        <p>If the Government taxed imports, it would raise the price that domestic producers could get for their oil, to the amount of the world price plus the tax. That would encourage drilling.</p>
        <p>But two hurdles stand in the Government's way. Washington has signed a free trade agreement with Canada, a major source of crude oil, and is negotiating a similar pact with Mexico, another major oil supplier. In addition, this country does not want to damage Mexico's economy, which is already shaky.</p>
        <p>If Canada and Mexico were excluded, it would be difficult to tax oil from Venezuela, with which Washington has cultivated strong ties, experts say. Venezuela is a member of the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries but during the oil embargo of 1973-74 it produced extra oil to help the United States weather a difficult period, and is doing the same now.</p>
        <p>If Venezuelan oil is exempted, what about oil from Saudi Arabia, which is also an ally of the United States? And if not Saudi oil, then who would be singled out? One expert suggested Iraq, Iran and Libya, from which imports are already effectively banned.</p>
        <p>And the timing for such a tax is dreadful. Few lawmakers are willing to add to the burden of higher oil prices with an oil tax.</p>
        <p>PROSPECTS: Nil.</p>
        <p>7 Conserve Electricity</p>
        <p>Nationwide, the Energy Depart ment says, utilities burn about 650,000 barrels of oil a day, accounting for about 6 percent of their fuel. But New York and New Eng land get about a third of their electricity from oil-powered generating plants.</p>
        <p>If electricity demand falls, many utilities continue to use the same amount of coal, hydroelectric and nuclear power, and the cut in output comes from lowering their use of oil. Conversely, if demand rises, the increase is met by burning oil because the plants that use cheaper fuels are already in full use.</p>
        <p>Of the 870,000 barrels of oil used each day in New England, 158,000 go to generate electricity, said Armond M. Cohen, senior attorney at the Conservation Law Foundation, a Boston group that has negotiated efficiency programs with utilities. Putting more insulation in home attics and walls, wrapping water heaters and pipes, installing low-flow showerheads and faucet aerators and putting in fluorescent lighting where appropriate can cut consumption by 15 to 20 percent in electrically heated houses, he said. These improvements can yield direct oil savings if the houses use oil for heat; if they use gas, they can save gas that would be available elsewhere as a substitute for oil. Many such changes could also be made in the commercial sector.</p>
        <p>In their manufacturing processes, most factories use big electric motors and put brakes on them to adjust them to the proper speed, and they use big pumps and reduce the flow to the proper level by forcing the pump to strain against a valve. If these companies bought smaller motors or variable-speed motors, which consume less power when less work is needed, and they modernized their lighting, they could save 12 to 15 percent of their electric consumption, Mr. Cohen said.</p>
        <p>In many cases, he said, it costs less to save a kilowatt-hour of electricity than to buy the oil to produce it.</p>
        <p>But even if such conservation makes sense economically, there are barriers. ''It's rare to find a business that will spend to improve energy efficiency if it doesn't pay back in a year or two,'' Mr. Cohen said, although a utility will build a new generator to meet inflated demand, while projecting a payback of 15 or 20 years.</p>
        <p>And ''most homeowners are so cash constrained that if they face a $2,000 or $3,000 investment that pays back in six months, they won't do it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>PROSPECTS: Despite resistance, increasingly efficient electrical use is likely. Many states, driven by worries about acid rain and climatic change as well as the oil crisis, will establish regulations that reward electric companies for selling less power.</p>
        <p>8 Give Tax Breaks To Drillers</p>
        <p>In addition to the standard corporate income tax, oil drill ers in the United States are taxed on revenues, in the form of royalties, which they pay to landowners on all oil taken from the ground, and severance taxes, which are based on the amount produced. When times are bad, this encourages the abandonment of marginal wells, some experts say, because the Government is taking a portion of the revenues, which are already lower than expenses.</p>
        <p>Robinson West, president of the Petroleum Finance Company, a Washington consulting firm, said the United States should follow the example of countries that tax profits; it would reap proportionally more in good years and would avoid depressing production in bad ones.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eck of Amoco argues that the 1986 tax law penalizes projects with a heavy start-up investment and slow recovery of resources, like drilling for hard-to-get deposits. An investment tax credit or accelerated depreciation to reduce taxes on those projects and unconventional gas wells could stimulate production, he said.</p>
        <p>But some drilling companies will report record profits this year, making it hard to argue that they deserve tax breaks.</p>
        <p>PROSPECTS: The mood in Washington is to cut spending and raise taxes to close the budget deficit. Giving drillers more money is unlikely.</p>
        <p>9 Breathe New Life Into Nuclear Power</p>
        <p>Opponents of nu clear power have a long list of prerequi sites: solve the waste storage prob lem, ''prove'' nu clear power is safe, insulate customers from the effects of cost overruns, exhaust the potential for improved efficiency first.</p>
        <p>Many utilities agree. They do not want to be stuck with radioactive wastes, they are afraid of cost overruns, and they would prefer not to build anything.</p>
        <p>''Nuclear is a long-range solution,'' said Timothy Guzzle, chief executive officer of Teco Energy, the parent of the Tampa Electric Company.</p>
        <p>PROSPECTS: For now, none.</p>
        <p>10 Do Nothing; Wait and See</p>
        <p>Drillers are find ing oil a lot faster than customers are using it. Proved re serves, or oil found and waiting to be pumped, rose by 50 percent in the 1980's. True, these reserves are not in North America, but in the long term, the supply of willing sellers seems large. Some, notably the Saudis, are determined not to let the price get too high, lest substitutes be found. The oil market will have occasional wild periods, as in 1973 and 1979, but the long-term average price is likely to be moderate.</p>
        <p>Constructing an energy policy, winning public support and enforcing the rules is expensive, inconvenient and a little painful. And it must compete for attention with problems like a budget deficit, a shaky economy, an education crisis, homelessness, the environment and the drug problem.</p>
        <p>PROSPECTS: For doing little, excellent.</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 25, 1990, Tuesday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day yesterday about energy policy choices referred incorrectly to a comment on fuel economy by Thomas H. Hanna, president of the Motor Vehicle Manufacturers Association. He said cars that get 40 miles a gallon or better -not 50 or better - made up less than 3 percent of the market last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 25, 1990, Tuesday, Late Edition - Final</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day yesterday about energy policy choices referred incorrectly to a comment on fuel economy by Thomas H. Hanna, president of the Motor Vehicle Manufacturers Association. He said cars that get 40 miles a gallon or better -not 50 or better - made up less than 3 percent of the market last year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
