<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Warns Senate on Changes to Clean Air Bill</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="318400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DC163AF933A15752C0A966958260" item-length="669" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Warns Senate on Changes to Clean Air Bill</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush wrote to leaders of the Senate today warning that he would oppose amendments to strengthen the Clean Air Act if the costs to the economy exceeded ''the already considerable costs'' of the legislation he proposed last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush wrote to leaders of the Senate today warning that he would oppose amendments to strengthen the Clean Air Act if the costs to the economy exceeded ''the already considerable costs'' of the legislation he proposed last year.</p>
        <p>President Bush wrote to leaders of the Senate today warning that he would oppose amendments to strengthen the Clean Air Act if the costs to the economy exceeded ''the already considerable costs'' of the legislation he proposed last year.</p>
        <p>Administration officials estimate that the legislation the Senate plans to take up Tuesday would cost industry and consumers $40 billion a year by the year 2000. The President's bill, they said, would achieve almost the same reduction in airborne pollutants at a cost of $19 billion a year.</p>
        <p>The President's letter raises the level of an argument that has erupted among policy makers and lobbyists here over the costs and benefits of cracking down on air pollution. Changes in the Clean Air Act are expected to be among the most important and contentious issues Congress will handle this year.</p>
        <p>The Senate bill would require major new programs to curb urban smog, acid rain and toxic air pollution as well as programs that would begin to address the global warming problem. The President's bill would have similar programs, but would not go quite as far as the Senate proposals, whose costs would rise each year as increasingly stringent pollution limits go into effect.</p>
        <p>Late this week, White House and Environmental Protection Agency officials circulated estimates that put the cost of the Senate bill at $40 billion a year by the year 2000.</p>
        <p>'Minimum Tests of Balance'</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said in his letter that the only bill he would accept is one that meets ''minimum tests of balance and reasonableness.'' Among those tests, he wrote, were that the bill maintain the same environmental protection and cost levels of his Administration's bill; that it have controls to lower pollution ''for the least cost per ton of reduced pollutant,'' and that it avoid new taxes.</p>
        <p>''The bill,'' the President said, ''should not impose aggregate costs on the economy that exceed the already considerable costs embodied in the Administration's bill.''</p>
        <p>But the President's letter did not mention a possible veto of any legislation that did not meet all his standards. Congressional staff aides said today that they doubted that Mr. Bush would veto a clean air bill this year in the face of what is widely perceived as strong public support for such legislation.</p>
        <p>Senate aides who drafted the legislation said the Administration estimate of $40 billion miscalculated the cost of new controls. Among other things, they said, the figures overestimated the costs of lowering car pollution.</p>
        <p>Public health and environmental groups, meanwhile, contend that reducing air pollution will save the country far more money than it will cost to achieve such reductions.</p>
        <p>Benefits to Health, Some Argue</p>
        <p>A report today by the American Lung Association concludes that the benefits of improved public health would significantly outweigh the costs.</p>
        <p>The lung association report was based on a survey of dozens of studies of medical expenses, lost days of employment and premature deaths attributed to exposure to polluted air. It said these costs amounted to tens of billions of dollars a year.</p>
        <p>James S. Cannon, the author of the lung association's report, said a range of $40 billion to $50 billion a year for medical costs from all forms of air pollution seemed most reasonable, although one survey cited in the report found that pollution from automobiles alone resulted in health costs to the nation of nearly $100 billion a year.</p>
        <p>On Thursday the Business Roundtable issued a report on the legislation coming before the Senate, saying the costs could be as much as $104 billion a year and that the best estimate of the costs of legislation pending before Congress is $54 billion.</p>
        <p>The roundtable, an association of executives of big corporations who seek to influence policy making, warned that the higher costs estimated for the Senate bill ''could result in a shutdown or significantly reduced production in United States industries whose total revenues exceed $100 billion annually.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
