<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public Ownership Is Good Public Relations</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="370682"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND POWER AUTHORITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND LIGHTING CO (LILCO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KESSEL, RICHARD M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCRANDIS, JOSEPH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DB1F31F931A15754C0A966958260" item-length="400" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public Ownership Is Good Public Relations</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Sometimes public leaders lose touch with reality as they sit at their lonely pinnacle of power. Some never had much of a grasp to start with. Richard Kessel, chairman of the Long Island Power Authority, is an example.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Sometimes public leaders lose touch with reality as they sit at their lonely pinnacle of power. Some never had much of a grasp to start with. Richard Kessel, chairman of the Long Island Power Authority, is an example.</p>
        <p>Sometimes public leaders lose touch with reality as they sit at their lonely pinnacle of power. Some never had much of a grasp to start with. Richard Kessel, chairman of the Long Island Power Authority, is an example.</p>
        <p>In his Long Island Opinion article, he tries to share his prejudice against Lilco and his fantasy of an electricity-starved but nuclear free Long Island.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kessel seems to dwell on Lilco's ability to reward their executives, yet fails to observe his own string of rewards for his anti-establishment behavior at the hands of his personal benefactor and ideological twin, Gov. Mario M. Cuomo.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kessel and Govenor Cuomo also seem to confuse Lilco with a spiritual entity, for they hold Lilco personally responsible for Hurricane Gloria and its resultant problems.</p>
        <p>However, with all their faults, and there are more than a few, at least Lilco delivers a product and a service. If it were not for Messrs. Kessel, Cuomo and their ilk, we on Long Island would have adequate electricity this year. Instead we will probably experience ever more outages and brownouts, while L.I.P.A. will exhort all of us to use less electricity, or to use it when we should be sleeping. No doubt L.I.P.A. will issue a plethora of reports and hot air, the sum of which will have no more practical use than to drive a child's pinwheel or start charcoal for a barbecue.</p>
        <p>As we swelter and suffer, let us remember that it is we, Lilco's ratepayers, who will pay the billions of dollars that the Shoreham plant costs, and the interest on that debt. And if you have the stamina, you can ponder where the money will come from to dismantle the Shoreham plant, and to convert Shoreham or build another facility to generate more electricity.</p>
        <p>Justice would be served if we could pass the bill on to Messrs. Kessel/Cuomo. But since their pockets are not deep enough, the honor will fall to all of us. And some will pay happily, knowing that we have dismantled a safe, clean and environmentally benign electricity generating plant, and have exchanged it for a huge debt and carbon dioxide generating plants burning fossil fuels that will become ever more expensive.</p>
        <p>JOSEPH SCRANDIS</p>
        <p>Westbury</p>
        <p>Letters should include the writer's name, address and telephone number for verification. Send letters to The Editor, Long Island Weekly, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
