<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Northern Hemisphere Snow Cover Found to Be Shrinking</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="396764"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEAT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D71F3BF933A05753C1A966958260" item-length="879" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Northern Hemisphere Snow Cover Found to Be Shrinking</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE part of the Northern Hemisphere covered by snow has been shrinking in the last three years, and its expanse is among the smallest since scientists began making reliable satellite observations of snow cover in 1972, climatologists say.</p>
        <p>The changes appear to mean that for the most part, the winter snow season now begins a little later and ends a little earlier in the northern United States and Canada, said Dr. David A. Robinson, a climate expert at Rutgers University who participated in the study.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE part of the Northern Hemisphere covered by snow has been shrinking in the last three years, and its expanse is among the smallest since scientists began making reliable satellite observations of snow cover in 1972, climatologists say.</p>
        <p>The changes appear to mean that for the most part, the winter snow season now begins a little later and ends a little earlier in the northern United States and Canada, said Dr. David A. Robinson, a climate expert at Rutgers University who participated in the study.</p>
        <p>It is too early to tell whether the shrinking snow cover in North America, Europe and Asia results from natural climatic variations or from global warming that many scientists believe will result from a continuing buildup of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping chemicals in the atmosphere, Dr. Robinson said.</p>
        <p>But he said the findings coincided closely with fluctuations in Northern Hemisphere temperatures in a decade that experienced some of the warmest temperatures of the last century. And since the satellite observations provide a comprehensive view of what is happening that ground-based temperature readings and snow measurements cannot achieve, he and other scientists say, they could provide an important indicator of climatic change in the future.</p>
        <p>"If you did see a carbon dioxide effect, this is probably how it would look," said Dr. George Kukla of Columbia University's Lamont-Doherty Geological Observatory, an authority on the climate and the role of snow.  "On the other hand, the record is too short to be convinced that what you're seeing is a carbon dioxide impact."</p>
        <p>Snow cover, scientists say, is an important element of the Earth's climate system. It affects the temperature of the atmosphere by reflecting sunlight, and accurate measurement of the extent of snow is considered essential to understanding the myriad factors that produce a net warming or cooling effect. The new study is seen as a step in that direction. Checking Natural Variation</p>
        <p>Scientists also say they need to know more about the natural variability of snow cover if this variability is ultimately to be distinguished from the effects of global warming.  "The longer this record gets," Dr. Kukla said of the satellite observations, "the more we will know about natural variability."</p>
        <p>The latest study was conducted by Dr. Robinson and Dr. Kenneth F. Dewey, a climatologist at the University of Nebraska, and is reported in the current issue of the scientific journal Geophysical Research Letters.</p>
        <p>The scientists analyzed weekly "snow charts" produced by meteorologists of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration who routinely interpret the satellite images. The charts depict the boundaries between snow-covered and snow-free land surfaces of the Northern Hemisphere. From them, the researchers calculated the average extent of snow coverage for each month and year starting in 1972.</p>
        <p>They found that snow cover in 1988 and 1989 was at its lowest level of the 18-year period, dropping 8 to 10 percent below the annual average of about 10 million square miles. Dr. Robinson has since updated the analysis to include monthly and annual averages through August 1990. The updated analysis shows that the average annual snow cover for the period from September 1989 through August 1990 was 9.5 million square miles, among the lowest for comparable periods since the reliable satellite observations began.</p>
        <p>The other two low years were September 1988 through August 1989, with 9.3 million square miles, and September 1987 through August 1988, with 9.5 million square miles. The largest expanse of snow recorded for a comparable period was from September 1978 through August 1979, with 10.6 million square miles.</p>
        <p>The highest monthly average was 20 million square miles, recorded in February 1978, and the lowest was August 1988, with 900,000 square miles. Advancing a Little Later</p>
        <p>The Eurasian land mass accounted for most of the snow cover.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robinson said the data indicated that the area covered by winter snow in North America was not changing, but the snow line advances southward a little later in the fall and retreats a little earlier in the spring in most recent years. "It's not something so dramatic that people are going to be flinging their windows open in the middle of winter," he said.  "People in many parts of the U.S. would not recognize any major change at all."</p>
        <p>But to the extent that snow cover is missing when it might otherwise be expected, he said, it might be warmer than otherwise. This is because when snow is on the ground, it reflects sunlight and enhances the cold; but when the ground is clear, more solar energy is absorbed by the surface and this heat warms the air. This effect is particularly pronounced in the springtime, climatologists say.</p>
        <p>The analyses say nothing about the depth of snow that might accumulate where it does fall, Dr. Robinson said.  This is governed by a variety of shifting climatic and meteorological factors. And in fact, he said, warmer temperatures could produce more atmospheric moisture and greater snow volume in colder northern latitudes. Theoretically, such temperatures could also lead to more low-pressure areas bearing more snow in more temperate latitudes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
