<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Researchers Prepare For Fist Human Tests Of an Artificial Lung</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="315451"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LUNGS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TESTS AND TESTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALTMAN, LAWRENCE K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lungs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D9103AF93AA35752C0A966958260" item-length="1566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Researchers Prepare For Fist Human Tests Of an Artificial Lung</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ALTMAN, LAWRENCE K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A DEVICE that adds oxygen and removes carbon dioxide from the blood has been developed as a temporary artificial lung, ready for its first human tests. The device is to be inserted in a vein in the groin or neck and then guided into the body's main vein in the chest, where it can stay in place for up to a week, easing the burden on the lungs while they heal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A DEVICE that adds oxygen and removes carbon dioxide from the blood has been developed as a temporary artificial lung, ready for its first human tests. The device is to be inserted in a vein in the groin or neck and then guided into the body's main vein in the chest, where it can stay in place for up to a week, easing the burden on the lungs while they heal.</p>
        <p>A DEVICE that adds oxygen and removes carbon dioxide from the blood has been developed as a temporary artificial lung, ready for its first human tests. The device is to be inserted in a vein in the groin or neck and then guided into the body's main vein in the chest, where it can stay in place for up to a week, easing the burden on the lungs while they heal.</p>
        <p>The first tests of the device on humans are to be carried out soon on 10 patients in four medical centers.</p>
        <p>The device is called an intravascular oxygenator, or IVOX. The device is expected to perform the equivalent of about half of normal breathing, giving a life-saving boost to patients with respiratory failure and tiding them over a crisis. It is not a substitute for the lungs, which are left in place to function as well as they can.</p>
        <p>Tested in Animals</p>
        <p>The device has been tested in animals. Researchers said it did not damage the blood or organs in experiments involving 150 sheep and dogs and lasting up to 19 days.</p>
        <p>The aims of the initial human experiments are to substantiate data established in animals and to confirm the safety of the device in humans. The experiments have been approved by the Federal Food and Drug Administration and the ethics committees at each institution.</p>
        <p>Experiments aimed at determining the device's value in treating patients will be conducted later.</p>
        <p>The device's chief developer, Dr. J D Mortensen, developed an earlier version of the device with financial support from the National Institutes of Health. That version did not exchange enough oxygen and carbon dioxide to be clinically useful. The newest version was financed privately by Cardiopulmonics Inc. of Salt Lake City, a company Dr. Mortensen helped found.</p>
        <p>Helping Patients Recover</p>
        <p>If the device succeeds in human experiments, Dr. Mortensen says it could help tens of thousands of people each year. Dr. Mortensen, who is chairman of Cardiopulmonics, said the device could help patients recover from acute episodes of respiratory failure resulting from inhalation of smoke or noxious agents, drugs, severe pneumonia and scores of other ailments.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mortensen, who is 70 years old, stopped performing chest surgery a decade ago to devote full time to developing the device.</p>
        <p>''We're not at the stage where we can do away with lungs,'' he said in an interview. Yet success with the device would be an important step toward the ultimate goal of a permanent artificial lung for people with chronic respiratory problems, like emphysema or obstructive lung disease.</p>
        <p>Experts have called the device a potentially important development because it could become a relatively simple and inexpensive solution to a major medical problem.</p>
        <p>A Note of Caution</p>
        <p>But Dr. Claude J. Lenfant, director of the National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute in Bethesda, Md., and others cautioned that many artificial devices have worked well in animals only to prove disappointing in humans.</p>
        <p>Dr. Pierre M. Galletti, an expert in artificial organs at Brown University in Providence and a scientific adviser to Cardiopulmonics, said that he was skeptical when he first learned about the device two years ago. He says he expects that the device will work in humans because it did in animals. But ''whether it will make any difference in terms of survival remains to be seen,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The four participating medical centers are Penn State's Hershey Medical Center, the LDS Hospital in Salt Lake City, the University of Michigan Medical Center in Ann Arbor, and the Los Angeles County-University of Southern California Medical Center. The Hershey and LDS teams received the first devices last week. ''We're ready to go,'' said Dr. Michael T. Snider, a professor of anesthesiology who heads the Hershey team. With the flu season and winter respiratory problems at hand, Dr. Snider said he expected to implant a device for the first time within three weeks.</p>
        <p>The researchers said they were extremely encouraged by results of the animal experiments. Nevertheless, there is always apprehension when scientists make the leap from experiments on animals to those on humans.</p>
        <p>''You never know from animal studies how such a device will perform in humans,'' Dr. Snider said.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of Thin Tubes</p>
        <p>The device, which looks like a mass of twisted spaghetti, contains hundreds of thin-walled hollow tubes made of polypropylene, coated with a silicone and dotted with tiny pores. The silicone and polypropylene block fluid but allow the exchange of gases with blood as it passes over the tubes, similar to the way in which gases pass through natural membranes in the air sacs of the human lung.</p>
        <p>The synthetic tubes are also coated with heparin, an anticoagulant, to prevent the formation of blood clots.</p>
        <p>A vacuum pump outside the body creates a suction to pull oxygen into the vein and withdraw carbon dioxide through additional tubes.</p>
        <p>Each hollow tube is nearly two feet long but is only about as thick as a human hair. Hundreds of the tubes are crimped and twisted so they can be slipped through the vein in the neck or groin. Once in place in the body's main vein, the vena cava, which is about two inches in diameter in the chest and abdomen, the strands are unfurled to exchange gases without impeding the flow of blood.</p>
        <p>Cells extract oxygen from blood as it circulates through the body. Oxygen-poor blood passes through the vena cava on its way to the lungs for the normal exchange of carbon dioxide and oxygen and repetition of the cycle. The device exchanges the gases before the blood reaches the lungs.</p>
        <p>Animal research with the device has suggested that supplying more oxygen-rich blood to damaged lungs may improve their performance and speed their healing.</p>
        <p>Seeking to Deliver Oxygen</p>
        <p>IVOX is the latest in a centuries-old scientific quest to provide oxygen to a diseased body. Many attempts to inject oxygen directly into blood vessels, skin and the abdomen failed in animals and humans; recipients died suddenly when gas bubbles clogged arteries or lodged in the lungs. Other experiments using hydrogen peroxide met similar disasters.</p>
        <p>Early this century doctors developed safe ways to deliver oxygen through the nostrils. More recently, doctors have developed a variety of methods, including mechanical ventilators, to deliver oxygen to the lungs.</p>
        <p>But the high pressures needed to deliver large amounts of oxygen can tear the lungs, and the oxygen itself often causes other pulmonary damage. This further diminishes the ability of the damaged lungs to deliver enough oxygen to the body.</p>
        <p>In the last 40 years, scientists have developed heart-lung machines and other devices to put oxygen in the blood. But with these machines, the exchange is made outside the body. Blood is drained from the body, oxygen added, and then the blood is pumped back into the body.</p>
        <p>Existing therapies that add oxygen outside the body are expensive because they require teams of technicians to monitor the devices at the bedside and are available only at major medical centers. Even in the hands of experts, bleeding is a major risk because of the drugs needed to reduce the chances of a blood clot.</p>
        <p>Device May Be Safer, Simpler</p>
        <p>The device is expected to be much simpler, less costly and safer.</p>
        <p>''If the device can do a third or more of the normal breathing,'' Dr. Mortensen said, ''then the ventilator can be turned down to lower and safer levels or turned off completely, and the assistance from the IVOX can buy enough time for the lungs to recover.''</p>
        <p>The Utah researchers have not tested the device for extended periods because they do not expect to use it for longer than seven days. Experience suggests that if a patient does not recover within a week, survival is unlikely.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mortensen said that a variety of measurements were used to document that the device exchanged oxygen and carbon dioxide when the natural lungs were left in animals.</p>
        <p>''We turned it on and off and on and off to see the changes,'' Dr. Mortensen said.</p>
        <p>The researchers also used smoke and chemicals to injure the lungs of anesthetized animals in experiments intended to simulate respiratory failure in humans. The animals responded to the device, Dr. Mortensen said.</p>
        <p>''The studies were absolutely essential to show that the IVOX did not hurt the animals,'' Dr. Mortensen said. ''But the reason for going to humans now is that there is no other good model for treating true respiratory failure in an intensive care unit except humans.''</p>
        <p>Selecting the First Patients</p>
        <p>Cardiopulmonics, which was founded in 1985, said it has spent $8 million in venture capital to develop the device.</p>
        <p>The first 10 patients will be selected from a group who cannot live without a mechanical ventilator and whose chances for survival are less than 10 percent, by standard medical reckoning. Doctors are not counting on extending the lives of these patients. Their primary goal is to determine whether the device damages blood or tissue.</p>
        <p>While the devices are inserted, the doctors will rely on laboratory tests that measure the level of gases in the blood to assess whether the devices are functioning. If the blood gases show enough improvement, the amounts and pressure of oxygen will be reduced.</p>
        <p>If the device proves safe among the 10 patients in the first stage, the trials will be expanded to test its efficacy among 100 patients in more than a dozen hospitals.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
