<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turin's Baroque Splendors</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="372302"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">TURIN (ITALY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ITALY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERNIER, OLIVIER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JUVARRA, FILIPPO (17TH CENTURY)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUARINI, GUARINO (1624-1683)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Turin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DA163FF93AA15754C0A966958260" item-length="2777" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turin's Baroque Splendors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Oliver Bernier; Oliver bernier is the author of, most recently, of ''Words of Fire, Deeds of Blood: The Mob, the Monarchy and the French Revolution'' (Little, Brown).</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERNIER, OLIVIER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Turin, the capital of a small state half on one side of the Alps, half on the other, where the ruler spoke French and most of but part of the population Italian, is an improbable place for some of the best architecture in Italy, especially since it was invaded with great regularity by French, Spanish and Austrian armies; and yet in the 17th and early 18th centuries it became home to two architects of genius, Guarino Guarini and Filippo Juvarra, brought there by successive Dukes of</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Turin, the capital of a small state half on one side of the Alps, half on the other, where the ruler spoke French and most of but part of the population Italian, is an improbable place for some of the best architecture in Italy, especially since it was invaded with great regularity by French, Spanish and Austrian armies; and yet in the 17th and early 18th centuries it became home to two architects of genius, Guarino Guarini and Filippo Juvarra, brought there by successive Dukes of</p>
        <p>Turin, the capital of a small state half on one side of the Alps, half on the other, where the ruler spoke French and most of but part of the population Italian, is an improbable place for some of the best architecture in Italy, especially since it was invaded with great regularity by French, Spanish and Austrian armies; and yet in the 17th and early 18th centuries it became home to two architects of genius, Guarino Guarini and Filippo Juvarra, brought there by successive Dukes of Savoy.</p>
        <p>As a result, dazzling and unusual examples of Baroque architecture are to be found in Turin, while, just a 20-minute drive away, the rococo thrives at Stupinigi, an enchanting country palace.</p>
        <p>Conveniently, most of the city's monuments are within a few minutes' walk from one another, and the best place to start, both geographically and chronologically, is the Piazza San Carlo.</p>
        <p>Designed in 1640 by Carlo da Castellomonte on the orders of Marie Christine, a French-born princess then Regent for her underage son, it sets just the right mood: lined with deep arcades above which plain, handsome houses faced with ocher stucco come together impressively, it is, of course, a reminder of its French ancestor, the Place des Vosges in Paris, but adapted to a different climate, and it proves that the Regent knew good architecture and was interested in city planning.</p>
        <p>From there, a broad, arcaded street leads to the Piazza Castello. Directly in front, the Palazzo Reale (Royal Palace) stretches out on three sides of a rectangle, and while the palace is quite undistinguished, it serves as a pleasing backdrop.</p>
        <p>Just to its left, however, and then again behind it, two complex, oddly shaped domes catch the eye; while directly to the right, clad in stone baked by the sun to a golden color, stands the Palazzo Madama, one of the most beautiful buildings in Europe. It takes a good deal of self-restraint simply to walk past; but it makes sense to begin with the closest of the two odd domes, that of San Lorenzo.</p>
        <p>Built as a chapel for the palace, it was designed in 1668 by Guarini, a monk who also happened to be a great architect; and while its style is clearly influenced by that of Borromini, who had died the year before, it remains a highly individual statement.</p>
        <p>Seen from the outside it seems almost not to exist, hidden as it is behind a palace wing; but then, rising above it, the drum of the dome is made of eight convex sides, each pierced by a large oval window topped by a semicircular pediment and flanked by double pilasters. This circular movement is emphasized by the next level, which looks like a pyramid of semicircular, windowed arcs. Then comes an octagonal pavilion and that, in turn, is topped by a small dome.</p>
        <p>Altogether it is as odd yet compelling a structure as can be imagined. Still, if the forms are complex, the surface is plain cream-colored stucco, and the surprise awaiting the visitor within is all the greater.</p>
        <p>As befits its function, San Lorenzo is small; but when you enter, you find yourself in a cocoon of polychrome marble and gilt bronze. Black, white, dark green, maroon and apricot, the colors glow while columns, pilasters and altars seem to dance around the circular space.</p>
        <p>Three side altars on each side allow for a profusion of ornament, while directly in front, the main altar, behind its curved apricot marble balustrade, stands in its own oval space. But even more astonishing than all these riches is the dome itself. Apparently floating over giant arches (when in fact it is carried by the piers that connect them) it manages to be both intricate and unsubstantial.</p>
        <p>Windows open everywhere; arcs crisscross so as to create a multiplicity of thin forms curving upward to the octagonal central opening, and light pours in to the otherwise windowless church.</p>
        <p>This use of unusual geometric forms defined by an abundance of natural light is typical of Guarini; in another masterpiece, the Chapel of the Holy Shroud, these elements are combined just as effectively. Built as an addition to the church of San Giovanni, just behind the Royal Palace, it, too, is invisible from the outside except for its dome, and that is even odder than San Lorenzo's. Here, the drum is unusually tall, and each facet consists of a high arched window. A wavy pattern is thus created; above it is a rising sea of wavelike semicircular forms that end in a round platform supporting a three-level pagodalike pavilion. Inside, the mood is properly somber but grand.</p>
        <p>Linked to the church by a vast windowed arch, the chapel is reached by two symmetrical staircases, each topped by a barrel vault and made to seem even more majestic by the alternation of pilasters and niches on the sides. Each staircase leads to a round black marble vestibule that opens into the main space.</p>
        <p>There, too, the walls are clad in black marble while the floor is aved with light and dark gray marble adorned with bronze stars.</p>
        <p>Even at the first level, the rhythm of the architecture is highly complex: arcades framed with freestanding Corinthian columns and contained by double giant pilasters alternate with semicircular balconies, each topped by a golden bronze balustrade and adorned with a red stucco drape. Above this, powerful semicircular arches covered with high-relief stucco pentagons alternate with arc-sided rectangles in which the reliefs are cruciform. Both elements are pierced by large round windows, and then it all begins. The drum, with its tall windows, seems to be nothing but light, and it supports a froth of superimposed semicircular pediments leading up to the star-shaped lunette. Here, too, light streams in so that this vast construction seems utterly weightless.</p>
        <p>When it came to inventive forms and playing with the circle, though, Guarini could do just as well with a secular building. Two minutes away from the Piazza Castello, the Palazzo Carignano is abundant proof of that. Built in red brick from 1679 to 1685 for a cousin of the Duke of Savoy's, it starts at either end with a square pavilion; then two concave wings move toward the center only to become convex as they approach it, while at the center itself, a scooped-out section is filled in with a projecting semicircular balcony-pavilion held up by four Tuscan columns.</p>
        <p>Above it all a half-cupola supports a semicircular pediment topped by a broken, wavy pediment. Movement is everywhere: even the pilasters are adorned with forms that look like horizontal exclamation points, and the windows are framed in wavy pediments and drapery. The result is extraordinarily graceful: instead of the large, boxlike palaces that had been the norm, what we see is a building of fluid elegance.</p>
        <p>Back at the Piazza Castello a very different sort of genius awaits us. Where Guarini is all sleight of hand and eye, Juvarra gives us majesty without pomp. What is perhaps most amazing about the dignified simplicity of his style is that, elsewhere in Europe, the rococo was becoming the norm; but just as Guarini practices an eccentric and unconventional Baroque, so Juvarra seems to have skipped right to the sort of neo-classicism that became popular in the late 1760's.</p>
        <p>There are several of Juvarra's works in Turin - the Cissors staircase in the Royal Palace, San Filippo Neri with its imposing central nave, Santa Cristina, on the Piazza San Carlo, where the gesticulating sculpture of the facade brings him closest to the liveliness of the rococo; but his two masterpieces are unquestionably the Palazzo Madama and the Superga.</p>
        <p>The Palazzo Madama, a building much admired by Napoleon, who made it his Turin residence, is, in fact, a screen over a screen. Before 1718 there was a square medieval fortress built in part on Roman foundations; when Vittorio Emmanuele II decided to improve his capital he asked Juvarra to design a sort of overall curtain wall so that, without destroying the old building, it could be given a decent appearance. As it turned out, only the new west facade was ever built; but as it is we have no reason to complain.</p>
        <p>From the outside, the Palazzo looks both grand and inviting: because the facade seems to be mostly windows, it beckons the viewer. But its giant orders keep us properly awed, and the slight forward movement of its center gives it just the right degree of animation. On the ground floor the entrance is a triple arcade with rusticated piers and trophies; above, on the piano nobile, four massive Corinthian columns framing three arched windows and emphasized by triple pilasters behind them continue the movement upward, and they are topped in turn by urns and sculpture. That, and the giant pilasters that march across the rest of the facade, balance the otherwise horizontal character of the facade: here, all is harmony and perfect proportion, with just enough movement to please the eye, but not enough to detract from the palace's quiet grandeur.</p>
        <p>The interior has just been closed for a restoration scheduled to last several years, an inconvenience all the greater that, inside, the architecture echoes and completes the facade; for there, as we climb the imposing double staircase, we realize that the facade is only a screen; and there is a second, interior facade, with its own rhythm of giant pilasters and arched openings, with a barrel vault connecting the two.</p>
        <p>It is as if, having gone behind a stage set, we found not only that its back was as striking as its front, but that yet another set awaited us behind the first one.5 Juvarra's other masterpiece, the Superga, is, if anything, even more imposing. In 1706 Vittorio Amadeo II, whose daughter was married to Louis XIV's grandson, betrayed his relative and ally. As a result, he soon found himself facing a French army and probable defeat; so, at a small chapel built on the tallest hill overlooking Turin, he vowed to build a church if the city held out; it did, and the church was built.</p>
        <p>Its position is utterly spectacular: its dome can be seen against the sky from much of the city, while from its piazza there is a dazzling view over Turin and the plain around it. Clearly the site called for a major statement, and that is just what Juvarra has provided.</p>
        <p>The church itself is nothing but a dome, preceded by a portico. Four giant Corinthian columns, in two groups of two with a wider central opening, support a triangular pediment in front; the portico itself is two columns deep, so that all we see is the vertical movement of the columns leading our eye to the tall drum with its rhythm of paired columns and to the high dome.</p>
        <p>Inside, the circular church, brightly lighted by the windows of the drum, is simplicity itself. Giant Corinthian columns frame the arches leading to shallow chapels topped with barrel vaults. Between the arcades there are rectangular doorways topped by small open balconies. There are no ornaments, no added curves: all is left to the architecture itself; and, as a result, the Superga almost takes one's breath away.</p>
        <p>Like all great architects, however, Juvarra was capable of renewing himself: while nothing could be purer, or easier to read, than the style of the Palazzo Madama and the Superga, the hunting palace he designed for Vittorio Amadeo II at Stupinigi, just outside Turin, is both complex and eccentric.</p>
        <p>Indeed, at first sight, the palazzina seems to ramble on endlessly: far away in the distance is the central pavilion, but before that, there are, first, two long perpendicular wings that form a sort of frame; each of these is connected to a semicircular wing that brings us a little closer to the heart of the palace; then comes, on either side, a wing with side pavilions protruding at an angle. That, in turn, brings us into a vast six-sided court at the center of which the cylindrical central pavilion rises.</p>
        <p>The effect, at first, is as complex as the description it requires; but then the visitor begins to realize he is entering a complete small universe. Those outflung wings welcome him as they remove him, little by little, from the country outside; and by the time he reaches the central pavilion, with its green copper dome crowned with a life-size stag the welcome is tinged with grandeur. Then, on the park side, Stupinigi is just as unexpected: there, the cylindrical central pavilion is framed by protruding diagonal wings.</p>
        <p>That this is all absolutely unorthodox hardly needs saying: there is not another palace in Europe like Stupinigi; but it is also remarkably effective. Not only has Juvarra provided, abundantly, for all the services of a hunting palace - horses, carriages, dog kennels, as well as servants' and courtiers' lodging - but he has also made the sovereigns themselves comfortable by giving each one of those parkside diagonal wings where they are removed from the bustle of the court.</p>
        <p>Inside, Stupinigi is full of treasures: much of the 18th- century decor and furniture has been preserved, so there are fresh and lively chinoiserie rooms, and rooms with hunting scenes, and rooms with the original brocade on the walls and cheerful gods on the ceiling.</p>
        <p>There is a game room, with orientalizing animals playing on the walls, and a trompe l'oeil room where painted mauve pilasters frame grisaille architectural views, and a small, enchanting faux-marbre neo-classical chapel created for the marriage of the Comte d'Artois, Louis XVI's brother, to a princess of Savoy. Scattered everywhere is a variety of first-rate furniture, both rococo and neo-classical, which includes some magical local pieces where the wood is inlaid with a mother of pearl decor.</p>
        <p>The center of Stupinigi, however, both qualitatively and geographically, is the great central hall. Designed by Juvarra, it rises the entire height of the domed pavilion and is open at three levels - arched French doors at the bottom, small, rectangular windows half way up and large arched windows on top. The result is a huge, light volume where the proportions are such as to make the very amplitude inviting. That it should be so, however, is due almost as much to Giambattista Crosato, the Venetian painter who frescoed every available surface. Only the four piers that lead up to a great arch on either side of the room are real: all the rest of the exuberant architectural decor is pure trompe l'oeil. So, there are pilasters, and pediments, and niches, and trophies, and medallions, and (faux) gilt-bronze vases and garlands, all in grey, lavender, gold, pale green and white. Putti fly and, at the ceiling level a variety of mythological creatures, draped in brightly colored robes hover, holding flowers. All the way at the top, Jason cheerfully slaughters the most appealing of dragons. The exuberance of this decor is as entrancing as its elegance: here, in this vast but amiable room, we feel as if we were attending an 18th-century fete.</p>
        <p>Still, looking is not everything. Perhaps the best way to cap a visit to the city's Baroque masterpieces is a dinner at Del Cambio, a restaurant that faces the Palazzo Carignano. Last decorated in the 1820's, it offers delicious food and dazzling service along with the best local wines.</p>
        <p>Then, when the meal is over, go out on the little Piazza, with palaces on every side, and some of the best architecture anywhere, and you will realize why Victor Emmanuel II, when, in 1861 he became King of Italy, was so reluctant to leave Turin.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO</p>
        <p>Accommodations The best hotel in Turin is the Jolly Principi di Piemonte, 15 Via Gobetti; telephone 519-693. The rooms, vast and comfortable, cost from $198 for a single to $247 for a double.</p>
        <p>Restaurants Following are two of Turin's better restaurants. Prices do not include wine.</p>
        <p>Del Cambio, 2 Piazza Carignano; 546-690. Good northern Italian food with, on Friday, a $100 fixed-price dinner copied from the 19th--century menus of the royal court. Other nights about $57 a person. Closed Sunday and from July 26 to Aug. 28.</p>
        <p>La Vecchia Lanterna, 21 Corso re Umberto; 537-047. The restaurant has a pleasant dining room, and nuova cucina food of very high quality. About $66 to $82 a person.</p>
        <p>Sightseeing Palazzo Madama is closed for renovation.</p>
        <p>Superga is open April 1 to Sept. 30 from 9:30 A.M. to 12:30 P.M. and 2:30 to 6:30 P.M; from Oct. 1 to March 30 from 10 A.M. to 12:30 P.M. and 3 P.M. to 5 P.M. Closed Friday, Jan. 1, Easter Sunday, Christmas Day, Sept. 8, and last two weeks of June. Free. Stupinigi is open Tuesday through Saturday from 9:30 A.M. to 4:50 P.M., on Sunday from 10 A.M. to 12:20 P.M. and 2 to 4:50 P.M. It can only be seen as part of an Italian-speaking guided tour. Admission $3.25. All churches are open every day from 8 to 12:30 P.M. and 4 to 7 P.M.O. B.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
