<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Bush Victory</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="399009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="ESSAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNORS (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SENATE (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUOMO, MARIO M (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRADLEY, BILL (SEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/William Safire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DD173AF93BA35752C1A966958260" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Bush Victory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The only time Richard Nixon quoted Walter Lippmann, not his favorite pundit, was the day after the midterm elections of 1970 in which the Republicans lost nine House seats.</p>
        <p>"Walter Lippmann said that according to the rules of the political game as it has been played in this country for the past 50 years," said the President, reading from some gems of research I had handed him,</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The only time Richard Nixon quoted Walter Lippmann, not his favorite pundit, was the day after the midterm elections of 1970 in which the Republicans lost nine House seats.</p>
        <p>"Walter Lippmann said that according to the rules of the political game as it has been played in this country for the past 50 years," said the President, reading from some gems of research I had handed him,</p>
        <p>"When the party in power loses little if anything in an off-year election, it has to be called a victory."</p>
        <p>History has repeated itself; the party in power in the White House has just lost nine House seats in the midterm election, not the usual 36. Therefore, according to the Lippmann Rule, President Bush has the right to call the 1990 results a victory.</p>
        <p>But just let him try it. The mindset that drives most interpretations of the results envisions a wounded politician in the White House, coattails in tatters and inflated ratings plummeting, his plums ripening for plucking in 1992. Having taken credit for the rain, Mr. Bush is now getting blamed for the drought.</p>
        <p>Clear your mindset. For a man about to be the first to occupy the White House during a wartime recession, George Bush is in pretty good shape.</p>
        <p>In his defining domestic moment, he stripped his party of its philosophy by caving in on his tax pledge -- but disaster did not befall Republicans.</p>
        <p>In pressing the advantage handed them by Desperation Darman, Democratic liberals reverted to the soak-the-rich pitch of their glory days -- but their retreaded fairness issue led to no day of glory.</p>
        <p>In retrospect, Mr. Bush might wish he had stuck to his guns and fought this election on a taxing-vs.-spending theme; most returns show voter displeasure aimed more at increased taxes than unincreased services. But let's keep our sextant fixed on Lipp-mann's guiding star: massive erosion averted is midterm victory.</p>
        <p>Another, crueler adage buttresses this wisdom, which I hope some pundit a generation hence will refer to as the Safire Rule of Relative Positioning:</p>
        <p>No politician is safely a success until all his potential opponents are failures</p>
        <p>. Consider the state of the '92 opposition in light of the '90 results.</p>
        <p>With his campaign coffers overflowing, Mario Cuomo, who in his previous campaign won over 65 percent of the votes for Governor of New York, this time eked out a bare majority over a couple of relatively impoverished opponents; the much-derided Republican, Pierre Rinfret, stunned his scoffers by receiving twice as many votes as the pollsters predicted. The dismal Cuomo showing has forced the Governor's national boosters to eat humble pie with melancholy danish.</p>
        <p>Equally heavily financed Bill Bradley, his aim fixed on the Presidential nomination, took his eye off the tax-cutting ball and dribbled away a big lead in New Jersey against an unknown. His disenthralled supporters say wryly he can no longer depend on a charismatic oratorical style alone.</p>
        <p>Senator Al Gore won handily in Tennessee. But the issue he is counting on to catapult him to the nomination is global warming -- and environmentalists lost their "Big Green" push in California by 2 to 1, which greens everywhere consider a polit-ecological disaster. (However, if it's 90 in the shade in New York on New Year's Day -- keep your eye on Gore.)</p>
        <p>Those eager to proclaim the President damaged in this election should turn to a Lincoln adage:</p>
        <p>You cannot beat somebody with nobody.</p>
        <p>This election may have diminished the Somebody, but it has surely slammed around the Nobodies.</p>
        <p>Perhaps you are unsatisfied with the notion that not losing badly is really winning. Surely you cannot prefer drawing such lessons as "nobody won" or "everybody lost." Does the campaign result have any meaning?</p>
        <p>Yes. Remember how the reformist goo-goos were bewailing the way incumbents could use perks and PAC's to keep themselves entrenched? They were right. And remember how all the pollsters and analysts were telling us how fed up the voters were with the budget messiness? They were right, too.</p>
        <p>The inertial power of incumbency is still the Immovable Object. Resentment of deadlocking and secretive and promise-breaking politicians is the Irresistible Force. In the campaign of 1990, they met. Result: The little loss by the party in power has to be called a victory.</p>
        <p>ESSAY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
