<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reviews/Theater;   A Spoof of the 1950's Moves to Off Broadway</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="356316"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSS, STUART</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FOREVER PLAID (REVUE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D71138F936A15756C0A966958260" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reviews/Theater;   A Spoof of the 1950's Moves to Off Broadway</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: When the Plaids, a mythical 1950's male quartet from eastern Pennsylvania, perform a piece of vintage kitsch like ''Three Coins in the Fountain,'' they don't merely sing it in smooth four-part harmonies that echo the Four Aces; they physically illustrate the lyrics with a painstaking literalness. A line like '</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: When the Plaids, a mythical 1950's male quartet from eastern Pennsylvania, perform a piece of vintage kitsch like ''Three Coins in the Fountain,'' they don't merely sing it in smooth four-part harmonies that echo the Four Aces; they physically illustrate the lyrics with a painstaking literalness. A line like '</p>
        <p>When the Plaids, a mythical 1950's male quartet from eastern Pennsylvania, perform a piece of vintage kitsch like ''Three Coins in the Fountain,'' they don't merely sing it in smooth four-part harmonies that echo the Four Aces; they physically illustrate the lyrics with a painstaking literalness. A line like ''See the ripples, how they shine'' is accompanied by hilariously synchronized arm wrigglings meant to simulate little wavelets.</p>
        <p>This is just the sort of thing that squeaky-clean harmony groups of the 1950's like the Four Lads, the Crew Cuts, the Four Aces and the Ames Brothers actually used to do in their performances. But the Plaids exaggerate it just enough to make it all seem as playfully surreal as their own fateful biography.</p>
        <p>That biography begins in the opening moments of their show, ''Forever Plaid,'' at Steve McGraw's, when the quartet, carrying candles and looking lost and frightened, stumbles into the club, literally from out of the past. It seems that a time warp and a hole in the ozone layer have combined to catapult them 26 years into the future from the moment on Feb. 9, 1964, when they died in a collision with a bus full of parochial-school girls on their way to see the Beatles on ''The Ed Sullivan Show.''</p>
        <p>''Forever Plaid,'' which was written directed and choreographed by Stuart Ross, has had previous lives, in regional theater and as a cabaret revue, but this is the first time it has been an Off Broadway show. Expanded and rewritten from its cabaret version, which opened last year at the same club, it is a thoroughly amusing, lightheaded spoof of the more insipid side of 50's pop culture.</p>
        <p>Over the course of the evening, the group, which sports matching plaid cummerbunds and bow ties, fantasizes the musical career it might have enjoyed had it not been cut short. Among many funny bits, the group offers its version of the Beatles' ''She Loves You'' (in which ''yeah, yeah, yeah'' becomes ''yes siree, Bob'') and tell the story of ''the golden cardigan,'' the sweater that Perry Como left behind after he was stranded in their hometown. The cardigan has become an icon to which the Plaids croon letter-perfect renditions of the Como hits ''Papa Loves Mambo'' and ''Catch a Falling Star.''</p>
        <p>Donning sombreros and playing bongos and maracas, the Plaids also ''go calypso,'' leading the audience through a sing-along of ''Matilida, Matilda,'' under Christmas-tree lighting augmented with bunches of illuminated bananas. The show reaches a pinnacle of goofiness with the group's three-minute capsule version of ''The Ed Sullivan Show.'' In that time, the Plaids become jugglers, fire-eaters, folk dancers, plate-spinners and Judy Garland, all while ''Lady of Spain'' is played on an accordion.</p>
        <p>Underneath its mockery of 50's squareness, ''Forever Plaid'' oozes nostalgia for the decade of the button-down mind and affection for its ultrasanitized pop. Stan Chandler, David Engle, Jason Graae and Guy Stroman, the singers who portray the Plaids, have refined a harmonic blend that is as tonally precise and dynamically controlled as that of any of their 50's antecedents.</p>
        <p>While James Raitt's arrangements do not exactly duplicate those of the original hit records, they offer a skillful pastiche of a style that the Plaids explain they developed at the Osterizer School of Harmonic Theory. It was there that they learned the four basic modes of vocal harmony: blend, puree, mix and chop. This sweet, funny little revue shows them to be more than adept at all four functions.</p>
        <p>Forever Plaid</p>
        <p>Written, directed and staged by Stuart Ross; musical continutiy, arrangements and musical direction, James Raitt; scenery, Neil Peter Jampolis; lighting, Jane Reisman; costumes, Debra Stein; assistant director, Larry Raben. Presented by Gene Wolsk, in association with Steven Suskin. At Steve McGraw's, 158 West 72d Street.</p>
        <p>WITH: Stan Chandler, David Engel, Jason Graae and Guy Stroman.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
