<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ed Woolard Walks Du Pont's Tightrope</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="391090"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLASTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTAINERS AND PACKAGING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DU PONT DE NEMOURS, E I, &amp; CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLUSHA, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WOOLARD, EDGAR S JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DB1338F937A25753C1A966958260" item-length="2988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ed Woolard Walks Du Pont's Tightrope</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN HOLUSHA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLUSHA, JOHN</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A big part of the future of America's largest chemical company can be found on a conveyor belt in an old warehouse here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A big part of the future of America's largest chemical company can be found on a conveyor belt in an old warehouse here.</p>
        <p>A big part of the future of America's largest chemical company can be found on a conveyor belt in an old warehouse here.</p>
        <p>Thousands of crushed, discarded plastic soft-drink bottles rattle down the belt in the Du Pont Company plant. Within a few hours the bottles will be shredded, separated into their two basic plastic components and shipped to other Du Pont plants to be recycled into new products.</p>
        <p>Once, E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company was content to sell the basic resins for the bottles and let someone else worry about what happened to the containers after they were used. Now, with environmental concerns on the rise and opposition to plastic packaging growing, the company is trying to establish itself as a friend of the earth by helping cope with the trash it had a hand in creating.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Edgar S. Woolard Jr., Du Pont's chairman and chief executive since April 1989, has made expressions of concern for the environment one of the hallmarks of his administration. He has referred to himself as the company's chief environmentalist as well as chief executive. And he has established an environmental services division and set targets for the reduction of toxic emissions, spending nearly $1 billion a year on the effort.</p>
        <p>''Our continued existence as a leading manufacturer requires that we excel in environmental performance,'' he said in a speech late last year.</p>
        <p>How well that performance is received by the public, environmentalists and regulators could have enormous consequences for Du Pont and, by implication, for other makers of the industrial world's plastic and chemical building blocks.</p>
        <p>In recycling bottles and other products, Du Pont is trying to combine good works with good business to produce a new source of income that could reach $1 billion a year by the end of the decade. But the company - which by many measures remains one of the nation's biggest polluters - is also trying to show that it is serious about cleaning up its own act. If it fails, it risks tough new regulations and a punishing consumer backlash.</p>
        <p>Mixed Reviews</p>
        <p>It is too early to tell how successful Mr. Woolard ultimately will be. But so far, the effort has drawn mixed reviews. Some environmental groups and industry experts praise Mr. Woolard for his stand. Others, however, say that the company's actions are sharply at odds with his words.</p>
        <p>''I cannot think of a single corporate leader at the level of Ed Woolard who has spoken as consistently on these issues as he has,'' said one supporter, Jay D. Hair, president of the National Wildlife Federation in Washington. ''He understands that in today's public climate, companies have to conduct their affairs in ways that are environmentally acceptable.''</p>
        <p>But some groups charge that the company, which had sales of $36 billion last year, is bypassing environmentally benign technologies to replace chlorofluorocarbons, compounds used in refrigeration and industrial cleaning that pose a hazard to the planet's protective layer of ozone. Instead, the critics say, Du Pont is concentrating on other families of chemicals that pose similar, though lesser, dangers.</p>
        <p>And critics also object to the company's continued use of deep-well injection to dispose of waste products, a process in which toxic materials are pumped thousands of feet into the earth.</p>
        <p>''In a word, no,'' said Rick Hind of the U.S. Public Interest Research Group about whether Du Pont is entitled to depict itself as environmentally concerned. Mr. Hind criticized the company, which is based in Wilmington, Del., for what he said was lobbying to allow continued use of agricultural chemicals linked to cancer and for trying to weaken the Superfund toxic dump cleanup rules.</p>
        <p>''They have all this concern about their image but somehow the reality does not match up,'' added Scott Klinger, an analyst at the Franklin Research and Development Corporation, a Boston-based investment firm that rates companies on their social responsibility. Franklin Research gives Du Pont a neutral ranking.</p>
        <p>Mr. Woolard, a 56-year-old industrial engineer known for his talents in cost-cutting and marketing, is in a tight spot when it comes to the environment, industry experts say.</p>
        <p>With billions invested in production facilities designed in a different era and with customers having billions more tied up in equipment dependent on chemicals like chlorofluorocarbons, he cannot move quickly enough to satisfy the demands of some environmental groups without risking financial disaster, the experts say.</p>
        <p>No Choice</p>
        <p>Yet despite Du Pont's vulnerability to criticism, Mr. Woolard had no choice when he decided to highlight the environmental issue, they add.</p>
        <p>''He cannot keep a low profile on this right now,'' said Leslie C. Ravitz, an analyst with Salomon Brothers. ''If he does not set the right example, people below him will not do what needs to be done, particularly if there is an incremental cost involved.''</p>
        <p>And they should have plenty to do, given the mood of the country about things environmental. For example, a poll conducted earlier this year by the Roper Organization for S. C. Johnson &amp; Son Inc., another maker of chemical products, showed that 72 percent of the respondents favor stiffer regulation of business to reduce pollution.</p>
        <p>In an effort to push responsibility for environmental and other activities further down the organization, Mr. Woolard has just eliminated Du Pont's executive committee structure, which has been in place since 1903. Mr. Woolard, who established an office of the chairman to replace the committee, said executives would now have more autonomy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Woolard says the situation is really quite simple: only business has the technical and financial resources to clean up the environment. ''The environmental groups cannot solve any of these problems,'' he said. ''Governments can't do it. Corporations have to do it.''</p>
        <p>The Cleanup List</p>
        <p>One of the things a corporation named Du Pont is going to have to do, according to Mr. Woolard, is to cut its toxic air emissions 60 percent from 1987 levels by 1993. Emissions of carcinogens are to be cut 90 percent by 2000. That is a tall order, given that Du Pont has been the nation's biggest emitter of toxic chemicals, according to data compiled by the group Citizen Action from reports filed with the Environmental Protection Agency. In 1988, the last year for which figures are available, Du Pont ranked sixth in releases of chemicals linked to birth defects and 10th in emissions of chemicals suspected of causing cancer. Overall, it discharged 338 million pounds of toxic materials that year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Woolard also said the company would stop injecting wastes deep into the ground by the end of the century, even though he stoutly defends the practice as environmentally sound.</p>
        <p>Here again business priorities clash with environmental goals. Du Pont has chemical plants in Texas and Louisiana that were designed to dispose of wastes by pumping them into wells drilled thousands of feet down. Mr. Woolard's plan is gradually to reformulate the production processes at the plants to reduce the amount of waste, rather than install expensive treatment equipment.</p>
        <p>But in the meantime, hundreds of millions of pounds of untreated wastes will be pumped into the ground. Environmentalists view deep-well injection as a loophole in Federal regulations that generally ban the dumping of untreated liquid waste. And some say there is considerable evidence that the wastes migrate from the wells to contaminate drinking water supplies.</p>
        <p>In a study of government documents and scientific literature, chemists at the environmental organization Greenpeace found 39 incidents of problems with deep wells operated by a number of companies - one incident involved Du Pont - in which hazardous materials escaped. According to the study, aquifers were contaminated in 11 instances and drinking water was affected in three.</p>
        <p>''This is a big deal on a regional scale,'' said Joe Thornton, the author of the report and a chemist in Greenpeace's Chicago office. ''It is a real threat to ground water.'' Du Pont responds that it detected the leak at the one company well cited by Greenpeace and repaired the problem without any environmental contamination. More broadly, industry executives argue that monitoring efforts are improving and the large number of wells in operation have a strong safety record.</p>
        <p>The deep-well issue aside, some environmentalists praise Mr. Woolard for seeking to change the industry attitude that some waste is an inevitable part of the production process. ''I believe anything that goes out the waste pipes may well be something that can be recycled, reused or sold,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''That is a brand new thought,'' said David Rowe at the Environmental Defense Fund. ''People used to think that a certain amount of emissions was a necessary part of production. So it is a major contribution.''</p>
        <p>Although it prefers to focus on the future, Du Pont has been forced to acknowledge some mistakes it made in the past. The company has set aside $330 million in the last two years to repair environmental damage at its plant sites and admits there could be ''significant'' additional outlays if more problems are uncovered.</p>
        <p>Nor will those cleanups be over any time soon. The company is pumping water from under its huge Chambers Works complex in southern New Jersey to strip off organic solvents that were released when the company manufactured dyes at the site.</p>
        <p>''We are pumping at Chambers, and we'll probably be doing it for another 10 years,'' Mr. Woolard said.</p>
        <p>Analysts say the company is wise to admit to past pollution problems and to start fixing them. ''The cost of waste disposal is going up geometrically,'' said George Krug, who is with Oppenheimer &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>New Income Stream</p>
        <p>Mr. Woolard thinks Du Pont can make money from the environment as well as spend on it. For one thing, he said, industrial customers who buy the bulk of the company's products have environmental concerns of their own and are eager to deal with technically sophisticated suppliers.</p>
        <p>''Our customers are feeling the pressure and they are saying to us, 'Can you give us more environmentally safe products,' '' Mr. Woolard said. ''They are willing to pay something more to know they have a partner that has excellent technology, is going to stay in business and be there to help them as the environmental problems continue to escalate.''</p>
        <p>The plastic recycling program, which is a joint venture with the nation's largest trash company, Waste Management Inc., is one such effort. The plastic packaging industry in particular is under pressure because its products are highly visible as litter and have little history of recycling. About a dozen communities across the country have voted bans on plastic packaging unless it can be recycled.</p>
        <p>In fact, most plastics are easily recyclable, particularly if the different types can be separated. Du Pont recycles two common plastics at the Philadelphia plant. One is polyethylene terepthalate, known as PET, which is the main portion of large soft-drink bottles. The other is high-density polyethylene, or HDPE, which forms the base of soft-drink bottles and is used in most plastic milk bottles.</p>
        <p>The company has two plastic recycling plants running now - the other is in Chicago - and ultimately plans five, each of which could process 180 million bottles a year. The bottles are ground up and the two plastics are separated in a water bath since HDPE floats while PET is denser than water. The resulting flakes are shipped to other Du Pont plants to be used in products like the company's line of Rynite engineering materials and Selar barrier resins.</p>
        <p>Du Pont does not expect to make a lot of money on the bottles. ''The margins will probably be tight,'' said George F. Schreiber, manager of the recycling operation. ''We hope to break even next year.''</p>
        <p>But the bottle effort is helping to spread the word about the growing applications for recycled plastics and may lead to more business with consumer products companies.</p>
        <p>A Question of Timing</p>
        <p>Perhaps no environmental issue has been more vexatious for the company and more indicative of the bind Mr. Woolard is in than Du Pont's policies on chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists congratulate the company for agreeing to halt production by 2000 after the preponderance of scientific evidence showed the compounds were hazardous to the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>But others criticize Du Pont, which is the world's largest producer of the materials, for not acting sooner. And many have called for an end to CFC production well before 2000 to prevent an increase in skin cancer rates, which have been associated with lessened ozone protection.</p>
        <p>Du Pont executives point out that most existing cooling equipment uses CFC refrigerants and that none of the proposed replacements - including Du Pont's choice of hydrochlorofluorocarbons, or HCFC's - will work without substantial modifications to the equipment.</p>
        <p>''There is $135 billion in air-conditioning and refrigeration equipment in the United States alone,'' said Bruce Karrh, vice president for safety, health and environmental affairs. ''One reason we can't immediately stop making CFC's is that the equipment manufacturers have to make new equipment to use the new products. We think it would be irresponsible if we arbitrarily stopped.'' The company has begun a recycling program, however, to stretch existing supplies as CFC production is cut.</p>
        <p>Du Pont also disagrees with some environmental groups that have called for the early phase-out of HCFC's, which critics complain also deplete the ozone layer. Du Pont says HCFC's pose a minimal danger - they have only a fraction of the ozone-depleting potential of the worst CFC's, it contends - and are by far the most practical replacement for CFC's. While some proposed substitutes are safe for the ozone, they can be corrosive or dangerously volatile, the company says. Moreover, Du Pont argues that because it is planning to invest $1 billion in plants to make the HCFC's, it needs assurances that they can be sold for at least 20 years to earn an adequate return on its investment.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Woolard said he intends to maintain a high profile as an advocate for a cleaner environment. ''It is incumbent on leading businessmen to gain credibility to convince legislators, educators and the public at large that the only way to accomplish these things is through research and technology change,'' he said, adding, ''You cannot do that if they do not trust you.''</p>
        <p>HOW DU PONT DINES ON DETRITUS</p>
        <p>DEEPWATER, N.J.</p>
        <p>Like vast witch's cauldrons, the waste-water treatment tanks at Du Pont's Chambers Works facility here on the southern coast of New Jersey bubble black and ominous. Within them, a combination of activated carbon and microorganisms is absorbing and digesting organic chemicals contaminating the water and purifying it to the point where it can be discharged into Delaware Bay.</p>
        <p>The facility, which can process 40 million gallons a day, is a key part of Du Pont's plans to make money by offering environmental services. The plant was built to handle wastes from the company's dye-making operations here, a business it got out of in 1980.</p>
        <p>To keep the plant running, Du Pont began selling treatment services to outside customers and now has nearly 1,000 accounts ranging in size from the Exxon Corporation to mom-and-pop operations. Each day the plant processes about 100 tank trucks of material, everything from chemical process residues to batches of shampoo that did not meet specifications.</p>
        <p>The microorganisms feed on many of the chemicals in the water and the carbon absorbs many of the others. Periodically the carbon is removed and baked to remove the chemicals and then returned to the treatment tanks.</p>
        <p>There are two main stages of treatment now. Du Pont is spending $160 million to upgrade the plant with a third treatment stage to remove more contaminants.</p>
        <p>In a related move here, the company is spending $125 million to double its capacity to incinerate toxic wastes so it can handle more materials, like paint and paint solvents, that are not suitable for water treatment. It is also expanding a landfill on the 1,400-acre Chambers site to bury the ash left after incineration.</p>
        <p>RECYCLING REFRIGERANTS</p>
        <p>The industrialized nations of the world have agreed to phase out chlorofluorocarbon production within 10 years. But some industrial cooling equipment has a service life of up to 40 years and will not be able to use substitutes being developed for CFC's.</p>
        <p>Du Pont's solution is to recycle existing refrigerants, which grow less effective over time as they become contaminated by lubricating oil and other substances.</p>
        <p>The company will buy back common refrigerants like CFC 11 and 12 for $5 to $10 a gallon in minimum amounts of 500 pounds. (A typical car air-conditioner has about three pounds of refrigerant; a supermarket chilling system, on the order of 2,000.) The material is reprocessed by distillation. Du Pont is using the reclaimed material in its internal operations now, but wants to start selling it to outside customers as volumes grow.</p>
        <p>Du Pont expects interest in recycled refrigerants to increase as declines in production pinch supplies. Demand would also grow if regulations are enacted against venting the materials to the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>''This is a good demonstration of the cradle-to-grave approach,'' said C. D. McCain, manager of the recycling program in Deepwater, N.J. ''We make the original material and we give the user a way to get rid of it.''</p>
        <p>One possible drawback to the operation is the danger that some people will try to slip hazardous materials, such as polychlorinated biphenyls, into the old refrigerant. If contamination is detected, Du Pont will incinerate the batch and charge the sender $1 to $2 a pound for the service.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
