<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="326378"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DF1139F937A25751C0A966958260" item-length="566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Collapse of Drexel</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Collapse of Drexel</p>
        <p>The Collapse of Drexel</p>
        <p>Drexel Burnham Lambert began selling its securities and its parent company filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection. The moves mark the demise of a firm that had come to symbolize the fast-money years on Wall Street. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>It is the end of an era in which speculative debt became Wall Street's stock in trade. Floyd Norris: Market Place. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Unlike banks, securities firms are not answerable to any Government agency with the authority to supervise them in their entirety. News Analysis. [D5.]  The Federal Reserve and S.E.C. worked to limit damage to the financial markets. [D5.]</p>
        <p>Those who have a vested interest in Drexel's fate are scattered across the business landscape. [D5.]  Wall Street firms said they had been flooded with calls from Drexel employees. [D4.]</p>
        <p>Bankruptcy specialists said Drexel was likely to end up liquidating itself. [D4.]</p>
        <p>Markets</p>
        <p>Prices of ''junk bonds'' fell sharply but recovered, and trading was volatile all day. [D5.]</p>
        <p>Reverberations from the Drexel crisis reached the credit markets, where prices of short-term Treasury securities moved higher and bond prices recorded gains of more than half a point. [D14.]  Yields were mixed on C.D.'s and money market accounts. [D14.]</p>
        <p>Stock prices closed mixed on sharply higher volume. The Dow Jones industrial average added 4.96 points, to 2,624.10. [D8.]</p>
        <p>The price of copper futures surged on New York's Commodity Exchange. [D16.]  The dollar was mostly higher. [D16.]</p>
        <p>Companies</p>
        <p>Chrysler lost $664 million in the fourth quarter and its profits fell 65.8 percent for the year.[D1.]</p>
        <p>Forstmann Little and Allen E. Paulson bought Gulfstream Aerospace from Chrysler for $825 million in cash. Mr. Paulson sold Gulfstream to Chrysler in 1985 for $637 million. [D1.]</p>
        <p>Bertelsmann is believed to be close to selling its 39 Doubleday Book Shops to Barnes &amp; Noble/B. Dalton. [D1.]</p>
        <p>VMS Partners said many of its commercial properties were so troubled that it had no choice but to stop paying certain bills. [D1.]</p>
        <p>Integrated Resources filed for bankruptcy protection under Chapter 11 of the Federal Bankruptcy Code. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Great Northern Nekoosa is putting itself up for sale, the latest step in its attempts to fend off Georgia-Pacific. [D6.]</p>
        <p>A Public Service Commission audit found that New York Telephone overpaid the purchasing division of its parent, Nynex. [D20.]</p>
        <p>First Executive formally rejected a $6-a-share offer from Rosewood Financial, its largest shareholder. [D6.]</p>
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>After an extensive study of airline competition, the Government concluded that there was no cause for alarm in the shrinking number of major airlines. [D1.]</p>
        <p>Retail sales rose a strong 1.6 percent in January, the sharpest gain in more than a year. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Technology</p>
        <p>Six months behind schedule, McDonnell Douglas began flight tests of the jumbo jet on which its future rides. [D7.]</p>
        <p>A computerized shadow-boxing system allows two people to square off without hurting each other. [D7.]</p>
        <p>Today's Columns</p>
        <p>For President Bush, global warming has become another of the universe's great mysteries. Peter Passell: Economic Scene. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Former Surgeon General Koop called for a ban on broadcast beer and wine ads. Randall Rothenberg: Advertising. [D18.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
