<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SCIENTISTS REPORT FASTER OZONE LOSS</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="363434"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDF123FF937A15755C0A966958260" item-length="741" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SCIENTISTS REPORT FASTER OZONE LOSS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: New scientific evidence that the earth's ozone layer is being destroyed more quickly than previously reported is being presented in London to negotiators working on a treaty to speed the elimination of chemicals that cause the problem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: New scientific evidence that the earth's ozone layer is being destroyed more quickly than previously reported is being presented in London to negotiators working on a treaty to speed the elimination of chemicals that cause the problem.</p>
        <p>New scientific evidence that the earth's ozone layer is being destroyed more quickly than previously reported is being presented in London to negotiators working on a treaty to speed the elimination of chemicals that cause the problem.</p>
        <p>A report by Ivar S. A. Isaksen of Norway's Institute of Geophysics says balloon observations in the lower stratosphere show a 10 percent reduction in ozone since 1967 over the middle latitudes of Europe and North America. The observations were made over Switzerland, Germany and Canada.</p>
        <p>The lower stratosphere is where industrial chemicals containing chlorine, including chlorofluorocarbons, halons, carbon tetrachloride and methyl chloroform, react on the surface of ice and dust crystals and destroy ozone molecules. Ozone in the atmosphere shields the earth's surface from excessive ultraviolet radiation from the sun, which has been found to cause skin cancer, cataracts and suppression of the immune system in human beings. The radiation also harms wildlife and crops.</p>
        <p>More Rapid Loss Feared</p>
        <p>Last year scientists convened by the United Nations Environment Program reported that ozone throughout the atmosphere had been depleted by 3 percent to 5.5 percent over the mid-latitudes in winter. The readings reported by Dr. Isaksen, who is a member of the international group of scientists that has been studying the problem, suggests that the loss of ozone may be even more rapid than that.</p>
        <p>Dr. Susan Solomon, an atmospheric chemist with the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration who is an expert on ozone depletion, said in a telephone interview that Dr. Isaksen's figures were consistent with recent data from satellite measurements.</p>
        <p>Although the loss of ozone has been most pronounced at the poles, particularly over Antarctica, where a loss of 50 percent has been reported, Dr. Isaksen reported that new satellite measurements had found a 3 percent loss over the equator over the last 10 years. That is where the rate of depletion is supposed to be the smallest.</p>
        <p>The new findings could affect the deliberations of the negotiators in London, who are now preparing to strengthen an existing treaty to reduce the production and use of chlorofluorocarbons and other ozone-depleting chemicals. Fifty-six nations are now parties to a treaty, signed in Montreal in September 1987, that requires them to reduce their production and use of chlorofluorocarbons by 50 percent by 2000.</p>
        <p>Complete Ban Urged</p>
        <p>Shortly after that agreement was reached, however, new scientific data emerged showing that the loss of ozone was greater than estimated; that led to calls for strengthening the treaty. As negotiators prepare for meeting of ministers of the treaty nations next week, a consensus has already been reached that chlorofluorocarbons should be phased out completely by 2000 and other chemicals should be reduced.</p>
        <p>But there is disagreement over how fast the chlorofluorocarbons should be phased out and to what extent the other chemicals should be eliminated.</p>
        <p>The United States and several other countries, including Japan and the Soviet Union, support a schedule that would require chlorofluorocarbon production to be reduced by 20 percent by 1993, 85 percent by 1997 and 100 percent by 2000. The European Community is pressing for quicker phaseout that would require production to be cut by 50 percent in the period from 1991 to 1992, by 85 percent between 1995 and 1996 and 100 percent by 1997 to 2000. Several countries, including Norway, Australia, New Zealand and Austria are calling for an even more rapid schedule that would eliminate chlorofluorocarbon production entirely by 1997.</p>
        <p>Treaty Seen as Inadequate</p>
        <p>An analysis by scientists for Friends of the Earth, an international environmental group, indicates that under the plan supported by the United States ozone-destroying chlorine in the atmosphere would rise by 150 percent over current levels and would not start to decline until approximately 2050.</p>
        <p>David D. Doniger, a lawyer for the Natural Resources Defense Council who is observing the London meeting, said the new data show that unless there is a rapid phaseout of chlorofluorocarbons and other chemicals, the revised treaty could be found to be inadequate ''a month after it is signed.''</p>
        <p>A State Department official said that it was expected that a consensus would be reached without difficulty in London and that a new treaty would be signed next week.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
