<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Book Notes</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="388568"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACQUIRED IMMUNE DEFICIENCY SYNDROME (AIDS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE, EAST</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCDOWELL, EDWIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DB1E3EF930A35753C1A966958260" item-length="707" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Book Notes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Edwin McDowell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCDOWELL, EDWIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>Three Popular Topics</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>Three Popular Topics</p>
        <p>Three Popular Topics</p>
        <p>To judge from books published in the last year, the environment, AIDS and Eastern Europe are much on the mind of authors and publishers.</p>
        <p>All three categories showed big increases since last year, according to figures compiled from the five-volume Subject Guide to Books in Print 1990-91, published by R. R. Bowker.</p>
        <p>More than 390 new titles deal with environmental issues ranging from recycling to deforestation to depletion of the ozone layer. Michael Johnson, a senior editor of the guide, said that no precise comparable figures were available for the previous year, but added that the total of new titles was ''significantly higher'' than in any past year.</p>
        <p>The 107 new titles published about AIDS last year are almost 10 times the figure for 1985, when 11 new titles were published.</p>
        <p>And 242 new titles were published last year about individuals and events in Eastern Europe, a figure that Mr. Johnson said was also unusually high in comparison with past years. While these include scholarly books from university presses, much of the increase is from commercial publishing houses responding to the changes that have swept that part of the world.</p>
        <p>In all, the Subject Guide lists 855,000 titles in print under 66,000 subject headings, including such new categories as Leveraged Buyouts, Insider Trading in Securities, and Nudity in the Performing Arts.</p>
        <p>For Aid to the Arts</p>
        <p>Speaking of the performing arts, W. W. Norton has signed Prof. Kathleen Sullivan of the Harvard Law School to write a book defending Federal financing of the arts, without restrictions on the artists and institutions receiving funds. Professor Sullivan testified before a Congressional committee and the independent commission appointed this year to re-examine the National Endowment for the Arts, whose financing procedures have come under criticism from Senator Jesse Helms and others. Norton expects to receive the manuscript early next year, for possible publication by the year's end.</p>
        <p>Origin of a Best Seller</p>
        <p>''Wealth Without Risk,'' by Charles J. Givens, has been on the hard-cover best-seller list for 85 weeks and has more than one million copies in print. It originated in a fitness center.</p>
        <p>Three days in a row, while he was riding a stationary bicycle at a fitness center, Fred Hills, a senior editor at Simon &amp; Schuster, saw Mr. Givens talking about personal finance to Bryant Gumble on the ''Today'' show.</p>
        <p>''I wondered when was the last time a financial author was on the 'Today' show three days in a row, and without a book to sell,'' Mr. Hills said. He decided then and there to offer Mr. Givens a book contract, sight unseen, and he soon received approval to offer a $100,000 advance. ''I knew there had to be a good book in there somewhere,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Givens, a wealthy Florida entrepreneur, was not overly impressed with the size of the advance, even after Mr. Hills explained that in publishing terms it was a lot of money for someone who has neither published a book nor submitted a book proposal. But the idea of writing a book appealed to Mr. Givens's entrepreneural spirit, and the author and editor came up with the idea for ''Wealth Without Risk.''</p>
        <p>The book, published in 1989, has never stopped selling. And next month it will be joined by a new book by Mr. Givens, also published by Simon &amp; Schuster, ''Financial Self-Defense.'' It is described as a compilation of strategies to protect consumers against scams, hidden charges and half-truths.</p>
        <p>The Barry Story</p>
        <p>In January, British American will publish ''The Mayor Who Stayed Too Long: The Story of Marion S. Barry,'' by Jonathan I. Z. Agronsky. The author, a longtime Washington journalist, will not only tell the story of Mayor Barry but will also examine the drug problem and black urban leadership in the United States.</p>
        <p>The book is something of a departure for British American Publishing, a Latham, N.Y., house that publishes mainly literary fiction under its own name and under the Paris Review Editions imprint.</p>
        <p>''As a small house, we have the luxury of publishing whatever we want,'' said Bernard F. Conners, the chairman of British American, which publishes about 15 books a year and is distributed by Simon &amp; Schuster.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
