<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="374404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DE173BF934A3575BC0A966958260" item-length="1319" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A2-11</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A2-11</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A2-11</p>
        <p>The United Nations Security Council registered its outrage at Iraq's invasion of Kuwait by ordering a far-reaching trade and financial boycott on both countries.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>A naval blockade of Iraq is being considered by American and British officials. They said that to insure enforcement of the economic sanctions on Iraq they would be prepared to organize such a blockade.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.S. acts to raise Mideast strength</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Reporter's Notebook: A dervish Bush whirls even faster</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Iraq drastically cut the flow of oil through twin pipelines that cross southern Turkey and normally carry more than half its total oil exports. The country apparently is already feeling the effects of an American-orchestrated boycott.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>After years of discreet trade-offs, U.S. tests the Saudis</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Oil prices rose sharply again and financial markets around the world tumbled as the international embargo against oil from Iraq and Kuwait appeared to be taking hold.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Cutting budget gap now discounted</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Hundreds of Westerners in Kuwait, including at least 28 American citizens, were rounded up by Iraqi soldiers. It was not known what Iraq planned to do with them.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>National elections in the Germanys may be moved up because of the East German Prime Minister's realization that reunification will cost far more than expected and that monetary union has not slowed East Germany's economic decline.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Serb minority bucks Croatian rule</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Pakistan's Government collapsed. Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto, the first woman to head a modern Islamic state, was dismissed by the President, who accused her administration of corruption, nepotism and other illegal acts.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Indian soldiers seize 12 leaders of Kashmir's separatists</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>U.S. and Vietnam hold talks on Cambodia</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>A Liberian rebel leader seized about a dozen foreigners, including an American, as hostages from a hotel outside Monrovia, the State Department said. The hostages, all men, were said to be unharmed.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Slaying of two Jews stirs violence in Jerusalem</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Mauthausen Journal: Gypsies visit a death camp</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>National</p>
        <p>A12-17, A20, B5</p>
        <p>A large incineration of dioxin will soon be held in Jacksonville, Ark., unless a small, determined band of residents have their way. A state contractor plans to burn 28,500 barrels of toxic waste, including dioxin, at an abandoned pesticide plant.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Midland Journal: Residents of the West Texas town who make their living directly or indirectly from oil say they are not nearly as happy about Iraq's invasion of Kuwait as they assume the rest of the country assumes they are.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>The Lieutenant Governor of Georgia, Zell Miller, is the heavy favorite in the runoff for the Democratic gubernatorial nomination. In recent polls, he has held a lead of up to 20 percentage points over the former Mayor of Atlanta, Andrew Young.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>A stance favoring abortion rights by the American Bar Association should be abandoned, lawyers at the association's annual meeting said. They called upon the group's policymaking body to return to neutrality on the issue.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Advocates for people with AIDS are expressing concern that the public is growing weary of hearing about the disease and that a sense of alarm has given way to a resigned acceptance, making it harder to raise badly needed private funds.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Large amounts of housing money have been pledged by Congress this year to strengthen current programs and to create new ones. The bills follow a decade in which Federal housing programs stagnated.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Approval for some bank mergers has been withheld by Federal regulators in recent months until the companies agreed to improve service to poor neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>States raised taxes by $7.6 billion in 1990, study finds</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Jury in Barry trial deliberates all day; reaches no verdict</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Audit is ordered of church funds</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>To young Milwaukee drivers, cruising ban is un-American</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Bodyguard guilty in drug killing</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>Regional</p>
        <p>B1-5</p>
        <p>More than 1,000 new police officers are to be hired by next spring to increase neighborhood foot patrols in New York City, Mayor Dinkins said. He said the city would pay for the move by cutting other services.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>An infant was shot in the head in Manhattan when a bullet tore through an apartment wall as he lay sleeping in bed with his grandmother, the police said. He was in stable condition.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Only three weapons were turned in -all by one person - on the first day of an amnesty program for people with illegal guns in New York City.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Six felonies in eight hours linked to one gunman</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Man fatally shot in argument over a pay phone</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>A mother is removed from jogger trial</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>A Westchester County Court judge dismissed a murder indictment against Carolyn Warmus, a 26-year-old teacher accused of killing her lover's wife, saying the district attorney's office had manipulated the grand jury.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>The East Tremont neighborhood of the Bronx seems to be on the mend. By the hundreds, people have begun moving into buildings being reconstructed under New York City's 10-year, $5.1 billion plan to create new and affordable housing.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>People accused of drunken driving are not entitled to jury trials, the New Jersey Supreme Court ruled, even though those convicted for the third time can be jailed for six months, fined $1,000 and lose their licenses for 10 years.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>The tax revolt in New Jersey, up to now a citizens' protest with no recourse in this non-election year, is reverberating in both the Legislature and the Governor's office, and Democrats now fear it could carry into next year's legislative elections.</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Riverside Church picks unionist as No. 2 minister</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>Coast Guard blames new carelessness for spills</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Science Times</p>
        <p>Drug trials are moving abroad as cost rises in the U. S.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Using physics and computers to create aquatic thrills</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Violent outbursts now being attributed to brain damage</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Swedish tree rings put global warming in perspective</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Magellan nears Venus in trip to map the planet's surface</p>
        <p>C10</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>High technology and the movies</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>Smithsonian faces uncertain future</p>
        <p>C14</p>
        <p>Theater: ''Los Rayos Gamma''</p>
        <p>C11</p>
        <p>Music: ''Ariadne'' in Santa Fe</p>
        <p>C13</p>
        <p>Word and Image: Two van Gogh books</p>
        <p>C16</p>
        <p>Obituaries</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>O. B. Hardison Jr., author and head of Folger Library</p>
        <p>Harold E. Beste, electronics researcher and engineer</p>
        <p>Fashion Page</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>Clothes that can pack up and go</p>
        <p>Sports</p>
        <p>Baseball: Mets let Cardinals take another</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Palmer and Morgan inducted into Hall of Fame</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>Column: Rhoden on Cool Papa Bell</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Football: Jets list two new starters</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Strategy for the gulf crisis</p>
        <p>Embargo and economic fallout</p>
        <p>Fighting crime, and fear</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>William Safire: Now or later?</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Gary Hart: Ill equipped for the crises of the 90's</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Hal Lux: Today's fast track - bankruptcy</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Stuart M. Butler: No truce in the war on poverty</p>
        <p>A19</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
