<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Northeast, a Battle Over Fuel</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="315097"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEATING FUEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PIPELINES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORTHEASTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DD1339F93BA35752C0A966958260" item-length="1774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Northeast, a Battle Over Fuel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>SHELTON, Conn.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: An energy war is taking shape, as the owners of giant natural gas reserves in the Canadian Rockies prepare to challenge the oil barons from Houston to Riyadh. The battleground is the Northeast - the part of the country most reliant on fuel oil.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: An energy war is taking shape, as the owners of giant natural gas reserves in the Canadian Rockies prepare to challenge the oil barons from Houston to Riyadh. The battleground is the Northeast - the part of the country most reliant on fuel oil.</p>
        <p>An energy war is taking shape, as the owners of giant natural gas reserves in the Canadian Rockies prepare to challenge the oil barons from Houston to Riyadh. The battleground is the Northeast - the part of the country most reliant on fuel oil.</p>
        <p>At a time when American oil production is declining, dependence on imported oil is growing and worries about the environment are pervasive, many analysts point to the advantages of natural gas.</p>
        <p>It is, they say, a fuel that is clean and easier to find in North America than oil. They predict that despite a complex, cumbersome procedure for building new pipelines, gas will substitute for oil and coal in generating power, heating homes and firing industrial plants.</p>
        <p>Price Rises Will Moderate</p>
        <p>And as the ability grows to substitute one fuel for the other, sharp jumps in the price of energy will moderate, experts say. In addition, new supplies of natural gas could provide some protection against disruption caused by embargo or war.</p>
        <p>The pipeline partnership based here could transform the Northeast from a gas-supply backwater at the end of a pipeline from the Gulf of Mexico to a player in the middle, poised comfortably between supplies from the Gulf and the Midwest and the Canadian Rockies. It is rapidly winning Government approvals for the largest of 18 new or improved pipelines that within two years could increase the amount of gas available in the region by one-third, a rise unprecedented in the last three decades.</p>
        <p>But the prospect of a switch to gas has led fuel oil dealers to mount a campaign to show that if a pipeline is underused and therefore less efficient, the cost will fall mostly on consumers. The oil dealers are protesting in part because they are worried about losing customers.</p>
        <p>The biggest of the gas pipeline projects in the Northeast would run from Alberta, Canada, to Long Island and Boston. The main leg, the 369-mile, $523.7 million Iroquois pipeline, would carry enough gas to the New York metropolitan area to create three times as much electricity as the mothballed Shoreham nuclear plant would have provided. The amount would be 578 million cubic feet a day.</p>
        <p>'Last Stronghold' for Oil</p>
        <p>''This area is the last stronghold for heating oil,'' said Robert J. Reid, a Canadian pipeline engineer who is president of Iroquois Gas Transmission System, a consortium of 21 Canadian and American companies. One reason is that oil from Gulf Coast or Caribbean refineries is easy to transport by tanker to New York and Boston, and in barges up the Hudson and Connecticut rivers.</p>
        <p>If it were used exclusively in homes, gas from the Iroquois pipeline could meet the energy needs of one million of them, he said. If the gas replaced oil, it would displace more than 30 million barrels a year, assuming that the pipeline averages 80 percent of capacity, as its sponsors say it will. (In practice, experts expect that much of the new supplies will meet growth, thus preventing increases in oil imports.) Mr. Reid said the project, scheduled for completion in 1991, could be doubled in capacity by adding compressor stations.</p>
        <p>Aided by Federal Policy</p>
        <p>The Iroquois pipeline and the other projects that would increase gas deliveries in the Northeast are the result of a policy set in motion in the summer of 1987 by the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission to stimulate pipeline construction. The commission declared an ''open season'' for pipeline applications in the Northeast, then urged applicants to merge their projects to eliminate competing proposals.</p>
        <p>Last January, the commission tentatively approved Iroquois, which would run from Waddington, N.Y., on the St. Lawrence River, under the Hudson near the bridge that carries Interstate 84, through the southwest quarter of Connecticut, and from Milford across Long Island Sound to Huntington, L.I.</p>
        <p>The commission also approved a proposed Champlain pipeline, which would run 340 miles from the Canadian border near Philipsburg, Quebec, through Vermont, New Hampshire and Massachusetts, ending near Boston. But the sponsors of that project have put it on hold. As Iroquois's prospects became stronger, potential suppliers for Champlain dried up, largely because of peculiarities in the system used to set prices on the Trans-Canada pipeline, which would supply both projects. #18 Projects Cleared In all, 18 projects received preliminary approval from the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission. The projects carry a total of three billion cubic feet a day of new capacity, said Robert H. Schroeder, chief of the market analysis branch at the commission. Some of the pipelines will replace old equipment, and not all of the pipelines will be built, but Mr. Schroeder and other experts expect that the net effect will be to add one-third to existing transmission capacity in Pennsylvania, New Jersey, New York and the six New England states.</p>
        <p>The new pipelines are part of a major shift, according to the natural gas industry. George H. Lawrence, president of the American Gas Association, an industry trade group based in Washington, predicted in an interview that gas consumption nationwide would rise by one-third over the next 20 years. Gas's share of the national energy market - including vehicle fuel - will grow by four percentage points, to about 28 percent, at the expense of oil and coal, he said. The Northeast, he added, is ''basically deficient in gas.''</p>
        <p>Environmental Factors</p>
        <p>Producers are especially eager to enter the Northeast market because there is so much oil to displace and because environmental considerations could require energy users to burn gas instead of coal or oil. To curb air pollution, some coal-burning power plants may switch to gas, or burn a mixture of 15 percent gas and 85 percent coal, a technique called co-firing that raises combustion temperature and reduces formation of pollutants. And by early in the next century, a number of fleet vehicles could be running on natural gas.</p>
        <p>Even without those changes, many see a strong demand for gas. Charles W. Linderman, manager of fossil fuels at the Edison Electric Institute, a Washington trade association of investor-owned utilities, said in an interview, ''There is no question in the minds of anyone I know in the electric business or gas business that the gas capacity in the pipelines up there is not adequate to meet demand.''</p>
        <p>The electricity industry is particularly interested in the gas supply because most of the power plants under construction or planned in New York and New England are turbines meant to run on heating oil or natural gas, whichever is available. Electric demand in the region is near the limits of the generating equipment and is expected to rise.</p>
        <p>Four of the user-owners of the Iroquois pipeline are independent power producers, which will burn the gas to make electricity.</p>
        <p>Cleared in New York</p>
        <p>The Iroquois expansion has won approval from some major regulatory agencies, including the New York State Public Service Commission. The New York Power Authority, which burns gas to make electricity, also endorses the project, and has bought 2 percent of Iroquois.</p>
        <p>Iroquois, the commission said, would give New York access to Canadian gas fields with much larger reserves. If drillers never discovered another cubic foot of gas, Canadian reserves would last 30 years at current rates of production; Gulf Coast reserves would last only seven or eight years.</p>
        <p>But fuel oil dealers are objecting, and campaigning to show that if the pipeline is underused and therefore unsuccessful, the cost will fall mostly on consumers.</p>
        <p>''From Alberta to New York, 90 percent of the cost is fixed cost,'' said a consultant hired by heating oil dealers, Robert Means, who is a former director of the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission's Office of Regulatory Analysis. Fixed costs must be paid no matter how much the pipeline is used, and if the pipeline runs at less than the 80 percent capacity projected by its sponsors, the fixed costs will be spread over fewer cubic feet of gas, raising costs, he said.</p>
        <p>Even if the pipeline is fully used, the oil dealers say, construction will still hurt consumers unless Iroquois is serving new demand. Otherwise, they argue, the new pipeline will simply drain traffic from older pipelines, making them less efficient and raising costs for consumers.</p>
        <p>Some gas experts think the oil dealers might have a point. ''It's hard to say that Iroquois is not going to displace some other gas supplies,'' said George E. Briden, director of interstate gas supply at Equitrans Inc., a pipeline company operating in Pennsylvania and West Virginia. ''I don't think it will be one-for-one, but it would test anyone's credibility to make the claim that it won't displace any.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Briden added, however, that ''supply will create its own demand.''</p>
        <p>The fuel oil dealers worry that if new supplies of gas are made available, gas utilities will aggressively promote sales, with rebates or low-interest loans for homeowners who want to convert their furnaces, and inducements to developers.</p>
        <p>''Once they convert to gas,'' Mr. Greenes said, ''they never switch back.''</p>
        <p>The oil dealers' target audience is the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, which must grant final permission for the Iroquois. The commission would set the rates that would determine how the risk is shared among the pipeline owners and customers.</p>
        <p>In this case, however, the analysis is more complicated because those two groups overlap; the Brooklyn Union Gas Company owns 11.1 percent, the Southern Connecticut Gas Company owns 2.4 percent, and the Connecticut Natural Gas Corporation owns 2.4 percent of Iroquois. If the pipeline is underused, raising costs for those companies buying the gas it carries, the cost would be passed through to homeowners and other retail customers in most cases.</p>
        <p>The pipeline owners also bear some risk, however. Under the standard Federal Energy Regulatory Commission rules, pipelines can bill customers for ''capacity'' charges, whether they ship gas or not, and for charges based on volume. The capacity charges would cover interest on the debt financing - the source of 75 percent of the capital - and return on equity over 20 years. But profit on the equity portion would come from charges for gas shipped.</p>
        <p>The other partners include Trans Canada Pipelines (29 percent), Tennessee Gas Pipeline (12.8 percent), Yankee Energy Systems (10.3 percent), CNG Transmission (6.4 percent), Texas Eastern Transmission (6.4 percent), ANR Pipeline (6.4 percent), AEC Pipelines (6 percent), New Jersey Resources (2.4 percent) and J. Makowski (2.4 percent).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
