<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Israelis Devise Plastic Suit as Shield Against Iraqi Gas</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="380031"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="CONFRONTATION IN THE GULF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICAL WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLASTICS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D61F39F93BA1575BC0A966958260" item-length="1042" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Israelis Devise Plastic Suit as Shield Against Iraqi Gas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SABRA CHARTRAND, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>KIBBUTZ HAZOREA, Israel, Aug. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Hadar Polak was ambling past a bicycle rack, looking like a primitive astronaut in the plastic chemical warfare protection suit he was demonstrating, when a friend drove past and shouted at him, ''Don't publicize our factory too much, or we'll be Saddam Hussein's No. 1 target!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Hadar Polak was ambling past a bicycle rack, looking like a primitive astronaut in the plastic chemical warfare protection suit he was demonstrating, when a friend drove past and shouted at him, ''Don't publicize our factory too much, or we'll be Saddam Hussein's No. 1 target!''</p>
        <p>Hadar Polak was ambling past a bicycle rack, looking like a primitive astronaut in the plastic chemical warfare protection suit he was demonstrating, when a friend drove past and shouted at him, ''Don't publicize our factory too much, or we'll be Saddam Hussein's No. 1 target!''</p>
        <p>Mr. Polak's factory is a large plastics plant on this kibbutz in the center of Israel, near Megiddo. In one corner of the huge complex, kibbutz engineers have taken a design for nylon food wrap and developed a thin sheet of plastic that is resistant to mustard gas.</p>
        <p>The plastic is used to make protective suits - pants, hooded jackets and gloves - for soldiers, firefighters and first aid and emergency workers to wear in the event of a chemical-weapons attack. Kibbutz Hazorea has been selling the plastic to the Israeli Defense Ministry for several years.</p>
        <p>A Western Customer</p>
        <p>Now the kibbutz and the ministry say a Western army deployed in the Persian Gulf has asked how long it would take to deliver $3 million worth of the suits. They refuse to say which Western army is involved, but $3 million would buy more than 30,000 suits. And no one but the United States has that many soldiers in the gulf.</p>
        <p>Kibbutz Hazorea is one of several subcontractors employed by the Defense Ministry to produce an array of chemical-warfare defense gear -gas masks, protective clothing, antidote drugs, chemical-detection sensors and alarms, mobile laboratories and decontamination equipment.</p>
        <p>The Government has been amassing this defensive equipment since the 1960's. Stockpiling began in earnest after the 1967 war, when the Israeli Army captured Egyptian chemical-weapons stores in the Sinai desert and got a look at what they might be up against in the years ahead.</p>
        <p>The military now says it has several million gas masks and anti-chemical weapons kits, which include antidote syringes, detection litmus paper and decontamination powder. It says its stockpile is sufficient for each person in Israel and that it is still trying to obtain enough similar protective gear for Palestinians in the occupied territories.</p>
        <p>Again Prepared for War</p>
        <p>Still, even knowing that the protective equipment is at hand, a low-level sense of fear permeates Israel these days. For almost 40 years, Israelis have been told to keep the millions of bunkers that dot the country ready for war. At the first word of enemy bombs, they are to scurry into the subterranean shelters that are a mandatory part of every home built since 1956.</p>
        <p>Now suddenly, the menace of Iraq's chemical weapons has sent Israelis looking for safety as high above the ground as possible - away from heavy gases that, after detonation, fall quickly to the earth.</p>
        <p>The army says casualties can be reduced 50 times if civilians and soldiers put on gas masks within 30 seconds of a chemical attack. But this means that the military's untested mask distribution plans, chemical detectors and monitors have to be in place and working smoothly.</p>
        <p>The military has been hesitant to hand out the masks before an attack is immiment because it says people will not take proper care of them. But public awareness of ways to deal with chemical weapons is mounting. The Education Ministry just announced that Israel's schools would conduct gas-mask drills and teach a million schoolchildren how to respond to attack. Newspapers have published the Civil Defense Authority's emergency guidelines, including an English translation in The Jerusalem Post on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Work Proves Enriching</p>
        <p>At Kibbutz Hazorea, members of the collective who work in the factory say producing the protective plastic suits helps reduce their own fears.</p>
        <p>''We can see that we are making something which will cut down the affect of chemical weapons,'' says Rami Harpaz, the factory's general manager. ''And at a time like this, the fact that we are working and contributing to the defense effort helps us stay calm and keep things in perspective.''</p>
        <p>The plastic sheets that are ultimately cut into the protective suit pattern and then sewn together with heat seals roll off a huge machine not far from a sign that declares: ''We work here without defects.'' Each sheet is one-tenth of a millimeter thick and looks and feels like ordinary transparent plastic.</p>
        <p>''Regular plastic doesn't stop gases from going through,'' says one of the suit's designers, Yiftah Nir. ''Our suit is a combination of materials. The plastic in the middle is a barrier material that prevents the gases from penetrating; then there are two adhesive layers, and two heat-sealing layers.''</p>
        <p>Greenhouse Effect</p>
        <p>The suit has been tested with mustard gas in a Defense Ministry laboratory, and for wear and comfort by kibbutz members. Mr. Harpaz says the pants, jacket and gloves passed the gas test. But the wearer is dreadfully uncomfortable after only about 20 minutes.</p>
        <p>''The problem of the suit is it doesn't breathe, so you start to sweat to death pretty quick,'' Mr. Harpaz said. ''You really can't wear it any longer than two hours, although in our tests the suits stands up for at least six hours.''</p>
        <p>With a pause and a smile he added: ''It might last longer than that, but our members who test it only work six-hour shifts. After that, they take the suit off and go home.''</p>
        <p>Outside, after about five minutes, the sample suit worn by Hadar Polak started to look like the windows of a greenhouse. The plastic steamed up, and condensation began rolling down the inside. Mr. Polak's face was drenched. Consider the Alternative. . .  ''I'd wear this thing if there was a war,'' he said. ''I wouldn't have any choice. But I'd be very unhappy. It's really uncomfortable, really hot.''</p>
        <p>Many of the firefighters, first aid workers and volunteers who are expected to help Israelis recover from a chemical warfare attack will suffer the same discomfort. The suit may protect them from chemical fallout, but it will make firefighting, clearing rubble and aiding the injured difficult at best. And American soldiers serving in Saudi Arabia, where the temperatures are even higher, will be no less uncomfortable.</p>
        <p>''It's hot, but not any hotter than army gear and a helmet,'' said Eliezer Shurow, a kibbutz member. Then he added: ''Well, I'd rather be hot than - you know.''  CONFRONTATION IN THE GULF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
