<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Don't Count on Carbon Dioxide to 'Enrich' the Earth;   What Plant Growth?</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="356131"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDF1238F937A15756C0A966958260" item-length="671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Don't Count on Carbon Dioxide to 'Enrich' the Earth;   What Plant Growth?</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Sherwood B. Idso (letter, May 7) criticizes Senator Al Gore's Earth Day article (''To Skeptics on Global Warming . . .,'' Op-Ed, April 22), in which the Senator called attention to the problems of a rapid warming of the earth caused by the accumulation of heat-trapping gases in the atmosphere. Mr. Idso bases his criticism heavily on Senator Gore's interpretation of the data from the Vostoc ice core, a 160,000-year record of temperature and atmospheric carbon dioxide and methane concentrations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Idso claims that the data show the earth was not responsive to changes in the carbon dioxide concentration during that period. He suggests further that the benefits of increased carbon dioxide outweigh any disadvantages. He contends the principal benefit is the stimulation of growth of plants by the enhanced carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The Vostoc core data show that over 160,000 years temperature and concentrations of carbon dioxide and methane, the principal heat-trapping gases of concern, marched in lockstep: as temperature increased, so did the concentrations of those gases; as temperature dropped, so did the concentrations of the gases drop.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Idso is correct that it is not possible to infer cause and effect from this record and that the several reversals of the temperature trend are thought to have been caused by changes in the amount of solar energy received on earth, he has overlooked the single point that is certain: the dominant pattern over 160,000 years of glacial time was inconsistent with his hypothesis.</p>
        <p>As temperatures and the concentration of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere rose in the past, there was no great surge in plant growth. Had there been the surge that he sees as so promising, the concentration of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere would not have continued to climb. The carbon would have been sequestered in plants and soil. Any benefit in the realm that Mr. Idso claims was certainly small. The dominant influence throughout the 160,000 years was one in which a warming made more carbon dioxide and methane; a cooling resulted in the removal of those gases from the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The atmosphere now contains about 355 parts per million of carbon dioxide. The highest concentration in the previous record was about 280 p.p.m. While many factors affect earth's temperatures, there is little question as to whether heat-trapping gases like carbon dioxide and methane trap heat. They do. Nor is there doubt as to whether the addition of these gases to the atmosphere will warm the earth. It will. Whether that influence will dominate in the near future remains a question, but the continued accumulation of such gases assures that the time when their influence will become dominant, if it is not clear already, is rapidly drawing closer.</p>
        <p>While there are experimental data supporting Mr. Idso's assertions about the advantages of increased concentrations of carbon dioxide to certain plants, there are no data showing that the 25 percent increase in the concentration of carbon dioxide over the last century has been a boon to agriculture or resulted in any enhanced growth of trees or other plants. His assertions are unjustifiably optimistic and misleading in suggesting that the human environment will benefit from enhanced carbon dioxide in the atmosphere. It will not.</p>
        <p>When the effects of further rapid warming of the earth are incorporated into the calculus that Mr. Idso advances, the problems become far more serious for agriculture. Increases in temperature result in more rapid evaporation of water and a reduction in soil moisture. Warmer is drier. The hot dry summer of 1988 reduced the United States grain crop by 30 percent, a grim reminder that the warming of an earth now populated by 5.3 billion people holds large risks that will not be mitigated by the marginal and so far ephemeral advantages Mr. Idso advances as important.</p>
        <p>GEORGE M. WOODWELL</p>
        <p>Dir., Woods Hole Research Center</p>
        <p>Woods Hole, Mass., May 10, 1990</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
