<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>United Parcel to Alter Its Trucks In Los Angeles to Use Natural Gas</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="367382"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOG</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRUCKS AND TRUCKING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES (CALIF)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED PARCEL SERVICE OF AMERICA INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENSON, RICHARD W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DE133FF932A25754C0A966958260" item-length="1127" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>United Parcel to Alter Its Trucks In Los Angeles to Use Natural Gas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENSON, RICHARD W</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, July 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The United Parcel Service said today that it planned to convert its 2,700 delivery trucks in the smog-choked Los Angeles area to run on cleaner-burning natural gas in the first major step by a company to comply with strict new vehicle-emissions laws here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The United Parcel Service said today that it planned to convert its 2,700 delivery trucks in the smog-choked Los Angeles area to run on cleaner-burning natural gas in the first major step by a company to comply with strict new vehicle-emissions laws here.</p>
        <p>The United Parcel Service said today that it planned to convert its 2,700 delivery trucks in the smog-choked Los Angeles area to run on cleaner-burning natural gas in the first major step by a company to comply with strict new vehicle-emissions laws here.</p>
        <p>The action by United Parcel, which operates one of the nation's largest truck fleets, was applauded by local officials as evidence that the region's new anti-smog rules, the nation's toughest, can be met on schedule and as evidence that Southern California can be a model for nationwide efforts to improve air quality.</p>
        <p>''This is a major breakthrough in alternative fuels that we think will be a harbinger of things to come,'' Mayor Tom Bradley said at a news conference announcing the company's plan.</p>
        <p>Plan for the Next Century</p>
        <p>The Los Angeles basin has more than 7.5 million vehicles and suffers from the worst smog problem in the country, with air quality failing to meet Federal standards more than half the days of the year. Air quality regulators last year approved a plan calling for 40 percent of cars and 70 percent of trucks in the region to run on cleaner fuels like natural gas, methanol and electricity by 1998. By 2007, the plan calls for all vehicles to use such alternative fuels.</p>
        <p>United Parcel will begin by converting 20 trucks in conjunction with the Southern California Gas Company and operating them, starting early next year, in downtown Los Angeles. Assuming the initial conversions work as expected, the company and Government officials said, United Parcel would convert the rest of its more than 2,000 gasoline-powered trucks in the next five years, followed by several hundred diesel-powered vehicles.</p>
        <p>Siro DeGasperis, a vice president of United Parcel, said the company eventually plans to convert to natural gas all its trucks in cities with air problems. He said such a shift would involve about half the company's total fleet of more than 100,000 distinctive brown trucks. There was no timetable for the changeover, he said.</p>
        <p>Conversion involves installing three cylinders capable of holding 15 gallons of compressed natural gas, enough to drive 60 to 80 miles on city streets, within the daily range of a United Parcel truck in an urban area. The system also requires regulators to reduce the pressure of the gas as it is fed first into a device that mixes the natural gas with air and then into the truck's standard gasoline engine.</p>
        <p>Test Program in Brooklyn</p>
        <p>United Parcel has been running a test program in Brooklyn with the Brooklyn Union Gas Company, involving 10 natural gas-fueled vehicles, and plans to expand the program into Manhattan in conjunction with the Consolidated Edison Company of New York. Mr. DeGasperis said the company is also planning projects soon in Dallas and Houston.</p>
        <p>''Ultimately, nationwide, our goal is to experiment and expand the program to most urban areas with an air quality problem,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In the Brooklyn test, each of the 10 vehicles cost $3,000 to $3,500 to convert to natural gas, with the bulk of the cost paid by Brooklyn Union Gas, Mr. DeGasperis said. He said United Parcel is negotiating with Southern California Gas about sharing the cost of converting the trucks in the Los Angeles program.</p>
        <p>The company also said it is working with the Acurex Corporation of San Francisco to develop a new natural gas-fueled engine specifically for its vehicles.</p>
        <p>In the mid 1970's there were shortages of natural gas in the United States that led to rationing in some Northern and Eastern cities during winter months. But after natural gas prices were deregulated in the Carter Administration, exploration and drilling picked up so much that by the mid-1980's there was an abundant supply of natural gas.</p>
        <p>Industry executives say supplies should remain more than adequate in coming years, even if natural gas becomes the alternative fuel of choice for vehicles. Among its advantages as a vehicle fuel, natural gas does not need to undergo any refining or processing, as methanol does, and it does not require any further technical breakthroughs, as electric-powered cars do. In addition, natural gas already has a widespread distribution network, with lines running into many homes and businesses.</p>
        <p>Experiments With Buses</p>
        <p>Spurred by California's regulations and the increasingly tough Federal rules, state and local governments, the automobile industry, oil companies and suppliers of electricity and natural gas are all working on programs to develop less-polluting vehicles.</p>
        <p>A number of public transit authorities in California are experimenting with buses fueled by methanol, an alcohol-based fuel. The General Motors Corporation is developing an electric car that could be on sale here by the end of the decade if consumers show sufficient interest and if some technical hurdles can be overcome. And General Motors is expected to announce within the next several weeks that it will build trucks specifically designed to run on natural gas, eliminating the need for costly conversions from traditional gasoline and diesel engines.</p>
        <p>There are currently about 30,000 vehicles in the United States that can run on natural gas, most of them operated by gas companies and other businesses with large fleets of vehicles that return to a central maintenance and refueling station each night. Many were converted from gasoline in the 1970's, when high gasoline prices made natural gas an attractive alternative on economic grounds.</p>
        <p>But most of the research in the field is now driven by air quality concerns rather than fuel prices. Natural gas costs about 25 percent less per mile than gasoline.</p>
        <p>Based on its test program in Brooklyn, which began a year ago, United Parcel said use of natural gas significantly reduced emissions of the gases that cause smog. Emissions of carbon monoxide were reduced by 85 percent, nitrogen oxide by 25 percent, carbon dioxide by 23 percent and hydrocarbons by 13 percent.</p>
        <p>In another move intended to cut the pollution on California's roads, the Ford Motor Company plans to announce Wednesday that it will give a $700 rebate to residents of the Los Angeles area who trade in older cars without pollution equipment when they buy certain new models of the company's cars.</p>
        <p>Company officials acknowledge that the program, which will affect only about 1,000 vehicles, is largely a symbolic gesture that will have little effect on air pollution.</p>
        <p>To qualify for the Ford plan, the vehicles must have been manufactured before 1971, and they must be registered to residents of Los Angeles, Orange, Riverside, San Bernardino or Ventura counties.</p>
        <p>The $700 certificates issued by Ford will be good toward the purchase of one of the company's smaller models, including Escort and Festiva.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
