<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Next Bold Step Toward Fusion Proposed</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BIG SCIENCE: IS IT WORTH THE PRICE? - A PERIODIC LOOK AT THE LARGEST NEW RESEARCH PROJECTS" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="390053"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUSION (NUCLEAR REACTION)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PRINCETON UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">COMPACT IGNITION TOKAMAK (FUSION DEVICE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fusion (Nuclear Reaction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DA1038F93AA35753C1A966958260" item-length="2036" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Next Bold Step Toward Fusion Proposed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
      <dateline>PLAINSBORO, N.J.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ON a grassy site here surrounded by cornfields and dense woods, not far from Princeton University, scientists want to build a machine of vast complexity and cost that they hope will lead to a powerful new source of energy half a century from now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ON a grassy site here surrounded by cornfields and dense woods, not far from Princeton University, scientists want to build a machine of vast complexity and cost that they hope will lead to a powerful new source of energy half a century from now.</p>
        <p>ON a grassy site here surrounded by cornfields and dense woods, not far from Princeton University, scientists want to build a machine of vast complexity and cost that they hope will lead to a powerful new source of energy half a century from now.</p>
        <p>Their proposal is confronting the Bush Administration with a difficult choice as it tries to develop new sources of energy while cutting an enormous budget deficit.</p>
        <p>The machine, the Compact Ignition Tokamak, would be the next stage of development in what is turning into a century-long quest to harness the kind of thermonuclear fire, or fusion energy, that lights the sun and produces the awesome blast of the hydrogen bomb.</p>
        <p>Scientists here at the Princeton University Plasma Physics Laboratory say the new machine could be a major step toward ushering in a future age of relatively safe, cheap, clean and nearly inexhaustible energy.</p>
        <p>But the device, meant to be switched on in 1998, would cost nearly $1 billion, a huge sum in an era of tight Federal budgets. Moreover, skeptics say the machine, even if successful, offers no guarantee that the field could advance in the 21st century to produce electrical power that would be economically competitive. They say that fusion advocates, long noted for promising more than they deliver, are engaging in another of their periodic bouts of hyperbole meant to promote Federal financing of yet another costly project.</p>
        <p>The new machine would be based on traditional ''hot'' fusion principles rather than the low-temperature or ''cold'' fusion that was proposed with great fanfare last year. The allure of cold fusion was that it seemed to promise enormous energy from simple devices that worked at room temperature, in contrast to hot fusion machines, which must operate at temperatures above those on the sun, and are vastly complicated and expensive. But after a year of intense investigation, most experts have dismissed the notion that cold fusion, if it exists, will ever be a significant energy source.</p>
        <p>Controlled fusion, which seeks to fuse hydrogen atoms to generate bursts of usable energy, has long been one of the most risky, daunting, contested and costly aspects of big science ever undertaken by the Federal Government. Billions of dollars have already been spent but, even amid reports of progress, the goal of practical fusion energy always seems to recede into the distance. Today experts estimate that the payoff, if it comes at all, will represent an investment of tens of billions of dollars as well as roughly a century of hard work by generations of scientists. The pursuit got under way in the 1940's and, in optimistic Government scenarios, could culminate in the 2040's with the operation of the first commercial power plant.</p>
        <p>Fusion produces energy by fusing, or welding, the atoms of light elements together. In contrast, the nuclear fission reactors now in operation generate energy by breaking apart the atoms of heavy elements like uranium.</p>
        <p>In the interior of the sun, where temperatures are 14 million degrees centigrade and gravitational pressures are crushing, nuclear particles are driven so close together that they fuse and release vast energy. In a fusion reactor, the temperature must be even higher, around 100 million degrees centigrade, since the fusion fuel undergoes far less compression than materials at the center of the sun. The main fuel for fusion experiments is a heavy form of hydrogen known as deuterium, which is found in endless quantities in water.</p>
        <p>For years, the main path to achieving controlled fusion has been to heat fusion fuel so it breaks into a cloud of electrically charged particles known as a plasma, which can be contained by magnetic fields. No earthly vessel would be up to the task. Any kind of metal, ceramic or glass would melt. So magnetism has been used to build increasingly powerful magnetic ''bottles,'' which today are usually housed in building-size machines that have a doughnut shape.</p>
        <p>The job has not been easy. Edward Teller, a founder of the field, once said that confining the plasma with lines of magnetic force was ''like trying to confine jelly with rubber bands.'' The hot plasma would heat water to rotate turbines and generate electricity.</p>
        <p>A Vast Supply of Energy</p>
        <p>Despite the challenge, scientists here say the practical payoffs are so great that forging ahead is worth the risk and expense. In theory, they say, the process could extract far more energy from the top two inches of Lake Erie than exists in all the earth's known oil reserves. And they say the alternatives of relying on coal supplies that pose a threat of global warming, or on nuclear fission reactors that raise safety concerns and generate mountains of high-level radioactive waste, or on oil from politically unstable parts of the world, are likely to grow increasingly disagreeable in the 21st century.</p>
        <p>''The fight over oil at $100 a barrel is going to make the fight at $30 look pretty trivial,'' said Dr. Rob J. Goldston, the scientific head of the proposed machine. ''The question is whether there will be a new energy source to keep us at a high level of civilization.''</p>
        <p>Skeptics dismiss this type of statement as misguided at best. Dr. Lawrence M. Lidsky, a nuclear engineer at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, quit the field six years ago because he felt fusion reactors would be too big, too complex, too expensive and too fragile to be practical. He still feels that way.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to make an economically based argument for fusion,'' he said. ''You can't justify it, especially as other sources of energy look better and better, as people find better ways to gasify coal and build fission reactors'' that are safer.</p>
        <p>In spite of such sentiments, the Federal Government may be edging toward greater support for fusion research. In late September, a panel of scientists, formed at the behest of Energy Secretary James D. Watkins, urged the department to greatly expand the financing of its fusion effort, citing progress in the field and the size of potential payoffs. Specifically, it backed the building of the new machine, which seeks to contain the energy of nuclear fusion with powerful magnetic fields.</p>
        <p>Here at the Princeton Plasma Physics Laboratory, the nation's largest center for fusion research, the current big machine is known as the Tokamak Fusion Test Reactor (Tokamak being a Russian acronym for doughnut-shaped chamber). Built at a cost of $314 million and switched on in 1982, it recently achieved temperatures of 400 million degrees centigrade, a world record, and triggered fusion reactions that can be interpreted as just shy of break-even, the point where the energy released by a fusion reaction matches that put in to cause the fusion, if only for a moment. In the course of the decade, the machine has been slowly advancing the three key fusion parameters: temperature, density and time of plasma containment.</p>
        <p>Introducing New Problems</p>
        <p>The device, rising some five stories, emits a high-pitched whine during a ''shot.'' The critical action lasts one second before it dies out because of limitations in the plasma-heating mechanism and the need to cut rising temperatures of powerful magnets. In late 1993, the device is expected to reach break-even after its fuel supply gets a dose of tritium, a heavy form of hydrogen that speeds the reaction.</p>
        <p>But tritium will introduce new problems. Nearby in a hangar-like hall is a $5 million robotic arm, some 25 feet long, that is meant to inspect and repair the machine's interior once tritium is added. Today people can go inside. But with the addition of tritium, the machine will vastly increase the production of subatomic particles known as neutrons, making its parts radioactive.</p>
        <p>In a vacant lot next to this machine, Princeton scientists would like to take the next big step in the fusion venture, the Compact Ignition Tokamak, at a cost of $940 million. This would be the first machine in the world to achieve the true burning of fusion fuel, the point where fusion reactions are so abundant they become self-sustaining. Its ''shots'' would nonetheless be brief, lasting about 10 seconds.</p>
        <p>To attain ignition, the new machine would reach the same general temperatures as the current machine but have a plasma that is far denser and less likely to lose heat, a feat achieved mainly by better design of its doughnut-shaped chamber and more powerful magnets. Its energy output would be much greater than the current Princeton machine.</p>
        <p>So too, its need for robotic maintenance would be greater, since it would operate far longer with tritium fuel and the resulting fusillade of neutrons, which not only induce radioactivity but make parts brittle and prone to break. Dr. John A. Schmidt, the leader of the project, said its robots would cost about $66 million.</p>
        <p>The proposed plan, which the Energy Department has yet to back, would have construction start in 1992, under the budget currently being prepared by the Bush Administration. $6 Billion Proposal Beyond that machine, the attainment of fusion energy would require a series of additional multibillion-dollar machines. One is known as the International Thermonuclear Experimental Reactor, a joint effort between the United States, the Soviet Union, Europe and Japan to build the world's first fusion reactor early in the 21st century. While the Princeton device would ignite fusion fuel in short bursts, the 10-story international machine, estimated to cost at least $6 billion, would be the first to operate continuously.</p>
        <p>Some experts believe that fusion, more than any other ''big science'' project, will become a catalyst for international cooperation, since its research costs will become too great for any single country and the payoff would be so enormous that many countries will want to share in the venture.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Dr. Kenneth L. Kliewer, dean of science at Purdue University, a self-described fusion skeptic who became an advocate after joining the Federal fusion panel, said the Princeton machine was a critical precursor to the international collaboration.</p>
        <p>''We need additional and important data,'' he said. ''The Princeton machine gives the U.S. an opportunity to be a prominent and important partner in the fusion business.'' Several reports have recently said the United States is starting to fall behind the fusion efforts of other countries.</p>
        <p>Beyond the international collaboration would be another machine, conceivably built by the United States alone, that would have, in addition to the reactor, a welter of pipes, plumbing and turbines meant to turn fusion heat into electricity. The Federal panel said such a Federal demonstration plant might be completed by 2025. The final step in the process would be the construction of a commercial plant, which the panel said might be accomplished by 2040.</p>
        <p>Scientists here at Princeton say fusion is so attractive that the enterprise should proceed with dispatch. Fusion reactors might produce less radioactivity than their fission counterparts by a factor of thousands, they say. And a meltdown, the potential worst catastrophe of a fission reactor, is impossible with fusion.</p>
        <p>Hurdles to Overcome</p>
        <p>But skeptics note that the field is haunted by hurdles that threaten its commercial success. Dr. Lidsky of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology said the neutron barrage would be so great that the materials in a fusion reactor would probably be continuously damaged, hurting its prospects of ever turning a profit. A reactor, he added, would also be vastly more complex than a fission reactor, meaning it would probably break down a lot.</p>
        <p>Princeton scientists say these are very real problems that the program seeks to address. Dr. Schmidt, head of the proposed new machine, said fusion researchers' aim was to develop new materials and metals that are far stronger than current ones. And he conceded that a fusion reactor would be ''much more complex,'' saying the program was trying to find ways to simplify the endeavor.</p>
        <p>''There's no assurance that fusion power will be economical and competitive,'' Dr. Schmidt said, ''but that's the whole point of the program - to find out'' if that is possible.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
