<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Perrier to Bow to F.D.A. and Change Label</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="345096"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOTTLED WATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MISLEADING AND DECEPTIVE ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABELING AND LABELS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FOOD AND DRUG ADMINISTRATION (FDA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SOURCE PERRIER SA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MEIER, BARRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDA1E31F93AA25757C0A966958260" item-length="609" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Perrier to Bow to F.D.A. and Change Label</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARRY MEIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MEIER, BARRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The ''eau,'' as Perrier promotions state, is expected to be back on American store shelves next week. But the mineral water's label claims are about to change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The ''eau,'' as Perrier promotions state, is expected to be back on American store shelves next week. But the mineral water's label claims are about to change.</p>
        <p>The ''eau,'' as Perrier promotions state, is expected to be back on American store shelves next week. But the mineral water's label claims are about to change.</p>
        <p>The Federal Food and Drug Administration has ruled that the mineral water's claim to be ''naturally sparkling'' is false. And Perrier's American distributor recently agreed to drop the phrase from bottle labels by July 30, according to an F.D.A. official.</p>
        <p>''It is not a naturally sparkling water,'' said Edward J. McDonnell, director of the F.D.A.'s district office in Boston. ''It is fabricated from carbon dioxide and water, which are taken out of the ground separately.''</p>
        <p>'We Didn't Agree'</p>
        <p>Jane Lazgin, a spokeswoman for the Perrier Group of America Inc., in Greenwich, Conn., said that while the company believed its previous descriptions of the beverage were accurate, it had bowed to the F.D.A.'s wishes.</p>
        <p>''We didn't agree,'' Ms. Lazgin said, ''but we decided to make the change because we want to be responsible to the Government and consumers.''</p>
        <p>The F.D.A move comes amid a possible crackdown on bottled water claims in general. Early this month, Representative John D. Dingell, Democrat of Michigan, told the F.D.A and the Federal Trade Commission that he was concerned about the Perrier case and might hold hearings on the bottled-water industry's marketing and quality-control practices.</p>
        <p>In February, trace amounts of the toxic chemical benzene were discovered in some Perrier bottles, prompting a worldwide recall. Although Source Perrier S.A. of France had crafted an image of the beverage as a pure, natural product, the incident disclosed that Perrier not only mechanically added gas to water, but also that the gas contained numerous impurities, which must be removed. These include benzene and hydrogen sulfide, which smells like rotten eggs.</p>
        <p>'Host of Chemical Impurities'</p>
        <p>''There are a whole host of chemical impurities in the gas,'' Mr. McDonnell said, ''and the integrity of the product depends on refining the gas so that it is of food-grade quality.''</p>
        <p>The contamination occurred because Source Perrier had failed to change carbon filters that removed those impurities. Michael Burke, director of the New York State Bureau of Public Water Supply Protection, said the benzene contamination, which began around last June, coincided with the changing of natural gas wells at the Perrier spring in Vergeze, France.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burke said the information that Perrier supplied to state officials indicated that the company relied not on chemical tests, but on the smell of hydrogen sulfide to decide when to change filters. (Source Perrier now regularly tests for chemical contaminants in the gas and water.) The new well, however, apparently had lower levels of hydrogen sulfide, Mr. Burke said, so benzene apparently began seeping through the filter before the smell of rotten eggs did.</p>
        <p>Listing the Contents</p>
        <p>Ms. Lazgin, the Perrier spokeswoman, said that explanation was similar to one provided by a consultant hired by Perrier. Both the company and public officials said the incident did not pose a health threat.</p>
        <p>To start selling Perrier again in the United States, the company has agreed to start listing the beverage's contents - water and carbon dioxide - on its label and to drop the claim ''calorie free'' from labels, Mr. McDonnell said.</p>
        <p>''That is misleading because water does not contain calories,'' the F.D.A. official said.</p>
        <p>The company will also provide the agency with the results of daily laboratory tests for any possible benzene contamination, he said. Recent tests have not detected the chemical's presence, Mr. McDonnell added.</p>
        <p>COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
