<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>40-Year Countdown Is Seen for Environment</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="325567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WORLDWATCH INSTITUTE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D7163AF932A25751C0A966958260" item-length="578" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>40-Year Countdown Is Seen for Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The world has about 40 years to achieve an environmentally sustainable economy or descend into a long economic and physical decline, according to a report issued today by the Worldwatch Institute.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The world has about 40 years to achieve an environmentally sustainable economy or descend into a long economic and physical decline, according to a report issued today by the Worldwatch Institute.</p>
        <p>The world has about 40 years to achieve an environmentally sustainable economy or descend into a long economic and physical decline, according to a report issued today by the Worldwatch Institute.</p>
        <p>In its annual State of the World Report, which is published in nine languages, the Washington-based research group says the current trend in population growth, excessive consumption of wood, minerals and other materials in producing energy, the release of toxic substances in the environment and exponential economic expansion are already eroding the natural systems that sustain life on earth.</p>
        <p>But the report concludes that current scientific knowledge and available technology are advanced enough to help create a new global economy that could be sustained into the indefinite future.</p>
        <p>Lester R. Brown, president of the institute and a chief author of the report, contends that the transition to such a viable economy will have to be made within the next 40 years. ''If we have not succeeded by 2030,'' he said, ''environmental deterioration and economic decline will be feeding on each other, causing social structures to disintegrate.''</p>
        <p>The report suggests elements of an economy that could be sustained over the long run. In general, these include cutting the growth of population below currently projected rates, stabilizing emissions of industrial gases that are accumulating in the atmosphere and are expected to change global climate, and eliminating the loss of forest cover and plant and animal species.</p>
        <p>The report also says there must be a more equitable distribution of the world's riches, with a narrower gap between rich and poor countries.</p>
        <p>The report contends that a global population of 9 billion by the year 2030, as projected by the United Nations, would not permit a sustainable world economy. Birth rates in developing countries like Ethiopia, India and Nigeria are already pressing against the limits of food supplies and other resources, the report says. It contends that a global population stabilized at 8 billion is the maximum that could be sustained comfortably.</p>
        <p>Solar Power to Grow</p>
        <p>Because of the potentially ''catastrophic'' changes caused by fossil fuels, the report predicts, ''the world economy of 2030 will not be powered by coal, oil and natural gas.'' Instead, it says there will be heavy reliance on solar power in all its forms, including solar thermal power and wind power.</p>
        <p>Carbon emissions, the report says, must be reduced to one-eighth of the current levels to ward off changes that could wreak havoc on the global economy. The report predicts that there will be much less reliance on private automobiles and a greater reliance on public transportation and, in urban areas, on bicycles, which are increasingly used in many countries in Asia and Europe.</p>
        <p>Profound Shifts Required</p>
        <p>If a sound economy is achieved over the next 40 years, it will also rely heavily on recycled materials and much less on virgin materials, the institute's researchers say. The destruction of tropical forests will have ceased, they predict, and much of the world will be reforested.</p>
        <p>But the report said none of these changes can take place without shifts in ''the social, economic and moral character of human societies.''</p>
        <p>Above all, ''movement to a lasting society cannot occur without a transformation of individual priorities and values,'' it said. ''Materialism simply cannot survive the transition to a sustainable world.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
