<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Egypt Asks Help for New Alexandria Library</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="326098"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIBRARIES AND LIBRARIANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EGYPTIAN CIVILIZATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EGYPT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALEXANDRIA (EGYPT)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">COWELL, ALAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Egyptian Civilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Egyptian Civilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DF143FF930A25751C0A966958260" item-length="693" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Egypt Asks Help for New Alexandria Library</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COWELL, ALAN</byline>
      <dateline>CAIRO, Feb. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Short on cash, long on dreams of glories past recalling, Egypt is asking the world to finance the rebirth of antiquity's greatest trove of wisdom: the Library of Alexandria, where scholars once gathered their knowledge of gods and stars and science on scrolls of papyrus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Short on cash, long on dreams of glories past recalling, Egypt is asking the world to finance the rebirth of antiquity's greatest trove of wisdom: the Library of Alexandria, where scholars once gathered their knowledge of gods and stars and science on scrolls of papyrus.</p>
        <p>Short on cash, long on dreams of glories past recalling, Egypt is asking the world to finance the rebirth of antiquity's greatest trove of wisdom: the Library of Alexandria, where scholars once gathered their knowledge of gods and stars and science on scrolls of papyrus.</p>
        <p>Alexandria these days is a tawdry place, a rundown port on a polluted sea, and Egypt itself has problems that occlude historical greatness: It is $55 billion in debt, it cannot feed itself, its population is growing too fast to house or school, and more than half its 55 million people cannot read or write.</p>
        <p>Yet today in the Nileside resort of Aswan a panoply of queens and sheiks, princesses and presidents assembled under the auspices of the United Nations Educational and Scientific Organization to hear appeals for cash to finance a library project that will cost more than $150 million before a single book or text is bought.</p>
        <p>President Francois Mitterrand of France was there, and so too was Princess Caroline of Monaco, Queen Sofia of Spain and Queen Noor of Jordan. Sheik Zayed bin Sultan al-Nahayan of the United Arab Emirates led dignitaries from Arabia, and pledged $20 million toward the project. Saudi Arabia pledged $3 million.</p>
        <p>As the celebrities arrived, dancing girls danced, bands played and people lined the route into town to cheer, restrained by security forces worried by two recent acts of violence in Egypt -the killing of nine Israelis on a tour bus, and an abortive assault by a teen-age gunman on the palace that President Hosni Mubarak uses as a residence.</p>
        <p>Melina Mercouri, the former Greek Culture Minister and movie actress, arrived and spoke of ancient greatness spreading beyond the Parthenon. ''It was Egypt that served as the cradle of science, knowledge and wisdom,'' she said of the years when Alexandria flourished as the world's center of learning under a dynasty founded by Ptolemy, a Macedonian general.</p>
        <p>Alexandria itself was founded by Alexander the Great after he entered Egypt in 332 B.C. to rout the Persians, but he died in 323 B.C. before the city was completed. Then, in Ptolemaic times, the Alexandria Library assumed great fame until, in 48 B.C., the Romans came and sacked the place and much of the library burned. Until then, it had contained more than 650,000 papyrus scrolls on which the scholars of antiquity had inscribed all that was known about the universe and the gods, mathematics and philosophy. Every known work of scholarship was translated into Greek there.</p>
        <p>Euclid, the Greek scholar who devised geometry, and others including Aristophanes and Archimedes studied and taught there as the library became a university. Its successor, if it is built, will draw on newer inventions, including video cassettes and microfiches.</p>
        <p>Some foreigners and diplomats here say the new library's function as a reminder of past greatness to offset modernity's grim portents is as significant as whatever it may achieve academically.</p>
        <p>Other outsiders have shown interest in the construction contracts involving the library, which is to open in 1995. A Norwegian company recently won an international competition to decide who should design the new museum and drew up a $500,000 feasibility study financed by the Oslo Government. The design is for a library built half underground, with its visible portion molded in the shape of the rising sun of ancient Egypt.</p>
        <p>At their gathering today, the celebrities signed what they called the Aswan Declaration calling on all governments, organizations and individuals to contribute money, aid and works of art or science to the new library.</p>
        <p>It was not clear, however, how much further research was needed before construction begins. The Egyptian Government has donated a site measuring over 400,000 square feet, near the place where the old library stood.</p>
        <p>In Cairo, however, some Egyptian researchers, working independently of the library project, have produced dire and unproven forecasts that say Alexandria could be in trouble if, as some prognostications maintain, global warming and other factors raise the level of the Mediterranean to dangerous levels over the next half-century.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
