<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BIG SCIENCE: IS IT WORTH THE PRICE?    A periodic look at the largest new research projects.;   Heavy Costs of Major Projects Pose a Threat to Basic Science</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="357008"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DE1431F934A15756C0A966958260" item-length="3153" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BIG SCIENCE: IS IT WORTH THE PRICE?    A periodic look at the largest new research projects.;   Heavy Costs of Major Projects Pose a Threat to Basic Science</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Federal Government has embarked on the most ambitious array of big science projects ever, with some experts saying they herald a new age of discovery while others are warning that their great cost could cripple vital parts of the nation's scientific effort and eventually the American economy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Federal Government has embarked on the most ambitious array of big science projects ever, with some experts saying they herald a new age of discovery while others are warning that their great cost could cripple vital parts of the nation's scientific effort and eventually the American economy.</p>
        <p>The Federal Government has embarked on the most ambitious array of big science projects ever, with some experts saying they herald a new age of discovery while others are warning that their great cost could cripple vital parts of the nation's scientific effort and eventually the American economy.</p>
        <p>The scale of American science has never been greater. Examples are the $1.5 billion Hubble Space Telescope now orbiting high above the Earth, the $3 billion project to map the human genetic structure, the $8 billion Superconducting Supercollider planned for the plains of Texas and the $30 billion space station Freedom taking shape on computer design consoles. $100 Billion Operating Costs All told, new projects now planned for completion in the 1990's will cost more than $60 billion to build. And that is just the start. More than $100 billion will be needed to operate the instruments over their lifetimes, placing a heavy mortgage on the nation's research spending well into the future.</p>
        <p>Virtually all the projects have worthy objectives, or at least a plausible rationale. Some, like the supercollider, may be close to indispensable if certain scientific gains are to be made in the search for elementary particles and forces. Backers of the projects generally see them as the key to the nation's future success in pushing back the frontiers of science.</p>
        <p>''Bigness is an inevitable component of the evolution of science and we must learn to live with it,'' said Dr. Leon M. Lederman, a Nobel laureate in physics at the University of Chicago and a former director of Fermi National Laboratory, which runs the nation's largest particle accelerator so far.</p>
        <p>Critics Cite Big Drain</p>
        <p>But critics say big projects drain funds from small-scale research vital to the creation of new products and jobs and often to the advance of science itself.</p>
        <p>''Big science has gone berserk,'' said Dr. Rustum Roy, professor of materials science at Pennsylvania State University, who is an adviser to the House Committee on Science. ''Good minds and a lot of money are going into areas that are not relevant to American competitiveness, American technological health, or even the balanced development of American science.''</p>
        <p>Dr. George F. Chapline, a physicist at the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory in California, said the trend bodes ill for the nation. ''It is very questionable whether these projects will contribute much to stopping America's industrial decline, and may even exacerbate it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the big instruments can take so long to plan and build, sometimes a decade or more, that they are sometimes seen as obsolete when switched on because science now moves so fast. Perhaps most troubling, this same lag is seen as causing bright graduate students to abandon some fields now dominated by giant instruments as they search for timely projects on which to base their Ph.D. research.</p>
        <p>Science Being Altered</p>
        <p>Most experts agree that the big projects are fundamentally altering the nature of American science and that the situation is serious because of the nation's fiscal troubles.</p>
        <p>''We have a crisis developing,'' said Representative George E. Brown Jr., a California Democrat who has served on the House science committee for nearly a quarter century. ''We're freezing out a lot of our good work because of the commitment to big science.''</p>
        <p>Even Administration officials concede that some big projects may eventually have to be delayed, canceled or undertaken with foreign partners to defray expenses.</p>
        <p>''The country needs the supercollider and the space station,'' said Erich Bloch, director of the National Science Foundation, the Government's main agency for the support of general science. ''But somewhere you have to make a decision about priorities when you find you can't do all of them simultaneously.''</p>
        <p>Real Spending Is Steady</p>
        <p>Adjusted for inflation, overall Federal spending for research and development in science and technology, including the military's, is little greater than at the height of the Apollo moon program. In 1967 the Government spent $46 billion, according to the National Science Foundation. For 1990 the figure is $48.2 billion.</p>
        <p>But while money has remained roughly constant, the number and size of big projects has grown substantially, taking a growing share of the Federal science budget and enveloping dozens of areas of astronomy, physics, chemistry, molecular biology and space science.</p>
        <p>A revealing catalogue of big scientific instruments has been complied by the Congressional Research Service of the Library of Congress. It lists all instruments costing more than $25 million. An analysis of that inventory shows the nation built nine projects in the 1950's for physics, astronomy, materials science and space science. The number rose to 34 in the 1980's. Moreover, the cost of the projects soared, even after discounting for inflation. The 1950's bill came to $260 million. The 1980's bill was $6.7 billion.</p>
        <p>The History</p>
        <p>Easy Discoveries Have Been Made</p>
        <p>Behind the push for big instruments is a fact scientists seldom mention. Most of the discoveries that can be made with simple instruments and little labor have already been achieved, so in many cases the scientific tools have to be large and powerful.</p>
        <p>''It's unfortunate but inevitable in all fields,'' said Dr. Richard A. Isaacson, a science foundation program manager. ''After you do the easy things, it gets harder and harder. Eventually the next step is very difficult and requires a lot of money and large facilities.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Isaacson said that it was important ''to keep a balance'' and make sure that small science projects at universities are adequately financed. ''But it's painful, he said. ''Maybe at some point science will come to an end because we can't afford the big facilities.''</p>
        <p>Experts have no formal definition of ''big science,'' but for the purposes of this article it is seen as any civilian research project whose construction costs are $100 million or more. This definition excludes military endeavors like the Strategic Defense Initiative, or Star Wars, on which more than $20 billion has been spent so far, and high-technology development programs like the proposed $5 billion aerospace plane that would fly off a runway into earth orbit. Such programs can have much the same impact in siphoning off money and technical talent from other worthy projects, but they are not usually considered scientific in nature.</p>
        <p>Others Wait in the Wings</p>
        <p>Beyond the big science projects already under way, others are waiting in the wings for Federal approval. These include the Compact Ignition Tokamak, a $480 million device for controlled nuclear fusion; the Advanced Neutron Source, a $500 million reactor for studying materials; and the Space Infrared Telescope Facility, an $800 million orbiting observatory for studying stars.</p>
        <p>Compounding the strain on the Federal budget is the fact that project costs often rise from the original estimates, sometimes precipitously. The space station was originally sold to Ronald Reagan's Administration and to Congress on the basis of an estimated cost of $8 billion, but its projected price is now more than $30 billion. Experts say part of the problem is that project officials deliberately underestimate expenses while seeking Federal approval.</p>
        <p>''There's willful self-delusion on the part of all the participants.'' said Frederick N. Khedouri, a budget official in the Reagan White House who oversaw most of the nation's big-science projects. ''They know the estimates are understated.''</p>
        <p>In dealing with inevitable costs rises, Mr. Khedouri said, managers at Federal agencies often ''sacrifice less visible but probably more important programs.'' The overall effect, he said, ''is a system in which bad science tends to drive out the good.''</p>
        <p>The Problems</p>
        <p>Big Projects And Big Politics</p>
        <p>Nowhere is the ascendancy of big science more evident than in the field of particle physics. The $8 billion supercollider is to be a behemoth some 54 miles in circumference, the biggest instrument in the history of science. Housed in a tunnel 150 feet beneath the rolling prairie of northeast Texas, the colossus is to boost proton beams to nearly the speed of light and smash them together, yielding debris expected to provide clues to the building blocks of nature.</p>
        <p>Scheduled to be switched on in 1999, the machine will cost $313 million a year just to operate. Over its 30-year lifetime, operations will run to an estimated $9.4 billion, with inflation taken into account.</p>
        <p>While many experts say the supercollider is on the forefront of science, some big projects are not viewed so kindly. Pork barrel politics, with the promise of lucrative contracts and jobs, are sometimes seen as a driving factor in their genisis. Another factor is the sheer expansionism on the part of Federal agencies.</p>
        <p>Assessment Depends on Size</p>
        <p>''The rigor with which new projects are assessed varies inversely with their size,'' said Dr. Lewis M. Branscomb, a physicist who held top science posts in the Federal Government and is now director of the Science, Technology and Public Policy Program at Harvard University.</p>
        <p>For instances, requests for small Federal science grants have to pass a gantlet of review committees and Government examinations. In contrast, some huge projects, like Star Wars, have their origins largely in high-level politics.</p>
        <p>At the same time, smaller projects can sometimes produce better science than the big ones, critics say. As an example they point to the space agency's $17 billion Earth Observing System, a group of six huge satellites now under development to monitor changes in the earth's environment at the turn of the century. Some critics say its size has been largely dictated by political forces and that a series of smaller craft would cost less, operate sooner and have greater flexibility to pursue fast-changing scientific questions.</p>
        <p>Small Can Mean Quick</p>
        <p>''In a timely way they would give the global warming information everybody is eager for,'' said Dr. Robert Jastrow, a space scientist at Dartmouth College. Moreover, he said, a quick return of data would help universities rebuild populations of bright young graduate students who are leaving for lack of challenging projects.</p>
        <p>''You can't plan a graduate career on a 10-year wait,'' Dr. Jastrow said. ''The field will dry up on the present timetable.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Freeman Dyson, a physicist at the Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton, said in his book, ''Infinite in All Directions,'' that some of the big projects take so long to build that they are virtually obsolete when completed.</p>
        <p>''The cutting edge of science moves rapidly,'' he said. ''The bigger and more ambitious the missions become, the more difficult it is to reconcile the time scale of the missions with the time scale of science.''</p>
        <p>The Results</p>
        <p>Mad Scramble For a Few Dollars</p>
        <p>As big projects have bloomed, small ones have withered. Critics fear that some of the most fertile areas of science are now falling into neglect. ''Significant advances in science typically result from small projects - not large ones,'' said Dr. Chapline of the Livermore laboratory. For instance, A.T.&amp;T. Bell Labs, with a relatively small budget for physics, has produced seven Nobel laureates in that field.</p>
        <p>An oft-cited example of small-science productivity comes from the field of superconducting materials that work at high temperatures and promise to revolutionize electric devices. A key breakthrough was made in 1987 by Dr. Paul Chu, a University of Houston physicist. That year his laboratory ran on $130,000, about half from the science foundation.</p>
        <p>Despite its allure, and a sizable amount of subsequent Federal financing, the endeavor has recently been eroded by budget pressure. ''Every worker in the field of the basic science of superconductivity in this country is experiencing repeated and severe funding cuts,'' Dr. Philip W. Anderson, a Nobel laureate at Princeton University, told Congress in March.</p>
        <p>Squeeze Is Surprising</p>
        <p>The squeeze is somewhat surprising since the science foundation, a main Federal patron of small science, has received substantial budget increases in recent years. This fiscal year it is spending $2.08 billion, up from $1.72 billion in 1988. But much of the increase has gone to science education and the establishment of large centers for science and engineering. And now the foundation has embarked on a spate of relatively large-scale science projects as well, including the $110 million High Magnetic Field Laboratory and the $190 million Gravitational Wave Observatory.</p>
        <p>The science foundation's budgets for small ventures in mathematics, physics, chemistry, engineering, biology and computer science have generally fallen, after inflation is taken into account, below their 1988 levels, according to John C. Crowley and Patrica Ann Levy, analysts at the Association of American Universities in Washington. ''They are weakening steadily,'' the analysts concluded in a recent paper, noting that two thirds of science foundation's competitive research programs were in budgetary decline.</p>
        <p>Trials of Individual Researchers</p>
        <p>''As projects grow larger, the politics of science change drastically in favor of sustaining the larger commitments,'' Mr. Crowley said in an interview. ''Over time, the individual investigator is being squeezed, both in terms of the real value of the average grant and in terms of the numbers of awards.''</p>
        <p>Of particular concern to some experts is the science foundation's physics budget, which supports small-scale research critical to the nation's industrial health but, after inflation is taken into account, has been decling for half a decade.</p>
        <p>''Things are out of whack,'' said Dr. Neil W. Ashcroft, a professor of physics at Cornell University. ''Condensed-matter physics is at the heart of modern technology, of computer chips, of all the electronic gadgets behind the new industrial order. Yet relative to the big projects, it's neglected.''</p>
        <p>The Proposals</p>
        <p>Strict Goals And More Money</p>
        <p>Remedies to the big-project drain on Federal science funds have been offered with increasing frequency in recent years. They include delays, cancellations, the imposition of cost ceilings and the sharing of expenses with international partners. A radical approach calls for doubling the Federal research budget so all science could be better financed.</p>
        <p>In an attempt to stop the upward creep of project costs, Congress last year limited to $1.6 billion two new NASA spacecraft, the Cassini Saturn Probe and the Comet Rendezvous and Asteroid Flyby, with the proviso that one be scrapped if there was a cost overrun. More recently, the House voted to put a $5 billion ceiling on the supercollider, with the remaining $3 billion to come from Texas and foreign partners.</p>
        <p>Another tactic, much discussed but seldom used, is to delay projects. The idea was broached most notably in April 1988 by Dr. Frank Press, president of the National Academy of Sciences, the prestigious honorary group for scientists. In a speech, he suggested that the pace of big projects might be slowed to permit the financing of less visible but important endeavors.</p>
        <p>Priority for AIDS Research</p>
        <p>He personally gave his highest priority to grants for individual researchers, to crises such as the AIDS epidemic and to science breakthroughs like high-temperature superconductors. Of secondary importance, he said, were large projects like the supercollider and the human genome.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Dr. Press reiterated his support for this approach given ''the current budgetary crisis.'' But over the coming decade, he said, the only real solution would be to double the Federal money spent on science.</p>
        <p>''With Reagan we doubled the defense budget without a hiccup,'' Dr. Press said. ''If you look at the competition around the world, science and technology is our sole advantage. Because of the relatively low cost, it's a very good investment.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloch, the science foundation's director, expressed skepticism over whether so much money would materialize. ''I don't think it's realistic,'' he said, adding that it was more important to make sure existing funds were ''spent wisely'' by instituting priorities and rearranging the budget.</p>
        <p>He urged that small-scale research be protected. ''We should not sacrifice the science base in in order to do these projects,'' Mr. Bloch said.</p>
        <p>Bush Backs Big Projects</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration has largely ignored proposals to delay big projects, forging ahead with a number of old and new endeavors. Some of these have yet to be approved by Congress, which might yet reject them. They include the $400 million Relativistic Heavy Ion Collider, $190 million Gravitational Wave Observatory and $140 million Eight-Meter Optical Telescopes.</p>
        <p>The Administration is seeking increased funds as the main way of achieving its goals for both big and little science. For the next fiscal year, it has requested a 12 percent rise in Federal funds for civilian research and development, from $23.8 billion to $26.7 billion.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Dr. D. Allan Bromley, science adviser to President Bush, praised the large facilities as essential ''tools young people will need in 5 or 10 years.'' But he also conceded the Administration had so far failed to support small science to the extent it wished.</p>
        <p>''We're not satisfied,'' he said, adding that in the next budget cycle the Administration would start a special initiative ''to make sure individual investigator projects are not squeezed out.''</p>
        <p>Foreign Partners Sought</p>
        <p>In addition to making new money available, the Administration wants to internationalize some of the nation's big science. It has three foreign partners for the space station and is seeking ones for the supercollider and some other projects.</p>
        <p>President Bush told the National Academy of Sciences last month that his Administration was ''exploring new ways to encourage international cooperation on big science,'' adding that the huge machines were of ''unprecedented scope and importance.'' He also pledged to double the sceince foundation's budget by 1993.</p>
        <p>Absent a dramatic rise in the financing of small-scale scientiic research or a sudden reversal in the Administration's plans for big projects, many scientists foresee a serious decline in the health of American science, with eventual damage to the nation's economy.</p>
        <p>''We've got to make some serious decisions,'' said Dr. Stephen M. Younger, a physicist at the Los Alamos National Laboratory in New Mexico. ''I'm a fan of the supercollider. I think we should build the space station, too. But unfortunately, there are people sleeping in the streets and the Japanese are running circles around us on projects like high-temperature superconductors. That's going to kill us.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
