<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Quiet Side of the Delaware Shore</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="377818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WILDLIFE SANCTUARIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PRIME HOOK NATIONAL WILDLIFE REFUGE (DELAWARE)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">DELAWARE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">DELAWARE BAY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ACKERMAN, JENNIFER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Delaware</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wildlife Sanctuaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD6143BF93AA2575BC0A966958260" item-length="2218" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Quiet Side of the Delaware Shore</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jennifer Ackerman; Jennifer Ackerman is writing a book of essays on the natural history of the lower Delaware Bay region.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ACKERMAN, JENNIFER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A mosaic of marsh, woods and upland fields, Prime Hook National Wildlife Refuge on the southwest shore of Delaware Bay is a welcome relief from the crush of the Eastern Seaboard. Its 8,800 acres of rich land draw tens of thousands of migratory birds and relatively few people. Flocks of geese and ducks gather in the fall, shorebirds and warblers in the spring.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A mosaic of marsh, woods and upland fields, Prime Hook National Wildlife Refuge on the southwest shore of Delaware Bay is a welcome relief from the crush of the Eastern Seaboard. Its 8,800 acres of rich land draw tens of thousands of migratory birds and relatively few people. Flocks of geese and ducks gather in the fall, shorebirds and warblers in the spring.</p>
        <p>A mosaic of marsh, woods and upland fields, Prime Hook National Wildlife Refuge on the southwest shore of Delaware Bay is a welcome relief from the crush of the Eastern Seaboard. Its 8,800 acres of rich land draw tens of thousands of migratory birds and relatively few people. Flocks of geese and ducks gather in the fall, shorebirds and warblers in the spring. In summer glossy ibises, black like vanilla beans, forage in the shallow waters, along with great blue herons and other waders. Several species nest in the refuge, among them hawks, terns, ring-necked pheasants, least bitterns, rails and five kinds of dabbling ducks.</p>
        <p>Prime Hook is one of three natural places that I visit often on the flat coastal plain of lower Delaware. The others - Cape Henlopen, a sandy peninsula at the mouth of Delaware Bay, and Trap Pond, in the far south of the state - are also oases of open space and stopover points for migratory birds. They are not what you would call wilderness areas: at Prime Hook, cultivated fields mix with marsh, and dikes control the flow of water; World War II concrete bunkers and gun emplacements pepper the dunes at Cape Henlopen; Trap Pond was built to power a mill. Still, they are places within them that seem remote, even primeval.</p>
        <p>The best way to see the far reaches of Prime Hook is by canoe. And the best route is Prime Hook Creek, a narrow, sheltered stream that winds through more than seven miles of swampy woods and open marsh.</p>
        <p>Waples Mill Pond Canoeing rents aluminum canoes for use at the refuge and offers advice on trails.</p>
        <p>In early spring, at the creek's headwaters near the pond, I am stretched out flat in my canoe as it glides beneath a low-slung span of State Route 1. I have only an inch or two to spare between the nose of the boat and the bottom of the bridge. Then comes a corridor of low-hanging limbs and fallen trees, but soon the tangle of branches passes, along with the roar from the highway, as the watercourse widens and enters the refuge.</p>
        <p>The broad upper reaches of the creek invite probing along the swampy fringes. It is utterly quiet, except for the chatter of birds and the swish of paddles. Though tidal, Prime Hook Creek has virtually no current, so the paddling is easy and there's no need to time the trip for high or low tide. A melange of sweetbay magnolias, red maples and sweet gums dominate the banks. Prothonotary warblers flash golden yellow in the dark branches of the low brush. In spring, they nest on the banks in tree cavities or crannies only 5 to 10 feet from the ground. Off the creek, shallow ponds harbor nesting boxes for wood ducks and are good spots to watch the courtship displays of the colorful drakes.</p>
        <p>You can also see warblers and ducks from land at the refuge. The half-mile Boardwalk Trail wanders through woods and hedgerows, then follows a raised boardwalk into marshland studded with nesting boxes. But like Prime Hook's other two and a half miles of footpaths, this one is buggy in summer. Not the canoe trail. According to the refuge manager, George O'Shea, the deer flies that haunt Prime Hook's dryland paths avoid the water. And the mosquito, he said, ''is primarily a night animal.''</p>
        <p>Downstream, the canoe trail narrows and meanders through dense, swampy woodland. Blooming red maples canopy the stream, the reflective waters doubling their delicate pink blossoms. Along the banks grow stands of seaside alder, a rare, glossy-leaf shrub found only in Delaware, Maryland and two counties in Oklahoma.</p>
        <p>Woodland yields to a marsh of cattail and millet after a few miles, good habitat for river otters (the refuge has a population of 40 to 50) and muskrats, whose grassy, humped lodges appear by the dozen. At the end of the canoe trail near Refuge Headquarters, clouds of snow geese suddenly swirl up from the reedy screen. I drift, leaning back in my canoe to listen to the din and watch the shifting V's pass low overhead.</p>
        <p>Down the coast from Prime Hook, bay meets ocean at Cape Henlopen State Park, more than 3,300 acres of dunes, pinelands, marsh and open shore three miles east of Lewes. Change is the coin on this sandy peninsula. One day the wind is calm, the water smooth; the next it is howling yellow, heavy surf smacking the shore with each swell. One moment is stark white and night blue; the next all gray, silver, taupe and whey. Though the cape has existed for thousands of years, wind, waves and currents have changed its shape. Today the peninsula's seashore is moving west; its tip is moving north, growing 100 feet a year. Almost nothing here stays put.</p>
        <p>That goes for wildlife, too. With a shift in wind, Cape Henlopen is deluged with hawks or warblers or monarch butterflies, battered from a long bay crossing. After one recent rain storm, about 2,500 gannets sought refuge in the park's coastal waters, so close to shore you could see the twany heads and tapered bills of the giant white sea birds. More than 240 species of birds have been spotted at the cape, most of them migrants.</p>
        <p>A restored World War II observation tower offers views of the park (a rare pleasure in lower Delaware, where the bald cypress is the highest peak). The 70-foot concrete cylinder rises from the back slope of the Great Dune, a long sandhill that is moving south like some great migrating whale, burying the trees in its path. The tower was used to spot German U-boats and to aim the fire of shore batteries. Cool and damp inside, it echoes with reverberating footsteps on metal stairs. Viewing slats grid the walls with slanted bars of light. From the top platform, the landscape spreads before you flat as a sand dollar: to the north runs a large belt of pineland, where low swales support cranberry bogs with club moss and tiny insect-eating sundews. Beyond it, the cape curves like a scimitar into the heart of the bay. To the west lies spartina marsh, shot through with tidal creeks and fingerlike ridges of loblolly pine. The south belongs to sand dunes.</p>
        <p>Six miles of hiking trails wind through these areas. The Dune Overlook Trail, three miles long, starts near the tower and explores the walking dunes. These dunes once traveled 60 feet a year but have been slowed by the growth of vegetation. On their windward side appear bare tree forms that were covered by sand, then released, gaunt and skeletal, as the dunes moved forward. The dwarf pine on a sandy peak may be the topmost branches of a 30-foot tree. This is a troublesome place, hot, arid, shifting, but life holds on: the velvet ant, the pine lizard, the hairy wolf spider. In early morning, before the winds, the sand is scribed with the tracks of rabbits, snakes, mice and voles.</p>
        <p>One spur of the trail follows a ridge of pines through a prairie-like marsh of smooth cordgrass and whorls of finer salt hay. Now the domain of Northern harrier and white-tailed deer, the forested ridge was once a curved sand spit on the old cape's bay shore; the marsh was a shallow bay. Currents and rising sea level have reshaped the peninsula from a cockscomb of curved spits to its present bold profile.</p>
        <p>The two-mile Beach Loop Trail traces the finger-like spit of today's cape, starting at a parking lot on the bayside, arcing north around the tip, then south along the seaside and back to the lot. The point of the peninsula is a nesting ground for terns and the protected piping plover, a small, stocky shore bird the color of dry sand. The park sometimes closes the Loop Trail in summer during the plover's nesting season, so it's a good idea to check at the park office before starting out.</p>
        <p>In spring, Cape Henlopen's bay shore is anything but tranquil. It looks like the aftermath of battle, with the helmet-like shells of horseshoe crabs cast about in ragged lines. Amid the shells, hundreds of shore birds squabble and fret, jabbing aggressively at shallow pits in the sand. To see what all the fuss is about, I dig my finger into a pit and withdraw a clump of tiny pearly green pellets: the eggs of horseshoe crabs. At high spring tide, these arthropods emerge by the thousands to mate in the shallows of the bay and lay their eggs on the shores.</p>
        <p>Flocks of sanderlings, red knots, ruddy turnstones and other migratory shore birds descend from night skies to gorge on the crab eggs before continuing their trip from as far south as Tierra del Fuego to nesting grounds in the Arctic. The spectacle usually peaks in mid-to-late-May.</p>
        <p>To look up or down, to birdwatch or beachcomb: the conflict is constant. On the shores are perfect channeled whelks, jingle shells and clam shells, bone white on the inside and rayed with lavender. For me, wildlife most often wins out. Pods of dolphin play the margins of the sea, not 50 fifty yards offshore. Eighteen brown pelicans settle on the tip of the point. A twin, tight province of north and south, Cape Henlopen sees southern species such as the pelican at their northern limit, and true northerners such as the eider duck far south of their normal range.</p>
        <p>The freshwater swamp in and around Trap Pond State Park looks more like a Southern bayou than the bottomside of Delaware. Delaware's first state park, the pond lies 30 miles southwest of Cape Henlopen, near the town of Laurel. One of the northernmost stands of bald cypress in the country, this old mill pond and the park's surrounding 900 acres lie in the region once known as the Delaware Everglades, a 50,000-acre cypress swamp that supported trees well over 100 feet high and many centuries old. Few of the old-growth trees survive. Most went for shingles, posts and boats or were lost to peat fires that swept the area in 1930. Still, young cypresses grow tall and shaggy along the pond's margins and form thick swamps near its headwaters. The bulbous trunk of the tree stabilizes it in the soft mucky soils. The cone-shaped ''knees,'' which now and then sprout from the roots and protrude from the water, help support the tree and carry oxygen to its flooded roots.</p>
        <p>Though you can see the cypresses from points along the park's six miles of woodland paths, nothing beats wandering by boat through the maze of buttressed trunks and knees (except in wet summers, when warm, humid air alive with insects make the ride slow and itchy). A canoe trail leads from Trap Pond to Records Pond along the James Branch River, Delaware's best canoe stream. Survival Products in Salisbury, Md., about 15 miles south of Trap Pond, rents canoes for use on the trail. The clear, tea-colored waters of the James Branch flow through old stands of cypress, including one giant more than 500 years old and 33 feet in circumference. En route is a tiny place of wild beauty: Trussum Pond, where cypresses emerge from a black surface choked with white waterlilies and yellow-flowered spatterdock. This woodland swamp is hardly a shadow of the mature forest that once grew here. Still, it remains - like Prime Hook and Cape Henlopen - a small but essential blank spot on an otherwise crowded map.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO</p>
        <p>General Information Expect heavy traffic along the Delaware coast in the summer. On weekends, parking at Cape Henlopen is limited.</p>
        <p>Prime Hook National Wildlife Refuge. R.D. 3, Box 195, Milton, Del. 19968; 302- 684-8419. Open year round, sunrise to sunset.</p>
        <p>Cape Henlopen State Park, 42 Cape Henlopen Drive, Lewes, Del. 19958; 302-645-8983. Open year round, 8 A.M. to sunset.</p>
        <p>Trap Pond State Park, R.D. 2, Box 331, Laurel, Del. 19956; 302-875-5153. Open year round, 8 A.M. to sunset.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay Both Cape Henlopen State Park and Trap Pond State Park offer campsites from April 1 to Oct. 31 on a first-come, first-served basis.</p>
        <p>Cape Henlopen State Park, 42 Cape Henlopen Drive, Lewes, Del. 19958; 302-645-8983; $12 a night; 155 sites in a sandy pine forest, showers, picnic tables and sewage disposal.</p>
        <p>Trap Pond State Park, R.D. 2, Box 331, Laurel, Del. 19956; 302-875-5153; $8 to $10 a night; 140 sites, showers. Rates at the following are for two people a night in peak season. The Inn at Canal Square, 122 Market Street, Lewes, Del. 19958; 302-645-8499; $110 to $125 with Continental breakfast. Rooms overlook Lewes-Rehoboth Canal and are furnished with 18th-century reproductions.</p>
        <p>New Devon Inn, Second and Market Streets, Lewes, Del. 19958; 302-645-6466; $90 to $125 with Continental breakfast. Recently renovated; all rooms furnished with antiques.</p>
        <p>Savannah Inn Bed and Breakfast, 330 Savannah Road, Lewes, Del. 19958; 302-645-5592; $38 to $54 with vegetarian breakfast including homemade bread. Seven rooms with shared bath. No air-conditioning.</p>
        <p>Spring Garden Bed and Breakfast, R.D. 1, Box 283A, Laurel, Del. 19956; (302) 875-7015; $55 to $75 with country breakfast and complimentary wine and cheese. Historic home furnished with antiques.</p>
        <p>How to Go</p>
        <p>Canoe rentals for Trap Pond are available at Trap Pond State Park from 10 to 5 daily from Memorial Day to Labor Day, on weekends in September. Canoes for use on the James Branch River can be rented at Survival Products, 1116 North Salisbury Boulevard in Salisbury, Md.; 301-543-1244. Open year round from 9 A.M. to 6 P.M. Monday to Friday, 9 to 5 on Saturdays. Reservations accepted. For Prime Hook Creek, canoes are available at Waples Mill Pond Canoeing, R.D. 1, Box 138, Milton, Del. 19968; 302-684-8084. Open year round, sunrise to sunset. J. A.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
