<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BELIEFS</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="318357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Columns/Beliefs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Columns/Beliefs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DB103BF933A15752C0A966958260" item-length="976" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BELIEFS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Steinfels</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A century ago, science and religion were engaged in open combat. The relationship has now settled to something between cold war and polite indifference. Bitter skirmishes occasionally break out over evolution. Adventurous theologians or scientists occasionally carry peace proposals across the lines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A century ago, science and religion were engaged in open combat. The relationship has now settled to something between cold war and polite indifference. Bitter skirmishes occasionally break out over evolution. Adventurous theologians or scientists occasionally carry peace proposals across the lines.</p>
        <p>A century ago, science and religion were engaged in open combat. The relationship has now settled to something between cold war and polite indifference. Bitter skirmishes occasionally break out over evolution. Adventurous theologians or scientists occasionally carry peace proposals across the lines. In between these extremes, science and religion, as different approaches to understanding the universe, remain rivals for the ultimate allegiance of many educated people.</p>
        <p>It is this lingering rivalry that lends significance to the appeal, issued last Monday by 23 distinguished scientists, including three Nobel Laureates, for an alliance between religion and science to preserve the world's environment.</p>
        <p>Besides recognizing the power of religion to shape behavior, the 23 scientists said, ''Many of us have had profound experiences of awe and reverence before the universe.''</p>
        <p>''Efforts to safeguard and cherish the environment need to be infused with a vision of the sacred,'' they concluded.</p>
        <p>Citing the peril of global warming, the depletion of the onene layerththe extinction of plant a a animal e=ecies, the destruction of rain forests and the threat of nuclear war, they said such problems ''must be recognized from the outset as having a religious as well as a scientific dimension.''</p>
        <p>The call for joint action by science and religion was issued on the opening day of a conference in Moscow sponsored by the Global Forum of Spiritual and Parliamentary Leaders on Human Survival. More than a thousand religious, political and scientific leaders from 83 nations attended the conference, including members of the newly elected Supreme Soviet. Mikhail Gorbachev gave the closing address yesterday.</p>
        <p>Did the scientists' appeal for collaboration with religion signal a fundamental shift in the relationship of these two spiritual superpowers? Did it implicitly reject, for example, the tenet that religion, excepting those elements that science can verify, is a primitive approach to reality destined for extinction in a properly ordered world?</p>
        <p>Or was it simply a pragmatic recognition that religion, however unreasonable, is not apt to go away soon - and therefore ought to be put to as good a purpose as possible?</p>
        <p>What makes these questions especially intriguing is the appeal's author, the astronomer Carl Sagan. Ten years ago, in ''Cosmos,'' his popular television series and best-selling book, Mr. Sagan's attitude toward religion smacked more of the old antagonism than the new friendliness.</p>
        <p>This fact was noted not only by the conservative believers who objected to use of the series in public classrooms. John J. O'Connor, The New York Times's television critic, for example, complained that ''Cosmos'' treated science ''as a monolithic repository of 'truth.' '' Foremost among the program's assumptions, he wrote, ''is that science is infinitely superior to 'religion and superstition,' which are usually linked in Dr. Sagan's observations. Religion, especially, is characterized as being opposed to enlightened progress.''</p>
        <p>Has Mr. Sagan changed his views? Well, yes and no. ''I believe that my position has been perfectly consistent,'' he said before departing for Moscow. ''The idea of awe and reverence toward the cosmos permeated the series.'' ''My objection has never been to the religious instinct or impulse but to the bureaucratization of religion,'' he added.</p>
        <p>But he has also become increasingly aware of the universality of religion, Mr. Sagan said, and of its potential as ''a force for good.''</p>
        <p>Although other signers of his draft had sought to revise phrases about global warming or the ozone layer, Mr. Sagan said, not one had questioned the language about religion, reverence and the sacred.</p>
        <p>Does that indicate a striking readiness among at least one group of scientists to turn to an essentially religious vocabulary? Or does it merely indicate that a word like ''sacred'' is now open to virtually any meaning that individual signers would give it?</p>
        <p>One of those signers, Victor Weisskopf, a physicist who worked on the Manhattan Project to build the first atom bomb and an elder statesman of the scientific community, did not hesitate to affirm that religion is an independently valid way of understanding human experience, alongside science and art. ''There are realms in human experience that are outside science,'' he said this week.</p>
        <p>A second signer, Jerome Wiesner, former president of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and science adviser to President John F. Kennedy, emphasized scientists' hard-won recognition that they could not ''make a better world by our own efforts.''</p>
        <p>''I took 'sacred' to mean something that is overwhelmingly important in our eyes,'' Mr. Wiesner said. ''We have only one planet, and in that sense it is a sacred thing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wiesner's statement unintentionally points to another question about the scientists' appeal. Are they proposing a new common ground with religion that is, in fact, incompatible with the strong refusal of the Abrahamic faiths - Judaism, Christianity and Islam - to identify God with the world?</p>
        <p>The Rev. Richard J. Neuhaus, a Lutheran theologian, summed up the suspicion of some believers that the marriage of religion and environmentalism may give birth to is a new nature religion. ''Christians and Jews don't stand in awe and reverence before the universe,'' he said. ''They stand in awe and reverence before the Creator of the universe.''</p>
        <p>Yet such wariness has not kept over a hundred religious leaders from welcoming the scientists' appeal. Not all these leaders are theologically liberal, and many are surely aware of the appeal's ambiguous aspects. If they foresee difficulties, apparently these are outweighed by their sense of the planet's peril and the importance of bridging a gap between two of the great forces shaping the world.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
