<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CONGRESS TO TEST BILLS ON CLEAN AIR</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="336094"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900319T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D71E3EF93AA25750C0A966958260" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CONGRESS TO TEST BILLS ON CLEAN AIR</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Clean air legislation faces crucial tests this week in both the Senate, where amendments on the floor could unravel a compromise fashioned with the Bush Administration, and the House, where a bill is being readied in committee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Clean air legislation faces crucial tests this week in both the Senate, where amendments on the floor could unravel a compromise fashioned with the Bush Administration, and the House, where a bill is being readied in committee.</p>
        <p>Clean air legislation faces crucial tests this week in both the Senate, where amendments on the floor could unravel a compromise fashioned with the Bush Administration, and the House, where a bill is being readied in committee.</p>
        <p>The Senate amendments, dealing with smog in cities, auto emissions and benefits to displaced coal miners, are backed by environmentalists who say the compromise between the Senate's original bill and President Bush's proposal is inadequate to assure healthy air quality over the next decade. The compromise was drafted in closed negotiations between White House officials and senators, including the majority leader, George J. Mitchell of Maine. They oppose the amendments that will be offered starting Monday.</p>
        <p>Passage of one or more of the provisions could open the way for a nasty floor battle and raise the possibility of a veto by President Bush, who opposed the original Senate bill as too costly.</p>
        <p>In the House, the Energy and Commerce Committee is scheduled to start voting Tuesday on main elements of its bill to amend the Clean Air Act. The committee will have to wrestle with many of the same issues that gave Senate negotiators so much trouble.</p>
        <p>Debate on Fate of Miners</p>
        <p>These include requirements for cities that have not been able to reduce smog to levels set by the law, and proposals for mandatory automobile fuels that pollute less than gasoline.</p>
        <p>The first amendment likely to be voted on in the Senate is a proposal by Senator Robert C. Byrd, Democrat of West Virginia, to provide financial relief and job retraining for miners of high sulfur coal who might lose their jobs because of the plan now under consideration to control acid rain.</p>
        <p>The proposal, made after an impassioned speech by Mr. Byrd about his experiences in the coal fields and the hard lives of mining families, would provide up to four years of benefits to miners who are displaced as coal-fired electric power plants meet new anti-pollution requirements by switching from the high-sulfur coal generally mined in the East to the low-sulfur coal that generally comes from the West.</p>
        <p>Senator Byrd said his proposal would cost a maximum of $700 million. But Administration officials said they feared the amendment could be turned into a kind of welfare bill in areas where, for reasons unrelated to acid rain controls, the coal industry is in decline. In that case, the Senator's amendment could cost billions of dollars, the Administration officials warned, and suggested that its adoption could produce a Presidential veto of the clean air bill.</p>
        <p>An amendment strongly supported by environmentalists would restore a provision that was in the original bill requiring a second, mandatory round of controls on auto emissions in 2003 after the first such round called for in the compromise. The provision, being offered by Senators Tim Wirth, Democrat of Colorado, and Pete Wilson, Republican of California, would be implemented only if 12 or more cities were still violating the smog standards of the law by 2001. The Wirth-Wilson controls would go into effect unless Congress voted to cancel them.</p>
        <p>Federal Intervention Provision</p>
        <p>A third major amendment, to be offered by Senator John Kerry, Democrat of Massachusetts, would restore some of the changes made in the Senate negotiations that, he contends, weakened the tools needed to clean up the smoggiest cities. These include mandatory Federal plans for cleaning the air when state efforts are not sufficient. The compromise bill removed that provision, which was in the original 1970 Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>The same amendment would require cities with severe smog problems to force motorists to use fuels that pollute less than gasoline, like reformulated gasoline, alcohol and natural gas. The compromise bill includes a program for alternative fuels, but critics say it is not aggressive enough.</p>
        <p>Supporters of the amendments say they are optimistic. But a test of opposition to the compromise bill may have come in the earlier defeat in the Senate, 65 to 33, of an amendment offered by Senator Frank R. Lautenberg, Democrat of New Jersey, to restore provisions to control on emissions of toxic chemicals.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Senator Richard H. Bryan, Democrat of Nevada, withdrew an amendment opposed by the Administration that would have required improved fuel efficiency by automobiles to reduce carbon dioxide in exhaust. Carbon dioxide is the most important of the gases accumulating in the atmosphere that scientists believe will cause long-term global warming by retaining the sun's heat. Senator Mitchell promised to consider the proposal in another piece of legislation that would specifically deal with the global warming problem.</p>
        <p>Some 225 amendments in all have been scheduled, but Mr. Mitchell said last week that only a few of those would actually be offered on the floor.</p>
        <p>Paying for Acid Rain Control</p>
        <p>In the House committee, one issue that will likely provoke heated debate is how to share the costs of reducing emissions that contribute to acid rain. A proposal by Representative Philip R. Sharp, Democrat of Indiana, would impose a fee on factories, smelters and other sources of sulfur pollution in the air so that power plants would not bear the full burden. Coal-powered plants in the Midwest would be required by the pending legislation to make substantial reductions in their sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide emissions, which are the source of acid rain.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
