<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wild Bill Shakespeare in Central Park</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="365101"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="STAGE VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK SHAKESPEARE FESTIVAL</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NIGHTINGALE, BENEDICT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANTOON, A J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREEMAN, MORGAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ULLMAN, TRACEY</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">TAMING OF THE SHREW, THE (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED7173DF932A35754C0A966958260" item-length="1666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wild Bill Shakespeare in Central Park</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Benedict Nightingale</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NIGHTINGALE, BENEDICT</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Ten, fifteen years ago it was still an exception. Now it seems almost to have become the norm. Like it or mistrust it, the updating of Shakespeare is no longer an oddity, but a theatrical convention that all but the most squeamish of traditionalists must surely learn to accept.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Ten, fifteen years ago it was still an exception. Now it seems almost to have become the norm. Like it or mistrust it, the updating of Shakespeare is no longer an oddity, but a theatrical convention that all but the most squeamish of traditionalists must surely learn to accept.</p>
        <p>Ten, fifteen years ago it was still an exception. Now it seems almost to have become the norm. Like it or mistrust it, the updating of Shakespeare is no longer an oddity, but a theatrical convention that all but the most squeamish of traditionalists must surely learn to accept.</p>
        <p>Mark you, there is still plenty of room for creative debate. Precisely how are we to bring the 426-year-old William Shakespeare vividly to life in the world of Gorbachev and Madonna, Margaret Thatcher and Donald Trump? Is it always desirable or even permissible to update those antique costumes and relocate those far-off settings? For example, how is a producer to win a contemporary audience over to a play as alien, emotionally and chronologically, as the one the New York Shakespeare Festival is currently presenting in previews in Central Park? (The official opening is July 12.) Bring together ''The Taming of the Shrew'' and a director determined to make his production accessible and topical, and anything seems possible. Petruchio might be a grim mullah hauling an over-Westernized Katherina off to his minaret to instruct her in Islamic obedience. He might resemble Hugh Hefner, she Gloria Steinem. The action could then occur partly at Playboy headquarters, partly in the cabin of an executive jet. The denouement might consist of the former feminist submissively posing in a louche centerfold. That would set the audience's tongues wagging, as well as the Bard spinning in his grave.</p>
        <p>The director A. J. Antoon's solution for Central Park seems conservative by comparison. His ''Shrew,'' with Tracey Ullman in the title role and Morgan Freeman as Petruchio, is set in Oklahoma or thereabouts in the 1880's, when men walked tall and uppity women could count themselves lucky that electric cattle prods had not yet been invented. Critics will soon discover whether the tone of the production is ironic or straightforwardly comic, its tenor sexist or feminist, reactionary or radical, or something interestingly in between. What is certain is that out-of-period costumes and sets can have much more than a decorative effect. They may tilt interpretation, shape meaning. That is what can make them exciting. That is also what can make them damaging.</p>
        <p>Let's acknowledge at the outset how common they have become. When Joseph Papp announced the Public Theater's Shakespeare marathon in 1987, he said that a time-warped Bard would be ''the exception, not the rule.'' In fact, ''Taming of the Shrew'' is the ninth of the 14 plays so far presented to be updated. The characters of ''The Winter's Tale,'' ''Much Ado,'' ''Cymbeline,'' ''Love's Labor's Lost'' and ''Hamlet'' have variously disported themselves in 18th-century, Regency, Victorian, 1930's and modern dress. ''A Midsummer Night's Dream'' involved colonial potentates, Hispanic peasants and native Indians and their spirits in the Brazilian jungles. A fin-de-siecle ''Twelfth Night'' came with Riviera settings and a gambling casino. Christopher Walken, in black shirt and leather jacket, arrogantly mumbled his way through Steven Berkoff's Fascist ''Coriolanus.''</p>
        <p>Nor are things more conservative at the Shakespeare headquarters in England. So far this year the Royal Shakespeare Company has opened or revived seven productions of its house-dramatist's work, and only two have been set in Elizabethan times. The ghosts of Jane Austen, Byron and Noel Coward, respectively, hovered over ''All's Well,'' ''Pericles'' and ''As You Like It.'' ''The Comedy of Errors'' occurred in a Dali-esque dreamscape, peopled by figures in green and purple business suits. ''Troilus and Cressida'' combined khaki tunics with medieval breastplates and Grecian helmets, suggesting the characters were simultaneously fighting at the Somme, Agincourt and Marathon. Such mixed-period productions are becoming increasingly common, especially in Britain.</p>
        <p>But ''common'' is by no means a strong enough word for out-of-period Shakespeare in general. These days, it seems to be everywhere. Here is the American director Mark Lamos setting ''Hamlet'' in some banana republic, here the Englishman Michael Bogdanov transforming ''Henry V'' into a play about Falklands War jingoism, with bellicose slogans on the patriotic louts' T-shirts. Here is Lee Breuer's Deep South ''Lear,'' with a matriarch rather than a patriarch in the main role, and here Peter Hall's ''Coriolanus,'' with Ian McKellen sauntering through Rome in a natty white suit, a sword improbably draped over his shoulder. And why on earth not?</p>
        <p>After all, taste changes, imagination moves on. In the 18th century strict critics thought it better to rewrite Shakespeare than tolerate the ''improbability'' of a play whose plot lasted longer than the time it took to view it. That now seems absurd. But even in those persnickety times, they permitted Garrick's Macbeth to dress like a general in George I's army. Moreover, they expected this wigged redcoat to fight with a sword rather than pistols. If they could buy such incongruities then, we should have little problem accepting, for instance, a Petruchio who is described as coming to his wedding ''with a linen stock on one leg and a kersey boothose on the other'' - yet turns out to be wearing some weird combination of jeans and velvet pants. All we have to do is agree to take another step in that continuing process: the suspension of disbelief.</p>
        <p>Thus there was no need for Mr. Antoon to change the word ''Athens'' to ''this place'' or ''this town,'' as he did in his recent ''Midsummer Night's Dream.'' Why should audiences find it more difficult imaginatively to accept a Brazilian Greece than the Chinese one Tisa Chang presented in New York last year - or, of course, the flying circus in which Peter Brook famously located the play in 1971? The true problems faced by Shakespearean directors are far less superficial than that. What does updating the Bard add to the understanding and enjoyment of his work, and what does it subtract?</p>
        <p>At worst, it can draw attention to its own cleverness. Some critics felt that to be the case with JoAnne Akalaitis's ''Cymbeline'' at the Public Theater, with its antique bikes, its mustachioed villain, its parody Victorianism. Such trickery may also be a symptom of a larger, more life-threatening malady, a kind of gangrene of the play's spirit. Interpretation turns out to mean slant, and slant to mean shrinkage. ''Lear'' becomes a clinical study of senility, ''As You Like It'' ecological propaganda. ''The Tempest'' dwindles into a picture of colonialism, complete with an Ariel armed with Jomo Kenyatta's fly-whisk and clearly destined to become the prime minister of Prospero's imperial domains.</p>
        <p>There was some justification for the last of these productions, staged by Jonathan Miller in London a few years ago. Shakespeare was probably influenced by tall tales he had heard from the American colonies-to-be. But the author had something to communicate about private matters like hope, love, forgiveness, reconciliation, none of which seemed vastly to interest Mr. Miller. That is to say, the production emphasized one aspect of the play at the cost of others. It opted for modern relevance rather than entering the play's heart. That is an accusation that can be leveled at many a director less able than Mr. Miller. It is not so much what they do as what they do not do; not what their out-of-period productions achieve, but what they omit.</p>
        <p>Yet updating can illumine as well as diminish. Trevor Nunn's ''All's Well That Ends Well,'' which visited New York in 1983, set a battle scene on what appeared to be Platform 7 of the Florence railroad station 100 years ago. Yet the clanking, the steam and the Victorian uniforms actually unclogged a tricky play. The Jacobean code of honor, so vital to Shakespeare and so remote to us, became far more comprehensible when it was transposed to a world of officers, gentlemen, pomposity and priggishness more strongly inscribed on our mental maps.</p>
        <p>Again, virtually every London critic agreed that Bill Alexander's production of ''The Merry Wives of Windsor'' four years ago was the wittiest in memory. Somehow the 1950's setting - Mrs. Ford and Mrs. Page plotting revenge on Falstaff beneath dryers at the local hairdresser's - gave the play an immediacy and edge missing from more conventional revivals.</p>
        <p>It might be argued that out-of-period production is best suited to Shakespeare's comedies. His tragedies, being bigger and more complex, have more to lose. Update ''Lear,'' and you may end up with only those aspects of the play your chosen period is peculiarly fitted to illustrate. Yet Mr. McKellen gave what some thought his finest performance to date as Iago at Stratford last year, and did so not in Jacobean armor but in the kind of button-up uniform our grandfathers might have worn while crouched behind their Gatling guns. Somehow it added to the aridity, the thin-lipped ordinariness that made his interpretation so threatening.</p>
        <p>Again, modern dress failed to reduce Kevin Kline's production of ''Hamlet'' earlier this year into a case study of Danish bureaucracy or Elsinore office politics. Some reviewers felt it unobtrusively helped the cast, starting with Mr. Kline himself, give confident, unfussy performances.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, the test of a Shakespearean director and a Shakespearean production can be stated with almost embarrassing simplicity. It is surely not whether a play has been angled to preach some specific sermon about perestroika, the ozone layer or some other aspect of our world. It is whether it has acquired sharpness and eloquence yet retained its richness and intricacy. It is whether the performers have been liberated to find all the depth and variety that the text and their talents jointly allow. If that can somehow be achieved by setting ''The Taming of the Shrew,'' or any other play, in the 19th-century West or inside Stalin's Kremlin or on an iceberg in Antarctica in the year 2000 - well, who dares complain?</p>
        <p>STAGE VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
