<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fashion;   Just the Thing for Dazzling Everyone on the Avenue</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="56" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="337414"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HATS AND CAPS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EASTER</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOCKSWENDER, WOODY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD7163AF936A15750C0A966958260" item-length="529" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fashion;   Just the Thing for Dazzling Everyone on the Avenue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WOODY HOCHSWENDER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Come Easter, three weeks hence, some people will stick bunny ears through holes cut in their straw hats and take a stroll down Fifth Avenue. Others will place things like stuffed chickadees, wooden soldiers, origami tulips and dried fruit on their hats, as they take part in the annual procession past St.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Come Easter, three weeks hence, some people will stick bunny ears through holes cut in their straw hats and take a stroll down Fifth Avenue. Others will place things like stuffed chickadees, wooden soldiers, origami tulips and dried fruit on their hats, as they take part in the annual procession past St.</p>
        <p>Come Easter, three weeks hence, some people will stick bunny ears through holes cut in their straw hats and take a stroll down Fifth Avenue. Others will place things like stuffed chickadees, wooden soldiers, origami tulips and dried fruit on their hats, as they take part in the annual procession past St. Patrick's Cathedral.</p>
        <p>Maybe a few will go over to Henri Bendel's and buy an edibile Easter bonnet, an amazing merchandising breakthrough that allows one literally to eat one's hat.</p>
        <p>But this is not for them. This is for those who see themselves in an Irving Berlin song, on the avenue, Fifth Avenue, in springtime. This is for people who believe that hats are charming, and sound charming: the picture hat, the sailor, the stovepipe hat, the lampshade, the bubble beret, the platter - all part of the great lost language of clothes.</p>
        <p>This, frankly speaking, is for people who want to spend some money.</p>
        <p>Healthful and Fashionable</p>
        <p>Hats, of course, are a fine investment, given what is known about the ozone layer. They are also quite fashionable these days. On the ground floor of Bergdorf Goodman, one can find eloquent proof that fine millinery is no longer a vanishing art. There are dazzling hats by Anne Moore, who dresses everyone from Madonna to society women at Ascot, including a large picture hat with a clump of cabbage on top that radiates in the sun.</p>
        <p>At Macy's, Le Chapeau, a new shop on the third floor, has one of the most varied selections in the city. The hats by Eric Javits, including lace-embroidered derbies and lace pillboxes with chenille-dotted veils, are the kind you only wear on Sunday, with gloves.</p>
        <p>Downtown, one can rummage around Barneys New York for more avant-garde hats, including a few that look like they were crushed in the box. Barneys carries a couture variation on the Rasta tam, a little wool cap used to hold one's dreadlocks in place, but adapted into a porkpie.</p>
        <p>It is said that the lowering of automobile rooflines in the 1960's contributed to the demise of fancy hats even more than the onset of beehive hairdos. But even if one owns a Rolls, one has to be careful with hats.</p>
        <p>Matching the Face</p>
        <p>More than a garment, they are a frame for the face. They should be becoming to the personality and suitable to the occasion. (If one has a beehive, one should stick to pillbox hats, tiny little pillboxes, preferably pinned.) Easter bonnets these days seem to be extraordinarily expensive. But they are, in a sense, precious art objects. Where, for instance, can you buy a decent painting for $150? A well-worn millinery anecdote is apposite: A lady comes into the showrooms of Halston, who started out as a milliner. She is in a desperate hurry to find a hat for a cocktail party that evening.</p>
        <p>Halston takes a pink ribbon and twirls it around her head, pinning it, just so, here and there - wrapping, styling. Voila! ''It's marvelous,'' she said. ''How much?'' Six hundred and fifty dollars, she was told. ''Six hundred and fifty dollars,'' she gasped. ''For a ribbon?'' The designer carefully unwound the ribbon from her head and held it out in his hand and said, ''The ribbon, madam, you can have for free.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
