<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wyoming's Bonanza: Plentiful 'Clean' Coal</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="411547"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WYOMING</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCINNIS, DOUG</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wyoming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED81030F93BA15751C1A966958260" item-length="1444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wyoming's Bonanza: Plentiful 'Clean' Coal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUG McINNIS, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCINNIS, DOUG</byline>
      <dateline>BLACK THUNDER JUNCTION, Wyo.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eight times a day, an empty mile-long coal train eases into this desolate railroad junction. Each train leaves with some 11,500 tons of coal from the Black Thunder Mine, the nation's largest coal mine.</p>
        <p>A bonanza of easily mined, clean-burning, low-sulfur coal has transformed Wyoming in the last 15 years from a bit player into the largest coal-producing state in the nation. And changes in the Federal Clean Air Act enacted earlier this year to reduce acid rain are expected to keep mines operating at top speeds in the Powder River Basin, a 9,700-square-mile region between South Dakota's Black Hills and Wyoming's Big Horn Mountains. The region is home to the country's seven largest coal mines, including Black Thunder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Eight times a day, an empty mile-long coal train eases into this desolate railroad junction. Each train leaves with some 11,500 tons of coal from the Black Thunder Mine, the nation's largest coal mine.</p>
        <p>A bonanza of easily mined, clean-burning, low-sulfur coal has transformed Wyoming in the last 15 years from a bit player into the largest coal-producing state in the nation. And changes in the Federal Clean Air Act enacted earlier this year to reduce acid rain are expected to keep mines operating at top speeds in the Powder River Basin, a 9,700-square-mile region between South Dakota's Black Hills and Wyoming's Big Horn Mountains. The region is home to the country's seven largest coal mines, including Black Thunder.</p>
        <p>That is good news for the pack of big mineral companies, including ARCO, which owns Black Thunder. The companies poured into the area after air emission standards were tightened in the late 1970's. Those standards touched off a boom for clean-burning Western coal that even in recent years has produced annual sales growth rates of 8 percent. The new laws, which require a reduction in sulfur dioxide emissions of 10 million tons a year by the year 2000, may spur sales of this coal by an additional 3 percent or 4 percent a year, according to Jim Herickhoff, president of the Thunder Basin Coal Company, the ARCO subsidiary that operates the Black Thunder Mine.</p>
        <p>Powder River Basin coal is so low in sulfur that utilities that burn it can meet the new standards without installing multimillion-dollar pollution control systems. The basin has proven reserves of 56 billion tons, enough to supply the nation for more than 50 years at current consumption rates.</p>
        <p>But mining companies may have trouble extracting the coal quickly enough to meet the new demand. That could lead to price increases. "I would not be surprised if low-sulfur, low-ash coal would command a 15 to 20 percent premium over dirtier coal with the same heat content," said Kenneth Friedman, a mining analyst with Boettcher &amp; Company, a Denver brokerage firm. Buyers now pay very little premium, he said.</p>
        <p>The Federal Clean Air Act has created a quandary for environmentalists. While they approve of the sulfur emission standards, they worry about the effect that increased mining and larger-scale strip mining will have on plants, wildlife and scarce groundwater supplies in the basin, which includes a federally protected grassland.</p>
        <p>"If they mined even a tenth of the coal in the Powder River Basin, it would have a noticeable impact," said Ronn Smith, an officer of the Powder River Basin Resource Council, an environmental group that monitors the area.</p>
        <p>"A lot of people would say this is a great place to mine because there's nothing out here," he said. "We disagree. It's good ranch land."</p>
        <p>The mining boom started here after amendments to the Federal Clean Air Act were passed in 1977 that required cuts in sulfur dioxide emissions. Previously, the basin had been second choice for mining companies. Eastern coal enjoys an advantage because its heat content is up to a third higher than Western coal, while its transportation costs to Eastern markets are far lower. "You can buy all the coal you want for $5 a ton," said Ken Miller, Black Thunder's engineering manager. "But it costs you $12 to ship it to eastern Nebraska, $20 to Texas." In contrast, Eastern coal sells for $18 a ton and up.</p>
        <p>But Powder River Basin coal contains a maximum of one-half of 1 percent sulfur, compared with the 4 percent or 5 percent found in coal in Ohio, West Virginia and parts of Kentucky. When the cost of removing sulfur from Eastern coal is factored in, the Western coal is competitive.</p>
        <p>Mineral companies including ARCO, AMAX Coal Industries, the Exxon Coal and Minerals Company, the Shell Mining Company, the Peabody Coal Company and the Kerr-McGee Coal Corporation rushed in to meet demand for low-sulfur coal after the laws were enacted and production surged.</p>
        <p>Last year, Wyoming production hit 171 million tons, up from just 7 million tons in 1970. The Black Thunder Mine, which opened in December 1977, produced 29.6 million tons last year, more than double any other mine.</p>
        <p>Because of the Thunder Basin Coal Company, nearby Wright, with a population of about 1,400, has sprung up from virtually nothing in recent years. Further north, Gillette has grown to more than 20,000 residents in two decades, from about 2,000.  4,000 Jobs</p>
        <p>The production surge has produced some 4,000 jobs in a state that has staggered with the collapse of its oil industry and whose population has declined. The $225 million the state received in coal royalties and taxes in the 1990 fiscal year -- about 12 percent of its budget -- helped stave off a state income tax.</p>
        <p>In geological terms, the Powder River Basin is a marvel. Nowhere else in the world are there as many seams of coal 50 feet or more thick, said Jim McClurg, a professor of geology at the University of Wyoming. Coal seams in deep Eastern mines are generally 5 feet to 10 feet thick and can run as thin as 30 inches.</p>
        <p>And Powder River Basin coal is near the surface. These factors keep extraction costs lower than they are in the East.</p>
        <p>Even so, producers here may not be earning as much as their counterparts at Eastern mines. "On average, I would say Powder River coal is less profitable," said Dan Roling, coal analyst at Merrill Lynch Capital Markets. He said that because of the high cost of transporting the coal out of the area, Powder River producers have had to hold down prices to stay competitive.  'Margins Are Very Slim'</p>
        <p>"Our margins are very slim," said Curt Burton, a spokesman for ARCO Coal, referring to the Thunder Basin Coal Company, one of its three subsidiaries. "That doesn't mean we are not making money. But it's done on volume."</p>
        <p>ARCO Coal earned $64 million in the nine months that ended Sept. 30, down from $66 million a year earlier. ARCO will not say what portion of that comes from Thunder Basin, but the unit accounts for about 85 percent of the company's coal production. The subsidiary does not disclose sales.</p>
        <p>Like Eastern producers, coal mining companies here must also adhere to Federal laws requiring land reclamation. The Thunder Basin unit, for example, takes elaborate steps -- spending about $10,000 an acre -- to restore its mine site, much of which is within the Federal Thunder Basin National Grasslands.</p>
        <p>First, top soil is scooped off and saved. Then the remaining dirt and rocks that lie above the coal seams are used to fill strip-mine sites that dip hundreds of feet into the ground. This process flattens the hilly terrain.</p>
        <p>The top soil is returned, and the land is contoured to restore the flow of streams. More than 20 types of native grasses and shrubs are planted to re-create eastern Wyoming's arid grazing land. Straw is crimped into the newly planted ground to hold in precious moisture while the plants take hold.</p>
        <p>Lyle Randen, the mine's environmental manager, said the company also builds rock piles to provide habitats for small animals, and outcrops for birds.  Weight Gain for Cattle</p>
        <p>Water quality on restored land is very similar to what it was before mining, he said. Cattle that graze on reclaimed mine land have shown about double the weight gain that would have been expected for the area, he said.</p>
        <p>"We've proven at the Black Thunder Mine that we can reclaim the land to equal or better use than it was in its native state," Mr. Randen said.</p>
        <p>That does not mean the landscape has not changed. To fill coal seams of up to 70 feet wide, hills in the area are leveled. "The thing that results is a landscape similar to the surface of a pool table," said John Zelazny, conservation program director for the Wyoming Wildlife Federation. Contours are needed to maintain the variety of vegetation required for biological diversity, he added.  Effect on Ground Water</p>
        <p>The most pressing issue is the effect on groundwater, said David Alverswerth, director of the public lands and energy division of the National Wildlife Federation. "To my knowledge, nobody has reconstructed an aquifer," he said. "That is an almost impossible challenge for the mining industry."</p>
        <p>Now, conservation groups are waiting to see how the new clean air legislation ultimately affects the ecology of the West.</p>
        <p>"The big question is what kind of landscape we can expect once many miles have been reclaimed," said Mr. Zelazny of the Wyoming Wildlife Federation. "Nobody can tell what the landscape will look like 50 years from now. It may compact. It may all blow away. There aren't any 50-year-old reclamation sites around."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
