<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Defense Cuts Top Delegation's Agenda</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="314590"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILD CARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNORS (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND SOUND</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROWLAND, JOHN G (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MORRISON, BRUCE A (REP)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DD113AF934A35752C0A966958260" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Defense Cuts Top Delegation's Agenda</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: WEATHERING cuts in defense spending, reducing pollution in Long Island Sound and passing child care legislation for working families top the state's Congressional agenda for 1990.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: WEATHERING cuts in defense spending, reducing pollution in Long Island Sound and passing child care legislation for working families top the state's Congressional agenda for 1990.</p>
        <p>WEATHERING cuts in defense spending, reducing pollution in Long Island Sound and passing child care legislation for working families top the state's Congressional agenda for 1990.</p>
        <p>Some Connecticut lawmakers, including two who are running for governor, will have to find time between campaign stops to conduct their legislative business. The rest will be in the same boat as most members of Congress: trying to pass legislation at a time when the Government has no money.</p>
        <p>The 1990 gubernatorial election is expected to dominate the state's political news in the next 10 months and much of the attention will focus on Washington as United States Representatives John G. Rowland, Republican of Waterbury, and Bruce A. Morrison, Democrat of New Haven, begin campaigns for the state's top office. The delegation could get even busier if Representative Barbara B. Kennelly, Democrat of Hartford, contest.</p>
        <p>How will they find time to legislate in Washington and run for governor?</p>
        <p>'Working Twice as Hard'</p>
        <p>''By working twice as hard,'' Mr. Morrison said. ''I will continue to do my job. It will aid me in my race for governor that I will continue to be effective in my specific responsibilities in Washington.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rowland says he faces less of a problem because in his view ''we have a unique advantage of having the nomination pretty much sewed up.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. Morrison is hustling to muster convention support and votes for the primary, Mr. Rowland said, he will be concentrating on his job in Washington and preparing for the final election.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rowland and Mr. Morrison, along with virtually the entire eight-member Connecticut delegation in Washington, mentioned the impending cuts in the defense budget as a major local priority for Connecticut.</p>
        <p>''Connecticut very definitely needs both the Federal and state government to get heavily involved in planning for reduced military expenditures,'' Mr. Morrison said. ''We've got to make sure that Connecticut's peace dividend is not unemployed workers.''</p>
        <p>Two Strategies</p>
        <p>Mr. Rowland, a member of the House Armed Services Committee, said he has two strategies: to make sure Connecticut does not take an unfair share of the cuts and to create policies that will encourage businesses to convert to nonmilitary production and to hire unemployed defense workers.</p>
        <p>Representative Sam Gejdenson, Democrat of Bozrah, whose district includes the Electric Boat Division of General Dynamics, where nuclear submarines are built, has been a leader in the push to diversify the state economy and plans to continue working toward that goal.</p>
        <p>The state's two Senators, Christopher J. Dodd and Joseph I. Lieberman, both Democrats, will be the only members of the delegation not facing some kind of election in 1990. But their agendas appear full for the coming year.</p>
        <p>Senator Dodd has been running up a hefty long-distance telephone bill maintaining contacts in Central America amid the tumultuous developments there. A top priority for Mr. Dodd will be monitoring the Nicaraguan elections next month.</p>
        <p>Child Care Legislation</p>
        <p>Domestically, the top item on Senator Dodd's list - and also a key issue for Representative Kennelly - is child care legislation, which has come close to passing two years in a row. ''I'm hopeful, based on the statements made by the majority leader and others that they consider it a top priority,'' Mr. Dodd said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman, who ends his freshman year in the Senate, said that he would continue to push his environmental agenda. Among the first bills to be taken up this year by the Senate is the Clean Air Act, a revision that includes acid rain legislation important to Connecticut.</p>
        <p>Senator Lieberman said he would also focus on the continuing study of pollution in Long Island Sound. And he is seeking to establish Connecticut's first national park, at the Weir farm in Ridgefield. He said he does not plan to back down from his support of a capital gains tax cut, a position that drew some criticism last year in Democratic circles.</p>
        <p>Representative Christopher J. Shays, Republican of Stamford, counts himself among those who follow former House Speaker Thomas P. O'Neill's slogan that ''all politics are local.'' He listed the Federal budget deficit as his ''first, second and third'' local priorities.</p>
        <p>''Nothing is more important than that,'' Mr. Shays said. He also lists commuter rail service to New York and the cleanup of Long Island Sound as two other important measures.</p>
        <p>Representative Nancy L. Johnson, Republican of New Britain, sounds somewhat un-Republican when she lists child care, affordable housing, the Clean Air Act and a solution to the problem of trying to provide health care for the uninsured as her priorities for 1990. She heads a Republican panel looking into ways the Federal Government can help the uninsured without breaking the bank.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
