<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cleaner Air, at Last</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="395908"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DB1231F934A15753C1A966958260" item-length="537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cleaner Air, at Last</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After 13 years of official indifference, and against heavy odds, Congress has acted to clean the nation's air. A bill that would completely overhaul the Clean Air Act of 1970 now needs only formal approval by the Senate and the President's signature. Both are expected. Congress has worked too hard to turn back now. And Mr. Bush got the ball rolling in the first place.</p>
        <p>The 1970 law was a monument, passed early in the new era of environmental consciousness. It spared the United States the unregulated industrial pollution that afflicts nearly all Communist countries. But even as amended in 1977, the law ignored some problems and failed to keep pace with others. Three of five Americans still live in the hundred urban areas that fail to meet air quality standards -- despite annual spending of $35 billion, mostly by the private sector.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After 13 years of official indifference, and against heavy odds, Congress has acted to clean the nation's air. A bill that would completely overhaul the Clean Air Act of 1970 now needs only formal approval by the Senate and the President's signature. Both are expected. Congress has worked too hard to turn back now. And Mr. Bush got the ball rolling in the first place.</p>
        <p>The 1970 law was a monument, passed early in the new era of environmental consciousness. It spared the United States the unregulated industrial pollution that afflicts nearly all Communist countries. But even as amended in 1977, the law ignored some problems and failed to keep pace with others. Three of five Americans still live in the hundred urban areas that fail to meet air quality standards -- despite annual spending of $35 billion, mostly by the private sector.</p>
        <p>For the first time, the new bill would require action to stop acid rain. It would phase out the chemicals that destroy the ozone layer in the upper atmosphere. It would impose tighter restrictions on car exhaust and mandate cleaner gasoline, thereby reducing urban smog. And it would try to cut cancer-causing emissions around factories by 90 percent within 10 years.</p>
        <p>The bill does not go as far as many had hoped. Industry is given generous lead times to meet the requirements, and officials in high-pollution areas like New York City say the benefits will be too long in coming. But industry isn't happy either. The automobile, oil and utility companies face burdensome regulations and $25 billion in extra annual costs. The result, though, will be cleaner air -- and a fairer distribution of the burden for producing it.</p>
        <p>The responsibility for tackling urban smog, for example, is greatly enlarged. For years, much of the onus fell on the auto industry, and the new bill calls for making cleaner cars. But now, for the first time, the oil companies will be required to produce a cleaner gasoline for old as well as new cars. The retooling costs at refineries will be substantial; so will the reductions in smog-forming emissions and carbon monoxide.</p>
        <p>The bill does less than it might have to encourage the development of non-gasoline fuels like methanol, ethanol and natural gas. It offers two modest initiatives. One is a California pilot program that would mandate the production, by 1996, of a modicum of cars powered by fuels other than gasoline. Another provision would encourage non-gasoline fuels in fleet vehicles.</p>
        <p>Over all, this is an honorable bill -- and a tribute to a few legislators determined to surmount fierce pressures and their own personal rivalries to produce a workable compromise. Mr. Bush deserves great credit for first proposing to tackle a problem his predecessor cynically ignored. But there were moments when his interest flagged and other moments when his advisers seemed to disown the initiative.</p>
        <p>In the end, however, others held firm, notably George Mitchell, the Senate majority leader; Henry Waxman, the California Congressman who struck crucial tactical bargains with Representative John Dingell, champion of the auto makers; and Mr. Bush's own Environmental Protection Agency. His signature will honor their persistence.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
