<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Technology;   As Oil Prices Rise, the Hydrogen Car Is Looking Better</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="379451"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HYDROGEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHORTAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEUTSCH, CLAUDIA H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrogen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DF1E3CF935A1575BC0A966958260" item-length="1221" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Technology;   As Oil Prices Rise, the Hydrogen Car Is Looking Better</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA H. DEUTSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DEUTSCH, CLAUDIA H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: On the surface, the hydrogen-powered car looks as if it were made by a malevolent Rube Goldberg.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: On the surface, the hydrogen-powered car looks as if it were made by a malevolent Rube Goldberg.</p>
        <p>On the surface, the hydrogen-powered car looks as if it were made by a malevolent Rube Goldberg.</p>
        <p>It backfires like the cars in the old comic movies. Its engine knocks incessantly. Its fuel tanks are huge and unwieldy, yet it still can't go more than 100 miles, tops, before it needs refueling. And it costs a fortune to run.</p>
        <p>But no one is ready to dismiss the hydrogen car quite yet. In fact, now that Saddam Hussein's march on Kuwait has raised the specter of gasoline shortages and skyrocketing gasoline prices, hydrogen's status as one of the most abundant elements on earth is adding to its luster as a motor fuel.</p>
        <p>''The fact that hydrogen can be produced domestically is certainly in its favor,'' said Joan M. Ogden, a physicist at Princeton University. Added Stephen K. Lowe, chief of public affairs at Siemens Solar Industries, ''Another 40 days of war in the Middle East and people may not be talking about fuels just in terms of cost-effectiveness.''</p>
        <p>Even before the Iraqi invasion, there was good reason to push for hydrogen-fueled cars. Hydrogen burns squeaky clean, spewing forth little else but water vapor and non-troublesome amounts of nitrogen oxides. ''The payoff in improved environmental quality is so high that hydrogen cars merit more research,'' said Susan J. Hedman, director of policy research at the University of Maryland's Center for Global Change.</p>
        <p>Actually, in the early to mid-1970's, most car companies in the United States and abroad experimented heavily with hydrogen-powered cars. They all ran up against the same obstacles: It took more energy to get the hydrogen than the hydrogen itself provided. The processes for deriving that energy were polluting. And no one could figure out how to put enough gaseous or liquid hydrogen into a car to give it a decent cruising range.</p>
        <p>According to A. John Appleby, director of Texas A. &amp; M. University's Center for Electrochemical Systems and Hydrogen Research, a cylinder containing the energy equivalent of a gallon of gasoline in compressed hydrogen would weigh between 65 and 200 pounds. To say that it's better than electric - it would take a one-ton lead acid battery to give an electric vehicle the same energy as a gallon of gas - is faint praise.</p>
        <p>Liquid hydrogen gives three times as much energy as gasoline by weight, but takes up about three times as much space. And it must be stored at 423 degrees below zero or it will boil away.</p>
        <p>These problems have certainly dampened domestic ardor for hydrogen fuels. The Department of Energy spends only about $2.4 million a year on hydrogen research. Detroit, too, is concentrating on other alternative fuels like methanol or reformulated gasoline.</p>
        <p>''Hydrogen will just not be available at cost and volume that is appropriate for motor transportation for 20 or 30 years,'' said Nicholas Gallopoulos, who heads the General Motors Corporation's engine research department. The Ford Motor Company is ''looking at it, sure, but it is not on the front burner,'' said Donald R. Buist, director of Ford's automotive emissions and fuel economy office, who guesses that gasoline would have to hit $4 a gallon before hydrogen came close to being cost competitive.</p>
        <p>It is in Europe, where gasoline prices already are high, that research into hydrogen cars is proceeding apace.</p>
        <p>BMW, for one, has an experimental sedan with a modified 3.5 liter, six-cylinder engine that converts hydrogen liquid to gas in a heat exchanger when the engine is running. Many experts say BMW's research could lead to liquid-hydrogen-powered trucks and buses.</p>
        <p>Daimler-Benz has concentrated on hydrides, metal alloys like titanium iron and magnesium nickel that, when powdered, can absorb huge quantities of hydrogen. Heat from the exhaust or cooling system can free the hydrogen and send it to the engine.</p>
        <p>Over the last decade Daimler has tested two hydrogen systems. One used hydrogen alone in a 2.3 liter, four-cylinder engine, fitted with a hydrogen distributor instead of a carburetor and a system that injects water to prevent backfiring and to reduce production of oxides of nitrogen.</p>
        <p>The second combined gasoline and hydrogen for use in station wagons with fuel-injected, six-cylinder engines. The engine got only hydrogen when the car idled and only gasoline at cruising speeds.</p>
        <p>The tests, which were funded by the West German Government, proved that ''the operation of vehicles with hydrogen is possible and controllable,'' said Dr. Hans-Ulrich Hoss, Daimler's head of hydrogen research. He said Daimler has a project scheduled for next year to develop a hydrogen-powered bus with improved storage technology.</p>
        <p>Both BMW and Daimler report that hydrogen's reputation as a dangerous fuel is overblown. Unlike gasoline, it has no toxic fumes, and the famous pictures of the Hindenburg blowing up notwithstanding, it is no more explosive than natural gas.</p>
        <p>Moreover, it is easy to prevent it from accumulating to explosive densities. Hydrogen molecules are tiny enough to leak through minute cracks in storage containers but are so light they quickly float away. And it is fairly easy to mount hydrogen storage tanks on rear axles or other crash-insulated parts of the car, and to equip cars with electronic sensors that open vents or windows to let out any leaking hydrogen.</p>
        <p>The real sticking point is finding economical sources for hydrogen. Here, too, strides are being made. The European Community and Canada are testing the feasibility of using surplus hydroelectric power from rivers in Quebec to produce hydrogen. One of the game plans is to transport the hydrogen by ship to Hamburg, West Germany, where it would be used to run some 150 buses.</p>
        <p>In the United States, many researchers are hoping that breakthroughs in nuclear fusion or in solar energy will provide economical ways to fuel electrolysis, the process of making hydrogen by passing an electric current through water to split it into hydrogen and oxygen. In fact, there already have been great improvements in thin-film silicon solar cells, manufactured from silicon derived from sand and capable of cheaply converting sunlight into electricity.</p>
        <p>Some researchers suspect that solar hydrogen produced in the American Southwest would be roughly competitive with synthetic fossil fuels by the turn of the century. Mr. Lowe of Siemens could see photovoltaic cells fueling electrolysis near the sea, with the resulting hydrogen shipped to desert areas that would welcome it for its energy value and for the water it would yield.</p>
        <p>While everyone still argues about hydrogen in cars, it is already being used in planes, where volume of fuel is not nearly as important as weight. The Russians have developed an airplane that flies on liquefied hydrogen. The National Aeronautics and Space Administration, meanwhile, is studying whether slush hydrogen, a hydrogen slurry that takes up less space than liquid hydrogen, is a good idea for the space shuttle.</p>
        <p>The Shuttle already uses hydrogen fuel cells, battery-like devices that, in Dr. Appleby's view, represent the best scenario for using hydrogen in cars.</p>
        <p>''Instantly rechargeable electric vehicles equipped with lightweight hydrogen fuel cells would have three times the fuel efficiency of the internal combustion engine under urban conditions,'' he said. ''This is where the future should go.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
