<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Microbial Agents May Help Kill Crop Pests</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="367239"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PESTICIDES AND PESTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MICROBIOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Microbiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDE113DF933A25754C0A966958260" item-length="2189" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Microbial Agents May Help Kill Crop Pests</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ARMIES of bugs and microbes, their powers enhanced in some cases by genetic engineering, are being unleashed in fields and laboratories in a widening effort to control destructive agricultural pests without resorting to chemical pesticides.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ARMIES of bugs and microbes, their powers enhanced in some cases by genetic engineering, are being unleashed in fields and laboratories in a widening effort to control destructive agricultural pests without resorting to chemical pesticides.</p>
        <p>ARMIES of bugs and microbes, their powers enhanced in some cases by genetic engineering, are being unleashed in fields and laboratories in a widening effort to control destructive agricultural pests without resorting to chemical pesticides.</p>
        <p>The effort includes a major expansion of the classical form of biological control, in which insects' natural enemies are imported and set loose in the fields. More and more farmers are now deploying mass-produced battalions of pest-killing insects and parasites, and the number of biological agents available to them has more than doubled over the last decade.</p>
        <p>But beyond that, researchers are deciphering the ways in which a wide variety of microorganisms kill or suppress other microbes, weeds, fungi and insects that destroy crops and diminish agricultural yields. They are using this knowledge to custom-design better new biological agents through genetic engineering.</p>
        <p>Although biological control accounts for only about 1 percent of the $20 billion spent globally on pest control each year, research is rising sharply.</p>
        <p>''There's a big information explosion,'' said Dr. R. James Cook of the Department of Agriculture's biological control research unit at Washington State University, who headed a 1987 study of the subject by the National Academy of Sciences. Ten years ago, he said, perhaps 1 percent of the 500 or so scientific papers presented at annual meetings of plant pathologists dealt with biological control; today, 25 to 30 percent do.</p>
        <p>Eleven microbial pest-control agents have been approved for commercial use by the Environmental Protection Agency since 1980; five of the approvals have come in the last two years, and at least three more are expected this year. About half of all applications from pesticide manufacturers for permission to do field research now involve biological controls, said William Schneider, a microbiologist in the agency's office of pesticides - an ''almost exponential'' rate of growth.</p>
        <p>On one research frontier, scientists are isolating and mass-producing genes from one strain of bacteria that produces an antibiotic that kills disease organisms. They are transferring the genes to other varieties of bacteria, creating new strains that can use the same antibiotic.</p>
        <p>By such gene transfers, they hope to tailor-make microorganisms that can control diseases in environments where none otherwise would; to enhance the potency of control microbes; to make a single strain of microbe effective against more than one pest, and to design control microbes that will commit suicide after doing their job. In a parallel effort, they are also trying to incorporate disease-resistant genes in the crops themselves, and some of these agents are expected to be commercially available in the next five years.</p>
        <p>Scientists are also delving into the enormously complex ecology of the soil to understand the teeming microbial communities whose interactions partly determine the health of crops. Biological control is primarily an exercise in manipulating this largely unexplored micro-environment. There, microbes and higher forms engage in a constant struggle, in which organisms harmful to crops are often held in check naturally; humans are seeking to enhance, augment and guide the process.</p>
        <p>Fungus 1, Moth 0</p>
        <p>In a striking display of pest control occuring spontaneously in nature, a wild fungus first identified only a year ago has greatly reduced the defoliation of Northeastern forests this summer by what scientists had feared would be one of the most destructive gypsy moth infestations in years. A lot remains unknown about the fungus, but scientists hope they can ultimately understand it well enough to adopt it as a weapon against gypsy moths in many parts of the country.</p>
        <p>The resurgence of interest and research is being driven by a number of pressures. Many scientists and environmentalists believe that chemical pesticides are contaminating the environment. They say, furthermore, that production of the chemicals depends too heavily on energy from fossil fuels to be indefinitely sustained, and that some chemical pesticides are losing their effectiveness as pests develop resistance to them. And an aroused public, fearing dangerous residues in foods, is turning thumbs down on chemical pesticides.</p>
        <p>Some experts believe that biology will eventually overtake chemistry as the predominant means of pest control. ''It's going to have to,'' said Lester E. Ehler, a professor of entomology at the University of California at Davis. But he and many others say biological agents are not a total answer.</p>
        <p>''It's dangerous to rely solely on biological control because it doesn't always work,'' said Dr. Ehler. Ideally, he and other scientists say, biological controls should be used as part of an integrated approach that also involves crop rotation, new strains of disease-resistant crops and some chemical pesticides - with chemicals used sparingly, as a last resort.</p>
        <p>''It is not a quick-fix silver bullet,'' Dr. Cook said of biological pest control. As promising as it is for a broad range of plant diseases and insect pests, it is much less so for weeds and some fungi.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, he said, chemical pesticides fail to control many diseases, particularly root diseases of field crops. ''I see biological control as filling a major gap that has simply been left by the inadequacies of chemical control,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Microbes Have Their Limits</p>
        <p>Whatever their inadequacies, synthetic chemical controls have ruled modern agriculture since World War II. Overshadowed by the chemicals, research on biological languished until the 1980's. Part of the difficulty has been the limitations inherent in biological control.</p>
        <p>A microbe might work in one part of the country but not another, or in one season but not another. And although biological agents tend to be more stable and longer-lasting, they generally do not bring about the dramatic kill that chemical pesticides can; rather, they hold the pests within tolerable bounds. All this makes companies reluctant to stand behind guarantees.</p>
        <p>Biological agents have a big economic drawback as well: unlike chemical pesticides, they do not control a broad spectrum of pests. A given agent works against one pest on one crop and may require only one application. This creates a narrow ''niche market'' that many large manufacturers find unprofitable.</p>
        <p>Much of the resurgent research is aimed at overcoming these limitations.</p>
        <p>For a century, farmers have been practicing ''classical'' biological control: the loosing of predatory insects, parasites and nematodes against insect pests and weeds. Today, about 50 such agents are sold in the United States. This is more than double the number available a decade ago, Dr. Ehler said, ''and the list is growing year by year.''</p>
        <p>''A farmer can call up a supplier and say, 'I need 50,000 parasites,' and put them out,'' he went on. In one of the best examples so far, he said, mites that afflict California strawberries have been successfully and routinely countered by turning predatory mites loose against them.</p>
        <p>''Growers have started opting for biological control,'' Dr. Ehler said. ''It's been available for 30 years, but they've only recently started using it because they've been forced into it by problems with pesticides.''</p>
        <p>The Scientific Obstacles</p>
        <p>Even so, there are scientific obstacles. Two-thirds of all natural enemies introduced as classical control agents have failed to become established, said Dr. Ehler. The challenge, he added, is to predict what will work and what will not.</p>
        <p>But even greater challenges confront scientists who are trying to turn microorganisms against crop diseases. Researchers at the University of Wisconsin have lately discovered a new control agent, bacillus cereus UW85, and are unraveling the mechanism through which it suppresses the fungus phytophthora, which attacks the roots of alfalfa and soybeans.</p>
        <p>They have found that late in its growth cycle, UW85 produces an antibiotic that attacks the fungus. So they applied bacteria of the right age to soybean seeds and planted them.</p>
        <p>The results were mixed, said Jo Handelsman, the leader of the project. Over four seasons, soybean yields increased by as much as 42 percent in some fields but not at all in others. ''It works very well in the upper Midwest, but does not seem to work in the South,'' she went on. ''In Missouri and Mississippi, it was a total and complete washout.''</p>
        <p>Researchers in the Department of Agriculture laboratory at Washington State University have had a similar experience with a bacterium that controls a fungal disease called take-all. A major pathogen for wheat crops around the world, take-all can cut crop yields in half and is not well controlled by chemical pesticides.</p>
        <p>But again, said Dr. Cook of the laboratory, ''we have a certain number of failures because the organisms do not like the environment we put them in.''</p>
        <p>Custom-Made Bacteria</p>
        <p>One way to overcome such inconsistencies may be through genetic engineering. So the Washington researchers are trying to customize bacteria for given environments. They have discovered the mechanism through which the bacterium works: an antibiotic, phenazine-1-carboxylic acid, that it produces on wheat roots. In studies conducted by Dr. Linda Thomashow and Dr. L. S. Pierson, the gene responsible for producing the antibiotic has been isolated and cloned, and is now being inserted into other bacteria.</p>
        <p>A next step would be to insert the antibiotic gene into bacteria that would flourish in environments where the original antifungal bacterium cannot. It might also be inserted into bacteria that control other diseases. Some researchers envision the genetic engineering of microorganisms that would attack a variety of pests, as chemical pesticides now do.</p>
        <p>Other researchers foresee using genetic techniques to make biological control agents more powerful. ''What we'd like to be able to do is increase the virulence'' of an agent, said Olen C. Yoder, a plant pathologist at Cornell University, ''but retain its specificity so that it would never harm anything but the target.'' Furthermore, he said, it should be possible to construct biological agents so that they ''do their job and then commit suicide so that they don't persist in the environment,'' where there is a remote chance they could exchange genetic material with natural organisms.</p>
        <p>Other researchers are inserting pest-control genes into plants. At the Monsanto Company in St. Louis, for example, scientists are routinely introducing genes into nearly three dozen vegetable crops, hoping to enable them to repel insects. Commercial introduction of some of the agents is planned for the mid-1990's.</p>
        <p>Against 'Magic Bullets'</p>
        <p>Some scientists warn against such strategies, especially if they are viewed as magic bullets to be used in disregard of the ecology of the fields, much as chemical pesticides have been. ''That's a simple-minded solution,'' said Dr. Majorie Hoy, an entomologist at the University of California at Berkeley. Introducing pest-control genes into plants might work, she said, ''but it certainly can induce resistance in pests, and it can have negative effects on beneficial insects.''</p>
        <p>Many scientists see the proper use of biological controls as being inseparable from a broader strategy of manipulation of the microenvironment of the soil and the field. So some are focusing their research on understanding the ''communities'' of microbes, harmful and beneficial, whose interactions in large part determine the health of crops.</p>
        <p>Chemical pesticides tend to destroy these communities, but researchers are finding that the communities themselves, if left to function freely, can hold plant diseases in check through natural competition. ''It's there, but it's not breaking out as a disease or a pest,'' said Stephen Gliessman, an agricultural ecologist at the University of California at Santa Cruz.</p>
        <p>When the Chemicals Stop</p>
        <p>Chemical pesticides wipe out not only pests but also the beneficial organisms that compete with them. In a three-year-old study of the ecology of plots of strawberries, a group headed by Dr. Gliessman is looking at what happens when the use of chemical pesticides ceases. ''We predicted that we were going to get a buildup of pathogens, fungi primarily, that would force us to abandon the soil after a couple of years,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The disease organisms did multiply. But to the researchers' surprise, so did a whole range of other microorganisms that began to function as a balanced whole, with no one strain of organism winning out. ''It's the diversity and the numbers that keep pathogens in check,'' said Dr. Gliessman.</p>
        <p>The next step is to try to identify the ways in which the organisms interact, with an eye toward manipulating the microecology so that beneficial organisms, genetically engineered and otherwise, can operate in it effectively and permanently.</p>
        <p>''In biological control, we talk about a balance,'' said Dr. Hoy. ''You maintain some pests at low levels to maintain the beneficials; they've got to eat something.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
