<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Baking Soda Maker Strikes Again</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="361439"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER BEHAVIOR</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CHURCH &amp; DWIGHT CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FEDER, BARNABY J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MINTON, DWIGHT C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">EGAN, WILLIAM C (CO EXEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">VOLK, SPENCER J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D6143EF935A25755C0A966958260" item-length="1621" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Baking Soda Maker Strikes Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARNABY J. FEDER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FEDER, BARNABY J</byline>
      <dateline>PRINCETON, N.J.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Nearly 150 years after the family-run business that became the Church &amp; Dwight Company began making baking soda, a new and more aggressive management and the environmental movement are breathing new life into the company's famous Arm &amp; Hammer trademark.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Nearly 150 years after the family-run business that became the Church &amp; Dwight Company began making baking soda, a new and more aggressive management and the environmental movement are breathing new life into the company's famous Arm &amp; Hammer trademark.</p>
        <p>Nearly 150 years after the family-run business that became the Church &amp; Dwight Company began making baking soda, a new and more aggressive management and the environmental movement are breathing new life into the company's famous Arm &amp; Hammer trademark.</p>
        <p>Dwight C. Minton, the chief executive whose great-great-grandfather started the enterprise in 1846, decided three years ago that his company had outgrown the leadership skills of the founding family. Today, Mr. Minton, who is 55 years old, is sharing the job of running the company with a team of experienced executives recruited from marketing powerhouses like Procter &amp; Gamble and Johnson &amp; Johnson.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Minton says, the company is equipped to improve its marketing of existing baking, cleaning and deodorizing products and also extend its trusted Arm &amp; Hammer trademark to new products like deodorants, shampoos, skin-care items and mouthwash. Church &amp; Dwight is also pursuing more exotic applications for sodium bicarbonate, the key mineral compound in Arm &amp; Hammer products, and the other minerals it produces. It has developed an environmentally friendly paint-stripping compound, an air-pollution-control substance and a system for removing lead from water systems. ''To ignore the environmental movement's implications for our company would be actionable,'' Mr. Minton said. ''It fits so much of what we do.''</p>
        <p>Company executives are also optimistic about the growth prospects for Megalac, an additive for dairy-cow feed, and sodium bicarbonate products that help cows digest the rich foods they are given to increase milk production.</p>
        <p>It is not the first revival for Arm &amp; Hammer, of course. In the 1970's, shortly after the first Earth Day, Church &amp; Dwight gained a foothold in the detergent business with a phosphate-free product that used sodium bicarbonate. It also built a new market for baking soda - deodorizing refrigerators.</p>
        <p>This time, the company considers itself better prepared to attack the new opportunities systematically, and investors seem to be sharing the optimism. Most analysts are cautious about the stock at the moment, but only because the price has nearly doubled in the last year. [In over-the-counter trading Friday, the shares closed unchanged at $20 each.]  ''They appear to be doing all the right things,'' said Mark Kurland, who follows the company for Mabon, Nugent. ''But I'd say it's fairly priced now at over 17 times projected 1990 earnings.''</p>
        <p>Wall Street analysts expect the company to earn about $21 million this year, up from $8.7 million last year, when results were depressed by an $11.7 million write-off related to the sale of two businesses. Revenues are expected to be about $410 million, up from $388 million.</p>
        <p>Anti-Pollution Products</p>
        <p>Some of the run-up seems to have stemmed from investor interest in companies that are likely to prosper from the stricter environmental standards being imposed by all levels of government. Sodium bicarbonate, when fed into a smokestack, can absorb the chemicals that cause acid rain before they are emitted. It is probably not competitive with other technologies in larger plants, but Church &amp; Dwight hopes to find a growing market in smaller municipal and industrial power plants.</p>
        <p>Investors attracted to the company as an air-pollution play have also discovered its new paint stripper, which the company hopes will begin paying back development costs by the end of the year. The product, known as Armex, was invented to help restore the Statue of Liberty in 1986 and can strip paint without the use of toxic solvents in a process that resembles gentle sand-blasting.</p>
        <p>A Top Trademark</p>
        <p>In the Arm &amp; Hammer trademark, the company has a firm foundation on which to build. Homes without the distinctive yellow Arm &amp; Hammer baking soda box, with its famous red-ringed logotype of a cocked, muscular arm holding a hammer, are few.</p>
        <p>By one estimate, Arm &amp; Hammer baking, deodorizing or cleaning products are used in 95 percent of American homes. A recent Arizona State University study indicated that the trademark was recognized by 92 percent of respondents, making it one of the nation's top five trademarks. That name recognition has allowed the company to repel many attempts over the last century to erode Church &amp; Dwight's dominance in consumer products based on sodium bicarbonate.</p>
        <p>''Arm &amp; Hammer is as American as apple pie,'' said Spencer J. Volk, who is 56 and brought 30 years of experience at Procter &amp; Gamble, Pepsico and the Beatrice Company to the position of president and chief operating officer that Mr. Minton created last summer. ''Heck, it's in the apple pie.''</p>
        <p>There is not much doubt in Mr. Minton's mind that Church &amp; Dwight would have choked on its growth opportunities without its recent management changes.</p>
        <p>The company had grown from revenues of just $16 million when Mr. Minton succeeded his father as chief executive in 1969, to $318 million in 1987. But it approached the end of the 1980's with a highly personal management style and a strategy more suited to a small company founded in the last century than to the modestly diversified enterprise it had become.</p>
        <p>To be sure, Mr. Minton had overseen more strategic hits than misses. But there were more surprises both good and bad than there should have been. The laundry detergent business, for example, turned out to be far more prosperous than the company had imagined when it introduced a phosphate-free product in 1970, but it took 15 years to come up with the right pricing strategy. Now, detergents priced at a 20 percent discount to Procter &amp; Gamble's Tide, the market leader, are Church &amp; Dwight's biggest revenue generator.</p>
        <p>Poorly Planned Expansion</p>
        <p>On the other hand, poorly planned expansion led to the growth of an unwieldy distribution system. And earnings failed to keep pace with revenue growth, which disappointed both analysts and family members, who still control 43 percent of the shares.</p>
        <p>''My confidence in how much I knew probably peaked about the time I took over,'' said Mr. Minton, a Stanford Business School graduate who was just 34 when he became chief executive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Minton set out to gather expert support by recruiting men like Mr. Volk; Anthony P. Deasey, 41, who came in 1988 from Chesebrough-Pond's to become chief financial officer, and William C. Egan 3d, 45, who joined the company in April to head the Arm &amp; Hammer division after 16 years at Johnson &amp; Johnson. Stephen Bershied was also lured from Procter &amp; Gamble in April to become head of research and development.</p>
        <p>Changes Are Planned</p>
        <p>As the new executive team takes hold at Church &amp; Dwight's modern headquarters in a leafy glade on the outskirts of this university town, the company is acting increasingly like the $1 billion business it fully expects to become within a few years.</p>
        <p>These are among the changes:</p>
        <p>* Consolidation of the distribution system, after a study by the consulting firm A. T. Kearney recommended a reduction from 21 to 14 sites.</p>
        <p>* More regular price increases to lift profit margins on products like baking soda, where the company controls 85 percent of the market.</p>
        <p>* A strategy to encourage licensing the Arm &amp; Hammer trademark to others incorporating the company's sodium bicarbonate in their products, like agricultural companies that include it in feed mixes or, most recently, Johnson &amp; Johnson, which is using it as a deodorizer in sanitary napkins.</p>
        <p>* More strategic partnerships patterned after the company's joint venture with the Occidental Chemical Corporation, which produces potassium bicarbonate, a mineral used in fire extinguishers and television picture tubes. The company is working with three leading European chemical companies - ICI of Britain, Henkel &amp; Cie of West Germany and Solvay &amp; Cie of Belgium - to establish European markets for Armex, the industrial paint stripper. Through a partnership with Schmidt Manufacturing Inc., Church &amp; Dwight has developed equipment to apply Armex to the automotive, aircraft and other markets.</p>
        <p>* Investment in the electronic reporting service of Information Services Inc., which gives headquarters faster and more sophisticated analyses of consumer buying patterns and the effect of sale promotions.</p>
        <p>* More consumer-use surveys like last year's study that turned up the surprising result that people who use baking soda as a deodorizer in refrigerators think they change the box every four months, but actually do so every 14 months. That led to a new advertising campaign geared to seasonal reminders to replace the box.</p>
        <p>Despite signs that Church &amp; Dwight is thinking bigger and more analytically, executives remain aware that they are a long way from true market power in a world where they repeatedly bump up against multinational behemoths like Procter &amp; Gamble, Unilever and Colgate-Palmolive.</p>
        <p>A Price Follower</p>
        <p>In most consumer markets, Church &amp; Dwight must be a price follower, whether it is in detergents that the company prices at a discount to the market leader or toothpastes, where its product is sold at a premium. Thus, the company's profit margins are at the mercy of its competitors.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the industry giants have the manufacturing, distribution and advertising budgets to drastically change the balance of power with new products in a matter of months. When Procter &amp; Gamble recently began test-marketing concentrated detergents in small packages in the Southwest, after discovering they had been rapidly embraced in Japan, alarm bells went off in Princeton.</p>
        <p>''As soon as I arrived and learned what was going on,'' said Mr. Egan, the Arm &amp; Hammer division chief, ''developing our own concentrate became my most urgent project.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
