<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Greening the Cabinet</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="320019"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CABINETS AND SUB-CABINETS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DF173CF936A15752C0A966958260" item-length="326" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Greening the Cabinet</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In proposing to promote the Environmental Protection Agency to cabinet status, President Bush yesterday pre-empted attention for a costless project that Congress, eager to strike blows for the environment, is likely to approve anyway. The idea sounds good; it may even do some good.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In proposing to promote the Environmental Protection Agency to cabinet status, President Bush yesterday pre-empted attention for a costless project that Congress, eager to strike blows for the environment, is likely to approve anyway. The idea sounds good; it may even do some good.</p>
        <p>In proposing to promote the Environmental Protection Agency to cabinet status, President Bush yesterday pre-empted attention for a costless project that Congress, eager to strike blows for the environment, is likely to approve anyway. The idea sounds good; it may even do some good.</p>
        <p>The cabinet is not as exclusive as it used to be. George Washington was served by four cabinet officers - the secretaries of State, Treasury and War and the attorney general. It was not until 1953, with the birth of the department now called Health and Human Services, that the pressure for prestige began to mount. Its most recent and parochial product was the elevation of the Veterans Administration.</p>
        <p>The cabinet has now swollen from four members to 14; a Department of Environment would make No. 15. The institution long ago ceased being a group of intimates from whom Presidents might seek serious advice. It's become an outer cir-cle, which with each added member grows more and more distant from the center of power.</p>
        <p>Still, the Environmental Protection Agency has as good a claim as any to membership because of its wide responsibilities. William Reilly, the present administrator, already enjoys a close relationship with Mr. Bush, but future chiefs may benefit. Even if sliced 15 ways, cabinet rank carries some stature that may help the E.P.A. head on Capitol Hill and in interagency committees.</p>
        <p>Ohio's John Glenn, who promoted the bill in the Senate, believes cabinet rank will also help abroad, now that worldwide solutions are required for the new environmental issues of ozone layer depletion, climate warming and the destruction of tropical forests. The United States is the only industrialized country whose environmental minister is of subcabinet rank.</p>
        <p>In proposing cabinet status for the environment, Mr. Bush and Congress heed the legislative symbolism of promoting a better environment. Now comes the harder part - laws to do so in substance.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
