<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Presto! Science Joins the Birthday Party</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="380930"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARTIES (SOCIAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENBERG, MERRI</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KREVER, RITA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDB1739F931A3575AC0A966958260" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Presto! Science Joins the Birthday Party</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MERRI ROSENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENBERG, MERRI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE good-natured shouts, teasing and playful behavior of the nine boys at Toby Roberts's birthday party in Mamaroneck were typical for 9-year-olds. So, too, was the idea of entertainment, without which no suburban party seems to be complete.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE good-natured shouts, teasing and playful behavior of the nine boys at Toby Roberts's birthday party in Mamaroneck were typical for 9-year-olds. So, too, was the idea of entertainment, without which no suburban party seems to be complete.</p>
        <p>Welcome to a ''Mrs. Wizard'' science birthday party. If the idea seems a contradiction in terms - Science? Fun? Birthday? - Mrs. Krever's scientific sleight of hand soon dispels any idea that science has to be boring.</p>
        <p>Creations and Explanations</p>
        <p>As the children dropped water into a mysterious powder and licked their fingers with glee when that mixture somehow became Jell-O, or created swirling colored designs with food coloring, milk and dishwashing liquid, Mrs. Krever kept up a steady patter explaining the scientific reasons for what was happening.</p>
        <p>A well-shaken Diet Coke bottle that inflates a balloon offers a lesson in the benefits of carbon dioxide and oxygen. To present a graphic illustration of a chemical reaction, Mrs. Krever teaches the children how to combine baking soda, vinegar, food coloring, water and dishwashing detergent. The results exploded on Toby Roberts's lawn as a dramatic cascade of homemade volcanoes.</p>
        <p>An Ancient Need</p>
        <p>''For hundreds and thousands of years before TV and Nintendo, you had people who needed entertainment,'' said Mrs. Krever, who lives in Greenburgh with her husband, a contractor, and two sons, an 8-year-old and a 3-year-old. ''These are traditional entertainments in the purest sense.'' Mrs. Krever, a Brooklyn native who graduated from Erasmus High School and Hunter College, developed ''Mrs. Wizard'' as an after-school program for her son's elementary school.</p>
        <p>''There was a science program already in place but there weren't many after-school programs for boys, and I wanted to do something non-sexist,'' Mrs. Krever said. ''I thought science was important for kids today, and I wanted them to do it in a hands-on way. I had a child who was interested in science, and I was interested as someone who came to science late in life, from teaching. Everybody is so ecologically aware, but before you can get into recycling, you have to know what you're trying to save.''</p>
        <p>Word of Program Spreads</p>
        <p>As word-of-mouth spread from her success in the after-school program, Mrs. Krever was approached by friends and neighbors to assist in their children's birthday parties.</p>
        <p>About a year ago, Mrs. Krever began ''Mrs. Wizard'' as a science party business and she now performs at three to four parties a week in the county, in Riverdale and in Manhattan. She can be reached at (914) 693-7326.</p>
        <p>Besides the one-hour birthday parties, which are geared for 6- to 12-year-olds and cost $150, Mrs. Krever has also done workshops for the Ardsley Library, Mamaroneck's Storytime book store, and the White Plains Y.M.C.A.'s after-school recreation program.</p>
        <p>''Each party is geared to the child whose party it is,'' Mrs. Krever said. ''I try to key in to the child's age, because different ages have different needs. Sixes like to mix things, while 8's like invisible inks and secrets. I provide prepackaged materials for each child, as well as a goody bag for home.''</p>
        <p>Toothpicks and Frozen Peas</p>
        <p>Mrs. Krever uses safe household ingredients that children are likely to find in their own kitchens and pantries, and teaches experiments that children can easily replicate. Some favorites are crystal sculptures made of toothpicks and frozen green peas; ''gelatin scars,'' formed of thick gelatin and cotton balls for a Halloween disguise; mixing colored water and oil in a bottle to demonstrate that oil and water don't mix; '' heat mobiles,'' made from a silver-foil pie plate that is cut into a spiral and suspended over a lamp, and the 15th-century Italian ''dancing spaghetti'' experiment, which is done when dried, broken pieces of pasta are dropped into a mixture of baking soda, vinegar and colored water.</p>
        <p>''Parents get excited that their children are excited,'' she said. ''The kids are open and receptive. Different kids learn in different ways, and react differently. I'm always surprised by the reactions of kids.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
