<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who's Environment Czar, E.P.A.'s Chief or Sununu?</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="326798"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1988</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOWD, MAUREEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUNUNU, JOHN H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REILLY, WILLIAM K (ADMR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DF143AF936A25751C0A966958260" item-length="1754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who's Environment Czar, E.P.A.'s Chief or Sununu?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DOWD, MAUREEN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As the nation's defense recedes as an overriding issue and the environment becomes a more important one for Republican candidates, the White House chief of staff's role is being watched with alarm by many environmentalists and with concern by some Republican strategists and officials.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As the nation's defense recedes as an overriding issue and the environment becomes a more important one for Republican candidates, the White House chief of staff's role is being watched with alarm by many environmentalists and with concern by some Republican strategists and officials.</p>
        <p>As the nation's defense recedes as an overriding issue and the environment becomes a more important one for Republican candidates, the White House chief of staff's role is being watched with alarm by many environmentalists and with concern by some Republican strategists and officials.</p>
        <p>Although unwilling to criticize President Bush publicly, these Republicans voice concern that with important decisions looming on offshore drilling and the Clean Air Act, Mr. Bush seems to be relying increasingly on the advice of John H. Sununu, the chief of staff, who is a mechanical engineer by training and an environmental skeptic by temperament.</p>
        <p>Environmental lobbyists and organization leaders also say they are alarmed because Mr. Sununu has asserted his influence at the expense of William K. Reilly, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, whose appointment was hailed as a sign that Mr. Bush was serious about his campaign pledge to be ''the environmental President.''</p>
        <p>Political Motives Charged</p>
        <p>Mr. Sununu, who is strongly supported by the business wing of his party and by many senior aides, dismisses criticism of his role as ''pure politics,'' and says the environmental movement is conducting an orchestrated offensive to scuttle Mr. Bush's portrayal of himself as an environmentalist.</p>
        <p>''The President has a commitment to moving forward on the environment,'' Mr. Sununu said, ''but he wants to do it in such a way that we don't make irreversible moves without knowing the benefits and negative impacts of each move.''</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Sununu and Mr. Reilly say there is no personal animosity between them, but people familiar with the relationship say it is a setup for conflict.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sununu treats Mr. Reilly cordially, officials say, but fears that the E.P.A. Administrator, a former head of the World Wildlife Fund and the Conservation Foundation, could be influenced by advocates of extreme positions, both from environmental groups and from inside his agency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly has taken his licks from Mr. Sununu on the theory that as long as he has Mr. Bush's ear, he should get as much as he can for his environmental constituency. Mr. Reilly is also said by officials close to him to fear that Mr. Sununu, if his blunt intrusions go unchecked, could tarnish Mr. Bush's chances for a distinguished environmental record.</p>
        <p>Those close to Mr. Reilly say he worries that the responsibility for making good on Mr. Bush's campaign promises rests on his shoulders. But many environmentalists suggest that Mr. Reilly runs the risk of seeming to be a patsy for Mr. Sununu if he mistakes access for influence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly was bested twice by Mr. Sununu last week, first when the chief of staff softened a Presidential speech on global warming and later when he weakened an agreement between the environmental agency and the Army Corps of Engineers to protect wetlands.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly said that he had come out of the scrapes ''O.K.'' and that the Administration was moving forward on its goals, despite an outcry from many environmentalists and his old allies denouncing Mr. Sununu as ''Dr. No'' and ''the new James Watt,'' referring to Ronald Reagan's first Secretary of the Interior.</p>
        <p>List of Gains Cited</p>
        <p>''The Bush team has put E.P.A. into the starting lineup and we frequently get hits,'' he said. ''In other Administrations, the agency has been a bench warmer.''</p>
        <p>As ''hits,'' Mr. Reilly's aides point to the phasing-out of chlorofluorocarbons, air pollutants thought to damage the protective ozone layer of the atmosphere; a ban on asbestos, which is linked to cancer; additional enforcement officers for hazardous waste cleanup; the 57 percent increase in the 1991 budget for global warming research, and the 12 percent increase in the Environmental Protection Agency's budget.</p>
        <p>They also say Mr. Reilly's achievements should be viewed in comparison with the record of the Reagan Administration, rather than in the context of ''rhetorical battles'' with Mr. Sununu that represent minor setbacks.</p>
        <p>Indeed, worried that President Bush might be offended by news reports of friction on the global warming issue, Mr. Reilly made a point of riding in the limousine with the President when he went to make his speech on the subject last week, White House officials said. Mr. Sununu was in the car as well and the two men assured Mr. Bush they were both happy with the speech, which was denounced by many environmentalists and by scientists and diplomats from Europe as too tepid.</p>
        <p>Many White House officials support Mr. Sununu, saying he needs to keep an eye on Mr. Reilly. One official said Mr. Reilly was a captive of his bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>In a column in The Washington Post today, Rowland Evans and Robert Novak suggested that Administration officials are growing more suspicious that Mr. Reilly may be privately feeding complaints in the press that the President has scaled back on environmental commitments.</p>
        <p>''With Reilly soon to get Cabinet status, he is seen by colleagues as the enemy within - the Trojan horse of an environmental movement determined to make up for the lost Reagan years,'' the columnists wrote.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists' Fears</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly's longtime supporters among the environmentalists, however, disagree and say they are beginning to fear that he has been too easily subdued. They fret that Mr. Sununu has tied Mr. Reilly's hands and that the environmental chief has become more concerned with his White House access and the planned Cabinet status for his job than with fiercely battling for the cause.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly is trying to reassure his friends that despite the dustups with Mr. Sununu, he believes that the President has his heart is in the right place, as one official close to Mr. Reilly put it, and that Mr. Bush is the sort of man who actually asks how the Brazilian rain forests are doing.</p>
        <p>''One way of looking at it is that it is flattering to have the chief of staff's attention,'' said an E.P.A. official enjoying what he called ''the rarefied air'' of access to the highest levels of the Administration.</p>
        <p>Administration supporters of Mr. Reilly say he has the will and charm to counteract Mr. Sununu's influence with the President. They say that he maneuvered his way into the trip last summer to the Paris economic summit conference, where he grew much closer to Mr. Bush, a fellow Yale University graduate, and that the President and Mrs. Bush have taken Mr. Reilly and his wife to the theater.</p>
        <p>White House officials insist the clash between Mr. Sununu and Mr. Reilly is gentlemanly and rooted in their differing perspectives.</p>
        <p>Officials say that as a veteran of the environmental movement, Mr. Reilly fears that Mr. Sununu will tarnish Mr. Bush's credentials if he holds sway too forcefully. They say Mr. Sununu believes that Mr. Reilly is a well-intentioned and loyal administrator who deserves a fair chance to influence the President but that it is his mission to prevent both Mr. Bush and Mr. Reilly from being led astray by extremists.</p>
        <p>Explaining why he is now helping formulate policy rather than merely executing it, Mr. Sununu said he had a deep distrust of the E.P.A. bureaucrats ''who forget that it is Bill Reilly and the President who make policy, not some folks deep down within the system who are not answerable to the American public.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sununu said that when advisers are not in consensus on a policy matter, he does not prevent Mr. Reilly or other Cabinet officials from meeting Mr. Bush individually if they want to register a dissenting opinion.</p>
        <p>Bush May Like the Conflict</p>
        <p>As a former Texas oil man, Mr. Bush wants to pay attention to economic consequences. He may also prefer the mild conflicts between the men. He likes having advisers on one side appealing to his moderate, good-government impulses and another side appealing to his hardball political side. That way, the President can split the difference and feel that he has satisfied his decent impulses while protecting his conservative political base.</p>
        <p>''Sununu's the lightning rod so that the President can stay above the fray,'' a White House official said.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists said they took as another bad omen this week the White House withdrawal of the appointment of a respected lawyer, Dan Reicher, as deputy general counsel of the White House Council on Environmental Quality.</p>
        <p>Although the chairman of the council, Michael Deland, took responsibility for the withdrawal, saying he had not realized what a ''persistent critic'' of the Administration Mr. Reicher was, the environmentalists suggested that White House pressure had been brought to bear, and that the affair was another example of Mr. Sununu's influence with the President.</p>
        <p>The chief of staff made his stand on the environment clear from the beginning. After the worst oil spill in the nation's history, in Valdez, Alaska, last March, Mr. Sununu chided the press for focusing on the oil that was spilled rather than ''the bulk of the oil that was kept on the ship.''</p>
        <p>A Worry for Republicans</p>
        <p>But while Mr. Sununu's position may appeal to the traditional business wing of the Republican Party, the party is also working to maintain its newfound appeal on an issue that has become increasingly important to younger voters. Some party analysts assert that while Mr. Sununu sees himself as protecting the President from extreme treaties or regulations his success may squander hard-won gains among these voters.</p>
        <p>Administration officials say Mr. Sununu enjoys nothing more than using his engineering and computer expertise to debunk the predictions of imperfect computer models that forecast a severe threat from global warming.</p>
        <p>The traditional role of the chief of staff is as a nonideological coordinator and honest broker for the presentation of different views to the President and to execute the President's decisions.</p>
        <p>But by becoming a policy formulator with strong conservative views on issues like abortion and the environment, Mr. Sununu may be setting himself up as someone ''you have to get on your side,'' as one Bush insider put it.</p>
        <p>J. Michael McCloskey, the chairman of the Sierra Club, said: ''What is really unfair is that Bush has put in a person as his chief of staff who is not a neutral member of the Administration on enviromental issues. He is the most aggressive advocate of an extreme position.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sununu is unrepentent. ''Folks inside the White House think I'm being constructive,'' he said, ''so it doesn't matter what the perception is on the outside.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
