<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nation's Library Calls on Chemists to Stop Books From Turning to Dust</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="355725"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIBRARIES AND LIBRARIANS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LIBRARY OF CONGRESS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDE133CF931A15756C0A966958260" item-length="1735" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nation's Library Calls on Chemists to Stop Books From Turning to Dust</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: AT a rate of more than 200 volumes a day, books in the Library of Congress, the largest library in the world, are turning to dust. But after a decade of research, accidents and administrative delays, the library reports that it is about to take a major step toward stopping the rot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: AT a rate of more than 200 volumes a day, books in the Library of Congress, the largest library in the world, are turning to dust. But after a decade of research, accidents and administrative delays, the library reports that it is about to take a major step toward stopping the rot.</p>
        <p>AT a rate of more than 200 volumes a day, books in the Library of Congress, the largest library in the world, are turning to dust. But after a decade of research, accidents and administrative delays, the library reports that it is about to take a major step toward stopping the rot.</p>
        <p>Within the next four months the institution plans to call for bids from chemical-processing companies for a preservation program aimed at saving 16 million endangered books and manuscripts, a major portion of the library's 21 million volumes. These represent a major part of America's cultural heritage.</p>
        <p>The library's initiative will have far-reaching effects on many other institutions throughout the world, where book decay is destroying hundreds of millions of valuable volumes. Some 300 million acidic books in North American research libraries and 400 million in Europe need treatment, according to archivists at the Library of Congress. Although scientists believe they understand the causes of the problem, experts differ as to how to solve it most effectively and cheaply, and the forthcoming Library of Congress decision will carry weight with many other major collections of books and manuscripts.</p>
        <p>The root of the problem is the acid that forms in most modern paper. Until the end of the 18th century, most paper was made of flax or cotton fibers that required little chemical treatment for use in books and documents. Such paper has often survived for many hundreds of years without decaying; paper documents more than 2,000 years old are still in existence. A page from America's first newspaper in 1690 was recently placed on exhibit at the Library of Congress, and it still looks fresh. But since the middle of the 19th century, papermakers have primarily used fiber extracted from wood, which is much cheaper and more plentiful than flax or cotton.</p>
        <p>Paper made of wood fiber, however, must be treated with a waterproofing substance called sizing, which prevents printing from blurring. The most common form of sizing, alum rosin, facilitates printing. But alum (the common name for aluminum sulfate), is an enemy of the cellulose fibers in paper. When exposed to warmth and high humidity, aluminum sulfate molecules split up and form an acidic solution. Cellulose fibers, which are made of molecular chains of carbon atoms, are easily split by even weak acids. The strength of the fibers is destroyed, and paper made from them becomes as fragile as a dead leaf.</p>
        <p>Dr. Chandra J. Shahani, a scientist at the Library of Congress who investigates preservation techniques, said it had long been obvious that books printed on acidic paper must be deacidified if they are to be preserved. Without such treatment a typical book survives for less than 50 years before becoming too fragile to use.</p>
        <p>In recent decades, manufacturers have begun to make wood-fiber paper that is alkaline rather than acid, paper that is stronger and more durable than acidic paper. Roughly one quarter of the paper now used for printing books in the United States is the long-lasting alkaline type. By using new sizing agents that do not contain rosin alum and by impregnating paper pulp with calcium carbonate, manufacturers produce acid-free paper that is highly resistant to decay.</p>
        <p>But the recent trend toward printing books on alkaline paper does not help about 97 percent of all books published since 1900, those printed on acidic paper. Age and acid have already destroyed many of these books.</p>
        <p>Rescuing Valuable Books</p>
        <p>Library conservators have developed some delicate techniques for saving a handful of extremely valuable volumes. Each book must be taken apart and tested to make sure that solvents will not damage its inks, sizing or binding materials. The book is then deacidified in special liquid solutions, one page at a time, and is finally dried and rebound.</p>
        <p>But such time-consuming procedures cost up to $35 a page, far too much for reconditioning large collections. In the late 1970's chemists developed various techniques for immersing large numbers of books in liquids or vapors that would neutralize paper acid and halt decay. Dr. Shahani said the liquid methods were based on extremely penetrating solvents, mixtures of chlorofluorocarbon solvents (Freons) and alcohol. Alkaline buffering chemicals (like methoxy magnesium methyl carbonate) dissolved in such solvents penetrate pages of books sprayed by or immersed in the solution, and when the solvent is evaporated, chemicals left in the paper neutralize acid.</p>
        <p>This is the basis of a process developed by Wei T'o Associates, which built a deacidification plant for the Canadian National Library in 1979 that treats up to 150 books a day. Another liquid process, ''Bookkeeper,'' developed by Koppers Chemical Company in 1981, uses fluorocarbon solvents to deposit particles of magnesium oxide in paper.</p>
        <p>Front-Running Method</p>
        <p>The best known vapor treatment method was invented in the early 1970's by chemists at the Library of Congress, Dr. George B. Kelly Jr., John Williams, Robert McComb and Donald Sebera. The process, patented in 1976, is the front-running candidate for a mass-production system. The library has licensed Akzo Chemicals Inc. of Chicago, the American subsidiary of the Netherlands-based company Akzo NV, to develop the method as a manufacturing technique.</p>
        <p>The vapor deacidification method is based on the compound diethyl zinc (DEZ), which is a colorless liquid at room temperature. The vapor produced from evaporating DEZ has enormous penetrating power, and the pages of a book exposed to it become impregnated after only a few hours.</p>
        <p>Developers of the DEZ technique say that not only does the vapor neutralize all acid in book paper, but it deposits in the paper tiny particles of zinc oxide, a buffering agent that neutralizes any acids that may continue to form after treatment. Richard F. Miller, director of the book preservation project at Akzo, says the useful life of a book printed on acidic paper can be lengthened by three to five times by DEZ treatment. The vapor does not affect ink, covers or bindings, and books treated with DEZ in hermetically sealed gas chambers are indistinguishable in appearance from untreated counterparts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller believes the method will cost about $10 per book. A commercial-scale plant for treating Library of Congress books at a minimum rate of 500,000 books a year could be built for $10 million, he says. The potential market for any practical deacidification treatment is enormous.</p>
        <p>But DEZ poses some problems. For one, the cost of processing books using the DEZ method is probably significantly higher than using alternative methods. The liquid chemical is difficult to handle because it reacts violently with water, and in air it catches fire spontaneously, sometimes exploding.</p>
        <p>Explosion at Test Site</p>
        <p>In 1985 a DEZ test site operated for the Library of Congress at the National Aeronautics and Space Administration's Goddard Space Flight Center caught fire and exploded. But various chemical industries have learned to use diethyl zinc safely, and a pilot plant built by Akzo's subsidiary near Houston to test the book treatment method has operated without incident for two years.</p>
        <p>Some questions about the method were raised by a House of Representatives panel, and these led to a review of book-treatment technology by the Congressional Office of Technology Assessment. In a 1988 report, scientists at the agency office concluded that the DEZ method seemed to offer major advantages over competing systems, but that comparison tests by independent laboratories were needed.</p>
        <p>The Congressional agency said increasingly stringent government limitations on the production and use of Freon solvents would affect the methods based on liquid solvents. Freon solvents, used in air-conditioners and foam plastics, have been indicted by scientists as harmful to the stratospheric ozone layer that protects life on earth from dangerous solar ultraviolet radiation.</p>
        <p>The Library of Congress is preparing a formal request for bids, in which proposals for building and operating deacidification plants will be invited. Robert Lincoln, the library's assistant general counsel, said an independent panel would then be created to evaluate proposals on the basis of cost, effectiveness, safety and other factors.</p>
        <p>The panel will first select the method to be used and then pick the contractor to carry it out. Testing methods must be evaluated, other technical issues must be resolved and potential challenges by unsuccessful bidders must be considered, so the process may be lengthy, Mr. Lincoln acknowledged.</p>
        <p>Cold-Temperature Storage</p>
        <p>Elaborate processing of acidic books and papers could be avoided by storing them at cold temperatures, preservationists agree.</p>
        <p>Dr. Alan Calmes, preservation officer at the National Archives, said his institution had considered placing some of its immense collection of papers and documents in cold storage. ''For every reduction in storage temperature of 10 degrees Celsius, the life of a paper document is roughly doubled,'' he said. ''The trouble is that books and papers must be easily accessible to researchers, whose needs change from year to year.''</p>
        <p>The National Archives are therefore no longer considering cold storage, although the institution's entire collection has been stored in an air-conditioned building at 68 degrees Fahrenheit and 45 percent relative humidity since 1935. Microfilm and other photographic copies are made of some deteriorating documents, and video disks are increasingly used by archivists to store documents and pictures. But librarians say the cost of these methods is too high for general application to large collections.</p>
        <p>Deciphering Outdated Disks</p>
        <p>''Already, there are computer tapes made long enough ago that they can no longer be read by today's equipment,'' a preservation specialist said. ''Two thousand years from now, will anyone be able to decipher today's disks and tapes? The written word is the surest record.''</p>
        <p>Whatever recorded form the art, literature, music and archives of the future may take, scientists will be needed to keep it alive, preservationists agree.</p>
        <p>''As long as the human race entrusts its records to impermanent materials,'' Dr. Shahani wrote in the magazine American Scientist, ''the knowledge and expertise of the scientist will be needed to preserve them.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
