<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Waves' Action Could Ease Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="388335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="SCIENCE WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DB1F3DF931A35753C1A966958260" item-length="379" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Waves' Action Could Ease Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: GLOBAL warming might pump enough extra energy into the atmosphere to make winds blow faster over the ocean, whipping up the water so much that more salt particles would be thrown into the air, where they would create bigger clouds that in turn would counteract the warming, British scientists say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: GLOBAL warming might pump enough extra energy into the atmosphere to make winds blow faster over the ocean, whipping up the water so much that more salt particles would be thrown into the air, where they would create bigger clouds that in turn would counteract the warming, British scientists say.</p>
        <p>GLOBAL warming might pump enough extra energy into the atmosphere to make winds blow faster over the ocean, whipping up the water so much that more salt particles would be thrown into the air, where they would create bigger clouds that in turn would counteract the warming, British scientists say.</p>
        <p>This feedback mechanism would be one of many that climatologists expect to affect cloud formation as the climate warms. Some of the feedbacks would increase the warming by causing clouds to trap more heat and some would diminish it by making clouds more reflective, and scientists are a long way from calculating the net effect on global warming or even isolating all the mechanisms.</p>
        <p>John Latham and M. H. Smith of the University of Manchester report in the current issue of the British journal Nature that they have demonstrated a feedback effect that could begin when, as they say is possible, global warming causes oceanic winds to increase. It is well established, the report says, that winds generate airborne particles, or aerosols, when they disturb the water's surface, causing whitecaps to form and bubbles to burst. Most of the aerosols are particles of sodium chloride.</p>
        <p>Higher winds would generate more particles, according to the report, which would then become nuclei around which water vapor would condense, forming more of the tiny droplets that make up clouds. Bigger clouds would reflect more of the Sun's heat back into space, the scientists say, reducing the heating of the planet.</p>
        <p>They calculate that an average increase in wind speeds of 5 to 10 meters a second, or 11 to 22 miles an hour, would be enough to compensate for currently predicted levels of global warming. An international consensus of scientists predicts that the average global temperature will increase by about 2 degrees Fahrenheit by the year 2025 and more than 5 degrees by the end of the next century if concentrations of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases in the atmosphere continue to grow at present rates.</p>
        <p>In an accompanying letter in Nature, Dr. Latham said it seems feasible to conduct a controlled experiment in which cloud-condensation nuclei are introduced into the atmosphere to study the effects on cloud formation and the trapping of atmospheric heat.</p>
        <p>SCIENCE WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
