<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Now, Vidalia Onions To Sweeten Winter</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="400729"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ONIONS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KLEIMAN, DENA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDD103EF937A25752C1A966958260" item-length="1133" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Now, Vidalia Onions To Sweeten Winter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENA KLEIMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KLEIMAN, DENA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DELBERT BLAND didn't have to go to college to learn the law of supply and demand.</p>
        <p>All he needed was to hoard some onions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DELBERT BLAND didn't have to go to college to learn the law of supply and demand.</p>
        <p>All he needed was to hoard some onions.</p>
        <p>And now due in large part to his efforts, Vidalia onions, those almost sugary Georgia bulbs that are usually available for a scant six weeks in the spring, are for sale right now (though at more than twice their usual price).</p>
        <p>"What we want," said the 34-year-old Mr. Bland, whose family is the country's largest grower of Vidalia onions, "is to create demand."</p>
        <p>To build demand, and thereby raise the price, Mr. Bland and 250 other growers this year for the first time stockpiled more than 10 million pounds of onions from the spring harvest and stored them in low-oxygen "controlled atmosphere" bins so they could be available for the holidays.</p>
        <p>Partly because of their novelty, winter Vidalias are selling for about $1.50 a pound, compared with an average of 58 cents a pound last spring. The growers' hope is that with stepped-up marketing, the price will climb even further.</p>
        <p>Even in season, Vidalias, a slow-growing variety that thrives on less sunlight than most onions and so is grown in the winter, are limited in supply; that is because a true Vidalia can be grown only in the soil of certain counties of Georgia. The current supply will be on sale through Thanksgiving; the onions will not be available again until May.</p>
        <p>"We convinced people for 10 years that true Vidalia onions were only available in May and June," said Mr. Bland, who prides himself on being able to outsmart the marketplace despite having only a high-school education. "Now we're saying, 'Wait a minute. What we told you for the last 10 years is not necessarily true.' "</p>
        <p>Mr. Bland, who does not like to eat onions ("I prefer chewing tobacco"), was in New York last week with other growers to try to create some excitement over the new availability of Vidalias. They were the hosts of a lunch that featured (what else?) onion soup, onion relish, onion rings, even onion cake.</p>
        <p>The growers discussed, for example, the science of onion storage. (The onions are kept in an atmosphere of 3 percent oxygen, 92 percent nitrogen and 5 percent carbon dioxide, in bins similar to those used for apples.)</p>
        <p>They spoke of taking Vidalia onions around the world. (The onions are marketed in Europe, but the growers are hoping to send them to Japan.) They even talked about trying to turn the Vidalia into a cause for national celebration.</p>
        <p>"The Fourth of July is not an onion party," Mr. Bland said. "We'll make it one."</p>
        <p>Vidalia onions were first bred in 1931, but it was only over the last decade that through aggressive marketing they exploded into a $25 million-a-year business. Although the yellow granex hybrid onion -- the Vidalia variety -- is grown in other parts of the country, Georgia's special loamy soil, rainfall and climate are generally credited as being responsible for a special sweet flavor.</p>
        <p>Under state law, only onions grown in 13 counties and parts of seven others can be labeled "Vidalias." It was at a farmers' market in Vidalia, a town in east central Georgia about 70 miles west of Savannah, where the special onions were first sold during the 40's.</p>
        <p>The stockpiling plan is not the first of Mr. Bland's onion innovations. It was Mr. Bland who about six years ago, seeing the huge success of the Sunkist orange, thought of actually labeling the onions with a Vidalia sticker and promoting the name.</p>
        <p>Currently, about 70 percent of the special Georgia onions are sold in grocery stores across the country and the rest by mail order.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bland and his family, who did not begin to grow onions until 1980, now farm 900 acres of onions in Reidsville, grossing about $10 million a year.</p>
        <p>Their meteoric success is due in large part to the persistence of Mr. Bland, who was intrigued by customer demand for the onions at his local supermarket and who persuaded his father, Raymond, 64, to get out of the tomato business and try onions.</p>
        <p>He was so convinced that the Vidalia onions would catch on that in 1981, he jumped in a truck and traveled around the country giving away onions to any store willing to carry them.</p>
        <p>"All I want is the opportunity for you to try them," Mr. Bland recalled telling any produce managers who would listen. "It's a new thing. It's the wave of the future." It worked, and the next year grocery chains across the country placed orders. Whereas in 1978, according to the Georgia Department of Agriculture, farmers grew 600 acres of Vidalia onions, this year they grew 5,700 acres.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bland's next brainstorm was to sell the onions by mail order, and he placed a $2,700 advertisement in Southern Living magazine. But his father was against it.</p>
        <p>"My father thought it was nonsense to sell 10-pound bags," Mr. Bland said. "He said it was too confusing and better to sell by the truckload."</p>
        <p>So the younger Mr. Bland decided to cancel the ad -- but was told it was too late.</p>
        <p>From that single advertisement, Mr. Bland said, he received 1,000 orders, and thus was born the family's mail-order business, which now sells $5 million a year of such diverse products as onion holders, onion batter and onion relish. Although Mr. Bland said he does not read much, the family regularly advertises their onions under the name Bland Farms in The New Yorker and Food and Wine, among other publications.</p>
        <p>"Me and some other growers do so much advertising that it has stirred interest," Mr. Bland said. "People keep seeing this and are saying 'God, there must be something to this.' "</p>
        <p>A key to his personal success, Mr. Bland said, is having secured the rights to the telephone number (800) VIDALIA, which he had to buy for $20,000 from another onion entrepreneur.</p>
        <p>About six years ago Mr. Bland heard about the work of a scientist at the University of Georgia, Dr. Doyle Smittle, who was trying to come up with a way to store onions. Last year the low-oxygen technique, which essentially slows the aging process, was deemed ready to be put into practice and Mr. Bland built a $2 million warehouse for his onions.</p>
        <p>"My wife said I was crazy," said Mr. Bland, adding that the wholesale market at the time was $15 for a 50-pound bag. In October, he sold the same quantity for $35. "I ain't got no education," Mr. Bland said, "but I think that's pretty good."</p>
        <p>As for the future, Mr. Bland said it might be possible someday to have Vidalias year-round. (Even with the new storage technique, the quality of the onions deteriorates slightly each week and now, though they are still edible, they have lost some of their crispness.) But even if such a day does come to pass, he added, he will be against it.</p>
        <p>"If I could get my price I'd sell them all in one day," Mr. Bland said. "We got to get them off the market and have people really want them again."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
