<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Faces Acute Water Shortage In 90's, Government Expert Says</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="403126"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHORTAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUDLOW, MICHAEL D (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDB1739F930A15752C1A966958260" item-length="559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Faces Acute Water Shortage In 90's, Government Expert Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Government expert has warned that the United States could face a severe water shortage in the 1990's.</p>
        <p>The severe drought that struck much of the nation in 1988 was the first indication of what could become a continuing problem, said the expert, Dr. Michael D. Hudlow, director of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Office of Hydrology, who spoke Tuesday at a news conference called to discuss water conditions and resources.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Government expert has warned that the United States could face a severe water shortage in the 1990's.</p>
        <p>The severe drought that struck much of the nation in 1988 was the first indication of what could become a continuing problem, said the expert, Dr. Michael D. Hudlow, director of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Office of Hydrology, who spoke Tuesday at a news conference called to discuss water conditions and resources.</p>
        <p>"I believe we're headed into a water management crisis in the 1990's," he said. "We're going to have real extreme drought conditions going into next spring unless Mother Nature cooperates and gives us a bumper crop of snowfall in the mountains of the West.</p>
        <p>"As we move toward the 21st century, short supplies of clean water could rival expensive oil as one of the nation's most serious concerns unless we start now to implement strategies to better manage our water supplies."</p>
        <p>California Faces Shortage</p>
        <p>The water outlook in much of the West is precarious, depending heavily on the winter snows, he said. California already faces a serious water shortage.</p>
        <p>"Extreme drought still grips much of the West, from California to Montana, and in parts of the Southeast," Dr. Hudlow said. "In mid-October, drought conditions in much of Georgia and the Carolinas ended with a significant flooding episode."</p>
        <p>Water shortages are developing as part of the normal variability of climate, he said, with the relatively wet years of the 1970's and early 1980's giving way to a drier period.</p>
        <p>And he said his prediction did not include the threat that increasing levels of carbon dioxide and other man-made gases will trap and retain heat from the sun, in a process similar to what happens in a greenhouse. Some scientists say this greenhouse effect could raise temperatures worldwide and change rainfall patterns; Dr. Hudlow said it could make a water shortage worse.  Forecasting Water Supplies</p>
        <p>While forecasting floods and drought now depends on climate records and short-term weather forecasts, Dr. Hudlow said a new water supply forecasting system was being developed by his agency.</p>
        <p>Called the Water Resources Forecasting Service, the system is being tested at the Colorado River Basin Forecast Office in Salt Lake City. Using long-range climate and weather models, the system can study the conditions in a local river basin and calculate probabilities of floods, drought or a return to normal conditions. If the testing goes well and money is made available, Dr. Hudlow said, the system could be put into national service by 1992.</p>
        <p>The system could provide local water managers and civil defense officials with information on the probabilities of flooding or drought, helping them make decisions, he said. For example, reservoir managers might be reluctant to reduce water levels out of concern that they would later have too little water for generating power, irrigating crops and other uses. But if they had a reliable forecast that there would be a good chance of severe flooding, they could make a decision to lower reservoir levels so flood water could be trapped and damage prevented.</p>
        <p>"We didn't do it right in '88," Dr. Ludlow said, referring to the lack of accurate forecasts of water conditions in that drought year. "We've got to get in a position to do it right now."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
