<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>President Wins Initial Test On Clean Air Compromise</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="336639"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WIRTH, TIMOTHY E (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILSON, PETE (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D9123AF932A15750C0A966958260" item-length="938" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>President Wins Initial Test On Clean Air Compromise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush and the Senate leadership tonight withstood the first major test of their compromise bill to reduce air pollution, when the Senate narrowly refused to impose stricter controls on automobile emissions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush and the Senate leadership tonight withstood the first major test of their compromise bill to reduce air pollution, when the Senate narrowly refused to impose stricter controls on automobile emissions.</p>
        <p>President Bush and the Senate leadership tonight withstood the first major test of their compromise bill to reduce air pollution, when the Senate narrowly refused to impose stricter controls on automobile emissions.</p>
        <p>The vote against the amendment on emissions was 52 to 46.</p>
        <p>The amendment, proposed by Senators Tim Wirth, Democrat of Colorado, and Pete Wilson, Republican of California, would have added, among other things, a new and stricter round of auto emission controls to the measure that White House and Senate negotiators worked out in months of closed negotiations.</p>
        <p>President Bush and other Administration officials vigorously opposed the amendment, saying it would cost too much money and produce only minimal improvement in air quality. And tonight's vote represented a victory for Mr. Bush and the Senate majority leader, George J. Mitchell of Maine, both of whom expended considerable influence and prestige in achieving the clean-air agreement.</p>
        <p>The compromise, intended to reduce acid rain, urban smog and airborne toxic chemicals, includes elements of both the original Senate bill and the legislation proposed by Mr. Bush last year. It is opposed by environmentalists, who contend it does not go far enough in assuring improved air quality, and by industry, which complains that its costs will be excessive.</p>
        <p>Senator Mitchell warned today at the close of debate on the amendment that its passage would assure the collapse of the compromise. ''If we don't get a clean air bill this year,'' he said, ''we will not get a clean air bill this century.''</p>
        <p>A substantial number of conservatives who often vote against environmental legislation joined senators who favor strong environmental measures to try to pass the amendment. The conservatives were apparently trying to break the agreement with the White House and undermine prospects for a clean air bill this year.</p>
        <p>Mitchell's Influence Is Cited</p>
        <p>The rejection of the Wirth-Wilson amendment removes one hurdle to the passage of clean air legislation this year. But supporters of the amendment said that public opinion in favor of better air quality was gathering momentum and that Congress would be compelled to respond to it.</p>
        <p>Senator Wilson said after the vote that in ''the ordinary course of events we would have had a 2-to-1 majority for this amendment'' but that Mr. Mitchell had used his influence to turn a lot of votes around.</p>
        <p>A Senator who asked not to be named said Senator Mitchell ''broke a lot of arms'' to obtain the votes necessary to defeat the amendment. He said Mr. Mitchell reminded several Senators that they had legislation that would need his support.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitchell will need all of that influence to turn aside an amendment being offered by Senator Robert C. Byrd, Democrat of West Virginia. It would provide financial benefits to coal miners who may lose their jobs because of acid-rain provisions of the compromise bill.</p>
        <p>The White House opposes the Byrd amendment on grounds of cost, and Administration officials said its inclusion in the bill could lead to a Bush veto.</p>
        <p>First Changes Since 1977</p>
        <p>The House Energy and Commerce Committee is drafting its own version of clean air legislation and is facing many of the same difficulties as the Senate in trying to satisfy the White House. But key members of the House have agreed on provisions regarding controls on auto emissions.</p>
        <p>The legislation being considered would be the first change to the Clean Air Act since 1977. Mr. Bush said he could not accept the bill proposed by the Senate Environment and Public Works Committee because it would cost over $40 billion a year to carry out. He said the $40 billion was more than twice the cost of the clean air bill he offered last summer.</p>
        <p>When it became clear that there were insufficient votes to block a filibuster supported by Mr. Bush, Mr. Mitchell agreed to closed negotiations with the Administration.</p>
        <p>Provisions for Vehicles</p>
        <p>Provisions dealing with automobiles were one of the most hotly debated issues in the negotiations.</p>
        <p>Industry lobbyists, particularly from the auto and oil industries, worked furiously to ease requirements for stricter controls and alternative fuels in the original bill, while environmentalists and public health officials said that without the new standards the goals of the Clean Air Act could not be met.</p>
        <p>The Wirth-Wilson amendment would have done the following:</p>
        <p>* Require catalytic converters that remove pollution from auto tailpipes be guaranteed to work for 100,000 miles, the normal working life of a car, instead of the 50,000 provided by the compromise legislation.</p>
        <p>* Impose a mandatory second round of controls on tailpipe emissions to go into effect in 2003, unless Congress votes to the contrary. The compromise bill requires only that pollution from car exhausts be reduced once in the mid-90's and mandates a second round only if 12 or more cities outside California are not meeting the health standards by 2001.</p>
        <p>* Require the use of cleaner-burning gasoline, with a higher oxygen content, in all cities that have serious smog problems.</p>
        <p>* Require the use of trucks and cars that burn clean fuels of any kind, including ethanol, methanol, natural gas or electricity, in government and commercial fleets beginning in 1994.</p>
        <p>* Require the use of general passenger cars that burn clean fuels starting in Los Angeles in 1994 and in other severely polluted areas in 1997. Los Angeles has the nation's worst smog problem.</p>
        <p>Hydrocarbons and other pollution from motor vehicles are the biggest source of the smog that continues to shroud 100 major American cities.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
