<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Windy Mideast</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="332315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="FOREIGN AFFAIRS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, FLORA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">OP-ED</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900306T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D6143AF935A35750C0A966958260" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Windy Mideast</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Flora Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, FLORA</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The change in the world's political climate is finally touching the Middle East. Don't hold your breath. Things are moving in millimeters, nothing like the giant leaps that 1989 brought in East Europe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The change in the world's political climate is finally touching the Middle East. Don't hold your breath. Things are moving in millimeters, nothing like the giant leaps that 1989 brought in East Europe.</p>
        <p>The change in the world's political climate is finally touching the Middle East. Don't hold your breath. Things are moving in millimeters, nothing like the giant leaps that 1989 brought in East Europe.</p>
        <p>Still, it is becoming more fashionable to sound a bit moderate than to shout shrill defiance. The hard-liners are being put on the defensive, no longer assured that extremism and intimidation will keep them on top.</p>
        <p>Different groups and pressures are at work in various countries. But they all add up to recognition that the receding cold war has given economic and political factors priority over the old ideological and strategic bulwarks. The expression comes in some surprisingly blunt ways.</p>
        <p>The Emir of Bahrain told a Persian Gulf newspaper the other day that he deplored how democratic forces in Kuwait and other gulf states were ''trying to imitate Eastern Europe in doing away with totalitarian rule.''</p>
        <p>Iraq's President, Saddam Hussein, heavy-handed as usual, told the new Arab Cooperation Council, comprising Iraq, Jordan, Egypt and Yemen, to watch out for the U.S. ''now that the Soviet Union has abandoned in a way and for a time its role as the prime international defender'' of the Arabs. ''Based on our friendship with the Soviets,'' he said, ''we never expected they would give in to American pressure'' to allow widespread emigration of Jews. He urged Arab investors to transfer funds from America to the Soviet Union, as though they could buy back Moscow's help that way.</p>
        <p>But this is a diversion from his greater concern with Iran, where something is stirring. There have been a lot of signals that Teheran is getting ready to arrange release of some, perhaps all, of the 18 Western hostages in Lebanon and that talks are going on with the U.S. The biggest problem seems to be the continuing power struggle in the Iranian regime.</p>
        <p>Iran's President, Hashemi Rafsanjani, is getting desperate at his country's terrible economic situation, and looks abroad to ease it. Iranian exiles report large, angry demonstrations in several cities and claim some 200 to 300 people have been killed in the streets in the past fortnight.</p>
        <p>European foreign ministries with diplomats in Teheran consider this a large exaggeration, but say there have been public disturbances. Teheran radio broadcast two telephone numbers last weekend for citizens to voice their grievances on a 24-hour hot line set up by Mr. Rafsanjani, an attempted steam valve.</p>
        <p>Obviously, freeing the hostages would improve Iran's relations with the West, probably leading to the end of Washington's oil embargo, release of blocked funds and perhaps new international credits. Baghdad wants to force Iranian concessions on the stalled negotiations for a peace settlement before tensions disappear. Passions are no longer a reliable barrier.</p>
        <p>Israel, too, is feeling the East-West thaw and economic pinch. In one way it is a benefit: the arrival of hundreds of thousands of Soviet Jews would fulfill an old dream. But Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir put his foot in it with his claim that it would take a ''big Israel'' to settle them. He avoided calling it ''Lebensraum,'' but the implication was that large-scale immigration would justify refusing to cede any occupied territory.</p>
        <p>That riled the Arabs, and Washington, and probably persuaded the Soviets not to allow the direct Moscow-Tel Aviv flights they had been considering. In any case, Mr. Shamir had boxed himself in over his own plan to hold elections in the territories to produce Palestinian negotiators.</p>
        <p>The Israeli Labor Party has accepted. Washington is getting impatient. The refuseniks in Mr. Shamir's own Likud party have already broken away. He will face a fight to keep the leadership but he can no longer argue that he has to stall to keep his party together. Now he has set new terms; if Labor agrees, talks will begin in Cairo about talks for interim Palestinian autonomy to lead to talks about a settlement some day. Only talk.</p>
        <p>There is no assurance that the compromise that alone can bring peace lies in the foreseeable future. Mr. Shamir said in an evident reference to Washington, ''no nation can ask of us concessions and sacrifices that they would never make if their own security was at stake.''</p>
        <p>But that's the whole point. Israel's security is at stake as long as it has no peace. In the Soviet Union and in Eastern Europe, leaders have come to see there's a better chance for security and prosperity from a gentle wind than from a chilly blast. South Africa's President, F. W. de Klerk, is trying it. There's still strong resistance in the Middle East but the idea is gaining. Political global warming makes a difference.</p>
        <p>FOREIGN AFFAIRS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
