<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Visit to a Tiny Planet: Within Glass Walls, Five Climates and 3,800 Species</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="348884"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ORACLE (ARIZ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SPACE BIOSPHERES VENTURES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MYDANS, SETH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BASS, EDWARD PERRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DE143EF933A05757C0A966958260" item-length="1335" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Visit to a Tiny Planet: Within Glass Walls, Five Climates and 3,800 Species</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MYDANS, SETH</byline>
      <dateline>ORACLE, Ariz.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: It is no small project to try to reproduce the planet in miniature. Even Noah aboard his Ark breathed the open air and drank rain that fell from the sky.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: It is no small project to try to reproduce the planet in miniature. Even Noah aboard his Ark breathed the open air and drank rain that fell from the sky.</p>
        <p>It is no small project to try to reproduce the planet in miniature. Even Noah aboard his Ark breathed the open air and drank rain that fell from the sky.</p>
        <p>In Biosphere II, an airtight, watertight glass-walled structure of no more than 3.15 acres, four men and four women plan to spend the next two years in what is intended as a self-sustaining environment independent of the outside world except for electricity and information.</p>
        <p>Addressing questions that never faced Noah, planners for the privately financed project have had to focus on details like finding a hummingbird that would not fly so high that it would hit the structure's ceiling.</p>
        <p>Here on the sunbaked edge of the Sonora Desert, workers are in the process of ''inoculating'' their tiny ocean with algae and preparing their miniature rain forest, savanna, marsh and desert for plant life.</p>
        <p>Many Uncertainties</p>
        <p>Nothing approaching this in scale has been tried before. Despite the high confidence of its planners, the uncertainties seem countless, from the chemistry of the soil to the acidity of the air to the interactions of many species of animals, insects and the eight enclosed researchers themselves.</p>
        <p>The only closed ecological systems that have shown sustained success until now are glass globes about the size of a softball containing tiny shrimp and algae.</p>
        <p>Some scientists question the rigor of the project's approach, saying there is more theater than science in the project, which will cram together five climatic zones as well as living quarters and a tiny farm.</p>
        <p>They say too many variables have been left untested and too much confidence has been placed in the ability of the project's ecological system to regulate its own processes.</p>
        <p>A Leap Into the Unknown</p>
        <p>On the other hand, they say the privately financed venture is taking an exciting leap into the unknown that could never have been tried under the painstaking scientific strictures of established institutions.</p>
        <p>''Let's put it this way,'' said Gene Odam, a professor of ecology who is director emeritus of the Institute of Ecology at the University of Georgia. ''If you didn't have enthusiasm for something completely new and untried, you'd never do it. If they fail, so what? It isn't up in the air and nobody is going to lose their life.''</p>
        <p>The project's $30 million in initial capital, and very likely much more before it is complete, comes from Edward Perry Bass, a 44-year-old Texas multimillionaire whose earlier ventures have included communes and survivalist groups, a 300,000-acre Australian ranch and an ecologically oriented hotel in Katmandu, Nepal.</p>
        <p>Margret Augustine, who heads the enterprise, Space Biospheres Ventures, said the project would have applications in space, in research into closed ecological systems and in the marketing of scientific processes.</p>
        <p>Planners say they are trying out the sort of enclosed but complete habitat in which humans might one day live on the Moon or on Mars. Perhaps as fancifully, its organizers have written about the project's potential applications for survival after a nuclear war.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, they say, the venture can gather data about life on earth, which participants call Biosphere I, and market spinoff technologies and processes. Since the project is a private enterprise, the planners have broken with scientific practice and kept much of the data to themselves. It is not clear just what spinoffs it might be able to market. #3,800 Species in Biosphere In September, if all goes as planned, the eight researchers will shut themselves inside what looks like a gigantic greenhouse, covered with a specially treated glass skin.</p>
        <p>Along with them, planners say, will be 3,800 other species of plants, insects and animals that they hope will feed each other as in nature.</p>
        <p>As in nature, everything is to be recycled, including the air, which the researchers will exhale as carbon dioxide and the plants will revitalize with oxygen. But nature will need mechanical assistance in this miniature world cut off from the larger forces of wind, weather and the earth's atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Computers, reading more than 3,000 sensors scattered through the enclosure, are to regulate temperature, humidity, artificial tides and the change of seasons.</p>
        <p>Beneath its lush surface, vivid with tropical plants and birdsong and rich with the scent of flowers, will lie mechanical guts that look like the engine room of a battleship. Under the biosphere's steel base, masses of pipes and pumps and fans are being installed to cool and filter the air, store water in the ''dry season,'' recycle human and animal waste and ''breathe'' the structure's air as it expands and contracts with changing temperatures.</p>
        <p>While some scientists have questioned the planning for Biosphere II, criticism is generally muted. Some scientists say they do not want to dampen enthusiasm for large-scale private financing for projects like this. Others say project officials have intimidated critics with threats of legal action.</p>
        <p>One of the few scientists who would discuss the project for attribution was David Stumpf, a plant biochemist who said he resigned from Biosphere II in 1988 after three years of work when some of his criticisms were ignored.</p>
        <p>Former Participant's Doubts</p>
        <p>He said he was concerned that the researchers could not feed themselves from their 20,000-square-foot farm, that the level of carbon dioxide in the air could climb too high and that a system of filtering the air through packed soil might not work on this scale.</p>
        <p>''Their premise seems to be that everything will be just fine, and I just don't agree with that approach,'' he said. ''But you've got to admit that NASA wouldn't give $30 million and say, 'Go build a structure in Tucson and try and make it work.' Lockheed wouldn't. The Pentagon wouldn't. So, more power to them.''</p>
        <p>Charles Hutchinson, an associate professor at the Office of Arid Lands Studies at the University of Arizona, described the project as ''a scientific crap shoot.''</p>
        <p>''Where the criticism comes is in their top-down approach to the science, in which you take a bunch of components, throw them all together, shake them up and hope everything will work in the end,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In interviews, participants in the project seemed reluctant to discuss its uncertainties, voicing confidence in their five years of experimentation with flora, fauna and machinery. But they gave examples of imaginative solutions to problems that seemed to illustrate the broad possibilities for unforeseen dynamics and interactions.</p>
        <p>Providing Gum for Monkeys</p>
        <p>In the separate but sometimes connecting ecologies, attention has had to be given to details like the chemistry of soils, the rate of growth of trees and the provision of natural gum for monkeys.</p>
        <p>An experimental stand of ginger trees must, if the project is to succeed, protect the rain forest from excessive sunlight at its glassed-in perimeter. Bamboo from Taiwan and India must shield it from salt-water spray from the adjacent 25-foot-deep ocean.</p>
        <p>There had been concern that termites, needed to break down the grasses in the savanna, might also feed on materials used to seal the biosphere's glass and steel skin. A new sealant was produced that should be resistant to termites.</p>
        <p>Pollinating Jungle Plants</p>
        <p>Hummingbirds have been selected to pollinate many of the jungle plants. Planners say they believe they have successfully matched the shape of the bill of the species they have chosen with the shapes of the thousands of flowers they will feed upon. And they say they believe they have selected a species that does not fly so high that it will hit the glass ceiling.</p>
        <p>When the researchers finally enter the structure and pull the airtight door shut behind them, the entire complex should begin to function as a whole, like a complex, living organism.</p>
        <p>If it works, or even if it fails, the researchers say Biosphere II will be an object lesson in the interconnectedness and vulnerability of forms of life on earth.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
