<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scarce Metal Hits $7,000 An Ounce</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="365744"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RHODIUM (METAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D61439F937A35754C0A966958260" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scarce Metal Hits $7,000 An Ounce</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Reuters</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, July 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The price of rhodium, a little-known but environmentally important precious metal, soared by $1,000, to a record $7,000 an ounce today, and some analysts expect the metal to climb higher before speculative pressures subside.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The price of rhodium, a little-known but environmentally important precious metal, soared by $1,000, to a record $7,000 an ounce today, and some analysts expect the metal to climb higher before speculative pressures subside.</p>
        <p>The price of rhodium, a little-known but environmentally important precious metal, soared by $1,000, to a record $7,000 an ounce today, and some analysts expect the metal to climb higher before speculative pressures subside.</p>
        <p>A member of the platinum metal group, rhodium is a primary ingredient in automobile catalytic converters - cylindrical ceramic blocks, structured like honeycombs, that are chemically treated and coated with platinum, rhodium and other precious metals. They convert the harmful car exhaust gasses of carbon monoxide, nitrogen oxides and hydrocarbons into carbon dioxide, water and nitrogen.</p>
        <p>Cuts Nitric Oxide Pollution</p>
        <p>Rhodium's specific role is to reduce nitric oxide pollution, and as more stringent environmental laws have been passed, the amount of the metal used has grown. About 80 percent of rhodium output is used for making catalytic converters. Chemicals, electronics and glass use the rest.</p>
        <p>The price run-up this year has been attributed to a supply shortage, caused by production problems at a large South African refinery. More recently, stockpiling by nervous industrial users has added to those pressures, the analysts said.</p>
        <p>The price of rhodium doubled between the end of 1989 and last week, moving from $1,746 an ounce in December to $3,425 last Wednesday - and then doubled again in just six days to reach today's record.</p>
        <p>Growing global pressures for legislation to reduce the level of nitric oxide from car exhausts are expected to keep rhodium demand high, the analysts said. In a tight market, they added, this will keep the price up.</p>
        <p>''The metal has no foreseeable substitute, and it is impossible to predict when the bubble is likely to burst,'' said John Taylor, a mining analyst James Capel &amp; Company, a London brokerage. [Gordon Bassett, an analyst with Johnson, Matthey North America Inc. in Philadelphia, cited an ''inflexible'' supply and some short-term production problems as the chief reasons for the run-up. ''But there's been a bit of a snowball effect lately,'' Mr. Bassett said.</p>
        <p>''There has been some extra strong buying from Japan, which we think is just inventory building. But that has spilled over into the market and caused something of a panic.'' [Johnson, Matthey North America is a unit of Johnson, Matthey P.L.C., the London concern that is the world's largest rhodium trader.]  The current shortfall is accentuated because most of the world's rhodium production of 330,000 ounces a year is committed to long-term contracts between producers and industrial users. Only 30,000 ounces to 60,000 ounces are freely traded, and no futures market exists in the metal.</p>
        <p>Despite the price increase, the analysts said automobile buyers need not worry. The amount of rhodium used in catalytic converters is minuscule. ''Even at $7,000 an ounce,'' Mr. Bassett of Johnson, Matthey North America said, ''there is only about $60 worth of rhodium in the average car.''</p>
        <p>Discovered in 1803</p>
        <p>The metal was named by William Hyde Wollaston, an English chemist and physicist who first extracted it in 1803, after the Greek word for rose, ''rhodon,'' because of the rose color of a number of its compounds. But in its pure state, rhodium is spongy and has a silver-white color.</p>
        <p>Rhodium began its record-setting ascent last November, when production problems arose at a new refinery owned by Rustenburg Platinum Holdings Ltd. in Bophuthatswana, South Africa. The refinery is managed by Matthey Rustenburg refiners, which is jointly owned by Rustenburg and Johnson, Matthey P.L.C. Rhodium is found within platinum and extracted by a complex process.</p>
        <p>Increased output from the South African platinum operations of Lonrho P.L.C., the British conglomerate, is expected to make up most of the shortfall, while Impala Platinum Holdings Ltd., another South Africa company, will also benefit, the traders said.</p>
        <p>Other producers like the Soviet Union and Canada have not yet been able to fill the gap, because it takes about six months to extract and refine rhodium from the platinum-bearing ore, Mr. Bassett said. Soviet producers, however, are using higher rhodium prices to get agreements on longer-term contracts and increase their hard-currency earnings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
