<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Urged to End Opposition to Ozone Aid</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="360854"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TOLBA, MUSTAFA K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD71131F930A25755C0A966958260" item-length="653" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Urged to End Opposition to Ozone Aid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The head of the United Nations Environment Program strongly urged the United States today to reconsider its decision to oppose new financial aid to third-world countries to help them phase out chemicals that are destroying the earth's ozone layer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The head of the United Nations Environment Program strongly urged the United States today to reconsider its decision to oppose new financial aid to third-world countries to help them phase out chemicals that are destroying the earth's ozone layer.</p>
        <p>The head of the United Nations Environment Program strongly urged the United States today to reconsider its decision to oppose new financial aid to third-world countries to help them phase out chemicals that are destroying the earth's ozone layer.</p>
        <p>The official, Mustafa K. Tolba of Egypt, executive director of the program, said that if the industrialized countries failed to provide the economic and technical help required by the third-world nations, the ''global bargain'' to protect the earth's environment would fall apart.</p>
        <p>He said he was optimistic that the United States would change its position before a meeting in London this week called to strengthen an existing international treaty to protect ozone in the atmosphere from being destroyed by chlorofluorocarbons and other industrial chemicals.</p>
        <p>But at a Senate Foreign Relations Committee hearing today, Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d reiterated that the Administration preferred to use ''existing resources'' to help the third-world countries adhere to the ozone treaty.</p>
        <p>Opposition to providing additional money to help the third-world countries phase out the offending chemicals originated with Richard G. Darman, director of the Office of Management and Budget, and John H. Sununu, the White House chief of staff, Administration officials said.</p>
        <p>While the American contribution would only be about $20 million, the White House officials reportedly feared that providing such additional funds would open the door to broad demands by those countries for assistance in solving their environmental problems.</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration wants such aid to be provided from existing funds from the World Bank or other international lending institutions. The Administration also opposes the creation of a new fund at the World Bank for environmental programs.</p>
        <p>Legislation has been introduced in Congress that would require the Government to contribute funds to help the poorer countries protect the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>In a speech at the National Press Club today, Dr. Tolba called for a ban on the chemicals destroying the ozone layer when the nations gather in London this month. Under a protocol signed in Montreal in September 1987, those who agreed to the treaty committed themselves to a 50 percent reduction in the production and use of the chemicals by the end of the century.</p>
        <p>Since then, new scientific information has shown that the destruction of the ozone layer is proceeding even more rapidly than previously recognized. A thinning ozone layer permits more ultraviolet radiation from the sun to penetrate to the earth's surface, causing skin cancer and cataracts in humans and harming crops and wildlife.</p>
        <p>Dr. Tolba also said today that he expected the international community to adopt a treaty ''with teeth'' to address the global-warming problem when it gathers at a conference in Brazil two years from now.</p>
        <p>Carbon dioxide, chlorofluorocarbons and other industrial and agricultural gases are accumulating in the atmosphere and, by trapping radiation from the sun, will cause the earth to warm substantially in the next century through a process called the greenhouse effect, many scientists believe. Despite some lingering skepticism about the scientific issues surrounding the greenhouse effect, Dr. Tolba said, ''we are moving toward a truly global consensus on the need for action and action now.''</p>
        <p>Although the Bush Administration has been stressing the need for more information about the scientific and economic implications of a global-warming treaty, ''the United States, I am sure, will not block unanimity'' but will meet ''its responsibilities toward its own people and the world at large,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At the luncheon, which was sponsored by the World Resources Institute, the United Nations official also emphasized the need for a treaty through which the nations could cooperate to preserve the world's biological diversity.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
