<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why They Killed Chico Mendes</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="377943"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKE, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REVKIN, ANDREW</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHOUMATOFF, ALEX</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BURNING SEASON, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WORLD IS BURNING, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DE1E3EF93AA2575BC0A966958260" item-length="1328" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why They Killed Chico Mendes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE; James Brooke is the chief of The New York Times's Rio de Janeiro bureau.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKE, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>THE BURNING SEASON</p>
        <p>The Murder of Chico Mendes and the Fight for the Amazon Rain Forest.</p>
        <p>By Andrew Revkin.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 317 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Houghton Mifflin Company. $19.95.</p>
        <p>THE WORLD IS BURNING</p>
        <p>By Alex Shoumatoff.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 377 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Little, Brown &amp; Company. $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>THE BURNING SEASON</p>
        <p>The Murder of Chico Mendes and the Fight for the Amazon Rain Forest.</p>
        <p>By Andrew Revkin.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 317 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Houghton Mifflin Company. $19.95.</p>
        <p>THE WORLD IS BURNING</p>
        <p>By Alex Shoumatoff.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 377 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Little, Brown &amp; Company. $19.95.</p>
        <p>THE BURNING SEASON</p>
        <p>The Murder of Chico Mendes and the Fight for the Amazon Rain Forest.</p>
        <p>By Andrew Revkin.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 317 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Houghton Mifflin Company. $19.95.</p>
        <p>THE WORLD IS BURNING</p>
        <p>By Alex Shoumatoff.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 377 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Little, Brown &amp; Company. $19.95.</p>
        <p>On the night of Dec. 22, 1988, in the small town of Xapuri in the remote Brazilian state of Acre, Francisco (Chico) Mendes Filho stepped out of his wooden-frame cottage and into the blast of a shotgun. Fleeing into the darkness, the killer undoubtedly believed that the union leader's murder would go the way of the murders of a thousand other Brazilians in land disputes in the 1980's - unpunished and largely forgotten. But to the dismay of ranchers determined to convert the western Amazon into cow pasture, that single shotgun blast has echoed around the world.</p>
        <p>During the scorching hot summer of 1988, Americans and Europeans started listening to scientists who warned that the burning and clearing of the Amazonian rain forest was contributing to a gradual warming of the earth known as the greenhouse effect. Other scientists said that a living pharmacy was going up in smoke before even 1 percent of the Amazon's plants had been studied.</p>
        <p>In life, Mendes was a unionist who defended the rights of his fellow Amazonian rubber tappers to live in the forest and harvest rubber and nuts. In Acre, where 130 ranchers expelled an estimated 100,000 tappers from the forest, Mendes fought back, rallying families to stand in front of chain saws and bulldozers. In death, Mendes, an international eco-martyr, became the catalyst for popularizing the concept that the wealth of the Amazon resides in its profusion of plant and animal life, not in its thin, sandy soil.</p>
        <p>''In leading this struggle to preserve the Amazon, Chico Mendes had made a lot of trouble for a lot of powerful people,'' Andrew Revkin writes in ''The Burning Season.'' ''He was to the ranchers of the Amazon what Cesar Chavez was to the citrus kings of California, what Lech Walesa was to the shipyard managers of Gdansk.''</p>
        <p>''The Burning Season'' and ''The World Is Burning'' - both part biography and part biology - explore Mendes's life within the wider context of the destruction of the Amazon forest. Each book provides a readable examination of a complex issue bound to loom large in the 1990's. There is considerable overlap, of course, and only the specialist will want to read both volumes. Of the two, ''The Burning Season'' seems to be more thoroughly researched and more comprehensive. A nature writer by trade, Mr. Revkin demonstrates a solid grounding in the Amazon's ecology. Alex Shoumatoff has expanded ''The World Is Burning'' from a piece in Vanity Fair and a project on the greenhouse effect. Not displaying the stylistic virtuosity of some of his recent writing, Mr. Shoumatoff appears to have hurriedly welded together his book before the Mendes market cools.</p>
        <p>But there is little indication that interest will lag in the amiable, unassuming man a Brazilian film maker recently described as the greatest Brazilian hero of this century. In May, the novelist Marcio Souza published ''O Empate Contra Chico Mendes,'' which is to provide the plot for a Warner Brothers movie. This month the cinematographer Chris Menges starts filming scenes of burning rain forest.</p>
        <p>This reviewer's heart sank on reading that Mr. Revkin needed translations of 120 hours of interview tapes. But despite the handicap of not fully understanding what Brazilians were telling him face to face, he has written an admirable work. One particularly compelling chapter relates the little-known history of many rubber tappers: in 1942, as the Japanese blocked Allied access to British rubber plantations in Malaysia, the United States began sending thousands of Brazilians from the drought-stricken northeast part of that country to collect rubber in the Amazon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Revkin's book benefits from his ability to turn a polished phrase. And insights into Mendes's early years and his projection onto the international stage flowed from the full cooperation given the author by Mendes's three closest allies: Adrian Cowell, a British film maker; Mary Helena Allegretti, a Brazilian environmentalist and the president of the Institute for Amazonian Studies; and Stephan Schwartzman, an American anthropologist who works for the Environmental Defense Fund. Mr. Revkin's original research also brings alive Mendes's mentor, Euclides Fernandes Tavora, a middle-class Communist who, in the 60's, was on the run from Brazil's military. Appearing one day at the Mendes family's forest clearing, Tavora introduced the illiterate young Chico to books, newspapers and union organizing.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Revkin has culled the slightest wisp of the first person from his text, Mr. Shoumatoff crashes around in ''The World Is Burning'' like a third-world Hunter Thompson. His account winds confusingly through time, switching back and forth like an Amazon tributary. But Mr. Shoumatoff, a student of Brazilian society for the last 14 years and the author of three other books on Brazil, excels at explaining that country's culture. Citing its inoperancia, or tropical breakdown, he accurately describes the slaying of Mendes as a sloppy mix of commission and omission: ''The Amazon has a soporific effect. It's a big part of the inoperancia problem. . . . So many things conspire against your remaining on schedule and on the ball. It's a constant struggle just to maintain consciousness, to fight off tropical entropy, torpid, rachitic, stultified, paranoid paralysis. . . . Tasks like apprehending perpetrators, keeping them behind bars, gathering evidence, trying them and sending them up the river, become too daunting, more than anything you think you could possibly get together.''</p>
        <p>But in the spirit of fairness, he notes the perception of some Brazilians that they are being asked to bottle up the Amazon's wealth to meet the demands of Americans and Europeans who long ago destroyed their own forests. Many Americans see the building of a road from Acre through Peru to the Pacific as the beginning of the end of the western Amazon. Many Acre residents see the road as a means out of economic stagnation and isolation.</p>
        <p>Today, environmentalists, economists and government officials are struggling with the challenge of how to bring economic development and a higher standard of living to the Amazon's inhabitants without eliminating the region's forest cover. Tourism, mining and selective lumbering and produce harvesting may offer some answers.</p>
        <p>In retrospect, Chico Mendes's death marked a turning point for Brazilian environmental policy. Responding to domestic and international outcries, the Brazilian Government suspended tax subsidies for ranching in the Amazon and established a string of rubber reserves in Acre. In July, Brazil's military, which has long viewed ecologists as security threats, promised to lend helicopters to help repress fires in the rain forest. And Brazilian climatologists now argue that deforestation of the Amazon would throw Brazil's weather out of whack, jeopardizing the nation's position as the world's second largest food exporter after the United States.</p>
        <p>In June, the river town of Xapuri saw its first jury trial in years. On June 22, Darci and Oloci Alves da Silva, the half brothers who are suspects in the Mendes murder, were convicted and sentenced to 12 years in prison for shooting into a crowd of protesting rubber tappers in May 1988. Judicial officials say the Mendes murder trial could begin soon.</p>
        <p>But the old ways die hard in Xapuri. On the day the da Silvas were convicted, Mendes's widow, Ilzamar, and his union successor, Osmarino Amancio Rodrigues, both received death threats. And on July 10, a priest who works with the rubber tappers was driving past the da Silvas' ranch when two shots rang out. The priest, Isaias Franca Maia, escaped with minor injuries.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
