<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Genetic Maps May Point the Way To Healthier and Sturdier Crops</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="315449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GENETICS AND HEREDITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEARY, WARREN E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DA103AF93AA35752C0A966958260" item-length="1030" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Genetic Maps May Point the Way To Healthier and Sturdier Crops</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEARY, WARREN E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: EVEN as plans are being made for an international effort to map the entire genetic blueprint of humans, plant scientists are proposing similar efforts to understand the hereditary messages that control the characteristics of plants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: EVEN as plans are being made for an international effort to map the entire genetic blueprint of humans, plant scientists are proposing similar efforts to understand the hereditary messages that control the characteristics of plants.</p>
        <p>EVEN as plans are being made for an international effort to map the entire genetic blueprint of humans, plant scientists are proposing similar efforts to understand the hereditary messages that control the characteristics of plants.</p>
        <p>Among other goals, the research could produce tools to modify plant life to better withstand environmental changes and stresses like shifting climates, acid rain and destruction of native habitats. If, for example, global warming changes the growing season in currently productive agricultural areas, they say, it may be possible to develop wheat or corn that adjusts and thrives under the new conditions.</p>
        <p>The Agriculture Department has established an office in its principal scientific branch, the Agricultural Research Service, to lay plans for what it hopes will be a 10-year, $500 million program to study the genes that control traits like drought resistance and nutrient use in economically important plants.</p>
        <p>In a broader project, the National Institutes of Health and the Energy Department are leading a Federal effort to map the human genome, or genetic blueprint, in cooperation with other countries. The proposed 15-year program, estimated to cost more than $3 billion, would attempt to locate and establish the chemical structure of each of the estimated 50,000 to 100,000 genes that reside on the 46 chromosomes in each human cell.</p>
        <p>Basic Material of Heredity</p>
        <p>Genes are segments of DNA, or deoxyribonucleic acid, the basic material of heredity, which controls production of proteins responsible for all characteristics of an organism.</p>
        <p>A goal of the plant genome mapping program is to understand how different plants work at a basic genetic level to handle such things as heat stress and pest resistance, and to see if beneficial characteristics might be transferred among different crop varieties. No decision has been made on what crops or characteristics will be studied first, but candidate plants recommended by various interests include wheat, barley, cotton, tomatoes, corn, potatoes and soybeans.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jerome P. Miksche, the Agriculture Department plant scientist who was appointed in August to head the proposed project, said the program would not attempt to chart all the DNA in one plant, as the human genome project is to do for people. The number of chemical subunits that make up DNA is about the same in a plant like corn as it is in humans, he said, and completely mapping its genetic structure would rival the human project in size and expense.</p>
        <p>''It makes more sense to focus on gene systems or traits, such as growth, heat tolerance or moisture content, and see how those things are regulated by genes in several different plants,'' Dr. Miksche said in an interview. ''If we find the gene for heat tolerance in a plant, for instance, we could take it out and see if we can transfer it to important crops in anticipation of climate changes.''</p>
        <p>Wider Project Envisioned</p>
        <p>Even with this effort, scientists have not given up on the idea of completely mapping the genome of one plant. The National Science Foundation, the Federal agency that sponsors much of the nation's basic research, is considering a proposal to map all of the genetic material of a small weed called Arabidopsis thaliana.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mary E. Clutter, an assistant director of the foundation, said Arabidopsis is a simple, well-studied plant that would be an ideal candidate. The entire genome of the flowering weed, which has no known benefit but produces thousands of seeds, is smaller than one human chromosome and the plant goes through several generations within one year, making it an ideal model for potentially beneficial genetic work with other plants.</p>
        <p>''We envision a project that can be done in 10 years for maybe about $70 million,'' Dr. Clutter said.</p>
        <p>Supporters of the project will meet this spring to prepare a formal research plan to submit to an international meeting in hopes of encouraging wide participation by scientists from other countries.</p>
        <p>Dr. Clutter said the foundation already spends about $1.5 million annually on Arabidopsis research and additional work on the plant is being sponsored worldwide. Additional money may be sought later from the National Science Foundation for more formal research.</p>
        <p>Dr. Sharon R. Long, a Stanford University scientist who conducts research on plants and the bacteria that interact with them, supports both proposals. But she particularly applauded the Agriculture Department idea of focusing on plant function instead of trying to do detailed studies of a few plants. While some plants like corn or wheat have been studied extensively at genetic levels, others have been neglected, she said.</p>
        <p>Less Detail</p>
        <p>Genetic mapping can be done with different amounts of precision, she said, and some plants could benefit from even less-detailed mapping of their genetic structure. Alfalfa, for example, is an important farm plant that has been bred and studied for years, she said, but not at the molecular level. Even a preliminary chromosomal map that generally locates some of its gene functions, when combined with what is known from traditional breeding, would be an enormous boost for alfalfa research, Dr. Long said.</p>
        <p>Functions, such as how it picks up nutrients or retains moisture, affect productivity and the ability of a plant to respond to environmental change, and this is what we should be studying.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Miksche said the proposed project, for which his department may seek start-up funds in the next Federal budget, would involve giving grants and contracts to researchers from academic institutions, private industry and government. The Agriculture Department and others have long sponsored research into plant genetics, but supporters of the project said these diverse efforts have not been well focused and financing has been erratic.</p>
        <p>Several influential Congressmen on Senate and House agriculture and science committees have been urging the Agriculture Department to do more biotechnology research, including gene mapping. But the reception for such a program is likely to depend in part on how it addresses environmental concerns about the type of project.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
