<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hanson to Buy a Stake in Peabody</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="327117"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PEABODY HOLDING CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HANSON PLC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">BOEING CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">BECHTEL INVESTMENTS INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">EASTERN ENTERPRISES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEWMONT MINING CORP</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D71E3CF935A25751C0A966958260" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hanson to Buy a Stake in Peabody</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Hanson P.L.C., the British-based investment concern, said yesterday that it had agreed to buy a 45 percent stake in the Peabody Holding Company, the largest coal producer in the United States, for about $504 million. The share Hanson is buying is now held jointly by three companies: the Boeing Company, Bechtel Investments Inc.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Hanson P.L.C., the British-based investment concern, said yesterday that it had agreed to buy a 45 percent stake in the Peabody Holding Company, the largest coal producer in the United States, for about $504 million. The share Hanson is buying is now held jointly by three companies: the Boeing Company, Bechtel Investments Inc.</p>
        <p>Hanson P.L.C., the British-based investment concern, said yesterday that it had agreed to buy a 45 percent stake in the Peabody Holding Company, the largest coal producer in the United States, for about $504 million. The share Hanson is buying is now held jointly by three companies: the Boeing Company, Bechtel Investments Inc. and Eastern Enterprises.</p>
        <p>The rest of the company is owned by the Newmont Mining Corporation, which said it has begun talks with Hanson and other companies on the sale of its 55 percent interest in Peabody. Hanson officials say they have not made any decisions beyond the purchase of the 45 percent stake.</p>
        <p>''We have engaged in this transaction and, later, we will look at the other options,'' said David H. Clarke, chief operating officer of Hanson's operations in the United States. ''We're delighted to own 45 percent of Peabody, and we're going to take things one step at a time.''</p>
        <p>The transaction is subject to regulatory approvals and the consent of Peabody's lenders and Newmont.</p>
        <p>Analysts said the three companies had been interested in selling their holdings in Peabody for some time, adding that the company's earning had been relatively flat in the last two years. They said the price Hanson paid seemed to be a fair one.</p>
        <p>Productivity Improved</p>
        <p>Marc D. Cohen, an analyst with Kidder, Peabody, said Hanson was buying part of Peabody because ''it wants to expand its industrial exposure in the United States.''</p>
        <p>He noted that Peabody had improved its productivity in recent years because it had renegotiated many long-term contracts with customers. ''They are not locked into as many of the long-term, fixed contracts that can be a drag on earnings when market conditions shift,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Sir Gordon White, Hanson's chairman, said that Peabody's coal business ''represents an attractive investment,'' and that he expected a strong demand for coal in coming years. ''In the United States today, over half the electricity produced comes from coal and it is far more abundant than petroleum,'' he said. ''This is a source of energy upon which America can rely well into the future.''</p>
        <p>Peabody produces 9 percent of the coal mined in the United States. It produced 87 million tons last year and has reserves of 8.7 billion tons. The company, which is privately held, had pretax earnings of $136.5 million last year, down slightly from $138 million in 1988.</p>
        <p>Debt a Factor</p>
        <p>For the last three years, Newmont has been seeking to reduce $2 billion in debt from a special dividend it paid to shareholders to thwart a takeover attempt by T. Boone Pickens, the investor. Newmont attempted a recapitalization plan for Peabody last year but abandoned it because of what it termed uncertainties resulting from a coal miners' strike and the Bush Administration's proposals to combat acid rain. Newmont said several options remained open to it and Hanson that might be discussed later.</p>
        <p>The recapitalization plan would have yielded a $425 million pretax dividend from Peabody to Newmont, along with a $75 million payment to Newmont from new Peabody investors, while allowing Newmont to keep its equity in Peabody.</p>
        <p>''If we receive the kind of cash we're contemplating getting from a transaction, it could lower our interest costs from $89 million last year, to less than half that this year,'' said James F. Hill, a Newmont spokesman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clarke of Hanson said Peabody had historically been ''a solid company with an excellent management team.'' He said the company had effectively repositioned itself into a low-sulfur coal producer that would have fewer of the environmental problems associated with medium- and high-sulfur coal.</p>
        <p>In the United States, Hanson's operations include SCM Chemicals, Ames Tools, Universal Gym, Kaiser Cement, Jacuzzi Whirlpool Bath and Spa Products, Faberware Cookware and Gold Fields Mining. In Britain, Hanson's holdings include Imperial Tobacco, Consolidated Gold Fields, and London Brick and Butterley Brick.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
