<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Venezuela Pushing 'Liquid Coal'</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="391966"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BITUMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VENEZUELA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKE, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD7143DF936A25753C1A966958260" item-length="1376" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Venezuela Pushing 'Liquid Coal'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKE, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>MORICHAL, Venezuela</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: With oil prices surging, some electric power company managers are seeing some relief through the huge bitumen reserves here in eastern Venezuela.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: With oil prices surging, some electric power company managers are seeing some relief through the huge bitumen reserves here in eastern Venezuela.</p>
        <p>With oil prices surging, some electric power company managers are seeing some relief through the huge bitumen reserves here in eastern Venezuela.</p>
        <p>Using the label ''liquid coal,'' Venezuela started marketing a bitumen and water emulsion this year that is liquid and easy to handle like oil but priced like coal - a cheap and stable commodity.</p>
        <p>Patented under the name Orimulsion, the fuel comes from Venezuela's vast Orinoco Heavy Oil Belt and can be burned in power plants as an alternative to coal or to the international standby, Heavy Fuel Oil No. 6, after a plant has been modified. The most expensive part of the modification is adding scrubbers to smokestacks to remove Orimulsion's relatively high concentration of sulphur, which causes acid rain, from emissions.</p>
        <p>Successful Tests</p>
        <p>After two years of successful tests in power plants in Canada, Britain and Japan, the world power generating industry appears to be optimistic about the product.</p>
        <p>One reason is the price. Depending on contracts, Orimulsion is sold at $8 to $9.50 a ton, or about $1.10 to $1.30 a barrel. In contrast, heavy fuel oil is now selling for about $19 a barrel, sharply up from $10 a barrel at the end of July.</p>
        <p>''We have 11 plants that can be converted to Orimulsion,'' said Ray Golden, a spokesman for the Florida Power and Light Company, in an interview. ''It could mean $3 to $5 billion in fuel savings over 15 years.'' He added: ''Orimulsion is a win-win situation. It's stored, transported and burned like oil, but priced like coal.''</p>
        <p>Environmental Waiver Needed</p>
        <p>His company expects to be the first American utility to conduct trial tests, probably in December, and feasibility studies are under way at power companies in Maine, Massachusetts, Puerto Rico and Virginia. But test burns in the Florida company's 400-megawatt unit in Sanford, Fla., will depend on the Environmental Protection Agency's granting a temporary waiver of air emission limits to allow the burning of 2.5 million barrels of the new fuel.</p>
        <p>''Once the Middle East crisis hit, my phone started to ring,'' said Blair A. Kennedy, Orimulsion's project manager for the New Brunswick Power Company, in a telephone interview. After test-burning 1.1 million barrels of the fuel, the Canadian utility is negotiating a 20-year supply contract with the Venezuelans.</p>
        <p>Venezuela is the only country to produce the fuel commercially, but plant managers do not appear to be overly worried about becoming dependent on a single supplier. Once boilers, pipes and pumps have been modified, a plant can switch back and forth in the same day between Orimulsion and heavy fuel oil.</p>
        <p>The world's largest deposits of extra-heavy crude and bitumen - 1.2 trillion barrels - lie below the dry, flat plains here in northeast Venezuela. With current technology, largely steam injection, about 22 percent, or 270 billion barrels, can be recovered, making the field equal to slightly more than one-quarter of the world's proven oil reserves.</p>
        <p>Production in the five-year-old Orimulsion project is to jump from 6,000 barrels a day this year - largely for tests - to 700,000 barrels a day in 1996, said Carlos San Borregales, corporate director for Bitumenes Orinoco S.A. Known as Bitor, the company is a marketing subsidiary of the national oil company, Petroleos de Venezuela.</p>
        <p>Using Salt Water</p>
        <p>The emulsion is created by heating salt water and forcing it into the deposits, which loosens the material to be pumped up. On the surface, the salt water is removed and fresh water added. The emulsion appears to resolve the longstanding problems of transporting and burning an oil so heavy that once above ground, it takes on the consistency of butter.</p>
        <p>''The problem has always been how to get this gunk out and sell it somewhere,'' Kim Fuad, an editor of Petroleum Intelligence Weekly, said in a telephone interview from London.</p>
        <p>Although drilling started around here in 1935, in the next 30 years only 58 exploratory wells were drilled because the extra-heavy oil was uneconomical to produce in the days of cheap oil. 800 Wells Drilled But after OPEC sent oil prices surging on world markets and Venezuela formed its national oil company in 1975, the Government embarked on a five-year, $545 million exploratory program. Now, 800 wells later, geologists have a clear idea of the dimensions of the 20,000-square-mile energy province that lies between 500 and 4,000 feet below ground.</p>
        <p>In 1982, Intevep S.A., the research affiliate of Petroleos de Venezuela, teamed with British Petroleum Research International, a unit of the British Petroleum Company, to find a way of moving the tar through pipelines. B.P. was interested because it wanted to exploit the vast Athabasca tar sands fields in Alberta. Canada has the world's second-largest bitumen deposits, 890 billion barrels.</p>
        <p>In 1984, the researchers came up with an emulsion of 70 percent oil and 30 percent water that B.P. labeled ''transoil'' and Intevep labeled ''imulsion.'' In 1985, they began testing it.</p>
        <p>But B.P. apparently has given up on trying to produce the emulsion commercially because production costs in the cold climate of Canada, from $8 to $12 a barrel, were far higher than the costs in this equatorial nation, where the average bitumen well produces 1,000 barrels a day.</p>
        <p>Question of Quotas</p>
        <p>While scientists at the laboratory of Lagoven S.A., a subsidiary of Petroleos de Venezuela here, are working to improve the product, lawyers are working on a still-unresolved hurdle - production quotas of the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries, of which Venezuela is a member.</p>
        <p>Venezuela's official line is that Orimulsion is a ''non-conventional product,'' and OPEC quotas do not apply to certain products, including bituminous crudes. Nevertheless, many Venezuelans expect a fight with OPEC once Orimulsion starts cutting into sales of its more expensive competitor, Heavy Fuel Oil No. 6.</p>
        <p>''Orimulsion is an energy material that we cannot place with the liquid hydrocarbons, but with coal,'' said Venzuela's President, Carlos Andres Perez, in an interview in Caracas. ''In the 1990's, it will play an important role in replacing coal.''</p>
        <p>Alberto Quiros Corradi, a former oil company executive, said in an interview in Caracas, ''Fuel oil is on its way out, but it would worry OPEC if Orimulsion starts ending up in refineries.''</p>
        <p>More Stable Pricing</p>
        <p>To defuse the issue, oil company officials are marketing Orimulsion as a replacement for coal, often measuring the new fuel in metric tons rather than barrels. As an attraction to power companies, the oil officials are linking the price of Orimulsion to coal instead of to oil, which has fluctuated wildly. Bitor offers buyers long-term, 15- to 25-year supply contracts with the price pegged to a basket of international coal prices. The price of coal has varied little over the last 20 years.</p>
        <p>''We offer price stability,'' said Mr. San Borregales of Bitor. To promote sales in North America, Bitor last year opened a marketing affiliate, the Bitor America Corporation, in Boca Raton, Fla.</p>
        <p>The main drawback of Orimulsion is the relatively high sulfur content of its bitumen base - 3.8 percent, almost in the middle coal's range of 1 to 8 percent sulfur content.</p>
        <p>Financial Times Report</p>
        <p>Last year, a Financial Times Management Report found that converting a 500 megawatt oil-fired plant to Orimulsion could cost $3 million. Adding scrubbers to limit sulfur and electrostatic precipitators to block chimney ash would raise the cost to $74 million.</p>
        <p>Tightening environmental standards in the United States and Europe are making anti-sulfur equipment inevitable for most power companies. To convert the same oil-fired power plant to coal would cost $203 million, according to the 1989 study, ''Orimulsion: A Revolutionary New Fuel for Power and Industry.''</p>
        <p>Straying from the dry, technical language of the 100-page study, Miri Zlatnar, its author, wrote: ''From the substantial test data available on Orimulsion illustrating its efficient combustion performance and highly competitive cost per ton, together with the required investment capital, one can deduce that its potential in the energy market is almost awesome.'' FPL Groupd (Florida Power and Light)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
