<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Congressional Negotiators Agree On New Curbs on Car Emissions</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="390346"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DE113CF932A25753C1A966958260" item-length="674" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Congressional Negotiators Agree On New Curbs on Car Emissions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Staff members of the House-Senate conference committee rewriting the Clean Air Act reached agreement today on an array of new standards for reducing air pollution from motor vehicles that will begin to take effect in the mid-1990's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Staff members of the House-Senate conference committee rewriting the Clean Air Act reached agreement today on an array of new standards for reducing air pollution from motor vehicles that will begin to take effect in the mid-1990's.</p>
        <p>Staff members of the House-Senate conference committee rewriting the Clean Air Act reached agreement today on an array of new standards for reducing air pollution from motor vehicles that will begin to take effect in the mid-1990's.</p>
        <p>The compromise breaks a three-week deadlock, mainly by accepting the House version, which calls on automobile manufacturers to reduce emissions of hydrocarbons by 35 percent and nitrogen oxide by 60 percent, starting with 1994 model cars. Hydrocarbons and nitrogen oxide are components of urban smog.</p>
        <p>The negotiators hope to resolve other differences between the House and Senate versions quickly to give both houses time to consider the bill before Congress's adjournment, which is now scheduled for Oct. 19.</p>
        <p>The leaders of the conference, Representative John D. Dingell, Democrat of Michigan, and Senator Max Baucus, Democrat of Montana, said they expected the new emissions standards to be approved by the negotiators.</p>
        <p>Industry Impact Is Seen</p>
        <p>''This was the toughest title of the bill,'' said Senator Baucus. ''I've talked to Senate conferees and House conferees, and this agreement is tantamount to approving these provisions.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dingell said, ''I suspect that industry is going to lose some sleep trying to comply with what are some very stringent provisions.''</p>
        <p>The completion of the new emissions standards came after negotiators argued over a proposal Mr. Dingell made late last month to limit the authority of states to enforce auto-emission standards as strict as those in effect in California. The current Clean Air Act includes a provision that allows states to adopt and enforce California's auto-emission standards, which are stricter than the Federal regulations and require auto makers to build two types of cars, one for California and another for the rest of the country.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dingell said he feared that if states adopted the California regulations, as New York did in September, but enforced them differently, companies would be required to make even more types of cars to meet the various standards.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dingell dropped his proposal after conferees agreed to specify in the bill that auto makers would have to design only two types of cars, to meet the California standards and the new Federal standards.</p>
        <p>On to Plant Emissions</p>
        <p>With the motor vehicle provisions finished, the House and Senate staff members turned late today to the sections of the bill that focus on reducing emissions from power plants and other industries that cause acid rain, and to regulations to limit factory emissions of 190 chemicals that are said to cause cancer.</p>
        <p>Senator Baucus said he and Representative Dingell met today with several conferees and Representative Thomas S. Foley, the Speaker of the House, and agreed to try to finish the bill by midnight Sunday.</p>
        <p>The regulations to reduce pollution from motor vehicles that were agreed to today include these measures:</p>
        <p>* Oil companies would be required to develop new kinds of gasoline that burn more cleanly. The new fuels would be sold, beginning in 1992, in the cities that have the worst problems with carbon monoxide pollution.</p>
        <p>* Auto manufacturers would be required to design and build cars for the Southern California market that use entirely new technology that would sharply reduce emissions of pollutants. The program will begin with the 1994 model year, when 150,000 cars are to be offered that reduce emissions of volatile organic compounds by 50 percent.</p>
        <p>* By 1998, all cars sold in the United States would be required to have pollution-control equipment that can meet the new emissions standards and sturdy enough to last for 10 years or 100,000 miles.</p>
        <p>* By 1996, 40 percent of all new cars must be equipped with a system to trap volatile organic chemicals that escape in refueling. All new cars would need the filters by 1999.</p>
        <p>Tim McCarthy, a spokesman for the Motor Vehicles Manufacturers Association, said he did not know the effect that the proposed regulations would have on the cost of an automobile.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
