<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Exxon Votes Down Environmental Plans</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="347396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">EXXON CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAWL, LAWRENCE G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAYES, THOMAS C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DB143EF935A15757C0A966958260" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Exxon Votes Down Environmental Plans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS C. HAYES, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAYES, THOMAS C</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, April 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Under siege by environmentalists for more than a year, Lawrence G. Rawl, the chairman of the Exxon Corporation, won a measure of support today as a series of environmental initiatives were overwhelmingly rejected at the company's annual shareholders' meeting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Under siege by environmentalists for more than a year, Lawrence G. Rawl, the chairman of the Exxon Corporation, won a measure of support today as a series of environmental initiatives were overwhelmingly rejected at the company's annual shareholders' meeting.</p>
        <p>Under siege by environmentalists for more than a year, Lawrence G. Rawl, the chairman of the Exxon Corporation, won a measure of support today as a series of environmental initiatives were overwhelmingly rejected at the company's annual shareholders' meeting.</p>
        <p>Shareholders belonging to various environmental groups, including Friends of the Earth, the National Wildlife Federation and an organization of Alaskan fishermen, were vastly outnumbered by the company's supporters and were often booed or shouted down during the meeting, which lasted 3 hours and 45 minutes.</p>
        <p>Rosemary King, a retired Exxon employee and a stockholder, said, ''Exxon has put forth the greatest effort.'' She suggested that environmentalists dissatisfied with the company's handling of the Exxon Valdez oil spill in Alaska should ''store your car, stop flying airplanes and walk or ride a horse in the winter snow or summer heat.''</p>
        <p>But the gathering of 1,850 stockholders fell silent when three women living near Exxon refineries and chemical plants in Texas pleaded with Mr. Rawl and the company's 14 other directors to address the untold suffering they said was caused by toxic wastes Exxon employees had dumped in their neighborhoods in recent years.</p>
        <p>'Damaged Beyond Repair'</p>
        <p>''I want to beg you to have waste reduction,'' said Gloria Chaplin, an environmental advocate who lives with her three children near the nation's largest petrochemical refinery, which Exxon owns and operates in Baytown, Tex.</p>
        <p>''When I moved there in 1979, I didn't know what toxic waste was,'' she said in a trembling voice. Now, she continued, ''my children's bones break easily and their noses bleed whenever they get near paint. We have been damaged beyond repair. I can't believe all of you would want to hurt other people.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rawl, who presided over the meeting, said he was unaware of the hazardous waste problems in communities near Exxon sites in Texas. ''All I can tell you,'' he told Mrs. Chaplin in a sympathetic voice, ''is I will look into your situation.''</p>
        <p>The Exxon shareholders voted down six proposals that among other things would have committed the company to detailed reviews and public disclosures of its handling of toxic chemicals, created a committee of directors devoted to environmental issues and required it to disclose the amount of carbon dioxide emissions from its plants and adopt a plan to reduce them.</p>
        <p>'We Are Very Encouraged'</p>
        <p>None of the proposals received more than 10 percent of the more than 900 million shares that were voted at the meeting. But Brent Blackwelder, a vice president of Friends of the Earth, said the proposals had drawn more support than many environmentalists had anticipated.</p>
        <p>''We are very encouraged by this and will continue our effort to make Exxon environmentally more responsible,'' he said in an interview.</p>
        <p>The environmentalists called on Mr. Rawl to resign and said the Exxon Valdez oil spill on March 24, 1989, had led to a growing incidence of alcoholism and abuse of children and spouses in communities near Prince William Sound.</p>
        <p>The Exxon chairman seemed to go out of his way at the onset of the meeting to accommodate his critics, but later ridiculed some and angrily rejected the protests of others.</p>
        <p>In one instance, he said he would consider a proposal from Jay D. Hair, president of the National Wildlife Federation and an oustpoken critic of Exxon's handling of the Alaskan spill, to meet privately with him to assess Exxon's efforts in Alaska.</p>
        <p>''I'd like to be reasonable with you on a beach in Alaska,'' Mr. Rawl said. Exxon resigned from the federation's corporate council last summer after Mr. Hair publicly assailed Exxon's efforts in Alaska.</p>
        <p>In the opening minutes of today's meeting, Mr. Hair assailed the company's optimistic portrayal of its cleanup program in Alaska, which was presented in a six-minute video that featured local residents, environmentalists and Exxon employees.</p>
        <p>The Exxon chairman also showed flashes of temper. When a fisherman from Prince William Sound, Robin Dexter, said the company should use double-hulled tankers as a measure to reduce odds of future disastrous spills in the region, even at the cost of $120 million a ship, Mr. Rawl cut him short, saying: ''Thank you very much. You've had enough time.'' Double Hulls Are Rejected Mr. Rawl said Federal law prohibits Exxon from using foreign-built tankers to tranport oil from one American port to another. He said Exxon would face huge costs compared with other oil companies if it were forced to replace its tanker fleet with double-hulled vessels made in the United States.</p>
        <p>He said the double-hulled tankers Conoco Inc. recently said it would use will be purchased from Korean shipyards at $50 million a vessel and will be used by Conoco to transport oil to foreign ports from operations in the Gulf of Mexico.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rawl also used the meeting to announce that Exxon would soon sell a cleaner gasoline in 40 cities and towns along the Gulf Coast and Eastern Seaboard, including New York City. Exxon is the sixth oil company to announce a cleaner-burning gasoline, and its program will be the largest.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
