<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Weapons Plant Pressed for Accounting of Toll on Environment and Health</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="326755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC WEAPONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLUTONIUM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REAL ESTATE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">COLORADO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">DENVER (COLO)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROCKY FLATS NUCLEAR WEAPONS PLANT (DENVER)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DOW CHEMICAL CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROCKWELL INTERNATIONAL CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions/Western States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado/Denver</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plutonium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DA103BF936A25751C0A966958260" item-length="1790" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Weapons Plant Pressed for Accounting of Toll on Environment and Health</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>DENVER, Feb. 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Rocky Flats Plant, the sole supplier of plutonium triggers for thermonuclear weapons, is facing the most intense pressure in its 38-year history for a full public accounting of accidents and operations that have contaminated the Denver area with plutonium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Rocky Flats Plant, the sole supplier of plutonium triggers for thermonuclear weapons, is facing the most intense pressure in its 38-year history for a full public accounting of accidents and operations that have contaminated the Denver area with plutonium.</p>
        <p>The Rocky Flats Plant, the sole supplier of plutonium triggers for thermonuclear weapons, is facing the most intense pressure in its 38-year history for a full public accounting of accidents and operations that have contaminated the Denver area with plutonium.</p>
        <p>The Colorado Department of Health will choose a company on Thursdayto undertake the largest study ever conducted on whether accidental emissions of plutonium from Rocky Flats have been a health threat.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, 10,000 retired workers and 50,000 business and property owners in communities surrounding the plant filed separate lawsuits against two former corporate managers of Rocky Flats. The suits seek millions of dollars from the Dow Chemical Company and the Rockwell International Corporation to finance medical studies and to pay for a decline in property values and business they contend was caused by environmental contamination and fear of the plant.</p>
        <p>And in January, James D. Watkins, the Secretary of Energy, announced the start of two sweeping studies of the environmental and health toll of Rocky Flats and the 16 other principal plants and laboratories in the nuclear weapons industry.</p>
        <p>Dismantling Bulwarks of Secrecy</p>
        <p>Here and elsewhere in the 12 states that are home to these plants, the bulwarks of secrecy that have protected them from outside interference for most of the 45 years of the atomic age are being dismantled.</p>
        <p>''I've always found that when you talk about Rocky Flats in this area, everybody has just a piece of the truth,'' said Albert J. Hazle, a radiation protection specialist for the Colorado Department of Health. ''The environmentalists have a piece. People living around the plant have a piece. The state has a piece. Nobody has the whole truth. It's time for the Energy Department to make the whole truth known.''</p>
        <p>The new manager of Rocky Flats, EG&amp;G Inc., a longtime weapons industry contractor based in Wellesley, Mass., said it would cooperate with the calls for disclosure. ''We welcome a new era of openness,'' said B. Philip Warner, general manager of the plant for EG&amp;G. ''We don't feel we can be successful by saying the public does not have the right to know what's going on here and what went on.''</p>
        <p>Dow Chemical, which built Rocky Flats and managed it from 1952 until 1975, and Rockwell International, which managed the plant until last Dec. 31, have defended their role at the plant. In a statement issued from its headquarters in Midland, Mich., Dow Chemical said, ''Worker safety and environmental matters were always important considerations for Dow at Rocky Flats.''</p>
        <p>Rockwell International did not respond to a reporter's request for comment. But on Jan. 3, three days after leaving the plant, Rockwell took out full-page advertisements in Denver's two daily newspapers saying the company had been victimized by turf battles, political disputes and unfair news coverage. Rockwell said it had managed Rocky Flats ''with proper concern for public health, safety and the environment.''</p>
        <p>Source of Concern: Plutonium</p>
        <p>The source of concern about Rocky Flats is the plant's principal product: plutonium.</p>
        <p>Plutonium is a man-made element produced by bombarding uranium with neutrons in a reactor. It is one of the most toxic elements known and emits alpha particles, a type of radiation that is most dangerous when it is inhaled or ingested. One-millionth of a gram of plutonium, a microscopic speck, is capable of initiating cancers if it lodges in tissue, scientists say. The amount of plutonium that accidentally escaped from Rocky Flats has never been established, and scientists have long been at odds about the health risk.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department, which for years insisted that Rocky Flats was a model of efficient management, now estimates that 3.2 ounces of plutonium has escaped from the plant since it opened in 1952. The department acknowledges that the area around the plant, including parts of Denver, has been contaminated by plutonium from the plant, but says the risk to residents is so small as to be of no concern.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Edward A. Martell, a radiochemist at the National Center for Atmospheric Research in Boulder, Colo., is one of several scientists who have studied the contamination, and he estimated the emissions were 10 to 20 times the level stated by the Government and the risk to public health substantially greater.</p>
        <p>''It takes minuscule amounts of plutonium to cause cancer or promote cancer,'' Dr. Martell said in an interview. ''We know there is an awful lot of plutonium out there. The soil-borne contamination has been progressively redistributed by wind in the direction of the heart of Denver. Plutonium-induced cancers in people may take 20 or 30 years to develop. In effect, everybody living within 8 or 10 miles east and southeast of Rocky Flats may be guinea pigs.''</p>
        <p>Classified Documents</p>
        <p>One of the principal sources of data for the Colorado Department of Health study will be the classified documents locked in Rocky Flats' technical library or in restricted files at the National Archives and Records Administration center here. Dr. Ellen J. Mangione, director of the state health department's Division of Disease Control and Environmental Epidemiology, said the Energy Department had assured the state that it was prepared to make the records available to the researchers. Dr. Mangione also said she would seek public disclosure of the records studied by the researchers.</p>
        <p>The records are also of interest to Bruce H. DeBoskey, the lawyer who filed the lawsuits on behalf of plant workers and property owners on Jan. 30. Mr. DeBoskey said he would seek to prove that workers and residents had been exposed to hazardous levels of plutonium.</p>
        <p>The Government and the state agree that the most plutonium was released into the atmosphere in fires in 1957 and 1969 and through leaks from thousands of corroded steel barrels stored in a field on the 380-acre plant site for a decade beginning in 1958.</p>
        <p>By far the most complete public account of the fires and the plutonium leaks is a three-volume study written in 1978 by Howard K. Holme, a Denver lawyer. In July 1985, Mr. Holme settled lawsuits against the Government, Dow Chemical and Rockwell for at least $9.2 million on behalf of owners of about 2,000 acres of contaminated farmland near the plant. The exact amount of the settlement and the terms are secret.</p>
        <p>Mr. Holme's report, based on 60,000 documents that were edited for his review, has been in storage since 1985 at the National Archives here. The Energy Department in 1984 prepared a point-by-point response that confirmed most of the facts in the Holme report. The New York Times was made aware of the existence of both documents by an investigator in Mr. DeBoskey's law firm and obtained copies of them.</p>
        <p>Spontaneous Fire in 1957</p>
        <p>The Holme report says that two hours before midnight on September 11, 1957, a fire was discovered in a plutonium production room in Building 771, one of the most important installations at Rocky Flats. The fire began spontaneously (plutonium burns in the presence of oxygen) and rapidly spread out of control because of a series of mistakes made by supervisors and firefighters.</p>
        <p>Instead of water, which firefighters from the plant thought might cause a chemical reaction with plutonium, carbon dioxide was used to battle the flames without success. And in a violation of procedures, firefighters turned on the building's exhaust fans, which fanned the fire and carried hot gases into the main air exhaust system. At 10:37 P.M., almost half an hour after the fire was discovered, water lines were brought into the building and the flames in the production room, where the blaze erupted, were extinguished.</p>
        <p>But 12 minutes later an explosion occurred in the exhaust system. The bank of 620 filters in the system that prevented plutonium dust from reaching the atmosphere during normal operations had ignited. The filters, which had not been cleaned for four years, burned for 13 hours and were destroyed, the report says.</p>
        <p>Thick black smoke with an unknown amount of plutonium poured from the 150-foot-tall ventilation stack throughout the night, Mr. Holme says in his report. The fire was so hot it melted the top of the exhaust stack and destroyed the radiation monitors. It was extinguished at 11:28 A.M. the next day after causing nearly $1 million in structural damage.</p>
        <p>Unable to Account for 30 Pounds</p>
        <p>The report says that up to 92 pounds of plutonium were consumed in the fire. That would be enough to build triggers for about 35 nuclear weapons. The Atomic Energy Commission, the predecessor of the Energy Department, estimated that less than an ounce of plutonium was released into the atmosphere. Mr. Holme, though, says that after the building was cleaned, Rocky Flats was unable to account for 30 pounds of plutonium.</p>
        <p>A much larger fire on Sunday, May 11, 1969, destroyed the interiors of Building 776 and Building 777, the plutonium manufacturing and assembly areas, causing $45 million in damage and burning up at least 2,200 pounds of plutonium worth $22 million, the report says. This fire also burned through the filters in the building's exhaust system, and witnesses reported that plutonium-contaminated smoke rose into the atmosphere from a ventilation duct on the roof. In a declassified report delivered to the Congress in 1969, the Atomic Energy Commission said the fire was contained by 8 P.M., five and a half hours after it began, and that less than half an ounce of plutonium was released into the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The Holme report also says management lapses led to the outdoor storage of 5,200 barrels of liquid plutonium wastes, a practice that was unauthorized. The report says that plutonium leaked from the barrels for years and that one reason for the seepage was that Dow Chemical purchased second-hand steel barrels to contain costs.</p>
        <p>Documents provided to Mr. Holmes said Dow and the Atomic Energy Commission were aware for years that plutonium was leaking onto the dry ground and that plutonium-contaminated dust was blowing toward downtown Denver, 16 miles away. In 1969, after a year of clearing away the barrels, Dow paved the 3.3-acre field to contain dirt contaminated with plutonium. No soil samples were taken before the paving took place. The Energy Department estimates that 1.7 ounces of the plutonium that leaked blew away.</p>
        <p>Twice since October 1988, the nuclear processing areas of Rocky Flats have been shut for emergency repairs and retraining; the latest closing was ordered in November. Mr. Watkins said earlier this month that the plant would not reopen until independent experts had studied its safety and recommended the plant be restarted.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
