<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>COOKING</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="360287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FLASTE, RICHARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DF1231F933A25755C0A966958260" item-length="1765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>COOKING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD FLASTE; Richard Flaste, the deputy editor of The Book Review, is the co-author of ''Pierre Franey's Low-Calorie Gourmet.''</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FLASTE, RICHARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Suddenly and for no apparent reason, on a recent azalea-brightened late spring day, I started to think about barbecued ribs, spicy-sweet and moist, and was captured by the thought of them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Suddenly and for no apparent reason, on a recent azalea-brightened late spring day, I started to think about barbecued ribs, spicy-sweet and moist, and was captured by the thought of them.</p>
        <p>Suddenly and for no apparent reason, on a recent azalea-brightened late spring day, I started to think about barbecued ribs, spicy-sweet and moist, and was captured by the thought of them.</p>
        <p>Like anyone in the hot grip of an obsession-compulsion - like a serial killer or a crazed lover - I could not get the image out of my mind until I'd done something assertive, something cathartic. Fortunately, the cure in this case is benign: you cook the things slowly and well and then you devour them. But I wasn't going to eat ribs and nothing else (I wasn't that crazy), so I decided to surround them with vibrant Southern dishes. Here's that rib-provoked menu: Missouri ribs Buttermilk biscuits Tidewater coleslaw Honeyed tomatoes Mint julep peaches All those dishes came from this season's cookbooks, which, as a group, show distinct signs of the conservative retrenchment in cooking. The trend hallows regional tastes, the freshest ingredients and traditional techniques that are often pleasingly simple to execute. Servings can be large, and they don't have to be pretty. A warm-weather advantage is that this sort of cooking so often lends itself to outdoor activities: grilling, picnics and parties.</p>
        <p>There is no one true Southern food, since it varies so much from Maryland to Texas, but taken as a whole, Southern cooking is among the most enduring regional fare we have. Stubborn to the point of being oblivious, it relies on fats that are frequently scorned these days, but its earthiness and its bountiful use of seasonal vegetables give it a wholesome feeling, anyway.</p>
        <p>The buttermilk biscuits I made came from Bill Neal's BISCUITS, SPOONBREAD, AND SWEET POTATO PIE (illustrated, 334 pp., Knopf, $19.95), an authoritative journey through the baking and related confectionary cooking of the South. Mr. Neal, the chef at Crook's Corner, an exuberant restaurant in Chapel Hill, N.C., is maturing into one of the most interesting and readable spokesmen for Southern cooking, which he likens more to Mexican than European cuisines.</p>
        <p>Before I got going on those buttermilk biscuits I was led by Mr. Neal toward a deep appreciation of them. In a clear and lively writing style he expounds on the appeal of sour over sweet biscuits and explains the chemistry of why they rise (it's the carbon dioxide that emanates from the combination of cream of tartar and bicarbonate of soda in the commercial baking powder that is a staple of Southern baking). The astonishing thing about biscuits, if you've never made them before, is that they are baked in a matter of just a few minutes, ready long before the kitchen has had a chance to break into its sauna routine.</p>
        <p>Other recipes here are authentic guides to the likes of shortbread, peach pudding and fried mush. An earlier book, ''Bill Neal's Southern Cooking'' (University of North Carolina), revised in 1989, is broader in scope, and the sensible companion to the current volume. (He has also edited a collection of Southern garden writing, ''Through the Garden Gate,'' reviewed on the facing page.) The Missouri ribs in my menu have their provenance partly in Missouri and partly in Cambridge, Mass., where Chris Schlesinger is the proprietor of the East Coast Grill. In a book they've titled THE THRILL OF THE GRILL: Techniques, Recipes, &amp; Down-Home Barbecue (illustrated by Laura Hartman Maestro, photographs by Vincent Lee, 395 pp., Morrow, $24.95), Mr. Schlesinger and John Willoughby offer a wide-ranging, informative and inviting survey of grilling possibilities. Mr. Schlesinger is a professionally trained chef and a wellspring of practical tips. For instance, if you want to grill duck, a bird with enough flammable fat to qualify it as an incendiary device, it should be roasted first to remove most of the fat, and then finished on the grill.</p>
        <p>The book manages to take you the considerable distance from sake-marinated grilled frogs' legs to grilled ham hocks and black-eyed peas. The section on barbecuing (a time-consuming process that is distinct from grilling) is written casually - it's a bit too folksy for me, actually - but it is an intense excursion into traditional approaches. It's all here: the pungent spare ribs of Kansas City as well as the smoky chopped pork of eastern North Carolina, the latter anointed as Mr. Schlesinger's ''personal favorite'' and the ''real original.'' The dish Mr. Schlesinger calls Missouri-style ribs (the ''style'' is there to signal a departure from traditional smoking in favor of more convenient first-stage cooking in the oven) is rubbed with dry spices and then very gently baked at 180 degrees for three hours before it is finished on the grill and doused in a vinegary sauce. The result is crusted on the outside and a miracle of tenderness inside. The Tidewater coleslaw I prepared also came from Mr. Schlesinger. It is a simple, biting mayonnaise-based slaw whose main flavorings are celery seed and vinegar.</p>
        <p>A book that is more narrowly focused than its title might indicate is LEE BAILEY'S SOUTHERN FOOD &amp; PLANTATION HOUSES (photographs by Tom Eckerle, 176 pp., Clarkson N. Potter, $30). What Mr. Bailey, a prolific food writer, did this time is go back to his aunt's home in Natchez, Miss., and - along with the Pilgrimage Garden Club there - create a collection of recipes inspired by that one small region of the South. Some are true to the letter of tradition, others true to no more than the spirit.</p>
        <p>He offers elegant Southern menus, each framed by one of the grand houses of the area: ''Lunch Under the Trees at Edgewood'' is centered on an artful arrangement of shrimp, crawfish and crabmeat that he calls Natchez seafood salad. The photos here are, as they have been in Mr. Bailey's other books, stunning, with an emphasis in this volume that is as much on the mansions as it is on the food. Although he frequently diverges from strict Southern approaches (soy sauce and ginger on the barbecued brisket!), I will always have him to thank for my introduction to those honeyed baked tomatoes, Natchez-style (honey is drizzled over seeded tomato halves, and then they are topped with tarragon and bread crumbs).</p>
        <p>The mint julep peaches - fruit quickly warmed in butter, sugar, bourbon and mint - came from a book with no Southern intentions at all, Betty Fussell's HOME PLATES: A Shopping, Cooking, Eating &amp; Wine Guide for Everyday (illustrated, 224 pp., Dutton, $12.95), which will be available in a few weeks. In the past, Ms. Fussell has often demonstrated her scholarly appreciation of American regional cuisine. Here she offers up an idiosyncratic small book of efficiently written recipes that are meant to be lively but not exhausting. Ms. Fussell likes variations on a theme. So you get a recipe for beef strips cooked quickly with a Chinese-style star anise sauce, and then she urges you to use the same cut of beef with a Mexican sauce or a green sauce or brandied butter with peppercorns. It's all very simple, and playful, too.</p>
        <p>As I continued to read and cook from the summer books, that simplicity of execution and playfulness kept popping up as themes. One of the happiest of the current books is THE YACHTING COOKBOOK: Glorious Menus and Quick Dishes Afloat and at Home by Elizabeth Wheeler and Jennifer Trainer (photographs by Kristen Brochmann, 160 pp., Crown, $30). No one actually needs a yacht to cook the dishes in this book. Cooking on boats forced these authors to use space and ingredients economically, and that sense of discipline is, of course, useful in small urban kitchens as well as mountaintop campsites. An offering that seems to please them especially - they testify that their ''friends are crazy about this dish'' - is a grilled butterflied leg of lamb with a mustard vinaigrette.</p>
        <p>Although a boned leg of lamb is awkward to maneuver on a grill, everything else in the preparation and cooking is usually a snap, and the finished dish is almost always impressive no matter whose recipe you're following. This one calls for a heavy mustard marinade and then a thick mustard sauce (accented with mint). It's pungent, wholly successful, and it gave me the confidence to keep working my way through the book and its other, often splendid, straightforward recipes. The recipes are couched in menus that emphasize fruit and fresh vegetables and often minimize the cooking. For instance, there's the ''cozy cabin dinner'' with its chili, corn bread, green salad, sliced tomatoes and banana crisp.</p>
        <p>Mark Charles Miller's COYOTE CAFE: Foods From the Great Southwest (illustrated, 192 pp., Ten Speed Press, $24.95) arrived on bookshelves earlier than some of the other books, but it looks as if it were meant for summer all along. On nearly every page, brilliantly colored illustrations evoke the American desert, its people, wildlife and vegetation. Mr. Miller owns the Coyote Cafe in Santa Fe, N.M. He appears to be an extraordinarily skilled chef, and he writes well. The food he offers here is Southwestern, which is to say it is strongly influenced by the lusty peasant cooking of Mexico: refried beans, chicken tamales and the like. But since Mr. Miller has evidently scaled the heights of cuisine, there's a lot of elegance here as well: lobster and scallops with vanilla in corn husks or confit of duck tamale begins to show some of his creativity at work. One of the most popular dishes at his restaurant is a lot simpler, a fried steak with red chili onion rings, and a recipe for that is included, too.</p>
        <p>A book that's bound to be welcomed by many cooks this summer is THE LOAVES AND FISHES PARTY COOKBOOK by Anna Pump and Sybille Pump with Gen LeRoy (illustrated by Melanie Parks, 238 pp., Harper &amp; Row, $19.95). It's organized around the seasons, and the section on summer parties includes recipe suggestions and menus for occasions ranging from a brunch for six to a wedding reception for 40. The dishes are often intended for early preparation, like the chilled veal rolls, filled with a mixture of veal, bacon, mushrooms and onion, or a lemon-basil chicken salad. The aim is to help you plan an event so well that when the guests arrive ''you should be free to be outside with them,'' soaking up as much good weather as everyone else.</p>
        <p>The book is written with the kind of enthusiasm that often degenerates into treacle in recipe books, but in this case it escapes that pitfall and is cheerfully reassuring instead. Maybe too reassuring. That wedding reception for 40 calls for serving a shrimp salad that begins with 10 pounds of shrimp, poached and shelled. Now, let's see. That's about 300 shrimp to shell. Better get help.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
