<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rising Iron Curtain Exposes Haunting Veil of Polluted Air</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="341721"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="UPHEAVAL IN THE EAST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DB1F39F93BA35757C0A966958260" item-length="1637" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rising Iron Curtain Exposes Haunting Veil of Polluted Air</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>KATOWICE, Poland</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In the depths of a salt mine in Poland, men, women and children lie in bed, bundled in coats and tugging at heavy blankets. In an upside-down world, they have come to this underground clinic to breathe clean and healing air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In the depths of a salt mine in Poland, men, women and children lie in bed, bundled in coats and tugging at heavy blankets. In an upside-down world, they have come to this underground clinic to breathe clean and healing air.</p>
        <p>In the depths of a salt mine in Poland, men, women and children lie in bed, bundled in coats and tugging at heavy blankets. In an upside-down world, they have come to this underground clinic to breathe clean and healing air.</p>
        <p>Above ground, in more conventional clinics, doctors using portable inhalators administer moist and purified air to children. ''Whenever the smog is heavy, the wards fill up,'' said Dr. Henryk Kowalski, a laryngologist at a regional children's hospital.</p>
        <p>Clean air has become a luxury here and in the industrial zones of Central Europe, where poisonous gases and toxic dust roam freely. As the secrets of the Eastern bloc's formerly Communist nations become known, this one may be the saddest. In the years when Soviet-bloc rulers claimed that they were forming ''a new socialist man,'' they were in many instances condemning this man and his family to severe lung and heart disease, cancer, eye and skin ailments and, often, sickly children and shorter lives.</p>
        <p>Avoiding the Truth</p>
        <p>In much of Eastern Europe, comprehensive health surveys are not yet available because Communist Governments hid or ignored many of the medical statistics.</p>
        <p>But from East Germany to Bulgaria, physicians, biologists and other health specialists are now eager to talk. And visiting experts from the United States and Western Europe have said that Central Europe's pollution is more dangerous and widespread than anything they have seen in the Western industrial nations, and that it occurs on a far greater scale than in the developing world, which does not have nearly as much industry.</p>
        <p>Health specialists throughout the region said that diseases traceable to a poisoned environment were consuming a large portion of public health budgets and boding ill for future generations. Similar problems from pollution affect many parts of the Soviet Union as well.</p>
        <p>A study of new mothers in the industrial region of Katowice and Cracow in southern Poland showed concentrations of lead, mercury, cadmium and other toxic metals in the placenta of every woman. The study's author, Dr. Josef Niwelinski of the University of Cracow, said more than half of the 1,000 placentas examined were deformed or damaged, ''most likely by the high level of carbon monoxide and sulfur dioxide in the air.''</p>
        <p>The findings were all the more worrisome, he said, because ''we studied only the most healthy mothers with normal births.''</p>
        <p>Another group of doctors is studying why in this region so many babies are born prematurely or die in the womb. Its preliminary conclusions are that at least 50 percent of the cases are caused by chemical changes in the mother's blood that leave the child short of oxygen.</p>
        <p>New Technology Ignored</p>
        <p>In the former East bloc nations as well as in the Soviet Union, the quality of air, water and food has deteriorated sharply over the past two decades as heavy industries and vehicles multiplied. To Western experts, the polluting practices seem all the more ruthless because they increased at a time when their dire consequences were already widely known.</p>
        <p>Experts said the technology to control pollution from antiquated installations was well known and in some Eastern European countries was even produced for export. Yet there are only minimal controls on much of Eastern Europe's industrial emissions, or none at all.</p>
        <p>Poland's pollution is widely described as the worst. The Polish Academy of Science said a third of the nation's 38 million people live in ''areas of ecological disaster.'' It said conditions were most hazardous in the coal and steel belt of Cracow and Silesia.</p>
        <p>A Hospital Bears Testimony</p>
        <p>The Chorzow hospital in the sprawling industrial zone around Katowice, an area of extravagant pollution with more than 1.5 million inhabitants. seems to bear witness to the degradation.</p>
        <p>Almost across the street from the hospital is a vast steel mill that has left the air dry and scorching. It forms a hellish circle with a power station and a chemical plant. The sting and smog from the plants were unmistakable inside the hospital wards.</p>
        <p>Three members of the hospital board, eager to share their grievances with a visitor, cited a litany of ills. They said that there had been a sharp rise in cancer, heart disease and emphysema and that too many men were dying in their 30's and 40's. While general statistics for adults were scarce, the board said it was widely accepted that the life expectancy for adults in this region was four years less than the average for adults in the rest of the nation. They said public health was degenerating to a level of the postwar years.</p>
        <p>''We have been telling the authorities about this for 20 years,'' said Dr. Jan Kern, director of health services. ''They always told us they were doing research, that they were putting in new technology. But they cannot fool us. We get the patients.''</p>
        <p>Babies With a Bad Start</p>
        <p>If the environment is harsh for adults, it is harder on the children. Dr. Bozena Cichos, a pediatrician in the children's hospital at Chorzow, said that in her nine years here she had seen a sharp rise in chronic bronchitis, asthma, pneumonia, meningitis and rickets. Underweight babies are becoming common, she said, and pregnancies of just 36 weeks - three or four weeks shortened - ''are so normal now we don't even consider them short.''</p>
        <p>''Quite a few of these babies keep coming back,'' she said.</p>
        <p>A new study in the Katowice area said 21 percent of the children up to 4 years old are sick almost constantly, while 41 percent of the children under 6 have health problems, including hearing or seeing disabilities, anemia and low weight and height.</p>
        <p>Some health experts in Eastern Europe say that as the environmental disaster is debated, there is a tendency to attribute all illness to pollution. They note that many adults and children eat unhealthfully, with high-fat or unbalanced diets, and that heavy smoking is common. But even those habits are aggravated by smog, said Dr. Marion Glowacz, an internist.</p>
        <p>Soil Unfit for Planting</p>
        <p>While levels of pollution in Eastern Europe vary according to the type of industry, it is clear that wind and water spread the hazardous substances over large areas and that sulfur from coal burning affects the breathing of millions of people. Unsafe levels of heavy metals in drinking water and on land used for agriculture are widespread. In Silesia, the Polish authorities have banned the growing of vegetables in the widely contaminated soil.</p>
        <p>The Czechoslovak Academy of Sciences recently disclosed that 50 percent of the country's drinking water does not meet even its outdated, lenient norms. In Prague, a city plagued by smog, many people complained of permanent headaches, asthma, nausea and intestinal trouble. And in northern Bohemia, home to many power plants and chemical works, officials said infant mortality was 12 percent higher than in the rest of the country; they said schoolchildren had to be sent to the mountains with their teachers at least one month a year.</p>
        <p>''Fifteen years ago we knew our forests were dying, the children were losing immunity and water stopped being drinkable,'' said Pavel Seifer, a spokesman for the Czechoslovak Green Party. ''But there was a party directive that the media should avoid information about the environment.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Seifer, who at the time was a journalist, added: ''We were told we have to fight the efforts of the West. They want to bring us to our knees through ecology.''</p>
        <p>The Risk of Speaking Out</p>
        <p>Several physicians in Hungary and Bulgaria said that warning of the degenerative effects of industry on people's health was frowned upon, perceived as an attack on the system. When Dr. Nikolai Ivanov complained two years ago about a copper plant in Shrednogorie, Bulgaria, that was causing arsenic and lead poisoning among his patients, he was publicly criticized by the local Communist Party leader.</p>
        <p>Although health officials in East Germany are still reluctant to respond to questions about public health, new unofficial reports indicate that in the industrial cities of Leipzig, Halle, Dresden and Karl-Marx-Stadt, rates of deaths caused by cancer and lung and heart diseases were 15 to 25 percent higher than in Berlin.</p>
        <p>Even in the mountain towns of northern Czechoslovakia and southern Poland, long famous for their spas, smog has set in and acid rain has killed large stretches of forest.</p>
        <p>Dr. Teresa Sregorczyk, a lung specialist in a sanitarium in Karpacz in southern Poland, said that her clinic was still operating effectively but that smog was hampering treatment in the sanitariums of the Jelenia Gora valley nearby. She said she often wonders what will happen to her little patients - 220 children at the moment - who already need prolonged treatment for asthma, bronchitis and tuberculosis. ''Most have been exposed to terrible pollution,'' she said. ''I know we are, too, but at least we developed our vital organs under more healthy conditions.''</p>
        <p>The Underground Treatment</p>
        <p>Curing was less orthodox in a nearby uranium mine where about 500 adults were descending for regular breathing sessions. On a recent morning in the salt mine at Wieliczka, near Cracow, adults and children were resting in the dim light, surrounded by gray salt rock. The air 650 feet below the surface felt chilly but moist and exhilarating. Dr. Isabela Wroblewska pronounced it ''as good for you as sitting in a strong sea breeze.''</p>
        <p>Stanislaw Pasierbeck, a factory worker from Zywiec who said his asthma attacks became unbearable five years ago at age 49, seemed accustomed to the alien world as he slipped off his blankets, fixed his miner's lamp and walked toward the nurse's station. ''This is very good air,'' he said. ''It is the only place where I can breathe deeply.''</p>
        <p>PLEASE DO NOT LOSE KICKER  UPHEAVAL IN THE EAST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
