<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Millions Join Battle for a Beloved Planet</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="346420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONCERTS AND RECITALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH DAY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCFADDEN, ROBERT D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DB1330F930A15757C0A966958260" item-length="1916" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Millions Join Battle for a Beloved Planet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. McFADDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCFADDEN, ROBERT D</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Two decades after the birth of the modern environmental movement, millions of people around the nation and the world renewed the call to arms for an endangered planet yesterday with an exuberant and bittersweet celebration of Earth Day 1990.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Two decades after the birth of the modern environmental movement, millions of people around the nation and the world renewed the call to arms for an endangered planet yesterday with an exuberant and bittersweet celebration of Earth Day 1990.</p>
        <p>Two decades after the birth of the modern environmental movement, millions of people around the nation and the world renewed the call to arms for an endangered planet yesterday with an exuberant and bittersweet celebration of Earth Day 1990.</p>
        <p>It was not quite The Day the Earth Stood Still, as an avalanche of publicity in recent weeks had prophesied, but by day's end organizers of the sequel to Earth Day 1970 said 200 million people in 140 nations had taken part in the largest grass-roots demonstration in history.</p>
        <p>And a vast patchwork quilt of marches, rallies, concerts, festivals, street fairs and other events in 3,600 communities in the United States, Europe, Asia, Africa and North and South America seemed to bear them out.</p>
        <p>''It's like earth's birthday,'' said Gordon Vestnys, a 25-year-old roofer, strolling at a fair overlooking San Francisco Bay and the Golden Gate Bridge. ''It's a gathering of people becoming more aware - and hopefully continuing after today with more consciousness and less Styrofoam.''</p>
        <p>From Italy to Nepal</p>
        <p>Diverse, contradictory, extravagant: the bewildering global panoply of happenings included a trash-picking trek up Mount Everest in Nepal, a 500-mile human chain across France, a gathering of space travelers at the United Nations, an ''eco-fair'' on a landfill island in Japan and a roadway ''lie-down'' by 5,000 people to protest car fumes in Italy.</p>
        <p>In New York, Los Angeles, Chicago, San Francisco, Atlanta and cities and towns across this country there were tree-plantings, litter sweeps, recycling exhibits, workshops on wildlife and endangered species, fairs and a sunrise-to-sunset clamor for environmental morality that often mimicked the hoopla of a political campaign.</p>
        <p>President Bush went fishing in the Florida Keys and used a telephone hookup to address thousands at an Earth Day rally on the Columbia River near George, Wash. Members of Congress, governors, mayors and hosts of other officials got on the bandwagon.</p>
        <p>But it was not a day for politicans or corporations, though many of them embraced the common good with solemn pronouncements upon polluted air and oceans, fouled rivers and beaches, the perils of acid rain and tropical deforestation, toxic wastes and mountains of garbage.</p>
        <p>Rather, it was a day for ordinary people and the meanings they chose to give it, a day to turn away from the memories of cold war and a hard focus on economic growth, to gather in vast throngs or quiet settings and express something about themselves and their world.</p>
        <p>'Start Saving the Earth'</p>
        <p>''It's really necessary to start saving the earth,'' said Kathy Bernstein, 60, at a festival in Chicago's Lincoln Park. ''I've got grandchildren, and it's necessary to imbue in them that you have to save things, not just be users.''</p>
        <p>At a fair in the Playa Del Rey district of Los Angeles, Leslea Meyerhoff, 22, explained: ''I'm here because I think an individual can make a difference if they are aware of recycling and conservation. One way to let people know of the environmental crisis is through activties like this that promote public awareness.''</p>
        <p>For some, like Philip C. Martinez, a drum-maker from the Taos Pueblo Indian Reservation in New Mexico, the urgency was greater. ''We're here to save our land,'' he said at a rally in Washington, D.C. ''They're trying to put both an airport and a nuclear waste dump near our reservation. Ten years ago, if we had said anything about it, nobody would have listened. Today, people care.''</p>
        <p>The Weather Seemed to Approve</p>
        <p>And in London, Andrew Lees of the British branch of Friends of the Earth said, ''If Earth Day does nothing else, it will give the clear message to politicians that millions of people are aware of the problems facing the earth and what needs to be done about it.''</p>
        <p>It was a balmy spring day in most of the United States. The sun arched over the continent in a sky that was pristine blue in the east and resembled a summer sea flecked with whitecaps in much of the rest of the country. Not everyone, however, turned out because of the day's gentle beauty or a commitment to the environment.</p>
        <p>''I'm here to see Bob Weir - I'll admit it,'' said Matt Herren, 18, at a blustery, rainy San Francisco Earth Day concert featuring the Grateful Dead star. And across the nation in Times Square, scene of an observance early yesterday, Jeffrey Aym, 21, of Morristown, N.J., acknowledged: ''We're here because we missed Woodstock,'' the peace movement's 1969 rock-and-drugs festival.</p>
        <p>But most people said they had come out because they believed their presence would make a difference, and the turnouts in many communities appeared to underscore a new political commitment to the environment by Americans, one coinciding with the fading era of confrontation with Communism.</p>
        <p>Evocations of the 1960's</p>
        <p>Some said the environmental movement had more support than any since the antiwar and civil rights protests of the 1960's.</p>
        <p>And, indeed, scenes reminiscent of the 1960's were abundant across the country. In New York, a huge throng -the police said 750,000, but it was like counting jelly beans in a jar - heard a concert in Central Park. In Washington, 125,000 people crowded onto the sun-drenched Capitol Mall: students in tie-dyed T-shirts and young professionals, older people who remembered the marches of a generation ago. Music and Frisbees floated up, and kites rode the breeze.</p>
        <p>Many across the land felt no need to attend spectacular events. They stayed home or met in small groups to plant flowers or saplings, clean up roadsides and vacant lots or just talk about their neighorhoods or why the loss of the ozone layer or the destruction of the Brazilian rain forests were important.</p>
        <p>It was possible for some, away from the crowds and the noise, to observe scenes of decorous beauty and be aware of the hidden pollution: sunlight shimmering like gold coins on a Connecticut lake choked with algae; vegetables banked at a stand in New York, an artist's palette of oranges, grapes and bright red tomatoes coated with pesticides; and the Hudson River, tainted with PCB's, flowing in stately procession like a doomed blue regiment moving South.</p>
        <p>Such awareness was the essential point of the day, its organizers said. ''It is incumbent upon each of us to make environmentally sound choices throughout our daily lives,'' said Denis Hayes, the 45-year-old chairman of Earth Day 1990 and an organizer of the first celebration 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>The Creation of a Coalition</p>
        <p>''If we consider the environmental consequences of our purchases, our options in transportation, our investments, and our votes, we can send a powerful message to our public policymakers and our business leaders to do the same.''</p>
        <p>Two years in the planning, Earth Day 1990 was orchestrated by a coalition of organizations - Greenpeace, the National Resources Defense Council, the Rainbow Coalition, the National Education Association, the Sierra Club, Planned Parenthood and many others - to evoke the idealism of Earth Day 1970, which launched the modern environmental movement.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, there was a widespread sense that this Earth Day had been sold to the American people with the same techniques employed by peddlers of soap and patriotism, but many also said that that was not a bad thing, given the urgency of the environmental cause.</p>
        <p>''It feels mass-marketed,'' said Armando Martis, a Brooklyn dancer who was headed for Earth Day events in midtown Manhattan. ''But that's good because it gets the message out to a lot of people.''</p>
        <p>Nearby, Rita Robbins said:''I don't think this is too commercial, although about 12 people have tried to sell me buttons - none of them biodegradable.''</p>
        <p>''It's a lot of hype, but for a good thing,'' said Donald Braler, a 30-year-old New York film technician.</p>
        <p>'Really Fast Start' Is Seen</p>
        <p>There were other grumblings about companies with poor-to-disastrous pollution records that for weeks had run Earth Day advertisements expressing concern for the ecology, all without the blessing of Earth Day organizers, who said corporate America had wrapped itself in a green flag.</p>
        <p>About 2,000 people were at the Washington Monument for Earthfest '90, an event sponsored by the Federal Environmental Protection Agency. John Denver sang a song he had written for the event, ''The Flower That Shattered the Stone,'' and the E.P.A. Administrator, William K. Reilly, gave a speech about the meaning of Earth Day.</p>
        <p>Afterward, he told reporters: ''It seems to me that the President has made a really fast start on the environment. I can't think of any 15-month period that produced as much by way of environemental initiatives, decisions and participation by a President.'' Later, he sat alone backstage, sipping a soda as the reporters streamed past him in pursuit of the actor Tom Cruise.</p>
        <p>The Tribute in New York</p>
        <p>In Central Park, a celebrity-studded concert entertained the crowd in the afternoon, and speakers included Gov. Mario M. Cuomo, Mayor David N. Dinkins, the union activist Caesar Chavez and others who talked of ecological responsibility.</p>
        <p>But there were other settings in the park, less noticed, that gave meaning to the day: contrasts of young and old, of death and renewal - last year's faded grass beside a blaze of yellow daffodils; old people on benches, faces upturned to a warming sun, dreaming of long ago, and out on the lake, far from the exhausts of automobiles, a young boatman upright on the prow, floating like an ancient Chinese dragon.</p>
        <p>On the Avenue of the Americas, huge throngs of people, at times all but immobilized by their own numbers, sampled a potpourri of arts and crafts, t-shirts and food, blaring rock music and exortations of environmental responsibility.</p>
        <p>Much of it had the flavor of a 1960's antiwar festival: amid books on yoga and meditation were booths draped with hand-made jewelry, yogis orange-robed and cross-legged, people strolling hand-in-hand and vendors of vegetarian cuisine like mango nectar and ''Southern fried cauliflower.''</p>
        <p>Recycling by the Homeless</p>
        <p>The avenue was in shade most of the day between walls of soaring skyscrapers that symbolized corporate America - Exxon, the New York Hilton, CBS, Rockefeller Center, Paine Webber, Manufacturers Hanover Trust. The buildings were closed and the avenue, normally choked with vehicles, teemed with life. A stand sold biodegradable bags, recycled denim rugs and bumper stickers and signs that proclaimed: ''Acid Rain Is a Bad Trip,'' ''No Cholesterol'' and ''High Fiber.''</p>
        <p>There were oases of beauty: baskets of pink petunias, red fuchsias, orange and purple impatiens, white peace lilies and banks of begonias, geraniums and renunculus. Nearby, a booth sold lovely bonsai: miniature windblown Japanese elms and junipers.</p>
        <p>But it was big trees that preoccupied a man on a bandstand. ''Every ton of recycled paper will save 17 trees that give off precious oxygen for our planet,'' he said. He spoke, too, of recycling, but only a few people were actually doing it, as they do every day - the homeless, picking their way through the crowd, collecting cans and bottles.</p>
        <p>Despite the vast numbers of people and events, there was something strangely serene about Earth Day. It hearkened back to the measured values of another age, when Americans raised a barn in an afternoon and took walks of an evening or gathered around a radio in a crisis to listen, not just to what they wanted to hear, but to a familiar voice talking sense.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
