<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cuomo's Green Period</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="379585"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="THE REGION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFERENDUMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUOMO, MARIO M (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SACK, KEVIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DD1F3FF935A1575BC0A966958260" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cuomo's Green Period</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SACK, KEVIN</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Gov. Mario M. Cuomo has been campaigning vigorously across the state. He has political advertisements on the radio. He has spent $300,000 on television commercials, just in August. ''The choice is very clear,'' he says solemnly, staring into the lens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Gov. Mario M. Cuomo has been campaigning vigorously across the state. He has political advertisements on the radio. He has spent $300,000 on television commercials, just in August. ''The choice is very clear,'' he says solemnly, staring into the lens.</p>
        <p>Gov. Mario M. Cuomo has been campaigning vigorously across the state. He has political advertisements on the radio. He has spent $300,000 on television commercials, just in August. ''The choice is very clear,'' he says solemnly, staring into the lens.</p>
        <p>The choice Mr. Cuomo refers to is not the one between him and Pierre A. Rinfret, the Republican candidate in the Nov. 6 gubernatorial election. It is whether to approve a referendum on the 21st Century Environmental Quality Bond Act, a $1.975 billion measure that Mr. Cuomo contends will ''help make New York's future clean and green.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo has campaigned aggressively for bond issues before, but rarely this early before Election Day. While no one questions Mr. Cuomo's sincerity in promoting the bond act, his political opponents believe the timing of his advertising blitz has as much to do with his own political condition as it does with the bond issue.</p>
        <p>As a political issue, the environment is hot. As a political candidate, Mr. Cuomo is not, or at least not as sizzling as in past years. As the bond act's most visible spokesman, the Governor can expect to reap the benefits that accrue to politicians who wrap themselves in popular issues.</p>
        <p>''I certainly hope so,'' Mr. Cuomo said in an interview. ''Adlai Stevenson said it: the best politics is good government.''</p>
        <p>Environmentalists see the tactic somewhat differently. ''He's trying to attach himself to environmental protection, which is an area that people are very concerned about and an area where he has been weak,'' said Larry Shapiro of the New York Public Interest Research Group.</p>
        <p>The Politics of Planting Trees</p>
        <p>Mr. Shapiro and other environmental advocates commend Mr. Cuomo for helping to close the Shoreham nuclear plant, for proposing legislation to reduce acid rain and for backing a $1.45 billion environmental bond act in 1986. But they criticize his administration for permitting the licensing of garbage incinerators, for being slow to finance toxic-waste cleanups and for not declaring a moratorium on development in the Adirondacks, as recommended by a gubernatorial commission.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Cuomo runs for his third four-year term, numerous private opinion polls indicate that his approval ratings have dropped. He faces the inevitable antagonism aimed at an incumbent who has been in office for eight years. The state's economy is sliding perilously close to recession. And this year's excruciating budget negotiations ended with the passage of a record $1.4 billion in new taxes.</p>
        <p>The Governor is expected to have little trouble disposing of Mr. Rinfret, a largely unknown candidate who has disappointed even the leaders of his own party. But the strength of Mr. Cuomo's showing in November is important to his political future, both to his ability to govern New York and to his status as a potential Presidential candidate in 1992.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo has done little to suggest he is planning a race for the White House. But should he run, it would not hurt him to be able to boast of ushering in a bond issue that would dedicate a record amount of money to land acquisition, solid waste management and water quality improvement, among other purposes.</p>
        <p>Since mid-June, Mr. Cuomo has made appearances on the measure's behalf in 19 cities, most of them in upstate New York where support for bond issues has usually been weakest.</p>
        <p>At 10 of the events he has planted sugar maple saplings, the state tree.</p>
        <p>The Governor also has spent his own campaign funds on the television commercial, which features pictures of billowing smokestacks, slimy seas and overflowing landfills.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo has declined to use any of his nearly $8 million war chest to help Democratic candidates for the State Senate, saying the funds were not contributed to him for that purpose. His aides said that principle does not apply to spending the money for the bond act commercials because Mr. Cuomo may benefit politically from the ads and because the bond act is crucial to his agenda.</p>
        <p>Republicans maintain that the Governor is trying to divert attention from more damaging issues.</p>
        <p>''If you had his record on taxes, spending and crime you would want to plant trees too,'' said Assemblyman John A. Faso, Mr. Rinfret's campaign manager.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo said he deliberately started the advertising campaign for the bond act early to give voters time to understand its import and to separate it from the noisy clutter of the fall campaign.</p>
        <p>He said he also was motivated by fears that the state's financial problems could influence people to vote against the bond act. In the next fiscal year, the bond act would add an estimated $28 million to the state's debt-service payments, a figure that would escalate to $201 million 10 years from now before gradually decreasing.</p>
        <p>''Some people, I believe mistakenly, regard the difficulty of these times fiscally and economically as being the reason to vote against the bond issue,'' Mr. Cuomo said. ''I see it as a good reason to vote for the bond issue. Making that case takes an awful lot of argumentation and discussion.''  THE REGION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
