<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Sense of Discovery in Landscapes</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="355044"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART SHOWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BRISTOL-MYERS SQUIBB CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAYNOR, VIVIEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D7143FF933A15756C0A966958260" item-length="901" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Sense of Discovery in Landscapes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIEN RAYNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAYNOR, VIVIEN</byline>
      <dateline>LAWRENCEVILLE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: WHAT was previously the Squibb Gallery has become the Gallery at Bristol-Myers Squibb. Titles must expand along with capitalism, it seems. Still, there is much to be grateful for: this could have been the Gallery at Bristol-Myers Beech-Nut Life Savers Squibb if the pharmaceutical company had not sold its gum and candy interests, in 1981.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: WHAT was previously the Squibb Gallery has become the Gallery at Bristol-Myers Squibb. Titles must expand along with capitalism, it seems. Still, there is much to be grateful for: this could have been the Gallery at Bristol-Myers Beech-Nut Life Savers Squibb if the pharmaceutical company had not sold its gum and candy interests, in 1981.</p>
        <p>WHAT was previously the Squibb Gallery has become the Gallery at Bristol-Myers Squibb. Titles must expand along with capitalism, it seems. Still, there is much to be grateful for: this could have been the Gallery at Bristol-Myers Beech-Nut Life Savers Squibb if the pharmaceutical company had not sold its gum and candy interests, in 1981.</p>
        <p>Thereby hangs the story behind ''From Homer to Hopper,'' the show that now hangs in the company's headquarters, which are three miles south of Princeton on Route 206. As told in the catalogue by the gallery's director, Pamela Sherin, this begins in Canajoharie, between Schenectady and Utica, N.Y. There, in the library, is the collection that was presented in 1926 by Bartlett Arkell, who was president of the Beech-Nut Packing Company, the village's principal employer, and his collection has been in the care of Edward Lipowicz for the last 33 years.</p>
        <p>Enter Edward Shineman Jr., a Beech-Nut executive born and raised in Canajoharie. Despite the corporate divorce, Mr. Shineman has maintained his connection with Squibb, and it was he who alerted Ms. Sherin to the collection and suggested it visit the Princeton area while the Canajoharie library-art gallery was undergoing renovation.</p>
        <p>There's nothing quite like stumbling on a well-stocked museum in an out-of-the-way place, and these 40 or so pictures, mostly landscapes, culled from a total of 200, convey the sense of discovery, hanging here in their gilt frames against the gallery's chocolate-colored walls. Introducing the show, Ronny Cohen, an art historian, makes much of the American search for truth and beauty (in upper as well as lower case). It is as if Keats had never existed, much less the painters of the Romantic Movement. Either that or their act needed cleaning up by these seemingly wholesome homespun Americans, most of whom studied in Europe and at least two of whom - the dandies Whistler and Sargent - spent their working lives there.</p>
        <p>George Inness is cited not only for admiring Corot but also for recognizing the profusion of detail that supposedly weakens many of the French master's efforts. Interestingly enough, it is detail that weakens the Inness in the show, a landscape under a rainbow that is busy with notes of white - on the faces of the cattle in the foreground, on the shirts of the haymakers behind and on the buildings in the distance.</p>
        <p>Sargent is praised as ''a sharp-eyed American artist,'' and Homer is by implication commended for pugnaciously insisting that, having selected his subject carefully, he painted it ''exactly as it appears.'' Well, this is not the first time that the national output has been regarded as an advertisement for democracy and, given the present populist climate - the art world equivalent of global warming -it won't be the last.</p>
        <p>The earliest work is ''Cooper Family Group,'' an anonymous circa 1825 canvas crammed with everything pertaining to self-made success. There is the father sporting splendid haberdashery; the mother in an off-the-shoulder gown; and the child, whose hair seems to have been curled for the occasion. Behind, red curtains frame a vista of white mountains, and in front is the engaging touch of the family dog poking his snout into the child's hand. The picture may well be ''truth in the American sense,'' but it is noticeable primarily for the disconcerting way the three subjects are staring in wildly different directions.</p>
        <p>As often happens in anthologies, portraits by Eakins and Sargent are juxtaposed and because Sargent is still widely regarded as a flashy performer, he suffers from the comparison. Even so, his head of a pretty young Italian woman manages to make Eakins seem officiously naturalistic with his study of the old, homely Mrs. Stokes, whose pince-nez hang on a cord around her neck. These painters are cat and dog and should be kept apart from each other.</p>
        <p>Homer is represented by illustrative watercolors, mostly scenes of fishing boats and children playing on rocky beaches. The best is an almost monochromatic view of a couple - she holding a fan, he a cane - sitting on the beach, dark silhouettes against a sea silvered by the moon. Hopper is represented meagerly by a watercolor - one of his more wooden efforts involving a dinghy pulled up on the beach behind a freight yard.</p>
        <p>The artists in between run from Albert Bierstadt with a relatively modest view of El Capitan, in Yosemite, to Grandma Moses, with one of her later, more greeting-card style scenes. Another cross section might be from Whistler to Albert Pinkham Ryder, the first represented by a tiny sunset over the Thames, the second by one of his more depressed-looking landscapes.</p>
        <p>Childe Hassam looks good in his summery view of Provincetown. Standing in the right place, the viewer can align the white sailboats in this scene with the chubby clouds in John Kane's ''Aspinwall.'' One of the naive painter's best efforts, this bird's-eye view of the Pennsylvania town features a paddle wheeler churning along the river, railroad yards, factories and, in the distance, a quilt of green fields.</p>
        <p>On view through June 3, the show purports to offer a new look at familiar artists but in actuality confirms consensuses already achieved. But this in itself is a very pleasant experience. The gallery is open Monday through Friday from 9 A.M. to 5 P.M., Thursday until 9 P.M. and Saturday and Sunday from 1 to 5 P.M.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
