<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TALKING: Solar Energy;   Systems Making a Comeback</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="350985"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOLAR ENERGY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKS, ANDREE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDE1530F935A35756C0A966958260" item-length="1101" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TALKING: Solar Energy;   Systems Making a Comeback</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREE BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKS, ANDREE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: REMEMBER the late 70's, when designs for solar systems like rooftop collectors, greenhouses and heat pumps were pouring off the drawing boards as fast as fuel prices rose? Fuel shortages were predicted and tax credits for renewable-energy installations tempted homeowners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: REMEMBER the late 70's, when designs for solar systems like rooftop collectors, greenhouses and heat pumps were pouring off the drawing boards as fast as fuel prices rose? Fuel shortages were predicted and tax credits for renewable-energy installations tempted homeowners.</p>
        <p>REMEMBER the late 70's, when designs for solar systems like rooftop collectors, greenhouses and heat pumps were pouring off the drawing boards as fast as fuel prices rose? Fuel shortages were predicted and tax credits for renewable-energy installations tempted homeowners.</p>
        <p>Then, as fuel prices started to fall, the Reagan Administration ended special tax credits and stories began to emerge of systems not fulfilling their glowing promises and of manufacturers and contractors who vanished.</p>
        <p>Now solar energy appears headed for a comeback. Concern about finite resources, polluted air and global warming, and talk of a new surge in fuel prices, have encouraged homeowners to give solar another chance. ''Many more people are beginning to request information again,'' said Catherine Dimatto, director of the Northeast Solar Energy Association in Greenfield, Mass.</p>
        <p>The remaining contractors tend to be more responsible and knowledgeable. They also use more advanced technologies, said Michael Brower, energy analyst with the Union of Concerned Scientists, a conservation group in Cambridge, Mass. ''The quality of the equipment as well as the design is now much higher,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Consider Thermomax USA, a St. Paul, Minn., maker of solar equipment for heating water and for heating and cooling space. It did most of its business overseas until a year or so ago, when domestic demand started picking up again, said Al Throckmorton, the president. The company, he noted, signed a contract in March to begin providing Sears, Roebuck with solar hot water systems on a trial basis through Florida stores.</p>
        <p>Builders say people ask most about solar options when renovation or new construction is being planned. ''Once you get going, it's free,'' said Robert Arndt, owner of a 15-unit apartment bulding in Brideport, Conn., who is looking into solar energy to lower his water-heating costs. Demand is also coming from those who already own or have bought a home with a defunct solar system.</p>
        <p>Some are encouraged when they learn that tax benefits and grants are still available. Others turn to solar when their fuel bills grow intolerable, as happened to Rick and Karen Kline before they installed a solar hot water system in their all-electric, four-bedroom, 3,000-square-foot home in Hamilton Township, N.J., two years ago. The system, window quilts and a wood stove have cut their electricity bills by about 40 percent, Mr. Kline said.</p>
        <p>Anyone needing to rehabilitate, update or install a system should read up on improvements in solar technology. One source is the ''Assessment of Solar Energy Technologies,'' a 56-page report published in 1989 by the American Solar Energy Society (send $20 to: ASEA, 2400 Central Avenue, Boulder, Colo. 80301).</p>
        <p>There is also the Directory of the United States Solar Thermal Industry, a 36-page book that describes technologies now available, published by the Solar Energy Industries Association. (Send $14.50 to SEIA, Suite 610, 1730 North Lynn Street, Arlington, Va. 22209).</p>
        <p>This association also offers, for $25.50, the Directory of SRCC Certified Solar Collector and Systems Ratings, which classifies manufacturers of solar collectors according to the product's BTU output and other criteria. A catalogue of all its publications is available free. The association (phone 703-524-6100) is also one of the few remaining referral sources for local contractors and installers, including those that rehabilitate or update ''orphan systems'' - the industry expression for systems made or installed by companies no longer in business.</p>
        <p>AMONG items to look for are greenhouse windows that offer better insulation and deflecting properties to mute the summer sun, solar heat-exchange water tanks designed to last considerably longer than the five to seven years of the early models, collectors that operate with greater efficiency in overcast skies, collector mounts less likely to damage roof membranes and a cheaper water-heating alternative called a thermo-syphon, designed for use in Southern states.</p>
        <p>This system, widely in use in Israel, comprises a water tank mounted above the collectors - rather than in the basement - to provide a natural-gravity flow of water.</p>
        <p>''We now know a whole lot more about what we need to do,'' said Everett Barber Jr., president of Sunsearch, a solar contractor in Guilford, Conn. Mr. Barber is also an associate professor of environmental technologies at the Yale School of Architecture.</p>
        <p>The most reliable solar contractors are undoubtedly those that entered the business more than 10 years ago, outlasting the period when lesser companies collapsed. Their references will also be more meaningful since earlier customers can be asked about the original installation as well as the level of follow-up service.</p>
        <p>Questions recommended when seeking references include: Did the workers who installed the system seem to know what they were doing? Was the company willing to provide a written quotation that included details of materials and manufacturers to be used? How long has the company been in business?</p>
        <p>Expect to pay around $3,000 for a two-panel domestic hot-water system, including installation, and about $2,000 for a thermo-syphon system for a Southern home. Rehabilitation of an existing hot-water system can range from a few hundred dollars for small changes or upgrades to $1,500 if a new heat-exchange tank is needed.</p>
        <p>Some of the remaining grants, loans and tax incentive programs should help cover the cost. The energy conservation programs sponsored by some utility companies are one source. For example, New Jersey Public Service Electric &amp; Gas is still offering customers a grant of $500 toward a domestic hot water system - a benefit the Klines used.</p>
        <p>State-sponsored, low-cost energy-saver loans are another. For instance, the Connecticut Energy Conservation Loan Program will finance the cost of installing any passive or active solar system or of upgrading or replacing parts of any existing system for homeowners in that state. Interest rates are based on income and area of residence. For example, a single person living in Stamford and earning $30,000 a year could qualify for a 3 percent interest rate. Call (800) 992-3665 for details. Finally, owners of investment or business property should be aware that a Federal businesss tax credit on solar equipment that was to have expired in 1989 has been extended to Sept. 30, 1990. It lets the investor or corporate owner charge 10 percent of the cost of any solar installation as a credit against income taxes due, noted Robert Grossman, a Washington tax lawyer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
