<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Global Climate Changes Seen As Force in Human Evolution</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="392357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EVOLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MONKEYS AND APES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">AFRICA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">VRBA, ELISABETH S (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monkeys and Apes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DA1F3EF935A25753C1A966958260" item-length="2030" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Global Climate Changes Seen As Force in Human Evolution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: IN an outpouring of analysis that reaches far beyond the study of fossils, scientists are sketching out the influential roles played by climate and ecology in shaping human evolution. In particular, two notable periods of worldwide climatic cooling that occurred within about the last six million years may have touched off critical ecological changes that forced the separation of hominids from apes and, later, of the human line from other hominids.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: IN an outpouring of analysis that reaches far beyond the study of fossils, scientists are sketching out the influential roles played by climate and ecology in shaping human evolution. In particular, two notable periods of worldwide climatic cooling that occurred within about the last six million years may have touched off critical ecological changes that forced the separation of hominids from apes and, later, of the human line from other hominids.</p>
        <p>IN an outpouring of analysis that reaches far beyond the study of fossils, scientists are sketching out the influential roles played by climate and ecology in shaping human evolution. In particular, two notable periods of worldwide climatic cooling that occurred within about the last six million years may have touched off critical ecological changes that forced the separation of hominids from apes and, later, of the human line from other hominids.</p>
        <p>Fossils are the principal evidence of hominid evolution, but they take scientists only so far. The emerging record of ancient climates and ecosystems has filled in some of the context of human origins, and this new perspective has stimulated a flood of ideas and scientific publications. The surge of research and analysis has not changed scientists' views on the timing and genealogy of the human emergence, but it is enabling them to fashion a possible explanation of the forces that drove it.</p>
        <p>''We're beginning to tell a story about how humans evolved,'' says Elisabeth S. Vrba, a paleontologist and evolutionist at Yale University. ''We've gotten to first base. Something we thought was ungettable is coming into reach. It's a very exciting time.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Vrba is a forceful advocate of the view that major episodes of cool world climate set off environmental disruptions in Africa, and that these in turn prompted widespread evolutionary changes, including the emergence of the line leading to humans. She bases this view, which she outlined in a number of publications in 1988 and 1989, on what she calls an ''intriguing correspondence'' among climatic, ecological and evolutionary events.</p>
        <p>The evidence includes records of the ancient climate that are preserved in the shells of tiny ocean animals called foraminifera. In periods of global cooling, greater concentrations of an oxygen isotope, oxygen-18, are left in the ocean and preserved in layers of foraminifera shells embedded in the ocean floor. These layers, according to analyses made over the last few years, record that a major global cooling gradually took place near the close of the Miocene period, which ended about five million years ago. A second, more abrupt and more extreme cooling episode followed about 2.5 million years ago.</p>
        <p>These coolings coincided with a drying of much of the African climate, and Dr. Vrba and others believe that the cooling caused the drying-out. The prolonged dryness made forests give way to grasslands and open savannas, as revealed by analyses of fossilized pollen and animals. Some species of antelopes, for instance, live only on grasslands, and the presence of their fossils indicate this change in habitat.</p>
        <p>Fossils also reveal a marked evolutionary ''pulse'' - an emergence of new species and demise of old ones - that occurred among antelopes about five million years ago and again, more abruptly, around 2.5 million years ago, according to studies published by Dr. Vrba in the mid-1980's.</p>
        <p>The first hominids, called australophithecines, appear in the fossil record at 4.5 million to 5 million years ago. And the genus Homo, the line to which modern humans belong, appears there unambiguously a little before two million years ago. The hominids apparently ''rode along'' on the successive pulses of general evolutionary activity among mammals, Dr. Vrba says.</p>
        <p>Forced From the Trees</p>
        <p>In one view, at least one species of tree-dwelling ape successfully adapted to the breakup of its forest habitat some five million years ago by coming down out of the branches and learning to forage afar on the ground. Inthe interest of efficiency, it began to move about on two legs and eventually evolved into a new, bipedal species - the first hominid. And as part of the second evolutionary flurry about 2.5 million years later, the struggle of some of those first hominids' descendants to survive in the transformed environment led them to adopt still newer foraging strategies that, in turn, stimulated the emergence of the bigger-brained genus Homo, the human family.</p>
        <p>As intriguing and provocative as the coincidences are, experts generally, including Dr. Vrba, do not regard them as proof that climate change was the driving engine of human evolution. ''They are generally loose correlations,'' says Frederick E. Grine, a paleontologist at the State University of New York at Stony Brook. David Pilbeam, a paleoanthropologist at Harvard University who has done pioneering work on human origins, said that to prove cause and effect would require ''a quite dense fossil record that's quite well dated and quite well calibrated to the climatic signal.'' That is more than the hominid fossils can deliver at this point, he said.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, said Dr. Pilbeam, the evidence to date is ''strongly suggestive'' that there was a relationship between climatic change and change in animal species about 2.5 million years ago, although the relationship in the case of any particular species is ''less clear.'' Dr. Grine, despite his reservations, said there ''seems to be a growing consensus'' that there is some linkage between climate and human evolution. ''I have no doubt there's something in them,'' he said of the correlations.</p>
        <p>And Richard G. Klein, a paleoanthropologist at the University of Chicago who is in the forefront of attempts to reconstruct human evolution and who last year published a book on the subject, says he accepts the proposition that ecological disruption forced by climatic change is what brought at least one species of ape down out of the African trees and made it into a two-legged walker and runner. ''There's too much coincidence between ground-dwelling bipedal hominids and the drier climate,'' he said. ''I can't see anything else'' that would account for the development.</p>
        <p>Robert Foley, a lecturer in biological anthropology at the University of Cambridge, England, says the need to adapt and the imperatives of natural selection would have put strong pressures on hominids' progenitors to become bipedal once they left the trees. Bipedal walking and running is a more efficient means of movement at the intermediate speeds required in foraging far afield, says Dr. Foley, who has explored the relationship among climate, ecology, behavior and evolution in articles and a book in the last three years. Moving about on two legs also promotes greater endurance and range and frees the hands for carrying things.</p>
        <p>Finding Food in Dry Seasons</p>
        <p>Dr. Foley believes that there were probably several early species of hominid, including the Australopithecine line from which the genus Homo eventually emerged. Sometime just before or around the big cooling of about 2.5 million years ago, this line produced a new and more advanced branch, the robust australopithecines, who flourished for at least a million years before becoming extinct.</p>
        <p>There is some argument as to whether the appearance of the robust australopithecines predates or coincides with the cooling. In any event, a number of anthropologists believe, the cooling and the ensuing disruption of habitats forced all hominids to adapt to drastically new conditions.</p>
        <p>Dr. Foley believes that in the driest seasons when food was scarcest, some australopithecines, following vegetarian habits that have been inferred from their big grinding molars and patterns of tooth wear, stayed in one kind of habitat and concentrated on coarse, hard seeds and tubers. These required a lot of time to harvest and offered meager nutrition. But other australopithecines, the ones who were to evolve into Homo, began to forage over a larger area and exploit a wider variety of foods - eventually including meat, which remains abundant in dry seasons.</p>
        <p>Robust australopithecines apparently were ''specialists'' who preferred one kind of habitat, the denser vegetation along rivers, according to an analysis of fossil sites published last year by Pat Shipman of the Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine and John Harris of the Natural History Museum of Los Angeles County. ''But when we looked at Homo,'' said Dr. Shipman, ''it was randomly distributed across all habitats. We took that to mean that Homo was a generalist that roamed very widely and used all kinds of resources.''</p>
        <p>More Time for the Kids</p>
        <p>A long train of evolutionary events appears to have followed from the advent of wide-ranging, generalized foraging and meat eating, which in turn appear to have resulted from the need to adapt to a changed environment.</p>
        <p>Because of the more generalized approach of genus Homo, says Dr. Foley, early members of that genus ''would have much larger home ranges and would have to understand a much wider resource base.'' He said this''would put a kind of evolutionary pressure on them to be more intelligent'' and would promote the development of bigger brains.</p>
        <p>At the same time, he and others say, meat in the diet would lead to improved nutrition, which in turn would enable mothers to bear the increased metabolic cost of nursing a baby through the time of its greatest expansion in brain size.</p>
        <p>Because it takes longer to fulfill those metabolic demands, Dr. Foley says, infancy and childhood became extended, requiring parents to make a much greater investment of time and effort in child-rearing. ''What's quite interesting is that it seems that this is not a general hominid characteristic,'' he said. ''It may be something that is unique to the line leading to ourselves.'' Some scientists suggest that the origins of the nuclear family may lie in this heightened level of parental involvement.</p>
        <p>Why did the robust australopithecines become extinct? In the animal kingdom, said Dr. Shipman of Johns Hopkins, ''there is a general rule that stands up pretty well: the specialist is at a disadvantage.'' Other scientists say that although the brains of the robust australopithecines were relatively small, their ponderous bodies put them at a disadvantage: the bigger the species, by and large, the slower its rate of reproduction. The robust australophithecines, in this view, could not reproduce fast enough to evolve genetically in response to environmental changes.</p>
        <p>By contrast, scientists say, the more lightly built, bigger-brained members of the genus Homo not only responded to their environment but thrived in it, ultimately emerging from their African birthplace to colonize the world, confront a new series of adaptive challenges in the colder, harsher North and evolve, in response to those challenges, into Homo sapiens sapiens - modern humans.</p>
        <p>The story of this rise to a kind of dominance is sometimes interpreted as one of evolutionary success. But Dr. Pilbeam of Harvard, noting that ''humans tend to tip the definition of success'' so that it fits them, urges caution in this judgment. One species of robust australopithecines, called Robustus, lasted for at least a million years. ''We've been around for 100,000,'' said Dr. Pilbeam. ''Under a certain definition of success, it's like we're not on the charts yet.''</p>
        <p>Human Ancestors Adapt to Shifts</p>
        <p>In one view of how humans may have emerged, major periods of global cooling caused ecological disruption that stimulated pulses of evolutionary change in a species of tree-dwelling ape and its hominid descendants. Adaptations eventually produced the recognizable large-brained ancestor above, an early member of the genus Homo, to which modern humans belong.</p>
        <p>BEFORE FIRST PULSE</p>
        <p>A species of tree-dwelling ape is believed to have been the ancestor of human beings.</p>
        <p>FIRST PULSE</p>
        <p>In a period of cooling, tropical forests gave way to more open country, forcing some apes to forage afar on two legs.</p>
        <p>SECOND PULSE</p>
        <p>Responding to a later cooling, still newer foraging strategies stimulated the emergence of the genus Homo.</p>
        <p>Source: Elisabeth Vrba; Illustration adapted from Susan Hochgraf</p>
        <p>Signatures Of Plants</p>
        <p>Some plants turn silica into phytoliths, or plant stones, which can scratch or bond to animal teeth. The phytoliths have left marks on fossils that indicate the animals' diets.</p>
        <p>The silicates solidify in and between cells to produce a distinctive form of phytolith in each plant.</p>
        <p>Source: Dr. Russell L. Ciochone</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
