<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="382018"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DE1E38F935A3575AC0A966958260" item-length="1286" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-21</p>
        <p>The White House called for patience. Administration officials appealed to Congress and the public to stand firm during an expected long standoff with President Saddam Hussein of Iraq.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>U.S. and Israel say they'll seek ''credible'' peace process</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-21</p>
        <p>The White House called for patience. Administration officials appealed to Congress and the public to stand firm during an expected long standoff with President Saddam Hussein of Iraq.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>U.S. and Israel say they'll seek ''credible'' peace process</p>
        <p>Tokyo and Moscow issue joint appeal on Persian Gulf crisis</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Thatcher prepares for costly and patient struggle</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>East Europeans agree to sell gas masks to Saudi civilians</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Crisis breathes life into a moribund U.N. panel</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>A set of conservative columnists has turned away from fighting liberalism and started battling one another over America's intervention in the Middle East.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>In Baghdad's bazaars, fear is in good supply</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Hussein says sanctions are depriving Iraqi children of milk</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Tunis bristles with hostility to U.S. gulf moves</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Anti-Semitism in Eastern Europe needs to be attacked on a major scale, Vatican officials and Jewish and Roman Catholic leaders from 16 nations said. Their statement followed a four-day meeting in Prague.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A resort town in West Germany turns into a shrine each summer as hundreds of thousands of people come to admire the most popular hero a German writer has ever produced: a wise Apache chief named Winnetou.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Rights observers reportedly ousted in Yugoslavia</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Romanian miners dispute criticism</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>The opponents of Benazir Bhutto, the former Prime Minister of Pakistan who was abruptly dismissed last month, seem willing to go to any lengths to discredit her so that she cannot be re-elected, politicians, diplomats and ordinary voters say.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Seoul rejects North's plan to end hostilities</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>U.S. to open talks with Cambodian Communists</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>De Klerk moves to reassure whites on a new constitution</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Panama's courts stalled by chaos</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Slavery helps build a boomtown in Amazon</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Killing of Brazil youths reported</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Mexico City Journal: A muted hurrah for Columbus</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>National</p>
        <p>A22-25, B8-14</p>
        <p>Many Americans infected with AIDS have not been receiving potentially life-prolonging drugs that were recommended by Federal authorities a year ago, medical experts say, because they have not been tested and do not know they are infected.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Dentist with AIDS tells ex-patients</p>
        <p>B12</p>
        <p>The Federal Medicare program is being squeezed as never before, and patients and doctors are both complaining. Some experts say Americans will have to put up more money or expect reductions in coverage, else the program become insolvent.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Higher risk is found among children of smokers</p>
        <p>B12</p>
        <p>Americans are ignorant about sex, according to a new survey. The Kinsey Institute and the Roper Organization asked 1,974 adult Americans 18 questions about their basic knowledge of sex and reproduction.</p>
        <p>B14</p>
        <p>Detroit has lost half its population since 1950, Federal officials say. What is worrying Detroit the most, though, is the prospect that it may become the first city ever to drop below 1 million in the census count.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The countdown for the space shuttle was abruptly halted because of a fuel leak and the launching of Columbia was postponed for a third time. The shuttle fleet has been plagued by such leaks for three months.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>The drug war remains a top priority despite events in the Persian Gulf, President Bush vowed. His statement came even as Congressional critics charged that the Administration's drug policy had largely ignored the nation's drug-ravaged cities.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Washington Talk: Drug war underlines fickleness of public</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Negotiators prepare for a last-ditch effort to cut the deficit</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>For deficit talks site, the price is right</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>Dukakis orders further cuts as state tax collections fall</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Senator's widow loses suit against government doctors</p>
        <p>B12</p>
        <p>Three radicals agree to plead guilty in bombing case</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Iran-contra data termed falsified</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Acid rain report confirms concern</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Arctic ozone levels are lower than expected</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Regional</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>The family of the young Utah tourist who was fatally stabbed in the New York subway Sunday were so fond of the city, friends and neighbors say, that they could well have appeared in an ''I love New York'' ad campaign.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Gangs that dance to a violent beat</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>No end to rising subway crime, chief asserts</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>Violence will now find Dinkins showing outrage</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>New York City's Schools Chancellor, Joseph A. Fernandez, is considering seeking legislation that would put the entire custodial work force directly under the control of the New York City Board of Education.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>No New York teacher layoffs</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Public schools in Tarrytown, N.Y., opened under the constraints of an austerity budget. The budget was imposed by the Board of Education after tax-weary voters twice rejected a proposed school budget.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Schools in New Jersey open amid uncertainty</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>A yacht club at the edge of the Bronx with a ''million-dollar view'' of the Manhattan skyline has survived for nearly a century as the neighborhood around it has changed.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Rinfret proposes cutting spending and taxes to bridge gaps</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>Three cases voided in sex incident near St. John's</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>First witness is heard in case of burned boy</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>The Home Section</p>
        <p>Home again, a long year after Huricane Hugo</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>The computers that mimic a desk</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Keeping house in the grand manner</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Parent &amp; Child</p>
        <p>C8</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>The Met's new Delacroix</p>
        <p>C15</p>
        <p>Music: Buddy Holly party</p>
        <p>C17</p>
        <p>Word and Image: TV networks prepare for fall</p>
        <p>C15</p>
        <p>Kitty Dukakis's memoir</p>
        <p>C15</p>
        <p>Health Page</p>
        <p>B15</p>
        <p>Personal Health</p>
        <p>With advent of new heart drugs, delay in seeking help is killer</p>
        <p>Obituaries</p>
        <p>Irene Dunne, film star</p>
        <p>D21</p>
        <p>Ivan Mihailoff, a Macedonian revolutionary</p>
        <p>D22</p>
        <p>Sports</p>
        <p>Baseball: Mets swept by Pirates</p>
        <p>B17</p>
        <p>Yanks beat Angels</p>
        <p>B18</p>
        <p>Column: Berkow on Mets-Pirates</p>
        <p>B17</p>
        <p>Football: Taylor signs</p>
        <p>B17</p>
        <p>McNeil to start</p>
        <p>B21</p>
        <p>Hockey: Devils get Claude Lemieux</p>
        <p>B21</p>
        <p>Tennis: Sampras stuns Lendl</p>
        <p>B17</p>
        <p>Graf and Sanchez in semi-finals</p>
        <p>B20</p>
        <p>Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>Where's their fair share?</p>
        <p>Deferred maintenance</p>
        <p>Assembly choices</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>William Safire: forget about Gulfo</p>
        <p>A27</p>
        <p>Uri Avnery: Recipe for disaster - Israeli invasion of Jordan</p>
        <p>A27</p>
        <p>Mark M. Lowenthal: As Helsinki nears, Gorbachev fades</p>
        <p>A27</p>
        <p>Ted Van Dyk: Will Powell run with Bush in '92?</p>
        <p>A27</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
