<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pastimes;   Around the Garden</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="46" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="370336"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FAUST, JOAN LEE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDD1138F931A15754C0A966958260" item-length="649" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pastimes;   Around the Garden</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joan Lee Faust</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FAUST, JOAN LEE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: For This Week: Keep after insect-disease problems before they overwhelm the plants. Transplanting and dividing continues. Finish pruning, especially spring-flowering species. Last call to apply fertilizer to ornamentals so the new growth has time to develop and harden before cold weather. Keep up fruit tree spray and rose spray as protective measures against disease problems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: For This Week: Keep after insect-disease problems before they overwhelm the plants. Transplanting and dividing continues. Finish pruning, especially spring-flowering species. Last call to apply fertilizer to ornamentals so the new growth has time to develop and harden before cold weather. Keep up fruit tree spray and rose spray as protective measures against disease problems.</p>
        <p>For This Week: Keep after insect-disease problems before they overwhelm the plants. Transplanting and dividing continues. Finish pruning, especially spring-flowering species. Last call to apply fertilizer to ornamentals so the new growth has time to develop and harden before cold weather. Keep up fruit tree spray and rose spray as protective measures against disease problems.</p>
        <p>Ajuga</p>
        <p>Q. Is there a chemical that will get rid of the ajuga, which is taking over a good part of my lawn? Hand weeding at this point would be difficult. Mrs. C.A. Younger, River Edge, N.J.</p>
        <p>A. We do not know of any chemical that would wipe out the ajuga planting without destroying the surrounding vegetation, too. This question points out the problem of allowing invasive species to take over. If aggressive plants such as ajuga are planted, they should be ''watched'' over the years to be sure they do not utilize more garden space than they should.</p>
        <p>Free Trees</p>
        <p>Q. Our local scout troop wants to take on a tree-planting project. Several organizations offer free trees in return for membership. Are there any pitfalls we should be aware of before we get the children involved this fall? Mrs. F.D.S., Chicago, Ill.</p>
        <p>A. Tree planting is in itself a noble idea, especially in this decade when there is concern for global warming. Trees absorb carbon dioxide and give off oxygen in the process of photosynthesis. Many organizations are involved with tree planting, especially the American Forestry Association, headquartered in Washington, which is spearheading a Global ReLeaf program to plant 100 million trees by 1992. The pitfalls: Do homework first to learn how the trees offered will grow. Many good intentioned organizations never state how big these ''free trees'' will grow. A great dane puppy is cute, but a mature one is another matter. For example, the National Arbor Day Foundation is offering 10 Colorado blue spruce conservation trees - free - to new members who contribute $10. (Bald cypress trees are shipped to contributors who live in the South and on the West Coast.) Although the literature touts the merits of the Colorado blue spruce as being evergreen, densely foliaged and no pruning needed, it never states how big these trees will grow. Both of these species when mature are huge forest trees! The Colorado blue spruce (Picea pungens) grows to at least 70 to 90 feet in height, while the bald cypress (Taxodium distichum), which does best in saturated soil, grows to 120 feet in height and its buttressed trunk can be massive.</p>
        <p>Hollyhock</p>
        <p>Q. I have some old-fashioned single hollyhocks, which are blooming beautifully. Several people have asked me for seed or suggested I sow the seed in place. Won't they reseed themselves? Should I cut the plants back after frost? L.E., Manhattan.</p>
        <p>A. Save the seed, when ripe, to give to friends and cut the hollyhock flower stalks back in fall. Since hollyhocks are perennial, they should survive in their spot for several years and may need dividing in as many years if the plantings become too thick. Self-sowing is also a possibility, but more likely the hollyhock roots will endure.</p>
        <p>China Peony</p>
        <p>Q. When we bought our house, we inherited a mystery plant which a friend has identified as a Chinese peony. Can you help us? The buds wither early although the plant is growing in full sun. K.G., Greens Farms, Conn.</p>
        <p>A. Most herbaceous peonies came from China and Japan. It is quite likely that this peony has the common peony diseasse, botrytis, which blasts spring buds and does not permit the foliage to develop properly. Nothing can be done now but next spring, when the peony buds are emerging, start a fungicidal spray program to protect the developing shoots. Repeat in 10 days or after rain. Also this fall be sure to discard old stems and leaves and be sure that the peony bed goes into winter bare and clean.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
