<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Role of Nuclear Power Is Disputed Despite Looming Energy Shortage</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="313691"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NUCLEAR WASTES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PUBLIC CITIZEN (ORGN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NADER, RALPH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D91E3AF931A35752C0A966958260" item-length="682" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Role of Nuclear Power Is Disputed Despite Looming Energy Shortage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As the 1990's begin, the nuclear power industry and its most vocal critics agree that the United States faces a new energy shortage, but they remain at odds over the role that nuclear power should play in averting a crisis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As the 1990's begin, the nuclear power industry and its most vocal critics agree that the United States faces a new energy shortage, but they remain at odds over the role that nuclear power should play in averting a crisis.</p>
        <p>As the 1990's begin, the nuclear power industry and its most vocal critics agree that the United States faces a new energy shortage, but they remain at odds over the role that nuclear power should play in averting a crisis.</p>
        <p>In a report assessing nuclear power in the last decade, environmental groups contend that the industry has not proven it can stand on its own economically or deal with the problems of safety and waste disposal.</p>
        <p>The report, ''A Decade of Decline: The Degeneration of Nuclear Power in the 1980's and the Emergence of Safer Energy Alternatives,'' was made public on Thursday. It was prepared by Ralph Nader's Public Citizen organization on behalf of several dozen environmental and anti-nuclear power groups around the country.</p>
        <p>New Fuel Shortage Looms</p>
        <p>The makings of an energy shortage in the new decade are not in dispute. Domestic oil production has fallen 13 percent since the Arab oil embargo in 1973, and oil imports have taken up the slack. Moreover, the possibility of global warming, which is caused the burning of fossil fuels and depletes the ozone layer, poses a potential threat to the environment and could force the nation to restrict the use of oil, coal and natural gas.</p>
        <p>''The nuclear industry is now seeking to exploit this situation by portraying itself as the solution to the nation's energy and environmental woes,'' the report said. Despite the promises of nuclear power, critics contend, the industry has grown more costly, safety has not improved and the problem of radioactive waste has not been solved.</p>
        <p>Responding to the report, proponents of nuclear plants said in interviews that as the cost of imported oil rises and domestic production shrinks, the industry will become more competitive and part of the solution to the energy crisis.</p>
        <p>But serious obstacles remain. In the last decade there were no orders for new nuclear reactors. Documents obtained from the Nuclear Regulatory Commission and the Department of Energy show that eight licensed reactors were closed and 60 that had been ordered or were under construction were cancelled.</p>
        <p>At the same time the cost of construction for new plants, not accounting for inflation, rose from $1,135 per kilowatt in 1980 to $4,590 in 1989, the report said. The cost of most ''renewable'' sources of energy, like hydroelectric, solar and wind power, declined, and their electric generating capacity grew by 27 percent, producing more power than nuclear plants.</p>
        <p>New Plants Said to Be Cheaper</p>
        <p>But industry officials say that the financial picture is improving and that in some cases nuclear power is cheaper than other sources.</p>
        <p>''Of course, the viable option is going to depend upon economics,'' said Richard Slember, vice president of Energy Systems at the Westinghouse Corporation, one of the nation's largest manufacturers of commercial nuclear reactors. The current generation of plants is cheaper, more efficient and much safer than previous designs, Mr. Slember said.</p>
        <p>Plants that began operating in the 1980's were expensive because of high interest rates, exorbitant construction costs and new safety requirements after the accident at Three Mile Island plant in Pennsylvania, said Cathy Steel Roche, media director at the United States Council for Energy Awareness, the industry's main trade organization. ''With those costs now under control, our belief is that nuclear power will be economically competitive.''</p>
        <p>The major stumbling block to the wider use of nuclear power, the industry contends, is not the plants but the regulatory process that has forced them to sit idle.</p>
        <p>''It's going to take some sort of crisis,'' said John Sillin of the Management Analysis Company in Washington, a consulting firm to the nuclear industry. ''The state licensing commissions will only come around when the brownouts continue and get worse.''</p>
        <p>But the report said the public is most concerned because it thinks the plants are neither safe nor reliable. Indeed, public support for nuclear power withered after the incidents at Three Mile Island and Chernobyl in the Soviet Union.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
