<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sununu Says He Revised Speech on Warming</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="323678"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON POST</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUNUNU, JOHN H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ENGELBERG, STEPHEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DC143FF936A35751C0A966958260" item-length="666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sununu Says He Revised Speech on Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN ENGELBERG, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ENGELBERG, STEPHEN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The White House chief of staff, John H. Sununu, acknowledged today that he had edited a forthcoming Presidential speech on global warming and insisted that the changes reflected President Bush's views on the issue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The White House chief of staff, John H. Sununu, acknowledged today that he had edited a forthcoming Presidential speech on global warming and insisted that the changes reflected President Bush's views on the issue.</p>
        <p>The White House chief of staff, John H. Sununu, acknowledged today that he had edited a forthcoming Presidential speech on global warming and insisted that the changes reflected President Bush's views on the issue.</p>
        <p>Some officials in the State and Energy departments and at the Environmental Protection Agency had urged Mr. Bush to take a stronger stand in his speech, which is scheduled for delivery Monday, on the issue of global warming. Many scientists believe that heat is trapped in the atmosphere by the pollutants of modern society, raising temperatures.</p>
        <p>The Washington Post reported Saturday that Mr. Sununu had ordered revisions to tone down the speech. Mr. Sununu responded today, appearing on the ABC News program ''This Week.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sununu said he had intervened against ''a little tendency by some of the faceless bureaucrats on the environmental side to try and create a policy in this country that cuts off our use of coal, oil and natural gas.''</p>
        <p>''I don't think that's what this country wants,'' he said. ''I don't think America wants not to be able to use their automobiles.'' ''I made changes in the speech that are reflective of the President's policies,'' Mr. Sununu said. The heads of the Government agencies involved in the issue concurred, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has said that while he is concerned about global warming, he does not believe the scientific evidence justifies major new proposals or spending programs.</p>
        <p>'Trying to Get the Answers'</p>
        <p>A White House official said Mr. Bush had not approved a final version of the speech, which will be given before the Intergovernmental Panel, an organization established by the United Nations in 1988 to study the the issue.</p>
        <p>Some environmental groups and other nations have advocated taking immediate steps, a view that is shared by some officials at the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>''The debate frankly is more over tone than policy,'' said one Administration official. ''We are moving forward in a number of areas on environmental regulation, and as we are doing that we are trying to get the answers scientifically about global warning. The speech is going to make that point.''</p>
        <p>Administration officials said Mr. Sununu's role in the drafting of the speech was not unusual. Presidential speeches are drafted by speech writers. Their work is sometimes based on briefings from the agencies that specialize in the issues and their work is often recast by senior officials. Mr. Sununu, who has a degree in nuclear engineering, has taken a close interest in environmental issues.</p>
        <p>Representative Claudine Schneider, Republican of Rhode Island, asserted today that the pending Senate legislation to amend the Clean Air Act was being substantially weakened in private negotiations among the Senate majority leader, George J. Mitchell of Maine, other senators and officials of the Bush Administration.</p>
        <p>The Clean Air Act amendments have passed the Senate Environment and Public Works Committee, and floor debate began last week in the Senate.</p>
        <p>Ms. Schneider, who is a member of the House Science and Technology Committee, declined to say who had told her about the meetings.</p>
        <p>Of particular concern, she said, was an agreement to delay imposition of stricter controls on nitrogen oxide from auto tail pipes. The negotiators also dropped a provision to reduce carbon dioxide pollution, which is seen as a major contributor to atmospheric warming, by requiring auto manufacturers to improve their vehicles' gasoline mileage. Representative Schneider said a failure to act to reduce such emissions would be ''disastrous.''</p>
        <p>Administration officials said tonight that the question of automobile emissions has not been discussed by the principals in the negotiations. The officials said no formal agreement had been reached on the issues mentioned by Representative Schneider. They said that the talks would continue this week and that their success depended on accords being reached on all of the elements of the bill.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
