<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>House Drafting Stiff Bill on Urban Air Pollution</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="340896"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DB163AF936A35757C0A966958260" item-length="794" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>House Drafting Stiff Bill on Urban Air Pollution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Now that the Senate has voted to amend the Clean Air Act, the legislative struggle has shifted to the House of Representatives, where a bill is being drafted that would crack down more strongly on urban air pollution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Now that the Senate has voted to amend the Clean Air Act, the legislative struggle has shifted to the House of Representatives, where a bill is being drafted that would crack down more strongly on urban air pollution.</p>
        <p>Now that the Senate has voted to amend the Clean Air Act, the legislative struggle has shifted to the House of Representatives, where a bill is being drafted that would crack down more strongly on urban air pollution.</p>
        <p>The House bill would address the same pollution problems as the Senate's: acid rain, smog and toxic chemicals. But there are significant differences in how each chamber would achieve its pollution reduction goals.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists and an industry spokesman said today that they favored major elements of the House legislation, being written by the Energy and Commerce Committee. Industry spokesmen said some provisions of the House version might even be less costly for manufacturers because they might not require the use of expensive pollution-control technology.</p>
        <p>Both the Senate and the House bills call for two stages of controls to be used to reduce pollution from automobile tailpipes and from plants that emit hazardous chemicals. In both cases the second round of controls, which would be more costly than the first, is contingent on different actions or developments. Industry representatives believe that under the House bill, the second round is less likely to go into effect for auto and chemical plants and so the House bill would be less costly over the long run.</p>
        <p>Differences on Cities</p>
        <p>Environmental lobbyists said the House version includes requirements that would be more effective in making cities clean up smog and other urban pollution. In particular, they praised a provision, absent in the Senate bill, that would require the Environmental Protection Agency to enforce a plan for reducing urban air pollution in areas where states are unwilling or unable to act.</p>
        <p>S. William Becker, executive director of an association representing state and local pollution control officers, said the House panel had approved provisions that were ''far superior'' to the Senate's, particularly those dealing with cities with dirty air. He noted that the House, unlike the Senate, would not permit cities to avoid making annual progress in reducing smog if they determined the costs were too high.</p>
        <p>William Fay, leader of a coalition of companies and trade associations lobbying on the air law, said the House provisions for controlling auto tailpipe emissions and toxic chemicals in the air were likely to be less expensive than the Senate legislation over the long run.</p>
        <p>But both sides express concerns about some provisions. Environmentalists complained that the House bill would give New York City, Chicago and Houston a longer period to reduce pollution. They also said that so far, the House bill had only a weak provision for requiring cars to burn cleaner gasoline. Industry complained about unnecessary stringent requirements for reducing nitrogen oxide pollution in cities and requirements that small business would have to pay for costly pollution reductions under the House bill.</p>
        <p>Drafting Processes Differ</p>
        <p>Like the Senate, the House is drafting its bill in a series of closed-door negotiations. But unlike the Senate process, the White House is playing no role in that of the House. It has not been invited participate by House leaders.</p>
        <p>Instead, the House bill is being hammered out by lawmakers representing the various regional interests across the nation. Key players are Representative John D. Dingell of Michigan, chairman of the Energy and Commerce Committee, whose interests in the bill include protecting the auto industry and workers who might be affected by the bill, and Representative Henry A. Waxman of California, chairman of the committee's Environmental and Health Subcommittee, who is interested in the strongest possible clean air bill for his Los Angeles district and for the nation.</p>
        <p>The two Democrats, long adversaries over air quality and other environmental legislation, have been able to reach agreements on amendments to the Clean Air Act dealing with urban smog, pollution from cars and toxic chemicals in the air.</p>
        <p>Today the committee was seeking to craft a provision that would reduce acid rain without causing economic hardships in coal mining states and in Midwestern states where coal-fired power plants produce much of the pollution that falls as acid rain over the Northeast. The House, like the Senate, would require a 10-million-ton reduction in sulfur dioxide emissions from power plants by the end of the century.</p>
        <p>In large part because of the meeting of minds between Mr. Dingell and Mr. Waxman, the House committee is moving more rapidly than expected by its members to write its bill to amend the Clean Air Act. The committee could complete its work this week. If it does, the legislation could move to the House floor by the end of April and be approved in May.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
