<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Children, Tips On Rescuing Planet</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="349947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">P3 (MAGAZINE)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDD103FF930A35756C0A966958260" item-length="536" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Children, Tips On Rescuing Planet</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Children hear about the problems all the time: the greenhouse effect, oil spills, acid rain. But do children understand what it all means? Not really, say the publishers of a new environmental magazine for children.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Children hear about the problems all the time: the greenhouse effect, oil spills, acid rain. But do children understand what it all means? Not really, say the publishers of a new environmental magazine for children.</p>
        <p>Children hear about the problems all the time: the greenhouse effect, oil spills, acid rain. But do children understand what it all means? Not really, say the publishers of a new environmental magazine for children.</p>
        <p>Called P3 because Earth is the third planet from the Sun, the magazine includes articles, cartoons, puzzles and pictures about the planet, its environmental problems and how children can learn to safeguard the environment. It is geared toward children 7 to 10 years old.</p>
        <p>''We have to teach them a responsible environmental ethic,'' said Randi Hacker, editor in chief and co-publisher of P3, ''and we have to start it out while they're young, while they still have all their raw feelings about the earth.''</p>
        <p>The March issue was the first, and about 9,000 copies were distributed. After the May-June issue is released on May 15, P3 plans to publish every month during the school year, from September to June.</p>
        <p>Many children hear about the environment from listening to their parents and from watching the news, Ms. Hacker said. But they often do not understand what environmental problems, like oil spills, mean to them. Since most elementary schools do not have a formal environmental curriculum, she said, ''we end up raising another generation as ignorant as we are to keep our earth clean.''</p>
        <p>The magazine's main goal is to educate children about the environment so they can act to preserve it, she said. The first issue tells children to write to politicians to help save elephants from ivory poachers, as well as to walk or to ride their bicycles whenever they can. Future issues will include articles on the greenhouse effect, garbage, trees, oceans and endangered species.</p>
        <p>''Every action everyone takes makes a difference,'' said Jackie Kaufman, P3's co-publisher and editor. ''We have environmental problems that have been in existence for 50 or 60 years. It will take at least as long to solve them. I may not be here, but my hope is that a lot of P3 readers may carry on the work.''</p>
        <p>Although Ms. Hacker and Ms. Kaufman do not have any publishing experience, they have written for children's magazines and television shows. During the past year, as they have learned more about the earth and its problems, they have also become staunch environmentalists.</p>
        <p>To get a child's perspective on the magazine, P3's board of advisers includes two students. One of them, Andrew Sherman, a third-grade pupil from Montgomery, Vt., said he thought the earth was in fine condition until he started reading the magazine's first issue. ''Now, you think it isn't very well,'' he said. Why was it important to know this? ''So that you try to save it,'' he said. Andrew recently put his words into action. On Earth Day, he told his father, Joe Sherman, not to use a spray can to paint an old bicycle. .</p>
        <p>''I hope you know you're destroying the ozone,'' Andrew told his father.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sherman laughed and said his son was right. But the next day he finished spray-painting the bike because, Mr. Sherman said, ''it wasn't Earth Day.''</p>
        <p>P3 is distributed free on request for a school year to elementary school libraries. A subscription for 10 issues costs $14 from P3, P.O. Box 52, Montgomery, Vt. 05470.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
