<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business People;   A President Is Named By Morrison Knudsen</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="390523"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MORRISON KNUDSEN CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SARSTEN, GUNNAR E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KING, HARRIET</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BUSINESS PEOPLE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D7103EF931A25753C1A966958260" item-length="398" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business People;   A President Is Named By Morrison Knudsen</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Harriet King</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KING, HARRIET</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Gunnar E. Sarsten, known for diversifying and tripling the size of the engineering company he headed, has been named president and chief operating officer of the Morrison Knudsen Corporation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Gunnar E. Sarsten, known for diversifying and tripling the size of the engineering company he headed, has been named president and chief operating officer of the Morrison Knudsen Corporation.</p>
        <p>Gunnar E. Sarsten, known for diversifying and tripling the size of the engineering company he headed, has been named president and chief operating officer of the Morrison Knudsen Corporation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sarsten is assuming the posts formerly held by Frank M. Adams, who was killed in a plane crash in May. Since the accident, William J. Agee, chairman and chief executive of Morrison Knudsen, has held Mr. Adams's titles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sarsten said in a telephone interview that the thought of a new career at the age of 53 has ''put a new vigor in my step.'' He envisions staying at Morrison Knudsen, which is based in Boise, Idaho, until the mandatory retirement age of 65. The huge company has interests in engineering, design, construction, rail systems and mining.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sarsten spent 29 years at United Engineers and Constructors International Inc., a Philadelphia-based subsidiary of the Raytheon Company. He was named president and chief operating officer in 1983 and chief executive in 1984.</p>
        <p>Designing and building nuclear power plants once accounted for 80 percent of the unit's business, but as utilities turned away from nuclear power, ''We found ourselves in the mid-1980's with all of our business going away,'' Mr. Sarsten said.</p>
        <p>He expanded into engineering for the chemical-processing and steel industries, oil refineries and acid rain studies, ''or we would have been dead,'' he said. The unit's revenues tripled, to $600 million in 1989.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sarsten said he welcomed the chance to join Morrison Knudsen because he would have a chance at the No. 2 job in a company that had $2.2 billion in revenues in 1989. ''This is a notable move up,'' he said. ''At Raytheon, I was in a fourth-level position behind the chairman, president and group vice president.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sarsten, who has been a registered professional engineer since 1964, received a degree in mechanical engineering in 1958 from the Stevens Institute of Technology in Hoboken, N.J. He served three years in the Air Force and, after joining United Engineers in 1961, completed graduate studies in mechanical engineering during four years of night school at the University of Pennsylvania. He and his wife, Marie, have three adult children.</p>
        <p>He said he was looking forward to life in Boise, noting, ''I'm an outdoors person.'' But as an avid sailor, he said he would miss cruising Chesapeake Bay on his boat, the Windsome.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
