<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Thicket of Environmental Policy, Bush Uses Balance as His Compass</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="365149"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARTER, JIMMY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D9153DF932A35754C0A966958260" item-length="1336" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Thicket of Environmental Policy, Bush Uses Balance as His Compass</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush's decisions on knotty environmental problems, like those he made this week on offshore oil drilling and the ancient forests of the Pacific Northwest, show a strong tendency to placate opposing interests and to soften the impact of difficult political calls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush's decisions on knotty environmental problems, like those he made this week on offshore oil drilling and the ancient forests of the Pacific Northwest, show a strong tendency to placate opposing interests and to soften the impact of difficult political calls.</p>
        <p>President Bush's decisions on knotty environmental problems, like those he made this week on offshore oil drilling and the ancient forests of the Pacific Northwest, show a strong tendency to placate opposing interests and to soften the impact of difficult political calls.</p>
        <p>This impulse toward straddling and buying time is typical of Mr. Bush's style on many issues, but on the environment there is a particularly sharp contrast between him and his two immediate predecessors.</p>
        <p>President Ronald Reagan consistently and unapologetically championed economic development over environmental concerns. President Jimmy Carter made preservation and anti-pollution efforts a theme of his Administration.</p>
        <p>Last Tuesday, Mr. Bush gave one decision to each side.</p>
        <p>His decision to cancel leases for offshore drilling off the coasts of California and Florida was a gesture of concern for the coastal environment that most oil industry spokesmen attacked as a serious mistake. It also gave him time to work out differences between oil and environmental interests and to break a deadlock with Congress that has blocked oil development on large swaths of the outer continental shelf for nearly a decade.</p>
        <p>But environmentalists were angered by the President's decision to delay protecting the ancient forests and their northern spotted owls, declared a threatened species by the Government just four days earlier, so as to safeguard logging jobs. The environmentalists complained that the decision ignored a scientific report by Mr. Bush's own Administration and set a dangerous precedent in wildlife protection.</p>
        <p>The decision also ran counter to the advice of senior officials in the Agriculture and Interior departments, who had urged adoption of the recommendation in the report, by the Interior Department's Fish and Wildlife Service, that eight million acres of ancient forest be set aside for owl habitat. But the White House decided not to act on the recommendation and to take more time to devise a plan to minimize the loss of jobs.</p>
        <p>A Tradition of Balancing</p>
        <p>This kind of balancing has been characteristic of Mr. Bush's environmental decision-making in his first two years in office. He proposed legislation that would require industries to clean up their airborne emissions, but threatened to veto any bill he thought would cost too much. He promised leadership on the problem of global warming caused by pollution, but then called for more scientific and economic research before making specific policy commitments.</p>
        <p>Even his appointments reflect his on-the-one-hand, then-again-on-the-other approach to environmental issues. He named two men popular with environmentalists, William K. Reilly and Michael R. Deland, to head the Environmental Protection Agency and the Council on Environmental Quality. But their initiatives have been restrained by the White House chief of staff, John H. Sununu, and the White House budget director, Richard G. Darman, who generally oppose environmenal actions that might hamper economic growth.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is probably bound to act as he has on these issues. In his 1988 Presidential campaign, he recognized the political benefits of fighting pollution and protecting natural resources, pledging to become ''the environmental President.'' But as a Republican President with close ties to business, Mr. Bush must frequently make decisions that conflict with environmental goals but accommodate his basic constituency.</p>
        <p>Buffeted by Cross Pressures</p>
        <p>''The problem here,'' said one well-placed Republican political operative from the conservative wing of the party, ''is that Bush constantly gets cross pressures. He knows politically what he must do, and he sets out to do it. Then, whatever he sets out to do usually gets watered down.''</p>
        <p>''He knows he should have blocked offshore drilling entirely,'' said this Republican, who spoke on condition of anonymity. ''It's what he started out wanting to do. Then all of his oil buddies from Texas start calling, and then Sununu weighs in, and by the time it comes out the other end, it doesn't please anybody.</p>
        <p>''The same thing with the spotted owl. He started out wanting to restrict timber work, but then the Republican senators start screaming, and then the White House starts backing off, and the cross pressures build up again.</p>
        <p>''What comes out is so much of 'please these people, please those people' that it winds up pleasing no one.''</p>
        <p>White House aides take a different view. Both decisions, they noted, came after years of intensive lobbying by economic and environmental interests, heavy maneuvering by Congress and intense activity in the courts.</p>
        <p>Roger Porter, assistant to the President for domestic and economic policy, made it clear to both the Agriculture and Interior departments that the President wanted a solution that found a balance between protecting jobs and saving the owl. ''The President genuinely considers himself an environmentalist,'' Mr. Porter said. ''On the other hand, he cares about jobs.''</p>
        <p>One Administration official, who insisted on anonymity, also said the White House was guided by concern over the economic implications of enforcing the Endangered Species Act, which requires protection of threatened species regardless of economic consequences. Senior officials in the White House believe that the act was intended to save species from specific local activities like the construction of a dam, not to block economic activity on a regional basis, like blocking logging throughout the Northwest.</p>
        <p>On the offshore oil issue, the President came down largely on the side of the environmentalists, the officials said, because he was persuaded that the risk to the environment was high and that the potential for finding large quantities of oil and gas was low.</p>
        <p>Fewer Headaches on Oil</p>
        <p>While neither decision this week pleased any faction completely, the new oil policy is likely to cause fewer political headaches for the President.</p>
        <p>It removes from the table for at least a decade an issue that has troubled and divided Republican legislators, particularly since the Exxon Valdez oil spill 15 months ago mobilized public opinion against offshore oil activity. Republican strategists are pleased that their candidates in important races in California and Florida this fall will now be spared a pummeling on the issue of offshore wells.</p>
        <p>Representative Leon E. Panetta, a Democrat from California who is a leader in his state's efforts to block offshore oil development that might threaten the environment, said Mr. Bush's decision meant ''that we have a long-term cease-fire instead of having year-to-year battles over temporary delays.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Panetta added, however, that the decision was not a permanent solution and that Congress would have to pass legislation codifying the President's decision so that this or other Administrations could not disavow it. Steven Goldstein, a spokesman for Interior Secretary Manuel Lujan Jr., said, however, that such legislation was unnecessary and would be opposed.</p>
        <p>Jobs vs. Owls</p>
        <p>The decision on Northwest forests is likely to generate more difficulty for Mr. Bush than the one on oil. Now that the northern spotted owl has been declared threatened, the White House will have to seek a change in the Endangered Species Act and perhaps other legislation, like the National Forest Planning and Management Act, to avoid complying with the recommendations of the scientific report to save large parts of the ancient forest. That would entail a fight with environmentalists and their allies in Congress.</p>
        <p>''I do not think the Administration will find national political support for re-doing the Endangered Species Act,'' said George T. Frampton Jr., president of the Wilderness Society. ''It will not fly on the Hill.''</p>
        <p>While consensus building may be the preferred method of making policy in American government, Mr. Bush is obviously discovering that it is difficult to find a middle ground in the uncertain terrain of environmental politics.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
