<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At the Movies</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="373319"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AWARDS, DECORATIONS AND HONORS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'NEAL, TATUM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STOCKWELL, DEAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEMME, JONATHAN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LITTLE NOISES (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SANDINO (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">EASTMAN, GEORGE, AWARD</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD91539F930A3575BC0A966958260" item-length="957" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At the Movies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lawrence Van Gelder</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>O'Neal as Conscience</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>O'Neal as Conscience</p>
        <p>O'Neal as Conscience</p>
        <p>''I'm really looking for projects where the woman is an interesting person,'' said Tatum O'Neal.</p>
        <p>Seventeen years after she made her film debut opposite her father, Ryan O'Neal, in ''Paper Moon'' with a performance that won her an Academy Award as best supporting actress, and six years after she stopped working at the age of 20, Miss O'Neal is in the midst of a comeback.</p>
        <p>Most recently, she completed work in ''Little Noises,'' opposite Crispin Glover, who is generally known as Michael J. Fox's father in the ''Back to the Future'' trilogy.</p>
        <p>''It's about a young man who steals some poems and ends up having to redeem himself,'' Miss O'Neal said of ''Little Noises.''</p>
        <p>In the movie, filmed under the direction of Jane Spencer in Hoboken, N.J., with a few scenes in Manhattan, Miss O'Neal plays the role of Stella, a playwright.</p>
        <p>''One of the words for me would be the conscience,'' Miss O'Neal said of her role. ''I'm also the love interest -in his dreams.''</p>
        <p>Miss O'Neal said she was drawn to the movie by the opportunity to work with Mr. Glover and by the film in general. ''I felt it's not a mainstream type of movie,'' she said. ''It's got more subtle details about the way people change and people live on the other side of the tracks of life.''</p>
        <p>With her work in ''Little Noises'' completed, Miss O'Neal - who is married to the tennis professional John McEnroe, with whom she has two sons, Kevin, 4 years old, and Sean, 2 1/2 - said: ''Right now I'm reading scripts and taking care of my husband and my children, looking for parts I think are interesting for women. I think there are a lot of scripts where the woman plays the wife or the girlfriend just to have the plot move along. I think there are a lot of stories written where the movie is not terribly interesting.'' So, she says, she's looking for roles where the woman ''is someone I think is interesting and I'd enjoy watching.''</p>
        <p>Miss O'Neal said that when she stopped working at the end of 1984 after making ''Certain Fury,'' ''I really just didn't stay in touch with the business. I needed to grow up. If you're not really grown up, it's difficult to play well-rounded roles. ''I fell in love and started a family.'' And, she said, after a time, ''I just thought I'd become very rounded as a person and I'd like to work. I thought acting was my best opportunity to work.'' So she came back.</p>
        <p>''I think I have quite a lot to offer,'' said Miss O'Neal, whose mother is the actress Joanna Moore. ''I think someone who has come from the situation I've come from, that's gone through what I've gone through - I mean growing up in Hollywood and being a child star and having a father in the movies and a mother in the movies - can be very powerful.''</p>
        <p>Sandinista Origins</p>
        <p>For someone who illustrates that a child star can leave the business and come back to be in great demand and to win widespread acclaim, one need look no farther than Dean Stockwell.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stockwell, now 54, was 6 years old when he began his acting career. Twice he ran from it, but a few years ago he came back for good. In the rare moments when someone hasn't got him in front of a camera - in films like Jonathan Demme's ''Married to the Mob'' and Wim Wenders's ''Paris, Texas'' and David Lynch's ''Blue Velvet'' and Francis Ford Coppola's ''Gardens of Stone'' - Mr. Stockwell spends his time alerting the public to such environmental dangers as the depletion of the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>But mostly his time is taken up with acting. Not only has he been busy on television with the time-travel series ''Quantum Leap,'' he's been busy as can be with feature films, among them ''Backtrack,' with Jodie Foster, Dennis Hopper and Charlie Sheen, in which he plays a crooked lawyer, and ''Palais Royal,'' with Kim Cattrall, in which he portrays a Mafia don.</p>
        <p>''The most recent of them and, I think, the most interesting of them,'' he said, ''is 'Sandino.' '' Written and directed by Miguel Littin, a Chilean exile who lives in Spain and Mexico, ''it is,'' said Mr. Stockwell, ''the story of Augusto Sandino in the 1920's, who is the only one in the Nicaraguan hierarchy to rebel against the installation of the first Somoza as dictator. Generations later, when the revolution overthrew the other Somoza, they named their revolution after Sandino.''</p>
        <p>In the film, Mr. Stockwell plays the role of an American Army officer pursuing the first of the Nicaraguan guerrilla leaders unsuccessfully in the countryside. ''I thought it was a story that people - other than those in Nicaragua and other Latin American countries - are unaware of,'' Mr. Stockwell said. ''He's another Zapata. The United States Government was trying to fight him with a world war.''</p>
        <p>Because of his commitment to making 22 new episodes of ''Quantum Leap,'' Mr. Stockwell said, he will have to limit his feature film work to the television show's hiatus, from April to July.</p>
        <p>But, he observed: ''I've been busy. I hope I stay that way. It looks like I will.''</p>
        <p>Eastman Award</p>
        <p>Jonathan Demme has been named the recipient of the 1990 George Eastman Award. The award was voted unanimously by the executive committee of Showeast, an alliance of eastern state chapters of the National Association of Theater Owners.</p>
        <p>The award is given annually to a film maker who embodies film industry traditions on the East Coast. To be presented Oct. 10, the award, sponsored by Eastman Kodak and Premiere magazine, includes a scholarship to be presented to the school or organization of the film maker's choice.</p>
        <p>Among Mr. Demme's films, in addition to ''Married to the Mob,'' are ''Citizen's Band,'' ''Melvin and Howard'' and ''Swimming to Cambodia.'' Martin Scorsese and Sidney Lumet have been recipients of the award.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
