<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senator Urges Military Resources Be Turned to Environmental Battle</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="364610"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CENTRAL INTELLIGENCE AGENCY (CIA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SENATE COMMITTEE ON ARMED SERVICES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NUNN, SAM (SEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDA1630F93AA15755C0A966958260" item-length="890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senator Urges Military Resources Be Turned to Environmental Battle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Calling environmental destruction ''a growing national security threat,'' Senator Sam Nunn, the chairman of the Senate Armed Services Committee, today proposed shifting substantial Defense Department and intelligence resources to address ecological problems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Calling environmental destruction ''a growing national security threat,'' Senator Sam Nunn, the chairman of the Senate Armed Services Committee, today proposed shifting substantial Defense Department and intelligence resources to address ecological problems.</p>
        <p>Calling environmental destruction ''a growing national security threat,'' Senator Sam Nunn, the chairman of the Senate Armed Services Committee, today proposed shifting substantial Defense Department and intelligence resources to address ecological problems.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nunn, a Georgia Democrat, was joined on the Senate floor by fellow Democrats Al Gore of Tennessee, Tim Wirth of Colorado, Jeff Bingaman of New Mexico and Jim Exon of Nebraska, all members of the Armed Services Committee, in calling for the creation of a Strategic Environmental Research Program.</p>
        <p>An influential Democratic leader who has played no significant role on environmental issues, Mr. Nunn made it plain that he had two goals: In an age of diminishing tensions with the Soviet Union, he wants to retain the extensive national security research apparatus at the Pentagon, the Energy Department and Central Intelligence Agency, and at the same time turn much of its focus to what he described as a rising security threat posed by degradation of the environment.</p>
        <p>The program outlined by Mr. Nunn would enlist the research talent available to the military and intelligence establishment, as well as its computers, planes, ships, satellites and other resources, to address environmental threats.</p>
        <p>Some new Federal spending would be required, including the costs of a proposed new Defense Environmental Research Council. No detailed financial estimates are available, but in general, planners foresee the diverting resources worth billions of dollars.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview, Mr. Nunn acknowledged that one purpose of his proposal was to retain research and technological capacity for the military establishment at a time when military budgets will be shrinking. ''But the major purpose is environmental,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In his speech, the Senator said that global environmental problems were worsening and leading to tensions that could pose military problems, especially in the third world.</p>
        <p>''The end of the cold war has greatly reduced the risk of superpower confrontation,'' Mr. Nunn said, but he added that pressures on the environment could increase the danger of ethnic or regional conflicts.</p>
        <p>The Main Problems</p>
        <p>Among the problems listed by Mr. Nunn were population pressures on food and water supplies, the depletion of the ozone layer in the atmosphere, large-scale destruction of forests and global warming linked to air pollution.</p>
        <p>Many traditional security problems remain, Mr. Nunn said, citing the proliferation of nuclear weapons, chemical weapons and missles in the third world; ''radical Moslem fundamentalism;'' global terrorism, and the drug trade. But he said he now believes ''that there is also a new and different threat to our national security emerging: the destruction of our environment.''</p>
        <p>''I believe that America must lead the way in marshaling a global response to the problems of environmental degradation, and the defense establishment should play an important role in this effort,'' Mr. Nunn said.</p>
        <p>Like Senator Nunn, who is a leading Congressional expert on military affairs, the top commanders at the Pentagon from Defense Secretary Dick Cheney down have been concerned about how they would keep the military establishment intact in a time of decreasing world tension.</p>
        <p>A Defense Department spokesman, Glenn Flood, said of the plan today: ''On the surface it sounds good. We just have to see what the specifics are before we can embrace everything he has proposed.''</p>
        <p>Unlocking Secret Data</p>
        <p>Among other things, Mr. Nunn's plan would open to nonmilitary scientists and researchers some data gathered by the armed services and intelligence agencies that is now kept secret. An example would be the thickness of polar ice as measured by the Navy's nuclear submarines.</p>
        <p>Military aircraft, ships, submarines and satellites could collect information on air and water quality and on global climate, Mr. Nunn said. The powerful computers used by the Defense and Energy Departments could be made available to civilian researchers. The two departments could devote research money and equipment now used for military programs to developing energy technology for civilian use, including new nuclear reactor designs, energy storage techniques and superconducting materials.</p>
        <p>Senator Nunn suggested that many resources could be used for military and environmental purposes at once. Aircraft and ships on military exercises, for example, could also collect environmental data.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nunn also stressed that the technology for cleaning up the environment would become an increasingly important economic factor in world trade. ''I would like to see American technology leading the world,'' he said. Although a growing number of scholars and Government officials have warned that environmental deterioration is a major threat to national security, this would be the first time the threat would be addressed in the nation's strategic planning. Senator Gore, who has long called for a shift in strategic thinking, said in an interview today that the most significant thing about the proposal is ''this philosophic point that the environment is recognized as a national security issue.''</p>
        <p>Senator John W. Warner, the ranking Republican on the Armed Services Committee, said he thought Mr. Nunn's proposal was ''worth serious consideration.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
