<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Version of the Dickens Classic</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="408905"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">THEATER THREE (PORT JEFFERSON, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRANK, LEAH D</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CHRISTMAS CAROL (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DC153FF935A25751C1A966958260" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Version of the Dickens Classic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Leah D. Frank</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRANK, LEAH D</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHARLES DICKENS fills his tales with the stuff of theater -- great ideas, melodrama, heroes and villains.</p>
        <p>His novels and short stories are often adapted into films, television specials and plays. The musical "Drood," based on Dickens's "Mystery of Edwin Drood," was the most recent Broadway version of the adaptations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHARLES DICKENS fills his tales with the stuff of theater -- great ideas, melodrama, heroes and villains.</p>
        <p>His novels and short stories are often adapted into films, television specials and plays. The musical "Drood," based on Dickens's "Mystery of Edwin Drood," was the most recent Broadway version of the adaptations.</p>
        <p>Now, three artists from Theater Three in Port Jefferson have added an adaptation with a new "Christmas Carol."</p>
        <p>Here we have all the old familiar characters:</p>
        <p>*The wealthy hard-hearted Scrooge, whose ice-cold demeanor melts like glacial ice in a global warming.</p>
        <p>*The abused but faithful employee, Bob Cratchit.</p>
        <p>*Fred, the poor but cheerful nephew.</p>
        <p>*A series of haunting hosts.</p>
        <p>*And crippled Tiny Tim, whose cry of, "God bless us, everyone," has reverberated through decades of holiday seasons and countless rewritings.</p>
        <p>To the Dickens classic tale, Jeffrey E. Sanzel and Brent Erlanson have written a book and lyrics, and Jeanette Barsi has supplied the music. They have tried to add a fresh twist to this oft-told Christmas story by framing it with a plot in which a semiprofessional community-theater company in Connecticut is presenting a musical version of "A Christmas Carol."</p>
        <p>The dramatization of the Dickens story is set as a play within a play, and parallels the personal problems among members of the theater company on Christmas Eve and Dickens characters.</p>
        <p>For example, the actor playing Scrooge is hostile and withdrawn, while the company actor playing the nephew Fred, whom Scrooge has disinherited for falling in love, is in love with the actress playing Margaret.</p>
        <p>In place of the ghosts who haunt and redeem Scrooge, the actors of this small theater company have to own up to their problems when a mammoth snowfall leaves them stranded in the theater.</p>
        <p>The problem with what Mr. Sanzel, Mr. Erlanson and Ms. Barsi have created is that their play runs alongside of Dickens's story, but the two never merge into a unified evening of theatrical entertainment.</p>
        <p>As the actors playing the members of the Winford Repertory Theater arrive on stage preparing for their final performance of "A Christmas Carol," their complex backstage relationships are exposed.</p>
        <p>Scrooge is a former television star who let success and alcohol overcome his talent. A co-owner of the theater was his former lover, who left him to marry the man who is now the other co-owner of the theater. An aspiring young actor named Damon wants professional pointers from the erstwhile star.</p>
        <p>The list of who wants what from whom is as numerous as the cast.</p>
        <p>But once the actors assemble and put on their makeup and costumes for their closing-night performance, the plot that has been established is abandoned for that of Dickens. And so while the players perform "A Christmas Carol," the story of an ill-tempered has-been actor hovers in the background like an interloping stage ghost.</p>
        <p>As presented by Theater Three, the attempt to tell the Christmas Eve stories of the Winford Repertory actors and of Scrooge, Marley and Tiny Tim dilutes both.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sanzel and Mr. Erlanson have written a promising opening: they are writing about a small suburban theater with which they are familiar, and their affection for their fictional theater troupe is real.</p>
        <p>When they transport their contemporary players into 19th-century London, however, they trip over Dickens and never recover. The first act ends so suddenly that not until the lights come up does the audience know an intermission has arrived.</p>
        <p>Neither the troupe at Winford nor the participants in the Dickens "Christmas Carol" are helped by the mediocre musical numbers. Each time a song is sung, the action comes to a screeching halt until the music ends, which makes the musical numbers more time consuming than illuminating.</p>
        <p>Mr. Erlanson has also directed this adaptation, and it is thorugh his directorial work that the action flows from Connecticut to London with ease. The Winford actors arrive on stage to begin preparation for their show as naturally as the Theater Three actors must have earlier arrived to begin putting on their make-up for the show we are watching.</p>
        <p>Where the evening bogs down is because of Mr. Erlanson the writer, rather than Mr. Erlanson the director.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sanzel, the co-author, also plays the double role of Scrooge in the Dickens play and Richard Morgan, the Winford actor playing Scrooge.</p>
        <p>As an actor, Mr. Sanzel is first-rate. His Scrooge is mean and wizened, while his actor is a man whose rage at the world is like a cauldron simmering just beneath his placid emotional facade.</p>
        <p>Of the rest of the cast, Amelia Chiaramonte gives a sharp performance as the theater's hard-working stage manager and replacement actress. Linda Kanner is believable as a happily married theater-loving manager and mother.</p>
        <p>As required for all holiday shows, the cast contains a number of children, all of whom are bright, perky and utterly charming.</p>
        <p>This updated reworking of "A Christmas Carol" delivers a break from the usual. Whether or not it is worth more than a "bah humbug" is the question. It continues through Dec. 29.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
