<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Headline</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="356699"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MOSER, PENNY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DAVIDSON, ART</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">IN THE WAKE OF THE EXXON VALDEZ (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D91F3BF934A15756C0A966958260" item-length="970" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Headline</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PENNY MOSER; Penny Moser wrote about the aftermath of the Exxon Valdez oil spill for the German magazine GEO.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MOSER, PENNY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>IN THE WAKE OF THE EXXON VALDEZ</p>
        <p>The Devastating Impact of the Alaska Oil Spill.</p>
        <p>By Art Davidson.</p>
        <p>Maps. 333 pp. San Francisco:</p>
        <p>Sierra Club Books. $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>IN THE WAKE OF THE EXXON VALDEZ</p>
        <p>The Devastating Impact of the Alaska Oil Spill.</p>
        <p>By Art Davidson.</p>
        <p>Maps. 333 pp. San Francisco:</p>
        <p>Sierra Club Books. $19.95.</p>
        <p>IN THE WAKE OF THE EXXON VALDEZ</p>
        <p>The Devastating Impact of the Alaska Oil Spill.</p>
        <p>By Art Davidson.</p>
        <p>Maps. 333 pp. San Francisco:</p>
        <p>Sierra Club Books. $19.95.</p>
        <p>Just when I thought I knew everything I wanted to about the Alaskan oil spill last year, along comes ''In the Wake of the Exxon Valdez.'' Art Davidson recounts this supertanker saga with so much vigor and fresh information that I was quickly hooked.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davidson, the author ''Minus 148 degrees: First Winter Ascent of Mount McKinley'' and, with Art Wolfe, of ''Alakshak: The Great Country,'' sets the scene dramatically. It's March 23, the evening of the midnight crash. Capt. Joseph Hazelwood is drinking in a bar and getting ready to assume command of the Exxon Valdez. At the same time, honchos from Alyeska, the oil consortium that owns the Trans-Alaska Pipeline and is responsible for spill emergencies, are in the Valdez Civic Center celebrating their cleanup of a British Petroleum tanker's spill two months earlier. (Never mind that it took them 15 days to pick up only 1,700 barrels of oil. They are celebrating anyway.) Meanwhile, in the Valdez city council chambers, Mayor John Devens is holding a citizens' meeting about oil safety, during which the townspeople express their fear that Alyeska has neglected its responsibility and that there is another accident waiting to happen. Little do they know.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davidson next puts the reader and the crew - along with a carryout pizza - right on board the ship. I find myself a passenger with 20/20 hindsight. I am simultaneously at the helm of the tanker; on watch up on the bridge; peering into the radar screen; and with Captain Hazelwood down in his cabin. There is ice ahead. And rocks. It's dark. I am nervous, but the captain and crew remain calm. By the time we are accelerating into Bligh Reef, I want to stand up and scream: ''Turn the boat. We're going to crash.'' It is not the last time I'll want to scream.</p>
        <p>''In the Wake of the Exxon Valdez'' reads like a whodunit. I had always thought Exxon dunit. But, as I read this book, ''Murder on the Orient Express'' came to mind. Exxon's misguided supertanker plunged the first knife into Prince William Sound. But British Petroleum - the majority holder of Alyeska - got a knife in, too, by bungling the initial response to the spill. Alyeska got in a lot of knives by not maintaining its cleanup equipment and crew. Those who could have helped stop the bleeding - the United States Coast Guard, the Department of the Interior and the State of Alaska - held meetings instead.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Davidson analyzes the Byzantine inter- and intra-agency politics, two things become clear: the pro-development and anti-regulatory policies of the Reagan era played a large part in the Valdez fiasco, and all the groups and agencies that could have ameliorated it were paralyzed by the fear that any decision they made could make their opponent's lawyer rub his hands together in glee.</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, environmentalists take some hard knocks in this Sierra Club book. For instance, Mr. Davidson implies there might never have been all those oily otters and birds if Exxon had been allowed to burn the oil before it spread. During a test the day after the spill, 15,000 gallons were burned off in under an hour. Exxon could have burned 50,000 gallons an hour. But Alaska decided not to do it until the state's Department of Environmental Conservation could look at how the burning might affect air quality. Meanwhile, 10 million gallons of oil got away and mixed with water. All things considered, it hardly seemed the moment to stop and ponder the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>About halfway through the book, I, the owner of a well-worn ''BOYCOTT EXXON'' sweatshirt, softened. Once the oil got loose, Exxon faced a nearly impossible task. And I had never before realized just how close the tanker Valdez came to snapping in half or rolling over, in the hours following impact, and just how dangerous this made the rescue. The men who dived under the teetering ship to inspect the hull were brave. So was the crew of the Exxon Baton Rouge, which tied up to the Valdez to take her remaining oil. When distraught fishermen needed money fast to save a crucial salmon hatchery, the Exxon Shipping president, Frank Iarossi, wrote a $1 million promissory note on his business card, telling them, ''It's as good as my word.'' It was.</p>
        <p>Other characters made Exxon look good by comparison. While there were some indefatigable local heroes, too many Alaskans whined about the oily hand that has fed them well and long. The players along the Potomac often put me more in mind of J. R. Ewing and Dagwood Bumstead than of elected officials.</p>
        <p>In one chaotic scenario, for instance, we see some National Park Service employees in Alaska desperately scrambling to divert the oil floating toward Kenai Fjords National Park. But they had little money or equipment. Back in Washington, the Department of the Interior and the Coast Guard saw no threat and said there was no need for action. In the next scene, we see the brokenhearted park superintendent walking over hundreds of dead birds on the beach and asking herself, ''What could I have done differently?''</p>
        <p>Not much. Officials from the Interior Department in Washington told the National Park Service employees in Alaska, ''If you spent money you don't have in your budget, we can take you to court to make you pay for it personally. And if you can't pay, you'll go to jail.''</p>
        <p>A few hours after the crash, Alaska's Gov. Steve Cowper was standing on the deck of the Exxon Valdez. The air smelled bad. He watched the oil move toward the horizon and said, ''I've never seen such a goddamned mess in my life.'' He could have said the same thing on every page of this book. A lot of things smelled bad. Only one of them was oil.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
