<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Executives See a Chance Of Deficit Cut</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="353308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXECUTIVES AND MANAGEMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCOME TAX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D8133DF937A25756C0A966958260" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Executives See a Chance Of Deficit Cut</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr., Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</byline>
      <dateline>HOT SPRINGS, Va., May 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Despite repeated disappointments, many of the nation's top corporate executives say they think there is at least an even-money chance for a breakthrough in budget negotiations that begin on Tuesday in Washington, with a sizable number supporting such an agreement even if it includes an increase in personal income taxes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Despite repeated disappointments, many of the nation's top corporate executives say they think there is at least an even-money chance for a breakthrough in budget negotiations that begin on Tuesday in Washington, with a sizable number supporting such an agreement even if it includes an increase in personal income taxes.</p>
        <p>Despite repeated disappointments, many of the nation's top corporate executives say they think there is at least an even-money chance for a breakthrough in budget negotiations that begin on Tuesday in Washington, with a sizable number supporting such an agreement even if it includes an increase in personal income taxes.</p>
        <p>''I'm encouraged that we will accomplish it finally this time, and it will have all kinds of good effects.'' said Edmund T. Pratt Jr., the chairman of Pfizer Inc., the pharmaceutical company.</p>
        <p>A significant reduction of the deficit is a goal that has eluded policy makers for half a decade or more.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pratt was one of the company chiefs interviewed at a meeting of the Business Council, a group wtih 100 active members, many of them chief executives of the nation's largest companies. They gather twice a year at the historic Homestead Hotel here.</p>
        <p>Others declaring themselves more or less optimistic included Lewis T. Preston of J. P. Morgan &amp; Company, John G. Smale of the Procter &amp; Gamble Company and Frank P. Popoff of the Dow Chemical Company.</p>
        <p>But though a majority of the executives said higher taxes would have to be part of any successful budget deal, not all were willing to accept higher income tax rates.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smale, for example, said he would have ''real difficulty'' with any plan to raise rates, including one that would eliminate a feature in the tax law that taxes a portion of middle-income earnings at 33 percent while those with higher incomes are taxed at 28 percent.</p>
        <p>Another participant, Michael J. Boskin, the chairman of the President's Council of Economic Advisers, cited rising interest rates and lower corporate profits as factors that prompted the Administration to make budget overtures. He also seemed to indicate that taxes involving fuels and the environment would be prominent candidates if the Administration did agree to higher taxes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boskin, one of the eight members of President Bush's negotiating team, met with reporters after a presentation to the Business Council on the environment, the main subject of the two-day gathering. He responded to an observation that the subject of environmental taxes is increasingly under discussion by noting that the Administration was ''predisposed toward user fees in general.''</p>
        <p>In February's Economic Report of the President, Mr. Boskin's office contended that economic incentives were to be preferred over statutory compulsions to deal with the environment and said ''a variety of policy tools, including user charges,'' could be employed, for example, ''to slow the buildup of greenhouse gases in the atmosphere.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Boskin declined to comment on whether he considered gasoline taxes to be user fees.</p>
        <p>Ending the Deadlock</p>
        <p>Many members of the Business Council seemed almost eager for new taxes if that would break the long-standing fiscal deadlock that, among other things, has forced the Federal Reserve to adhere to a relatively restrictive monetary policy that has produced high interest rates.</p>
        <p>The White House budget director, Richard G. Darman, another of the President's negotiators, said in a lecture last week at Harvard University that ''reducing the deficit is probably necessary to get interest rates satisfactorily down.''</p>
        <p>While the members agreed with the Administration in mostly favoring spending cuts over tax increases, they were considerably less interested in the mechanism by which reducing the deficit occurs than in seeing it accomplished.</p>
        <p>''Put everything on the table - and not take anything off if it solved the problem,'' advised one executive who asked not to be named. The executive supports raising the top income tax bracket to a uniform 33 percent.</p>
        <p>Willard C. Butcher, the chairman of the Chase Manhattan Bank, also proposed higher taxes and spending cuts, perhaps some kind of tax on consumption and the means-testing of entitlement programs like Social Security and Medicare to exclude those who do not need them.</p>
        <p>To raise the savings rate, Mr. Butcher suggested that no limit be imposed on the size of yearly contributions to individual retirement accounts.</p>
        <p>The Issue of Gas Taxes</p>
        <p>Roger B. Smith, the chairman of the General Motors Corporation, said that he opposed higher gasoline taxes because they are regressive, but that he could support a ''greenhouse'' or ''carbon'' fee, taxing fuels like oil and coal that pollute the air. He said such taxes would not fall so heavily on the poor.</p>
        <p>The group still had numerous doubters as to whether a deficit-reduction agreement could be reached.</p>
        <p>''It's not a very good start,'' said G. William Miller, the chairman of Federated Stores Inc. and Treasury Secretary during the Carter Administration, referring to the public sparring that has occurred since the negotiations were set. ''One still has to be skeptical.''</p>
        <p>Tom H. Barrett, the chairman the Goodyear Tire and Rubber Company, said he thought it ''too early to tell'' the odds of a successful outcome but he also expressed a fairly widespread suspicion that the talks would not be taking place had there not been some clandestine winks and nods.</p>
        <p>''It sounds,'' Mr. Barrett said, ''like there's something going on behind the scenes.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
