<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Celebrate and Protect the Earth</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="345280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH DAY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">YARROW, ANDREW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DB1F39F933A15757C0A966958260" item-length="2657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Celebrate and Protect the Earth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW L. YARROW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">YARROW, ANDREW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: NEW YORK CITY is barely a dot on the planet, occupying just 322 square miles of the earth's nearly 197 million, but this weekend it will overflow with outdoor performances, environmental exhibitions, street fairs, nature walks, cleanup projects and other activities on the 20th anniversary of Earth</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: NEW YORK CITY is barely a dot on the planet, occupying just 322 square miles of the earth's nearly 197 million, but this weekend it will overflow with outdoor performances, environmental exhibitions, street fairs, nature walks, cleanup projects and other activities on the 20th anniversary of Earth</p>
        <p>NEW YORK CITY is barely a dot on the planet, occupying just 322 square miles of the earth's nearly 197 million, but this weekend it will overflow with outdoor performances, environmental exhibitions, street fairs, nature walks, cleanup projects and other activities on the 20th anniversary of Earth Day.</p>
        <p>Two decades after the grass-roots mobilization that brought about a great leap forward in ecological consciousness, the problems of pollution of the air and water, acid rain, solid-waste disposal, recycling, toxic wastes and depletion of the ozone layer remain high on the world's agenda.</p>
        <p>But a spirit of hope and celebration characterizes the mammoth international observance of Earth Day 20, which is to culminate on Sunday with events in more than 130 countries and hundreds of events and celebrations in New York's five boroughs, including a morning pageant of performers and politicians in Times Square, an all-day environmental street festival on the Avenue of the Americas, an afternoon concert and rally in Central Park, programs about endangered species at the Bronx Zoo and at the New York Aquarium in the Coney Island section of Brooklyn and a photographic exhibition on the animals and plants of New York City at the New York Hall of Science in Flushing Meadows-Corona Park in Queens.</p>
        <p>''People are much more aware of environmental issues now than 20 years ago,'' said Pamela Lippe, the executive director of Earth Day 1990 New York City. ''So this Earth Day is focused on broadening the base of the environmental movement, sparking interest and involvement, and showing people what they can do.''</p>
        <p>It may seem improbable to celebrate nature in that most unnatural of locales -TIMES SQUARE- but that's exactly where a musical opening ceremony for Earth Day is to be held at 9:30 A.M. on Sunday. Paul Winter, the jazz musician and composer, is to be joined by an American Indian band called Four Winds and a Brazilian samba band called Pe De Boi. At 10 A.M., Mayor David N. Dinkins with the Manhattan Borough President, Ruth W. Messinger, and the Very Rev. James Parks Morton, dean of the Cathedral of St. John the Divine, are among those scheduled to speak.</p>
        <p>As a large hot-air balloon representing the earth rises above Times Square, several hundred performers, some dressed as endangered animals, are to parade toward the AVENUE OF THE AMERICAS.This is to begin a street fair, which is expected to fill the avenue from 42d to 59th Streets until 6 P.M. More than 125 environmental and community organizations are to be represented and products like energy-efficient appliances and alternative-fueled vehicles are to be displayed.</p>
        <p>There is also to be a green market, arts-and-crafts vendors, international foods, a walk-in fresh-air tank, a tongue-in-cheek environmental fashion show and entertainment on three stages. At the world stage, set up near 55th Street, there are to be salsa and African bands, an Italian Renaissance-music ensemble and an Israeli folk singer. New York rock musicians and dancers are to perform on a city stage, near 52d Street, and music and theater for children is to be presented on a stage near 48th Street.</p>
        <p>But if the environment (i.e., the weather) cooperates, Sunday's best-attended event is likely to be the concert and rally on the GREAT LAWN OF CENTRAL PARKfrom 2 to 5 P.M. The performers are to include Hall and Oates, the B-52's, Ric Ocasek of the Cars, the Roches, Ben E. King, Willie Colon, Edie Brickell and the New Bohemians, G. E. Smith and the Saturday Night Live Band and a 14-piece South African ensemble called Mahlathini and the Mahotella Queens. The hosts are to include Marlo Thomas, Christopher Reeve and Carly Simon. Gov. Mario M. Cuomo, Mayor Dinkins, the environmentalist Barry Commoner and Cesar Chavez of the United Farm Workers are to address the ways in which individuals, communities and businesses can work to protect the environment. Earlier in the day, at 11 A.M., Albert F. Appleton, the New York City Commissioner of Environmental Protection, is to speak at the CATHEDRAL OF ST. JOHN THE DIVINE,Amsterdam Avenue and 112th Street (316-7540). For information on the events at Times Square, the Avenue of the Americas and Central Park: 517-0762.</p>
        <p>Another Earth Day nexus is the eco-nightclub WETLANDS PRESERVE, at 161 Hudson Street. The weekend's lineup includes reggae music at 10 tonight (admission: $10); a film on dolphins and a performance by the 1960's band Rare Earth at 9:30 P.M. tomorrow (admission: $15) and a free bring-your-own-instruments jam session and closing party on Sunday at 5 P.M. Information: 966-4225.</p>
        <p>In addition to the high-profile events, Earth Day will be celebrated with a wide variety of museum exhibitions and programs, films, festivals in city parks, ecology-minded tours and public gardening and cleanup activities. Museums At the AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY,Central Park West at 79th Street, endangered species are the subject of tours from 10:30 A.M. to 4 P.M. on Sunday. Scientists are to hold informal talks throughout the museum. Admission is $4; $2 for children. Information: 769-5100.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most profound image of the earth's fragility has been conveyed by photographs taken on manned space missions. More than 60 photos from America's first decade in space are included in a three-month exhibition, ''The View From Space: American Astronaut Photography, 1962-1972,'' which is to open tomorrow on the third floor of the NEW YORK PUBLIC LIBRARY,Fifth Avenue and 42d Street. Hours are 10 A.M. to 9 P.M. on Mondays, Tuesdays and Wednesdays and 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. Thursdays through Saturdays. Admission is free. Information: 869-8089.</p>
        <p>A so-called pollution party and children's workshops on ecosystems and the effects of pollutants are to be held at 11:30 A.M. on Sunday at the CHILDREN'S MUSEUM OF MANHATTAN,#212 West 83d Street. Admission is $4. Information: 721-1234.</p>
        <p>For reading about ecological issues and nature, there will be more than 400 books from 200 publishers at the SMALL PRESS CENTER,#20 West 44th Street, through May. Hours are 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. on Sunday and 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. Monday through Friday. Admission is free. Information: 764-7021.</p>
        <p>Artworks about human uses and abuses of the environment are on view in the third-floor gallery of the CENTRAL PARK ARSENAL,Fifth Avenue and 64th Street. The exhibition, ''Unnatural Causes,'' is to open on Sunday. After that, it may be seen on weekdays through May 11, from 9 A.M. to 4:30 P.M. Admission is free. Information: 360-3423.  Two museums in Flushing Meadows-Corona Park in Queens have scheduled events. At the NEW YORK HALL OF SCIENCE,#47-01 111th Street, a photographic exhibition on the animals and plants of New York City is on view through April 29, and environmentally clean technologies are to be demonstrated on Sunday through April 28. Videos about local environmental concerns will be shown noon to 4 P.M. on Sunday. Museum hours are 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. Wednesdays through Sundays. Admission is $3.50; $2.50 for children and the elderly. Information: (718) 699-0005.</p>
        <p>A short walk away, at the QUEENS MUSEUM,a slide lecture on how artists interpret environmental problems is scheduled on Sunday at 2:30 P.M., and a film about strip mining will be shown an hour later. Admission is $2; $1 for students and the elderly. Information: (718) 592-2405.</p>
        <p>Most New Yorkers have little contact with agriculture, but a semblance of farm life may be experienced at the QUEENS COUNTY FARM MUSEUM,#73-50 Little Neck Parkway in Floral Park. Agricultural programs and exhibitions by the Environmental Protection Agency and the New York City Department of Sanitation are to be on view noon to 5 P.M. tomorrow. Admission is free. Information: (718) 347-3276.</p>
        <p>The offerings at the MUSEUM OF STATEN ISLAND,#75 Stuyvesant Place, in St. George, include local natural-history exhibitions and children's workshops tomorrow and a tree-planting excursion to Evergreen Park in Great Kills on Sunday; the park may be reached by taking the Staten Island Rapid Transit to the Bay Terrace station. The workshops cost $7; the walk is free. Information: (718) 727-1135. Zoos At the CENTRAL PARK ZOO,near Fifth Avenue at 64th Street, classes on conservation issues are to be held, with information on deforestation and illegal trade in endangered animals to be distributed tomorrow and Sunday. Hours are 10 A.M. to 5:30 P.M. Admission is $1; 50 cents for the elderly, 25 cents for children. Information: 439-6500.</p>
        <p>The plight of endangered species is also to be the focus at the BRONX ZOO, at Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road, tomorrow and Sunday and during the next six weekends. This Animals Alive festival is to include a conservation exhibition, a scavenger hunt and a mock cemetery near the Reptile House with mock tombstones for nearly 200 extinct and highly endangered species. Weekend hours are 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission is $4.75; $2 for children. Information: 367-1010.</p>
        <p>Talks about endangered aquatic species and children's workshops are planned from 1 to 5 P.M. on Sunday at the NEW YORK AQUARIUM,West Eighth Street and Surf Avenue in the Coney Island section of Brooklyn. Admission is $4.75; $2 for children. Information: (718) 265-3474. Parks and Gardens Naturally, nature will be the focus of programs in city parks and botanical gardens. Indeed, as the New York City Parks Commissioner, Betsy Gotbaum, said, many Earth Day events are planned in smaller neighborhood parks.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gotbaum is to be at JACKIE ROBINSON PARK,Broadhurst Avenue and 147th Street, tomorrow at 12:30 P.M. to open an afternoon of live music that is to be one of many tree-planting efforts in the city this weekend. Other parks where New Yorkers can join the natural-resources group of the Department of Parks and Recreation from 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. tomorrow include MARINE PARKin the Marine Park section of Brooklyn (information: (718) 965-8958) and HIGH ROCK PARKin Egbertville, S.I. (information: (718) 390-8000). The ALLEY POND ENVIRONMENTAL CENTER,#228-06 Northern Boulevard in Douglaston, Queens, is to lead a park cleanup from 9:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M. on Sunday (information: (718) 229-4000).</p>
        <p>Fairs with an ecological bent are also being offered throughout the city. The NEW YORK BOTANICAL GARDEN,Southern Boulevard and Fordham Road in the Bronx, is to hold its Environmental Fair from noon to 5 P.M. tomorrow and on Sunday, featuring tours of its 40-acre forest, lectures on medicinal plants, tree-planting demonstrations and a concert by a brass quintet. Conservatory admission is $3.50 ($1.25 for children and the elderly); parking is $4. Information: 220-8700.</p>
        <p>WAVE HILL,the tranquil Hudson River-front park at 249th Street and Independence Avenue in the Riverdale section of the Bronx, is to be the setting for several garden walks and a concert of Renaissance music by the Waverly Consort at 3 P.M. on Sunday. Concert tickets bought in advance are $13 and $12.50 for the elderly; tickets cost $1 extra at the door. Garden admission is $2; $1 for students and the elderly. Reservations: 549-3200.</p>
        <p>Also in the Bronx, at ORCHARD BEACH,there are plans for live music, boat rides on Long Island Sound, animals and exhibitions from 10 A.M. to 3 P.M. tomorrow (information: 430-1890). An American Indian band called the Youngbloods, puppeteers and ice-cream makers are to be at CROCHERON PARK,#33d to 35th Avenues and Little Neck Bay in Bayside, Queens, noon to 4:30 P.M. tomorrow. (information: (718) 520-5900 or 520-5932.) Earth Day activities in Brooklyn will be centered on PROSPECT PARK, where there are to be several performances and organized cleanup activities. A free musical program of earth-creation stories, from Genesis to the Bhagavad-Gita, is to be presented by the Prospect Park Environmental Center at the Tennis House at 1 P.M. on Sunday (information: (718) 788-8549).</p>
        <p>While the Urban Park Rangers lead a family-oriented Earth Celebration near the Picnic House from 2 to 5 P.M. on Sunday, the Dharma Swara Balinese Gamelan is to perform inside the Picnic House at 3 P.M.; admission is $5; $2.50 for the elderly. Cleanup outings are scheduled from 10 A.M. to 2 P.M. tomorrow along the lake, and from 10 A.M. to 2 P.M. on Sunday at Lookout Hill (information: (718) 788-0055). And two walking tours are scheduled tomorrow, beginning at Grand Army Plaza: a free tour led by the naturalist John Yrizarry is to be at 2 P.M. and an exploration called ''Art of the Olmstead Landscape'' is to be led by Gail Guillet at 1 P.M. (The cost is $6; $3 for the elderly and children.) Recycling is being encouraged at the BROOKLYN BOTANIC GARDEN,#1000 Washington Avenue in the Crown Heights section, where visitors may exchange cans, bottles and newspapers for plants during a garbage-for-green afternoon on Sunday from 12:30 to 3:45. Information: (718) 622-4433.</p>
        <p>Staten Island's main environmental fair is to be held tomorrow afternoon at Miller Field, a National Park Service property at New Dorp Lane near Hylan Boulevard in the New Dorp section. It is to include information booths, art and a 2 P.M. walk through the Samp White Oak Forest. Information: (718) 351-8700.  The largest neighborhood fair in Manhattan is to be the STUYVESANT PARK FESTIVAL,on Second Avenue between 15th and 17th Streets, where 150 vendors are to share the park with environmental-information displays, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. on Sunday. The rain date is April 29. Information: 684-4077. At the other end of the island, in INWOOD HILL PARK(near Isham Street and 207th Street), children's activities, nature walks, speakers and cleanup programs are planned by the Inwood Heights Parks Alliance from 11 A.M to 3 P.M. on Sunday. Information: 304-0730. And an eco-fair, with all the information one might want to learn on issues like alternative energy, ecologically sound investing and political organizing is to be held from 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. tomorrow at Louis Brandeis High School, 151 West 84th Street. Suggested admission is $5 to $10. Information: 226-7171. Films, Tours and Walks An abundance of educational films, tours and nature walks may also be found this weekend. A free environmental film festival is to be held at the PUBLIC THEATER,#425 Lafayette Street on Sunday. Among the six films are ones on the Brazilian rain forest (2:30 P.M.), the effects of the Chernobyl nuclear-plant disaster on Lapland (at 5 P.M.) and one called ''A Few Notes on Our Food Problem'' (8 P.M.). Information: 598-7171. ''Chico Mendes: Voice of the Amazon,'' a film about the murdered advocate of the Brazilian rain forest, is to be shown with ''Watsonville on Strike'' at the MAY THEATER,#66 Fifth Avenue (at 13th Street), at the New School for Social Research, at 9 P.M. tomorrow. Tickets are $6. Information: 741-5357.  The Audubon Society is conducting eight free nature walks in parks starting at 10 A.M. tomorrow. The two-hour walks include those in CENTRAL PARK(meet at the Loeb Boathouse) and INWOOD HILL PARK(meet at Isham Street and Seaman Avenue) in Manhattan, VAN CORTLANDT PARK (meet at the 242d Street IRT station) in the Bronx, FLOYD BENNETT FIELDin the Marine Park section of Brooklyn (meet at the Ecology Building) and in the JAMAICA BAY WILDLIFE REFUGEin Broad Channel, Queens (meet at refuge headquarters). Information: 691-7483. The marshlands of Jamaica Bay may also be explored in a free sunrise walk at 6 A.M. Sunday, which meets at CROSS BAY BOULEVARDat Broad Channel; reservations: (718) 474-0613.</p>
        <p>The most out-of-the-ordinary tours, however, are to be offered tomorrow from 1 to 3 P.M. by staff members of the New York City Department of Sanitation, who will escort visitors through the EAST HARLEM INTERMEDIATE PROCESSING CENTER,at 225-245 East 127th Street. The tours will provide a chance to see where 80 tons of recyclable metal and glass are processed a day and transformed into products like the so-called glassphalt used to pave city streets. Information: 334-8590.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
