<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Record 85 degrees Gets the Coats Off the Lion and the Lamb</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="334644"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PACE, ERIC</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED71F3DF937A25750C0A966958260" item-length="1210" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Record 85 degrees Gets the Coats Off the Lion and the Lamb</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC PACE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PACE, ERIC</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A subway station guitarist took his act joyously above ground to Battery Park. A woman from East Harlem forsook her soap opera to frolic outside with her grandson. A videomaker from Tribeca basked in the sun - but brooded about global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A subway station guitarist took his act joyously above ground to Battery Park. A woman from East Harlem forsook her soap opera to frolic outside with her grandson. A videomaker from Tribeca basked in the sun - but brooded about global warming.</p>
        <p>A subway station guitarist took his act joyously above ground to Battery Park. A woman from East Harlem forsook her soap opera to frolic outside with her grandson. A videomaker from Tribeca basked in the sun - but brooded about global warming.</p>
        <p>In myriad ways, life in the New York metropolitan area seemed to burst from its winter cocoon yesterday as the temperature fluttered upward to a record 85 degrees by 3 P.M. That was 15 degrees more than the all-time record set in 1929 and fully 38 degrees above normal for the date. And elsewhere across much of the East, record high temperatures in the 70's and 80's made yesterday feel like June. The National Weather Service reported record temperatures in Baltimore, Boston, Cleveland, Hartford and Washington. High temperatures were also logged in the Middle West. But not everything was balmy. Thunderstorms surged across Illinois and the southern Great Plains, spawning tornadoes that swept across south-central Kansas, where two people were killed and 14 others injured.</p>
        <p>''New York City feels like it's opened up today,'' said Ricardo V. Smith, a real-estate developer from the Flatbush section of Brooklyn, as he strolled City Hall Park in a sweatshirt of verdant green.</p>
        <p>The city and the suburbs seemed fresh, brightened, humanized, under a dappling of eastbound clouds. Al fresco bagel-eaters abounded. A blur of bicycles added other pastels to Central Park's fledgling green.</p>
        <p>'Take the Baby Outdoors'</p>
        <p>The streets seemed noisier as cars zipped by with their radios blaring salsa and whatnot through wide-open windows. And not a few New Yorkers confessed that they were taking the day off, more or less unofficially.</p>
        <p>Down at Battery Park, Luke Ryan, the guitar-player, grinned through his beard. ''It's like magic,'' he said. ''I'm out here in the sunshine - instead of playing in the BMT.''</p>
        <p>In East Harlem, Jacqueline Badger, a member of the tenant association at the George Washington Houses, said: ''It's just too beautiful today. I didn't even see my soap opera. I said to myself, 'No, take the baby outdoors.' ''</p>
        <p>And so Mrs. Badger skipped watching ''One Life to Live'' and took her 15-month-old grandson Joshua to romp on the pavement outside the project's community center.</p>
        <p>''The weather is so uncertain,'' she said philosophically, ''we better enjoy it.''</p>
        <p>Also relishing the weather, on a park bench outside City Hall, Kate Horsfield of Tribeca said the change in the weather was ''almost like a Broadway musical.''</p>
        <p>''Everybody starts dancing to a different rhythm,'' Ms. Horsfield, a distributor of videos, said. ''It's like they throw off all the burdens of winter. It's like they're energized.''</p>
        <p>''There's only two months 'til we appear on the beach,'' she added.</p>
        <p>But her loftmate, Ellen Spiro, broke in, saying ''With all the syringes that are going to wash up on the beach this summer, you got to look good?''</p>
        <p>Ms. Spiro, a video-maker with strong views on the environment, said, ''I always feel confused when I feel good in the unusually warm weather we're having nowadays, because I know it's related to the greenhouse effect.''</p>
        <p>Lee Grenci, a meteorologist at the Pennsylvania State University, said the heat came from the combination of high barometric pressure off the Southeast coast of the United States and upper-atmosphere winds east of the storms in the Great Plains.</p>
        <p>The Associated Press reported that the heaviest storm damage came in the south Kansas town of Hesston, where a boy was killed, 14 were hurt and more than 100 homes were severely damaged. Another fatality was reported in a nearby town.</p>
        <p>A Giant Heat Pump</p>
        <p>The high-pressure system, Mr. Grenci said, ''goes from the surface of the earth up to 30,000 feet, and it acts like a heat pump, drawing warm, moist air northward from the Gulf of Mexico.''</p>
        <p>The Great Plains storm system, he said, ''is wreaking havoc by spawning severe thunderstorms and tornadoes, and behind this storm system - to the west of it - is cold air.''</p>
        <p>''Now ahead of the storm system -to the East - the winds in the upper atmosphere are from the south, and these southerly winds impede the eastward advance of the cold air,'' he explained.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grenci predicted that temperatures would be only in the 60's in New York City today, and even lower farther north. They should reach the 70's in the western suburbs - and the weather will be humid.</p>
        <p>Even without having heard the forecast, Mr. Smith, who buys buildings from the city and fixes them up, said, ''It's nice, but let's be realistic - it could change.''</p>
        <p>Snow Leopards Hibernate</p>
        <p>At the Bronx Zoo, the snow leopards were sleeping on shady rocks, oblivious. ''With weather changes like this, they're going to take it easy, just like we do,'' said Michael Hutchins, coordinator of research at the Zoo.</p>
        <p>To the south, speeding toward the Financial District on the Broadway-Seventh Avenue IRT, Glenn Harrison, a blue-suited accountant from Yorkville, said of the weather: ''I love it. It puts people in the mood for love and respect - and I think we need more of that, especially in New York.''</p>
        <p>In the suburbs, the warm weather spread good feelings. Across Long Island, thousands of sunseekers basked at parks and beaches. At Jones Beach State Park, officials reported more than 25,000 people turned out to stroll the boardwalk, play touch football, fly kites or just pull up a beach chair.</p>
        <p>In Westchester County, jackets were shed, ties loosened, convertible tops lowered and ice cream cones quickly consumed as the temparature climbed. In New Jersey, some residents voiced mixed feelings, perhaps because they had been shoveling snow off their driveways only last Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The Sweat of Inspiration</p>
        <p>''It's wonderful, but this is no weather for this time of year,'' said Elisco Pretto of Bloomfield, N.J. ''People will get sick.''</p>
        <p>Some had special reasons for greeting the heat. Mickey Friedman, a Greenwich Village author of whodunits and suspense novels, said it was ''extremely inspirational.''</p>
        <p>''As a mystery writer, I write about trickles of perspiration breaking out and mists of perspiration on the upper lip and things like that, because my characters are tense a great deal of time,'' she explained. ''When there's snow on the ground, it's hard to remember what it's like to break out into a sweat - but this weather makes me remember.''</p>
        <p>But some rued the warmth. John R. Tobiason, a burly lawyer who lives in Washington Heights, mistakenly wore a wool winter suit and worked up an unseemly sweat for court at 60 Centre Street.</p>
        <p>''People look at me, disheveled like this,'' he lamented, with his shirt open and tie at half-staff. But he said that, as things turned out, his un-cool appearance wasn't a problem, because ''my adversary didn't show up and we adjourned the case for the day.''</p>
        <p>Also rueful was Tony Anzalone of Oceanside L.I., whose forehead was glazed with sweat as he chiseled the blacktop of West 43d Street with his jackhammer on behalf of a subsidiary of the New York Telephone Company.</p>
        <p>''I didn't know it was going to be so hot,'' he said, ''I got too much clothes on.''</p>
        <p>Yet his foreman, who would not give his name, looked on happily, hands in his pockets, and said, ''The men work better when they sweat a little bit.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
