<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Efforts to Halt Wetland Loss Turn Their Attention Inland</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="334392"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WETLANDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAND USE POLICIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOODS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wetlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900313T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D8103BF930A25750C0A966958260" item-length="1888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Efforts to Halt Wetland Loss Turn Their Attention Inland</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A new and contentious phase has opened in the struggle over the future of the millions of acres of marshes, swamps, bogs, prairie potholes and bottom lands that not only provide an irreplaceable habitat for wildlife but also help replenish the nation's water supplies and control its floods.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A new and contentious phase has opened in the struggle over the future of the millions of acres of marshes, swamps, bogs, prairie potholes and bottom lands that not only provide an irreplaceable habitat for wildlife but also help replenish the nation's water supplies and control its floods.</p>
        <p>A new and contentious phase has opened in the struggle over the future of the millions of acres of marshes, swamps, bogs, prairie potholes and bottom lands that not only provide an irreplaceable habitat for wildlife but also help replenish the nation's water supplies and control its floods.</p>
        <p>Despite longtime efforts by the Federal Government to arrest the steady shrinkage of this natural resource, an estimated 200,000 to 400,000 acres of wetlands continue to vanish each year, most in freshwater drainages in inland areas, where 95 percent of all wetlands lie. Largely untouched by Federal and state regulatory efforts, millions of acres of these freshwater wetlands have disappeared since the mid-1950's, overwhelmingly because farmers converted them to cropland.</p>
        <p>Efforts to preserve wetlands have focused mainly on coastal areas, but now environmentalists, politicians and regulators are engaged in a campaign to control the attrition of inland wetlands for the first time and ultimately to reverse it. They have declared their near-term objective to be no net loss of wetlands.</p>
        <p>Under the no-net-loss principle, conversion of wetlands would be permitted only if the user restored previously converted wetlands or created new ones. President Bush has embraced it, and two Federal agencies and some state governments are requiring it. Congress is holding hearings about whether it should be Federal law.</p>
        <p>But despite widespread acceptance of the basic principle, early attempts to put it into practice have encountered stiff and angry resistance. It comes especially from farmers who see regulatory efforts as a confiscation of their assets. ''I bought my farm, and if the Government wants it, they should acquire it the good old American way -buy it,'' Rick McGown, a Missouri farmer, said in handwritten testimony that he presented to Congress two weeks ago.</p>
        <p>And on Maryland's Eastern Shore, where most non-tidal wetlands lie on farms and the issue has become especially heated, enforcement of the no-net-loss policy has discouraged banks from lending money to farmers because of the uncertain status of their lands. It has also stopped development by preventing farmers from selling excess lands to developers, a move many had counted on to provide for their retirement.</p>
        <p>''The farmers are very upset,'' said Samuel Q. Johnson, an Eastern Shore legislator who is a member of the Maryland House of Delegates' committee on the environment. ''And not only the farmer. This thing is spreading to the banking community, to the real estate community. I know people who have been turned down on loans for land. It has nothing at all to do with their credit or ability to pay. It is simply the unknown factor about whether this was non-tidal wetlands.''</p>
        <p>Two real-estate developments worth $22 million together have shut down because of uncertainty over the situation, he said.</p>
        <p>Most non-tidal wetlands are on private property, and as the wetlands debate heats up, policy-makers are searching for ways to head off conflict and confrontation, allay concern and safeguard both public and private interests while making the no-net-loss principle a reality. Proposals are emerging in Congress, for instance, to offer tax incentives for wetlands conservation and even to pay farmers to reconvert land, which could then be placed in a wetlands conservation bank.</p>
        <p>Underlying the action and argument is a shift in perception about wetlands. Through most of American history, they have been considered wastelands to be eliminated and converted to productive use. ''For a long time, we regarded swamps as sources of pestilence that should be filled in as quickly as possible,'' says James Leape, a wetlands expert at the Conservation Foundation, a Washington-based organization that sponsored an influential national study of wetlands loss.</p>
        <p>Study Shapes New Debate</p>
        <p>The study was carried out by the National Wetlands Policy Forum, a broadly based group that included environmentalists, industrialists, government officials, developers and farmers. Its report, issued in late 1988, first proposed the no-net-loss goal. The report has largely shaped the renewed argument and is the focus of the Congressional hearings.</p>
        <p>Wetlands today are seen increasingly not as nuisances, but as an invaluable resource. Scientists say that they protect shorelines from erosion by ocean waves and storms and reduce the severity of inland floods by slowing and storing flood waters. They remove pollution from waters that flow through them and recharge underground aquifers. They store water in the wettest parts of the year and release it at a constant rate to maintain regular stream flows.</p>
        <p>They provide critical breeding and nesting habitats for a wide array of fish and wildlife, including migratory waterfowl. They support many commercial fisheries, provide an array of commercial products from cranberries and timber to fish and shellfish and offer widespread opportunities for hunting, fishing, boating, nature study and photography. And because of the gases they emit and absorb, like methane, nitrogen and carbon dioxide, they help maintain the planet's atmospheric balance.</p>
        <p>From Marshes to Tundra</p>
        <p>Wetlands include marshes extending across thousands of acres to wet spots smaller than a room and from the vast Okefenokee Swamp in Georgia to the squishy borders of inland rivers and lakes. They include not only Alaskan tundra but also the Everglades and the bottom lands of the Mississippi Delta.</p>
        <p>Ecologically speaking, the loss of wetlands can be disastrous. In one example, the conversion of prairie potholes of the upper Midwest to agricultural use has been ''extremely devastating'' to certain species of ducks, said Joseph S. Larson, an expert on wetlands who is the chairman of the department of forestry and wildlife at the University of Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>The potholes, large depressions in the prairie created when huge chunks of ice were buried in the last ice age and then melted, are the nesting grounds for ''probably 80 percent of the ducks in North America,'' said Dr. Larson. But so many of the potholes have been converted from wetlands to wheat fields, he said, that there has been a tremendous loss of habitat, and species like the redhead and canvasback ducks are in serious decline as a result.</p>
        <p>In addition, a number of communities have experienced serious flooding after wetlands were drained and replaced by streets, parking lots and other surfaces that allow water to run off more freely.</p>
        <p>Of more than 200 million acres of wetlands that existed in the contiguous 48 states when Europeans arrived in North America, an estimated 95 million remain, according to the Environmental Protection Agency. They are found across the country but are concentrated especially in the Southeast, the upper Midwest and the Northeastern coastal states. Another 200 million acres remain in Alaska in the form of tundra, which is frozen wetland.</p>
        <p>Government studies by the Fish and Wildlife Service have calculated that from the mid-1950's to the mid-1970's, 11 million acres of wetlands vanished, a net loss of about 550,000 acres a year, in the contiguous 48 states. About 80 percent of the loss resulted from the draining and clearing of inland wetlands by farmers. The remainder was attributed to such activities as urban and suburban development, which accounted for about 6 percent, dredging, mining and the discharge of pollution. Natural phenomena like erosion, storms and subsidence accounted for about 5 percent of the loss.</p>
        <p>Losses Are Being Disputed</p>
        <p>How much additional loss has occurred in the last 15 years is a matter of sharp contention. The Congressional Office of Technology Assessment estimated in 1984 that the rate was about 240,000 to 360,000 acres a year.</p>
        <p>Whatever the scope of the problem, spokesmen for farmers and developers minimize their constituents' contribution to it. ''I don't think agriculture has played that much of a part'' in the last 10 years, said Mark Maslyn, an official of the American Farm Bureau Federation, who took part in the Wetlands Policy Forum study. ''I think that was just a time and point in history that passed.''</p>
        <p>Losing Wetlands by Increments</p>
        <p>But environmentalists and some government officials insist that interests like agriculture and real estate are responsible for the continuing attrition. ''We're losing wetlands by small increments,'' says Hope Babcock, general counsel for the National Audubon Society, who also took part in the Wetlands Policy Forum study, ''and when you start nibbling away, pretty soon you're destroying a whole ecosystem.''</p>
        <p>Last month, the struggle over the issued sharpened as the no-net-loss principle was incorporated into an agreement between the Environmental Protection Agency and the Army Corps of Engineers over the enforcement of wetlands protection under Section 404 of the Clean Water Act. This section, which regulates the filling of wetlands, is considered by environmentalists the most important tool available for controlling wetlands loss.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists say that the authority of the Corps of Engineers in some ways does not extend far enough because it does not apply to the excavation, clearing or draining of wetlands. Such activities are responsible for most wetlands loss, especially inland. While coastal wetlands are reasonably well protected, said the 1984 report by the technology assessment office, freshwater wetlands away from the coasts ''are generally poorly protected.''</p>
        <p>In an attempt to help plug this gap, Congress in 1985 prohibited farmers from growing crops on any tracts converted from wetlands after that year. If they do, they are supposed to lose all their Federal farm program benefits, including subsidized loans, crop insurance and price supports.</p>
        <p>A number of states are embracing the no-net-loss principle and expanding it beyond filling-in of wetlands. Maryland has adopted one of the most far-reaching state laws incorporating the no-net-loss principle, and the Legislature is in a hot battle about approving the new regulations to complete the law. Gov. Mario M. Cuomo of New York has espoused no net loss. Among states besides Maryland that have enacted the principle into law is New Jersey, and other states, including Washington and South Carolina, are considering it.</p>
        <p>Looking to Economic Solutions</p>
        <p>In the end, many conservationists and officials are convinced, wetlands protection will have to look beyond regulation to economic solutions. ''It's unrealstic to expect private land owners to do what's good for society just out of the goodness of their hearts,'' said Ralph Heimlich, an analyst in the Economic Research Service of the Agriculture Department who has studied the wetlands issue extensively.</p>
        <p>Outright purchases of land for a wetlands conservation bank is one strategy being pursued in Florida, where officials plan to buy and restore more than 100,000 acres of freshwater marshland that were drained and converted into orange groves and truck farms.</p>
        <p>Other strategies being proposed involve economic aid for not developing or otherwise converting ecologically important wetlands, as well as tax breaks for donating them to a conservation reserve.</p>
        <p>''You have to begin to tilt the economic playing field,'' said Ms. Babcock.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
