<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Overboard on Ozone</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="352481"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUNUNU, JOHN H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DARMAN, RICHARD G (DIR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DF1231F932A25756C0A966958260" item-length="465" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Overboard on Ozone</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Every President needs a Darth Vader in the White House to thwart special pleaders and scrutinize even apple-pie issues. President Bush's chief of staff, John Sununu, and Budget Director, Richard Darman, have played this role zestfully in curbing what they see as excessive solicitude for the environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Every President needs a Darth Vader in the White House to thwart special pleaders and scrutinize even apple-pie issues. President Bush's chief of staff, John Sununu, and Budget Director, Richard Darman, have played this role zestfully in curbing what they see as excessive solicitude for the environment.</p>
        <p>Every President needs a Darth Vader in the White House to thwart special pleaders and scrutinize even apple-pie issues. President Bush's chief of staff, John Sununu, and Budget Director, Richard Darman, have played this role zestfully in curbing what they see as excessive solicitude for the environment. But in their latest foray, an assault on the international effort to protect the ozone layer, they have simply abandoned all sense of proportion and judgment.</p>
        <p>The U.S. persuaded the world to reach agreement on phasing out production of CFC's, a class of industrial chemicals that destroy the life-protecting layer of ozone in the upper atmosphere. Many developing countries that signed the Montreal protocol of 1987 asked for help in converting to the more costly substitutes, and Washington agreed in principle to provide it.</p>
        <p>An international group in Geneva has been working out the details, and proposed setting up a fund to which the U.S. would contribute around $20 million a year. The State Department and Environmental Protection Agency urged the Administration to support the proposal. But Mr. Darman and Mr. Sununu have now instructed that it be opposed.</p>
        <p>This is not an intelligent decision, for the following reasons: There is only one ozone layer, and there are a lot of people in India and China. It's in America's own interest for these and other developing economies to abandon CFC's as soon as possible. If the price tag is only $20 million, it's a bargain, particularly as the Treasury is reaping windfall profit taxes of $5 billion from the CFC industry as it phases down. The considerable damage already done to the ozone layer has been caused by CFC's manufactured in the United States. It's not too much to ask that Americans help less-developed countries avoid the same error. Every speaker from other countries at the Geneva conference expressed dismay at the U.S. stand. It's glorious to stand alone against the world when one is right, less so to cling to a position that puts the U.S. in the doghouse of world opinion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sununu and Mr. Darman are said to fear that modest help on CFC's now would lead to greater demands later if the world agrees to take action against the gases of global warming. But that's an issue for the future, to be dealt with on its merits. The threat to the ozone layer, and all living things on the planet, is present and real.</p>
        <p>A Secretary of the Interior in the Reagan Administration once suggested that the way to solve the ozone problem was to continue producing CFC's but let people buy sunglasses and sunscreen lotion to protect against the bath of ultraviolet rays. Mr. Bush risks gaining a reputation for equal profundity unless he quickly instructs Messrs. Darman and Sununu to quit trifling with serious issues.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
