<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Upheaval in the East: Romania;   Through a Thick Veil of Soot, Romanian City Faces Future</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="332109"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEALTH, PERSONAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ROMANIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">COPSA MICA (ROMANIA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOHLEN, CELESTINE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900305T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD91F30F936A35750C0A966958260" item-length="1111" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Upheaval in the East: Romania;   Through a Thick Veil of Soot, Romanian City Faces Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELESTINE BOHLEN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BOHLEN, CELESTINE</byline>
      <dateline>COPSA MICA, Romania, March 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: For about 15 miles around, every growing thing in this once-gentle valley looks as if it has been dipped in ink. Trees and bushes are black; the grass is stained. The houses and streets look like the inside of a chimney. Even the sheep on the hillsides are a dingy gray.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: For about 15 miles around, every growing thing in this once-gentle valley looks as if it has been dipped in ink. Trees and bushes are black; the grass is stained. The houses and streets look like the inside of a chimney. Even the sheep on the hillsides are a dingy gray.</p>
        <p>For about 15 miles around, every growing thing in this once-gentle valley looks as if it has been dipped in ink. Trees and bushes are black; the grass is stained. The houses and streets look like the inside of a chimney. Even the sheep on the hillsides are a dingy gray.</p>
        <p>There are two factories here. One makes black powder used in the manufacture of rubber. The other produces zinc, lead, copper, cadmium and other nonferrous metals. Together they spew out 30,000 tons of particles and soot each year, leaving Copsa Mica, with about 6,000 people, one of the most polluted places in all of Europe.</p>
        <p>The black powder is only the most visible pollutant. For those working in the metals factory, there is the constant stench and taste of sulfuric acid. But the more significant danger comes from the invisible pollution -high levels of lead and an undetermined threat from the stew of toxic compounds in the air.</p>
        <p>The soot and filth afflicting this quiet region 200 miles northwest of Bucharest are not new to Eastern Europe, just an extreme case. There was little chance to speak out against pollution and environmental health hazards during the long years of Communist control. And unlike the case in the West, where pollution and acid rain pose a similar threat, there is little ecological movement to speak of here.</p>
        <p>Hoping to Clean Things Up</p>
        <p>Romania and other Eastern bloc nations now hope to clean things up. But the cost of such efforts could place a serious burden on the economies of Middle Europe, which are trying with great difficulty to gain a sound footing as Communism recedes.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, the pollution and its fallout grow worse.</p>
        <p>Dr. Alexandru Balin, 38 years old, has been working for 13 years in the occuptional heath clinic connected to the metals factory at Copsa Mica (pronounced COPE-shah MEE-kah). He has watched as the workers' health deteriorated dramaticlly.</p>
        <p>In 1977, 70 people had been diagnosed with excessive or dangerous levels of lead in their bodies; today, there are more than 400. More than half of those working in the metals factory have above-normal levels.</p>
        <p>Lead poisoning produces different symptoms, of which the most common are nervousness and anemia. The side effects are temporary paralysis, rheumatism-like symptoms, acute abdominal pains, respiratory problems and rare cases of encephalitis.</p>
        <p>Long-Term Effects Unknown</p>
        <p>Long-term effects are unknown, doctors say, because comprehensive studies are lacking and workers disappear from the clinic's charts after retirement at age 50.</p>
        <p>Still, in 1985, Dr. Balin compiled a detailed report on the alarming situation, and he knows that the study landed on the desk of Nicolae Ceausescu, the Romanian leader who was deposed and executed in December.</p>
        <p>Two things happened as a result. The factory got the money to build a 750-foot tower that now sends the sulfuric emissions wafting in the direction of nearby mountain villages. And Dr. Balin was once again called to the offices of the Securitate, the secret police that has since been disbanded, and asked why he was making so much trouble.</p>
        <p>Before the Romanian revolution in December, Copsa Mica was generally shielded from foreign eyes. The metals factory, considered crucial to the Romanian economy, produced for the domestic market only. In the late 1970's, a Japanese company came to bid on a contract to install filters at the powder factory, but the contract was later withdrawn because it was considered too expensive.</p>
        <p>''Nobody knew about us,'' Dr. Balin said. ''Now people come, and they say we are the most polluted town in the world.''</p>
        <p>Cut off from the outside world, Dr. Balin and the other doctors did what they could to keep up with medical science and with the latest theories on treatment for lead poisoning. But they did not need foreign textbooks to know that the best prevention was to reduce exposure. At a similar factory in West Germany, Dr. Balin said, workers are given three' years pay for a maximum of two years' work.</p>
        <p>''Man is the most idiotic animal,'' he said. ''Horses can stay here only two years. Then they must be sold and sent to the mountains, or else they die.''</p>
        <p>Dirt as a Part of Life</p>
        <p>Ioan Zaharie, who worked at the factory for 17 years, visited the clinic last week for backaches, a recurring problem. He is the only one in his family to work in Copsa Mica, although the pay here is more than double the national average.</p>
        <p>''One in the family is enough,'' said Mr. Zaharie, 47 years old, who remembers when flowers still grew in Copsa Mica. But like many who live in the area, Mr. Zaharie sees the dirt as part of life, much like other miseries common to the Ceausescu era.</p>
        <p>The health problems that Dr. Balin and his colleagues have chronicled are not just caused by pollution. Hepatitis-B and tuberculosis are common in Copsa Mica; so is alcoholism. Hot water was not available in many apartments until recently. and many older houses have no indoor plumbing. Food supplies were marginally better here than elsewhere, but the difference, Dr. Balin said, was between getting salami eight times a year, or three.</p>
        <p>''I would say to them, you must eat and not drink,'' asid Dr. Balin. ''And they would ask me where to find something to eat. I would say, you must wash more often, and they would say, where to find the soap. When you have money, you have civilization; when you don't, you don't.''</p>
        <p>Now the Romanians are scrambling to make up for lost time. A new independent trade union visited Bucharest in January to wring promises of higher pay and more safety equipment from the new Government. Last week, half of the metals factory was closed for repairs, and plans call for it to be rebuilt from the ground up.</p>
        <p>Challenge Is Restoring Health</p>
        <p>But Dr. Balin, who since Dec. 22 has accumulated new duties as a member of the town council and an adviser to the union and to local ecologists, said that restoring people's health would be more complicated.</p>
        <p>''We still don't know how all these compounds react together,'' he said. ''There is no city in the world with all these toxics, and since we can't make tests, we still don't know.''</p>
        <p>The damage is not restricted to the working population. Dr. Balin quoted one report that showed children in Copsa Mica testing more than 5 percent below average on intelligence tests.</p>
        <p>In the region, hospitals have reported a striking increase in the number of babies born with malformed hearts: 16 were reported in 1988, Dr. Balin said, compared with five in 1977 to 1983. Bronchial asthma and other respiratory illnesses are common among children, according to Dr. Ute Deutschlander, the local pediatrician.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
