<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Many Crash as Roads Become Rinks in Sudden Morning Cold Snap</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="51" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="408852"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROADS AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HEVESI, DENNIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DF1F3DF935A25751C1A966958260" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Many Crash as Roads Become Rinks in Sudden Morning Cold Snap</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNIS HEVESI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HEVESI, DENNIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sudden formations of ice sheets turned roads into billiard tables yesterday morning, causing cars and trucks to bang into and bounce off each other in multi-vehicle fender-benders across Westchester County and northern New Jersey and into the Southern Tier of New York, the police reported.</p>
        <p>There were no serious injuries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sudden formations of ice sheets turned roads into billiard tables yesterday morning, causing cars and trucks to bang into and bounce off each other in multi-vehicle fender-benders across Westchester County and northern New Jersey and into the Southern Tier of New York, the police reported.</p>
        <p>There were no serious injuries.</p>
        <p>Twenty-five cars plowed into each other on one side of Route 3 in East Rutherford, N.J. Minutes later, two five-car pileups occurred directly on the other side of the same highway.</p>
        <p>Seventeen cars were involved in a chain-reaction accident in Waldwick, N.J., while 20 cars slammed into each other in Harrison, N.Y. And in Chemung, N.Y., along the Pennsylvania border, a chartered bus full of people visiting relatives in the state prison in Elmira slid off a road, injuring 28 of them.</p>
        <p>"The roads iced right up with a fine, misty rain, then it turned to hail and heavy snow," The Associated Press quoted a New York State trooper as saying about the accident in Chemung, which involved a bus chartered from the Cambridge Bus Company that had left New York City early in the morning.</p>
        <p>The police later said a driver under the influence of alcohol in a Jeep in front of the bus had skidded out of control while speeding. The bus bounced off the car and through a guard rail. Sharp Temperature Difference</p>
        <p>All of those accidents, as well as numerous other one-, two- and three-car mishaps, occurred between 9 and 10:30 A.M.</p>
        <p>Bob Stalker, a meteorologist with the National Weather Service at Rockefeller Center in Manhattan, said the big freeze ran along a line north and west of New York City that contrasted with far more moderate readings to the south and east.</p>
        <p>"You've got a big range of temperatures," Mr. Stalker said yesterday. "There's a warm front hanging along the coast right now, with temperatures around 45 to 50 degrees. The colder air is north and west.</p>
        <p>"Roads are completely iced over," he continued. "We're getting reports about it all the time; from Bergen County, Morris, Passaic, Sussex, Warren" in New Jersey. And in New York, he said, "There are reports of freezing roadways up in Rockland and Westchester."</p>
        <p>A Westchester County police communications officer, Nick Autorino, said "seven, eight or nine cars were involved" in an accident on the Saw Mill River Parkway near Tuckahoe Road.</p>
        <p>At the New York State police barracks in Hawthorne, Trooper Leon Williams said there had been a 20-car pileup where Interstate Highways 287 and 684 meet in Harrison.  'A 25-Car Hit on Route 3'</p>
        <p>A police dispatcher in Passaic County said there had been a five-car accident on Route 21, between exits 10 and 11, and a three-car accident, also on Route 21, near the Van Houten Street overpass in the city of Passaic.</p>
        <p>A Bergen County police sergeant, Scott Storms, said, "Besides numerous fender-benders, we had a 25-car hit on Route 3 westbound at the Hackensack Bridge. There were approximately 10 minor injuries and seven to eight vehicles towed from there." That accident was reported at 9:02 A.M.</p>
        <p>Minutes later, there were "two five-car hits on the eastbound side," Sergeant Storms said.</p>
        <p>An East Rutherford police spokesman, Officer Richard Freeman, said: "The bridge was a sheet of ice when I got there. There were eight or nine cars moved over to the right shoulder; other cars were still either up against the bridge abutment or one another. One car was pretty banged up, all the windows knocked out of it."</p>
        <p>Then, about 10 A.M., Sergeant Storms said, 17 cars ran into each other on Route 17 in Waldwick. And other multi-vehicle accidents occurred in Fair Lawn and Glen Rock. "We've got them all over the place," he said.</p>
        <p>In Clay, N.Y., a suburb of Syracuse, a Santa Claus on his way to surprise children at a Fire Department Christmas party crashed through the wall in a fire truck, sending cinderblocks flying and terrifying the children.</p>
        <p>Eleven people were injured, two of them seriously. The fire truck's driver told authorities that the gas pedal stuck.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
