<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="344775"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DC123FF93BA25757C0A966958260" item-length="583" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>THE ECONOMY</p>
        <p>Consumer prices climbed by 0.5 percent in March to make the annual inflation rate 8.5 percent for the first three months of 1990, the most rapid quarterly increase in nearly eight years, the Labor Department reported. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Sales of domestically produced cars and light trucks fell by 11.3 percent in early April.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>THE ECONOMY</p>
        <p>Consumer prices climbed by 0.5 percent in March to make the annual inflation rate 8.5 percent for the first three months of 1990, the most rapid quarterly increase in nearly eight years, the Labor Department reported. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Sales of domestically produced cars and light trucks fell by 11.3 percent in early April.</p>
        <p>THE ECONOMY</p>
        <p>Consumer prices climbed by 0.5 percent in March to make the annual inflation rate 8.5 percent for the first three months of 1990, the most rapid quarterly increase in nearly eight years, the Labor Department reported. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Sales of domestically produced cars and light trucks fell by 11.3 percent in early April. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Industrial production rose by 0.7 percent in March, the Fed reported, in a second consecutive strong showing that led analysts to suggest that the manufacturing recession may have ended. [D4.]</p>
        <p>Housing starts continued to fall in March from their January peak, the Commerce Department reported. [D4.]</p>
        <p>COMPANIES</p>
        <p>Citicorp earnings fell 56.3 percent because of bad loans. Earnings were up at Wells Fargo and NCNB. [D1.]</p>
        <p>Eastern's creditors and management presented sharply different views of a trustee running the airline. [D3.]</p>
        <p>McDonald's will buy recycled materials worth up to $100 million for building and remodeling its restaurants. [D14.]</p>
        <p>Four of the nation's 10 largest local telephone companies reported modest increases in sales and profits. [D3.]  United Telecom will become the Sprint Corporation. [D3.]</p>
        <p>Great American Bank sharply increased its estimate of losses from soured loans, making it a likely candidate for seizure. [D15.]</p>
        <p>The abrupt replacement of National Geographic's editor appears likely to alter the magazine's course. [D17.]</p>
        <p>Paine Webber reported a 17.4 percent profit rise, but the gains came against a weak quarter a year earlier on Wall Street. [D19.]</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>Deutsche Bank announced a joint venture to give it control over roughly a third of the banking network in East Germany. [D1.]</p>
        <p>The Justice Department froze hundreds of U.S. bank accounts suspected of having been used to hide nearly $400 million in Colombian drug profits. [D1.]</p>
        <p>BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY</p>
        <p>Most Americans will not see new less-polluting gasolines at local pumps for at least three years because of a shortage of a crucial additive. [D1.]</p>
        <p>Digital Equipment has developed a system for cleaning electrical equipment that will help the ozone layer. [D5.]</p>
        <p>MARKETS</p>
        <p>A former stock speculator was sentenced to four months in prison and fined $1 million for insider trading, closing the Government's most difficult Wall Street corruption case. [D1.]</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. censured Donaldson, Lufkin and suspended one of its managing directors for 45 days for the alleged, systematic misuse of securities belonging to customers for the firm's own profit. [D1.]</p>
        <p>The Dow, after dropping 21 points, fought back steadily for a gain of 2.71, to 2,765.77. [D6.]</p>
        <p>The bond market was rocked by the consumer price report, and prices of Treasury securities tumbled in heavy trading. [D12.]</p>
        <p>Two influential OPEC ministers reportedly agreed to reduce production to try to restore oil prices to their benchmark level of $18 a barrel. [D13.]  The dollar ended lower. [D13.]</p>
        <p>TODAY'S COLUMNS</p>
        <p>In the U.S.-Japanese trade drama, narrowing the gap between savings and investment might make a difference. Peter Passell: Economic Scene. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Buyout fever is about to sweep Europe - that, at least, is the hope of a number of new funds. Market Place. [D6.]</p>
        <p>The 1990's may turn out to be the age of ''melding,'' one advertising analyst says. Randall Rothenberg: Advertising. [D17.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
