<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BOOKS FOR VACATION READING</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="360283"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D71531F933A25755C0A966958260" item-length="7142" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BOOKS FOR VACATION READING</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: This list has been selected from books reviewed since the Christmas issue of December 1989. It only suggests high points in the main fields of reader interest. Books are arranged alphabetically under subject headings.</p>
        <p>Autobiography and Biography</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: This list has been selected from books reviewed since the Christmas issue of December 1989. It only suggests high points in the main fields of reader interest. Books are arranged alphabetically under subject headings.</p>
        <p>Autobiography and Biography</p>
        <p>This list has been selected from books reviewed since the Christmas issue of December 1989. It only suggests high points in the main fields of reader interest. Books are arranged alphabetically under subject headings.</p>
        <p>Autobiography and Biography</p>
        <p>AGAINST THE GRAIN: An Autobiography. By Boris Yeltsin. (Summit, $19.95.) This provocative book gives voice to the Russian-style populism and antiparty insurgency of its author, the most visible leader of the opposition to Mikhail S. Gorbachev.</p>
        <p>AMELIA EARHART: A Biography. By Doris L. Rich. (Smithsonian Institution, $19.95.) THE SOUND OF WINGS: The Life of Amelia Earhart, by Mary S. Lovell. (St. Martin's, $22.95.) Two biographies of the famous American pilot (and feminist) who vanished in the South Pacific in 1937. The authors agree on the important facts; Ms. Lovell is more skeptical about her flying skills than Ms. Rich, and thinks better of her husband and publicist, G. P. Putnam.</p>
        <p>BECOMING A POET: Elizabeth Bishop With Marianne Moore and Robert Lowell. By David Kalstone. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $22.50.) The fullest account so far of Bishop's life, David Kalstone's presentation approaches her creative activity through her close friendships with two other major poets.</p>
        <p>THE BOY-MAN: The Life of Lord Baden-Powell. By Tim Jeal. (Morrow, $24.95.) A monumental (670 pages) biography of the founder of Scouting, doing full justice to the complexities of the man and the contradictions in the movement he fathered.</p>
        <p>CAPTAIN SIR RICHARD FRANCIS BURTON: The Secret Agent Who Made the Pilgrimage to Mecca, Discovered the Kama Sutra, and Brought the Arabian Nights to the West. By Edward Rice. (Scribners, $35.) This life of the 19th-century explorer and sage is a first-class account of a strange and remarkable career.</p>
        <p>C. S. LEWIS: A Biography. By A. N. Wilson. (Norton, $22.50.) A skilled novelist and biographer (of Tolstoy) brilliantly and sympathetically demythologizes one of the most tendentiously written-about British authors of the 20th century.</p>
        <p>DADDY, WE HARDLY KNEW YOU. By Germaine Greer. (Knopf, $19.95.) Ms. Greer's enormous digressions and rambles are as entertaining as the principal action in this account of her quest to learn the origins of her own father, a man who, she finds, never knew his birth name or parents and lied about what little he knew.</p>
        <p>EVERY GOOD-BYE AIN'T GONE: Family Portraits and Personal Escapades. By Itabari Njeri. (Times Books/Random House, $17.95.) An impassioned, skillful, frankly subjective attempt to explore and expose the depth of a black American family heritage.</p>
        <p>A HIGHER KIND OF LOYALTY: A Memoir by China's Foremost Journalist. By Liu Binyan. (Pantheon, $22.95.) Repeatedly Mr. Liu wrote the truth; repeatedly he was punished for it, but never gave up faith in the party until Tiananmen Square. Strange and sad.</p>
        <p>HOW I BECAME HETTIE JONES. By Hettie Jones. (Dutton, $18.95.) The memoir of a young Jewish woman of the Beat Generation, who loved - and lost - the poet and black nationalist LeRoi Jones, is a valuable social document.</p>
        <p>THE LABYRINTH OF EXILE: A Life of Theodor Herzl. By Ernst Pawel. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $30.) Zionism's founder subtly rendered in the round, with both his grandeur and his pettiness.</p>
        <p>LOVE AND OTHER INFECTIOUS DISEASES: A Memoir. By Molly Haskell. (Morrow, $18.95.) A film critic's psychological journey through the terrifying sickness and near death of her husband, Andrew Sarris, also a distinguished film critic.</p>
        <p>MEANS OF ASCENT: The Years of Lyndon Johnson. By Robert A. Caro. (Knopf, $24.95.) The second volume of a projected four, Mr. Caro's account of Johnson's life from 1941 to 1948 - especially the ''stolen election'' that put him in the Senate - is the work of an indefatigable researcher and master narrator.</p>
        <p>MIDSTREAM. By Le Anne Schreiber. (Viking, $18.95.) A dauntless and moving memoir by a former Times editor who became a freelance writer while her mother died cruelly of cancer.</p>
        <p>RANDALL JARRELL: A Literary Life. By William H. Pritchard. (Michael di Capua/Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $25.) One of the most literary lives ever lived, Jarrell's was short on event but plentiful in wit, pathos and brilliance, as this careful biography shows.</p>
        <p>RICHARD NIXON AND HIS AMERICA. By Herbert S. Parmet. (Little, Brown, $24.95.) A thorough and thoughtful biography of both the 37th President and the society in which he came to power.</p>
        <p>SIMONE DE BEAUVOIR: A Biography. By Deirdre Bair. (Summit, $24.95.) Ms. Bair - to whom de Beauvoir granted liberal access for the last six years of her life - presents a detailed and demystifying account of the stellar French intellectual.</p>
        <p>WHAT I SAW AT THE REVOLUTION: A Political Life in the Reagan Era. By Peggy Noonan. (Random House, $19.95.) Ronald Reagan's speechwriter, an articulate true believer in her President's greatness, transforms what she beheld in Washington into fine, sometimes brusque and rough-cut social comedy.</p>
        <p>Children</p>
        <p>ANTARCTICA. Written and illustrated by Helen Cowcher. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $13.95.) The message of this visually dazzling book is clear: penguins have natural predators, and man, though different from the others, is part of that continuum. (Ages 5 to 8) BASEBALL IN APRIL: And Other Stories. By Gary Soto. (Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, $14.95.) These short stories deal sensitively with Mexican-American boys and girls becoming teen-agers in contemporary California neighborhoods. (Ages 12 and up) GALIMOTO. By Karen Lynn Williams. Illustrated by Catherine Stock. (Lothrop, Lee &amp; Shepard, $13.95.) A little boy in a village on the shores of Lake Malawi spends a day making a galimoto - a toy car - from various wires he gathers. The watercolor art broadens the scope of this engaging story. (Ages 5 to 9) JULY. Written and illustrated by James Stevenson. (Greenwillow, $12.95.) These childhood recollections incorporate soft-spoken pictures, touched with amusing grace and completely in harmony with the story they serve. (Ages 5 and up) TEHANU: The Last Book of Earthsea. By Ursula K. LeGuin. (Jean Karl/Atheneum, $15. 95.) This sequel to the prize-winning Earthsea fantasy trilogy explores the necessary and life-giving contributions of female magic, which is sometimes disguised as domesticity. There are dragons, of course, but also a poignant consideration of aging, among other adult themes. (Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>Crime</p>
        <p>THE BONE ORCHARD. By Joseph Trigoboff. (Blue Star/Walker, $18.95.) A New York City police detective tracks down the connection between a Latin American diplomat and two murdered male hustlers; the novelist has an eye for the murky, nighttime colors of New York's neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>DARK OBSESSION: A True Story of Incest and Justice. By Shelley Sessions with Peter Meyer. (Putnam, $21.95.) The finely detailed and thoroughly shocking narrative, both personal and social, of a Texas teen-ager who found all too little family or institutional support in trying to escape from an incestuous stepfather.</p>
        <p>DEVICES AND DESIRES. By P. D. James. (Knopf, $19.95.) This absorbing novel, the 11th by the British writer, places the detective Adam Dalgliesh on the trail of a serial killer.</p>
        <p>THE END OF LIEUTENANT BORUVKA. By Josef Skvorecky. (Norton, $18.95.) Five stories, camouflaged as police thrillers, about a good man's melancholy trajectory through the corrupt and corrupting world of post-Dubcek, pre-Havel Prague.</p>
        <p>AN EASY THING. By Paco Ignacio Taibo 2d. (Viking, $16.95.) Mr. Taibo composes a dense and disquieting picture of pervasive political chaos and social cynicism in a novel about a moody Mexico City gumshoe.</p>
        <p>IF EVER I RETURN, PRETTY PEGGY-O. By Sharyn McCrumb. (Scribners, $17.95.) Ms. McCrumb's characters give serious and intelligent thought to the ghosts raised by a high school reunion in Tennessee - including the tangible specter of a murderer.</p>
        <p>MURPHY'S FAULT. By Steven Womack. (Thomas Dunne/St. Martin's, $17.95.) New Orleans is the setting for this tough and articulate first novel about greedy politicians and their dirty deals.</p>
        <p>OCTOPUS: The Long Reach of the International Sicilian Mafia. By Claire Sterling. (Norton, $19.95.) Ms. Sterling's Palermo-based bosses are credited with the creation of a multinational empire whose principal target has long been the United States. SKELETON-IN-WAITING. By Peter Dickinson. (Pantheon, $16.95.) Spunky, clever Princess Louise is on the case in the author's second nifty thriller about an imaginary British royal family.</p>
        <p>UNBRIDLED. By Mark Daniel. (Ticknor &amp; Fields, $17.95.) This flashy debut novel features Georgie Blane, a champion steeplechase jockey turned crooked steeplechase jockey. The author's vision of this sporting world offers beauty and brutality, but no romance whatsoever.</p>
        <p>THE WESTIES: Inside the Hell's Kitchen Irish Mob. By T. J. English. (Putnam, $21.95.) The last incarnation and, apparently, final collapse of Manhattan's long-running West Side gang under the twin assaults of Federal crime fighters and gentrification.</p>
        <p>Current Affairs and Social Commentary</p>
        <p>BARBARIANS AT THE GATE: The Fall of RJR Nabisco. By Bryan Burrough and John Helyar. (Harper &amp; Row, $22.95.) A vivid and compelling account of the 1988 sale of RJR Nabisco for $25 billion.</p>
        <p>BIRTH POWER: The Case for Surrogacy. By Carmel Shalev. (Yale University, $19.95.) A liberal feminist lawyer argues forcibly that women should have the legal right to sell their reproductive services (and the obligation to fulfill their contracts).</p>
        <p>THE CATHOLIC MYTH: The Behavior and Beliefs of American Catholics. By Andrew M. Greeley. (Scribners, $21.95.) The priest, novelist, sociologist and maverick argues, with cogent figures, that Roman Catholics are better educated and richer than Protestants and more liberal on political issues.</p>
        <p>DIVORCING THE DICTATOR: America's Bungled Affair With Noriega. By Frederick Kempe. (Putnam, $24.95.) OUR MAN IN PANAMA: How General Noriega Used the United States - and Made Millions in Drugs and Arms. By John Dinges. (Random House, $21.95.) Much in these two accounts by professional journalists has been known to our Government all along but kept secret. Both books are excellent guides through the undergrowth of America's affair with the Panamanian dictator.</p>
        <p>THE FALL OF PAN AM 103: Inside the Lockerbie Investigation. By Steven Emerson and Brian Duffy. (Putnam, $21.95.) Two professional journalists have constructed a surpassing account of the 1988 bombing, rich both in drama and in anecdotal details.</p>
        <p>FLASHBACKS: On Returning to Vietnam. By Morley Safer. (Random House, $18.95.) A postwar reinterpretation of the country by a CBS correspondent whose reporting on the war was among the best broadcast journalism of the 1960's.</p>
        <p>FRUIT TRAMPS: A Family of Migrant Farmworkers. By Herman LeRoy Emmet. (University of New Mexico, Cloth, $45; Paper, $24.95.) In this study of a migrant family, words and pictures echo and drive each other to portray a life of deprivation and triumph.</p>
        <p>INTIFADA: The Palestinian Uprising - Israel's Third Front. By Ze'ev Schiff and Ehud Ya'ari. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $22.95.) A reporters' book that focuses on long-term trends and inquires what is distinctive or continuous about the Palestinian uprising.</p>
        <p>JUSTICE NOT VENGEANCE. By Simon Wiesenthal. (Grove Weidenfeld, $22.50.) Did Josef Mengele really drown in Brazil in 1979, or may the physician-murderer of Auschwitz still be alive? The man who brought Adolf Eichmann to judgment reflects on this and other cases from a life spent tracking Nazis.</p>
        <p>A LAW UNTO ITSELF: Power, Politics, and the IRS. By David Burnham. (Random House, $22.50.) An absorbing, critical, well-argued inquiry into our tax agency, by a former Times reporter.</p>
        <p>A MIRACLE, A UNIVERSE: Settling Accounts With Torturers. By Lawrence Weschler. (Pantheon, $22.95.) A disturbing account of the uneasy compromises between new civilian governments and the brutal military regimes they succeeded in Latin America.</p>
        <p>ONE, BY ONE, BY ONE: Facing the Holocaust. By Judith Miller. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $21.95.) A reporter and editor for The Times examines the ways five European countries and the United States have distorted and manipulated the memory of the Holocaust.</p>
        <p>THE PRIVATIZATION DECISION: Public Ends, Private Means. By John D. Donahue. (Basic Books, $22.95.) What government activities should be contracted out? This thoughtful book shuns global answers and explores how to examine individual cases.</p>
        <p>SLOW BURN: The Rise and Bitter Fall of American Intelligence in Vietnam. By Orrin DeForest and David Chanoff. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $19.95.) Mr. DeForest, the principal author, is an angry C.I.A. veteran, offering a sad tale of obduracy and incompetence.</p>
        <p>SMALL VICTORIES: The Real World of a Teacher, Her Students, and Their High School. By Samuel G. Freedman. (Harper &amp; Row, $22.95.) In a sad account of social neglect and failure, a former New York Times reporter spends a year at a battered inner-city high school and chronicles the heroic and often fruitless efforts of students and teachers to make learning possible.</p>
        <p>SOVIET WOMEN: Walking the Tightrope. By Francine du Plessix Gray. (Doubleday, $19.95.) Brilliant, sympathetic portraits of overworked, frustrated women whose men have neither the authority of patriarchs nor the utility of househusbands.</p>
        <p>TRIBES WITH FLAGS: A Dangerous Passage Through the Chaos of the Middle East. By Charles Glass. (Atlantic Monthly, $22.95.) An unfunny thing happened to this ABC correspondent in Beirut: he got kidnapped. But he escaped, and his story, despite its basic sadness, is entertaining, often even cheerful.</p>
        <p>THE UNDESERVING POOR: From the War on Poverty to the War on Welfare. By Michael B. Katz. (Pantheon, Cloth, $22.95; Paper, $14.95.) A searching, unsettling history of Government policies toward poor people, with provocative solutions for what to do next. WHAT LISA KNEW: The Truth and Lies of the Steinberg Case. By Joyce Johnson. (Putnam, $22.95.) A painful, fascinating effort by a skilled novelist to both narrate and understand (but not to excuse) the events and personalities that led to the horrendous child-abuse case of Lisa Steinberg, dead at 6 in November 1987 in New York.</p>
        <p>THE WORST YEARS OF OUR LIVES: Irreverent Notes From a Decade of Greed. By Barbara Ehrenreich. (Pantheon, $19.95.) Fifty essays - elegant, trenchant, angry and funny - that sum up the author's view of the 80's and aim to make us think (and wince).</p>
        <p>Essays, Criticism and Letters</p>
        <p>THE BOY WHO WOULD BE A HELICOPTER. By Vivian Gussin Paley. (Harvard University, $19.95.) An original essay on the practice of teaching young children, using their own stories as a vehicle of instruction, by a University of Chicago master teacher.</p>
        <p>THE DIARY OF H. L. MENCKEN. Edited by Charles A. Fecher. (Knopf, $30.) The good Mencken - a great writer, editor and friend - and the bad Mencken - anti-Semite, racist and crank - revealed in a compulsively readable diary, kept from 1930 to 1948.</p>
        <p>FIVE O'CLOCK ANGEL: Letters of Tennessee Williams to Maria St. Just, 1948-1982. (Knopf, $24.95.) Williams's letters to the Russian-born Englishwoman Maria St. Just reveal a cheerful, tender, civilized man far different from what has become the drugged, drunken, despondent received version of the playwright.</p>
        <p>FRANCOIS TRUFFAUT: CORRESPONDENCE 1945-1984. Edited by Gilles Jacob and Claude de Givray. (Noonday/Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, Cloth, $50; Paper, $19.95.) A hefty, well-annotated collection of the great French director's almost compulsive correspondence - often joking, always self-revealing.</p>
        <p>HENRY JAMES AND EDITH WHARTON. Letters: 1900-1915. Edited by Lyall H. Powers. (Scribners, $29.95.) The delightful record of a friendship between two very high literary pinnacles.</p>
        <p>IN SEARCH OF LOST ROSES. By Thomas Christopher. (Summit, $18.95.) A charming book-length essay on antique roses, from ancient Rome to Tombstone, Ariz., and on the obsessional characters who hunt and love them, by one of their number.</p>
        <p>LETTERS OF KATHERINE ANNE PORTER. Edited by Isabel Bayley. (Atlantic Monthly, $29.95.) Letters of astonishing clarity, keenness and vigor showing the author of ''Pale Horse, Pale Rider'' as an astute critic of life and a solid help to her friends.</p>
        <p>NOTES OF A HANGING JUDGE: Essays and Reviews, 1979-1989. By Stanley Crouch. (Oxford University, $22.95.) A bold and pitiless critic focuses his wrath chiefly on other African-American intellectuals and spokesmen whom he finds short on seriousness.</p>
        <p>A PRESENT OF THINGS PAST: Selected Essays. By Theodore Draper. (Hill &amp; Wang, $25.) Informed, argumentative observations by the hardest-headed of liberals, taking on cold-war bungling, American Communism and journalistic ethics.</p>
        <p>SOME FREAKS. By David Mamet. (Viking, $16.95.) Reminiscences and ruminations from left to right and back by a considerable playwright who is happy to exhibit his inconsistencies.</p>
        <p>THE PARIS REVIEW ANTHOLOGY. Edited by George Plimpton. (Norton, $25.) THE WRITER'S CHAPBOOK: A Compendium of Fact, Opinion, Wit, and Advice From the 20th Century's Preeminent Writers. Edited by George Plimpton. (Viking, $19.95.) Much has changed since Mr. Plimpton conceived The Paris Review in 1952, and these volumes - the first a collection of writing from the magazine, the second a compendium from its interviews - are handy, entertaining and high-spirited guides to the last four decades by the engineers of change themselves.</p>
        <p>Fiction</p>
        <p>ADULT ENTERTAINMENT. By John Metcalf. (St. Martin's, $15.95.) Two novellas and three short stories whose heroes long for lust but instead get wives, children, bills and crushed hopes; the truth, according to this Canadian writer, is simply no fun.</p>
        <p>ADVANCE, RETREAT: Selected Short Stories. By Richard Rive. (St. Martin's, $16.95.) Humane, observant stories from three decades by the late South African writer, one of the first to explore the meaning of mixed race in a rigid, dualistic society.</p>
        <p>AFTERLIFE. By Paul Monette. (Crown, $19.95.) A gallant, painful novel that concerns three ''AIDS widowers'' trying to reconstruct lives tenuously held in the wake of their lovers' deaths.</p>
        <p>AT THE GATES OF THE ANIMAL KINGDOM. By Amy Hempel. (Knopf, $17.95.) Tiny stories and lots of them, bringing an almost miraculous exactitude of observation and execution to bear on men and women stuck in various poses of comedy and loss.</p>
        <p>BABY OF THE FAMILY. By Tina McElroy Ansa. (Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, $18.95.) This genial first novel renders the life of a black Georgia family of the 1950's in rich detail; but humdrum it's not, for the protagonist is a little girl who talks with ghosts.</p>
        <p>BARKING MAN: And Other Stories. By Madison Smartt Bell. (Ticknor &amp; Fields, $19.95.) In a shifty, dangerous world, Mr. Bell's humane and mature stories require - and get - frequent small acts of heroism from their characters, even against heavy odds.</p>
        <p>BECAUSE IT IS BITTER, AND BECAUSE IT IS MY HEART. By Joyce Carol Oates. (William Abrahams/Dutton, $19.95.) That heart is dark, ignorant and isolated for the arriviste heroine of Ms. Oates's novel, who lives with responsibility for a homicide.</p>
        <p>BLUE TAXIS: Stories About Africa. By Eileen Drew. (Milkweed, Paper, $9.95.) The narrators of these deft, direct tales are mostly expatriate Americans whose ambivalent relationships to third-world surroundings make political problems deeply personal.</p>
        <p>THE BOOK OF EVIDENCE. By John Banville. (Scribners, $17.95.) In this persuasive novel we meet a first-person narrator who is a murderer and an existential philosopher of exceptional depravity.</p>
        <p>CHEKHOV'S SISTER. By W. D. Wetherell. (Little, Brown, $17.95.) Mr. Wetherell's elegant, subtle novel, which takes place in Yalta in 1941, is about people who refuse to be humiliated or become losers.</p>
        <p>THE CLONING OF JOANNA MAY. By Fay Weldon. (Viking, $18.95.) After the protagonist of this energetic, intelligent satirical fantasy learns that her domineering husband had her cloned 30 years ago, all five Joannas band together to readjust their lives.</p>
        <p>COLLECTED STORIES OF WALLACE STEGNER. (Random House, $21.95.) This gathering yields an overview of the author's progress and that of his medium: big, wholehearted tales that proceed with a characteristic sauntering ease.</p>
        <p>DECEPTION. By Philip Roth. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $18.95.) A swift, elegant, disturbing novel, composed of fragments of talk (much of it about sex) between a woman and a man named Philip, whose relation to the real-life Philip Roth is as problematical as ever.</p>
        <p>DOGEATERS. By Jessica Hagedorn. (Pantheon, $19.95.) A fast, frequently hair-raising first novel, full of images and fantasies reflecting the author's Philippine background, that maps the ruin at the heart of Philippine society in the last four decades.</p>
        <p>ESCAPES. By Joy Williams. (Atlantic Monthly, $18.95.) A collection of quirky, ominous short stories in which ''every person is on the brink of eternity every moment'' and few fail to fall in.</p>
        <p>FAMILY PICTURES. By Sue Miller. (Harper &amp; Row, $19.95.) A virtuoso realistic novel about the family and the perspectives within it, spacious and encompassing, that explores what it means to make a home, live at home and learn what home is.</p>
        <p>FEVER: Twelve Stories. By John Edgar Wideman. (Holt, $16.95.) A collection of strange and powerful work, stories grand at once in their impartiality and their sorrow, whose characters - like the rest of us - fail to recognize and love their fellow humans.</p>
        <p>FLOATING IN MY MOTHER'S PALM. By Ursula Hegi. (Poseidon, $17.95.) A deft, convincing little memoirlike novel about a girl growing up in Dusseldorf in the 1950's, a child's phantasmagoria of love versus loneliness, wholeness versus amputation.</p>
        <p>FRIEND OF MY YOUTH. By Alice Munro. (Knopf, $18.95.) This collection of short stories is full of marvels of construction, inquiry and retrospection as Ms. Munro's compulsively curious men and women work at finding out what has happened in their lives.</p>
        <p>THE FUGITIVE. By Pramoedya Ananta Toer. (Morrow, $16.95.) Written while its Indonesian author was imprisoned at the end of World War II, this suspenseful novel of his country's occupation by the Japanese weaves a web of motivation, character and emotion.</p>
        <p>THE FULL CATASTROPHE. By David Carkeet. (Linden/Simon &amp; Schuster, $18.95.) With humor and insight, Mr. Carkeet's fourth novel addresses the commonest of social diseases - a failing marriage - with the least likely of therapies: a live-in linguist.</p>
        <p>GOODNIGHT! By Abram Tertz (Andrei Sinyavsky). (Viking, $22.95.) A novel in the form of a chatty memoir whose charm lies more in details than exposition, even if the details concern the pre-Gorbachev bad old days of the author-narrator's imprisonment.</p>
        <p>HELL-BENT MEN AND THEIR CITIES. By Susan Dodd. (Viking, $17.95.) Short stories, intelligent, sympathetic and sometimes satirical, whose brave though unheroic late-20th-century characters endure while keeping one another's spirits up.</p>
        <p>HIS LITTLE WOMEN. By Judith Rossner. (Summit, $19.95.) Ms. Rossner's eighth book of fiction takes on - always with energy and humor - Hollywood, multiple marriages, the effect of divorce on children, cosmetic surgery, Playboy and Ms. magazine.</p>
        <p>HOLLYWOOD: A Novel of America in the 1920s. By Gore Vidal. (Random House, $19.95.) The latest wonderfully literate installment in Mr. Vidal's docudramatic revision of American history and politics features a movie star with a mission: to persuade producers to make anti-German World War I movies.</p>
        <p>HOMEBOY. By Seth Morgan. (Random House, $19.95.) Savagely comic and often brilliant, Mr. Morgan's first novel conveys a relentless, hellish vision of a San Francisco nether world of drugs and hustlers, thieves and exotic pimps.</p>
        <p>IN A FATHER'S PLACE. By Christopher Tilghman. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $18.95.) The author's first book contains seven short stories, clear and charged with feeling, set in various places, rich enough in significant detail to do the work of novels.</p>
        <p>THE KING. By Donald Barthelme. (Edward Burlingame/Harper &amp; Row, $16.95.) The author, who died last year, left us one more wild, parodic metafiction; in this one, King Arthur meets World War II.</p>
        <p>THE KNIGHT, DEATH AND THE DEVIL. By Ella Leffland. (Morrow, $22.95.) This vigorous novel about Hermann Goring, Hitler's baroque, enigmatic No. 2 Nazi, gives a credible sense of why Nazism succeeded in inflaming so many imaginations.</p>
        <p>LEWIS PERCY. By Anita Brookner. (Pantheon, $18.95.) Ms. Brookner concentrates her mature novelist's intelligence on an innocent, well-meaning man who gets beat up in the sexual wars.</p>
        <p>LIKE LIFE. By Lorrie Moore. (Knopf, $18.95.) Her characters are not a happy lot, but the author's witty and wry observations prevent these stories from being grim or maudlin.</p>
        <p>LONDON FIELDS. By Martin Amis. (Harmony, $19.95.) Set in the grimmest of possible worlds (London in 1999, where a global catastrophe - called just ''the Crisis'' - impends), Mr. Amis's novel pursues its vivid characters through a rich and complicated picaresque tale of destruction and self-destruction.</p>
        <p>MARY REILLY. By Valerie Martin. (Doubleday, $18.95.) Stevenson's story of Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde from the unexpected viewpoint of a housemaid, a woman fierce with love, loyalty and the will to figure out what's going on between good and evil.</p>
        <p>ME AND MY BABY VIEW THE ECLIPSE. By Lee Smith. (Putnam, $18.95.) Powerful short stories of small-town life and the passage of time in the American South, full of striving, jealousy and pettiness but also of transcendent generosity and devotion.</p>
        <p>THE MESSAGE TO THE PLANET. By Iris Murdoch. (Viking, $22.95.) Miss Murdoch's 24th novel treats men and women seriously through a kind of high philosophical clowning, starring a charismatic philosopher exposed to huge overdoses of real life.</p>
        <p>THE MUSIC ROOM. By Dennis McFarland. (Houghton Mifflin, $18.95.) The themes struck in Mr. McFarland's generous, hopeful and stylistically bold first novel include history and continuity, independence and separation, as its 29-year-old hero searches past and present for secrets of identity.</p>
        <p>THE NEUMILLER STORIES. By Larry Woiwode. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $18.95.) Utterly direct but sometimes painfully difficult in their emotional discriminations, most of these stories are the original versions of material later incorporated into the author's fine 1975 novel of Great Plains life, ''Beyond the Bedroom Wall.''</p>
        <p>ORDINARY MONEY. By Louis B. Jones. (Viking, $18.95.) A wacky, satirical first novel of life among the relatively disadvantaged of Marin County, California, who are saddled with responsibility for a truckload of counterfeit money (except it may be real).</p>
        <p>PALACE WALK. By Naguib Mahfouz. (Doubleday, $22.95.) Now available in English, the first volume of ''The Cairo Trilogy,'' reputed to be the masterpiece of the Egyptian novelist and 1988 Nobel laureate, nobly supports that reputation.</p>
        <p>PASSING ON. By Penelope Lively. (Grove Weidenfeld, $17.95.) Tough and shrewd, precise and understated, Ms. Lively's eighth novel renders a family's painful efforts to sort out and overcome the emotional legacy of a truly awful mother.</p>
        <p>PICTURING WILL. By Ann Beattie. (Random House, $18.95.) Complex points of view unfold to yield the shock of enlightenment in Ms. Beattie's fourth novel, a lyrical, deeply affecting story about a little boy and the people who love him, or should.</p>
        <p>THE QUINCUNX. By Charles Palliser. (Ballantine, $25.) Can you imagine a gigantic (788 pages) imitation of Dickens, abounding in wickedness, full of descriptive power, replete with plot and gratifyingly difficult to put down? Mr. Palliser did!</p>
        <p>REACHING TIN RIVER. By Thea Astley. (Putnam, $19.95.) A vivid novel about growing up in great big Australia; at its heart is an eerie, hypnotic, sentimental excursion across that brown land.</p>
        <p>RESTORATION: A Novel of Seventeenth-Century England. By Rose Tremain. (Viking, $19.95.) Ms. Tremain's fine sixth novel restores the good name of historical fiction as it propels its insecure hero through hassles high and low in Charles II's England.</p>
        <p>SHIRA. By S. Y. Agnon. (Schocken, $24.95.) For more than 20 years the Israeli Nobel laureate worked on this unfinished novel, whose protagonist is a German-born scholar and whose theme is art's search for a vision of tragedy when real horror is unbearably vast.</p>
        <p>SILVER LIGHT. By David Thomson. (Knopf, $19.95.) Mr. Thomson's third novel presents America's wild West from the Civil War to the 1950's, writ very large and loony in handsome prose, with loads of real, imaginary and intermediate characters.</p>
        <p>SOLOMON GURSKY WAS HERE. By Mordecai Richler. (Knopf, $19.95.) Mr. Richler's ninth and most complex novel chronicles, with frequent and intense indignation, the generations of the convoluted, manic Gursky family through Canadian history.</p>
        <p>A STONE OF THE HEART. By Tom Grimes. (Four Walls Eight Windows, $15.95.) The afflictions of adolescence are rendered in unique and universal terms in this first novel, set in Queens in 1961, about a 14-year-old boy who idolizes Roger Maris.</p>
        <p>SWEET TALK. By Stephanie Vaughn. (Random House, $16.95.) Ms. Vaughn's fine first story collection offers harrowing situations made alternately funny and sad by lively, believable characters.</p>
        <p>A TENURED PROFESSOR. By John Kenneth Galbraith. (Houghton Mifflin, $19.95.) A liberal economist learns to quantify investor irrationality and makes millions until conservatives cut him down in Mr. Galbraith's rollicking spoof of free-market ideology.</p>
        <p>THEN SHE FOUND ME. By Elinor Lipman. (Pocket Books, $18.95.) A deft, amusing first novel, full of entertaining mysteries, about an adopted daughter awkwardly reunited with her birth mother.</p>
        <p>THE THINGS THEY CARRIED. By Tim O'Brien. (Seymour Lawrence/Houghton Mifflin, $19.95.) A collection of interrelated stories that confront the meaning of the Vietnam War, examining with insight and sensitivity the nature of courage and fear.</p>
        <p>TITMUSS REGAINED. By John Mortimer. (Viking, $19.95.) Mr. Mortimer's splendid classical comedy of political manners in an English village paints all participants as greedy ninnies, most notably the title character, a politically prominent twerp.</p>
        <p>THE TONGUES OF ANGELS. By Reynolds Price. (Atheneum, $17.95.) The narrator of this chastely visionary novel looks back 34 years to examine his responsibility, perhaps, for a boy's death.</p>
        <p>THE TRICK OF IT. By Michael Frayn. (Viking, $17.95.) The versatile British satirist is right on form in this novel about an embittered critic who marries a distinguished novelist.</p>
        <p>WEDDING SONG. By Naguib Mahfouz. (Doubleday, Cloth, $16.95; Paper, $7.95.) THE BEGINNING AND THE END. By Naguib Mahfouz. (Doubleday, Cloth, $19.95; Paper, $9.95.) THE THIEF AND THE DOGS. By Naguib Mahfouz. (Doubleday, Cloth, $16.95; Paper, $7.95.) Three samples, all impressive, all diverse in both period and style, from among the 40-plus books of fiction by the versatile 1988 Nobel Prize winner, an Egyptian born in 1911.</p>
        <p>THE WILD COLONIAL BOY. By James Hynes. (Atheneum, $18.95.) Brian Donovan, the American protagonist of Mr. Hynes's sharp-eyed and convincing first novel, finds himself swiftly involved with an I.R.A. dispute and a young American woman backpacker.</p>
        <p>THE WOMAN AT THE WINDOW. By Marian Eldridge. (University of Queensland/International Specialized Book Services, Paper, $12.95.) Sixteen short stories, set in Australia with side trips, elegantly shaped and alive with narrative brilliance.</p>
        <p>VINELAND. By Thomas Pynchon. (Little, Brown, $19.95.)The passions of the 1960's continue to govern the lives of members of a California community.</p>
        <p>History</p>
        <p>BITING AT THE GRAVE: The Irish Hunger Strikes and the Politics of Despair. By Padraig O'Malley. (Beacon, $22.95.) The macabre enthusiasm of 10 I.R.A. prisoners who starved themselves to death is made at least explicable in this shrewd analysis. COMING OUT UNDER FIRE: The History of Gay Men and Women in World War Two. By Allan Berube. (Free Press, $22.95.) This deeply researched account shows that the military and perhaps a million homosexuals often coped with each other fairly well.</p>
        <p>FORGED IN BATTLE: The Civil War Alliance of Black Soldiers and White Officers. By Joseph T. Glatthaar. (Free Press, $24.95.) The absorbing story, more social than military, of the revolution through which 180,000 blacks fought for the Union in the Civil War.</p>
        <p>THE JEWS IN AMERICA. Four Centuries of an Uneasy Encounter: A History. By Arthur Hertzberg. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $22.95.) A broadly familiar story that rises to the superb in its account of the last 60 years or so, but is pessimistic about the future, foreseeing an end to Jewish history unless a spiritual revival supervenes.</p>
        <p>RED VICTORY: A History of the Russian Civil War. By W. Bruce Lincoln. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $24.95.) Between 1919 and 1921 the Soviet state was created out of chaos by armed force, this timely and thorough account by a university historian reminds us.</p>
        <p>THE SEARCH FOR MODERN CHINA. By Jonathan D. Spence. (Norton, $29.95.) Four centuries of Chinese history, from the decline of the Ming dynasty to the crushing of the democracy movement last June, are illuminated in a sweeping study of a nation both burdened and blessed with a rich past. THE SECOND WORLD WAR. by John Keegan. (Viking, $29.95.) THE TIMES ATLAS OF THE SECOND WORLD WAR. Edited by John Keegan. (Harper &amp; Row, $50.) A bold but balanced one-volume military history and a superbly produced and edited historical atlas that has no equivalent in its field.</p>
        <p>TOKYO RISING: The City Since the Great Earthquake. By Edward Seidensticker. (Knopf, $24.95.) An informal and contentious history of the Japanese capital from 1923 to the present, often anecdotal, equally often painstakingly thorough. AN UNCERTAIN HOUR: The French, the Germans, the Jews, the Klaus Barbie Trial, and the City of Lyon, 1940-1945. By Ted Morgan. (Arbor House/Morrow, $21,95.) An eloquent book of personal and public history by a French-born American journalist out to understand the contradictions of his former country.</p>
        <p>VOICES OF FREEDOM: An Oral History of the Civil Rights Movement From the 1950s Through the 1980s. By Henry Hampton and Steve Fayer with Sarah Flynn. (Bantam, $25.95.) An intimate survey sprung from the ''Eyes on the Prize'' television series.</p>
        <p>Poetry</p>
        <p>BETWEEN ANGELS. By Stephen Dunn. (Norton, $15.95.) Stephen Dunn is one of the strongest poetic voices in this country now. A man of quiet passion, he is a master of the short phrase. He can encapsulate daily experience wonderfully in lines that are richly crafted, but never decorative.</p>
        <p>THE COMPLETE POEMS OF ANNA AKHMATOVA. Edited by Roberta Reeder. (Zephyr, $85.) The first edition of all of the poems, in Russian and in an admirable English translation by Judith Hemschemeyer in which both sense and message strike with all the force of the original. All the passion, conscience, repentance, suffering that made Akhmatova the high priestess of Russian poetry in this century sing out.</p>
        <p>THE NIGHT PARADE. By Edward Hirsch. (Knopf, $18.95.) Emotional richness combined with a precision of language and metaphor make the best of these poems wonderful to read. Some seem to have forced themselves into being; silence was no longer possible.</p>
        <p>THE TONGUES WE SPEAK: New and Selected Poems. By Patricia Goedicke. (Milkweed, $9.95.) This volume spans 25 years of the work of a poet who is always aware of the political state of the world and of history. Her strengths are sincerity, memorable rhythms and great emotional power.</p>
        <p>Popular Culture</p>
        <p>THE DAME IN THE KIMONO: Hollywood, Censorship, and the Production Code From the 1920s to the 1960s. By Leonard J. Leff and Jerold L. Simmons. (Grove Weidenfeld, $22.50.) What couldn't happen on screen: a virtual negative history of sex in America.</p>
        <p>ENCHANTED DRAWINGS: The History of Animation. By Charles Solomon. (Knopf, $75.) An ambitious, sprawling illustrated account of the evolution of animated movies, packed with tales of warring studios, greedy producers and great artists.</p>
        <p>THE GREAT GOOD PLACE. By Ray Oldenburg. (Paragon House, $19.95.) A good society has places for people to hang out - taverns, cafes, barbershops - and Mr. Oldenburg, a sociologist, investigates what's become of ours and how to get them back.</p>
        <p>JEAN HOWARD'S HOLLYWOOD: A Photo Memoir. With photographs by Jean Howard and text by James Watters. (Abrams, $39.95.) Herself one of Hollywood's most beautiful and privileged people, Jean Howard snapped her shutter with a social historian's eye, capturing the great at play in the 1940's and 50's.</p>
        <p>THE MAN WHO SHOT GARBO: The Hollywood Photographs of Clarence Sinclair Bull. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $40.) Greta Garbo and other gods and goddesses, luminously rendered by the head of the M-G-M stills department from 1924 to 1961; 183 portraits in all.</p>
        <p>OUR NEW YORK. Text by Alfred Kazin. Photographs by David Finn. (Harper &amp; Row, $35.) A delightful collaboration on the New York landscape and its meaning by two wise old Brooklyn hands.</p>
        <p>SATURDAY NIGHT. By Susan Orlean. (Knopf, $19.95.) Eight hours in the hebdomadal cycle of American culture, sharply observed by a journalist with a gift for hanging around while paying attention.</p>
        <p>THE SPIRIT OF FOLK ART: The Girard Collection at the Museum of International Folk Art. By Henry Glassie. Color photographs by Michael Monteaux. (Abrams, $60.) With 154 splendid color pages, this rather ambitious illustrated essay celebrates a collection (located in Santa Fe, N.M.) that richly deserves it.</p>
        <p>WRITERS IN HOLLYWOOD: 1915-1951. By Ian Hamilton. (Edward Burlingame/Harper &amp; Row, $25.) An ably researched and entertaining account of the literati who condescended to, and profited from, the movie industry during its infant and golden years.</p>
        <p>Science Fiction</p>
        <p>HYPERION. By Dan Simmons. (Foundation/Doubleday, Cloth, $18.95; Paper, $8.95; Spectra/Bantam, Paper, $4.95.) THE FALL OF HYPERION. By Dan Simmons. (Foundation/Doubleday, Cloth, $18.95; Paper, $8.95.) Combined, these two make up a thousand-page novel; both are generously conceived and stylistically sure-handed works. THE DIVIDE. By Robert Charles Wilson. (Foundation/Doubleday, $19.95.) This literate thriller is a superbly crafted novel of character and a thoughtful exploration of what it might feel like to be a superman.</p>
        <p>RAMA II. By Arthur C. Clarke and Gentry Lee. (Spectra/Bantam, $18.95.) The sequel to Mr. Clarke's famous novel ''Rendezvous With Rama'' - about a vast alien spaceship that seems oblivious to humanity's best efforts to make an impression - is just as gripping in this second encounter.</p>
        <p>Science, Medicine and Psychology</p>
        <p>DISAPPEARING THROUGH THE SKYLIGHT: Culture and Technology in the Twentieth Century. By O. B. Hardison Jr. (Viking, $22.95.) A polymathic scholar and social critic's optimistic synthesis of future technology and consciousness.</p>
        <p>FLOW: The Psychology of Optimal Experience. By Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi. (Harper &amp; Row, $21.95.) ''Flow,'' according to the author, a professor of psychology at the University of Chicago, is a learnable state of consciousness that comes with rightly interpreting what we are doing and what is happening to us.</p>
        <p>FIRE &amp; ICE: The Greenhouse Effect, Ozone Depletion, and Nuclear Winter. By David E. Fisher. (Harper &amp; Row, $19.95.) THE NEXT ONE HUNDRED YEARS: Shaping the Fate of Our Living Earth. By Jonathan Weiner. (Bantam, $19.95.) There is, both authors assure us, a scientific consensus about global warming: it's coming. But something can be done, they believe, and these studies passionately and credibly urge attention to a threatening future that many of us seem to have despaired of in advance.</p>
        <p>THE SPACE TELESCOPE: A Study of NASA, Science, Technology, and Politics. By Robert W. Smith. (Cambridge University, $39.50.) A big book about big science, focused on the history of space technology and the development of the Hubble Space Telescope.</p>
        <p>WHAT KIND OF LIFE: The Limits of Medical Progress. By Daniel Callahan. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $19.95.) An ethical philosopher's tough-minded look at the debate about medical costs and society's resources, arguing for rules that would give far higher priorities to prevention than to high-cost care in marginal cases.</p>
        <p>Spies &amp; Thrillers</p>
        <p>THE BLUE GATE OF BABYLON. By Paul Pickering. (Random House, $18.95.) This blackly humorous espionage novel is about a young British diplomat in West Berlin who likes women too much for his own good.</p>
        <p>DEATH ROLL. By Sam Llewellyn. (Summit, $18.95.) Mr. Llewellyn, the Dick Francis of sailing, writes cleanly and unaffectedly about racing boats, real estate deals - and murder.</p>
        <p>PAPER CHASE. By Bob Cook. (St. Martin's, $14.95.) Four elderly, retired British agents decide to write their memoirs, gleefully inventing sensational stories about their past.</p>
        <p>ROMAN CIRCUS. By Frank O'Neill. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $19.95.) Mr. O'Neill's absorbing tale is about many things: Arab terrorism in Italy, a fading aristocracy, the Red Brigades, a romance between a princess and a C.I.A. man.</p>
        <p>THE RUNNING TARGET. By Gerald Seymour. (Morrow, $19.95.) A top deskman at British intelligence is kidnapped by Iranians in this scary and searing book.</p>
        <p>Sports</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: The People's Game, by Harold Seymour. (Oxford University, $24.95.) The third volume in Mr. Seymour's history of baseball broadly details the game outside so-called Organized Baseball and its capture by designing institutions.</p>
        <p>DAMNED YANKEES: A No-Holds-Barred Account of Life With ''Boss'' Steinbrenner. By Bill Madden and Moss Klein. (Warner, $19.95.) A well-told account of the decline and fall of the New York Yankees at the hands of the team's principal owner.</p>
        <p>KAREEM. By Kareem Abdul-Jabbar with Mignon McCarthy. (Random House, $18.95.) A memoir in the form of a diary, combining this amazing player's last season as a Los Angeles Laker with autobiographical recollections, mostly magnanimous.</p>
        <p>MEN AT WORK: The Craft of Baseball, by George F. Will. (Macmillan, $19.95.) An elegant analysis of what baseball players actually do, investigated by the conservative columnist with love and curiosity but without sentimentality or mythologizing.</p>
        <p>Travel, Nature and Adventure</p>
        <p>PLAYING WITH WATER: Passion and Solitude on a Philippine Island. By James Hamilton-Paterson. (New Amsterdam Books, Cloth, $19.95; Paper, $11.95.) A truly remarkable lyrical meditation on sea, sunlight and the analysis of consciousness.</p>
        <p>SONORAN DESERT SUMMER. By John Alcock. (University of Arizona, $19.95.) A handsome, thoughtful record of nature observation and conceptual ecology in a very hard place to live.</p>
        <p>A YEAR IN PROVENCE. By Peter Mayle. (Knopf, $19.95.) When the author, his wife and their dogs leave London for a sojourn in sunny Provence they encounter year-round surprises - icy mistrals, unwelcome visitors, burst pipes and village rustics.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
