<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Earth Day at 20: How Green the Globe? - A special report:   Guarding Environment: A World of Challenges</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="346199"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH DAY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CORPORATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Special Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D6143EF931A15757C0A966958260" item-length="5155" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Earth Day at 20: How Green the Globe? - A special report:   Guarding Environment: A World of Challenges</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Twenty years after the first Earth Day, the Cuyahoga River no longer catches fire on its way through Cleveland, and bald eagles, once threatened by DDT, have increased nearly sevenfold in the continental United States, enough for Government biologists to consider promoting the population to ''threatened'' from ''endangered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Twenty years after the first Earth Day, the Cuyahoga River no longer catches fire on its way through Cleveland, and bald eagles, once threatened by DDT, have increased nearly sevenfold in the continental United States, enough for Government biologists to consider promoting the population to ''threatened'' from ''endangered.</p>
        <p>Twenty years after the first Earth Day, the Cuyahoga River no longer catches fire on its way through Cleveland, and bald eagles, once threatened by DDT, have increased nearly sevenfold in the continental United States, enough for Government biologists to consider promoting the population to ''threatened'' from ''endangered.''</p>
        <p>Around the country there are scores of examples of modest environmental progress, which elected officials and industrial companies will hold up to public view today as thousands of people celebrate Earth Day 1990 and call on society to nurture nature. Everywhere, it seems, the thinking has changed; many corporations have dropped their old arguments pitting pollution against jobs and, sensing competitive advantage, are scrambling instead to demonstrate how ''green'' they are.</p>
        <p>But measuring progress is as hard as adding apples and oranges, elephants and ozone.</p>
        <p>From Streams to Stratosphere</p>
        <p>And the targets are shifting. Once concern was centered on narrow problems: the stream in the valley, the dump nearby, tiny snail darters or giant pandas. Increasingly, the issues are problems of the whole earth: industrial gases acting like glass in a greenhouse to trap heat around the earth, the destruction of the protective ozone layer. Scientists have discarded the image of Mother Nature with a black eye for one of Mother Nature stumbling toward a cliff.</p>
        <p>''The ozone hole is the smoking gun,'' said Michael Oppenheimer, a senior scientist at the Environmental Defense Fund, who called the thinning of the protective ozone layer ''real proof that humans threaten life on earth.''</p>
        <p>One sign of such change is that Earth Day, which began in 1970 as a nationwide event, has evolved at its 20th anniversary into a celebration across 140 countries, honoring Brazilian rain forests, protesting pollution in Eastern Europe and promoting behavior everywhere to preserve stratospheric ozone.</p>
        <p>In fact, the near-global agreement in Montreal in January 1989 to cut production of chlorofluorocarbons, which destroy ozone, is cited by many experts as the best example that as a species humans realize there is more to life than being at the top of the food chain.</p>
        <p>Around the nation, however, progress on the environment is mixed with frustration. Examples abound:</p>
        <p>*  Utilities in the United States are burning more than twice as much coal for electricity as they did in 1970, yet they are emitting 15 percent less sulfur dioxide, the coal byproduct that causes acid rain. The consensus, though, is that the reduction is not enough; 4,000 lakes in the United States and 164,000 in Canada are acidified or threatened, by the count of some environmental groups.</p>
        <p>*  The tailpipes of new cars emit 96 percent less carbon monoxide and hydrocarbons and 76 percent less nitrogen oxides than older models. But there are so many more vehicles and so much congestion that half of Americans live in counties that violated Federal clean air standards in 1988.</p>
        <p>*  Fish have returned to the Cuyahoga River and to Lake Erie, into which it empties, and other Great Lakes. But the flesh of many Great Lakes fish carries toxic chemicals that make them dangerous to eat, and casts doubt on the wisdom of restocking the lakes.</p>
        <p>''This is not the way to reconcile people with nature, and the public knows that,'' William K. Reilly, head of the Environmental Protection Agency, said of the poisonous fish. Mr. Reilly, who carries a business card of brown recycled paper, is himself a symbol of the ascent of environmentalism, if not the environment. A former president of the World Wildlife Fund-United States, he is likely soon to be elevated to the Cabinet.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, Many Environmentalists</p>
        <p>Seventy-six percent of all Americans now call themselves environmentalists, according to a Gallup Poll. But many advocates who used to distinguish themselves by using the label say the environment is worse. And some say attempts to measure real progress are only clouded by the appearance of consensus that comes when everyone from Greenpeace members to chemical company executives marches under the same environmental banner.</p>
        <p>The agencies and protective measures that sprang to life after the first Earth Day -among them the Environmental Protection Agency, the Clean Air Act and the Clean Water Act - have pushed the country to reduce pollution. But global problems that were not even recognized 20 years ago, like thinning ozone and the greenhouse effect, have clearly worsened.</p>
        <p>Those pose challenges to society that are different from what came before. In contrast to the dwindling population of eagles, these problems may require solutions before the symptoms are plainly understood. Kenneth H. Keller, a chemical engineer who is a former president of the University of Minnesota, recently wrote: ''Our ability to affect our ecological niche is accompanied by an inability to assess the effects of doing so. In contrast to similar problems in the past, we are faced with the situation that the negative effects may be irreversible if we do not act to correct them, but that forces us to act before we can be sure that we understand them.''</p>
        <p>Warring Dioxides</p>
        <p>And environmental problems are often pitted against each other in a way that makes the whole problem larger than the sum of its parts. For example, acid rain is curbed with scrubbers that remove sulfur dioxide from power plant emissions. But the use of scrubbers requires more coal to be used for each unit of electricity; that raises carbon dioxide emissions, accelerating the buildup of gases that act like panes of glass in a greenhouse to trap the sun's warmth.</p>
        <p>Eliminating chlorofluorocarbons to save the ozone layer will make scores of industrial machines less efficient, raising their fuel use and therefore their output of carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>The world is only coming to understand other environmental problems. For example, every year the Federal Government adds 35 to 50 plants, animals and insects to the list protected under the Endangered Species Act, and only 10 have been removed since the list was established in 1973. (Four recovered and six were determined to be extinct.) Species are being lost faster than they can be counted, but the Government list does not reflect that; the length of the list is only a factor of how fast the Fish and Wildlife Service can go through the legal process required to list the endangered species.</p>
        <p>Choices for the Third World</p>
        <p>While experts differ on the extent of progress by the United States, it is clearly ahead of Eastern Europe, where the collapse of the old political and economic order has revealed a history of almost unchecked destruction of natural resources.</p>
        <p>The most important choices being made in the coming decades may be in the developing countries, where population and economic activity are growing far faster than in industrial nations. If huge populations attain Western standards of consumption without some corresponding leap in efficiency, nature will reel.</p>
        <p>''We need to alter the presumption that increased consumption and economic growth are essential to prosperity,'' said Peter Dykstra, head of the Washington office of Greenpeace.</p>
        <p>CHANGING VIEWS</p>
        <p>Many Shades, All of Them Green</p>
        <p>If the physical world is ambiguous, the political world is not, especially since the Exxon Valdez impaled itself on Bligh Reef in March 1989 and the Chernobyl reactor spewed radiation across the Ukraine and much of Europe three years earlier. Concern for nature has claimed hearts and minds around the world. As Yogi Berra might have said, suddenly the environment is all around us.</p>
        <p>For example, a New York Times/CBS News Poll asked a random sample of Americans if they agreed that ''protecting the environment is so important that requirements and standards cannot be too high, and continuing environmental improvements must be made regardless of cost.''</p>
        <p>The question was framed in those provocative terms to identify people who felt strongly about the environment. When it was first asked, in September 1981, 45 percent said yes. This month, 74 percent did. Mr. Reilly, the E.P.A. Administrator, who was widely respected as an environmentalist before President Bush appointed him, said that if he had been asked the question by a poll taker, he would have answered no, that some steps would be too extreme even for him. And some suspect that the current fever of interest is an unsustainable fad.</p>
        <p>In the Mainstream</p>
        <p>But to be an environmentalist is to be in the mainstream, as demonstrated in a recent speech by none other than Edgar S. Woolard, the chairman of E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company, which once advertised ''Better Living Through Chemistry.'' Now he argues that survival belongs to the environmentally fit.</p>
        <p>''Industrial companies will ignore the environment only at their peril,'' he said. ''Corporations that think they can drag their heels indefinitely on genuine environmental problems should be advised: Society won't tolerate it, and Du Pont and other companies with real sensitivity and environmental commitment will be there to supply your customers after you're gone.''</p>
        <p>The idea that the public will reward companies that strike a protective pose toward nature seems demonstrated by the experience of Conoco, a Du Pont subsidiary that is the world's 20th-largest oil company, which recently announced that it was changing the recipe of its gasoline to reduce air pollution. From coast to coast, Conoco said, it received telephone calls from individuals and organizations asking where its gasoline could be bought. Public opposition to fishing methods that trapped dolphins in tuna nets led the biggest tuna canning companies to agree to buy only from fishing boats that use other methods.</p>
        <p>Other industrialists have said the public's changing attitude has changed too much. One casualty between this Earth Day and the first one, some companies say, is the credibility of the Federal Government; the model of future environmental regulation, they say, may be Alar, an herbicide that was effectively banned not by the Government, which said there was not enough information to justify the step, but by a report from a nonprofit environmental group widely reported on television and in newspapers.</p>
        <p>''Frequently stories of doom and gloom are reported without any scientific counterpoint or peer review,'' complained William D. Fay, administrator of the Clean Air Working Group, an industry lobbying group.</p>
        <p>Another industry spokesman, Richard M. Morrow, the chairman of Amoco, said environmental politics and bad or incomplete science were leading to poor choices in allocating scarce resources. Speaking of the national effort to clean up thousands of toxic waste sites, he said: ''The Federal Superfund program will spend huge amounts of money and tie up some of the country's top technical people to deal with waste sites that in many cases pose no particular threat to anyone. Yet the country is strapped for funds to deal with such issues as drugs, education and public health.''</p>
        <p>An 'Environmental Ethic'</p>
        <p>The reasons for the shift toward environmentalism are not clear even to those who have fought for it. Some trace it to a merger of two popular concerns: preservation of the wild and fear of cancer. A recurrent theme of environmental decay is the presence of new chemicals, often man-made, that are suspected or confirmed carcinogens.</p>
        <p>The global nature of problems like diminishing stratospheric ozone, deforestation and hunger has had its own effect on attitudes, blurring the boundaries between nations, some experts say. The environmentalists' response to the Chernobyl disaster - that a nuclear accident anywhere is an accident everywhere - has parallels that apply to pollution. Political change has also brought nations together; countries in the European Community are now moving as a single unit to impose tailpipe emission standards.</p>
        <p>Advocates in the field say they are surprised by the high level of public knowledge around the world about the ozone hole, especially given the confusing nature of ozone. The helpful molecule being destroyed in the stratosphere is the same one that is created by automotive pollution at ground level, where it causes irritation and lung damage.</p>
        <p>All this consciousness adds up to an important change for the environment, experts say, perhaps more than any invention, regulation or other development has wrought in the last two decades. What remains to be seen is how long the attitude, which also seemed dominant on previous Earth Days, will endure. But for now longtime environmental advocates are basking.</p>
        <p>James Gustave Speth, president of the World Resources Institute in Washington, said the biggest development since the first Earth Day was ''the steady and sometimes spectacular growth of worldwide public concern about environmental degradation, and of citizen action and organization to meet these challenges.'' John C. Sawhill, president of the Nature Conservancy, called it ''the gradual 'mainstreaming' of environmental activism.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dykstra of Greenpeace's Washington office said that in January 1988 his office received 1,000 requests for general information; by February 1990 that figure was 1,000 a day.</p>
        <p>Michael Deland, chairman of the President's Council on Environmental Quality, said an ''environmental ethic'' had emerged nationally and internationally since the first Earth Day.</p>
        <p>Where this ethic is leading is less clear. The collective push of the individual choices of Americans often points away from environmentally sound practice. For example, the average gas mileage of new cars declined 4 percent from the model year 1988 to 1990 after rising about 50 percent in the previous decade. Buyers are voting with their feet -specifically, the foot on the gas pedal. Americans still prefer heavier cars with bigger engines and better acceleration, the auto makers say. And the number of miles they drive rises about 2 percent a year, year in and year out.</p>
        <p>And garbage, that index of prosperity, is still rising. Discards per person per day, 2.5 pounds in 1960, reached 3.6 pounds by 1986, the most recent year for which the E.P.A. has released figures. Discards are increasing faster than recycling or burning to recover energy.</p>
        <p>Nearly every human activity affects the environment. The two pages to print this article in 1.7 million copies of The New York Times required nearly 20 tons of paper, which began as 400 evergreen trees, mostly spruce, that covered about two acres.</p>
        <p>While individuals may not always make the choices that help nature most, sometimes regulation forces steps that bring measurable progress. For example, tests showed that concentrations of the pesticide DDT in human tissue fell from an average of 8 parts per million in 1970 to 2 in 1983 as a result of a Federal ban. (Concentrations fell in bald eagles, too, leading to their partial recovery.) Lead concentrations in blood fell 40 percent from 1975 to 1981, and the number of people with more than 1 part per million of cancer-causing polychlorinated biphenyls declined from about 70 percent of the population in 1972 to about 10 percent in 1983.</p>
        <p>The gains are by no means uniform. For example, atmospheric concentrations of two of the most ozone-damaging chlorofluorocarbons, CFC-11 and CFC-12, increased by 85 percent from 1975 to 1985. The Montreal protocol, which took effect in July, will gradually reduce production of the chemicals.</p>
        <p>In the absence of a comprehensive yardstick of environmental progress, perhaps the closest thing is a broad measure of human health: life expectancy. It is now 75 years, up from 70.9 years in 1970, according to the Census Bureau.</p>
        <p>STAYING INVENTIVE</p>
        <p>Living Cleaner, Living Smarter</p>
        <p>All these signs of environmental progress and even degradation are actually a result of overall human progress, said Julian Simon, a professor at the University of Maryland business school who espouses the unconventional view that a bigger population is a plus because it means more human creativity and more progress.</p>
        <p>''The list of things we can worry about is reasonably short,'' he said. ''We can worry about getting fed, the safety of our children, having a car, things like that. Now we don't worry about our children dying of smallpox; as we successively solve one problem after another, we work our way down the list, and we've worked our way down to the environment.''</p>
        <p>For the United States, said Dr. Simon, this began in the 1950's and 60's with rising prosperity. In the third world, ''the super-poor can't pollute at all because they don't have anything to pollute with.'' But with economic progress, he said, ''they will get affluent enough that they want to buy cleanliness.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Simon's underlying thesis is that standards of living, the availability of raw materials and life expectancies are all rising because the world is progressively inventing its way out of problems, expanding the pie of materials, goods and services faster than it is adding people to divide the pie.</p>
        <p>Toward a Solar Future?</p>
        <p>The thesis that progress brings environmentalism may be tested soon in Eastern Europe, where the collapse of Communism has exposed environmental exploitation and an aspiration not only for political freedom, but also for clean air and healthy forests, and an end to what Mr. Dykstra of Greenpeace calls ''environmental repression.''</p>
        <p>Even less sanguine experts agree that the process of inventing the way out of problems is continuing on some level. With some encouragement from the Government, scientists and engineers are laying the technological foundations for what experts say will be an economy that does not consume scarce resources or continuously add pollution.</p>
        <p>The most promising invention of the last 20 years, says Dr. Oppenheimer of the Environmental Defense Fund, is the photovoltaic cell, which turns sunlight into electricity. The price of such cells is still too high to compete with electricity produced from oil but is falling rapidly; the Electric Power Research Institute, a utility research consortium based in Palo Alto, Calif., says some utilities may find solar cells cheaper than oil for some power needs by the middle of this decade.</p>
        <p>With continued progress, many hope that solar cells, with cheap energy storage systems, will supplant oil, coal and natural gas.</p>
        <p>That is in the future. A host of smaller technological advances in the last decade have enabled Americans to use energy more efficiently. And some experts say this could point the way for other countries.</p>
        <p>Increasing Efficiency</p>
        <p>At the American Council for an Energy Efficient Economy, Marc Ledbetter, a spokesman, pointed out that in the last 20 years, the American economy had grown by roughly half while energy use rose only about 10 percent. ''Had this improvement not occurred, we would now be spending an additional $150 billion per year on energy, emitting billions of more tons of carbon dioxide and other air and water pollutants,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The increase in efficiency comes from improvements in products that consumers are using. Technology holds out the prospect of continued improvements, of course, but partly because it has advanced much faster than the marketplace.</p>
        <p>For example, the average electric water heater in use in 1985 consumed 4,000 kilowatt-hours a year, according to the council, while the average new model bought that year required 3,500. But for years water heaters have been available that used only 1,500 kilowatt-hours a year, and the best expected to be available in the 1990's do the same work for just over 1,000 kilowatt-hours. An economist might find it cost-effective to rip out an old model and replace it with a new one, but few people bother. Even when an old appliance must be replaced because it has broken down, buyers sometimes balk at the higher purchase price of a more efficient model. And the pollution that comes from extra energy consumption is often not calculated in the price.</p>
        <p>The difference between the typical 1985 heater and the best 1990's heater, a difference of 3,000 kilowatt-hours a year, is equivalent to about 1.25 tons of coal. Each household that makes such a switch will save an attendant amount of carbon dioxide and sulfur dioxide from being released into the atmosphere through coal burning.</p>
        <p>The challenge for households and policy makers is how to push the American economy toward the 1,000-kilowatt-hour model. The trend toward greater energy efficiency stalled last year, and while it began improving again in late 1989, its future course is not certain.</p>
        <p>Abstinence Isn't Virtue</p>
        <p>The progress is important because the United States, with about 2 percent of the world's population, uses 24 percent of its energy, about twice as much as Western Europe and Japan per unit of economic output. In contrast, China, with about 20 percent of the world's population, uses 9 percent of its energy.</p>
        <p>For China, as for all the third world, this is a result not of virtue or voluntary abstinence but of poverty. If China were to achieve the same rate of energy consumption as the United States, that would nearly double world consumption. Much of the increase would probably come from burning more coal, vastly increasing the output of carbon dioxide and sulfur dioxide.</p>
        <p>One solution is to encourage the third world to use energy more efficiently that the United States does: in other words, when China puts a water heater in every house to make sure its leaders chose the most efficient one available.</p>
        <p>But the developing world seems least likely to make such choices. It seems to be polluting more and enjoying it less. A recent study by the Department of Energy found that in the United States, about 8 percent of the electricity generated is lost in transmission before it reaches the consumer. For Pakistan, the figure is 28 percent. It takes China 37 percent more energy to make a ton of paper than it takes the United States, the study reported.</p>
        <p>Some experts say that moving to very efficient practices would help the environment and also help the poor. This stands in contrast to the idea common in past decades that sound environmental practice was in conflict with economic development.</p>
        <p>'We Have to Take the Lead'</p>
        <p>''We've been the world's banker and the world's policeman before,'' said Tom Hayden, a California Assemblyman who has long been an environmentalist. ''Now instead of operating the most wasteful economy in the world, we have to take the lead in showing how environmental protection, human health and economic efficiency go together.''</p>
        <p>Some scientists say innovation can eliminate the main source of pollution in a generation. Dr. Oppenheimer, of the Environmental Defense Fund, said the United States could end its use of fossil fuels by Earth Day 2030 if Americans switched to 100 mile-per-gallon cars and mass transit, moved closer to work, used lightbulbs drawing 75 percent less current, modernized industry to grow while using less power and moved aggressively to develop renewable energy sources.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deland of the White House said, ''A sound and safe environment and a flourishing economy are two sides of the same coin.'' He said environmental improvement would require changes in the way people live their lives, but he added, ''As more and more people realize that changes in lifestyle do not result in less enjoyment or less leisure, but in cleaner air and water and better health, we will realize remarkable progress over the next 20 years.''</p>
        <p>ENDURING GROWTH</p>
        <p>More Mouths, Less Land</p>
        <p>Many experts say technological invention and economic progress will reach its limits in the face of rising population, which is now 5.3 billion and will probably be 1 billion higher by the turn of the century.</p>
        <p>That population appears to be putting more and more pressure on the planet. In the first chapter of the Bible, God gives Adam and Eve ''every herb bearing seed, which is upon the face of all the earth, and every tree,'' and Dr. Peter M. Vitousek, a Stanford biologist, said humans had taken a huge chunk of the gift. Of the total amount of energy captured by green plants worldwide, he calculated, nearly 40 percent is controlled or consumed by humans. The figure includes trees cut for lumber or paper, and grain harvested as animal feed.</p>
        <p>''That's an enormous fraction for one species to have control of,'' he said. ''It says that as the population continues to increase, we can't keep using things in a business-as-usual way.'' Dr. Vitousek's calculation also implies less and less for the other species.</p>
        <p>A growing population could be accommodated by developing plants that put more of their product into food and less into roots and leaves, he said. But right now, he went on, farmers are pumping well water for irrigation faster than it can be replenished, poisoning water with fertilizer and carrying out other steps that cannot be sustained for long. ''Our present mix of technology and population is too high,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Grains, People and Topsoil</p>
        <p>Some damaging practices are already taking their toll. Researchers at the Worldwatch Institute say world grain output, while racing ahead, is no longer racing as fast as population is. The reasons are erosion, over-irrigation and other practices that ruin farmland. The loss of protective ozone allows the entry of radiation that stunts plants as well as hurting animals. According to Worldwatch, grain output per person rose 26 percent in the 70's, but fell 2 percent in the 80's and will fall 7 percent more in the 90's.</p>
        <p>Cropland is literally disappearing, running down the rivers and blowing away with the wind, so much so that atmospheric scientists in Hawaii can tell when the spring plowing begins in China. Yet with 24 billion fewer tons of topsoil each year, the world's farmers now try to feed 86 million more people each year. That is about the amount of topsoil in Australia's wheatland. ''Those two trends cannot both continue,'' Lester R. Brown of Worldwatch said.</p>
        <p>The area under cultivation has fallen 7 percent since 1981 after rising 24 percent in the preceding three decades. The decline results partly from public policy in the United States, where farmers are paid not to grow, and partly from conversion of cropland to nonagricultural uses like housing and industry. But more of it is from erosion.</p>
        <p>The Soviet Union has abandoned 13 percent of the land on which it formerly grew grain. By 1980, India listed more than one-third of its land area as degraded, by wind, water, salt or other problems. The desert is advancing across Africa, and Latin America shows severe signs of stress. Crop yields in Africa are down 27 percent per person from their peak, and in Latin America 13 percent.</p>
        <p>The Press for Greater Output</p>
        <p>Food and development pressures do not stop at the shore. Despite numerous treaties, environmentalists say that the world still needs an effective international agreement to stop overfishing and that the lack of one has degraded oceans.</p>
        <p>The world can compensate for loss of cropland if the remaining land is more productive. Mr. Brown sees limits, however. In parts of Tamil Nadu state in India, the water table fell almost 100 feet during the 1970's; the increased agricultural production that irrigation allowed seems unlikely to be sustained.</p>
        <p>And the most productive places are in the middle and northern latitudes, where the greenhouse effect is postulated to be the strongest. And drought, like the one that hit the American plains in 1988, can result from greater heat as well as from lower rainfall.</p>
        <p>The solution may lie in finding new ways to put food on the table, or in strategies to have to set fewer plates.</p>
        <p>''The best technologies in the world,'' said Michael Fischer, executive director of the Sierra Club, ''will not save us if there are too many mouths to feed.''</p>
        <p>INVENTING CLEAN AIR: THE PACE OF PROGRESS</p>
        <p>Catalytic Converter</p>
        <p>In widespread use for a decade, the device has greatly reduced two types of pollutants emitted by tailpipes. It burns hydrocarbon molecules that did not fully combust as they passed through gasoline engines. It also splits apart nitrogen oxide that formed in gasoline combustion. A catalytic converter adds more than $400 to the cost of a car and cuts carbon monoxide emissions 76 percent and nitrogen oxide and hydrocarbon emissions 96 percent.</p>
        <p>Indutrial Scrubber</p>
        <p>Coal is cheap and abundant, but may include 3.5 sulfur. when burned, this makes sulfur dioxide, a major ingredient of acid rain. Scrubbers run smoke through lime or limestone, usually mixed with water, to bind it chemically. After two decades of improvements, the scrubbers can remove 95 percent of sulfur dioxide, but produce hundreds of thousands ot tons of waste a year at each plant. Scrubbers consume 5 percent of the energy produced by burning the coal, thereby raising total coal consumption.</p>
        <p>Photovoltaic Cell</p>
        <p>Photovoltaic cells make electricity directly from sunlight. Energy in the form of light hits the silicon of the cell and shakes loose an electron, which creates electric current. Scientists are pregressively raising the amount of energy that the cells capture, and lowering their costs; the Electric Power Research Institute, a utility consortium, says that later this decade solar cells will become cheaper than conventional power sources in the sunny Southwes</p>
        <p>AN ENVIRONMENTAL PARABLE</p>
        <p>Americans have lamps. Americans heat their water with electricity. Americans have refrigerators. These things are rare in countries like China. One American now uses as much electricity as 200 people in China.  China's leaders want their people to have refrigerators. They hope to distribute billions of light bulbs. There are big plans for hot-water heaters.</p>
        <p>Progress brings choices. Life in China is improving so quickly for so many that the choices China makes will make a big difference around the world. And there are more countries like China: with big or fast-growing populations, and with enough resources to make big leaps in the amount of electricity used.</p>
        <p>The more electricity used, the more coal burned. The more coal burned, the more pollution in the air. The more pollution, the more gasses in the air to trap heat.</p>
        <p>Some light bulbs (and water heaters) use a lot of electricity. Some do not. Good bulbs needs a fifth the electricity of bad bulbs. Good heaters need a quarter the electricity of bad heaters.</p>
        <p>A China with living standards raised to America's could avoid spewing more than 20 billion tons a year of carbon pollution into the air if it choses efficient appliances instead of inefficient appliances.</p>
        <p>Would that make a difference? That amount of pollution is more than triple the total carbon pollution now sent into the air each year by industry and other fuel users around the world.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
