<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Big Screen Pokes Fun at the Little</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="375671"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="FILM VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">JAMES, CARYN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D9163CF931A2575BC0A966958260" item-length="1385" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Big Screen Pokes Fun at the Little</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: While Bruce Willis is wiping out terrorists on the ground in ''Die Hard 2,'' a plane full of hostages is circling above Dulles Airport, carrying minor but symbolically loaded characters like a slick, creepy television reporter. William Atherton, as the same journalist whose snooping tortured the hero's family in the first ''Die Hard,'' ducks into a bathroom and phones in a live broadcast about the plane's dangerous situation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: While Bruce Willis is wiping out terrorists on the ground in ''Die Hard 2,'' a plane full of hostages is circling above Dulles Airport, carrying minor but symbolically loaded characters like a slick, creepy television reporter. William Atherton, as the same journalist whose snooping tortured the hero's family in the first ''Die Hard,'' ducks into a bathroom and phones in a live broadcast about the plane's dangerous situation.</p>
        <p>While Bruce Willis is wiping out terrorists on the ground in ''Die Hard 2,'' a plane full of hostages is circling above Dulles Airport, carrying minor but symbolically loaded characters like a slick, creepy television reporter. William Atherton, as the same journalist whose snooping tortured the hero's family in the first ''Die Hard,'' ducks into a bathroom and phones in a live broadcast about the plane's dangerous situation. In a solemn tone he pontificates, ''The truth is not among the hostages, because I, Dick Thornberg, am here to risk my life.''</p>
        <p>When he delivers that line, the caricature becomes funny and believable, all too reminiscent of the bad metaphors and inflated delivery so many television reporters seem to cultivate. But the portrayal goes beyond satire, for the film's nasty suggestion is that this character is simply doing what television journalists do best: jeopardizing the safety of innocent people.</p>
        <p>If popular culture reflects a society's most commonplace assumptions, then a remarkable number of this summer's mainstream movies are sending resentful messages about the power and silliness of television. They offer a 20th-century, electronic variation on the 18th-century query: if a tree falls in an empty forest, does it produce a sound? Today we wonder: if a plane is held hostage by terrorists and television does not report it, did anything really happen? Can a product exist without a television commercial? In movies at least, the answer is no.</p>
        <p>From that sleazy journalist in ''Die Hard 2'' to the Ted Turner-style network owner in ''Gremlins 2'' and the crime-fighting reporter in ''Teen-Age Mutant Ninja Turtles,'' the image of television may be caricatured and parodied, but it also serves as a touchstone for movie viewers. Just as seeing a distant event on television can make it seem more real, television references in movies link viewers to the fictional world of the film. However outrageous the story's events, television assures us they're real.</p>
        <p>And just as television commercials reveal more than we would like to know about the deepest wishes of our consumer society, parodies of commercials in ''Total Recall'' and ''Robocop 2'' define the social worlds of the films.</p>
        <p>There is a definite element of competitive hostility in the way these movies tweak television; the only film in which the medium serves some valuable service is ''Ninja Turtles,'' which owes much of its popularity to the television cartoon that preceded it. But even while these movies attack the competition for being omnipresent and self-important, the constant references affirm television's power to legitimize events and even to effect change.</p>
        <p>In films, television may seem a cheap link to reality and an easy target for satire, but often it is effectively used. The brightest part of ''Gremlins 2'' is not the familiar way the furry creatures multiply and create chaos in the Clamp Center office building. It is the character of the real-estate and media-tycoon Clamp, who blends the most excessive, egotistical aspects of Donald Trump and Ted Turner.</p>
        <p>By alluding to these public figures, the film situates its fantasy in a recognizable world, and television is a major factor in that setting. Clamp, who points out that viewers only like color films, owns a television empire filled with tacky, specialized programs that might, if we're unlucky, pop up on a real cable broadcast tomorrow. There is the Archery Channel and a program called ''Microwave With Marge'' that is disrupted when gremlins get into the cupboards and pots.</p>
        <p>Such arcane new programming is displacing the film's old-time hero, a horror-movie host called Grandpa Fred, in full Dracula costume with pasty white makeup and a long black cape. When the gremlins shut down the Clamp network, he recruits a young Japanese tourist who seems to have his eye permanently glued to his video camera, and they broadcast to let the world know about the gremlin takeover. As a reward, Clamp makes Grandpa Fred an anchorman, though the dunderheaded network owner tells his latest news star to get some sun and more stylish clothes. Dracula may have become a journalistic hero, but to Clamp the step from ghoul to anchorman is a matter of wardrobe. ''Gremlins 2'' coaxes the audience to identify with television and to sneer at it at once.</p>
        <p>Even when television news is viewed in a positive way, films can't resist taking a jab at the industry. April, the reporter who uses her broadcasts to help the Turtles shatter a crime ring, begins as someone the boys worship from afar - that is, from the distance of their television set. And though there is nothing true to life or to television in her extended, editorializing news reports, she is the figure who establishes for movie viewers the reality of the above-ground world, where no one suspects that talking Turtles are eating pizza in a sewer.</p>
        <p>But even this goody-goody reporter must fight a corrupt boss willing to sell out the truth. It would be foolish to perceive a weighty journalistic subtext in ''Teen-Age Mutant Ninja Turtles,'' but it would also be a mistake to ignore the film's contradictory messages about television. The noble broadcast journalist is a loner who fights the uncaring establishment for which she works; to her, objectivity seems an alien concept. Yet television is the turtles' best and most powerful ally in their fight against crime.</p>
        <p>Television plays a less conspicuous but more crucial role in ''Robocop 2,'' which begins with a parody of a commercial for ''Lethal Response,'' a product that sends an electric charge through potential car thieves. ''No need to call the police,'' promises the ''Lethal Response'' commercial (whose spokesman happens to be played by John Glover, the actor who is Clamp in ''Gremlins 2''; he must have the perfect angular face for sinister television types). The ''Lethal Response'' advertisement quickly and wittily establishes a near future where crime is rampant and the police seem useless.</p>
        <p>Throughout the film other commercials hint at the future's degenerate condition. A thick blue substance covering a beautiful model's face turns out to be ''Sun Block 5000,'' which offers ''protection for the new age,'' since ''we lost the ozone layer.'' Nothing else in ''Robocop 2'' is nearly as effective as these mock commercials, which take today's advertisments and nudge them just far enough into the future to fit the needs of the film.</p>
        <p>The parodies of commercials are less effective in ''Total Recall'' because they fail to keep pace with the film's futuristic posture. This is a world where a memory chip can simulate a vacation to Mars, yet television news and commercials remain unchanged. When Arnold Schwarzeneggar's character watches the morning news on a large panel in his kitchen, the anchorwoman's lead-ins and the news film from Mars looks remarkably like television in 1990. ''That's all for the news; stay tuned for the weather,'' the newscaster chirps. Then the screen is filled with a promo based on the kind of cheap joke that passes for futurism here: ''Tonight on ESPN, the fifth game of the World Series, live from Tokyo.''</p>
        <p>The commercial that Mr. Schwarzeneggar catches on a television in a subway car suggests that TV may be more ubiquitous in the future, but stylistically will be just like today. ''Do you dream of a vacation at the bottom of the ocean, but you can't float the bill?'' asks the ad for the memory-chip company, Rekall Inc. The commercial ends with a syrupy, lilting jingle: ''For the memory of a lifetime, Rekall, Rekall, Rekall.''</p>
        <p>Though ''Total Recall,'' with its 1990's construction workers and subways, wants to mix the recognizable and the futuristic, these archaic television programs are curiously intrusive. A medium as powerful as television would surely keep pace with a society that colonizes Mars. But like so many films, ''Total Recall'' uses television as a touchstone for today and mocks it as well, even though in this case the strategy works against the film's premise.</p>
        <p>All these films rely on the assumption that the public feels overwhelmed and assaulted by television, yet addicted to its reflections of reality. Movies have put this attitude to good comic and realistic use, but they can't quite mask their envy of all that power.</p>
        <p>FILM VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
