<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rome Journal;   Marcus Aurelius Rides Again, but Behind Glass</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="347309"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ROME (ITALY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HABERMAN, CLYDE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARCUS AURELIUS (121-180)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Rome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD8123FF935A15757C0A966958260" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rome Journal;   Marcus Aurelius Rides Again, but Behind Glass</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HABERMAN, CLYDE</byline>
      <dateline>ROME, April 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: On this day of Italian liberation, the most unliberated soul in town happened to be a figure often regarded, Shakespeare notwithstanding, as the noblest Roman of them all.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: On this day of Italian liberation, the most unliberated soul in town happened to be a figure often regarded, Shakespeare notwithstanding, as the noblest Roman of them all.</p>
        <p>On this day of Italian liberation, the most unliberated soul in town happened to be a figure often regarded, Shakespeare notwithstanding, as the noblest Roman of them all.</p>
        <p>An equestrian statue of Marcus Aurelius, Rome's philosopher-emperor of the second century, was back on the Capitoline Hill after a nine-year absence for study and cleaning.</p>
        <p>But the gilded bronze statue, considered an important symbol of this enduring capital, is not where many believe it belongs - in the center of the Piazza Campidoglio, the majestic square on the Capitoline where it was put in 1538. Instead, it has been relegated to a side courtyard, on public display but trapped behind glass in a small room where temperature and humidity levels are controlled.</p>
        <p>And there, local officials say, he will remain until they settle one of the burning issues before them: whether to return Marcus Aurelius and his horse to their old pedestal, as many here demand, or keep them under glass, confined but free of the corrosive air of modern Rome that threatens to destroy them. In a sense, it is a battle of tradition versus pollution, and for now pollution is winning.</p>
        <p>Warning of a Rail Strike</p>
        <p>For the last few days, Romans have celebrated the Emperor's return in tandem with other important events. Today was given to commemorating the day 45 years ago when Italy was freed from the last vestiges of Nazi occupation during World War II, and the country noted the occasion in familiar style, with ceremonies and warnings of a national rail strike 24 hours later.</p>
        <p>Last Saturday, April 21, was the date set aside to mark the legendary founding of the city by Romulus in 753 B.C., and there were traditional fireworks and speeches. But the real star was Marcus Aurelius, whose two-ton likeness is the only equestrian statue from ancient Rome known to have survived.</p>
        <p>Ten days earlier, he had returned to the Capitoline in a latter-day version of an imperial victory procession.</p>
        <p>Riding in a specially designed truck, while his horse rode in another, he traveled three miles through the streets of Rome, from an institute across the Tiber River, where they had been scrubbed clean, to the hill that is the seat of municipal government. Hundreds of loyal Romans on foot escorted them along the slow march, a tiny fraction of the many thousands that turned out on Rome's birthday last Saturday for the statue's first public display since 1981.</p>
        <p>It is so popular a symbol of the city's link to its glorious past that on that day alone, starting in the morning and continuing until 11 P.M., a reported 40,000 people trooped into the small side courtyard to view it in its glass cage. Yes, they said with satisfaction, Marcus Aurelius sparkled, in civil robes instead of a warrior's armor, his right hand extended in what some see as a gesture of peace.</p>
        <p>Rome Is Divided</p>
        <p>But how to keep him sparkling has divided the city council, art restorers and ordinary citizens.</p>
        <p>Some traditionalists insist that he be speedily returned to the marble pedestal in the heart of the square, designed in the 16th century by no less than Michelangelo, who had the Emperor in mind as the centerpiece. The empty pedestal there now is plain wrong, these people say.</p>
        <p>But others respond that it borders on madness to expose Marcus Aurelius once more to Rome's notorious pollution, which is bearable only to those who do not trust air that they cannot see. They say it is wiser to keep the original statue safely indoors and to put a faithful bronze copy out on the main square.</p>
        <p>Certainly, there is ample precedent for that in Italy. Michelangelo's David, standing in the Piazza della Signoria in Florence, is a copy; the original statue has been in the city's Accademia di Belle Arti since 1873. In Venice, the famous Greco-Roman bronze horses above the entrance of St. Mark's Basilica are also copies, the originals having been moved indoors long ago.</p>
        <p>Just One More Falsehood</p>
        <p>The debate over Marcus Aurelius is expected to continue for a long time, possibly years. For what it is worth, a journalist's informal survey this week of Italian visitors to the statue, an endeavor utterly devoid of scientific pretense, suggested that most thought it made sense to leave the sheltered Emperor where he now is.</p>
        <p>The director of the Capitoline Museums, Anna Mura Sommella, agreed that it was pointless to put Marcus Aurelius back on his pedestal until a substance has been found that can truly protect the bronze from acid rain and other corrosions. The statue, Dr. Sommella noted, is rather fragile in places after centuries of enduring the slings and arrows of outrageous treatment. There are even soft spots, she said, that reflect flawed attempts at restoration in the past.</p>
        <p>Yet somehow, the director added, it does not seem right to her to put a fake in the heart of Michelanglo's square. ''Little by little,'' she said with a faint sigh, ''we are getting used to the idea of a world that's entirely false.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
