<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>7 OFFER MOSCOW TECHNICAL HELP</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="460988"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="SUMMIT IN LONDON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRIVATIZATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNATIONAL MONETARY FUND (IMF)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT (IBRD)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DD133CF93BA25754C0A967958260" item-length="1039" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>7 OFFER MOSCOW TECHNICAL HELP</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, July 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Group of Seven industrialized democracies pledged today to provide large-scale technical expertise, but no substantial financial aid, to assist the Soviet Union's transition to a market economy.</p>
        <p>The leaders of the seven major capitalist powers also invited Moscow to become an associate member of the International Monetary Fund and World Bank and announced that they and their finance ministers would make regular visits to Moscow to assist its efforts toward economic change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Group of Seven industrialized democracies pledged today to provide large-scale technical expertise, but no substantial financial aid, to assist the Soviet Union's transition to a market economy.</p>
        <p>The leaders of the seven major capitalist powers also invited Moscow to become an associate member of the International Monetary Fund and World Bank and announced that they and their finance ministers would make regular visits to Moscow to assist its efforts toward economic change.</p>
        <p>After four hours of give-and-take with President Mikhail S. Gorbachev on his economic revision plans, the Group of Seven leaders also made public a six-point series of measures aimed at helping the Soviet Union's economic transition, including providing advice on rebuilding its oil economy and converting its industry from military to civilian use.  Monetary Fund's Expertise</p>
        <p>The leaders of the major industrial nations said technical aid was more appropriate than financial aid at this time because in their view, the Soviet economy was in such a shambles and changes were at such an early stage that monetary aid would be wasted.</p>
        <p>"Under the present circumstances, given the present situation in the Soviet Union, financial support would not be effective," said Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu of Japan.</p>
        <p>Group of Seven officials said making the Soviet Union a limited member of the I.M.F. would help integrate it into the world economy and provide Moscow with the fund's expertise in areas like setting up a modern banking system, privatizing enterprises and bringing down inflation.</p>
        <p>In pledging a higher form of cooperation with Mr. Gorbachev, the Group of Seven leaders strained to buttress his efforts toward change at a time when Soviet conservatives are seeking to sabotage those efforts.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister John Major of Britain said that in their meeting with Mr. Gorbachev, the seven questioned him about many economic topics, including privatization, property rights, removing price controls, reining in the money supply and breaking up monopolies.  New Rules on World Trade</p>
        <p>"What we did," Mr. Major said, "was satisfy ourselves about the intensity and the direction of reforms going on in the Soviet Union and the necessity to follow that up with continued dialogue."</p>
        <p>The declaration said that "a clear and agreed framework" in which "the center and the republics exercise their respective responsibilities" was fundamental for the success of Soviet political and economic change.</p>
        <p>The leaders said they were sensitive to the political context in which changes were being made and said they were "sensitive also to the importance" of shifting resources from military to civilian use.</p>
        <p>The Group of Seven leaders also pledged to work to complete by the end of this year a stalled round of negotiations aimed at setting new rules for more than $1 trillion in world trade.</p>
        <p>The leaders made the successful completion of the talks -- the Uruguay Round of negotiations under the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade -- one of their highest economic priorities. They committed themselves to intervene personally if their trade ministers fail to resolve the differences.</p>
        <p>Saying that liberalized trade would be a boon to third-world nations and Eastern Europe, the leaders said, "No issue has more far-reaching implications for the future prospects of the world economy than the successful conclusion of the Uruguary Round." The talks, which seek to set new rules for trade in farm goods, financial services, textiles and other areas, are named after Uruguay because they began in that country five years ago.</p>
        <p>The trade talks broke down in December after the European Community clashed with the United States, Canada and other farm-exporting nations over on how much to reduce the more than $300 billion in aid that the wealthy nations' farmers receive each year. The community refused to agree to deep farm-subsidy cuts that Washington and others were demanding.</p>
        <p>In a news conference, Mr. Major said he would consider summoning the Group of Seven leaders for a special meeting if the trade talks bog down.  Aid to Eastern Europe</p>
        <p>"If we lose this round, the big losers will be the developing nations," said Prime Minster Brian Mulroney of Canada. "Somebody has to bite some bullets."</p>
        <p>Several leaders said the European Community's new proposal to reduce farm subsidies increased the chances of a successful completion of the round.</p>
        <p>The declaration was upbeat on economics, saying the leaders "welcome the fact that there are now increasing signs of economic recovery." The declaration gave a nod to Washington's protracted appeals for lower interst rates, with all the leaders saying they commit themselves to monetary and budgetary policies that "provide the basis for lower real interest rates."</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Gorbachev's presence has dominated the summit meeting, the seven leaders took pains to reaffirm their commitment to help Eastern Europe's reform efforts.</p>
        <p>The declaration papered over differences on the environment. In their joint statement, the leaders called for establishing, within the next 12 months, a "framework convention on climate changes containing appropriate commitments" on reducing carbon dioxide and other gases believed to contribute to global warming.</p>
        <p>Several of the Group of Seven countries had been pushing for specific commitments on stabilizing carbon-dioxide emissions to 1990 levels by the year 2000 or 2005. But senior British and European Community officials said Washington had blocked an accord because of concerns that it would hurt economic growth.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups criticized the summit declaration's position on the environment as too weak. In a statement, Friends of the Earth and other environmental groups said, "The United States, the world's biggest polluter, is wrecking any prospects of an international agreement to cut emissions of carbon dioxide -- the main cause of global warming."</p>
        <p>The declaration called for reaching an agreement in principle within the next year on conserving the world's forests but environmentalists criticized the lack of progress on the subject since last year's Group of Seven meeting in Houston.</p>
        <p>SUMMIT IN LONDON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
