<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Atom Arms Labs Defend Role In the Post-Cold-War Future</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="464690"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC WEAPONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SANDIA NATIONAL LABORATORIES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LOS ALAMOS NATIONAL LABORATORY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LAWRENCE LIVERMORE NATIONAL LABORATORY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEED91330F930A3575BC0A967958260" item-length="1829" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Atom Arms Labs Defend Role In the Post-Cold-War Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Budgets for nuclear weapons will shrink with the ending of the cold war and the conclusion of the Strategic Arms Reduction Treaty, but "nuclear competence," a very expensive commodity, remains essential to the nation's defense, say directors of the laboratories that design America's nuclear weapons.</p>
        <p>Conserving that competence, which consists of specialized laboratories and equipment as well as a cadre of scientific specialists in nuclear weapons technology, now costs some $3 billion a year, not counting the cost of manufacturing the weapons themselves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Budgets for nuclear weapons will shrink with the ending of the cold war and the conclusion of the Strategic Arms Reduction Treaty, but "nuclear competence," a very expensive commodity, remains essential to the nation's defense, say directors of the laboratories that design America's nuclear weapons.</p>
        <p>Conserving that competence, which consists of specialized laboratories and equipment as well as a cadre of scientific specialists in nuclear weapons technology, now costs some $3 billion a year, not counting the cost of manufacturing the weapons themselves.</p>
        <p>With the United States nuclear arsenal of about 20,000 warheads slated for eventual reduction to 12,000, critics in Congress and elsewhere assert that continued multibillion-dollar spending on nuclear weapons plants far exceeds the reduced needs of national defense.  Administration Defends Labs</p>
        <p>But the Administration strongly opposes major reductions in the strength of the nuclear weapons laboratories.</p>
        <p>In his testimony before the Senate Committee on Energy and Natural Resources, Secretary of Energy James D. Watkins said on Tuesday that the United States must continue research in nuclear weapons to maintain nuclear deterrence in "an international scene that is multipolar rather than bipolar."</p>
        <p>Mr. Watkins, whose department pays for the nation's nuclear weapons laboratories, said that scientists from these institutions had played vital supporting roles as advisers in the negotiations for the new treaty, and that the security of the world would depend partly on the laboratories' continued technical strength.</p>
        <p>"Put bluntly," Mr. Watkins said, "even if we reduce our stockpile to just one weapon, I believe that this nation must still have a strong cadre of the world's best nuclear weapons designers and engineers, if we want to anticipate how other nations might try to build a clandestine bomb, to track the telltale signs of such activity."</p>
        <p>Critics say that the Department of Energy laboratories now design two new warheads a year, considerably fewer than during the height of the arms race, but that the laboratories' budgets and staff are only slightly smaller.</p>
        <p>Speaking for the Washington-based organization Physicians for Social Responsibility, Daryl Kimball said that the functions of two of the nuclear weapons laboratories, Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory and Los Alamos National Laboratory, could be merged, and that the money saved should be used for cleaning up nuclear waste and other contaminants from the half-century-old bomb program.</p>
        <p>"We're not sure which laboratory should be saved, but only one is necessary," he said.</p>
        <p>The laboratory directors concede that some budget cuts may be likely, but counter that the need for weapons-related research remains as great as ever, even if the strategic arms treaty signed this week is approved by the Senate.</p>
        <p>"The build-down of the nation's warhead stockpile," said Dr. Siegfried S. Hecker, director of Los Alamos National Laboratory in New Mexico, "means that the warheads we retain must be all the more reliable and effective, if we are to maintain a credible nuclear deterrence." Future Needs Unpredictable</p>
        <p>Moreover, he and the directors of the country's two other nuclear weapons laboratories said in interviews, the world is far short of achieving general nuclear disarmament, and it is impossible to predict future American needs requiring nuclear expertise in defense, deterrence, intelligence and disarmament verification.</p>
        <p>Even if the weapons laboratories' only purpose were to to detect the clandestine nuclear weapons programs of other nations, they said, this ability would be well worth the cost.</p>
        <p>Dr. Albert Narath, president of Sandia National Laboratories, said that budget cuts at all three laboratories were inevitable but that if cuts were too severe, national security would be at risk.</p>
        <p>"We all know that we'll have to take our knocks," he said, "but if the cuts are so deep that we lose our pools of experts, the nation will lose nuclear competence -- an indispensable asset in a world where nuclear proliferation has yet to be halted." Safety Issue Cited</p>
        <p>Dr. Hecker of Los Alamos said that nuclear weapons continue to become obsolete, and that the most important object in the design of new weapons was safety. Weapons need to be made even more resistance to accidental detonation, either of a nuclear charge or of the chemical explosives used to initiate the nuclear blast. A major challenge for designers has been the development of "insensitive" chemical explosives that are not easily detonated.</p>
        <p>"A Congressional advisory panel headed by Dr. Sidney Drell of Stanford University recently concluded that safety must be incorporated in future nuclear weapons themselves, not merely in the procedures used in handling them. The committee ordered top-priority competition between the nuclear weapons laboratories to develop such safety features, and that's the major thrust of our present work," Dr. Hecker said. Keeping track of the proliferation of nuclear weapons in many developing countries has become a major problem that American weapons laboratories are particularly qualified to address, according to Dr. John H. Nuckols, director of Lawrence Livermore Laboratory.</p>
        <p>"The world has had some unpleasant surprises in Iraq," he said. "Iraq's use of the calutron electromagnetic method for separating weapons-grade uranium came as quite a surprise. Our proliferation group at Livermore is rethinking these problems, with the object of reducing future surprises." New Cleanup Methods Sought</p>
        <p>Finding effective and economical methods for cleaning up the radioactive messes created by nearly a half century of nuclear-weapon production at such plants as Savannah River, S.C., and Rocky Flats, Colo., also figures prominently in the post-cold-war plans of Los Alamos and its two sister research laboratories, Lawrence Livermore Laboratory in California, and Sandia National Laboratories in Albuquerque, N.M., and Livermore, Calif.</p>
        <p>Reflecting the change in research goals, the Department of Energy has ordered the spending of $4 billion this year on cleaning up buildings, land and waterways near nuclear weapons plants that have been contaminated by various dangerous byproducts. This is more than one-third of the $10.5 billion budgeted by the department this year for nuclear weapons research, testing and production.</p>
        <p>All three nuclear weapons laboratories owe their existence to war or the threat of war.</p>
        <p>Los Alamos was founded in 1943 as part of the Manhattan Project that developed the first atomic bombs for use against the Axis. Livermore was created in 1952 during the Korean War, partly to develop a hydrogen bomb and partly to compete with Los Alamos, thereby spurring rival teams of scientists to extra effort.</p>
        <p>The founding director of Los Alamos, Dr. J. Robert Oppenheimer, and one of Livermore's founders, Dr. Edward Teller, were political as well as scientific adversaries, and the bitterness of their famous McCarthy-era dispute helped to create the competitive tradition between the laboratories that persists to this day. Under One University</p>
        <p>Both laboratories were placed under the administration of the University of California, which the Energy Department redesignated on Wednesday for another term as administrator.</p>
        <p>In 1949, the Government also created Sandia, a third nuclear-weapons laboratory, under the administration of what is today A.T. &amp; T. Bell Laboratories. Unlike Los Alamos and Livermore, Sandia does not deal directly with nuclear explosives but designs and tests other parts of nuclear weapons, including the complex electronic devices intended to allow only authorized officials to arm warheads. Much of Sandia's work is devoted to developing systems that guard against accidents or the use of weapons for nuclear blackmail or terrorism.</p>
        <p>The three laboratories are roughly equal in size. Livermore employs about 8,000, including 3,000 nuclear weapons experts, and its current budget is $1.175 billion. Los Alamos has about 7,540 employees and a budget of $928 million. Sandia has 8,500 with a budget of about $1.2 billion.</p>
        <p>Roughly one-third of the money spent by Los Alamos and Livermore is for the "core" mission -- research, development and testing of nuclear weapons. If such related fields of research as arms-reduction verification, nuclear intelligence, safeguards, security and improved nuclear processing methods are included, nuclear weapons account for somewhat more than half of the laboratory budgets. Competition Called Wasteful</p>
        <p>Los Alamos and Livermore remain in direct competition for funds, projects and scientific talent -- a fact that critics regard as wasteful. But the laboratory directors believe the competition is essential.</p>
        <p>Dr. Narath of Sandia said that although his laboratory was not itself in competition, rivalry between Los Alamos and Livermore "creates a kind of peer-review system, in which the two laboratories check each other and point out research errors and alternatives."</p>
        <p>All three laboratory directors said that their research goals began a transition from nuclear weapons as long ago as the early 1970's, and that programs unrelated to nuclear weapons benefit many branches of science. Research involving antimissile defense programs, which will continue at Livermore and Los Alamos, has produced laser systems that laboratory officials expect to benefit astronomy and other sciences. The gigantic power of computers used by the weapons laboratories to simulate the dynamics of nuclear explosions has been put to use on many other programs.</p>
        <p>Los Alamos, for instance, is a major participant in the Human Genome Project, a detailed analysis of the complete genetic code by which a human being is assembled from proteins and other substances. Besides conducting some of the analysis itself, Los Alamos is the repository of the GenBank, the national computer data base of all genetic sequence information. Work on Fusion Energy</p>
        <p>All three weapons laboratories have been deeply involved for more than a decade in efforts to exploit fusion energy -- the same source of energy that powers hydrogen bombs and stars -- as a cheap and nonpolluting alternative to the fossil fuels polluting the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>"If we are to take timely action to head off the effects of greenhouse warming," Dr. Nuckolls said, "it's essential that we move as fast as possible toward developing fusion power. The national laboratories are uniquely equipped to do this." But although directors of the laboratories feel that extracurricular projects contribute greatly to the value of their institutions, the main role of the Los Alamos, Livermore and Sandia will always be the maintenance of America's ability to wield and counter nuclear weapons.</p>
        <p>"That is our core mission," Dr. Hecker said, "and as long as the world faces threats of war, we must try to meet our responsibilities."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
