<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plumes from Deep Shape Earth and Climate</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="451870"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, WALTER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDF1E3BF932A25755C0A967958260" item-length="2404" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plumes from Deep Shape Earth and Climate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER SULLIVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GEOPHYSICISTS are constructing a new and striking history of the earth's geological past, and in particular of the great engine that pushes apart the sea floor and reshuffles the continents.</p>
        <p>The new picture has emerged from the study of "superplumes" of hot material widely believed to have risen 1,800 miles to the ocean floor from near the earth's molten core. A research ship equipped to drill deep into the ocean floor has recently brought back new evidence of the work of one of these superplumes -- great aprons of lava that were spewed across the floor of the Pacific Ocean.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GEOPHYSICISTS are constructing a new and striking history of the earth's geological past, and in particular of the great engine that pushes apart the sea floor and reshuffles the continents.</p>
        <p>The new picture has emerged from the study of "superplumes" of hot material widely believed to have risen 1,800 miles to the ocean floor from near the earth's molten core. A research ship equipped to drill deep into the ocean floor has recently brought back new evidence of the work of one of these superplumes -- great aprons of lava that were spewed across the floor of the Pacific Ocean.</p>
        <p>The activity of the superplumes may have had profound consequences for the earth's climate and life forms. During the most recent outburst of a superplume, some 120 million years ago, carbon dioxide gas was probably released in the volcanoes and would have built up in the atmosphere, producing a super greenhouse effect and setting off a vigorous worldwide bloom of plant plankton in the oceans. When the plankton blooms died and settled to the ocean floor, some experts believe, they provided the starting material for much of the world's oil.</p>
        <p>That superplume also appears to have spewed out lava beds of such size -- one is twice the area of Alaska and up to 25 miles deep -- that the oceans were raised and flooded much of the land. The superplumes, according to current thinking, are not the only force that makes the sea floor spread and the continents drift apart. But they could well give the moving floor a powerful shove, accelerating its usual glacial movement. Indeed the rate of continental drift appears to have tripled during the mid-Cretaceous period when the superplume was active..</p>
        <p>This period has long been recognized as a period in which waters rich in sea life flooded the continents, shedding to the bottom organic debris that formed such features as the white cliffs of Dover. The chalk of such cliffs, "creta" in Latin, gives the Cretaceous period its name.</p>
        <p>The underwater eruptions of the most recent superplume, according to newly determined dates, reached a peak about 120 million years ago. By about 60 million years ago, the superplume had subsided and conditions have since remained normal, although Dr. Roger L. Larson of the University of Rhode Island said that the next such superplume could be "just around the corner," geologically speaking.</p>
        <p>Evidence for such stirring events was presented at two meetings last month, one of the American Geophysical Union in Baltimore and another in Pasadena, Calif., marking the 100th anniversary of the California Institute of Technology.</p>
        <p>At the Baltimore meeting, Dr. Larson proposed that conditions initiated by the last "superplume" were responsible for creating half the world's oil, chiefly in the Persian Gulf. He suggested that an earlier superplume, which erupted 250 million years ago in the Carboniferous period, created the hot, swampy conditions that produced most of the world's coal.</p>
        <p>At the same time as the most recent "global burp," the superplume of 120 million years ago, there occurred a well-documented event in the history of the earth's magnetic field, a strange suspension of its intermittent reversals. The earth's field sometimes reverses itself, with the north pole becoming the south and vice versa. The reversals occur at irregular intervals of thousands or millions of years for reasons that are still not understood.</p>
        <p>But for a perplexing 41 million years in the mid-Cretaceous period the field remained normal. A similar long period, but with reversed polarity, apparently occurred during the Carboniferous period.</p>
        <p>The reason for such magnetic quiescence is unknown, but it must lie in the core, Dr. Larson said. One possibility, he suggested, was that a sudden release of heat from the core, forming the inferred superplume of the mid-Cretaceous period, could have induced faster circulation in the core and disrupted the process responsible for reversals. The Earth as an Apple</p>
        <p>The earth is often likened to an apple. The molten core and its solid kernel are enveloped in a rocky mantle comparable to an apple's pulp. The earth's crust is hardly much thicker, relatively speaking, than an apple's skin.</p>
        <p>From study of the shock waves transmitted deep through the earth from earthquakes, it appears that between the iron core and the rocky mantle is a transition zone about 100 miles thick. There, according to tests reported in March by scientists from the University of California at Berkeley, molten iron under extremely high pressure interacts chemically with silicate rocks like those in the mantle.</p>
        <p>The transition zone, some believe, may also contain slabs of sea floor material that have sunk all the way from the surface. One goal is to see if any such material is brought up by the plumes, demonstrating that there is complete circulation of the mantle.</p>
        <p>The original plume concept, less dramatic than that of "superplumes," was proposed in 1971 by Dr. W. Jason Morgan of Princeton University. He envisioned the earth as containing some 20 columns of hot, molten rock rising at inches or feet per year beneath key volcanic islands like Iceland and Hawaii. Each plume, like a thunderhead, would rise as a narrow column. Then, as it neared the surface and became less compressed, it would spread like a mushroom.</p>
        <p>The plumes would carry upward the heat generated by radioactivity in the mantle and, possibly, in the core. There is now little doubt among earth scientists about the existence of such plumes. The debate concerns the depth of their origin. What now appears a minority believes the plumes originate in the upper region of the mantle, rather than its base.</p>
        <p>Analyses of earthquake shock waves show that between those two parts of the mantle, at a depth of 400 miles, there is a fundamental change in composition. The change could represent the transition to a more compact form of rock in response to the greater pressure, or it could mark a change in chemical composition. Speedy Continental Drift</p>
        <p>At the Baltimore meeting it was evident that most in attendance believed the two parts of the mantle are chemically similar, that sea floor slabs that disappear into the deep ocean trenches sink all the way to the bottom of the mantle and that at least some plumes originate there. This was acknowledged by the leading skeptic, Dr. Don. L. Anderson of the Caltech Seismological Laboratory. He was outgoing president of the sponsoring organization, the American Geophysical Union, and this year's winner of its highest honor, the Bowie Medal.</p>
        <p>Dr. Anderson conceded that great changes occurred during the mid-Cretaceous period. The speed of continental drift increased threefold, he said in an interview, and new analyses indicate a migration of the planet's spin axis.</p>
        <p>The cause, he believes, was the breakup of the supercontinent, Pangaea, to form the continents of today, initiating large-scale "subduction" in which the sea floor descends into the earth, as occurs now around much of the Pacific. The formation of plumes could have been triggered from above by the reorganization of the earth's rigid plates as they drifted apart, he said. He believes the plumes formed at the base of the upper mantle, 400 miles down, rather than far deeper.</p>
        <p>After the concept of continental drift, or "plate tectonics," was accepted in the 1970's, geophysicists suggested that the mid-ocean ridges that formed as continents pulled apart could have displaced enough water to cause the rise in sea level known to have occurred during the Cretaceous period. Another explanation for the sea rise has now become available: the vast extent of the underwater plateaus formed at this period.</p>
        <p>New dates for these outpourings of lava and new estimates of their volume were presented at the Baltimore meeting. These were based partly on samples extracted from the plateaus by the Joides Resolution, the oceanographic vessel operated by the Ocean Drilling Program, an international effort based in Texas. Beneath mid-ocean water depths the ship is able to drill through thousands of feet of sediment and into the underlying rock.</p>
        <p>The largest submarine plateau on earth now appears to be the Ontong-Java Plateau, straddling the Equator east of New Guinea and north of the Solomon Islands. Last year the Joides Resolution drilled five holes into that rise. Analysis and dating of the cores from these holes, and of those from three already drilled by the ship's predecessor, the Glomar Challenger, have made it possible to document the history and development of the plateau. The 'Rolling Thunder' Process</p>
        <p>The Ontong-Java plateau, more than twice the area of Alaska, has been shown by seismic sounding to be more than 25 miles thick at its center. It was formed by extraordinary outpourings of lava between 120 million and 125 million years ago. Since then, as it was slowly carried north by motion of the sea floor, it has accumulated a covering of ocean sediment, mostly chalk and ooze, more than 3,000 feet thick.</p>
        <p>A plateau formed more recently in North America, some 14 million to 16 million years ago, and blanketed Washington and Oregon with 77,000 cubic miles of basalt. Far more extensive were the Deccan Traps deposited on western India 65 million years ago.</p>
        <p>At the Baltimore meeting Dr. Malcolm S. Pringle of the United States Geological Survey estimated that the volume of the Ontong-Java Plateau is 50 times greater than that of the Deccan Traps. In a process that he called "rolling thunder," he said that eruption of the four large plateaus of the Southern Hemisphere proceeded systematically from east to west. The eruptions began 135 million years ago with the Parana-Etendecka Platform in the South Pacific and ended 115 million years ago with formation of the Kerguelen Plateau in the southern Indian Ocean.</p>
        <p>Dr. Larson has estimated the amount of lava spread onto the earth's surface by these mid-Cretaceous eruptions, assuming that half the South Pacific plateaus had already descended into the earth as the sea floor was drawn down into deep ocean trenches. He calculates that oceanic eruptions, including those along mid-ocean ridges, increased 50 to 75 percent during the mid-Cretaceous period. That of the Ontong-Java lava, he believes, was almost 40 million cubic miles.</p>
        <p>A major contribution of Dr. Anderson's laboratory has been studying earthquake tremors whose paths traversed deep parts of the earth. Because hot rock transmits such waves more slowly than cold rock it has been possible to estimate temperatures throughout the interior .</p>
        <p>Two members of his group at Caltech, Dr. Toshiro Tanimoto and Dr. Yu-Shen Zhang, reported a critical finding from these studies. It has long been known that lava is rising into the mid-ocean ridges as the oceans spread apart. When such spreading was first proposed in the 1960's it was argued that this intrusion of lava is pushing the sea floor plates apart and is the cause of continental drift.</p>
        <p>Later it was proposed that the oceans are being pulled apart as the sea floor, having migrated far from the region of its volcanic birth and having accumulated a heavy burden of sediment, sinks by its own weight into the depths of the earth's mantle. An analogy would be a bath towel thrown into a filled tub. When one end becomes soaked and heavy it drags the rest down. Dr. Tanimoto and Dr. Zhang, on the basis of seismic data, found that hot material was rising into the ridges from depths less than 60 miles.</p>
        <p>Yet they were able to trace the hot plumes under Hawaii, the Azores and Iceland to depths greater than 100 miles. Below that, they explained, the plumes became too narrow for detection by their method. Thus it has not so far been possible to settle the plume argument by determining their depth, but the findings favor the "pull" rather than "push" theory of plate motion.</p>
        <p>Plume advocates believe such rising material plays a role in continental drift, creating a flow beneath the spreading ocean floor that gives its rigid plates an extra push. They also believe that a plume may push up a large region of the earth's surface. G. F. Davies of the Australian National University proposed that a region 5,000 feet higher than the rest of the sea floor, extending 6,000 miles from French Polynesia almost to Japan, is a remnant of the mid-Cretaceous superplume.</p>
        <p>He also pointed out that rock from plumes such as the one that formed Hawaii displays far more variability than that along mid-ocean ridges, presumably because plumes scavenge material from the base of the mantle. Sea-floor rocks have been subject to elaborate analyses in search of clues to their origin, including traces of sea floor that descended into the interior long ago.</p>
        <p>A number of papers presented in Baltimore sought to estimate how much volcanic carbon might have reached the mid-Cretaceous atmosphere, combining with oxygen to produce a "super greenhouse effect." A report by Dr. Ken Caldeira and Dr. Michael R. Rampino of New York University estimated that carbon dioxide in the air could have been 20 times the pre-industrial value, raising global temperatures about 18 degrees Fahrenheit.</p>
        <p>Dr. M. A. Arthur of Pennsylvania State University put the carbon dioxide level at 8 to 12 times normal. Much of this was said to have come from coastal volcanoes enriched with carbon derived from sediment in sea floor descending beneath them.</p>
        <p>In the May 30 issue of Nature, French scientists reported that Mount Etna is a rich source of carbon dioxide, not only from its crater but also via diffusion through its flanks. An accompanying commentary proposed that, before the industrial revolution, the world's volcanoes contributed 35 to 65 percent of what was needed to balance the loss of carbon in sedimentation.</p>
        <p>One hope for determining whether the upper and lower mantle differ chemically is analysis of specimens blasted from deep in the earth by the eruptions producing diamonds. Last month American and French scientists reported analyses of 324 fragments from such a formation at Jagersfontein, South Africa.</p>
        <p>The samples had been altered by the extreme pressure assumed to occur at depths as great as 300 miles. They contained minerals supposedly derived from sinking sea-floor slabs, but were not sufficient to determine whether those slabs had collected on the bottom of the upper mantle or were on their way to the bottom.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
