<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Technology; Mining Deep Underground for Energy</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="484709"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEAT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LOS ALAMOS NATIONAL LABORATORY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DB1530F930A35752C1A967958260" item-length="1364" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Technology; Mining Deep Underground for Energy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Across vast areas of the world, Government scientists say, it should soon be possible to drill a hole in the ground and harvest energy that is abundant and environmentally benign. This is not oil or gas, but heat.</p>
        <p>Researchers at Los Alamos National Laboratory in New Mexico are seeking to tap the heat within the earth, which comes from earth's molten core or from radioactive decay and which geologists say dwarfs the energy content of oil, coal or natural gas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Across vast areas of the world, Government scientists say, it should soon be possible to drill a hole in the ground and harvest energy that is abundant and environmentally benign. This is not oil or gas, but heat.</p>
        <p>Researchers at Los Alamos National Laboratory in New Mexico are seeking to tap the heat within the earth, which comes from earth's molten core or from radioactive decay and which geologists say dwarfs the energy content of oil, coal or natural gas.</p>
        <p>By the end of this month, after a decade of work, they hope to begin producing usable quantities of heat in the form of hot water, from the bedrock 12,000 feet under Fenton Hill, N.M. Water heated deep within the earth will be brought to the surface and used to make steam.</p>
        <p>One enthusiastic backer, Stewart Udall, a former Secretary of the Interior, said in a recent letter inviting energy specialists to a conference on geothermal heat that the technology is so promising that "at first blush, it might seem to be a product of science fiction speculation."</p>
        <p>The energy to be harvested in New Mexico is from hot dry rock, which is different from a technology already in commercial use using heat from underground. Several companies take heat from the wet rock in Rocky Mountain and Pacific Coast states to make electricity, by tapping into water that has seeped into rock that holds heat from the earth's core. But that water exists in only a few places.</p>
        <p>By contrast, after spending more than $160 million in Federal money on research and tests, Los Alamos researchers are convinced that hot dry rock is found almost everywhere, if the well is deep enough.</p>
        <p>In many places, they say, the temperature gradient between the surface and the rock below is large enough so the depth of the wells is easily within the ability of existing drilling technology. In about 2 percent of the land mass of the United States, according to Los Alamos scientists, the gradient per kilometer is greater than 45 degrees centigrade (or about 125 degrees Fahrenheit per mile), making hot dry rock practical if the electricity can be sold wholesale for 9 to 10 cents a kilowatt-hour.</p>
        <p>That price is not currently competitive with natural gas or coal plants, but it might be if credit were given for the fact that the generating system creates no carbon dioxide, the combustion product believed to cause climate change, or other pollutants.  The New Mexico test site has a slightly higher thermal gradient -- 65 degrees centigrade per kilometer -- and will bring up water at 240 degrees centigrade. Getting water that hot from a site with a smaller gradient would simply mean drilling deeper. Water not hot enough to make steam for electricity would still work well for heating homes, running factories and for meeting some needs in an electric plant.</p>
        <p>Even if a gradient of 60 to 70 degrees is required, vast parts of the western United States qualify, according to researchers.</p>
        <p>If the energy of the earth's crust could be economically tapped, the resource base would be hundreds of times larger than any now in use, according to a study published by Los Alamos in 1989.</p>
        <p>The standard measure of energy consumption from all sources is one quadrillion British thermal units. A B.T.U. is the amount of energy needed to raise the temperature of one pound of water by 1 degree Fahrenheit, and a quadrillion is a "1" with 15 zeroes. The United States consumes about 80 quadrillion B.T.U.'s annually, from coal, oil, gas, nuclear power and all other sources, but the estimated energy potential of hot dry rock nationwide is 10 million quads, the study found, more energy than this country uses in thousands of years.</p>
        <p>The Los Alamos study, which referred to the process as "mining heat," noted that many underground resources are not fully recoverable. "However, even if only 0.1 percent or 0.01 percent of the accessible hot dry rock resource base is ultimately extracted, the impact on the U.S. energy supply would be far-reaching," it said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Udall, who is chairman of the Center for Resource Management, a nonprofit organization in Salt Lake City that studies energy and environment issues, is organizing a conference next month to share information with government officials, utility officials, environmentalists and others on the potential of hot dry rock, with Los Alamos as a co-sponsor. Among the benefits he points out is that the system has no waste. The water that carries the heat from underground is re-injected through the other well, forming a closed loop.</p>
        <p>The Los Alamos test involves twin 12,000-foot wells, one for injecting water, the other for retrieving the hot water for steam. Drilling is a challenge, because by definition the rock is hot. Also, the target material is hard rock, not the softer sedimentary rock oil drillers go after. This makes the work cumbersome and costly.</p>
        <p>The reward at the bottom is rock that is very hot but also very solid. Technicians inject water at very high pressure, to open up fractures in the rock, through which the water flows. "People tell me they're less than a millimeter," said David V. Duchane, the program manager for the Los Alamos geothermal energy program. But no one is sure. "Remember," he said, "no one has ever been down there."</p>
        <p>So far the rock has not behaved exactly as expected. The original plan was to drill the ends of the two wells near each other, pump water into one and wait for it to flow to the other. But when the water was pumped in at pressure high enough to open fissures in the rock, at 2,700 pounds per square inch, the water went off in its own direction, probably following natural stress lines. Drillers had to move the bottom of the second well to find the water. Next time, said Mr. Duchane, they will drill the first hole, create the reservoir, locate it through micro-seismic tests and then drill the second well into it.</p>
        <p>Another problem, especially in the arid West, is that in an earlier test the system seemed to lose excessive amounts of water. Some of the water seemed to bleed away, but most, Mr. Duchane said, was probably absorbed by microcracks in the rock. "That can't go on forever," he said, predicting that at some point losses would drop to a small amount.</p>
        <p>Hot dry rock plants could be useful in balancing electric systems through the hours of the day, say backers. In years to come, many analysts expect windmills and solar cells to provide an increasing portion of electric power, but those sources are notoriously intermittent and must be complemented with plants that can start or stop quickly, a capability nuclear plants and most coal plants lack. Hot dry rock plants could alter output quickly.</p>
        <p>Outsiders are watching the experiment carefully. "It's not a sure thing, but it does have potential," saidDr. Evan E. Hughes, a project manager at the Electric Power Research Institute, a utility consortium in Palo Alto, Calif. "Hot dry rock could be big enough to supply virtually all the electricity we need."</p>
        <p>But the price must be competitive, he said, and "no one's going to believe it until they've seen it done." It will probably take more than a single test to demonstrate, Dr. Hughes added.</p>
        <p>John R. Bailey, a geologist in Tulsa, Okla., who is a consultant to O'Brien Energy Systems, a geothermal company, also believes hot dry rock has large-scale potential. Existing geothermal plants already produce energy for electricity and for everything from heating greenhouses to drying potato chips, he said, and hot dry rock is far more widespread.</p>
        <p>Successful fields at the moment, said Mr. Bailey and other experts, rely on having several production wells and a single well for re-injection. Thus the pair of wells at Fenton Hill will not represent the economic questions fairly.</p>
        <p>With natural gas at historic low prices, any new technologies face a stiff hurdle. But "if there were another energy crisis, this would be economically possible in the East," Mr. Bailey said.</p>
        <p>For example, he said, the Adirondack mountains in New York could be suitable, and lots of water is available there. "Ultimately, you can get hot dry rock almost anywhere, if you're willing to drill deep enough," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
