<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why Pay Ransom to OPEC?</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="430152"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSERVATION OF RESOURCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ORGANIZATION OF PETROLEUM EXPORTING COUNTRIES (OPEC)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DC113BF936A25750C0A967958260" item-length="560" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why Pay Ransom to OPEC?</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OPEC decided earlier this week to cut oil production by about a million barrels a day in an attempt to control oil prices. The modest cut -- 5 percent -- is probably enough to keep prices from collapsing, but it's unlikely to push them much above the current $18 a barrel.</p>
        <p>What price should Americans be rooting for? For some, the issue is simple: the price should be as low as possible because every extra dollar the U.S. pays OPEC is one less dollar for itself. For others, the issue is complicated by political factors: to protect the environment and reduce dependence on the politically volatile Middle East, the price should be high, perhaps even above OPEC's target of $21 a barrel, thus encouraging conservation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OPEC decided earlier this week to cut oil production by about a million barrels a day in an attempt to control oil prices. The modest cut -- 5 percent -- is probably enough to keep prices from collapsing, but it's unlikely to push them much above the current $18 a barrel.</p>
        <p>What price should Americans be rooting for? For some, the issue is simple: the price should be as low as possible because every extra dollar the U.S. pays OPEC is one less dollar for itself. For others, the issue is complicated by political factors: to protect the environment and reduce dependence on the politically volatile Middle East, the price should be high, perhaps even above OPEC's target of $21 a barrel, thus encouraging conservation.</p>
        <p>In this case, the simple idea is better. The best OPEC price is the lowest OPEC price. The need to conserve energy can be handled by piling on taxes. Taxes are paid by some Americans to other Americans. That makes a lot more sense than paying ransom to OPEC.</p>
        <p>Oil prices have been falling since the outbreak of war in the Persian Gulf and are now about the same as a year ago. With two of the largest oil exporters -- Iraq and Kuwait -- dormant, low prices might seem surprising. But oil production hasn't fallen very much because Saudi Arabia has raised its production by several million barrels a day. And demand for oil is weak because several large economies, including the U.S., are suffering economic slowdowns, if not recessions.</p>
        <p>Falling oil prices are an economic blessing for the U.S. and other oil-importing nations. Living standards rise because the nation is forced to give up less food, chemicals and computers in exchange for foreign oil. That's important for rich countries, and a matter of life and death for poor countries in Africa, Asia and South America. Falling oil prices lower production costs, thereby making investment more profitable, and give a temporary reprieve from inflation.</p>
        <p>Philip Verleger, an oil expert at the Institute for International Economics in Washington, makes a more subtle point: The U.S. needs low oil prices now to help build back stocks in anticipation of large needs next winter.</p>
        <p>The drawback of lower oil prices is that they stimulate consumption, and that creates problems.  Gasoline and other energy use pollutes air and water and contributes to global warming. Yet consumers pay for none of this damage. Nor do energy consumers pay the likely costs of future supply interruptions from the volatile Middle East or future military bills protecting Saudi Arabian and Kuwaiti oilfields.</p>
        <p>The most effective way to make consumers pay the</p>
        <p>full</p>
        <p>cost of energy is to levy higher energy taxes.  Americans would then switch to fuel-efficient cars, move closer to work, ride-share and make thousands of other decisions that would help protect the environment. And with higher energy taxes, Congress wouldn't need to micromanage new automobile technologies, light-bulb specifications and adoption of alternative fuels.</p>
        <p>The best tax would apply to all fuels, or at least all carbon-based fuels. A gasoline tax would be a good second choice. How high would the tax need to be? The estimates range from 20 cents to $2 a gallon.</p>
        <p>But disagreement over the level should not obscure the principle: Congress, not OPEC, has the responsibility to set the right price for America.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
