<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Questions, Questions, Questions</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="467306"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATHLETICS AND SPORTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LIPSYTE, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DA133CF935A2575BC0A967958260" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Questions, Questions, Questions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT LIPSYTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LIPSYTE, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERY so often I sit right down and write myself a letter. Mail is encouraging. Lately, I've posed questions. It seemed important, after four months back doing this, not to start thinking I know everything. Again.</p>
        <p>Who will replace Bud Harrelson?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERY so often I sit right down and write myself a letter. Mail is encouraging. Lately, I've posed questions. It seemed important, after four months back doing this, not to start thinking I know everything. Again.</p>
        <p>Who will replace Bud Harrelson?</p>
        <p>Nobody asked me. But maybe the author/shaman Robert Bly could deal them Iron John. The Mets need a "hairy man" mentor (this has nothing to do with the Yankees' problems with Don Mattingly), they need to drum together in the dugout. Since money, pride and even "statball" (more on that later) don't seem enough to motivate them, maybe the current men's movement could light a fire in their bellies. Of course, with their luck, just when they start bonding, when they learn to cry with Gregg Jefferies, that devil Frank Cashen will sign the first female player. She must be out there.</p>
        <p>Why do Giants fans boo Phil Simms?</p>
        <p>I don't get it either. See what happens tomorrow when they play the Jets. Or, ask a real sociologist, like the Mets' Kevin McReynolds, who had some provocative thoughts about New York sports fans when they were booing Darryl Strawberry. Cashen says New York is a "now town" with no sense of history or future. But how can anyone forget that Simms led the Giants to two Super Bowls, that he seems to be the hard-working, dedicated, sober, nonstatball performer who isn't always whining or renegotiating? Unless, of course, in a now town where drivers do not automatically make way for ambulances, Simms is the kind of role model who makes us uneasy.</p>
        <p>What will the Pats do for the Knicks?</p>
        <p>I simply don't know. Unless they've already done it. Before the basketball season even begins, while we should be sensitive to the problems of Bud and Phil, we are thinking about the dilemmas of Coach Riley and Center Ewing. Did Pat make the wrong decision by leaving broadcasting, where his hair alone justified his salary, to take a job that might dim his history in Los Angeles? Did Pat make the wrong decision by challenging his contract, losing arbitration, and risking the wrath of fans who will see him as another rich ingrate, like Strawberry? Or, will the two Pats bond through adversity, get in some hairy drumming time together, and solve each other's problems by actually winning some games?</p>
        <p>How can Bill Parcells be a member of the media?</p>
        <p>Beats me. He doesn't have Pat Riley's hair but he does have a Northern ol' boy charm, that sly, bullying wit that used to pass for hairy maleness before Iron John became the ideal mentor/coach. If this were a serious job for Bill we could care more, even hope he tells us why Giants fans boo Phil Simms, but it just looks like another former coach plowing close to the road while waiting for his next coaching job. It's certainly not as disgraceful as the government-journalism revolving door, but it will keep us trying to decode everything he says on the air. Is Bill speaking now for us or is he speaking for himself, to preserve his history and assure his future?</p>
        <p>When did Pete Rose kill Bart Giamatti?</p>
        <p>I haven't a clue. But as soon as Pete declared his innocence by attacking Howard Cosell, he became the No. 1 suspect. Pete will do or say anything for ink or air time (which I have profited from at times), but now that he is campaigning to rehabilitate his image from perpetrator to victim, the first step toward reinstatement in baseball and induction into the Hall of Fame, he has become a menace to the ozone layer. Pete was strictly a statball player and never an Iron John, and now he is charging Cosell with having written in his latest memoir, "What's Wrong With Sports" (Simon &amp; Schuster) that he caused Giamatti's heart attack. At most, Cosell implied that the stress added to such risk factors as cigarette addiction, being overweight, lack of exercise and family history. If Rose is back in the arena, we need Buddy Harrelson, the last player to stand up to him.</p>
        <p>Where have you gone, Joe DiMaggio?</p>
        <p>I haven't the foggiest. But if Joe wasn't in Central Park last night badgering Paul Simon to explain the line (Joe has said he isn't really sure what it means) he should have been knocking down the permanent left-field wall around The Nation, a weekly public-affairs magazine, that is currently deconstructing baseball's holiest time, the Clipper's 56-game hitting streak. Under the byline Gene Case is an article crammed with graphs and numbers that lead to a conclusion that calling the Streak "the premier one-season offensive record in the game" is "like saying Leroy Neiman is a greater artist than Pablo Picasso because Leroy Neiman paints at least one picture every day." Case writes that he "hates" the Streak because it unfairly casts DiMaggio as a "hero of statball . . . the substitution of personal agendas for the team agenda."</p>
        <p>Statball is a useful scaffolding from which to construct or deconstruct. It can help us understand Joe's Streak, Bill's new job, Pete's latest conniving, the Pats' dilemma and even Bud's problem. But until we can understand why Giants fans boo Phil Simms, you better keep those questions coming.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
