<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Something New Under the Sun</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="483001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="ABOUT CARS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MERCEDES-BENZ AG</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DA123DF934A15753C1A967958260" item-length="1103" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Something New Under the Sun</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marshall Schuon</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>COMING out of the camera shop, clutching newly developed photos of Caleb, my latest grandson, I realized that I was grinning. But it had nothing to do with the pictures, which I hadn't yet seen.</p>
        <p>No, it was that silver Mercedes glinting under the sun in the shopping center parking lot. The car was sort of clunky, sort of tall, but it also was an automobile with enough neat</p>
        <p>stuff</p>
        <p>to make even a jaded mouth tip up at the corners.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>COMING out of the camera shop, clutching newly developed photos of Caleb, my latest grandson, I realized that I was grinning. But it had nothing to do with the pictures, which I hadn't yet seen.</p>
        <p>No, it was that silver Mercedes glinting under the sun in the shopping center parking lot. The car was sort of clunky, sort of tall, but it also was an automobile with enough neat</p>
        <p>stuff</p>
        <p>to make even a jaded mouth tip up at the corners.</p>
        <p>Something as simple as the hood, for instance. When you pull the inside latch, the car sticks a black tongue out through its grille as a handle for the safety catch. At the other end, push the button to open the trunk and a silver handle motors forth so you can lift the lid. There are wipers on the headlights, thermopane windows all round -- and doors that close themselves.</p>
        <p>Neat.</p>
        <p>The silver car was a 400SE that Mercedes trotted out this month, one of five new S-class sedans that are here or coming soon. They are wider, taller and roomier than their predecessors, but they are also generally shorter and easier to park. The designations are 300SE, 300SD, 400SE, 500SEL and 600SEL, and they are the first new large sedans from Stuttgart in 11 years.</p>
        <p>Erich Krampe had been talking about them just last week at a meeting of the International Motor Press Association in New York. That is hardly astounding, though, because Krampe is the president of Mercedes-Benz of North America, and he views the cars as an important step toward future luxury.</p>
        <p>Right now, he said, the word seems to have lost its meaning, what with application to everything from Buick Regals to Rolls-Royces. But with pardonable self-interest he said he believes that the changing and flexible concept of luxury ultimately has its foundation in quality, durability and performance.</p>
        <p>"Around the middle of the 90's," he said, "I see a redefinition of what we call the luxury market. There will a premium market, defined by technology, image and price."</p>
        <p>In a sense, Krampe said, that has been happening for the past two decades, with technology such as antilock brakes, air bags, electronic traction control and safer car bodies being introduced by high-line manufacturers. Image also depends on individuality, he said, and that contradicts any auto maker's desire for high volume.</p>
        <p>"Whether the future will mean 'smart cars' or satellite-guided traffic control," he said, "the point is that most innovative technology will be introduced in this very special market before it finds its way into mass-produced cars."</p>
        <p>There is no question that the expensive Japanese models, notably Toyota's Lexus and Nissan's Infiniti, have hurt the sales of traditional luxury cars from Europe, but Krampe believes the Japanese penchant for mass production will ease that pinch in the future.</p>
        <p>Eventually, he said, they will begin competing more strongly against each other. And, as volumes grow, exclusivity and resale value will drop.</p>
        <p>"Some of the players will need to make tough decisions to attain either volume or image," he said. "I don't think you can do both."</p>
        <p>What he didn't have to say was that the price of his company's new S-class sedans qualify them right now as players in any premium market. The stickers begin at $69,400 for the 300SE and soar to $127,800 for the 600SEL, which carries the first production V12 engine built by Mercedes.</p>
        <p>The 400SE in the parking lot was somewhat middling, with a base of $77,900 and a take-home price of $81,665, which included an optional traction-control system at $2,565. And when I said it looked clunky, I was referring to the high roof and rump, the thick midsection and the sharply sloping nose.</p>
        <p>But all of that adds up to a steel unit-body that whispers through the wind, that is fast, that is safe and that even seems to have environmental responsibility as part of its pedigree. For one thing, only recyclable materials are used in the cars, and most plastic parts are labeled so they can easily be sorted for recycling.</p>
        <p>The S-class also uses an air-conditioning refrigerant that is free of the compounds that are meddling with the ozone layer. The cars come with their own two-zone climate system that features separate thermostats for the driver and front passenger.</p>
        <p>An optional system provides a third zone for the rear seat, and the back cabin deserves a separate zone. It is huge, and the leather couch fits comfortably, thank you. Leather, of course, coats much of the interior surface, at least that which isn't polished walnut or cloth that looks like suede.</p>
        <p>All of the new cars have smaller steering wheels than in the past, and all contain a standard air bag to complement the standard bag in the dash ahead of the passenger. Both front occupants also get a three-position memory system that remembers how they like to sit and that adjusts the driver's mirrors.</p>
        <p>The main gauge is a 160-miles per hour speedometer, which is optimistic but not outrageously so. These cars are fast.</p>
        <p>Five engines are available in the lineup, ranging from a 148-horsepower diesel to the 6-liter V12 that gives the 600SEL its 402 horses. All employ four valves per cylinder, and all are more powerful than the engines they replace.</p>
        <p>The 400SE's 4.2-liter V8 is rated at 282 horsepower, and it will move the 4,720-pound car to 60 m.p.h. in less than eight seconds. That is fairly spectacular, but perhaps the most amazing thing is the hush of all that performance.</p>
        <p>On the highway, you can't hear the engine. You can't hear the wind. In fact, about all you can hear is the sound of the tires, and that is in part because of the automatic system that Mercedes calls "soft-close" door latches. They work something like a power pull-down on an electric trunk lid, and they suck the doors tight against their rubber seals.</p>
        <p>The ride is, as always, stiff but thoroughly comfortable. And there are all the usual nice touches: wipers for the headlights, a massive sunroof that opens two ways, bins hither and yon, a windshield- washer system that heats everything including hoses and nozzles, and even a rear-view mirror that incorporates a tweeter for the stereo system.</p>
        <p>The side windows are thermopanes, designed to prevent fogging and to insulate against noise. They also are equipped with one-touch up-and-down functions, with an automatic reversing feature for safety.</p>
        <p>Yes, neat stuff. I was thinking about that, about all of it, as I popped the switchblade-type ignition key out of the case that holds the remote control for the central locking system and theft alarm. Then I went home and looked at the pictures of Caleb and grinned some more.</p>
        <p>ABOUT CARS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
