<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="447079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DD1E3CF932A15756C0A967958260" item-length="1171" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-11</p>
        <p>Soviet legislators adopted a measure granting Soviet citizens the right to travel and emigrate freely, but the bill will not take effect fully until January 1993, much later than its sponsors had hoped. Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-11</p>
        <p>Soviet legislators adopted a measure granting Soviet citizens the right to travel and emigrate freely, but the bill will not take effect fully until January 1993, much later than its sponsors had hoped. Page A1</p>
        <p>The United States lauds the bill but wants to read the details A8</p>
        <p>A team of Soviet economists arrived at Harvard University for meetings with American professors to draft a plan they hope could save the Soviet economy by offering reforms in exchange for Western aid. A7</p>
        <p>Yugoslavia says it is assured American aid will not end A3</p>
        <p>The United States will oppose lifting the trade sanctions against Iraq until President Hussein is out of power, President Bush said, hinting that the U.S. would use its Security Council veto to oppose any lifting. A1</p>
        <p>Kuwait tried to justify the sentences handed out to Kuwaitis accused of collaborating with Iraqi soldiers during the occupation. Western diplomats have appeared stunned by the trials and the stern sentences. A10</p>
        <p>Bush says Kuwait should extend fair-trial protections to all A10</p>
        <p>American soldiers entered Dohuk, putting allied troops farther into northern Iraq than before. The deliberately conspicuous display suggests that the allies may be near a decision to move forces to the city. A10</p>
        <p>Bush holds out the prospect of improved relations with Cuba A6</p>
        <p>President Lech Walesa apologized for the history of anti-Semitism in Poland. In an unusual, emotional speech before the Israeli Parliament, he told the nation's leaders, "I ask for your forgiveness." A5</p>
        <p>Nuweiba Journal: Lost secrets of Sinai are found (again) A4</p>
        <p>Violence has marred India's election. At least 40 people were killed and hundreds were wounded. There were reports of armed battles between candidates, and several cities were placed under curfew. A3</p>
        <p>South Africa forms commission on land issues for blacks A11  National A12-19</p>
        <p>The Democrats plan to outlaw quotas in hiring and promotion. The amendment to a civil rights measure is intended to blunt President Bush's criticism that such a bill would lead employers to use quotas. A1</p>
        <p>The debate on a military budget bill began. The Pentagon's $291 billion budget request is as much a captive of last year's budget agreement as it is largely free of consideration of the costs of the Persian Gulf war. A18</p>
        <p>Queen Elizabeth gives Schwarzkopf an honorary knighthood A12</p>
        <p>The new Senator from Pennsylvania, Harris Wofford, is a political insider who helped start the Peace Corps and worked with President Kennedy, but political analysts say his incumbency may be a short one. A14</p>
        <p>Senate investigation finds wide abuse in student loan program A19</p>
        <p>Judge declares mistrial in a case involving a Post reporter A16</p>
        <p>Two utilities in California announced that they would cut emissions of carbon dioxide by 20 percent in the next 20 years, largely by improving efficiency. They are the first American utilities to make such a promise. D1</p>
        <p>The New York Stock Exchange will remain open for trading beyond the 4 P.M. closing bell. Making its first step toward 24-hour trading, the Securities and Exchange Commission approved its request to extend the hours. A1</p>
        <p>Are older people effective workers? A study has found that, contrary to some perceptions, older workers can be retrained, have lower absenteeism rates and are often better salespeople than younger workers. A16</p>
        <p>Wisconsin and Chippewa Indians end fight over treaty rights A12</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court has overturned a death sentence in Idaho on the ground that the convicted murderer and his lawyer had not received "fair notice" that such a sentence was anything more than a remote possibility. A17</p>
        <p>Upper Providence Journal: A dead man is likely to be mayor A12  Regional B1-7</p>
        <p>City Councilman Robert J. Dryfoos maintains an unusual fund separate from his campaign treasury that has been used to pay for such personal expenses as clothes, trips, synagogue dues and health-club bills. A1</p>
        <p>Ever have trouble finding a toilet? Try installing one. A plan to open five public toilet kiosks in New York City has run into bureaucratic roadblocks, largely over the issue of access for the handicapped. A1</p>
        <p>Redistricting panel's chairman accused of helping an ally B6</p>
        <p>Former police chief seeks to be Queens District Attorney B3</p>
        <p>News analysis: Governor Cuomo has decided to risk an uncompromising, unpopular insistence on harsh measures to balance the budget rather than leave fiscal problems that could come to haunt him next spring. B1</p>
        <p>Will the city run out of cash without a budget deal in Albany?  B4</p>
        <p>Reporter's Notebook: Shattering the record for a late budget B4</p>
        <p>A gasoline tanker and a car collided at an intersection in the Bronx, killing five people. The crash ignited a fireball and rivers of blazing fuel that engulfed 11 stores and sparked secondary explosions in parked cars. B1</p>
        <p>The Met- and Mayor Dinkins- thank Walter Annenberg B5</p>
        <p>One man's fight to clear his name may be near an end. Choichiro Yatani, detained and nearly deported in 1986 because he appeared on the Government's list of suspect aliens, has sued to have his name removed. A1</p>
        <p>A four-day workweek was ordered for Suffolk County employees for the next 10 weeks to cope with a cash shortage and a projected $60 million budget deficit. A union plans to challenge the order.  B1</p>
        <p>A compromise smokers' rights bill was approved by New Jersey's Senate. Changes in the measure, which would prohibit discrimination against smokers at work, made it very likely that Governor Florio will sign it. B1  Business Digest D1  Science Times</p>
        <p>Indians reclaim ancestral foods for health's sake C1</p>
        <p>The Doctor's World: Thoughts on the President's illness C1</p>
        <p>Women's place in science narrows near the top C1</p>
        <p>Promising drug forces leukemia cells to behave normally C3  Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>The search for James Dean C13</p>
        <p>"Barton Fink" wins 3 prizes at Cannes C13</p>
        <p>Indian masks to be auctioned despite protests C18</p>
        <p>Comet leaving American Symphony C13</p>
        <p>Composers rediscover the public C13</p>
        <p>Film: "An Angel at My Table" C15</p>
        <p>Word and Image:Iris Murdoch defends art against Plato C17  Fashion Page B8  Obituaries D21  Sports</p>
        <p>Baseball: Kelly's on second and Sax is on third B11</p>
        <p>Yanks lose to Indians B9</p>
        <p>Mets settle on infield alignment B11</p>
        <p>Red Sox shut out Brewers B10</p>
        <p>Basketball: Riley, a master of control B9</p>
        <p>Jordan is m.v.p.  B13</p>
        <p>Hockey: Penguins need their own miracles B12</p>
        <p>The Indianapolis 500: Made in Britain D1  Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials A20</p>
        <p>Arrogance in Kuwait</p>
        <p>After Mexico, the main event</p>
        <p>A bold step toward safer blood</p>
        <p>Topics: Sudden death</p>
        <p>Letters A20</p>
        <p>A. M. Rosenthal: If I were a rich man A21</p>
        <p>Russell Baker: Allergy was all A21</p>
        <p>Aleksandar Nenadovic: Serbia, Croatia, chaos A21</p>
        <p>George J. Mitchell: Better than the Brady bill A21</p>
        <p>Jim Mullen: A prince for Passaic?  A21</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
