<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="456483"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0D8123EF933A05755C0A967958260" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International 3-11</p>
        <p>An ultimatum by the Yugoslav army was issued to the secessionist republic of Slovenia, saying that unless it agreed to a cease-fire the army would take "decisive military action." Page 1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International 3-11</p>
        <p>An ultimatum by the Yugoslav army was issued to the secessionist republic of Slovenia, saying that unless it agreed to a cease-fire the army would take "decisive military action." Page 1</p>
        <p>Slovenes seemed firm in their resolve to resist 8</p>
        <p>Next goal for Europeans: A Yugoslav political pact 8</p>
        <p>For Yugoslav-Americans, worries over bloodshed 8</p>
        <p>Kurdish leaders rejected a deal for autonomy offered by Iraq and said they would demand renegotiation of key points, raising new uncertainties about their fate as American and allied protection is being reduced. 6</p>
        <p>President Bush accused Baghdad of "cheating and lying and hiding" on the issue of nuclear inspections, as a top State Department official vowed that the United States would "solve this issue, one way or another." 6</p>
        <p>Twelve-hundred Kuwaiti refugees flee to Iraq 6</p>
        <p>A call for change within the P.L.O. is coming from a growing number of officials in the organization. The officials, stunned by the damage from supporting Iraq in war, want to dampen the role of hard-liners. 3</p>
        <p>Opposition to the Soviet Communists and momentum toward a new nationwide political movement appears to be gaining strength. A confidant of President Gorbachev said that he may be purged from the party. 11</p>
        <p>At strategic arms talks, accord proves elusive 10</p>
        <p>A plan for modernization in Pakistan at the heart of a program developed by the nation's Prime Minister, Nawaz Sharif. But experts say the program for sweeping economic and social changes is risky.  9</p>
        <p>Cuba vs. Pan Am Games: And the winner is?  7</p>
        <p>National 12-19</p>
        <p>Hazardous wastes at military bases have hampered the Defense Department's efforts to sell or lease the sites. The problem has become evident as officials prepare for a second round of base closings. 1</p>
        <p>A battle of two heart attack drugs is polarizing the medical community. Both are equally effective in saving lives, but one costs $2,200 a dose, the other as little as $76. Why do doctors prefer the expensive one? 1</p>
        <p>Global warming may be reversed for the next few years by atmospheric cooling caused by the eruption of the Mount Pinatubo volcano in the Philippines. The major factor is a chemical reaction, not a dust cloud. 1</p>
        <p>Cold season officially over but some barely noticed it 16</p>
        <p>An experiment in Chicago's schools toward decentralization began with great hope in 1989. But so far, the experiment, which empowered parent-led councils, has had more to do with politics than education.  1</p>
        <p>More schools being run by local panels 14</p>
        <p>An immigrant wave unlike any other is made up of Hispanic-Americans who, because of modern communications and transportation, can maintain ties with their culture to a degree generally not possible for others.  12</p>
        <p>News analysis: The civil rights bill has been the focus of much effort by Congress and President Bush over the last two months. Nevertheless, the two sides are no closer now than they were six months ago. 12</p>
        <p>U.S. judge is convicted in New Orleans bribe case 13</p>
        <p>Reagan requests search of '80 files 12</p>
        <p>California Assembly passes large tax increase 12  Regional 20-28</p>
        <p>New York State may have a budget. Governor Cuomo and legislative leaders announced agreement on a compromise plan to restore much of the almost $1 billion in spending vetoed earlier by the Governor.  1</p>
        <p>Albany trying to count prospective votes on gay rights 20</p>
        <p>Steps toward a budget compromise were taken by the Dinkins administration and the City Council. "We are making progress on all fronts," Mr. Dinkins said as they worked against a deadline of 12:01 A.M. tomorrow. 1</p>
        <p>Political memo: The world at City Hall turned upside down 21</p>
        <p>City Hall protests gained urgency as clock ticked down 21</p>
        <p>Leaders of Connecticut's Legislature said they would introduce Gov. Lowell Weicker's unpopular income-tax plan. It was not a sign of support for the plan, but a sense that the time for action was at hand. 20</p>
        <p>Budget talks in New Jersey stalled between the Democratic leaders of the Legislature a day before the budget deadline. The Senate president called off a session of his house to put pressure on the Assembly. 20</p>
        <p>Political Talk: The nuclear twist in Connecticut 22</p>
        <p>Biaggi released from prison28</p>
        <p>Councilman Robert J. Dryfoos of Manhattan, the target of a grand jury investigation, faces eviction from his office, garnishment of his salary and new questions about using publicly raised money for personal use.  24</p>
        <p>15-year-old wounded in shooting after crash in Bronx 27</p>
        <p>In summer, it's crickets, not gunfire 23</p>
        <p>Sharpton arrested in protest of Queens case 23</p>
        <p>New York consul general takes Israeli message to minorities 25</p>
        <p>Arts/Reviews 43-44</p>
        <p>Dance: Refracting X-change's many faces 43</p>
        <p>Music: Marian McPartland imparts intimacy to large spaces 43</p>
        <p>Campus Life 31-32</p>
        <p>Fashion 36-37</p>
        <p>Life Style 34</p>
        <p>Obituaries 26</p>
        <p>Pastimes 45-46</p>
        <p>Weddings 40-42</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
