<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: Ad Scene; When Jokes Backfire, Campaigns Explode</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="469516"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROTHENBERG, RANDALL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6D7163FF935A1575BC0A967958260" item-length="939" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: Ad Scene; When Jokes Backfire, Campaigns Explode</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDALL ROTHENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROTHENBERG, RANDALL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT may be the most powerful principle in marketing communications today, more pervasive than the "Unique Selling Proposition" that gave America "melts in your mouth, not in your hands," more potent than the theory of "Nameonics" that unleashed "Zest-fully clean." Like Newtonian physics, it operates invisibly.</p>
        <p>Yet all advertising people live and work under the First Rule of Advertising Dynamics: For every commercial, there is an equal and opposite reaction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT may be the most powerful principle in marketing communications today, more pervasive than the "Unique Selling Proposition" that gave America "melts in your mouth, not in your hands," more potent than the theory of "Nameonics" that unleashed "Zest-fully clean." Like Newtonian physics, it operates invisibly.</p>
        <p>Yet all advertising people live and work under the First Rule of Advertising Dynamics: For every commercial, there is an equal and opposite reaction.</p>
        <p>Like movies, television shows and rap records, advertising has become such a newsworthy form of entertainment that it often generates the kind of heat more often associated with films like Martin Scorsese's "Last Temptation of Christ." Sometimes, a campaign causes so much controversy that an agency must change its marketing plans -- even before anyone has seen the ads.</p>
        <p>In late 1989, to cite one example, a commercial for Drixoral cold medicine was canceled by several television networks without being broadcast after it was reported that the White House objected to the use of President Bush's picture. Nearly two years earlier, a scathing front-page review in Advertising Age of N. W. Ayer's first campaign for Burger King inflamed franchisees and helped cause the eventual dissolution of the client-agency relationship. Again, the review ran before the ads.</p>
        <p>The latest marketer to fall prey to the First Rule of Advertising Dynamics is Subaru of America.</p>
        <p>The Japanese automobile importer is about to embark on perhaps the most significant advertising campaign in its 24-year history. With the guidance of its new ad agency, Wieden &amp; Kennedy of Portland, Ore., the company is spending some $70 million to redefine its image, transforming Subarus from reliable but not necessarily fashionable cars into</p>
        <p>the</p>
        <p>vehicle for the smarter set.</p>
        <p>As part of Subaru's new image, it is introducing its first sports car, a sleek machine called the SVX. To appeal to Subaru's educated core consumer, Wieden &amp; Kennedy created print and television advertisements that satirized the standard sports car commercial's infatuation with speed.</p>
        <p>One print ad is headlined "Experience the feeling of having your head flattened out by G forces." But the copy says that experience "is excellent if you live on a race track." The "average responsible driver," it adds, is not "swayed by R.P.M.'s or speed."</p>
        <p>Likewise, in the SVX television commercial, a sarcastic announcer says the car "can reach speeds of 140 miles an hour." But he immediately follows by asking, "How important is that, with extended urban gridlock, gas at $1.38 a gallon and highways full of patrolmen?"</p>
        <p>Here is where the First Law of Advertising Dynamics came in. Auto-safety groups did not get the joke.</p>
        <p>The problem started nearly two weeks ago, when The Wall Street Journal quoted representatives of several auto-safety organizations who criticized the advertisements and called for their withdrawal. Charles A. Hurley, a vice president with the Insurance Institute for Highway Safety, called the ads "offensive and totally inappropriate." Other critics cited by the newspaper included the Center for Auto Safety and Advocates for Highway and Auto Safety, a coalition of safety groups.</p>
        <p>What The Journal did not report is that few, if any, of these organizations had actually seen the Subaru campaign at the time they attacked it, but were reacting to descriptions from a reporter who had been sent advance copies by the car company.</p>
        <p>Frances Seeger, a spokeswoman for the Insurance Institute for Highway Safety in Arlington, Va., said the organization had headlines and copy "read to us." Likewise, Judith Stone, the executive director of Advocates for Highway and Auto Safety, said the ads had been described and some of their copy read over the telephone to a representative of the group.</p>
        <p>Debra Barclay, a spokeswoman for the Center for Auto Safety in Washington, also said no one at her organization had seen the Subaru ad at the time the center complained to The Journal. "We've all been contacted with information about what the script says," she said.</p>
        <p>Chris Wackman, Subaru's marketing director, said he was mystified by the groups' reaction. "These ads are sarcastic references to the kind of advertising that is generally done for this kind of car," he said. Quoting one ad's admonition that "it's stupid, dangerous and a waste of precious fossil fuels to be breaking speed limits," he said, "I can't see that there's anything subtle about this campaign."</p>
        <p>But, as the comedian Steve Martin has sagely noted, to some people "comedy is not pretty." Ms. Stone, for example, contended that "a lot of people don't get the right message" when an ad is humorous.</p>
        <p>However premature the criticisms of Subaru's advertising, some damage appears to have been done. Although no magazines had complained about the SVX print ads, Mr. Wackman said the television networks "look as if they're going to hold us to some type of change" on the commercial. The likeliest modifications, he said, would involve the ad's joking references to the car's ability to go 140 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>In the end, the debate may well benefit Subaru, which wants to show its dealers and drivers that it is a risk-taking company willing to trust the intelligence of American consumers. Mr. Wackman conceded that the company might benefit, but said he was more reflective than exultant.</p>
        <p>"It probably will call attention to the ads, and that's fine, but I have to honestly say that it wasn't our intention to cause artificial attention," he said. "We thought we were doing it through the quality of the advertising."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
