<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Headliners; All Right, Who Turned Up the Heat?</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week In Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="414808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOUGLAS, CARLYLE C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D7173BF930A25752C0A967958260" item-length="393" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Headliners; All Right, Who Turned Up the Heat?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY CARLYLE C. DOUGLAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DOUGLAS, CARLYLE C</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE difference between global warming and a warmer-than-usual globe is that one is our fault and the other may not be. Another is that the former carries the cachet of epochal change -- melting polar ice packs, new coastlines here and there and radically new weather for everybody -- and the latter is just a bigger version of, "Hot, today, isn't it?"</p>
        <p>So the announcement last week by two different groups of climatologists that 1990 was the warmest year in recorded weather history, taken with the fact that the seven warmest years since 1880 all occurred since 1980, stimulated a new round of discussion over whether the feared global warming, driven by the human-caused greenhouse effect, has begun. Nobody was ready to say flat out that it had, but there seemed a definite shifting of opinion toward maybe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE difference between global warming and a warmer-than-usual globe is that one is our fault and the other may not be. Another is that the former carries the cachet of epochal change -- melting polar ice packs, new coastlines here and there and radically new weather for everybody -- and the latter is just a bigger version of, "Hot, today, isn't it?"</p>
        <p>So the announcement last week by two different groups of climatologists that 1990 was the warmest year in recorded weather history, taken with the fact that the seven warmest years since 1880 all occurred since 1980, stimulated a new round of discussion over whether the feared global warming, driven by the human-caused greenhouse effect, has begun. Nobody was ready to say flat out that it had, but there seemed a definite shifting of opinion toward maybe.</p>
        <p>The Goddard Institute for Space Studies in New York said that the average global temperature of 59.8 degrees in 1990 was about a quarter of a degree higher than the average in the 1980's, which were about one degree warmer than the 1880's. In Britain, scientists at the University of East Anglia and the British Meteorological Office also noted record global warmth in 1990.</p>
        <p>James E. Hansen of the Goddard Institute has previously said that the higher temperatures of the 1980's is probably attributable to the greenhouse effect, a warming caused by the accumulation of man-produced heat-trapping atmospheric gasses, mainly carbon monoxide, chlorofluorocarbons and methane. Last week he said the new figures made it more difficult to deny that greenhouse-related warming has begun.</p>
        <p>But people have been taking the earth's temperature on a regular and scientific basis for only about a century, so scientists say they cannot be sure whether the recent warm years reflect anything more than a continuance of natural climatic cycles that have been going on for ages. But they also say one never knows.</p>
        <p>James D. Angell of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration says he has been skeptical about the onset of the greenhouse effect. But, he added, "as these warmish years come one upon the other, you begin to waiver." The British team said it was still too early to conclude what caused what. Nevertheless they allowed as how the greenhouse effect was likely to have "played some role in contributing to the recent warmth."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
