<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chemists Make 'Smoke' As Solid As Plastic</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="488013"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMISTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AEROGELS (INSULATION MATERIAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PHOTOGRAPHY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INSULATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEAT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electricity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DB1131F93AA25752C1A967958260" item-length="1976" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chemists Make 'Smoke' As Solid As Plastic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AEROGELS, solid materials so light and ethereal that they are called "frozen smoke" or "San Francisco fog," have been little more than laboratory curiosities for most of the 60 years since the first one was created. But new forms of frozen smoke are now wafting from laboratories to manufacturers, who hope to exploit them in combating various threats to the environment.</p>
        <p>A chunk of the lightest of the new aerogels is so insubstantial it is difficult to see, except as a wisp of slightly bluish haze, the outlines of which are as blurred as a puff of smoke. This material, made of the same stuff as common sand, is lighter than any other solid. But despite its seeming lack of substance, it is strong enough to support astonishingly heavy weights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AEROGELS, solid materials so light and ethereal that they are called "frozen smoke" or "San Francisco fog," have been little more than laboratory curiosities for most of the 60 years since the first one was created. But new forms of frozen smoke are now wafting from laboratories to manufacturers, who hope to exploit them in combating various threats to the environment.</p>
        <p>A chunk of the lightest of the new aerogels is so insubstantial it is difficult to see, except as a wisp of slightly bluish haze, the outlines of which are as blurred as a puff of smoke. This material, made of the same stuff as common sand, is lighter than any other solid. But despite its seeming lack of substance, it is strong enough to support astonishingly heavy weights.</p>
        <p>One type of aerogel will be flown next year on the space shuttle to capture microscopic meteorite particles. Another type is used in instruments that record the faint flashes of blue light created by the passage of high-energy atomic particles through matter. Aerogels are being developed as catalysts to promote chemical reactions, as sound insulators, as elements in sonic range-finding devices used by automatic-focus cameras and as core material for windows and skylights that are virtually impermeable to heat.</p>
        <p>The lone American manufacturer of aerogels, Thermalux L.P. of Richmond, Calif., is preparing to make commercial quantities of these materials. And two national laboratories supported by the Department of Energy, Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory and Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory, both in California, are working on new aerogel formulations and uses.</p>
        <p>A potentially important use of several of the aerogels under development would be to replace the foam plastic now built into commercial and household refrigerators as thermal insulation. The tiny bubbles of chlorofluorocarbons blown into liquid plastic to make the familiar plastic foams are excellent thermal insulators. Heat flows through a chlorofluorocarbon, or CFC, only very slowly, and when bubbles of the gas are separated by microscopic plastic cells, heat transfer is even slower. But ideal though they are as insulators, CFC gases on their eventual release destroy the life-protecting ozone layer in the high atmosphere.</p>
        <p>But building refrigerators without CFC-foamed plastic poses tremendous engineering problems, especially since new Federal regulations will force American manufacturers to make refrigerators even more energy-efficient than they are now. To get along without CFC's while boosting efficiency, the next generation of refrigerators could require extremely thick walls containing some inferior insulator that would make up for the loss of the thin but efficient CFC-based insulating material now used. The change would make the new refrigerators bulkier than present-day models, or reduce their storage capacities, or both.</p>
        <p>Aerogel insulation may solve the problem, however. The best-known aerogels consist of microscopic networks of silica molecules, the same molecules that make up common beach sand. Silica aerogels are intrinsically better for the environment than foamed plastic, scientists say. Discarded plastic fills up waste dumps and creates monumental disposal problems for hospitals that receive pharmaceuticals, equipment and human organs packed in the foam. By contrast, silica aerogels used as insulating material simply disintegrate into fine sand when exposed to water, leaving no environmentally harmful residue.</p>
        <p>The empty channels and spaces in an aerogel's sponge-like structure are so minute that even bacteria and viruses cannot pass through them. And to the touch, an aerogel feels as solid as, say, a piece of glass. The particles and empty pores that make up an aerogel's structure are smaller in size than the wavelengths of visible light, a fact that makes many aerogels transparent. Despite their seeming solidity, aerogels consist mostly of air, and the lightest of them have densities only about three times greater than that of air itself. A sizable chunk of aerogel can rest on a flimsy house of cards or pile of foamy meringue without the slightest effect.</p>
        <p>Most aerogels are easily chipped or fractured. But according to Dr. Arthur J. Hunt of Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory, who founded the Thermalux company to commercialize aerogels, thin slabs of aerogel packed between hermetically sealed sheets of plastic, glass or metal are sturdy enough to be used even as structural material. When nine-tenths of the air inside such a package is pumped out, Dr. Hunt said, the result is a strong slab of insulator up to four times as effective in blocking heat flow as the same thickness of ordinary foamed plastic.</p>
        <p>Lawrence Livermore Laboratory began making and experimenting with aerogels in the mid-1980's for use in the laboratory's fusion energy program. Small pellets of aerogels used as sponges that hold heavy hydrogen fusion fuel were made into targets for powerful laser beams. The idea of such experiments was to use laser energy to implode an impregnated pellet, raising the temperature of its heavy-hydrogen contents to the point at which thermonuclear fusion begins. In recent years, fusion research in the United States has sharply declined for lack of funds. Promise as Insulators</p>
        <p>Livermore has also developed many new aerogels for other purposes, including a new group made of carbon-based resins (plastics) instead of silica. Some of the carbon-based aerogels show great promise as insulators, according to the Livermore scientist developing them, Dr. Richard W. Pekala. In common with Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory, Livermore is seeking to transfer aerogel technology to commercial enterprises while probing the complex chemistry and physics underlying these materials.</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Lawrence W. Hrubesh of Livermore, silica aerogels are polymers in which silicon and oxygen atoms are linked together like tangled strings of beads. Each "bead" is believed to be a roughly spherical cluster of about 1,000 atoms, and adjacent silica beads are linked to each other by covalent bonds -- chemical bonds to which each of the connected atoms contributes an electron.</p>
        <p>A feature of these inter-bead bonds that fascinates scientists is that they can swivel like ball-and-socket joints. This means that when an aerogel is compressed, its molecular joints can swivel enough to permit the structure to fold in on itself, filling the voids. When the pressure is released, the aerogel springs back, reverting to its original geometry.</p>
        <p>Aerogels were unknown to science until 1931, when Dr. Steven Kistler of Stanford Unversity made the first one. Scientists regard his achievement as a landmark, the potential of which has only begun to be realized.</p>
        <p>An aerogel starts out as an ordinary gel, a kind of material typified by gelatin deserts or fruit jelly. A gel consists of a sponge-like framework of protein or some other substance, in which the voids are filled with water or some other fluid. When the liquid is removed by drying, the structure ordinarily collapses because the molecules in ordinary liquids exert a force called surface tension. As the water trapped in the microscopic voids of a gel is removed, the surface tension the water exerts on the filamentary gel structure pulls this structure in on itself and crushes it.</p>
        <p>To remove liquid from a gel without wrecking its fragile supporting structure seemed as impossible as removing a single card from the bottom of a card house without knocking it down. But scientists found a way to do it using supercritical fluids.</p>
        <p>Supercritical fluids, which are unlike anything ordinarily encountered on the surface of the earth, are neither gases nor liquids, but something in between. By varying temperature and pressure, a common substance like water can be maintained as a liquid, or take the form of a solid, ice, or a gas, steam. But if temperature and pressure are raised above a certain "critical point," a substance takes the form of a supercritical fluid -- a bizarre state of matter with very useful properties.</p>
        <p>Supercritical fluid carbon dioxide, for example, has been used for a decade in Germany (and more recently by the General Foods Company's Sanka in the United States) to dissolve and extract caffeine from coffee, leaving no residue in the decaffeinated product.</p>
        <p>Silica aerogels start out with a reaction of chemicals dissolved in water, which combine to form a fine tracery of interlinked silicon and oxygen atoms entrapping microscopic channels and voids filled with water. At this stage, the gel resembles ordinary gelatin. Next, alcohol is added and allowed to diffuse into the gel, where it gradually replaces the water without disturbing the silica structure. Finally, the alcohol-substituted gel is placed in a kind of pressure cooker capable of compressing and heating the alcohol past its critical point to a supercritical state.</p>
        <p>Supercritical alcohol, unlike ordinary liquid alcohol, has no surface tension and therefore exerts no attractive force on solids in contact with it. Consequently, when the liquid alcohol trapped in the pores of a gel is converted to supercritical alcohol, it can be removed from the gel by gradually reducing the pressure. Since the fluid has no surface tension, its removal does not crush the gel's supporting silica structure. When this operation is complete, the silica skeleton remains intact, although void of liquid -- an aerogel. A Supercritical Detonation</p>
        <p>But supercritical alcohol processing can pose problems. The Airglass Company of Sweden makes aerogel material for use in high-energy physics experiments, and its method of extracting water from gel used supercritical alcohol. But in 1984 a gasket in the company's pressure vessel broke and vented supercritical alcohol, which immediately detonated. The explosion heavily damaged the plant and injured several workers.</p>
        <p>"That was one of the reasons the method we developed at Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory, which uses supercritical carbon dioxide instead of supercritical alcohol, attracted interest," Dr. Hunt said. This method, which he patented, is now used by the Thermalux company and is under study by several other research groups.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Hrubesh of Livermore points out that most of the silica aerogels produced by the carbon dioxide method disintegrate if exposed to water, while the alcohol method can produce aerogels less susceptible to humidity or water damage.</p>
        <p>To protect slabs of aerogels, Thermalux encases them between sealed sheets of plastic, metal or glass, and pumps out 90 percent of the air. Such slabs are excellent and sturdy insulators that could be incorporated in refrigerators, materials scientists say. Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory and Livermore are both working to improve the transparency of aerogels to be equal to that of window glass. It could then be used to fill the void between double sheets of window glass, providing far better insulation than the best storm window could ever offer.</p>
        <p>The only other company manufacturing aerogels, the BASF A.G. of Ludwigshaven, Germany, makes aerogel insulating material in the form of little balls that can be blown into the empty spaces between inner and outer building walls. Aerogels in this form are still too expensive to insulate ordinary buildings, but are suitable for such special applications as mobile hospital refrigerator trailers or the ultra-cold refrigerators used by infrared sensing instruments in space or on the ground.</p>
        <p>There is something about aerogels that is so appealing to many scientists that studying the material is its own reward. "I first saw a chunk of the stuff, very rare at the time, in 1980," Dr. Hunt said, "and I was so fascinated I've been working on aerogels ever since. It's been a great decade and I think aerogels are finally on their way."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
