<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Young Explorers, the Stars of Sky and Stage</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Winter Times Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="494024"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="CHILDREN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DE1638F936A25751C1A967958260" item-length="4110" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Young Explorers, the Stars of Sky and Stage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DULCIE LEIMBACH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONCE the hullabaloo of the holidays has been reduced to a hush -- after you've seen "The Nutcracker," celebrated Kwanza and New Year's, and attended a very British pantomime -- your family may be ready to settle down to facts and figures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONCE the hullabaloo of the holidays has been reduced to a hush -- after you've seen "The Nutcracker," celebrated Kwanza and New Year's, and attended a very British pantomime -- your family may be ready to settle down to facts and figures.</p>
        <p>January, February and March seem to be the months when museum education departments and New York City's Urban Park Rangers tackle the serious stuff. But they do so exuberantly. Two noteworthy events in March are the "Math Olympics" workshop for 6- and 7-year-olds at the New York Hall of Science and the park rangers' tour of the ecosystems in a secluded wetlands cove in Queens. There's also room on the schedule for astronomy, opera and crocodiles.</p>
        <p>To balance the scale, puppet shows and children's theater thrive in winter. For example, the Harbor Performing Arts Center, a professional music school in East Harlem, plans to stage a new musical, "A Wishing Well," in February. And when brain power has been overtaxed and theatrics have worn thin, legs can be stretched at track-and-field meets in various neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>Here is a sampling of activities in New York City that should keep children busy, challenged and content until spring. ALL AGES</p>
        <p>December</p>
        <p>"THE WONDERFUL STORY OF THE BABES IN THE WOODS," a new play in the form of an English "panto" (a harlequinade-pantomime tradition performed in England only at Christmastime). Performed by the New York-based Bare Bones Productions, the play by Vernon Morris, a former actor and director with the Royal Shakespeare Company, mixes burlesque and antics (like men dressing as women, and vice versa) centered on folk tales. Dec. 15 at 1 and 5 P.M.; Dec. 18-21 at 8 P.M. and Dec. 22 at 1 P.M. at the Synchronicity Space, 55 Mercer Street, SoHo. Tickets: $10 for adults, $7 for those 12 and younger. Information: (212) 808-0745. January</p>
        <p>"BEAUTY AND THE BEAST," a new Puppetworks show featuring music by Massenet, adapted for marionettes, with a live Beast (in costume) and a snail named Escargot. Jan. 4 through April 19 at the Puppetworks, 338 Sixth Avenue, at Fourth Street, Park Slope, Brooklyn. Tickets: $5 for adults, $4 for children. Information: (718) 965-3391.</p>
        <p>LOS PLENEROS DE LA 21, a concert celebration of the Three Kings Day with Los Pleneros, a plena and bomba band based in New York City, and with members of the Rincon Criollo Casita, a Puerto Rican casita in the South Bronx. Refreshments will be served. Jan. 5 at 2 P.M. at the Bronx Museum of the Arts, 1040 Grand Concourse, at 165th Street, Morrisania. Free. (Museum admission is also free on Sundays.) Information: (212) 681-6000.</p>
        <p>THREE KINGS DAY PARADE, the 15th annual parade based on the Epiphany celebration, featuring community residents dressed in costumes and live animals. Jan. 6 at 10 A.M. at El Museo del Barrio, 1230 Fifth Avenue, at 104th Street, Manhattan. Free. Information: (212) 831-7272. February</p>
        <p>CARIBBEAN CARNIVAL, a scaled-down winter version of the annual summer carnival in Brooklyn produced by the West Indian-American Day Association and sponsored by American Express. Featuring music, dance and original carnival costumes. Feb. 2 at 3 P.M. at the Brooklyn Children's Museum, 145 Brooklyn Avenue, at St. Marks Place, Crown Heights. Free with museum admission of $3. Information: (718) 735-4400.</p>
        <p>"ANOTHER SIDE OF WOLFE'S POND," an hourlong visit with the Urban Park Rangers to the secluded section of this Staten Island pond, where forest meets beach, with observations of the ecosystems. Sturdy shoes are recommended. Feb. 16 at 2 P.M. Meet at the Field House in the parking lot near Cornelia Avenue, off Hylan Boulevard, Prince Bay, S.I. Free. Information: (718) 667-6042. March</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL CAT SHOW, featuring more than 1,000 entries representing 40 breeds. With a display of cat clothes, collars, jewelry and grooming articles. March 6 from 3 to 10 P.M. and March 7 and 8 from 9 A.M. to 6 P.M. At the Arena and Rotunda, Madison Square Garden, Manhattan. Ticket prices to be announced. Information: (212) 465-6741.</p>
        <p>JUNIOR ROAD RUNNERS SERIES, for ages 2 and up. Children will run one block to one mile, depending on age. March 15 at 8:30 A.M. Central Park, entrance at 90th Street and Fifth Avenue, Manhattan. Sponsored by the New York Road Runners Club. Fee: $2 in advance for each race; $3 in the three days before the race. Information: (212) 737-7480.</p>
        <p>"A WETLANDS TREASURE," a tour of Udall's Cove in Queens, a 30-acre swamp area, with sightings of wildlife habitats, birds (herons, egrets, hawks) and possibly a fox. Led by the Urban Park Rangers. Binoculars are recommended. March 15 at 1 P.M. Meet at the northernmost end of Little Neck Parkway, at 255th Street, Little Neck, Queens. Free. Information: (718) 699-4204. 3 AND UP</p>
        <p>December</p>
        <p>"HARMONY CASTLE," a new puppet show by the creators of "Franklin the Wizard," performed by the Puppet Company; about Prince Tune, Princess Melody and King Stentor, who deal with an evil magician. Sundays at 1 and 3 P.M. through April 26 at the Metropolis Cafe's Metro Lounge, 31 Union Square West, at 16th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $7. Reservations: (212) 741-1646.</p>
        <p>"WILBUR THE CHRISTMAS MOUSE" and "SANTA CLAUS AND THE CHRISTMAS BELL," two original plays for children ages 3 to 7, produced by the Little People's Theater Company. The first is about a family with mice in their house, the second about two farmers who will do anything for money but work. Saturdays and Sundays at 1:30 and 3 P.M. through Jan. 5 at the Courtyard Playhouse, 39 Grove Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $6. Reservations: (212) 765-9540.</p>
        <p>"A CHRISTMAS CAROL," an adaptation of the Dickens classic, presented by the Westside Repertory Theater. Through Dec. 29; performances on Thursdays, Fridays and Saturdays at 8 P.M. and Sundays at 3 P.M. Tickets: $10 for adults, $8 for children. At the Westside Repertory Theater, 252 West 81st Street, Manhattan. Reservations: (212) 874-7290.</p>
        <p>"THE NUTCRACKER," featuring the New York Theater Ballet in this one-hour production especially for younger children. Saturday and Dec. 22, 23, 28, 29, 30 at 1 and 3:30 P.M. Gould Hall, 55 East 59th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $17.50 for adults, $12.50 for children 12 and under. Reservations: (212) 355-6160.</p>
        <p>"THE GIFT OF THE MAGI," a musical version of the O. Henry classic performed by the Interborough Repertory Theater. Dec. 27, 28 and 29 at 3 and 7 P.M. at the Don Quijote Experimental Children's Theater, 250 West 65th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $4. Information: (718) 522-2858.</p>
        <p>"NUTCRACKER AND THE MOUSE KING," an original musical adaptation based on the "Nutcracker" story, with song, dance and a sword duel. For ages 4 to 12. Presented by the Interborough Repertory Theater of New York. Dec. 28 and 29 at 2 P.M. at the Henry Street Settlement, Harry De Jur Playhouse, 466 Grand Street, Lower East Side. Tickets: $3 for adults, $2.50 for children. Information: (212) 598-0400. January</p>
        <p>"STORIES FROM AFRICA," featuring the storyteller Black Light and the Shadow puppets. Jan. 11 and 12 at 10:30 A.M. and noon at Puppet Playhouse, Asphalt Green, 555 East 90th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $3.50. Reservations: (212) 369-8890.</p>
        <p>"TUBBY THE TUBA," a children's concert by the Bronx Arts Ensemble based on the Paul Tripp story about a tuba that seems to wait forever for a chance to play a solo. With an introduction to the orchestra and audience participation. Jan. 19 at 2 P.M. at the Riverdale Y.M.-Y.W.H.A., 5625 Arlington Avenue, Riverdale, the Bronx. Tickets: $6. Information: (212) 601-7399.</p>
        <p>"YOU WON'T BELIEVE THIS, BUT," the Paper Bag Players' new musical, in which a runaway leak is chased by a plumber and caught when the audience lends a hand. Featuring a little girl, a dancing crocodile and a mystery at a country fair, all presented in skitlike formats with a one-man band. For children up to 10 years old. Saturdays and Sundays at 2 P.M. from Jan. 25 to March 8 at Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $12. Information: (212) 864-5400. February</p>
        <p>"THE HOBBIT," a puppet adaptation of J. R. R. Tolkien's fantastical tale, produced by Montreal's Theatre Sans Fils. Feb. 8 at 2 P.M. at the Brooklyn Academy of Music, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene. Tickets: $12 for adults, $7 for children. Information: (718) 636-4100 or (212) 307-4100 (Ticketmaster).</p>
        <p>"CINDERELLA," performed by the Herrick Marionettes. Feb. 22 and 23 at 10:30 A.M. and noon at Puppet Playhouse, Asphalt Green, 555 East 90th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $3.50. Reservations: (212) 369-8890.</p>
        <p>HARLEM GLOBETROTTERS, the entertaining basketball team now in its 65th year, featuring unusual basketball skills and audience participation. On Feb. 22 at 1 P.M., the Arena, Madison Square Garden, Manhattan. Tickets: $11 to $18. Information: (212) 465-6741. March</p>
        <p>"THE ORCHESTRA -- A HAPPY FAMILY," a concert in the Lolli-Pops series for children ages 3 to 5 that will introduce sections of the orchestra through the characters of Bow the Panda, Toot the Bird, Buzz the Bee and Bang the Lion. March 7 at 10:15 and 11:30 A.M.; March 8 at 1:15 and 2:30 P.M. Presented by the Little Orchestra Society at Gould Hall, 55 East 59th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $30. Information: (212) 704-2100.</p>
        <p>"DINOSAUR POWER," a three-part program to teach "future curators" 3 and 4 years old how life would have been different had dinosaurs not walked the earth; with an introduction to fossil fuels. March 10, 17 and 24 from 9:30 to 11 A.M. Staten Island Institute of Arts and Sciences, 75 Stuyvesant Place, St. George. Fee for the three workshops: $35 for nonmembers (including one adult), $25 for members. Information: (718) 727-1135.</p>
        <p>"BEARS," a program for children ages 4 to 6, who will find out how brown-bear mothers care for their cubs, what makes polar bears good swimmers, and how some bears sleep through winter without a meal. With songs, storytelling and crafts. March 14 from 10:30 A.M. to noon at the Bronx Zoo, Fordham Road at the Bronx River Parkway in the Fordham section. Fee: $17 for members, $19 for nonmembers. (Parents need not attend.) Information: (212) 367-1010.</p>
        <p>"PLAYING PURIM," a performance workshop for ages 3 and up, in which children will play characters from the biblical story of Esther. March 15 at 11 A.M. and 1 P.M. at the Jewish Museum at the New-York Historical Society, Central Park West at 77th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $5 for members, $7 for nonmembers. Reservations: (212) 399-3368. 5 AND UP</p>
        <p>December</p>
        <p>"B.O.T.C.H.: ADVENTURES IN THE LAND BELOW," a new jazz musical about children themselves lost in the subways. Written by Jon Agee. Presented by Tada, the children's theater company. Through Jan. 19 at the Tada Theater, 120 West 28th Street, Manhattan. Performances: Fridays, 7:30 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 and 3:30 P.M. Special holiday shows, at 1 and 3:30 P.M. on Dec. 23, 27, 30 and 31. Tickets: $7 for adults, $5 for children. Reservations: (212) 627-1732.</p>
        <p>"PETER PAN,"the return engagement of the Broadway production, featuring Cathy Rigby in the title role. Through Jan. 5 at the Minskoff Theater, 200 West 45th Street, Manhattan. Tuesday, Wednesday, Friday and Saturday at 7:30 P.M.; matinees on Tuesdays at 3 P.M. and Wednesdays through Sundays at 2 P.M. Tickets: $20 to $50. Information: (212) 307-4100.</p>
        <p>"SEE ME SHARE MY WORLD: UNDERSTANDING THE THIRD WORLD THROUGH CHILDREN'S ART," an interactive exhibition presenting children's drawings from Colombia, Honduras, India and Sierra Leone, focusing on daily life. Through Jan. 6 at the Brooklyn Children's Museum, 145 Brooklyn Avenue, at St. Marks Place, Crown Heights. Museum hours: Wednesday, Thursday and Friday, 2 to 5 P.M., and Saturday and Sunday from noon to 5 P.M. Suggested admission: $3. Information: (718) 735-4400.</p>
        <p>"YOU'RE A GOOD MAN, CHARLIE BROWN," a new version of the musical about the Peanuts characters, based on the comic strip by Charles Schulz. By On Stage Productions. Fridays at 7 P.M, Saturdays at 3 and 7 P.M. and Sundays at 3 P.M. through Jan. 19 at the Hartley House Theater, 413 West 46th Street, Manhattan. Special holiday performances Dec. 27 and Dec. 31 at 3 P.M. Tickets: $10 for adults, $8 for children. Information: (212) 666-1716.</p>
        <p>"THE ADVENTURES OF PINOCCHIO," the famous marionette's story told with Italian-made marionettes by the Teatro delle Marionette degli Accettella, in Italian; for ages 6 and up. Dec. 15 at 2 P.M. at the Henry Street Settlement, Harry De Jur Playhouse, 466 Grand Street, Lower East Side. Suggested donation: $3 for adults, $2.50 for children. Information: (212) 598-0400.</p>
        <p>KWANZA CELEBRATION, with music, poetry and dance presented by Waliyaya, a New York-based ethno-musicologist, teacher, poet and musician. Dec. 15 at 2:30 P.M. at the Brooklyn Children's Museum, 145 Brooklyn Avenue, at St. Marks Avenue, Crown Heights. Suggested admission: $3. Information: (718) 735-4400.</p>
        <p>"THE MIKADO," the operetta presented by the New York Gilbert and Sullivan Players, for children, with tongue-twister lyrics and fast-paced comedy. Dec. 26 through Jan. 5 at Symphony Space, Broadway at 95th Street, Manhattan. Performances Dec. 26 and 28 and Jan. 4 at 3 and 8 P.M.; Dec. 27 and 31 and Jan. 2 and 3 at 8 P.M. and Dec. 29 and Jan. 5 at 3 P.M.; no shows on New Year's Day. Tickets: $20 to $35; children receive a $5 discount. Information: (212) 769-1000. January</p>
        <p>"FISHY CALENDAR" and "SEA CREATURE PUPPETS," workshops at which children can make fish prints to decorate 1992 calendars (Jan. 5 or Jan. 12) and design a sea creature puppet (Jan. 19 or Jan. 26) using a variety of colorful art materials. Both at 2 P.M. at the Children's Center, South Street Seaport Museum, 165 John Street, Manhattan. Free with museum admission of $6 for adults and $3 for children. Information: (212) 669-9400.</p>
        <p>TRACK MEET, for children 6 and up, to compete in sprints (up to 3,000 meters), a one-mile race-walk, distance running, relay races, and high and long jumps. Sponsored by the Metropolitan Athletic Congress. Jan. 5 from 1 to 6 P.M. At Fordham University, Lombardi Center, Fordham Road and Southern Boulevard, Bedford Park, the Bronx. Fee: $4 per event; sign up the day of the meet. Information: (212) 227-0071.</p>
        <p>DUMPLING MAKING, a workshop at which children ages 5 and up will learn how to prepare, pinch, boil and dip Chinese dumplings. Jan. 11 from 10:30 A.M. to 12:30 P.M. at the China Institute in America, 125 East 65th Street, Manhattan. Fee: $10, including refreshments. Registration: (212) 744-8181.</p>
        <p>"FREEDOM TRAIN," a Theater works/USA revival, using dance, mime and traditional music to tell the story of Harriet Tubman and the Underground Railroad. Jan. 11, 12, 18 and 19 at 12:30 P.M. at the Promenade Theater, 2162 Broadway, at 76th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $15. Information: (212) 677-5959 or (212) 307-7171 (Ticketmaster).</p>
        <p>"GROWING UP WITH OPERA," a family program featuring the 90-minute Donizetti comic opera "Don Pasquale," in English, set in New York City in the 1920's. Sponsored by the Metropolitan Opera Guild. Jan. 12 and 18 at 2 P.M. at the Kathryn Bache Miller Theater, Broadway at 116th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $24. Information: (212) 769-7022.</p>
        <p>"JAZZ FOR JUNIORS," a jazz program featuring an ensemble and using audience participation to introduce musical improvisation. For ages 5 and up. Sponsored by the Henry Street Music School. Jan. 12 at 2 P.M. at the Henry Street Settlement, Louis Abrons Arts Center, 466 Grand Street, Lower East Side. Tickets: $3 for adults, $2.50 for children. Information: (212) 598-0400. February</p>
        <p>"RAPUNZEL," a Theaterworks/USA production with music, based on the classic story with some contemporary twists that focus on tensions between parents and children. Feb. 1, 2 and 9 P.M. at the Promenade Theater, 2162 Broadway, at 76th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $15. Information: (212) 677-5959 or (212) 307-7171 (Ticketmaster).</p>
        <p>"THE AFRICAN DRUM," an original shadow-puppet play with African drum music. Four interwoven African folk tales about a little girl, her animal friends and Zimwe, a bad man who tricks her. Presented by the Shadow Box Theater. Feb. 7, 14 and 28 at 10 and 11:15 A.M., and March 2 to 6 at 10:30 A.M. At the Y.W.C.A. of Brooklyn, 30 Third Avenue, at Atlantic Avenue, Boerum Hill. Tickets: $3.50. Reservations: (212) 724-0677.</p>
        <p>"BE MINE," a daylong family workshop at which participants will make scented sachets from potpourri, valentines with pressed flowers and lace, and mini-bouquets with dried flowers. Feb. 9 from 10:30 A.M. to 12:30 P.M. and from 2 to 4 P.M. At the New York Botanical Garden, 200th Street and Southern Boulevard, Bedford Park, the Bronx. Fee: $25 for nonmembers, $23 for members (admits one child and one adult). Information: (212) 220-8982.</p>
        <p>"CHARLOTTE'S WEB," an adaptation of the E. B. White book about the unlikely friendship between a spider and a pig, presented by the California Theater Center. Feb. 15 at 11 A.M. and 1 P.M. at the Triplex Theater, 199 Chambers Street, TriBeCa. Tickets: $7. Reservations: (212) 618-1980. March</p>
        <p>"MATH OLYMPICS," a program for children ages 6 and 7, where they will play logic games from around the world, including Nim, a Chinese reasoning game, and an African bean game. March 7 from 2 to 3:15 P.M. and March 8 from 1 to 2:15 P.M. at the New York Hall of Science, 47-01 111th Street, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, Queens. Fee per session: $10 for members, $12 for nonmembers (accompanying adults, $3.50). Reservations: (718) 699-0005.</p>
        <p>"ON TAP," featuring the legendary tap master James (Buster) Brown, who will perform with others shim-shamming their way through tap-dance history; presented by the Circuit Theater of Brooklyn, with a live jazz band. March 7 at 2 P.M. at the Brooklyn Academy of Music, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene. Tickets: $12 for adults, $7 for children. Information: (718) 636-4100 or (212) 307-4100 (Ticketmaster).</p>
        <p>"THE BAD, THE GOOD AND THE BEAUTIFUL," a program for ages 5 to 7, focusing on Purim, the celebration of the story of Esther in the Bible. Children will be read the story, act it out, wear masks and sing. March 8 at 10:30 and 11:30 A.M. at the Jewish Museum at the New-York Historical Society, Central Park West at 77th Street, Manhattan. Fee: $5 for members, $7 for nonmembers. Reservations: (212) 399-3368.</p>
        <p>"SLEEPING BEAUTY," a musical adaptation for ages 5 and up of the Perrault fairy tale with some new twists by Theater IV, a Virginia company. March 14 at 11 A.M. and 1 P.M. at the Triplex Theater, 199 Chambers Street, TriBeCa. Tickets: $7. Information: (212) 618-1980.</p>
        <p>TRACK AND FIELD PROGRAM, for ages 5 to 12, where children will practice and compete in the long and high jumps, shot put, sprints, hurdles, relays and distance running. March 15 at 2 P.M. Fee: $10 covers eight weeks, with drop-ins welcome. Asphalt Green, 555 East 90th Street, Manhattan. Information: (212) 737-7480. 7 AND UP</p>
        <p>December</p>
        <p>"BEADWORK: CORN HUSK DOLLS AND CRADLEBOARDS," an exhibition demonstrating the craft, design and technique of making corn husk dolls and cradleboards for carrying babies on the back, featuring the work of Tammy Rahr, a Cayuga Indian. Through March 15 at the Smithsonian Institution's National Museum of the American Indian, 3753 Broadway, at 155th Street, Manhattan. Museum hours: Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sunday from 1 to 5 P.M. Admission: $3 for adults; free for ages 7 and under. Information: (212) 283-2420.</p>
        <p>"EAGLE OR SUN," a return engagement for an adaptation of "The Broken Spears," a book written by the Aztecs about the Spanish conquest of Mexico. Presented by the Open Eye Theater, 270 West 89th Street, Manhattan. Dec. 21 and 28 at 8 P.M. and Dec. 22 and 29 at 2 P.M. Tickets: $10 for adults, $6 for children. Information: (212) 769-4143.</p>
        <p>15TH ANNUAL CANDLELIGHT CHRISTMAS CONCERT, with the Little Orchestra Society, the Metropolitan Singers, the Greek Choral Society, the soprano Andrea Del Giudice and the baritone Gary Simpson performing such music as Britten's "Ceremony of Carols," "Away in a Manger" and "Hark! The Herald Angels Sing." Dec. 21 at 7 P.M. at the Greek Orthodox Archdiocesan Cathedral of the Holy Trinity, 319 East 74th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $25 to $100. Information: (212) 704-2100.</p>
        <p>HOLIDAY SONGFEST, featuring the American Boychoir singing music spanning several centuries, from Georg Philipp Telemann to Britten's "Ceremony of Carols," as well as traditional Jewish melodies, spirituals and popular songs of the 1940's. Dec. 22 at 2 P.M. in Whitman Hall, Brooklyn Center for the Performing Arts, Brooklyn College, Campus Road and Hillel Place, Flatbush. Tickets: $17 to $24. Information: (718) 434-1900. January</p>
        <p>"ASTRONOMY NIGHT," where participants will watch a slide program indoors and then looking up at the night sky outdoors for winter constellations; led by an amateur astronomer. Jan. 10 at 7:30 P.M. at the Gateway National Recreation Area, Building One, Breezy Point district, Fort Tilden, Queens (near Jacob Riis Park). Free. Information: (718) 474-4600.</p>
        <p>"WINTER WONDERS BEACH WALK," a two-hour program in which families and others will explore the beach at Breezy Point in its winter state, with a special eye on looking for birds and sea life; led by a park ranger. Jan. 12 at 10 A.M. at the Gateway National Recreation Area, Building One, Breezy Point district, Fort Tilden, Queens (near Jacob Riis Park). Free. Information: (718) 474-4600.</p>
        <p>"A WOMAN CALLED TRUTH," a dramatic play about Sojourner Truth. Presented by the Open Eye: New Stagings for Youth. Jan. 18 to March 1 with shows Saturdays at 8 P.M. and Sundays at 2 P.M. at the Open Eye Theater, 270 West 89th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $10 for adults, $6 for children. Information: (212) 769-4143. February</p>
        <p>QUEENS TEEN TALENT SHOWCASE PERFORMANCE, an annual event sponsored by the Queens Council on the Arts, featuring teen-agers from the borough who are aspiring singers, dancers and rappers and who have auditioned for the show. Feb. 1 at 7:30 P.M. at La Guardia Community College, 31-10 Thomson Avenue, Long Island City, Queens. Tickets: free, available by sending a self-addressed stamped envelope to the council at 161-04 Jamaica Avenue, Jamaica, Queens 11432. Information: (718) 291-1100 or (718) 291-2787 (recording).</p>
        <p>"BASTIEN UND BASTIENNE," the singspiel composed by Mozart at age 12, based on a love story; in English. Presented by the Little Orchestra Society for the Happy Concerts for Young People series in collaboration with Lincoln Center's Mozart Bicentennial Celebration. Feb. 8 at 11 A.M. and 1 P.M. at Avery Fisher Hall. Tickets: $15 to $28. Information: (212) 704-2100.</p>
        <p>"HEIDI," a new musical by Theaterworks/USA, based on Johanna Spyri's book about the Swiss orphan who is sent to live with her grandfather and turns his heart around. Feb. 15, 16, 22 and 23 and March 1, 7 and 8 at 12:30 P.M. at the Promenade Theater, 2162 Broadway, at 76th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $15. Information: (212) 677-5959 or (212) 307-7171 (Ticketmaster).</p>
        <p>"ALWAYS SMILE AT A CROCODILE," a workshop for ages 7 to 11, at which children will see the new chameleon exhibition and learn about crocodiles, pythons and turtles. Feb. 23 from 10 A.M. to noon at the Bronx Zoo, Fordham Road at the Bronx River Parkway, Fordham. Fee: $17 for members, $19 for nonmembers. Information: (212) 367-1010.</p>
        <p>"A WISHING WELL," a new original musical about children from East Harlem and their experiences, featuring child actors from the theater department of the Harbor Performing Arts Complex. Feb. 27 at 6:30 P.M. and Feb. 29, March 7, 14, 15, 21 and 22 at 2 P.M. at the Harbor Performing Arts Complex, 1 East 104th Street, Manhattan. Tickets, $5. Information: (212) 427-2244. March</p>
        <p>"TRUE COLORS," a science workshop where 8- and 9-year-olds will learn about chromatography through detective techniques like ink separation and use of chemical indicators like red cabbage and grape juice to reveal acids and bases. March 14 from 2 to 3:15 P.M. and March 15 from 1 to 2:15 P.M. at the New York Hall of Science, 47-01 111th Street, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, Queens. Fee: $10 for members, $12 for nonmembers, $3.50 for each accompanying adult. Reservations: (718) 699-0005.</p>
        <p>"CONCERTS FOR KIDS," exploring Jewish musical traditions, focusing on Ethiopian and Moroccan Jews. March 22 at 1 P.M. at Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan. Tickets: $10. Information: (212) 362-8060.  CHILDREN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
