<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Headliners; Pollution, a New Worry for Smokey the Bear</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week In Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="443478"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D71F30F936A35756C0A967958260" item-length="338" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Headliners; Pollution, a New Worry for Smokey the Bear</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By B. DRUMMOND AYERS JR.</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BY definition, parks are meant to be restful places. But rest and retreat are increasingly difficult to come by in many national parks. There are too many cars, too many hikers, too many campers, too many climbers, fishermen and bird lovers, and too many developers crowding subdivisions and ranchettes up against park boundaries.</p>
        <p>Worse, there is now air pollution, an obscuring haze of acidic sulfates and searing ozone blown in from coal-fired plants and vehicle-choked cities. Some parks are slowly dying, their fragile trout streams, lakes, trees and flowers weakened and poisoned by toxic clouds and the acid rain that falls from them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BY definition, parks are meant to be restful places. But rest and retreat are increasingly difficult to come by in many national parks. There are too many cars, too many hikers, too many campers, too many climbers, fishermen and bird lovers, and too many developers crowding subdivisions and ranchettes up against park boundaries.</p>
        <p>Worse, there is now air pollution, an obscuring haze of acidic sulfates and searing ozone blown in from coal-fired plants and vehicle-choked cities. Some parks are slowly dying, their fragile trout streams, lakes, trees and flowers weakened and poisoned by toxic clouds and the acid rain that falls from them.</p>
        <p>The pollution problem is so serious in several parks, most notably Shenandoah National Park in the Blue Ridge Mountains of northern Virginia, that the National Park Service has proposed that the country rethink its industrial development policies. Abandoning its gentle Smokey the Bear role, the Park Service is vigorously opposing construction of new power plants, warning that two coal-fired installations planned for southern Virginia would hasten the demise of a park where some fish and trees are already dying. If the plants must be built, the Park Service says, the power companies should be required to offset new pollution by fitting old plants with more efficient controls.</p>
        <p>Environmental officials in Virginia and at the Federal Environmental Protection Agency contend that the plants would do no further harm to the park, famed for its scenic Skyline Drive that stretches from peak to peak for almost a hundred miles.</p>
        <p>Many environmentalists believe the White House will eventually be forced to take sides in the dispute. Meanwhile, Park Service officials say, they will continue to oppose construction of the plants in Virginia and more carefully monitor air pollution problems affecting other parks, in particular Great Smoky Mountains National Park on the North Carolina-Tennessee border, Acadia National Park in Maine and Grand Canyon National Park in Arizona.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
