<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Bell Tolls for Rain Forests</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="438433"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWN, MALCOLM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6D8143DF93AA25757C0A967958260" item-length="984" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Bell Tolls for Rain Forests</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWN, MALCOLM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT now takes less than 40 years for the human race to double, and there are few consequences of the population explosion more striking than the obliteration of the world's rain forests. The American Museum of Natural History has opened an exhibition dedicated to the natural treasure we are rapidly losing.</p>
        <p>Most Americans are at least vaguely aware that the global appetite for beef, lumber and land is cutting into rain forests at an almost unbelievable rate. According to United Nations statistics, an area of rain forest five times the size of Manhattan is felled every day -- a rate that would eliminate all rain forests by the year 2081.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT now takes less than 40 years for the human race to double, and there are few consequences of the population explosion more striking than the obliteration of the world's rain forests. The American Museum of Natural History has opened an exhibition dedicated to the natural treasure we are rapidly losing.</p>
        <p>Most Americans are at least vaguely aware that the global appetite for beef, lumber and land is cutting into rain forests at an almost unbelievable rate. According to United Nations statistics, an area of rain forest five times the size of Manhattan is felled every day -- a rate that would eliminate all rain forests by the year 2081.</p>
        <p>The new show, "Tropical Rain Forests: A Disappearing Treasure," running through June 2, was organized by the Smithsonian Institution Traveling Exhibitions Service in cooperation with the World Wildlife Fund. While the organizers of the exhibition deplore the destruction of rain forests, the displays are essentially tutorial and evenhanded. The points of view of various classes of people involved in the depletion of the Amazon rain forests are effectively presented by short recorded statements from a forest Indian, a jungle colonist, a rancher, a banker and a naturalist. A computer display asks the visitor to choose one of several strategies for saving rain forests, then responds by explaining the pitfalls of whatever choice is made.</p>
        <p>Whatever justification various economic groups may find for cutting into the rain forests, their activities are costing the world's pool of animal and plant species dearly, as the exhibition underscores; lemurs, kinkajous, jaguars, Bengal tigers, various chameleons and many birds are among the tens or hundreds of thousands of species facing extinction because of their loss of habitat.</p>
        <p>Diagrams, dioramas and photographs demonstrate how the damage can extend far beyond the dying rain forests themselves. Destruction of forests causes soil erosion and the silting of rivers and their deltas, for instance, and the silt is carried offshore and kills coral reefs, which are the habitats for many marine animals. The loss of rain-forest species may rob future scientists of clues to the design of new drugs with important therapeutic properties, the exhibition shows; among the pharmaceuticals that already owe their origins to natural products of the rain forests are heart medicines and tranquilizers.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most devastating long-term effect of loss of rain forests will be climatic. Rain-forest vegetation is a voracious consumer of atmospheric carbon dioxide, which is increasing at a troubling rate. Many scientists say most of the increase is a direct result of the population explosion and the increased burning of organic fuels (oil, coal, gas and wood). Carbon dioxide is a greenhouse gas because it traps the energy of sunlight and heats the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>If, as many scientists believe, this warming is inevitable, global agriculture could be radically affected, possibly precipitating mass famine. One of the few natural buffers easing the rapid increase of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere is the global system of rain forests, which consume carbon dioxide to manufacture the carbohydrates of plant material.</p>
        <p>But as the rain forests are killed off, this buffer is disappearing. Even if President Bush's "America the Beautiful" proposal for planting 10 billion trees in the next decade is successful, the effects of the destruction of the world's equatorial rain forests would be scarcely diminished. The Intangible Loss</p>
        <p>One of the losses sometimes overlooked in discussions of the rain-forest problem is that of the beautiful mystery that haunted the world's artists in another era -- an aura that the museum exhibition suggests.</p>
        <p>The "back to nature" artistic movement that flourished in England early in this century focused on tropical rain forests and inspired some of the most luminous literary description of the period. W. H. Hudson's romantic fantasy "Green Mansions" and Arthur Conan Doyle's "Lost World" were set partly under the cathedral-like arches of Amazon rain forests, and Joseph Conrad's evocative "Heart of Darkness" was based on the author's experiences with rain forests in the Congo.</p>
        <p>Well into the 20th century a hint of somewhat sinister mystery pervaded the great rain forests; within living memory, headhunters roamed the Peruvian forests from which the Amazon springs, and even today vestiges of forest Indian culture survive in Brazil and elsewhere in South America. But in the face of bulldozers and chain saws, the culture and mystery are evaporating.</p>
        <p>The museum show highlights some of the beauty that is dying out. A visitor entering the third-floor exhibition area passes a magnificent life-size model of the base of a gigantic buttressed fig tree, one of the principal anchors of rain-forest ecology. Hidden speakers broadcast the exotic sounds of forest birds, frogs and insects, and there are lush floral displays and representations of beautiful endangered animals.</p>
        <p>There are also before and after photographs and dioramas of rain forests as they were in their pristine state, as they were during the few years cattle grazed where the trees were felled, and in their final state: empty, eroded deserts, virtually devoid of life and ruined by man for any useful function. Where and When</p>
        <p>"Tropical Rain Forests: A Disappearing Treasure" will be on view at the American Museum of Natural History, Central Park West at 79th Street, through June 2. Sydney Horenstein, the museum's coordinator of environmental public programs, conducts special group tours of the exhibition for teachers and environmental associations; tours can be arranged by calling the museum at (212) 769-5726.</p>
        <p>Eight short films on rain forests around the world run from 10:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M. Sunday. Free with museum admission; suggested contribution, $5.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
