<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Third World Ecology Investments Sought</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="471437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN INVESTMENTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNATIONAL ENVIRONMENTAL INVESTMENT FUND</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D91331F936A3575AC0A967958260" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Third World Ecology Investments Sought</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Armed with Federal loan guarantees, a private partnership is seeking investors for third world business ventures with environmental goals that are as green as a dollar bill.</p>
        <p>But the program is getting a skeptical reception from some environmental groups, who view it with the same suspicion they have long directed toward international corporations and development agencies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Armed with Federal loan guarantees, a private partnership is seeking investors for third world business ventures with environmental goals that are as green as a dollar bill.</p>
        <p>But the program is getting a skeptical reception from some environmental groups, who view it with the same suspicion they have long directed toward international corporations and development agencies.</p>
        <p>The partnership, the International Environmental Investment Fund, is to be jointly managed by the investment bank Kidder, Peabody &amp; Company and the consulting group Booz, Allen &amp; Hamilton Inc. It was set up recently with the backing of the Overseas Private Investment Corporation, a Federal agency that tries to stimulate American exports by providing financing and insurance for international development projects. A New Approach</p>
        <p>Providing backing for an investment fund is a new approach for the agency, which is also supporting three regional funds to promote development in Africa, Eastern Europe and the Asia-Pacific region.</p>
        <p>The environmental fund's aim is to give private investors competitive returns in a fund that sponsors projects like renewable energy production, sustainable agriculture and forestry, pollution control and ecologically oriented tourism.</p>
        <p>The fund's initial capital of $100 million will consist of $60 million in equity put up by limited partners and $40 million borrowed with an OPIC guarantee of repayment. The minimum investment for a limited partner is $5 million. The fund is expected to attract large institutional investors like pension funds and university endowments that are seeking to put some of their money into "socially conscious" investments.</p>
        <p>Private companies and government agencies have begun to embrace environmentalism as a goal of international business. One sign of the trend is a meeting sponsored by OPIC, the United Nations and the World Bank on Thursday and Friday at the Plaza Hotel in New York, where more than a hundred speakers will address environmental investments.</p>
        <p>But leading environmental organizations are raising concerns about the OPIC fund's environmental credentials. They say the fund's sponsors have done nothing to guarantee that the projects it sponsors -- which have not yet been chosen -- will meet environmental standards.</p>
        <p>"I have a feeling that what we have got here is OPIC trying to put a green cloak over a standard investment fund," said Lawrence F. Williams, director of international programs for the Sierra Club in Washington. "At this point, I would urge the investor to be very cautious." Access to Experts</p>
        <p>Lawyers and managers at OPIC said in interviews that they would strictly supervise the fund's investments. They said they had access to experts who for years had helped the agency review the environmental effects of its activities.</p>
        <p>"We met directly with the entire alphabet soup of environmental organizations in this town," said Harvey A. Himberg, OPIC's director of environmental affairs. "We had the benefit of a lot of input from the environmental community."</p>
        <p>But OPIC's executive vice president, James D. Berg, in a letter sent last week to Senator Patrick J. Leahy, a Vermont Democrat who had questioned the fund's environmental standards, offered no concrete guidelines on how the fund would select projects or solicit public comments.</p>
        <p>"Determinations of sound environmental practice will be made on a case-by-case basis, using accepted definitions of sustainable development in each of the sectors in which the fund proposes to invest," the letter said. "As a private investment company with private-sector clients, the fund of necessity will be constrained with respect to public disclosure of potential investments before fund resources are committed."</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams of the Sierra Club said that was not enough. "Basically, it boils down to, 'Trust us,' " he said. Outside Input Suggested</p>
        <p>Paul Weatherly, an expert in environmental investing whose company, Resource Management Consultants, has been working for a number of environmental groups monitoring the fund, said that OPIC should establish an independent group to have input into selecting the investment projects.</p>
        <p>But Robert O. Draggon, OPIC's vice president for finance, compared this demand to "a Good Housekeeping seal of approval," and said, "The private sector just doesn't work that way."</p>
        <p>Howard L. Hills, OPIC's general counsel, said a large part of OPIC's mission was to bridge the gap between the financial community and the green movement. But he said it sometimes seemed easier to get the financial community interested in environmental projects than to get the environmental groups interested in the necessities of the marketplace.</p>
        <p>"If we just make bankers environmentalists, then we have failed," he said. "We also have to get the environmentalists to be responsive to the market forces that are going to be benefiting the environment."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
