<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Asteroids, a Menace to Early Life, Could Still Destroy Earth; High Heat and Asteroids Flavored Primordial Soup</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="453608"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EVOLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AMINO ACIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTEROIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asteroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFD81430F93BA25755C0A967958260" item-length="2259" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Asteroids, a Menace to Early Life, Could Still Destroy Earth; High Heat and Asteroids Flavored Primordial Soup</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIFE on Earth may have sprung into existence during a period so brief -- and so hostile to life as we know it today -- that scientists will have to reconsider traditional ideas about the chemical antecedents of all living things, several new studies suggest.</p>
        <p>Contradicting the widely held supposition that life arose from a relatively simple soup of amino acids, Dr. Norman R. Pace, a biologist at Indiana University, says that at the time life began to appear around 3.5 billion years ago, the surface of the Earth was probably scalding hot, possibly as hot as 300degrees Fahrenheit. Moreover, he believes, water might have been as destructive to the earliest forms of life as it proved to be for the wicked witch in "The Wizard of Oz."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIFE on Earth may have sprung into existence during a period so brief -- and so hostile to life as we know it today -- that scientists will have to reconsider traditional ideas about the chemical antecedents of all living things, several new studies suggest.</p>
        <p>Contradicting the widely held supposition that life arose from a relatively simple soup of amino acids, Dr. Norman R. Pace, a biologist at Indiana University, says that at the time life began to appear around 3.5 billion years ago, the surface of the Earth was probably scalding hot, possibly as hot as 300degrees Fahrenheit. Moreover, he believes, water might have been as destructive to the earliest forms of life as it proved to be for the wicked witch in "The Wizard of Oz."</p>
        <p>Deciphering the chemical origin of life, a problem that many scientists in the 1950's believed might be solved fairly quickly, has continued to frustrate biologists. Early assumptions about the composition of the Earth's early atmosphere, the chemistry and temperature of primordial seas, and the ability of simple compounds to combine into complex ones have been challenged by increasingly sophisticated experiments and deductions.</p>
        <p>While chemists have shown how the simplest organic building blocks could have formed on the infant Earth, no one has successfully demonstrated how these components could have combined on their own to create proteins or, more important, the genetic coding material that permits biological reproduction and is the essence of life.</p>
        <p>This check has convinced a few scientists that life is too complex to have arisen on Earth spontaneously, and must therefore have been imported from elsewhere. Most biologists reject this view. They contend that unless life arose as the result of a supernatural miracle, it must have a comprehensible chemical origin, whether that origin was on Earth or on some distant celestial outpost. Some believe that scientists have merely overlooked some obvious chemical mechanism that is bound to come to light soon.</p>
        <p>But proving that contention is not easy.</p>
        <p>In an article in the May 17 issue of the journal Cell, Dr. Pace, a member of the National Academy of Sciences and a specialist in the microbiology of cells, presents evidence that incipient life could not have endured conditions in oceans, lakes and tidal pools. If this is true, he says, life would have had to develop in relatively dry organic scums, a conclusion that directly contradicts the common opinion that the chemistry of life must develop in aqueous solutions.</p>
        <p>Dr. Pace's findings were challenged, however, by Dr. Stanley L. Miller of the University of California at San Diego. Dr. Miller is the chemist who demonstrated in 1953 and in subsequent landmark experiments that lightning bolts in the presumed atmosphere of the early Earth could have created the amino acidsand other chemicals that are essential to life.</p>
        <p>Whatever the case, Dr. Pace and Dr. Miller agreed in interviews, the uncertainties clouding the origin of  Genesis Clues Discovered In Craters of Moon</p>
        <p>Complicating the chemical prelude to life still further, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration reported this month that a survey of impact craters on the Moon reveal a pattern of asteroid bombardment in the early solar system so intense that it probably wiped out life on Earth several times before the ancestors of today's microorganisms, plants and animals came into being.</p>
        <p>According to scientists at NASA's Ames Research Center in California, this implies that the life forms ancestral to all of today's organisms must have arisen significantly later than some previous estimates. Fossil evidence suggests that the first primitive cells existed about 3.5 billion years ago. Yet the last great impact by an asteroid capable of extinguishing all life on Earth probably occurred only slightly earlier than this. Hence, NASA scientists believe that present-day life may have arisen from its chemical constituents in as little as one million years, hardly more than one five-thousandth of the Earth's geological history.</p>
        <p>Dr. Verne Oberbeck, Dr. Guy Fogelman and Dr. Kevin Zahnle at the Ames Research Center, basing their research on earlier studies of asteroid impacts by Dr. Kevin Maher and Dr. David Stephenson of the California Institute of Technology, say it is likely that during the Earth's first billion years, from 4.5 billion to 3.5 billion years ago, there occurred two "super impacts" by miniature planets. Each could have been several hundred miles in diameter, and would have had the destructive power of as much as five trillion megatons , sufficient to vaporize the Earth's oceans, melt its rocky crust, and send 3,000degrees-Fahrenheit rock vapor into the atmosphere, where it would remain for 1,000 years.</p>
        <p>One consequence of this calculation is that life must have originated in a very short period, at least by the standards of geological time. This may come as a considerable surprise to the theorists who believe the origin of life is so improbable an event that hundreds of millions of years would have been required for it to occur.</p>
        <p>The narrowing of this "window" in time does not disturb Dr. Miller.</p>
        <p>"I have always believed that the origin of life must have occurred within a span of no more than 10 million years," he said. "It must have been rapid, and the chemistry involved must have been robust -- that is, the necessary chemical steps must have occurred easily, without needing a whole lot of special conditions. We haven't hit on the secret yet, but I still feel that it's something fairly simple -- something that will make us kick ourselves for not having spotted it earlier." Evolution Chicken Soup To Human Beings</p>
        <p>Although experts do not agree on the composition of Earth's early atmosphere, most acknowledge that amino acids and some of the chemical building blocks of DNA could have been created simply by heat and electrical discharges. But the next step in the evolution has so far evaded scientists.</p>
        <p>"Going from chicken soup to the first cell remains a gigantic problem," Dr. Pace said, "and I just don't believe you can start life in one of Miller's pots." One reason for his skepticism, Dr. Pace said, is the extreme fragility of ribonucleic acid or RNA, the molecule regarded by many geneticists as nature's earliest vehicle for passing genetic information from one generation to the next.</p>
        <p>In modern cells, RNA is a mere intermediary between the proteins that run the cell's day-to-day operations and the DNA that contains the instructions for building the proteins. But since RNA is a simpler molecule than DNA, it has seemed to some scientists as the more likely of the two molecules to have evolved first from simple building blocks. According to a widely held theory, life began in what Dr. Walter Gilbert of Harvard University termed an "RNA world," gradually evolving into the organisms genetically formed by DNA.</p>
        <p>But if the first genetic material really was RNA, Dr. Pace said, theorists must take into account the fact that this compound is easily destroyed by water, particularly water at the high temperatures that prevailed during the early history of life.</p>
        <p>"Biological polymers, such as RNA, generally are formed by dehydration, the removal of water," Dr. Pace said. "The origin of life seems inconsistent with fully aqueous chemistry, particularly at high temperature."</p>
        <p>DNA, the basic genetic molecule in most modern forms of life (but not in such RNA-based viruses as the one that causes AIDS),is sturdy enough to withstand relatively harsh conditions. But if DNA developed only after life based on RNA had been established, the first RNA-based ancestors of life must have evolved in the relatively protective environment of some carbon-rich scum, Dr. Pace believes. Such an environment would contain some water but too little to be chemically destructive.  The Boiling Point Cradle of Life In a Steam Bath?</p>
        <p>Such organisms might have had features found in some very peculiar modern-day bacteria called hyperthermophiles -- microorganisms that thrive well above the boiling point of water.</p>
        <p>Dr. Thomas D. Brock of the University of Wisconsin at Madison, a leading expert in heat-loving bacteria, believes that Dr. Pace's hypothesis is plausible.</p>
        <p>"Evolution probably operated in only one direction," he said. "Starting with an organism that lives happily at very high temperatures, mutations could adapt its descendants to living at the ordinary temperatures we encounter today. But biochemical considerations make it much less likely that a low-temperature organism could evolve to something that would thrive in such places as the boiling springs at Yellowstone National Park, where we find lots of thermophiles."</p>
        <p>So it may be that modern heat-loving bacteria have something in common with the earliest forms of life, he said.</p>
        <p>The earliest living things may not only have been heat lovers, but may have derived their energy from sulfur compounds, rather than from the products of photosynthesis. The base of the modern food chain consists mostly of organisms that use the energy of sunlight in a complex photosynthetic process to convert water and carbon dioxide into carbohydrates. But some modern thermophilic bacteria derive their energy from sulfur compounds occurring in the dark, scalding-hot hydrothermal vents in the ocean floor, and in such hot springs as those at Yellowstone.</p>
        <p>The fragile RNA molecules that may have been the genetic medium in the first microorganisms might have survived the hostile external environment because they functioned within the protective walls of a primitive cell in a liquid relatively low in chemically available water, Dr. Pace believes. Although no one has shown how a fully functional cell could have evolved, several experiments have demonstrated how a spherical cell-like membrane could have formed from simple chemicals, including some known to have reached the Earth on meteorites.</p>
        <p>"We really don't know a lot about the environment inside even present-day cells," he said, "but it's reasonable to assume that it is more congenial to the cell's working parts than is the environment outside.</p>
        <p>"Take the common intestinal bacterium Escherichia coli. We know that it's about 80 percent water, but we don't know how much of that water is available for entering into chemical reactions," he said. The chemical availability of water depends on the substances dissolved in it, its acidity, and other factors.</p>
        <p>"You can't just stick a probe into a living cell and get realistic measurements of the things that affect the level of its available water," he said. "Limiting the amount of available water may have been crucial to the origin of life."</p>
        <p>Dr. Miller strongly disagrees.</p>
        <p>"I think Pace's assumptions that the water inside a cell is different from the water outside are thermodynamically wrong," he said. "In any case, you have to have water for life. At one time we were working to determine the minimum requirements for life on Mars. On Earth, you find no organisms that can live containing less available water than would produce a relative humidity of 75 percent, and I suspect it would be the same everywhere."</p>
        <p>The most important objective for scientists studying the origin of life, Dr. Miller believes, is to determine the nature of the first genetic material.</p>
        <p>"The problem is this," he said. "Whatever it was that served as a precursor to the RNA or DNA we see today is no longer around. You have nothing to lay your hands on. There are some things in the laboratory you can still do, but we haven't found the answer yet, and we don't really know what to look for." Panspermia Does Life Have Alien Roots?</p>
        <p>A few scientists believe that a theory called "panspermia," propounded in the 19th century by the Swedish chemist Svante A. Arrhenius, could circumvent the many obstacles seen to the advent of life on Earth. This theory, supported by the British astronomer Sir Fred Hoyle and by Dr. Francis H. C. Crick, co-discoverer of the helical structure of DNA, holds that the seeds of life drifted to Earth from interstellar space.</p>
        <p>Sir Fred believes that even modern-day organisms, including disease-causing types, continuously arrive from outer space, a theory that few scientists accept.</p>
        <p>"You can't dismiss panspermia out of hand," Dr. Miller said, "but my real objection is that it begs the question. If life originated elsewhere, then you still have to explain how it happened out there."</p>
        <p>The possible role of asteroid impacts in the origin and evolution of life remains a subject of seemingly endless scientific debate. Most planetary experts believe that the immense heat of an asteroid impact -- sufficient to vaporize the asteroid itself as well as the part of the earth it hit -- would have destroyed any compounds from which life might develop. But scientists also acknowledge that some surprisingly complex compounds, including amino acids, have been detected in some of the meteorites known as chondrites.</p>
        <p>The only conclusions about the origin of life on which scientists seem to agree are that despite all obstacles, life somehow did originate, but that the central mystery of how remains as dark as ever. Expectations that the problem would be swiftly solved after Dr. Miller's experiments with lightning discharges have dimmed with time.</p>
        <p>"I still believe that the answer lies right under our noses," Dr. Miller said, "but the light that we saw at the end of the tunnel seems to have gone out."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
