<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="458334"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DA113DF93BA35754C0A967958260" item-length="647" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A powerful new economic pragmatism is sweeping third world capitals from Brasilia to Bangkok. Countries that were once proud economic nationalists are now trying to forge closer ties with the rest of the world. Government officials and economists say they are committed to changes like allowing market forces to flourish, abandoning fiscal and monetary policies that were politically motivated and opening borders to foreign goods and investment.  [ Page A1. ]  India has begun a fundamental shift in priorities that looks to South Korea and prosperous Southeast Asian nations as guiding economic symbols, its new foreign minister says.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>A year ago, the idea of the "grand bargain" -- Soviet reform in exchange for Western aid -- would have been dismissed as an insult by the Kremlin and as a waste of money by the White House. The impossible now seems at least plausible. Economic Watch.  [ D1. ]  Interviews with scores of Americans reveals a deep ambivilance about the idea of a Soviet bailout financed by the United States.  [ A1. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A powerful new economic pragmatism is sweeping third world capitals from Brasilia to Bangkok. Countries that were once proud economic nationalists are now trying to forge closer ties with the rest of the world. Government officials and economists say they are committed to changes like allowing market forces to flourish, abandoning fiscal and monetary policies that were politically motivated and opening borders to foreign goods and investment.  [ Page A1. ]  India has begun a fundamental shift in priorities that looks to South Korea and prosperous Southeast Asian nations as guiding economic symbols, its new foreign minister says.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>A year ago, the idea of the "grand bargain" -- Soviet reform in exchange for Western aid -- would have been dismissed as an insult by the Kremlin and as a waste of money by the White House. The impossible now seems at least plausible. Economic Watch.  [ D1. ]  Interviews with scores of Americans reveals a deep ambivilance about the idea of a Soviet bailout financed by the United States.  [ A1. ]</p>
        <p>With a third Michelin star, a French chef hopes to increase his revenues by 50 percent and save himself from drowning under $40,000 in monthly debt payments.  [ A1. ] THE ECONOMY</p>
        <p>Economists may see the economy climbing solidly out of recession, but the people who meet payrolls and run the nation's businesses seem to be hearing a different drummer.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>California's big banks are feeling some big shocks, and the state's slumping economy is just one of them.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Coal producers and coal-burning utilities are deciding whether to go national with an ad campaign challenging the idea that burning fossil fuels will change the climate.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration says states systematically underestimated the huge increase in Medicaid costs in recent years, producing billions of dollars in bills for the Government.  [ A10. ]</p>
        <p>A task force of New York City officials and business and labor leaders is trying to devise an insurance policy to guarantee that as the city cuts its budget it does not sacrifice expensive but necessary undertakings.  [ B1. ]  Connecticut's Governor ordered state employees to report back to work beginning today, but the state is no closer to a resolution of its budget impasse.  [ B1. ] COMPANIES</p>
        <p>Federated and Allied are preparing for two hectic months as they begin working closely with two classes of creditors in hopes of emerging from bankruptcy protection next year.  [ D1. ] THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
        <p>The problem of "zapping" has been left largely unaddressed by broadcast networks and ad agencies, even though many executives acknowledge that the use of remote-control channel changers to avoid commercials is getting worse.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>British readers of the tabloid press have yet another choice, fresh from U.S. supermarkets: The National Enquirer.  [ D6. ]</p>
        <p>Allen H. Neuharth is poised to return to the limelight as chairman of the Freedom Forum, the Gannett Foundation's flashy new incarnation. The former Gannett Company chairman has long delighted in thumbing his nose at the newspaper establishment.  [ D6. ]</p>
        <p>Consolidation is a pervasive trend at advertising agencies, but now it is the clients' turn. Stuart Elliott: Advertising.  [ D7. ]</p>
        <p>Even if a television program has no ads, an ad agency may be lurking in the background. Randall Rothenberg: Ad Scene.  [ D6. ] TODAY'S COLUMNS</p>
        <p>Housing industry stocks have stopped climbing and have begun to trail the market. The falloff could signal that the housing rebound will be weaker than expected. Floyd Norris: Market Place.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>Trends in economic data appear to support the view that the economy is on course for a rebound. But some credit market analysts maintain that conditions could sour quickly, especially if long-term rates rise. Kenneth N. Gilpin: Credit Markets.  [ D5. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
