<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Our Towns</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="480636"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKS AND OTHER RECREATION AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREES AND SHRUBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREST AND BRUSH FIRES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SECTARIAN SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YELLOWSTONE NATIONAL PARK</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEWARK (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MALCOLM, ANDREW H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PAGAN, NATHALIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wyoming/Yellowstone National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DF143CF936A25753C1A967958260" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Our Towns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andrew H. Malcolm</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MALCOLM, ANDREW H</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This is a follow-up column about a Newark schoolgirl named Nathalie Pagan who had been to Maryland once, oh, and the edge of Pennsylvania too, although she was sleeping in the back seat at the time. Eleven-year-old Nathalie was one of thousands of New Jersey parochial-school students who sought $5 donations last winter to help replant burned areas of Yellowstone National Park.</p>
        <p>The prize for selling the most trees was a 2,282-mile trip to Yellowstone, a mystical place larger even than Newark. Every day after school, sometimes alone, sometimes with her Mom, Nathalie went door to door in her poor north Newark neighborhood, where fixing forests in a place called Wyoming does not top every family's priority list.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This is a follow-up column about a Newark schoolgirl named Nathalie Pagan who had been to Maryland once, oh, and the edge of Pennsylvania too, although she was sleeping in the back seat at the time. Eleven-year-old Nathalie was one of thousands of New Jersey parochial-school students who sought $5 donations last winter to help replant burned areas of Yellowstone National Park.</p>
        <p>The prize for selling the most trees was a 2,282-mile trip to Yellowstone, a mystical place larger even than Newark. Every day after school, sometimes alone, sometimes with her Mom, Nathalie went door to door in her poor north Newark neighborhood, where fixing forests in a place called Wyoming does not top every family's priority list.</p>
        <p>Nathalie had seen some 15-foot pines at her school, St. Michael's, on Bloomfield Avenue. But she had to study how trees turn carbon dioxide into oxygen, how Western trees grow taller than telephone poles and how they survive over a century without being vandalized. She passed this information on to neighborhood residents, 72 of whom were moved to sponsor a tree.</p>
        <p>When Nathalie's story appeared, money flooded in from across the country, pushing her total to 196 trees. This assured Nathalie of first place on St. Michael's tree-sales list; second place sold 36. Nathalie wrote a personal thank-you to each contributor. But, alas, Nathalie didn't win the contest. And Yellowstone and her 196 seedlings receded in her imagination.</p>
        <p>Last month Nathalie's teacher, Cynthia Murren, greeted the new seventh grader with some unbelievable news. "You're going to Yellowstone," she said. Nathalie didn't believe it. Then she did. Then she cried.</p>
        <p>When the youngster burst into her home on Grafton Avenue at 3 P.M., her parents didn't believe it. Then they did. Then they cried. It seems that a tire company had created the Firestone Firehawks, a new honor for youthful advocates of the environment. They chose Nathalie as one of five winners headed for Yellowstone with their mothers.</p>
        <p>To say that Nathalie was excited is like saying some cars use the Garden State Parkway. Even at 4 A.M., when Nathalie's parents, Alex and Marie, awakened her to drive to La Guardia Airport, Nathalie was excited. She saw a movie seven miles above the Rockies. Just on the landing approach to Yellowstone, she saw more trees than she ever knew existed.</p>
        <p>The other morning, promptly at 11, her dark curls, burgundy sweater and pleated plaid skirt neatly in place, Nathalie clutched her diary notes and made a formal report to Ms. Murren and 27 classmates in Class 7-A. Her um-free report, much practiced at home, provided the following details:</p>
        <p>The four days were very busy. It takes three planes to get to Wyoming. Everyone is friendly there. The hotel is made of logs. There are no televisions. The waterfalls are taller than her school. Old Faithful is a geyser. Some lakes are hot, which keeps them ice free so animals can get drinks in the winter. A television crew asked her about Newark. A boardwalk winds through the burned forest. Some trees have holes where birds live. The air is so clear you can see many miles. It doesn't smell like cars. The West seems to have more stars than New Jersey has people. Nathalie saw some of her seedlings. She made a friend named Angie from Los Angeles. They saw many animals, including a deer, an elk, a wild coyote and a buffalo that blocked the road; no vehicles tried to hit it. The plane home landed at 12:41 in the morning.</p>
        <p>The Firestone people gave her $20 spending money. Nathalie bought some Indian worry stones, which were passed around. Ms. Murren suggested everyone rub them, because a test on Yellowstone loomed after lunch.</p>
        <p>Nathalie also got Ms. Murren a sweat shirt. And the child displayed a beautiful Yellowstone charm bracelet, which was not passed around.</p>
        <p>But Nathalie did share neat photo arrangements -- shots of Nathalie and Old Faithful, Nathalie and her mother, Nathalie and a buffalo, Nathalie and a bus, Nathalie and a ranger, Nathalie and Angie, and an accidental close-up of Angie's feet.</p>
        <p>Sepros Malijin was curious whether she saw any poison berries. (No.) Melissa Cruz wondered whether Nathalie was ever scared way out there. (A little, near the buffalo.) Nathalie's presentation earned much applause. Nathalie's parents said this was her first moment of silence since Yellowstone.</p>
        <p>Nathalie says Newark looks different now. She has decided to become a lawyer because "I want to change many things." But first Nathalie will organize a school environment club. (She already wrote her Firestone thank-yous.)</p>
        <p>At night, Nathalie often thinks about her trip and those distant trees. "It seems," she said, "like a dream, it was so nice."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
