<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News SUmmary</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="488977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D71030F930A15752C1A967958260" item-length="1052" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News SUmmary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International 2-6  INVITATION TO MIDDLE EAST TALKS</p>
        <p>The United States invited Israel, the Palestinians and the Arab countries to resume their peace talks in Washington on Dec. 4.  Page 1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International 2-6  INVITATION TO MIDDLE EAST TALKS</p>
        <p>The United States invited Israel, the Palestinians and the Arab countries to resume their peace talks in Washington on Dec. 4.  Page 1</p>
        <p>P.L.O. CASE SAID TO BE CLOSED</p>
        <p>Israel's Attorney General has decided not to prosecute a Palestinian leader for contact with the P.L.O., the state radio reported.  4  DETAILS OF SALVADORAN MASSACRE</p>
        <p>Details of the largest mass killing of the Salvadoran civil war are just now coming to light after 10 years, along with demands for justice.  1  HOW GHALI WON THE TOP U.N. POST</p>
        <p>The United Nations chose Boutros Ghali as Secretary General after France, aided by Belgium, engineered the breaking of a deadlock from which Washington had hoped to benefit, diplomats said.  3  FIGHTING FOR ECOLOGY AND HIS JOB</p>
        <p>The Soviet Minister for Natural Resources Management and Environmental Protection opened a lobbying campaign against the planned abolition of his department.  3  New data from a satellite have confirmed a drop in the ozone layer.  5  YELTSIN SEEKS HELP IN GERMANY</p>
        <p>President Boris N. Yeltsin assured German business leaders that he was determined to transform the Russian economy and offer new possibilities for foreign investment.  5  EMBARGO MAY SPUR HAITI'S EXODUS</p>
        <p>Relief workers say the international embargo imposed on Haiti has increased the pain of poverty in ways likely to lead thousands more people to set out for the United States.  6  Haiti's deposed President meets with his foes.  6  CAR SMUGGLING THRIVES IN YEMEN</p>
        <p>Seiyun Journal: In Yemen, many cars are smuggled from Saudi Arabia or stolen from the oil companies prospecting for crude in Yemen.  2  National 7-10  STORM CLOUDS AT THE WHITE HOUSE</p>
        <p>The White House chief of staff said President Bush was responsible for the suggestion that credit-card interest rates should be lowered, a remark that helped send stock prices plummeting a week ago.  1  FAVORS IN A BANKING BILL</p>
        <p>Tucked away in the complex banking bill approved by a handful of senators on Thursday are a host of provisions written with specific home-state constituents in mind.  35  POLITICS 1, TAX CUTS 0</p>
        <p>With the blessing of the White House, a group of Republican lawmakers tried to embarrass the Democrats by offering a broad package of tax cuts that, just days before Congress is to adjourn for the year, stand no chance of enactment.  9  Congress made no progress on the F.D.I.C. or savings and loans.  9  ABOUT-FACE</p>
        <p>The Administration said it would revise its proposal defining America's wetlands. The change in position followed Federal scientists' finding that the proposal could have opened nearly half the currently protected areas to development.  1  'THE WORLD'S CLEANEST' FUEL</p>
        <p>California adopted gasoline standards that will require the most significant changes in fuel since the Federal Government ordered the removal of lead from gasoline nearly 20 years ago.  1  PARKS OR PORK BARRELS?</p>
        <p>A $73 million Federal project to build a theme park in Scranton, Pa., has touched off an extraordinary debate over the changing mission of the National Park Service.  1  NEW TURN IN ACCREDITATION FIGHT</p>
        <p>Members of a beleaguered college accrediting agency, under attack for using a cultural diversity standard that has been assailed as discriminatory, said they would accept a one-year renewal of Federal recognition instead of the usual five years.  8  Civil rights groups threatened to sue the Administration.  8  FLU TAKING A TOLL</p>
        <p>A nationwide flu outbreak has closed schools in six states and confirmed warnings that this will be an unusually grim flu season.  7  Four suspects in the Phoenix temple slayings won dismissal of charges.  7  How a mixed Boston neighborhood transformed itself.  7  Massachusetts began taking lottery bets by telephone.  10  Beliefs: An Ayatollah in exile.  12  Metropolitan Digest, 25  A VIEW ON WHAT AILS BUSINESS</p>
        <p>Businesses in the New York City region waiting for a national recovery to lift them out of their doldrums are looking in the wrong direction, several economists say. They say the problem has more to do with the wrenching changes being forced on industries, from banking to advertising to television, for which the city is a center.  1  Business Digest 35  Obituaries 11-12  WERBLIN DEAD AT 81</p>
        <p>David A. (Sonny) Werblin, the sports and entertainment impresario who signed Joe Namath to a ground-breaking rookie contract with the New York Jets, died on Thursday in Manhattan.  11  Daniel Mann, theater and film director.  11  Gladys Krieble Delmas, a philanthropist and writer.  11  Ernest Dichter, a consultant on consumer motivation.  12  William G. Mulligan, a lawyer.  12  John N. LaCorte, champion of Italians and Columbus Day.  12  Arts/Entertainment  1923 O'Casey play returning.  13  Music: Dutoit and the New York Philharmonic.  13  Classical Music in Review.  16  Dance: Peter Martins's "Poulenc Sonata." 13  Victoria Marks and the world since the creation.  17  Consumer's World 48  More men are coloring their hair.  Many airlines cutting fare for passengers with an emergency.  Variable rates don't always help credit-card holders.  Guidepost: Lights for that holiday glow.  Slippers that light your way in the dark.  Sports 29-33  Baseball: Bonilla gets offer from Mets.  29  Basketball: Ewing becomes the highest-paid player in team sports.  29  Knicks beat Pistons in Detroit.  33  Boxing: A fight, at least, for Holyfield.  32  Column: Anderson on Sonny Werblin.  29  Hockey: Devils rout Whalers.  32  Outdoors: Searching for steelhead.  32  Tennis: Seles and Sabatini advance at Slims 29  Editorials/Op-Ed  Editorials 22  Posturing on the homeless. U.N. turns to an Egyptian. Don't slam the door on China. Letters 22  Russell Baker: R.S.V.P. with class. 23  Anna Quindlen: Don't call me Ishmael.  23  Elinor Lipman: Are you the office sex pest?  23  Glenn T. Seaborg and Paul H. Nitze: A new era of energy.  23  William T. Close: With a friend like him.  23</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
