<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After the War, We Face Some Tough Questions</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="426855"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSIAN GULF WAR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDB1339F932A35750C0A967958260" item-length="702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After the War, We Face Some Tough Questions</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The hearts and minds of most Americans have been caught up in the daily pace of the war in the Persian Gulf. For understandable reasons, this has been a time when the nation was unable to think much beyond the successful attainment of the immediate United States military goals in the war.</p>
        <p>And yet think we must. For the war will come to an end, and when it is over, what then? Now is the time to begin setting the agenda for the foreign and domestic policy discussion that will inevitably follow the formal cessation of hostilities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The hearts and minds of most Americans have been caught up in the daily pace of the war in the Persian Gulf. For understandable reasons, this has been a time when the nation was unable to think much beyond the successful attainment of the immediate United States military goals in the war.</p>
        <p>And yet think we must. For the war will come to an end, and when it is over, what then? Now is the time to begin setting the agenda for the foreign and domestic policy discussion that will inevitably follow the formal cessation of hostilities.</p>
        <p>This requires opinion leaders and policy makers to distance themselves from the frenzy of military conflict and to think and speak courageously about the future of United States interests at home and abroad. This is not an easy charge and is made all the more troublesome by the suppression of dissent that occurs even in a democracy during wartime.</p>
        <p>What are the contours of this prospective agenda? Political challenges loom on the international and domestic policy fronts in the coming months, years and decades. Abroad, the United States must make a commitment to serious political reform in Kuwait and to rebuilding the devastated nation of Iraq.</p>
        <p>We must establish a working rapport with all Arab nations in the region that respects the important and often troubling differences between Western and Islamic cultures. It is time we recognized that "it is easy to impose a civilization but difficult to depose a culture," as the historian Geoffrey Barraclough has said. We cannot and should not attempt to refashion the Middle East in our image -- a tempting prospect to many.</p>
        <p>While civilization is fragile, culture is resilient. The challenge that faces the United States in the Middle East is to encourage and participate in an effort to reconcile the deep tensions between civilization and culture in this region. The just and immediate resolution of the Palestinian question is now, by any sensible account, the necessary prerequisite to this end.</p>
        <p>At home, the development of a national energy policy to achieve energy independence must be given top political priority after the war is over. America must free itself from dependence on imported oil and from the political and ecological perils of fossil fuels more generally. While it may not be easy, even Republicans should be willing to concede that at least on this issue Jimmy Carter was right all along and Ronald Reagan dangerously wrong.</p>
        <p>Additionally, one important lesson of the Persian Gulf should be that, as long as other Western nations remain dependent upon imported oil for their standard of living, the military capabilities and proclivities of the United States will also remain hostage to foreign oil.</p>
        <p>We must also return in earnest to a discussion about the domestic policy and budgetary implications of the end of the cold war. The President's hastily conceptualized vision for a "new world order" should not distract us from debating the domestic policy benefits of an immense annual peace dividend. Neither should the American people tolerate attempts by the Bush Presidency to replace the nuclear militarism of the cold war with a new high-tech militarism attendant to the "new world order."</p>
        <p>Finally, and before century's end, we must establish a respected deliberative role for the American people to play through their elected national representatives on the questions of war and peace. Congress must never again be placed in the position of acquiescing to military intervention, either through its own hesitancy or executive manipulation.</p>
        <p>Contrary to today's political practice, the American Founders understood that the decision to wage war was too serious and consequential to be left to the discretion of the President or any other single individual. Congress should always stand ahead of the President, not behind him, in matters of war and peace. Democratic foreign-policy making needs to become institutionalized and accepted as prevalent practice before the next military defense of the "new world order." MARK P. PETRACCA Irvine, Calif., Feb. 19, 1991 The writer is an assistant professor of politics and society, University of California.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
