<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DUST CLOUD ERUPTS ON HALLEY'S COMET</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="428415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HALLEY'S COMET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMETS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D7123EF934A35750C0A967958260" item-length="480" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DUST CLOUD ERUPTS ON HALLEY'S COMET</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five years after a much-heralded pass near Earth, an immense dust cloud has erupted from Halley's comet, making it hundreds of times brighter.</p>
        <p>The comet had been very faint, just an inert, potato-shaped ice ball almost 10 miles long. Its tail disappeared about five years ago as the remaining nucleus sped away from the Sun.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Five years after a much-heralded pass near Earth, an immense dust cloud has erupted from Halley's comet, making it hundreds of times brighter.</p>
        <p>The comet had been very faint, just an inert, potato-shaped ice ball almost 10 miles long. Its tail disappeared about five years ago as the remaining nucleus sped away from the Sun.</p>
        <p>But last month, when the comet was some 1.3 billion miles from the Sun, astronomers saw it had sprouted a shiny dust cloud that extended for about 180,000 miles.</p>
        <p>The cloud was more than 1,000 times brighter than the comet was supposed to be at that distance, said Dr. Karen Meech of the University of Hawaii Institute for Astronomy, who sighted it on Feb. 15.</p>
        <p>"To have something turn off and suddenly brighten up at this distance is unheard of," she said Tuesday in a telephone interview. Belgians Sight Phenomenon</p>
        <p>The brightening was first detected on Feb. 12 by two Belgian astronomers, Olivier Hainaut and Alain Smette, who were scanning the heavens from the European Southern Observatory in Chile. They found that the cloud had increased the comet's brightness nearly 300 times above what it was supposed to be.</p>
        <p>Since solar energy is thought to cause such bursts of clouds, Halley's behavior at such a great distance from the Sun is "rather startling," said Dr. Brian Marsden, associate director for planetary sciences at the Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics in Cambridge, Mass. "This is much farther than anything we've observed before," Dr. Marsden said.</p>
        <p>Dust clouds, called comas, are generally produced when solar energy vaporizes ice, blowing dust off the comet nucleus.</p>
        <p>But, at the time of the sighting on Feb. 12, the surface of Halley's nucleus would still have been extremely cold -- about minus 330 degrees Fahrenheit, the European Southern Observatory said. "It is therefore not a simple matter to explain the outburst," the observatory said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Meech said some frozen substance other than water ice, like carbon monoxide or carbon dioxide, could still be active at such a low temperature. A pocket of one of these substances might have been slowly vaporizing beneath the crust of the nucleus. At some point, mounting pressure may have caused vapor to burst through the crust, blowing out dust to create the cloud, she said. Dust Clouds Over Comets</p>
        <p>Dr. Meech said other comets produce dust clouds at comparable distances, but at a steady rate, rather than with a sudden outburst.</p>
        <p>Such comets are making their first visit to the inner solar system, and perhaps they contain easily vaporized substances that had largely been used up by comets like Halley's that have repeatedly passed near the Sun, she said.</p>
        <p>Another possible explanation for Halley's outburst is that a small piece of rocky space debris hit the comet, providing enough energy to vaporize some frozen substance, she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
