<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Summit in London; Excerpts From Group of Seven's Declaration: Progress, Policies and Plans</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="461135"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DE1230F93BA25754C0A967958260" item-length="1390" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Summit in London; Excerpts From Group of Seven's Declaration: Progress, Policies and Plans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Reuters</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, July 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the final declaration issued by the Group of Seven leading industrialized nations at the end of their economic summit meeting: Economic Policy</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the final declaration issued by the Group of Seven leading industrialized nations at the end of their economic summit meeting: Economic Policy</p>
        <p>Over the last year, some of our economies have maintained good growth, while most have slowed down and some gone into recession. But a global recession has been avoided. . . . We welcome the fact that there are now increasing signs of economic recovery. Progress has been made too in reducing the largest trade and current account imbalances. Our shared objectives are a sustained recovery and price stability. . . .</p>
        <p>We therefore commit ourselves to implement fiscal and monetary policies, which, while reflecting the different situations in our countries, provide the basis for lower real interest rates. In this connection, continued progress in reducing budget deficits is essential.</p>
        <p>This, together with the efforts being made to reduce impediments to private saving, will help generate the increase in global savings needed to meet demands for investment. We also welcome the close cooperation on exchange markets and the work to improve the functioning of the international monetary system.</p>
        <p>We will also, with the help of the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development and other institutions, pursue reforms to improve economic efficiency and thus the potential for growth. . . . International Trade</p>
        <p>We . . . commit ourselves to an ambitious, global and balanced package of results from the  [ Uruguay ]  Round, with the widest possible participation by both developed and developing countries. The aim of all contracting parties should be to complete the round before the end of 1991. We shall each remain personally involved in this process, ready to intervene with one another if differences can only be resolved at the highest level. . . .</p>
        <p>The principal requirement is to move forward urgently in the following areas taken together:</p>
        <p>a) Market access, where it is necessary, in particular to cut tariff peaks for some products while moving to zero products for others. . . .</p>
        <p>b) Agriculture, where a framework must be decided upon to provide for specific binding commitments in domestic support, market access and export competition, so that substantial progressive reductions of support and protection may be agreed in each area, taking into account nontrade concerns.</p>
        <p>c) Services, where accord on a general agreement on trade in services should be reinforced by substantial and binding initial commitments to reduce or remove existing restrictions on services trade and not to impose new ones.</p>
        <p>d) Intellectual property, where clear and enforceable rules and obligations to protect all property rights are necessary to encourage investment and the spread of technology. . . .</p>
        <p>We are convinced that O.E.C.D. members must overcome in the near future and, in any case, by the end of the year, remaining obstacles to an agreement on reducing the distortions that result from the use of subsidized export credits. . . . Central and Eastern Europe</p>
        <p>. . . We renew our own firm commitment to support their reform efforts, to forge closer ties with them and to encourage their integration into the international economic system. . . .</p>
        <p>All the Central and East European countries except Albania are now members of the International Monetary Fund and the World Bank. We welcome the steps being taken by those countries that are implementing I.M.F.-suported programs of macro-economic stabilization. It is crucial that these programs are complemented by structural reforms, such as privatizing and restructuring state-owned enterprises, increasing competition and strengthening property rights. . . .</p>
        <p>A favorable environment for private investment, both foreign and domestic, is crucial for sustained growth and for avoiding dependence on external assistance from governments. In this respect, technical assistance from our private sectors and governments, the European Community and international institutions should concentrate on helping this essential market-based transformation. . . .</p>
        <p>Expanding markets for their exports are vital for the Central and East European countries. We welcome the substantial increases already made in exports to market economies and we undertake to improve further their access to our markets and for their products and services, including in areas such as steel, textiles and agricultural produce.  The Soviet Union</p>
        <p>We support the moves toward political and economic transformation in the Soviet Union and are ready to assist the integration of the Soviet Union into the world economy.</p>
        <p>Reform to develop the market economy is essential to create incentives for change and enable the Soviet people to mobilize their own substantial natural and human resources. A clear and agreed framework within which the center and the republics exercise their respective responsiblities is fundamental for the success of political and economic reform.</p>
        <p>We are sensitive to the overall political context in which reforms are being conducted, including the "new thinking" in Soviet foreign policy around the world. We are sensitive also the importance of shifting resources from military to civilian use.</p>
        <p>We are concerned about the deterioration of the Soviet economy, which creates severe hardship not only within the Soviet Union but also for the countries of Central and Eastern Europe. Cutting Debt</p>
        <p>Developing countries are playing an increasingly constructive role in the international economic system, including the Uruguay Round. Many have introduced radical policy reforms. . . . We commend these countries and urge others to follow their example. Good governance not only promotes development at home, but helps to attract external finance and investment from all sources.</p>
        <p>Africa deserves our special attention. Progress by African governments towards sound economic policies, democracy and accountability is improving their prospects for growth. This is being helped by our continued support, focused on stimulating development of the private sector, encouraging regional integration, providing concessional flows and reducing debt burdens. . . . We will provide humanitarian assistance to those parts of Africa facing severe famine and encourage the reform of United Nations structures in order to make this assistance more effective.</p>
        <p>In Latin America, we are encouraged by the progress being made in carrying out genuine economic reforms and by developments in regional integration. . . .  The Environment</p>
        <p>The international community will face formidable environmental challenges in the coming decade. Managing the environment continues to be a priority issue for us. Our economic policies should insure that the use of this planet's resources is sustainable and safeguards the interests of both present and future generations. Growing market economies can best mobilize the means for protecting the environment, while democratic systems insure proper accountability.</p>
        <p>Environmental considerations should be integrated into the full range of government policies, in a way which reflects their economic costs. . . .</p>
        <p>Internationally, we must develop a co-operative approach for tackling environmental issues. Industrial countries should set an example and thus encourage developing countries and Central and East European nations to play their part. . . .</p>
        <p>The U.N. Conference on Environment and Development in June 1992 will be a landmark event. . . . We commit ourselves to work for a successful conference and to give the necessary political impetus to its preparation.</p>
        <p>We aim to achieve the following by the time of U.N.C.E.D.:</p>
        <p>a) an effective framework convention on climate change, containing appropriate commitments and addressing all sources and sinks for greenhouse gases. . . .</p>
        <p>b) agreement on principles for the management, conservation and sustainable development of all types of forests, leading to a framework convention. . . .</p>
        <p>We remain concerned about the destruction of tropical forests. We welcome the progress made in developing the pilot program for the conservation of the Brazilian tropical forest. . . . We call for further urgent work under the auspices of the World Bank, in cooperation with the European Commission. . . .</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
