<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends; Just How Bad Is the Air Over Kuwait?</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week In Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="458209"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RATINGS AND RATING SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CANCER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOOT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FRIENDS OF THE EARTH</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL SCIENCE FOUNDATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service"></person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D71330F934A35754C0A967958260" item-length="896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends; Just How Bad Is the Air Over Kuwait?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOUR months after the retreating Iraqis torched Kuwait's oil wells, the job of putting them out is bringing slow progress and bitter recriminations. So is the job of assessing the environmental damage.</p>
        <p>Thus far the United States Government has looked at the smoke as if it were over Pittsburgh, evaluating the pollution by the yardsticks of the Clean Air Act: ozone, carbon monoxide, acid rain and small particulates. Environmental advocates complain that the questions more important to this particular kind of pollution have gone unanalyzed so far -- the carcinogens in unburned and partially burned oil, and the great clouds of big soot particles, the ones that are too big to pose much danger to human lungs but might change the climate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOUR months after the retreating Iraqis torched Kuwait's oil wells, the job of putting them out is bringing slow progress and bitter recriminations. So is the job of assessing the environmental damage.</p>
        <p>Thus far the United States Government has looked at the smoke as if it were over Pittsburgh, evaluating the pollution by the yardsticks of the Clean Air Act: ozone, carbon monoxide, acid rain and small particulates. Environmental advocates complain that the questions more important to this particular kind of pollution have gone unanalyzed so far -- the carcinogens in unburned and partially burned oil, and the great clouds of big soot particles, the ones that are too big to pose much danger to human lungs but might change the climate.</p>
        <p>One result is that nearly all the troops will be long gone before the scientists figure out how dangerous their stay was, and many Kuwaitis will be home from exile before their country's air is analyzed. The issue will persist with the fires, and fewer than a third of the 625 have been extinguished thus far.</p>
        <p>But even in what scientists think they know, there are contradictions and incongruities. In early June two teams flew through the plumes but came out with markedly different results. A National Science Foundation team was astonished to find smoke so thick that its plane got zebra stripes of oil on it, but said the environmental damage was only a "concern," not a crisis; the Friends of the Earth said Washington was fiddling while Kuwait burned and things were getting worse. Calling It From 20,000 Feet</p>
        <p>Both groups were handicapped because they tried to call the scene from 20,000 feet, but this became obvious only indirectly. At a briefing last month in Washington, the science foundation team described sitting around over beers debating why some smoke was white. A skeptical CNN correspondent asked where they had found beer, since Kuwait is dry. It turned out that the team had been based in Bahrain, off the Saudi coast, and never set foot in Kuwait, settling for the turboprop tour.</p>
        <p>The Friends of the Earth group asserted that the situation was deteriorating and, to prove it, said pools of oil on the ground were beginning to catch fire. In fact, the pools have been burning intermittently; five men died in one in April. Oil experts say the pools become less flammable as they age, because the chemicals in crude oil that are easiest to light tend to evaporate first.</p>
        <p>But the observations of the rival teams do raise questions. One: just what is the white smoke? Oil experts here and in Kuwait say it must be steam from water that comes up from deep underground with the oil and boils near the fires. But the National Science Foundation's instruments found no water vapor in the plumes. Several scientists in that group concluded that it was light oil molecules turned to gas by the heat of the fire and later re-condensed into droplets.</p>
        <p>The Friends of the Earth team offered yet another theory: that it is water, but not water coming up out of the well. Rather, said Adam Trombly, a physicist and climatologist with the Aspen Institute for Advanced Studies, the ground is being cracked open by the disaster.  With no valves on top of them, the wells, which go as far as two miles down, are now handling more oil than they were designed for and are vibrating, creating fissures through which water and steam are shooting.</p>
        <p>That would presumably make the flow from underground harder to staunch. But it is less clear to oil men how cracks in the desert add up to environmental disaster. "If it's true, so what?" asked one oil expert at a company that does business in the Persian Gulf.</p>
        <p>The analysis thus far, from the National Science Foundation team and Environmental Protection Agency scientists who visited earlier, has mostly covered the garden-variety pollutants. But the pollutants that are mostly peculiar to Kuwait -- a class of carcinogens called poly-aromatic hydrocarbons, from unburned and partially burned oil -- still await measurement.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, many scientists have measured the pollution in its most obvious form, great clouds of smoke, but disagree as to what it means and on what to do, other than capping wells faster. Some Americans have criticized the Kuwaitis for insisting on competitive bids on essential fire-fighting equipment, while $100 million a day in oil leaked or burned, but apart from suggesting more help be hired, few have offered plans.</p>
        <p>Politics, or the suspicion of politics, underlies the dispute. Friends of the Earth maintains that the Bush Administration is playing down the environmental damage so as not to detract from the glitter of victory parades. They said the plume had risen to thousands of feet, far higher than the few hundred that Government scientists had first predicted. The science foundation said the plume had reached 22,000 feet, but maintained that this was far too low to cause climatic change. The Foundation's trip was paid for in part by the Defense Department, for research into the likelihood of a "nuclear winter" brought on by fires ignited by nuclear war.</p>
        <p>The two reports were, in effect, a declaration by environmentalists that the situation is halfway to catastrophe, and an assurance by Government-sponsored scientists that things would have to get twice as bad before there was a serious problem.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
