<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recycling Offers a Cleaner, Cheaper Solution Than Incineration</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="475309"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCINERATORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LIPTAK, BELA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEED7113EF932A1575AC0A967958260" item-length="459" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recycling Offers a Cleaner, Cheaper Solution Than Incineration</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>You report that the administration of Mayor David N. Dinkins is planning to spend $1 billion on building and expanding New York City incinerators (news article, Sept. 5). The city would be much better served if that $1 billion was spent on developing the markets for recycling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>You report that the administration of Mayor David N. Dinkins is planning to spend $1 billion on building and expanding New York City incinerators (news article, Sept. 5). The city would be much better served if that $1 billion was spent on developing the markets for recycling.</p>
        <p>You report that the city plans to burn 68 percent of its trash, or 10,000 tons a day. But trash-to-ash incineration is not a waste-disposal method; it is only a waste-reduction method. Incineration and recycling can both reduce the weight of municipal solid waste by about 75 percent.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, the remaining 25 percent residues are not similar. If the residue is from recycling, it can be safely disposed of in regular landfills, but if the residue is incinerator ash, which contains heavy metals and dioxins, it cannot. If the city was to burn 10,000 daily tons of trash, it would also have to build a disposal site for 2,500 daily tons of incinerator residue, some of which is toxic.</p>
        <p>One should also realize that recycling and incineration are in conflict: the more combustibles are recycled, the more difficult it is to burn the remaining solid waste. If all the paper and plastics are recycled, what is left is no longer combustible. Therefore a long-range contractual commitment to incineration could also mean an agreement to limit the recycling of combustibles.</p>
        <p>The incinerator industry likes to call incinerators resource-recovery or waste-to-energy plants. You also use these terms. This is misleading because overall incineration still wastes energy: it takes much more energy to produce such combustible materials as plastics than the amount of energy recovered by burning them. Every ton of paper recycled saves 17 trees; every aluminum can recycled reduces twentyfold the energy cost of producing a new one.</p>
        <p>The building of new incinerators will also result in the release of large quantities of carbon dioxide, further worsening the greenhouse effect. Recycling creates a whole new industry; it creates the types of low-skill jobs that are most needed, and it does not contribute to air pollution, does not generate toxic residues, does not exhaust resources, and it does not cost as much as incineration.</p>
        <p>To build just one 3,000-ton-per-day incinerator costs about $400 million. To reinstate the recently cut back recycling program in New York costs only $30 million. Incineration and recycling compete for financing from the same budget. If the sums required for building incinerators were spent to finance recycling programs, it would result in a better investment and less pollution.  BELA LIPTAK Stamford, Conn., Sept. 5, 1991 The writer is author of "Solid Waste Disposal and Recycling in the 1990's."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
