<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York State Weighs Canceling A Huge Canadian Power Contract</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19910906T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="469928"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HYDROELECTRIC POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTRACTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK POWER AUTHORITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HYDRO QUEBEC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONSOLIDATED EDISON CO OF NY INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND LIGHTING CO (LILCO)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ORANGE AND ROCKLAND UTILITIES INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydroelectric Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0D61039F93AA1575BC0A967958260" item-length="1192" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York State Weighs Canceling A Huge Canadian Power Contract</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The future of a giant hydroelectric construction project in northern Quebec, already under siege from environmentalists, faces a new threat: a move by New York State to back away from a $17 billion, 21-year contract to buy power.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday night, the New York Power Authority said it had reached an agreement with Hydro-Quebec to delay until Nov. 30, 1992, a decision on whether to buy one million kilowatts of hydroelectricity from the Canadian utility. The New York authority had originally said it would decide by the end of this year and, if it agreed to the sale, begin buying the power in 1995.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The future of a giant hydroelectric construction project in northern Quebec, already under siege from environmentalists, faces a new threat: a move by New York State to back away from a $17 billion, 21-year contract to buy power.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday night, the New York Power Authority said it had reached an agreement with Hydro-Quebec to delay until Nov. 30, 1992, a decision on whether to buy one million kilowatts of hydroelectricity from the Canadian utility. The New York authority had originally said it would decide by the end of this year and, if it agreed to the sale, begin buying the power in 1995.</p>
        <p>It said on Tuesday that it was reconsidering the Canadian deal because conservation efforts, among other factors, had improved the state's energy outlook since 1989, when the original agreement was reached. The Power Authority, a state agency that resells electricity to utilities at no profit, has been Hydro-Quebec's largest customer outside of Canada. It supplies about a quarter of the state's electricity.</p>
        <p>If the authority decides against going ahead with the contract, Hydro-Quebec would be likely to delay its sprawling Great Whale hydroelectric project near James Bay, utility officials and environmentalists say.</p>
        <p>If the contract is ratified, the Power Authority would buy one million kilowatts year-round, enough for one million households at any given moment. It would sell about 80 percent of the power to three utilities in the New York metropolitan area: Consolidated Edison, the Long Island Lighting Company and Orange and Rockland Utilities.</p>
        <p>Con Edison, which serves New York City, would buy almost half of the Canadian power for $6.1 billion over 21 years. If the contract falls through, the utilities would have to find additional power through further conservation or from greater reliance on independent power producers.</p>
        <p>The Great Whale project, 650 miles north of Montreal, is at the heart of Hydro-Quebec's plans to expand its northern Quebec operations, already among the world's largest sources of hydroelectric power.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists as well as the people in the region, chiefly the Cree Indians and the Inuit, have fought to stop the project. They say the utility's plan to dam the Great Whale River to generate the power, thereby flooding hundreds of square miles, would doom the hunting, trapping and fishing that have defined a way of life there.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists say that if New York cancels its agreement, the Great Whale project could be delayed for many years. The utility, which is owned by the province of Quebec, agrees there would be a delay but says it would be for only two or three years.</p>
        <p>Lining up big export customers like New York State is an important step if Hydro-Quebec is to obtain financing from Wall Street investors for the James Bay expansion, which the utility says is necessary to meet Quebec's growing energy demand. Second Thoughts</p>
        <p>The Power Authority's move to extend the deadline for a decision suggests that it is having second thoughts about the economics of the deal. In 1984, hydroelectric power from Hydro-Quebec met 8.8 percent of New York State's needs. But the total has dropped substantially in the last few years because of low water levels in Quebec.</p>
        <p>"These are signs that the deal is beginning to unravel," said State Senator Franz S. Leichter, Democrat of Manhattan, who has been a leading political opponent to the contract.</p>
        <p>In an interview, the authority's chairman, Richard M. Flynn, denied that the authority was smoothing the way for a contract cancellation. Instead, he said, the 11-month delay would be spent reviewing the cheapest ways to provide power to the state as well as the environmental costs of dependence on fossil fuels like oil.</p>
        <p>A draft of a New York State energy plan released this month found that a new contract with Hydro-Quebec could raise electricity rates slightly for New Yorkers. But it also noted that alternative power sources like oil- and coal-fueled plants could increase air pollution in parts of the state where pollution levels already exceed Federal standards.</p>
        <p>Mr. Flynn said the authority could decide to go ahead with the Hydro-Quebec contract but negotiate for a lower price or delay its 1995 starting date.</p>
        <p>In a statement Tuesday night, Mr. Flynn said that since 1989, when the tentative contract was signed, projections of the state's energy needs had changed because of progress in utility conservation programs and an increasing use of independent suppliers.</p>
        <p>"Now it's appropriate to re-evaluate the contract in light of these changed conditions," Mr. Flynn said.  Cuomo Says Option Open</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, Gov. Mario M. Cuomo has said in meetings with opponents of the contract that cancellation remained an option, said Frank Murray Jr., a spokesman for the Governor. But the state has yet to conclude that the Canadian power is uneconomical, he said. The Power Authority chairman is appointed by the Governor and confirmed by the State Senate.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Hydro-Quebec said he did not know what the Power Authority would conclude.</p>
        <p>"Frankly, I don't know. Every option is open," said the spokesman, Pierre Bolduc, executive vice president for external markets, in a telephone interview from Montreal. "We are aware that there are second thoughts about the contract in New York."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolduc said Great Whale would be built with or without the New York State contract because the Quebec economy would eventually require the power. He said the loss of the contract would probably delay the project's start-up, but only for perhaps two years, from 1998 or 1999 to 2000 or 2001. Big Setback Seen</p>
        <p>But people who have followed Hydro-Quebec's strategy say cancellation of the New York contract would be a major blow to the utility.</p>
        <p>"If New York pulls out, then Hydro-Quebec has to go back to the drawing board," said Jan Beyea, chief scientist for the National Audubon Society, which has been fighting the Great Whale project for five years.</p>
        <p>The society and other environmental groups have apparently been heard. Assemblyman William B. Hoyt, a Democrat of Buffalo and a leading opponent, said that a "ferocious environmental movement" had arisen in the last year in New York State and that the Power Authority's decision shows that Governor Cuomo "doesn't want to be painted into a corner" on the issue.</p>
        <p>This month, Mayor David N. Dinkins of New York wrote to the Power Authority chairman, Mr. Flynn, asking the agency to further study the economic value of the new hydropower.</p>
        <p>Hydro-Quebec's plan has also created a jurisdictional dispute in Canada; the province of Quebec is battling the Federal Government in Ottawa over who has final say on environmental review.</p>
        <p>James A. Dumont, a lawyer for several environmental groups as well as the Cree Indians, compared the fight against the new hydroelectric power to the long battle against nuclear energy, in which construction of many nuclear plants has been too costly to continue.</p>
        <p>"We may not have convinced the skeptics about the environmental problems," he said, "but for financial reasons the contracts will die."</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 6, 1991, Friday</p>
        <p>A map on Aug. 29 with an article about a proposed hydroelectric plant in Canada misidentified an island off the east coast of Canada. It is the island of Newfoundland, not Prince Edward Island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 6, 1991, Friday</p>
        <p>A map on Aug. 29 with an article about a proposed hydroelectric plant in Canada misidentified an island off the east coast of Canada. It is the island of Newfoundland, not Prince Edward Island.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
