<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Many Pros and Cons of the 55-M.P.H. Speed Limit</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="480075"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROADS AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPEED LIMITS AND SPEEDING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FEYERHERM, MARVIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speed Limits and Speeding</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D7143DF930A25753C1A967958260" item-length="408" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Many Pros and Cons of the 55-M.P.H. Speed Limit</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a Forum page article on Sept. 29, Donald L. Pevsner proposed raising the 55 mile-an-hour national speed limit on Interstate highways. He argued that the limit, set during the oil crisis of the early 1970's, is retained because it is a source of income for states, insurance companies and makers of radar-detection equipment. He suggested raising the Interstate speed limit to 70 m.p.h. except in congested urban areas and in unsafe terrain.</p>
        <p>Some of the letters received in response follow.</p>
        <p>Reasons to Slow Down</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a Forum page article on Sept. 29, Donald L. Pevsner proposed raising the 55 mile-an-hour national speed limit on Interstate highways. He argued that the limit, set during the oil crisis of the early 1970's, is retained because it is a source of income for states, insurance companies and makers of radar-detection equipment. He suggested raising the Interstate speed limit to 70 m.p.h. except in congested urban areas and in unsafe terrain.</p>
        <p>Some of the letters received in response follow.</p>
        <p>Reasons to Slow Down</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Mr. Pevsner believes "there is no oil shortage in the world today." Does this mean that if we have it, let's use it, with no thought for the future? Remember that each extra gallon of gasoline used contributes that much more carbon dioxide, carbon monoxide and unburned hydrocarbons to our already polluted atmosphere.</p>
        <p>He talks as if "today's cars" are the only vehicles on the road. He should realize that a 2,000- to 3,000-pound car traveling at 70 m.p.h. is one thing, but an 80,000-pound 18-wheel truck is quite another, and both will certainly have to continue to share the highways. The truck, just by virtue of its weight, has as much as 40 times the destructive power of a car. During a collision, it is much less maneuverable and its stopping distance is much greater than that of a car.</p>
        <p>Consider also the effect of increased speed on the available energy dissipated in the event of a collision. A vehicle in motion possesses a certain amount of kinetic energy. A vehicle traveling at 70 m.p.h. has 62 percent more energy available for destruction as one at 55 m.p.h.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pevsner also implies that limits are imposed only by the highway designs. Does he mean that if a straight section of highway was designed for 200 m.p.h. that traffic should be allowed at that speed? What about the inevitable human errors? What about the possibilities of mechanical failures? What about reaction-time limitations?</p>
        <p>Mr. Pevsner seems to pity the poor souls who have so little emotional control while driving that they feel compelled to exceed the speed limit. If they are treated unfairly by their insurance companies, let there be legislation to correct that. Psychological counseling may also be in order.</p>
        <p>It is certainly in order to question unreasonable speed limits, but let it be done with a little less emotion and more logic. MARVIN P. FEYERHERM Randolph, Vt., Sept. 30</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
