<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plants May Teach How to Make Fuel From Sunbeams</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="424641"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PHOTOSYNTHESIS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOLAR ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFD9173FF93AA25751C0A967958260" item-length="2457" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plants May Teach How to Make Fuel From Sunbeams</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SCIENTISTS believe they are on the verge of constructing test-tube versions of photosynthesis, the basic life process in which plants tap the sun's energy. Their aim is to open the way to new sources of usable energy based on the cheapest and most abundant of raw materials: sunlight, water and carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>In principle, the effort could eventually enable chemists to mount a new two-front attack on the threat of global warming posed by the buildup of carbon dioxide from burning fossil fuels. Artificial assemblies of photosynthetic molecules that converted the sun's energy into liquid fuels like hydrogen would both cut demand for oil, and remove carbon dioxide from the atmosphere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SCIENTISTS believe they are on the verge of constructing test-tube versions of photosynthesis, the basic life process in which plants tap the sun's energy. Their aim is to open the way to new sources of usable energy based on the cheapest and most abundant of raw materials: sunlight, water and carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>In principle, the effort could eventually enable chemists to mount a new two-front attack on the threat of global warming posed by the buildup of carbon dioxide from burning fossil fuels. Artificial assemblies of photosynthetic molecules that converted the sun's energy into liquid fuels like hydrogen would both cut demand for oil, and remove carbon dioxide from the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>"That's the dream," said Dr. Mark Wrighton, a chemist at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology who is in the forefront of photosynthesis research.</p>
        <p>"We can see how to do it and we're embarking at this point on a faithful reproduction of the biological system," he said in an interview. "We hope we'll be able to make inexpensive molecules, make them efficiently and make them durable."</p>
        <p>Dr. Wrighton was the main speaker on the subject at the Second Annual Frontiers of Science Symposium conducted recently by the National Academy of Sciences at Irvine, Calif., where many of the latest advances were described.</p>
        <p>"Understanding has been developing very, very fast," and the close circle of scientists working on the problem has become "a very excited group of people," said Dr. George L. McLendon of the University of Rochester, another speaker.</p>
        <p>In a critical step, chemists have already put together elegant artificial versions of the basic molecular mechanism that is at the heart of photosynthesis. In this mechanism, solar energy strikes molecules of chlorophyll inside the leaves of green plants. The energy infuses electrons with new force, sending them leaping and cascading from molecule to molecule, transferring energy as they go.</p>
        <p>The chain of reactions ultimately results in the conversion of atmospheric carbon dioxide to the carbohydrates that sustain almost all life. Oxygen is released to the atmosphere as a byproduct.</p>
        <p>Scientists believe they will be able in time to manipulate the process to produce not only carbohydrates, but also hydrogen, methane and other forms of chemical energy. Methane is the essential ingredient of natural gas, the burning of which emits less carbon dioxide than either coal or oil. The burning of hydrogen emits no carbon dioxide. It could be used to power motor vehicles or, combined with oxygen in a fuel cell, to make electricity.</p>
        <p>Plants convert solar energy to chemical energy inside organs called chloroplasts, tiny components of plant cells. The parts of the chloroplast that capture solar energy and set off the cascade of electrons are known as photochemical reaction centers. These are complexes of proteins and the green-colored chlorophyll molecules that give plants their distinctive color.</p>
        <p>Photosynthesis begins when particles of light, known as photons, strike molecules of chlorophyll. Each photon boosts an electron in the chlorophyll to a higher energy state. The excited electron then jumps across to a special "carrier" molecule nearby. This is the first in a sequence of leaps by electrons between molecules that are held in precise positions in a special membrane in the reaction center.</p>
        <p>Along the way, the electrons give up some of the energy imparted to them by the photon. In a reaction separate from the chain of jumping electrons, this energy is harvested as a compound known as adenosine triphosphate, or ATP. This compound plays an important role in the subsequent manufacture of carbohydrates. 'Dark Photosynthesis'</p>
        <p>Back in the main stream of electron flow, the energy level of the leaping electrons is reboosted by a second photon, and the electrons cascade down a second series of molecules. This chain of events culminates in the creation ofa molecule called nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate hydride, or NADPH. The NADPH molecule is a sort of special-purpose battery that stores electrons for the vital reaction in which NADPH teams with ATP to convert carbon dioxide from the air into carbohydrates, or sugars.</p>
        <p>These sugars provide food for plants and hence for almost all life. The reactions that create them constitute a second phase of the process, called "dark photosynthesis" because it is not directly dependent on sunlight.</p>
        <p>The electron that is lost at the start of photosynthesis, when a photon strikes the first chlorophyll molecule, must be replaced so as to restore the system to its initial state. Replacement electrons come from water molecules through a mechanism that is not yet completely understood. In surrendering electrons, the water molecules split apart into hydrogen atoms and oxygen. The oxygen is released to the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Despite their considerable understanding of this mechanism, scientists have only recently gained insight into what Dr. McLendon calls the "basic ground rules that nature is playing with." These involve, for instance, such critical details as the way in which the parts of the system are physically arranged in relation to each other, the distances electrons must travel and the speeds at which the action takes place.</p>
        <p>"There is nothing magic about the molecules used in photosynthesis," said Dr. Thomas E. Mallouk of the University of Texas at Austin, another participant in the Frontiers of Science symposium. "What's special about it is that they're organized in a certain spatial arrangement that allows the electrons to go in one direction in the chain."</p>
        <p>How the leap of electrons happens "is one of the big things that's been worked out in the past six years," said Dr. McLendon. "The distances that the electron has to jump are very big compared to the sizes of the molecules. It is clear that in photosynthesis, electrons can jump a lot farther than we used to think." Building Molecules That Work</p>
        <p>In the last few years, scientists in several laboratories have designed assemblies of molecules that mimic the photochemical reaction center in its ability to absorb photons and excite electrons. "We can make very complicated molecules now, and big ones," and they work, said Dr. Wrighton of M.I.T., whose laboratory is one of the makers.</p>
        <p>The first such molecule was synthesized in 1983 by chemists at Arizona State University. It consisted of an electron-donating molecule, a light-absorbing molecule and an electron-accepting molecule, all linked in the right way to make the photochemical reaction possible.</p>
        <p>Scientists say progress has been rapid since then, and several laboratories have produced synthetic molecules that duplicate the essence of photosynthesis.</p>
        <p>One of the latest, reported last year, is a five-part molecule called the pentad system, produced by the Arizona State laboratory that first created the triad molecule. "We're basically using the same building blocks as nature, but we're controlling the structure differently," said Dr. Devens Gust, a leader of the Arizona team.</p>
        <p>The pentad molecule is made of organic chemicals that absorb light and receive and donate electrons. The chemicals are porphyrins, quinones and sometimes materials derived from chlorophyll itself. But while nature embeds the molecules in protein, the Arizona State researchers hold them together through chemical bonds.</p>
        <p>The salient advantage of the molecule, said Dr. Gust, is that it mimics the multistep cascading of electrons so as to maintain an energetic state long enough for useful products to be derived. If the chain is too short, the energy will simply dissipate before anything useful can happen. 'Microscopic Swiss Cheese'</p>
        <p>Dr. Mallouk's group at the University of Texas is duplicating the light-induced cascade of electrons with a chain of nonbiological molecules containing the metal ruthenium. These molecules absorb light like chlorophyll. The molecule was devised by Michael Gratzel, a Swiss chemist.</p>
        <p>The Texas team has strung five of these molecules together, embedding them in a matrix made from minerals called zeolites. The zeolites are full of empty spaces, "like microscopic Swiss cheese," says Dr. Mallouk, and the spaces can be strung together to make tunnels about the size of a molecule.</p>
        <p>By choosing zeolites with the right pore size, the Texas team believes it will be possible to solve a major problem: how to hold the molecules in place at proper distances and angles from each other. This orientation "is going to be central to getting high efficiency whether we make electricity or whether we make chemical fuel," said Dr. Wrighton.</p>
        <p>In the first place, the molecule at one end of the electron-transfer chain must be kept away from the molecule at the other end; otherwise, the two molecules would exchange electrons and all the energy originally absorbed from the sun would be lost as heat. And even if they can be kept apart, molecules must be arranged in certain ways, relative to each other, for maximum efficiency of energy conversion from solar to chemical.</p>
        <p>Most of the artificial assemblies of molecules until now have been suspended in an electrolyte solution. This means that although the early steps of photosynthesis can be carried out efficiently, the energy is ultimately dissipated. Apart from the Texas zeolite method, researchers are trying to embed the molecules in some sort of biological material, as in nature; to bind them to films, and to suspend them chemically, as Dr. Wrighton's group is trying to do, between two electrodes.</p>
        <p>Researchers face an even more difficult problem in the question of how water molecules yield up electrons to replace those lost by chlorophyll. They do not fully understand this process, although they know that a manganese compound plays a critical role. 'Like a Tinker Toy Box'</p>
        <p>A group headed by Dr. Thomas J. Meyer of the University of North Carolina is approaching the problem by substituting a ruthenium compound for the manganese compound, which is hard to manipulate in an artificial system because it is so unstable. The more stable ruthenium mimics the action of manganese so well, said Dr. Meyer, that "we're beginning to get a good handle" on electron replacement.</p>
        <p>Still another challenge is presented by "dark photosynthesis," the final part of the process in which NADPH and ATP are used to create carbohydrates from carbon dioxide. Duplicating this, says Dr. Meyer, "is difficult chemistry" and "no picnic."</p>
        <p>How close are scientists to fashioning artificial photosynthetic systems that could produce usable energy?</p>
        <p>"We could almost put all this together in a single device now, but we're not quite ready yet," said Dr. Meyer. "It's just like a Tinker Toy box. All the pieces are lying around, some of them assembled, but the complete assembly has yet to be done."</p>
        <p>Dr. McLendon says that while "many people have done elegant synthesis and have made some lovely molecules," scientists understand the process "to about a 90 percent level.</p>
        <p>"But that's like saying we understand engineering principles to within 90 percent of building a bridge," he said. "You wouldn't want to drive over it." Economic Question Remains</p>
        <p>And even if all these problems are solved, years of further development will be required before any operational devices can be produced.</p>
        <p>A major question is how much of the energy carried by photons can be converted to practical use. Theoretically, said Dr. Wrighton, 20 to 25 percent could be converted. This efficiency would rival that of conventional photovoltaic systems.</p>
        <p>With such efficiencies, scientists believe, artificial photosynthesis might be used to produce a variety of fuels. In theory, chemists could manipulate the photochemical reaction center so as to produce methane or hydrogen in place of NADPH.</p>
        <p>Once the technical problems are solved, the question of economic feasibility remains. But the prospect of converting the sun's energy directly into liquid fuels, and of removing unwanted carbon dioxide from the atmosphere, is too important to ignore. So scientists are pressing ahead on the basic science of the problem in the hope of an eventual payoff.</p>
        <p>Dr. McLendon calls it "the scientific field-of-dreams approach" to technological advance: "If you build the foundation, it will come." Green Power: Inside the Plant's Energy Factory In photosynthesis, plants convert solar energy into the compounds ATP and NADPH, which play key roles in chemical reactions that create sugars out of atmospheric carbon dioxide. The sugars sustain almost all life, and the process releases oxygen to the atmosphere as a byproduct. All this takes place in tiny organs, called chloroplasts, within leaf cells. Scientists hope to open up new sources of energy by duplicating the process artificially. The Chemical Cascade of Energy Photosynthesis begins inside a complex of proteins and chorophyll, called a photochemical reaction center, when a photon, or particle of sunlight, strikes a chlorophyll molecule. The photon boosts an electron to a higher energy state, and it jumps to a special "carrier" molecule. This is the first in a sequence of such electron leaps. At the same time, protons accumulate in the lumen, or cell interior. Electrons lose energy along the way. To regain it, they jump to a second chlorophyll molecule, where a second photon reboosts the energy level, and a second cascade of electrons begins. It ends with the synthesis of NADPH. The protons that have accumulated in the lumen trigger the synthesis of ATP. Outside the photochemical reaction center, in the stroma, ATP and NADPH drive the manufacture of sugars from carbon dioxide. To restore the system to its initial state, the electron that is lost from chlorophyll at the start must be replaced. It comes from water molecules which then react to release oxygen to the air. Sources: Dr. Mark Wrighton; "Molecular Biology of the Cell"; "Molecular Cell Biology" Giant That Lost Race to Moon Soviet space officials have released details of the N1 rocket, designed to carry men to the Moon in the 1970's, a space ship whose existence was denied until a year ago. It failed because its many first-stage engines could not be mede to deliver stable, reliable thrust, the officials now say. Like the successful Unites States Saturn 5, it was about 370 feet long. The first three stages were to place the lunar module and Soyuz transport vehicle into Earth orbit. The fourth stage was to propel the vehicles toward the Moon, and the fifth stage was for insertion into lunar orbit, initial descent and return to Earth. Source: Daniel Gauthier, Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
