<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Key Signal of Cells Found to Be A Common Gas</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="457038"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOLOGY AND BIOCHEMISTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NITRIC OXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOLATA, GINA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFD91131F931A35754C0A967958260" item-length="2250" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Key Signal of Cells Found to Be A Common Gas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINA KOLATA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KOLATA, GINA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A SIMPLE and familiar chemical best known as a precursor of acid rain and smog is emerging in a surprising new role, as one of the most powerful known substances in controlling bodily functions. It has escaped physiologists' attention until now because it survives in the body for a mere five seconds or so, and because it bears no resemblance to any known biological regulator.</p>
        <p>The chemical is nitric oxide, and new findings show it is a messenger molecule involved in a wide range of activities. It mediates the control blood pressure. It helps the immune system kill invading parasites that sneak into cells. It stops cancer cells from dividing. It transmits signals between brain cells. And it contributes to the large-scale death of brain cells that can debilitate people with strokes or Huntington's disease.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A SIMPLE and familiar chemical best known as a precursor of acid rain and smog is emerging in a surprising new role, as one of the most powerful known substances in controlling bodily functions. It has escaped physiologists' attention until now because it survives in the body for a mere five seconds or so, and because it bears no resemblance to any known biological regulator.</p>
        <p>The chemical is nitric oxide, and new findings show it is a messenger molecule involved in a wide range of activities. It mediates the control blood pressure. It helps the immune system kill invading parasites that sneak into cells. It stops cancer cells from dividing. It transmits signals between brain cells. And it contributes to the large-scale death of brain cells that can debilitate people with strokes or Huntington's disease.</p>
        <p>Scientists expressed their amazement at discovering that nitric oxide is crucial to so many biological systems. As word of nitric oxide's significance spread, researchers first reacted with disbelief and then asked themselves how they could have missed the signs of its presence for so long.</p>
        <p>The nitric oxide discoveries, "were a total surprise," said Dr. Michael Marletta, a biochemist at the University of Michigan.</p>
        <p>"They still are a surprise," he said, adding: "Many scientists, when you first tell them about this, say it's just too unusual to believe. Some people still look at me, when they're being polite, with a sidelong glance."</p>
        <p>Dr. Salvador Moncada, research director at Wellcome Research Laboratories in London, said he wrote a short paper at the end of 1988 proposing that the nitric oxide was a universal signal transducer, meaning a intermediary that converts messages from one form to another. "People said I was mad," Dr. Moncada recalled.</p>
        <p>Now, Dr. Moncada said, the feeling is that "we have stumbled onto something very very big." Now, he said, "when we look at what we are doing, we often ask, 'How could we have missed this?' "</p>
        <p>Drug companies are starting to take the nitric oxide discoveries very seriously, hoping to develop from them new drugs to control blood pressure, prevent atherosclerosis, treat migraine headaches, prevent deaths from septic shock and help protect brain cells threatened by degenerative diseases and strokes.</p>
        <p>The first role of nitric oxide in the body was reported in 1987, and a cascade of other roles have been discovered in the five years since. Recent findings about nitric oxide indicate that it may provide the missing link between high blood pressure and heart disease. When nitric oxide touches the muscles that encircle blood vessels, the muscles instantly relax. This expands the vessels and lowers blood pressure. At the same time, Dr. Moncada said, nitric oxide regulates the accumulation of cholesterol plaque, which can clog coronary arteries.</p>
        <p>Putting the two together, Dr. Moncada said that inadequate production of nitric oxide could cause both high blood pressure and heart disease and could thus explain why the two conditions often go together.</p>
        <p>In the brain, researchers are finding that nitric oxide serves two roles. In small quantities, it is a neurotransmitter, carrying messages between cells. But some cells make much larger amounts of it, and then it forms a sort of toxic cloud that kills other cells. This happens after a stroke and in some degenerative diseases, including Huntington's disease, and possibly Alzheimer's disease.</p>
        <p>Researchers hope to protect brain cells in these cases by developing drugs that inhibit the formation of nitric oxide.</p>
        <p>Nitric oxide may even be used by the body to relax the stomach muscles, making the stomach expand so it can be filled with food. In a recent issue of Nature, the British science journal, Dr. John R. Vane of the William Harvey Research Institute in London and his colleagues reported that nitric oxide is released in the stomachs of guinea pigs to allow muscles to soften to accomodate food. In the Vessels Blood Pressure And Heart Effects</p>
        <p>Like other pivotal discoveries, the nitric oxide finding came about through serendipity as various groups worked on different problems that turned out to be part and parcel of the same thing.</p>
        <p>The story began a decade ago when investigators found that there was a mysterious substance that was made by the endothelial cells that line blood vessels. The substance diffused to the smooth muscle cells that grip the blood vessels and made the muscles relax. Yet the substance, which was known as endothelial-derived relaxing factor, appeared only fleetingly. No one had been able to capture it and characterize it before it was gone.</p>
        <p>The existence of this mysterious agent was discovered in 1980 by Dr. Robert Furchgott of the Downstate Medical Center, in Brooklyn, of the State University of New York. He and and Dr. Louis Ignarro of the University of California at Los Angeles speculated in 1986 that it might be nitric oxide, since the biochemical properties of nitric oxide were very similar.</p>
        <p>Another clue came from a finding that the old medicine nitroglycerine, which people have taken since the 19th century to alleviate the chest pains of heart disease, was slowly and inefficiently broken down in the body into nitric oxide.</p>
        <p>Dr. Moncada followed up this idea. He obtained a machine used to measure nitric oxide in the exhaust from cars and adapted it to look for the chemical in the exhalations of cells. There it was. Then he bought a tank of the gas, which is poisonous, and puffed wisps of it onto smooth muscle cells. They relaxed, exactly as they were known to do in response to the endothelial-derived relaxing factor.</p>
        <p>In studying how nitric oxide controls blood pressure, researchers found that blood pressure soared when the endothelial cells that line the arteries were preventing from making the chemicald. Conversely, when people were dosed with a little nitric oxide, their blood pressure dropped. An old remedy for seriously high blood pressure, sodium nitroprusside, is effective because it releases nitric oxide, scientists discovered.</p>
        <p>The emerging view of blood pressure control is that vessels constantly release puffs of nitric oxide that instantly relax the blood vessels and just as quickly are gone. Dr. John Hibbs of the University of Utah School of Medicine noted that this view is exactly the opposite of the prevailing theories.</p>
        <p>"We had always thought that the major signals that control blood pressure were signals that caused blood vessel constriction," Dr. Hibbs said. "Now we know that the major signal dilates blood vessels."  In the Cells Key Componentt Of Immune System</p>
        <p>A second thread of the nitric oxide story started with a question about substances that cause cancer. Researchers at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology wondered whether mammals synthesize nitrates and nitrites and, if so, whether they are being converted by cells into cancer-causing nitrosamines.</p>
        <p>The main source of nitrites and nitrates is the diet. The chemicals are in vegetables and are used as preservatives in cured meats. To test whether these are the only sources, Dr. Steven Tannenbaum of M.I.T. gave student volunteers a diet very low in nitrites and nitrates and analyzed their urine to see if they were making and excreting the chemicals anyway.</p>
        <p>During the experiment, one of the students developed a viral illness with diarrhea. Suddenly, she began secreting nine times the normal amount of nitrites and nitrates. This suggested to Dr. Marletta, who was at M.I.T. at the time, and to Dr. Dennis Stuehr, that white blood cells of the immune system, which are recruited to fight a viral infection, might be making nitrates and nitrites.</p>
        <p>They looked at macrophages, the scavenger cells of the immune system, and found that when these white blood cells were stimulated to fight an infection, they made nitrates and nitrites. They published a paper describing their results in 1985. Two Independent Discoveries</p>
        <p>Dr. Hibbs said he was enormously excited when he saw the paper. He had been studying macrophages since the early 1970's, trying to understand how they killed infected cells. And he already knew that the macrophages needed one crucial amino acid to do the job.</p>
        <p>That amino acid was arginine, which the cells converted to another amino acid, citrulline. A derivative of arginine could block the reaction and completely block the macrophages' lethal powers. "It was very puzzling to me at the time," Dr. Hibbs said. "How could the conversion of arginine to citrulline be associated with the killing of cells?"</p>
        <p>Then he realized what must be happening. When arginine is converted to citrulline, it loses a nitrogen atom.  And that nitrogen is turned into nitric oxide, which is what kills the infected cells.</p>
        <p>Dr. Marletta was on the same track, and the two scientists independently discovered the second link in the nitric oxide story. Not only did the compound relax blood vessel muscles, but it could also be made on demand by macrophages and other cells to kill invading organisms.</p>
        <p>Such parasitic invaders, like the mycobacteria that cause tuberculosis and leprosy, or the cryptococcus and toxoplasma organisms that often plague people with AIDS, slip inside healthy cells and try to take up residence there. The cells can destroy them with puffs of nitric oxide.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hibbs said that even cancer cells use nitric oxide, making it to control their own growth. When cancer cells start producing the compound, they stop growing. The cancer cells are prodded to produce nitric oxide by immune system hormones, including gamma interferon and tumor necrosis factor. Dr. Hibbs said that explained how the immune system hormones help defend the body against cancer. In the Brain Understanding Mass Cell Deaths</p>
        <p>Then brain researchers became intrigued. Dr. Solomon Snyder, a neurobiologist at Johns Hopkins University, said that as he learned of the nitric oxide work, he said to himself, "This is too nice not to be in the brain," and he and his colleagues soon found that nitric oxide had a major role in neurons. The enzyme that makes nitric oxide is present in greater quantities in the brain than anywhere else.</p>
        <p>Dr. Snyder said that the brain enzyme is in the cytoplasm, the substance that makes up the body of the cell, but he suspects it can move to the membrane that encases the cell when the cell needs to make nitric oxide. Then the chemical can be released outside the cell without hurting the cell that makes it.</p>
        <p>Nitric oxide acts as a neurotransmitter, passing messages between brain cells, Dr. Snyder discovered, but it is unlike any neurotransmitter ever found before. All the others are stored in little bags inside cells and released when they are needed. Nitric oxide, in contrast, is created only when needed.</p>
        <p>In addition, Dr. Snyder found, nerve cells sometimes release clouds of nitric oxide that they use to kill other nerve cells. But the cells making nitric oxide are themselves mysteriously protected from the noxious gas.</p>
        <p>For years, neurobiologists had been puzzled by a strange finding in the brains of people with Huntington's disease and, it has been reported, Alzheimer's disease. Although most nerve cells in certain areas of these patients' brains eventually died, some did not. Scientists could pick out the cells that are impervious to the killing going on around them by staining them with a dye, nitroblue tetrazolium, which made them turn blue. A Mystery Unravels</p>
        <p>But no one understood why the cells that turned blue were immune to the cell killing. Dr. Snyder and his colleagues found that the dye was identifying the nerve cells that were actively making nitric oxide. "Not only are those neurons uniquely resistant to the neurotoxicity that is going on around them, but they cause it," Dr. Snyder said.</p>
        <p>The researchers looked next at cell deaths in strokes. For a decade, investigators have known that the real damage from strokes occured after the initial event, when a blood vessel that supplied the brain was blocked.  That initial blockage starved a small group of brain cells, which quickly died.</p>
        <p>Then, nerve cells in a large surrounding area, 10 times the size of the area of initial cell death, begin to react. They release glutamic acid, a chemical that stimulates other cells to unleash a cloud of nitric oxide. The nitric oxide in turn kills all the cells in the area except the one releasing it.  Cells treated with N-methyl-arginine, a chemical that stopped them from making nitric oxide, did not kill their neighbors, Dr. Snyder found.</p>
        <p>Dr. Snyder and his colleagues have now isolated the gene for the protein that brain cells use to make nitric oxide. The structure of the protein indicates that it is regulated by many factors</p>
        <p>As the nitric oxide story develops, more and more scientists are asking themselves how they could have failed to find the chemical in years past. While nitric oxide's existence is fleeting, its breakdown products are not. "We have known for years that we excrete nitrates in our urine, but no one has ever really thought about that before," said Dr. Moncada.</p>
        <p>The problem, Dr. Moncada said, is that scientists were looking for the complex and missed the simple. "We were always thinking in terms of complex mediators," he said. "But this is very simple. We are beginning to realize that it is so simple it must be universal. And it is so beautiful that it must be in many different biological systems."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
