<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Campus Life: Clarkson; Solar Car Steers Pupils to Careers In Engineering</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="435838"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOLAR ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENGINEERING AND ENGINEERS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CLARKSON UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROCHESTER INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Engineering and Engineers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0D81E3EF934A35757C0A967958260" item-length="504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Campus Life: Clarkson; Solar Car Steers Pupils to Careers In Engineering</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>POTSDAM, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What does one do with a used homemade car -- especially one that relies on solar power and has been driven more than 1,600 miles?</p>
        <p>Teams of students at Clarkson University and the Rochester Institute of Technology have recycled their used solar cars and embarked on a venture to help attract more elementary- and secondary-school students to careers in science and engineering.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What does one do with a used homemade car -- especially one that relies on solar power and has been driven more than 1,600 miles?</p>
        <p>Teams of students at Clarkson University and the Rochester Institute of Technology have recycled their used solar cars and embarked on a venture to help attract more elementary- and secondary-school students to careers in science and engineering.</p>
        <p>Clarkson and R.I.T. were the only two colleges in New York State to compete in last summer's GM Sunrayce U.S.A., an 11-day solar-car race from Orlando, Fla., to Detroit involving 32 teams from the United States, Canada and Puerto Rico.</p>
        <p>In conjunction with the New York State Energy Research and Development Authority, each school has now developed a program that includes putting their student-built cars on display at grade schools, high schools and public events.</p>
        <p>Gregory A. Dolan, a communications associate for the authority, said the agency gave each school $5,000 to cover travel costs. In addition, he said, each school received $15,000 toward the development of its cars.</p>
        <p>Building Interest in Science</p>
        <p>Along with the solar-car projects, the authority sponsors an annual student research competition in which high school students design and build science projects to explore possible solutions to present and future energy problems.</p>
        <p>"These projects help stimulate an interest in science for those who think that science is boring and all textbooks," Mr. Dolan said.</p>
        <p>As part of their school visits, team members talk about alternative energy sources, like solar power, that could ease dependence on fossil fuels. Team members also try to interest students in taking math and science electives in high school, directing them toward careers in those fields.</p>
        <p>Since last fall, Clarkson's solar car has made approximately 50 appearances at schools and festivals throughout the state.</p>
        <p>Practical Benefits Stressed</p>
        <p>"Visiting the schools exposes the students to high technology in a practical sense," said Keven B. Dunphy, Clarkson's solar-car project coordinator and team member. "By getting the chance to sit in the car and seeing what happens when the car is driven, the students begin to appreciate the practical uses of science and technology."</p>
        <p>Since the end of the race, students from the Rochester Institute of Technology have visited about a dozen schools in the Buffalo-Rochester area.</p>
        <p>"Our goal is to promote engineering and scientific interests in grade schools and high schools, because there is a decrease in the number of scientists and engineers nationwide," said Lynn W. Bishop, a junior majoring in mechanical engineering at R.I.T. and a member of the school's solar-car team.</p>
        <p>During the visits, Mr. Bishop said, some students were skeptical that the sun-powered car could run, but once they saw it in action, they became believers.</p>
        <p>"We try to convey to them that anything can be done when you put your mind to it," he said. "We show them that math and physics can be interesting and very rewarding."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
