<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="487185"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DD173DF935A25752C1A967958260" item-length="1029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International 2-5  HOPE FOR SOLUTION IN HAITI</p>
        <p>Haitian lawmakers and a delegation from the Organization of American States have agreed on steps toward restoring constitutional government. Officials said the process might pave the way for the return of Haiti's deposed President.  Page 3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International 2-5  HOPE FOR SOLUTION IN HAITI</p>
        <p>Haitian lawmakers and a delegation from the Organization of American States have agreed on steps toward restoring constitutional government. Officials said the process might pave the way for the return of Haiti's deposed President.  Page 3</p>
        <p>BAKER PRESSURES BEIJING</p>
        <p>Opening talks in Beijing, Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d asked Chinese leaders to halt any transfers of nuclear arms technology to countries like Algeria and Iran and release political prisoners.  3  HOW TO PUNISH LIBYA</p>
        <p>The White House indicated that it would pursue diplomatic means before considering military retaliation against Libya for the 1988 bombing of a Pan Am jet. Officials talked of a possible oil embargo.  4  PALESTINIAN UNDER FIRE</p>
        <p>The Israeli police recommended that Hanan Ashrawi, the main voice of the Palestinians at the recent Middle East peace talks, be brought to trial for supposedly having met with P.L.O. officials.  4  SOVIET ARM SALES STIR FEAR</p>
        <p>Pentagon officials fear that Moscow is setting off a wave of arms proliferation by selling weapons and technology for badly needed cash.  5  TURF WAR IN MOSCOW</p>
        <p>Like many Soviet officials, Foreign Minister Boris D. Pankin is trying to figure out what his job is and struggling to keep it from being swallowed by the republics.  5  A HINT TO BRITAIN</p>
        <p>Ending two days of talks, Chancellor Helmut Kohl of Germany and President Francois Mitterrand of France warned that the European Community must take decisive steps toward unity at a meeting next month.5  DAY BY DAY IN DUBROVNIK</p>
        <p>Against a backdrop of medieval walls and tourist hotels, the people of Dubrovnik endure a nerve-wracking siege by Yugoslav gunners.  4  Bacolor Journal: The threat from a volcano is far from over.  2  Fresh acrimony among rival factions in Cambodia.  3  National 6-8, 26  CONVICTIONS OVERTURNED</p>
        <p>A Federal appeals court threw out the convictions of John Poindexter, the highest-ranking Reagan Administration official to be found guilty in the Iran-contra affair.  1  THE F.D.I.C.'S BIG LEGAL BILLS</p>
        <p>The Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, the world's largest employer of private lawyers, is wasting much of the $700 million it is paying them this year, two studies say.  1  CHANGING MEDICARE FEES</p>
        <p>In the biggest change in Medicare in 26 years, the Government issued a fee schedule that will increase payments to family doctors while reducing payments to specialists.  1  STOCK MARKET PLUNGES</p>
        <p>Stock prices tumbled nearly 4 percent, with the closely watched Dow Jones industrial average losing 120.31 points to close at 2,943.20. Biotechnology and insurance stocks were particularly hard hit.  1  2 B.C.C.I. OFFICIALS INDICTED</p>
        <p>The Justice Department announced the indictment of two officials of the Bank of Credit and Commerce International and a major shareholder on fraud and racketeering charges. But they are not in the United States, and it is uncertain they can be tried.  1  NO BIG FUN ON THE BAYOU</p>
        <p>Louisiana is full of rage and fear in the hours before the gubernatorial runoff between former Gov. Edwin W. Edwards and State Representative David Duke, a former Ku Klux Klan leader and neo-Nazi.  1  REVIEW OF POSTAL WORKERS</p>
        <p>A day after a former postal workers killed four supervisors, the postmaster general ordered a review of the personnel records of all the Postal Service's 750,000 workers as well as former employees.  6  IMPACT OF THINNING OZONE</p>
        <p>A leading marine scientist said today that the thinning of the atmospheric ozone layer over Antarctica had allowed ultraviolet radiation to penetrate much deeper into the ocean than suspected.  6  EVALUATING AID FOR COLLEGES</p>
        <p>Education Secretary Lamar Alexander said he would favor changing the relationship linking Federal financial aid to the accreditation of colleges and universities.  26  EXTRA BENEFITS FOR JOBLESS</p>
        <p>The Senate passed and sent to President Bush a bill providing extra unemployment benefits to those who have been out of work at least half a year. It also passed a measure making the extra benefits more generous in some states, but that bill must be considered by the House.  46  Many jobless say a few weeks of extra benefits won't help much.  46  Metropolitan Digest, 21  VIRULENT TB STRAIN KILLS 13</p>
        <p>A drug-resistant strain of tuberculosis has killed 12 inmates and a guard in the New York State prison system, and officials say it is the most alarming medical problem in the prison community since AIDS.  1  Business Digest 33  Sports 28-32  Baseball: Inquiries about Chambliss.  30  Basketball: Ewing fined $6,000.  29  Nets drop another game.  30  Celtics romp over Sixers.  30  College season tips off.  30  Columns: Vecsey on Florida football.  29  On Horse Racing.  32  Football: The Game in Florida.  29  Giants talk about Cowboys.  31  Jets' McNeil ready and willing.  31  Sports Leisure.  32  Sports People.  32  Tennis: Americans advance in A.T.P.  31  Consumer's World 48  Rising fraud is worrying automobile insurers  Car thefts are bedeviling auto rental agencies  Personal CD players are compact and versatile  Guidepost: Many holiday dishes can be prepared in advance  Obituaries 27  Tony Richardson, film director  Eugene J. Kupjack, creator Of miniature rooms for museum  Arts/Entertainment  More tinkering with Avery Fisher Hall's acoustics.  9  New Michael Jackson video.  9  Classical Music in Review.  12  Dance: Wim Vandekeybus.  9  Editorials/Op-Ed  Editorials 18  The trail from Lockerbie. Peace pipe for city budget. Limiting babel in the market. Ethnic politics at City Hall. Letters 18  Russell Baker: The Kevin excess.  19  Anna Quindlen: The waiting list.  19  Robert H. Kupperman and Tamara Kupperman: Pan Am 103.  19  Howard H. Hiatt: Meet Dr. Jarman. He makes house calls.  19  S. Scott Whitlow: Gender perfect.  19</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
