<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cree Chief Asks New York To Drop Hydroelectric Plan</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="477730"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREE INDIANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HYDROELECTRIC POWER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">QUEBEC PROVINCE (CANADA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COME, MATTHEW COON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Quebec</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydroelectric Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DF1430F932A35753C1A967958260" item-length="529" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cree Chief Asks New York To Drop Hydroelectric Plan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Cree Indian chief from Quebec's sub-Arctic came to New York City yesterday to urge the state to cancel huge contracts for hydroelectricity that would be generated on his native land, but state officials strongly suggested that they favored moving ahead with the purchase.</p>
        <p>The 20-year, $19.5 billion contracts were recently put under a year-long review in the face of bitter complaints from the Cree and environmental groups that the hydroelectric projects would devastate a vast stretch of wilderness near James Bay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Cree Indian chief from Quebec's sub-Arctic came to New York City yesterday to urge the state to cancel huge contracts for hydroelectricity that would be generated on his native land, but state officials strongly suggested that they favored moving ahead with the purchase.</p>
        <p>The 20-year, $19.5 billion contracts were recently put under a year-long review in the face of bitter complaints from the Cree and environmental groups that the hydroelectric projects would devastate a vast stretch of wilderness near James Bay.</p>
        <p>In testimony before a state legislative hearing in Manhattan, as members of environmental groups demonstrated outside, Matthew Coon Come, the grand chief of the Quebec Crees, told the lawmakers that the planned flooding of the Great Whale River would destroy traditional fishing and hunting grounds of the Cree and that other hydroelectric developments already in operation to the south were "eating away at the soul of my people."</p>
        <p>But at the hearing, Robert A. Hiney, the New York State Power Authority's vice president for marketing and development, repeatedly pointed to what he said would be the ecological and economic benefits of the hydropower for New Yorkers compared to burning fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hiney also disputed recent assertions by some utility analysts that the power may not be needed. He noted that more stringent Federal clean-air standards may speed up the closing of some oil plants and ultimately make the hydropower essential for meeting the state's energy demands.</p>
        <p>The issue of the Quebec hydropower has become extremely contentious in New York, with many energy officials defending it as an ideal way to curb air pollution within New York State and critics calling it an unacceptable export of environmental problems. The final decision is up to Gov. Mario M. Cuomo, who has said he will await the results of the state review of the contracts.</p>
        <p>The contracts call for a total of 1,800 megawatts of power, enough to provide as much as 10 percent of the state's average energy demand.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's hearing, sponsored by Assemblyman William B. Hoyt, a Buffalo Democrat, and State Senator Franz S. Leichter, a Manhattan Democrat, was one of the first in what is expected to be a lengthy series of public forums to examine the contracts in coming months.  'Remarkable Accomplishment'</p>
        <p>"The Cree have constructed no great earth works and built no pyramids," the Cree chief said, "but our grandfathers always managed to leave the land as it had been, and that was a remarkable accomplishment." Later, the chief met briefly at City Hall with Mayor David N. Dinkins. The Mayor was among those who called for a review of the contracts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoyt, a fervent opponent of the Quebec project who is chairman of the Assembly's Energy Committee, clashed repeatedly with Mr. Hiney over whether the power authority had a responsibility to take into consideration the project's impact on the Cree, Inuit Eskimos and the natural habitat of James Bay.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hiney said he was confident that the Canadian authorities would conduct an adequate environmental review. "They're a Western democracy," he said. "They have laws."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
