<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Global Threat Seen From Oil Fires</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="455320"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL SCIENCE FOUNDATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DD1430F936A15755C0A967958260" item-length="1038" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Global Threat Seen From Oil Fires</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In findings that confirmed earlier estimates, a team of scientists said today that the smoke from burning oil wells in Kuwait would not rise high enough or stay in the atmosphere long enough to affect the global climate.  But the researchers said the fires were causing substantial regional changes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In findings that confirmed earlier estimates, a team of scientists said today that the smoke from burning oil wells in Kuwait would not rise high enough or stay in the atmosphere long enough to affect the global climate.  But the researchers said the fires were causing substantial regional changes.</p>
        <p>The team, sent to the Persian Gulf by the National Science Foundation, made 35 flights through the billowing smoke on two airplanes. Although the smoke was thick and the planes became coated with oil thousands of feet in the air, there were unexpectedly low levels of some pollutants.</p>
        <p>Levels of sulfur dioxide, a cause of acid rain, and various other poison gases were lower than expected, the researchers said, and the level of ozone was less than on a sunny day in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>One important effect on Kuwait itself is the covering of the desert with oil and oil soot, said the scientists. "In effect, Kuwait is being painted black," said Dr. Larry Radke, director of the Research Aviation Facility at the National Center for Atmospheric Research. Walking on blackened desert would be like walking on asphalt, rather than white sand, he said.  Inquiry on Carcinogenics</p>
        <p>The team still has not analyzed its samples for the presence of carcinogenic chemicals called polyaromatic hydrocarbons, which are present in oil and are created by incomplete burning.</p>
        <p>The scientists in the group also differed sharply from oil experts in Kuwait on the source of white plumes rising from the wells. Firefighters and petroleum engineers in the country have been stating with assurance for weeks that this is steam, formed from water that is increasingly seeping into the oil flow because all pressure controls were blown up by Iraqi troops. But the scientists who reported today said that it was smoke, or possibly oil molecules that had turned to a gas in the heat of the fire and then re-condensed into droplets in the open air.</p>
        <p>The team's findings were also contradicted today by a group sent by Friends of the Earth International, an environmental organization, which asserted that the fires were becoming worse and that the white plumes were, in fact, steam, rising out of fissures in the earth created by the uncontrolled rush of oil to the surface. The group also said that pools of oil from the wells had recently begun catching fire, although such pools were burning in April, weeks before the team arrived.</p>
        <p>When the fires were first set by Iraqi troops, some researchers feared that smoke would rise to the stratosphere, the region of fast-moving air above the clouds, where it would spread out and linger, casting a shadow that would lower the earth's temperature. But the team concluded that this fear was unfounded. None of the smoke had risen above 22,000 feet, the team said, and most of it was much lower. In the Persian Gulf region, the stratosphere is at about 35,000 feet.</p>
        <p>But Adam Trombly, a physicist and climatologist who was a member of the Friends of the Earth group, said the smoke had already moved above levels in the United States Government's initial projections, which were that the smoke would not rise above 3,300 feet, and that each later report had found a higher ceiling.</p>
        <p>The National Science Foundation group was financed in part by the Defense Nuclear Agency, which is interested in the effects of large-scale fires because of the concern that in a nuclear war, huge fires would throw so much soot into the atmosphere that a "nuclear winter" would result.</p>
        <p>The fires in Kuwait are far larger than any other man-made event on which the hypothesis could be tested, but perhaps only 1 percent as large as the fires that would follow a large-scale nuclear exchange.</p>
        <p>Based on the height to which the soot from the wells has risen, Dr. George Ullrich, deputy director of the agency, said today, "the data suggest a considerably more benign assessment of the nuclear winter scenario."</p>
        <p>Another question raised by scientists about the fires, whether they will add to a "greenhouse effect" of global warming caused by the burning of fuel, was played down by the scientists. Prof. Peter V. Hobbs of the atmospheric sciences department of the University of Washington estimated that the emissions were equal to about 1 percent of normal global production.</p>
        <p>Dr. Radke pointed out, "The oil burning at the wellhead now would have been burned at the tailpipe," and said that the issue was not how much pollution the burning created, but the difference in pollution with an uncontrolled burn. Drop in Temperatures</p>
        <p>One effect, said the researchers, was that in Bahrain, an island off the Saudi Arabian coast that they used as their base, temperatures in May were 7.5 degrees Fahrenheit below normal, making it the coldest May in 35 years. But Dr. Hobbs said that "clearly it is not" of major global consequence. Some members of the group said the volcano in the Philippines was likely to have a greater impact.</p>
        <p>While the fires are small on a global scale, Dr. Hobbs pointed out that they are a huge regional problem, with a plume of smoke stretching 800 miles. The wells are burning in an area the size of Manhattan, he said, and if the plume were superimposed over a map of the United States, with the fires in New York, the smoke would cover Florida.</p>
        <p>The scientists did not offer any insight into the more immediate question of the effects on human health. Findings Called Preliminary</p>
        <p>The National Science Foundation team was made up of 27 scientists. The results given today were described as preliminary.</p>
        <p>But the Friends of the Earth also described them as understated. Mr. Trombly asserted that the National Science Foundation was deliberately trying to play down the importance of the fires, in collusion with the Federal Government, because the environmental problem "tends to diminish the military glitter and glitz" that the country is now enjoying.</p>
        <p>Brent Blackwelder, vice president of the American chapter of the group, said, "It is abundantly clear that the situation is out of control." He said the wartime allies should be doing more to fight the fires. In the northern part of the country, almost nothing has been done, he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
