<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Environmental Tax Urged for Some Products</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="421905"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">WORLDWATCH INSTITUTE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D6163CF933A25751C0A967958260" item-length="676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Environmental Tax Urged for Some Products</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Worldwatch Institute, a leading environmental research group, said today that governments should impose heavy taxes on "products and activities that pollute, deplete or otherwise degrade natural systems."</p>
        <p>By taxing products like the carbon in coal and oil and activities like dumping hazardous wastes, the United States could raise more than $130 billion a year while protecting the air, water and other natural systems that support life, the institute said in its 1991 "State of the World" report.The report acknowledged that such taxes would be passed along to consumers in the form of higher prices for things like gasoline, paper, waste disposal, drinking water, farm produce and electricity. To offset the effect on low-income families, it said, income taxes could be reduced.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Worldwatch Institute, a leading environmental research group, said today that governments should impose heavy taxes on "products and activities that pollute, deplete or otherwise degrade natural systems."</p>
        <p>By taxing products like the carbon in coal and oil and activities like dumping hazardous wastes, the United States could raise more than $130 billion a year while protecting the air, water and other natural systems that support life, the institute said in its 1991 "State of the World" report.The report acknowledged that such taxes would be passed along to consumers in the form of higher prices for things like gasoline, paper, waste disposal, drinking water, farm produce and electricity. To offset the effect on low-income families, it said, income taxes could be reduced.</p>
        <p>It identified eight potential "green" taxes: $100 a ton on the carbon content of fossil fuels like coal and oil; $100 a ton on hazardous wastes; $64 a ton on paper from virgin pulp; a tax of 50 percent of total sales of pesticides; $150 a ton on sulfur dioxide emissions; $100 a ton on nitrous oxides emissions; $5.83 a kilogram on chloroflurocarbon sales, atax already in effect in the United States, and $50 per acre-foot of water for depletion of water under the ground. 'Correcting Market's Failure'</p>
        <p>"Taxes are appealing because they offer an efficient way of correcting for the market's failure to value environmental services," the report said. "Taxing products and activities that pollute, deplete or otherwise degrade natural systems is a way of insuring that environmental costs are taken into account in private decisions -- whether to commute by car or bicycle, for example, or to generate electricity fromcoal or sunlight."</p>
        <p>The report said a tax on the carbon content of fossil fuels was "urgently needed" to slow the onset of global warming caused by the carbon dioxide that results from burning them.</p>
        <p>A study by the Congressional Budget Office last year found that although such a tax could be effective in reducing carbon dioxide emissions, it would be "hazardous for the economy if imposed too rapidly."</p>
        <p>But the budget office said that phased in gradually over the next 10 years and reaching $100 a ton by the year 2000, such taxes would reduce the gross national product growth by as little as 1 percent and no more than 2 percent over that period. The $100 a ton charge maintained over the longer run would hold the G.N.P. 1 percent below what it would have been annually, thebudget office estimated.</p>
        <p>Congress is not considering environmental taxes, and the draft energy plan being circulated by the Bush Administration pointedly omits any new taes on fuels like gasoline.  One Environmental Tax Working</p>
        <p>There is relatively little experience with environmental taxes in this country. The Federal Government did impose a $5.83 a kilogram tax on chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, two years ago as incentive to industry to find substitutes for these widely used industrial chemicals that endanger the earth's protective ozone layer. The tax is expected to raise about $5 billion over five years.</p>
        <p>Kevin Fay, executive director of the Alliance for Responsible CFC Policy, an industry lobbying group, said that the tax was effective at raising revenue but was probably not needed to force producers to make less harmful substitutes. Production of CFC's is "way down," Mr. Fay said, adding that the chief reasons were the slack economy and the pressure from scientists and environmentalists to find substitute chemicals, as well as an international treaty requiring that use of the chemicals be ended by the year 2000.</p>
        <p>A variety of environmental taxes have been introduced by Western European countries in recent years. A report by the Commission of the European Communities last year found that many of them had achieved their purposes. For example, an 8 percent tax on leaded gasoline, introduced in Britain in 1989, led to an increase in the market share of unleaded gasoline to 30 percent from 4 percent in one year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
