<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Scientists See No Danger in a Decade's Delay in Curbs on Warming</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="431601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATURE (JOURNAL)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHLESINGER, MICHAEL E (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JIANG, XINGJIAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DB163CF932A15750C0A967958260" item-length="878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Scientists See No Danger in a Decade's Delay in Curbs on Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 10-year delay in taking action to curb global warming would mean little further increase in the level of warming predicted by the end of the next century, according to calculations by scientists who advise a United Nations panel dealing with climate change.</p>
        <p>Controls deferred for a decade would, by the year 2100, achieve 95 percent of the reduction in the warming that would be achieved by imposing the controls immediately, the scientists say in a study appearing today in the British journal Nature.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 10-year delay in taking action to curb global warming would mean little further increase in the level of warming predicted by the end of the next century, according to calculations by scientists who advise a United Nations panel dealing with climate change.</p>
        <p>Controls deferred for a decade would, by the year 2100, achieve 95 percent of the reduction in the warming that would be achieved by imposing the controls immediately, the scientists say in a study appearing today in the British journal Nature.</p>
        <p>The results suggest that "the urgency is probably somewhat less than some people have tended to make it appear," said Dr. Michael E. Schlesinger, a climatologist at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. He is the author of the study along with another researcher at the university, Xingjian Jiang. The authors said a delay would give scientists time to pursue a "crash program" of research to reduce uncertainties about the severity of the expected warming. Scientists Are Divided</p>
        <p>Certain atmospheric gases, chiefly carbon dioxide, trap heat from the sun, much as a greenhouse does. Concentrations of the gases are steadily growing, mostly as the result of industrial and motor vehicle emissions. Scientists say this could cause the earth's surface temperature to increase by more than 5 degrees Fahrenheit by the end of the next century, with catastrophic effects on climate, crops, ecosystems and sea levels.</p>
        <p>Some scientists supported the finding being reported today. Others, while acknowledging that it may be accurate so far as it went, said that the finding failed to take account of a number of factors, and that using it as a guide to policy could be dangerous.</p>
        <p>The finding appears to support the Bush Administration's position that "it's better to get it right than to act precipitously," especially when the cost of action is high, said William K. Reilly, Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>The Administration also believes research should proceed in tandem with "action that is justified for other common-sense reasons" in addition to global warming, said Michael Deland, the chairman of the White House Council on Environmental Quality. The White House maintains that environmental actions already taken will keep United States emissions of heat-trapping gases from increasing for the next decade. Gore Sharply Differs</p>
        <p>But Senator Al Gore, the Tennessee Democrat who has strongly opposed the Administration's position, said in a statement, "The longer we wait, the harder the necessary actions become." He said delay would be "irresponsible" given the "potential for disastrous consequences."</p>
        <p>Dr. Schlesinger's group at Illinois, using a computerized mathematical model of the climate system, made the projections of future global warming adopted last year by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change. This is a United Nations-sponsored group that is providing scientific advice for continuing international negotiations on a global warming treaty. The Illinois researchers calculated that if no steps were taken to limit emissions of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases the average surface temperature of the globe would rise by 4 to 9 degrees Fahrenheit by the year 2100.</p>
        <p>In the study being published today, they greatly broaden the possible range of warming expected by 2100 if no action is taken, placing it at 1.6 to 10.6 degrees. Much of the difference is accounted for by a lower assessment of the climate's sensitivity to heat-trapping gases. That assessment was made by Dr. Richard Lindzen, a meteorologist at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, who has argued that the global warming threat is exaggerated.</p>
        <p>The calculations being reported today are also based on a mathematical model. They indicate that whatever the degree of warming, little difference would be made by a 10-year delay in instituting controls, which would include such measures as reducing the burning of fossil fuels like coal and oil. The scientists assumed it would take 20 years to phase in any controls.</p>
        <p>The results, the study said, indicate that "the penalty is small" for a 10-year delay.</p>
        <p>"I think it has to be reckoned as reasonable," Dr. Lindzen. Are Factors Overlooked?</p>
        <p>Other climatologists said that while the finding might be correct it overlooked several important factors. Some scientists say the expected global warming may well proceed not gradually, as the Schlesinger calculations assume, but unevenly, with sudden spurts in temperature as climatic thresholds are reached. This possibility of sudden change makes it dangerous to wait, said Dr. James E. Hansen, a climatologist at the Goddard Institute for Space Studies in New York.</p>
        <p>Dr. Michael Oppenheimer of the Environmental Defense Fund agreed. Moreover, both he and Dr. Hansen said, delay would make it more difficult and expensive to impose controls on heat-trapping gases if, after 10 years, they were deemed necessary.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly said improvments in technology could make it easier to reduce emissions in the future. He also said the certainty about warming that would come from more research would be useful in overcoming the skepticism of some undeveloped countries about the need for controls.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
