<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation; The Environmental Impact of President Bush</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week In Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="469157"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WETLANDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DIOXIN (CHEMICAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAZARDOUS AND TOXIC SUBSTANCES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wetlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5D6153AF936A1575BC0A967958260" item-length="1199" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation; The Environmental Impact of President Bush</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 1988, George Bush stood on the deck of a boat in Boston's filthy harbor and proclaimed himself an environmentalist. Throughout the campaign he promised to scrub the skies with a strengthened Clean Air Act, set a goal of "no net loss of wetlands" and do everything in his power to halt global environmental threats. "Those who think we're powerless to do anything about the greenhouse effect," he declared in a speech in Michigan in August 1988, "are forgetting about the White House effect."</p>
        <p>This month, prompted by Administration proposals to open millions of acres of wetlands to development and to officially lower the risk estimates for dioxin and other long-feared contaminants, Mr. Bush's record on the environment is undergoing more scrutiny than at any other time in his Presidency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 1988, George Bush stood on the deck of a boat in Boston's filthy harbor and proclaimed himself an environmentalist. Throughout the campaign he promised to scrub the skies with a strengthened Clean Air Act, set a goal of "no net loss of wetlands" and do everything in his power to halt global environmental threats. "Those who think we're powerless to do anything about the greenhouse effect," he declared in a speech in Michigan in August 1988, "are forgetting about the White House effect."</p>
        <p>This month, prompted by Administration proposals to open millions of acres of wetlands to development and to officially lower the risk estimates for dioxin and other long-feared contaminants, Mr. Bush's record on the environment is undergoing more scrutiny than at any other time in his Presidency.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists, to no one's surprise, attacked the wetlands and dioxin proposals and asserted that the President was backing away from pledges he made in the campaign. "He's talking the talk, but he's not walking the walk," said Representative Gerry Sikorski, a Minnesota Democrat who is an influential voice on environmental issues.</p>
        <p>But industrialists say that the President appears capable of balancing business and environmental goals, and they are encouraged. "If you compare this Administration with the last three, there is no doubt the President has taken the point on environmental issues," said Gordon D. Strickland, a vice president of the Chemical Manufacturers Association in Washington.</p>
        <p>An examination of the record suggests that Mr. Bush's environmental policies are neither as good as the White House says nor as bad as the environmental community contends.</p>
        <p>The Administration, with its eye to the 1992 campaign, argues that Mr. Bush's record on the environment puts him in the first rank of conservation-minded Presidents. "In the last two-and-a-half years, George Bush has done more for the environment than virtually any of his predecessors," said Robert E. Grady, the associate director for natural resources, energy and science at the White House Office of Management and Budget.</p>
        <p>At the top of the list of achievements credited to Mr. Bush is the new Clean Air Act enacted last year. The President broke a stalemate in Congress and helped to push through the most comprehensive environmental statute ever enacted, a law that sets out to reduce urban smog, cut acid rain, and control toxic chemicals in the atmosphere. But environmental groups say that in writing the Federal regulations mandated by the law, the Administration is blunting its effect.</p>
        <p>For example, the Clean Air Act requires companies to get permits that set limits on the levels of pollutants they are allowed to emit. But a proposal offered by the White House would allow companies to exceed those limits automatically if states do not review requests for changes within seven days.</p>
        <p>But environmentalists give the Administration credit for the move by E.P.A. Administrator William K. Reilly in 1989 to block the construction in Colorado of the Two Forks Dam, which would have destroyed a scenic canyon. And this month, the E.P.A. was praised for helping to reach an agreement to reduce haze in the Grand Canyon. Mr. Bush also set a 10-year moratorium on oil drilling off the coasts of New England, southern Florida and California. He authorized the Energy Department and the Pentagon to spend nearly $7 billion this year for cleaning up toxic chemicals and radioactive contamination from weapons manufacture. And he signed a treaty banning imports of ivory.</p>
        <p>"Looking at the record, you see he cares," said Brooks B. Yeager, the Washington legislative director for the National Audubon Society. "You also get a sense that he could be much better than he is, that he could carve a niche for himself. But he seems paralyzed at times. In the large problem areas where taking action requires facing down the conservative elements of his constituency, he's been much more hesitant."  Planetary Problems</p>
        <p>In the national energy strategy made public in the Persian Gulf War, Mr. Bush called for increased production by opening the untouched Arctic National Wildlife Refuge in Alaska to oil exploration while at the same time asking for very modest energy conservation measures.</p>
        <p>In the debate over global climate change, which has put the United States at odds with most of its allies, the Administration has insisted that it is already doing more than other nations to reduce the threat. The White House says the Clean Air Act and an international treaty to phase out the use of chlorofluorocarbons, chemicals that destroy the earth's ozone shield, make the United States a leader in efforts to counteract global warming. Environmental scientists, however, say the United States is steadfastly resisting limiting its production of carbon dioxide, the principal cause of global warming, because of concerns about curtailing industrial expansion.</p>
        <p>Then there is the wetlands policy announced earlier this month. After coming under heavy political pressure from developers, oil companies and other industries that contribute heavily to the Republican Party, the President proposed action that could reduce by tens of millions of acres the amount of low-lying bottomlands, marshes, swamps and other wetlands now protected from development.</p>
        <p>The White House said the new policy would still safeguard more land than was protected before 1989, when the existing wetlands policy was put into effect. But the Environmental Defense Fund, a national group based in New York, said the proposal "would constitute probably the largest weakening of an environmental regulation in U.S. history."</p>
        <p>The energy, global warming and wetlands policies largely reflect the attitudes of the President's closest conservative aides, say Administration officials: John H. Sununu, the chief of staff; Richard G. Darman, the director of the Office of Management and Budget; Michael J. Boskin, the head of the Council of Economic Advisors; and Roger P. Porter, the domestic policy adviser. Vice President Dan Quayle has also become an influential player in environmental issues as head of the White House Council on Competitiveness, which has emerged as an important voice for business interests.</p>
        <p>More moderate members of the Administration, led by Mr. Reilly of the E.P.A., have challenged the conservative view on environmental issues, but by all accounts Mr. Bush has been satisfied to let the two sides battle without interfering. Against such stiff competition, Mr. Reilly is generally overwhelmed.</p>
        <p>Administration officials say Mr. Sununu, Mr. Darman and Mr. Boskin are convinced that aggressive measures on the environment alienate the party's business constituency. Mr. Reilly and his supporters say such thinking is short-sighted. In case after case, factories that modernize pollution equipment find that they also become more efficient. Polls show that 75 to 85 percent of the public supports tough environmental regulation. In its quest to become the majority party, some officials say, the environment could play an important role for the Republicans, especially in attracting young voters.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
