<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Film; Saving the Savages, but Losing Themselves</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="491897"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CANBY, VINCENT</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">AT PLAY IN THE FIELDS OF THE LORD (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DB1F3FF935A35751C1A967958260" item-length="971" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Film; Saving the Savages, but Losing Themselves</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT CANBY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CANBY, VINCENT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"At Play in the Fields of the Lord," Hector Babenco's adaptation of the Peter Matthiessen novel, is a big, melancholy screen adventure, vividly realized in the jungles of Brazil, about people out of touch with one another and at dangerous odds with a primeval world they understand not at all.</p>
        <p>With fidelity to the book, and to the look, sound, heat and wet of the exotic locale, Mr. Babenco evokes the arrogant confusion of a small group of mismatched North Americans, caught in a brutal landscape that overwhelms them even as it's disappearing. Though the movie sometimes has trouble expressing what's on its mind, it is a rare movie in that it has something on its mind to express.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"At Play in the Fields of the Lord," Hector Babenco's adaptation of the Peter Matthiessen novel, is a big, melancholy screen adventure, vividly realized in the jungles of Brazil, about people out of touch with one another and at dangerous odds with a primeval world they understand not at all.</p>
        <p>With fidelity to the book, and to the look, sound, heat and wet of the exotic locale, Mr. Babenco evokes the arrogant confusion of a small group of mismatched North Americans, caught in a brutal landscape that overwhelms them even as it's disappearing. Though the movie sometimes has trouble expressing what's on its mind, it is a rare movie in that it has something on its mind to express.</p>
        <p>The principal characters include a pair of mangy bush pilots, Moon (Tom Berenger) and Wolf (Tom Waits), who, low on money and gas, are stranded at a godforsaken jungle outpost, their passports and single-engine plane impounded. Wolf is a profane, hard-drinking urban lout.  Moon is a moody loner, who is also half American Indian.</p>
        <p>Also in the village, staying at the only hotel, are two youngish missionary couples, Leslie and Andy Huben (John Lithgow and Daryl Hannah) and Martin and Hazel Quarrier (Aidan Quinn and Kathy Bates) who, with their small son, have just arrived from the States.</p>
        <p>The Hubens and the Quarriers share an earnest, psalm-singing, fundamentalist Christian faith. They are out to save the savages (Hazel Quarrier's term) from their Stone Age ways and from the Roman Catholic priests who, if they could, would have saved the savages first.</p>
        <p>The screenplay, adapted by Jean-Claude Carriere and Mr. Babenco, tells several stories simultaneously.  It's about Moon's reverse conversion when he leaves civilization's squalid outpost to join the Niarunas, an especially primitive Indian tribe he associates with his own North American people.</p>
        <p>It's also about the missionaries' attempt to set up a jungle church to convert the Niaruna, about the collapse of the courage of one of the missionaries, the loss of faith of another and the madness of a third. "At Play in the Fields of the Lord" doesn't play smoothly, but it often plays well.</p>
        <p>The film's most interesting character, acted by Mr. Quinn with a secretive kind of intelligence, is Martin Quarrier. Trapped in a marriage to a woman of small, unstable mind, Martin would honor both his marriage and his faith and becomes, almost in spite of himself, heroic.</p>
        <p>Unlike the Quarriers' marriage, the Hubens' appears to be a happy one. It seems to be a true union of body, mind and spirit, but then it become apparent that Leslie Huben is the sort of man who is more skillful at public relations and moral compromises than at his work in the field.  Except for the particular crisis that these missionaries must face, the Hubens' marriage would probably have been a long and satisfying one.</p>
        <p>Though the enlightened Martin Quarrier is the center of the film, the character on whom the film rests is Moon, whose search for identity is not dramatized in any convincing way. It isn't just that the movie cannot enter Moon's thoughts. The novel has the same problem, even though Mr. Matthiessen devotes many pages to Moon's drug-induced hallucinations before he makes his big leap to freedom.</p>
        <p>"At Play in the Fields of the Lord" looks sensationally good. There is no faking these jungle locations, whether seen from the air, as Moon's fragile plane flies wanly into a time long past, or on the ground, where the flora can be as malignant as the fauna. A number of individual scenes stand out, including an early bar encounter of the drunken Moon with the naive Martin Quarrier and an amused, patient Catholic priest.</p>
        <p>Says Moon, "If the Lord made Indians the way they are, who are you to make them different?" That is the film's worthy but not exactly novel point.</p>
        <p>The life at the jungle church settlement is richly realized. Yet an important scene, in which the beautiful Andy Huben goes skinny-dipping, seems wildly out of place, if only because Miss Hannah's body looks too magnificent to be entirely true in these circumstances. The scene is essential to everything that happens afterward and is taken directly from the book, but fidelity sometimes backfires.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lithgow and Miss Hannah, who grows more secure as an actress with every film, are fine in complex roles that are exceptionally well written.  Miss Bates is splendid as a big, slow, furious and frightened woman, someone who should never have ventured south of Orlando, Fla. Mr. Berenger maintains his self-respect in sequences that often suggest the National Geographic come to life.</p>
        <p>Though the film features a spectacular penultimate sequence, it seems not to know how to end. It sort of drifts away, perhaps trying to soften its own well-earned pessimism.</p>
        <p>Whatever the reason, "At Play in the Fields of the Lord" leaves one a bit bemused, vaguely worrying about the fate of the rain forests and the ozone layer as the endangered Indians. To this extent, the movie can be said to engage the intellect somewhat more than the emotions.</p>
        <p>"At Play in the Fields of the Lord," which has been rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian), has nudity, violence and vulgar language. At Play in the Fields of the Lord Directed by Hector Babenco; screenplay by Jean-Claude Carriere and Mr. Babenco, based on the novel by Peter Matthiessen; director of photography, Lauro Escorel; edited by William Anderson; music by Zbigniew Preisner; production design, Clovis Bueno; produced by Saul Zaentz; released by Universal Pictures. Running time: 180 minutes. This film is rated R. Lewis Moon . . . Tom Berenger Leslie Huben . . . John Lithgow Andy Huben . . . Daryl Hannah Martin Quarrier . . . Aidan Quinn Wolf . . . Tom Waits Hazel Quarrier . . . Kathy Bates</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
