<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="483743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DD1231F933A05753C1A967958260" item-length="1172" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-13</p>
        <p>The Middle East peace talks begin today in Madrid under a mood of guarded optimism after both Israeli and Palestinian leaders issued encouraging statements. Page A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: The conference has already highlighted new relationships between Arabs and Arabs, between Israel and the United States and most importantly between the United States and the Soviet Union. A11</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-13</p>
        <p>The Middle East peace talks begin today in Madrid under a mood of guarded optimism after both Israeli and Palestinian leaders issued encouraging statements. Page A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: The conference has already highlighted new relationships between Arabs and Arabs, between Israel and the United States and most importantly between the United States and the Soviet Union. A11</p>
        <p>Two scholars serve as Palestinian's data base A12</p>
        <p>At Israel funeral, mood is defiant A12</p>
        <p>Mubarak warns Israelis on East Jerusalem issue A12</p>
        <p>Peace talks offer a maze of issues A11</p>
        <p>Presidents Bush and Gorbachev met, and later Mr. Bush praised his "friend" and urged the restive Soviet republics to give him power to negotiate foreign aid programs. A10</p>
        <p>The Ukraine's independence drive no longer seems like an improbable, passing whim. Presidential candidates staunchly support independence, and the Parliament has authorized the formation of an army and a central bank. A1</p>
        <p>President Walesa offered to serve as his own Prime Minister over Poland's fragmented legislature, a move that was immediately condemned by some as a step toward one-man rule. A1</p>
        <p>Medieval Dubrovnik confronts life under siege A5</p>
        <p>"Boat people" would be returned by the tens of thousands from detention centers in Hong Kong to Vietnam under an agreement reached by the British and Vietnamese governments. A1</p>
        <p>A U.S. trade ban on Haiti was announced by the Administration, sharply raising the pressure on the hemisphere's poorest country to return to constitutional rule. A3</p>
        <p>Tokyo Journal: A TV idol unclothed A4</p>
        <p>Belgian troops, defying Mobuto, stay in Zaire to help foreigners A6 NATIONAL A16-23</p>
        <p>A far-reaching anti-smog program, based on California's rules requiring cleaner cars, would be adopted by nine Eastern states and the District of Columia under an agreement reached by the states' governors and the Mayor of Washington. A1</p>
        <p>U.S. unveils rules to limit acid rain A23</p>
        <p>The economy expanded for the first time in a year during the July-September quarter but the recovery was already losing momentum by Labor Day, the Commerce Department reported. A1</p>
        <p>Despite billions in tax increases, states cut back A16</p>
        <p>House leaders say compromise possible on jobless benefits A20</p>
        <p>A former senior White House aide said he had terminated a $600,000 legal contract to represent the former head of Saudi Arabian intelligence who is under scrutiny in the investigation of the Bank of Credit and Commerce International. D1</p>
        <p>Charges that the Reagan campaign struck a deal with Iran in 1980 to delay the release of American hostages until after the election will be investigated by an inquiry authorized by the Senate Foreign Relations Committee. A22</p>
        <p>A Pennsylvania Senate candidate, Harris Wofford, has made sharp gains in voter polls by being a strong advocate of national health insurance. His opponent is former Attorney General Dick Thornburgh.  A16</p>
        <p>U.S. and states head for clash over medicaid A21</p>
        <p>Strikes cripple six Los Angeles hospitals A20</p>
        <p>The suspect in the assassination of Medgar Evers, the civil rights leader, has been linked by prosecutors to a little-known racist group whose members are said to consider themselves "God's executioners." Prosecutors are seeking to block his release from jail on bond. A18</p>
        <p>New radar images of Venus reveal that the planet has apparently been resurfaced by volcanic eruptions and its second-highest mountain covered with lava from an active volcano, scientists reported.  A21</p>
        <p>Computer is pushed to edge to solve old chess problem A18</p>
        <p>Split on homosexuality, church rejects a prospective leader A19 REGIONAL B1-6</p>
        <p>New York City's public hospitals, their direction and the quality of care they provide are greatly influenced by large private medical schools, which provide them with many doctors. This influence is at the heart of a simmering controversy.  A1</p>
        <p>Leonard Jeffries's reappointment as chairman of the black studies department at City College was denounced by Governor Cuomo, even as Dr. Jeffries complained that he had not been given a chance to defend himself before a decision was made to limit his term. B1</p>
        <p>Governor Florio urged voters to "send a message" to President Bush by voting against Republicans in the elections next Tuesday for control of the New Jersey State Legislature.  B1</p>
        <p>The Suffolk County Executive, Patrick Halpin, is a Democrat in a county thick with Republicans. But in his re-election bid he seems to be running more against the area's poor fiscal shape than against his Republican opponent, Robert Gaffney.  B1</p>
        <p>Weicker in a deal to restore jobs B3</p>
        <p>Support for needle-exchange plans to combat AIDS has been growing on many fronts, as reflected by acquittals for those arrested for giving out needles illegally, studies indicating the programs are effective, and an endorsement by the National Commission on AIDS. B1</p>
        <p>The mother of a Utah tourist who was slain during a subway robbery testified that her family had hoped to see her son alive at the hospital where he was taken but that he had died on the way there. B3</p>
        <p>Two are killed in a shootout at a Harlem gambling den B3</p>
        <p>Bias cited in beating of two blacks B3</p>
        <p>Public hearings will take input on shelter issue B4 BUSINESS DIGEST D1 The Living Section</p>
        <p>Few people will eat whatever crawls onto the plate C1</p>
        <p>I'll have my milk with cream, and pass the butter C1</p>
        <p>Eating Well C1</p>
        <p>At hash houses, which fork?  C3</p>
        <p>In Nepal, artichokes teach a lesson C10</p>
        <p>Wine Talk C12 Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>Parisians flock to "Les Mis" C15</p>
        <p>Theater: "The White Rose" C15</p>
        <p>Film: "Black Robe" C15</p>
        <p>Music: The Pop Life C15</p>
        <p>Dance: Works by Meredith Monk C14</p>
        <p>Word and Image: Two views of the Bill of Rights C19</p>
        <p>Two looks at Paul McCartney C20 Education Page B7</p>
        <p>Science centers help schools bring classes alive</p>
        <p>To teach distant pupils, educators in Kentucky turn on TV Obituaries D25</p>
        <p>Ben Hill Willingham, executive in apparel and textile field</p>
        <p>Dr. Joseph F. Fletcher, pioneer in field of medical ethics</p>
        <p>Frederick G. Frost Jr., architect Sports B8-13</p>
        <p>Baseball: It's Showalter for Yanks B9</p>
        <p>Columns: Anderson on Steinbrenner and Showalter B9</p>
        <p>Smith on Baseball B11</p>
        <p>Football: Discussing tapes, Dye is anxious but firm B9</p>
        <p>Hockey: Rangers edge North Stars B9</p>
        <p>Islanders top Sharks B13</p>
        <p>Marathon: New York organizers look ahead B10 Health Page C13</p>
        <p>Simplifying surgical removal of precancerous lesions Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials A24</p>
        <p>Momentum in Madrid</p>
        <p>Why the delay on Dr. Jeffries?</p>
        <p>Computer speech, also free</p>
        <p>Mary Cantwell: Downtown</p>
        <p>Letters A24</p>
        <p>Anna Quindlen: Things that don't go bump A25</p>
        <p>Leslie H. Gelb: Mideast tricks or treaties?  A25</p>
        <p>Arthur Hertzberg: Not love but marriage in Madrid A25</p>
        <p>Raghida Dergham: A call for candor by Arabs A25</p>
        <p>Stephen Breyer: Russian judges want real justice A25</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
