<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Imaginary Monsters That Dare a Visitor to See the Show</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="437296"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART SHOWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAYNOR, VIVIEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BEERMAN, MIRIAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D7163AF937A25757C0A967958260" item-length="934" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Imaginary Monsters That Dare a Visitor to See the Show</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIEN RAYNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAYNOR, VIVIEN</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MIRIAM BEERMAN'S 41-year retrospective is more than the State Museum here can handle. It is not so much the size of the show, although the 128 works, many of them measuring 6 feet by 7 feet or more, do seem wedged into their space, but rather its character, which is somewhat forbidding. Monstrous figures in colors that are alternately somber and lurid, they challenge the visitor to enter the gallery.</p>
        <p>Evil has been an obsession with this painter for most of her career. And it is evil in the heroic style expressed with mannerisms that recall Jose de Cuevas, Leon Golub, Francis Bacon and other artists who began their careers after World War II.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MIRIAM BEERMAN'S 41-year retrospective is more than the State Museum here can handle. It is not so much the size of the show, although the 128 works, many of them measuring 6 feet by 7 feet or more, do seem wedged into their space, but rather its character, which is somewhat forbidding. Monstrous figures in colors that are alternately somber and lurid, they challenge the visitor to enter the gallery.</p>
        <p>Evil has been an obsession with this painter for most of her career. And it is evil in the heroic style expressed with mannerisms that recall Jose de Cuevas, Leon Golub, Francis Bacon and other artists who began their careers after World War II.</p>
        <p>The Social Realism that had prevailed before the war rose again in its aftermath, but with a more sophisticated "world" view. Goya, who said all there was to say about human savagery, was a major influence. But so, too, was Picasso in his "Guernica" period, and it seems that he more than any other artist pointed the way to a new kind of figuration. The trail of carnage left by the war, of course, provided motivation.</p>
        <p>For a while, realism flourished in Paris and London, as well as in the United States. But when Abstract Expression came stomping in at the end of the 1940's, the figure was put out to grass, and ideas about a moralistic art were abandoned. There remained, however, many holdouts, including the sculptor Leonard Baskin, who once wrote that "man has made of Arden a landscape of death," adding that "in limning its horror," he himself held "the cracked mirror up to man."</p>
        <p>Though reinstated briefly and with tongue in cheek by Pop, the figure was not returned to full circulation until the 1980's, and by that time high seriousness had been replaced with Pop-oid irony. Miss Beerman would pass for a Neo-Expressionist were it not for her obvious sincerity and her skill. She studied with Kuniyoshi and Morris Kantor at the Art Students League, with the Abstract Expressionist Adja Yunkers at the New School for Social Research and on a a Fulbright grant at Stanley William Hayter's Atelier 17 in Paris.</p>
        <p>Yet it is her sincerity that often arouses ironic feelings in the viewer, and the reason is partly that the artist plays it at full volume and partly that the horrors of daily life, augmented by the mass media, are draining away the reserves of compassion, just as fluorocarbons are said to be destroying the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Though born of a reaction to cruelty in general and the Holocaust in particular, Miss Beerman's monsters are imaginary, and when they are not humanoids with jaws agape and teeth itemized, they are humanoids with animal attributes. One does not run into "Homo-Amphibian" at the supermarket, but one might encounter him in an extraterrestrial movie.</p>
        <p>In her catalogue essay, Alison Weld, assistant curator in the museum's bureau of fine art, quotes Miss Beerman saying that when images of men became more than she could bear, she turned to the animal world. This she has done straightforwardly in the over-life-size "salon" portraits of a turkey and a langur monkey.</p>
        <p>But elsewhere, the animals merely heighten the impression of disgust with the world, as in "Fly-Man," an etching-aquatint of a three-legged creature with wings and a human face, and in the painting "Money Eaters," where porcine humans chomp on real dollar bills.</p>
        <p>Chronologically, the show begins with conventional woodcuts and collages made from fragments of paintings. These are Cubist in derivation and often quite beautiful, although the outstanding early work is "Bird in Flight," an etching-intaglio of a Klee-like image in pink and grays.</p>
        <p>The first painting of substance is the life-size nude looming gold and brown in chiaroscuro of reddish brown (1962). Ms. Weld reports that this is an autobiographical work done when the artist was pregnant with her son.</p>
        <p>It is followed by a huge man's head occupying the lower half of a canvas like a landscape, and it, too, is devoid of ulterior motives, or what might be regarded as Miss Beerman's philosophy of life.</p>
        <p>This appears toward the end of the 1960's, most notably in "Death of Marat," a Baconian image where the corpse lies along the bottom as one figure, shrouded, bends over it, and another enters from the side. If Ms. Weld is right in sensing intimations of castration, then this picture is indeed an enigma.</p>
        <p>Between the late 60's and the late 70's, animals appear alone or merged with human forms. With the 1980's, Miss Beerman returns to mankind but with empathy and a touch of self-identification. Note the two "Imaginary Self-Portraits" of van Gogh that emulate the master's style if not his features.</p>
        <p>The color that used to be somber and applied in washes or broad sweeps of impasto is now lighter and brighter and worked, layer upon layer, into crusty masses. There are paintings dealing with the plagues of Egypt, concentration camp ovens and the shoes left behind by the victims.</p>
        <p>Finally, there is the recent "Pink Skull (Self Portrait With Muse)" in which the artist, her face a ravaged mask compared with the amiable visage photographed in the catalogue, leans across another mask, while the skeleton peeks over her turquoise shoulder.</p>
        <p>This is a powerful but not exactly agreeable show. It is clear that Miss Beerman has no time for Hannah Arendt's "banality of evil"; it is also clear that some of the demons she wrestles are her own.</p>
        <p>The show, one of a series devoted to New Jersey contemporaries, closes next Sunday. The museum, at 205 West State Street, is open Tuesday through Saturday from 9 A.M. to 4:45 P.M. and Sunday from 2 to 5 P.M.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
