<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; Warmer Globe, Greener Pastures?</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="474560"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ECONOMIC SCENE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DA123DF93BA2575AC0A967958260" item-length="786" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; Warmer Globe, Greener Pastures?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LOOKING forward to a winter beach vacation on balmy Cape Cod? There may not be scheduled flights from La Guardia Airport -- the runways are so often flooded at high tide. But the highways are reliable, now that the Rhode Island dikes have been reinforced and bridges all raised by five feet.</p>
        <p>This vision of the future may seem unthinkable. While it is widely understood that the accumulation of "greenhouse" gases in the atmosphere could dramatically change weather patterns over the next century and raise the level of the oceans, it is also widely assumed that governments can and must check global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LOOKING forward to a winter beach vacation on balmy Cape Cod? There may not be scheduled flights from La Guardia Airport -- the runways are so often flooded at high tide. But the highways are reliable, now that the Rhode Island dikes have been reinforced and bridges all raised by five feet.</p>
        <p>This vision of the future may seem unthinkable. While it is widely understood that the accumulation of "greenhouse" gases in the atmosphere could dramatically change weather patterns over the next century and raise the level of the oceans, it is also widely assumed that governments can and must check global warming.</p>
        <p>But a new report from the National Academy of Sciences dares to challenge this environmentally correct view, examining the prospects for adapting to a warmer, drier climate rather than preventing weather changes. And though the authors draw no conclusions, this provocative study suggests that the warm, new world might not be unpalatable.</p>
        <p>In April a separate National Academy panel on global warming plumped what has been dubbed the "no regrets" greenhouse policy. Until the timing and consequences of warming were better understood, the panel concluded, it made sense to cut greenhouse emissions only where the cutting would be free or relatively cheap.</p>
        <p>The contemplated reductions, totaling one-third of current emissions, were less than most environmental lobbies wanted and more than the Bush Administration was ready to accept -- and thus represented a pleasing political middle. But it left open the question of how much farther to go if, as expected, the climate continues to warm in spite of low-cost remedial action. The answer, economists say, ought to depend in part on how costly it would be to adapt to climate change.</p>
        <p>The new National Academy report, from another panel headed by Paul Waggoner at the Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station, focuses on the adaptation option. While its conclusions are couched in the language of science, the overall impression is sunny: Most societies would probably be able to cope with the 2 to 9 degree Fahrenheit warming now expected by the mid-21st century.</p>
        <p>Human health, the panelists concluded, would not be significantly affected. People adapt well to warmer climates -- indeed, migration southward since the invention of air-conditioning suggests that many prefer their world without winter.</p>
        <p>Nor is there reason to believe that economic productivity would change much. Manufacturing and most services are relatively insensitive to weather: it is as easy to build tractors in Florida as in Minnesota. Moreover, the life of most capital equipment and structures is short relative to the time frame of global warming, making it relatively cheap for business to change technology or location to accommodate the weather.</p>
        <p>Farming and fishing would be more dramatically affected by a warmer and drier climate. But together, these industries contribute a scant 3 percent to America's G.N.P. And in any case, agriculture is far more adaptable than is generally understood; conceivably, higher crop yields from a carbon-rich atmosphere would fully offset the added costs of irrigation and genetic adaptation.</p>
        <p>The big-ticket adjustments, the panelists believe, would be protection of coastal areas from flooding and building the capacity to move and store more fresh water. But according to an independent study by the panel's economist, William Nordhaus of Yale, these costs would be spread over decades and need not amount to more than a quarter of 1 percent of G.N.P.</p>
        <p>If you sense something is missing here, you are not alone. The perspective of the study is that of economists and engineers: Nature is an economic tool and a playground for humans. Therefore, rapid, irrevocable changes in the global ecology are a liability only to the degree that they reduce productivity or upset the users of the playground.</p>
        <p>This position has its appeal if one believes that the value of, say, wilderness or species diversity exists only in the eyes and minds of the beholders. But there is no simple way for the beholders to put a price tag on such intangibles. And many environmentalists are not even prepared to try, as long as the option of preservation is available.</p>
        <p>The implicit optimism of the National Academy's adaptation panel suggests that policy makers are going to have a tough time ducking this core issue of environmental values. If the costs of adaptation are indeed modest, it would probably pay to roll with the greenhouse punch. Unless, of course, the intangible losses from rapid ecological change are given great weight -- and societies are ready to spend tens or even hundreds of billions of dollars to avoid them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
