<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends; In Search of a Trade Pact With the Environment in Mind</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week In Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="437400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREE PORTS AND TRADING ZONES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SURO, ROBERTO</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Free Ports and Trading Zones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DB1F3CF937A25757C0A967958260" item-length="1135" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends; In Search of a Trade Pact With the Environment in Mind</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTO SURO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SURO, ROBERTO</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FROM Austin to Ottawa, President Carlos Salinas de Gortari of Mexico barnstormed the continent last week, promoting a free trade agreement as a way to change the world. Addressing the Texas Legislature on Friday he said, "Seldom do these opportunities arise in the course of our history."</p>
        <p>It was unusual billing for a subject normally considered more arcane than miraculous, but the agreement now under discussion among the United States, Canada and Mexico portends an unusual type of bonding among nations. Not merely a case of bureaucratic changes in tariffs and customs rules, the North American Free Trade Zone, if it ever comes to pass, promises to be an argumentative mixed marriage in which the partners expend a lot of effort adapting to each other.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FROM Austin to Ottawa, President Carlos Salinas de Gortari of Mexico barnstormed the continent last week, promoting a free trade agreement as a way to change the world. Addressing the Texas Legislature on Friday he said, "Seldom do these opportunities arise in the course of our history."</p>
        <p>It was unusual billing for a subject normally considered more arcane than miraculous, but the agreement now under discussion among the United States, Canada and Mexico portends an unusual type of bonding among nations. Not merely a case of bureaucratic changes in tariffs and customs rules, the North American Free Trade Zone, if it ever comes to pass, promises to be an argumentative mixed marriage in which the partners expend a lot of effort adapting to each other.</p>
        <p>Nowhere is this more apparent than when talk of trade turns into worry over the environment, and that will be the first point on which the United States and Mexico in particular will have to decide how much alike they want to become.</p>
        <p>In his travels last week President Salinas frequently contended that he is leading his countrymen out of a past that has left a toxic legacy and that he is now committed to enforcing anti-pollution standards as rigorous as those anywhere in the world. Major environmental groups on both sides of the border are determined to hold the Mexican Government to these promises by having them written into any free trade agreement.</p>
        <p>In the coming weeks Congress is due to consider the Bush Administration's request for extended authority to negotiate trade agreements on the "fast track," which means Congress can only vote a treaty up or down. Leading Democrats have already asked the President to explain how he will deal with environmental questions in the talks, and his formal response is expected soon.</p>
        <p>On Capitol Hill the environmental issue has become a lightning rod for legislators who have many reasons to be obstreperous on free trade. Some are inspired by the unions' fear of losing jobs to Mexico's cheap labor market. Others worry that American factories will face unfair competition from plants in Mexico that are not subject to strict environmental regulations. A few simply see a chance to challenge the President on a foreign policy issue.</p>
        <p>The issues seem at once clearer and larger when seen apart from Washington politicking.</p>
        <p>"The environmental movement has come to realize that you cannot separate economic decision-making from environmental decision-making," said Stewart Hudson, acting director of the International Program Division of the National Wildlife Federation. "As a matter of long-term strategy," he added, "we believe that macro-economic policies are the place where we can begin to install new styles of development that meet human needs without sacrificing the environment."</p>
        <p>So far, the environmentalists have scored mixed results in applying this strategy to complex, multinational issues like ozone depletion, global warming and the lending practices of institutions like the World Bank. Both the pollution problems and the solutions that arise in the Mexico talks are simple by comparison.  Taking a Stand</p>
        <p>Moreover, the environmental groups now have an issue that allows them to focus their influence on Washington, because the United States can insist that future development in Mexico under a free-trade regime will have to meet certain environmental standards.</p>
        <p>For example, a trade agreement could include a requirement that both countries adopt standardized toxic waste disposal rules, which would prevent Mexican companies from simply dumping wastes imported from the United States.</p>
        <p>"We have to take a stand here and set a correct model," Mr. Hudson said.</p>
        <p>The stakes for Mexico are far greater. Even though Mexico is the United States' third-largest trading partner after Canada and Japan, it accounts for less than 7 percent of the nation's foreign trade. Mexico, however, does more than two-thirds of all its trade with the United States. While a free trade agreement would have only a small impact on the American economy, at least in the short term, it will immediately redefine the Mexican economy.</p>
        <p>The idea of a free trade agreement only became plausible after President Salinas began an economic program that has shrunk the state sector, opened markets to foreign goods and permitted greater foreign investment. After a series of economic disasters in the 1980's Mexico has started to show a turnaround.</p>
        <p>Much of the Salinas program was a response to popular discontent that in the 1988 elections threatened his Institutional Revolutionary Party for the first time since it came to power more than 60 years ago.</p>
        <p>That same frustration has focused on the environment, and President Salinas has responded on this score too. He has instituted new rules that are as tough on paper as any in the United States, and he has begun the long, slow process of enforcing them.  Last month he showed a willingness to absorb substantial economic costs when he shut down the giant March 18 Refinery in Mexico City because it was contributing mightily to the capital's air contamination.</p>
        <p>"Mexico is in a process of rapid change and the free trade agreement can be a major element in that process and the environment is one of the areas where the change will be most evident," said Roberto Sanchez, an environment specialist at the Colegio de la Frontera Norte, a research institute in Tijuana. "But the change will only occur if the American environmentalists give up some of their romantic notions and let us find our own way.</p>
        <p>"They want to save the planet, but it is not the same planet on their side of the border as it is on ours. They can afford to defend the environment for its own sake. Our people need to use the environment to survive."</p>
        <p>Already some on the American side are backing off their early demands. For example, Dick Kamp, director of the Border Ecology Project, a policy and research group in Naco, Ariz., said he originally imagined that it would take the Mexicans a decade to harmonize their environmental standards with those of the United States.</p>
        <p>"I can see now that it will take more like 15 or 20 years and a considerable investment of money," he said.</p>
        <p>Other challenges come from groups like the Border Trade Alliance, whose members include businesses in both countries. It favors keeping any action on the environment a matter of separate bilateral talks that are not drawn into the free trade agreement.</p>
        <p>Whatever the technicalities and whatever the results, the focus on trade and the environment is already obliging Mexico and the United States to look at each other more closely and to understand better what each wants. As President Salinas said to the Texas Legislature, "We are, in effect, building a new relationship."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
