<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Panel Says Nation Has Ability to Adapt to Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="471794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DC1F3AF934A3575AC0A967958260" item-length="622" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Panel Says Nation Has Ability to Adapt to Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If global warming caused by human activity makes the world significantly hotter, the United States should still be able to adapt at a reasonable cost, a panel of the National Academy of Sciences said today.</p>
        <p>The committee said the effects of warming weather on nature would be hard to control, but it was optimistic about the ability of American industry and farming to adapt to the climate change, known as the greenhouse effect because of the way pollutants trap heat in the atmosphere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If global warming caused by human activity makes the world significantly hotter, the United States should still be able to adapt at a reasonable cost, a panel of the National Academy of Sciences said today.</p>
        <p>The committee said the effects of warming weather on nature would be hard to control, but it was optimistic about the ability of American industry and farming to adapt to the climate change, known as the greenhouse effect because of the way pollutants trap heat in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>"Human adaptability is shown by people working in both Riyadh and Barrow," the panel's report said. "Recent American migration has, on average, been toward warmth." Dissent From a Member</p>
        <p>One of the 14 panel members dissented, saying in a footnote that the committee's "complacent tone is unwarranted." The member, Jane Lubchenco, a professor of zoology at Oregon State University, said that indirect costs, especially the environmental effects of some of the adaptation measures, had not been adequately considered.</p>
        <p>"The implicit message of the report is that humans can adapt to the predicted climate changes without worrying about these other costs," she wrote.</p>
        <p>The panel recommended diversifying water supplies, improving insulation in buildings and encouraging conservation of as many animal species as possible as "a natural protection against surprises and shocks, climatic and otherwise."</p>
        <p>Since climate change might force some endangered species to migrate, the report said, "conservation efforts need to give more attention to corridors for movement, to assisting species to surmount barriers, and to maintaining species when their natural environments are threatened."</p>
        <p>The adaptation panel is one of four committees working on a National Academy of Sciences study of the policy implications of global warming.</p>
        <p>Another panel published a report in April saying the United States should take modest steps to limit production of greenhouse gases, despite uncertainty about the threat of global warming.</p>
        <p>Both sides in the debate, those who urge immediate action and those who say such measures are too costly considering the uncertainty, praised that report.</p>
        <p>Greenhouse gases, like carbon dioxide, methane and chlorofluorocarbons, trap heat around the earth. The academy's April report said that growing amounts of industrial emissions were likely to increase temperatures by 2 to 9 degrees Fahrenheit by the middle of the next century.</p>
        <p>The adaptation panel, headed by Paul E. Waggoner of the Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station in New Haven, found no cause for alarm. "The historical evidence suggests that American farmers can keep up with the gradual climate change of the magnitude the panel assumes," the report said. "The capacity of humans to adapt is evident in the rapid technological, economic and political changes of the past 90 years," the panel said. "The average renewal period for machinery and equipment and the average age of buildings are one to three decades." Strain on Developing Countries</p>
        <p>The report said it might be harder for developing countries to adapt to global warming. It encouraged "efforts to advance regional mobility of people, capital and goods," better preparations for disaster and famine relief and expansion of free-market economies, so that changing prices can serve as market signals that would encourage people to adapt to global warming.</p>
        <p>The committee concluded that even low-lying cities would be able to survive global warming, but said there seemed to be little that humanity could do to help the marine environment adapt to climate change.</p>
        <p>"None of the projected effects of the warming would make large areas uninhabitable," the committee wrote.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
