<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Study Challenges 'Biodegradable' Claims</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="428029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLASTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTAINERS AND PACKAGING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CORNELL UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ICI AMERICAS INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KRUPP, LARRY R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JEWELL, WILLIAM J (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910305T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDA1531F936A35750C0A967958260" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Study Challenges 'Biodegradable' Claims</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A NEW study appears to support what environmentalists have contended for some time: that so-called biodegradable plastic products, from disposable diapers to garbage bags, do not disintegrate into their natural elements as their manufacturers say.</p>
        <p>"People have jumped to the conclusion that biodegradable plastics are good, but the truth is, they don't biodegrade," said Dr. William J. Jewell, an author of the study and a professor of agricultural and biological engineering at Cornell University.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A NEW study appears to support what environmentalists have contended for some time: that so-called biodegradable plastic products, from disposable diapers to garbage bags, do not disintegrate into their natural elements as their manufacturers say.</p>
        <p>"People have jumped to the conclusion that biodegradable plastics are good, but the truth is, they don't biodegrade," said Dr. William J. Jewell, an author of the study and a professor of agricultural and biological engineering at Cornell University.</p>
        <p>The study, which has not yet been published, tested a dozen plastics found in household products that were labeled "biodegradable." It is the first study to contradict the assertions of manufacturers, who began adding ingredients like starch and sugar to plastic several years ago, saying the products would disintegrate in landfills. Reaction to Findings</p>
        <p>Some researchers who did not take part in the study said the findings were impressive because the study tested plastics in intensive bacterial environments under aerobic and anaerobic conditions. But other outside researchers said that while the study tested biological conditions, including variations in heat and moisture, it did not simulate a typical landfill environment, where plastics break down at much slower rates.</p>
        <p>In the study, the plastics were placed in containers called bioreactors, full of bacteria that decompose materials by feeding off them within a matter of days. For example, a paper bag, which can take decades to biodegrade into carbon dioxide and water in a landfill, was reduced to its natural elements within a day.</p>
        <p>"We had a constant, very high-level chomping going on by the bacteria," said Dr. Jewell, who conducted the study with Larry R. Krupp, a graduate student who began the research for his master's thesis. "It was like the acid vat in the movie 'Batman.' The bacteria would attack paper cups and sheets like hungry tigers."</p>
        <p>The study concluded that most plastic products now sold, including sandwich bags, plastic egg cartons, disposable food containers, magazine mailers and six-pack beverage rings, did not break down into their natural elements, though they may decompose into smaller pieces of plastic.</p>
        <p>Only one of the plastics tested showed any signs of change. The product, composed of natural polymers, is made by ICI Americas Inc. and is not sold commercially. Environmental groups have long complained that products called biodegradable or photodegradable do not live up to the promises on their labels.</p>
        <p>"It's been a marketing ploy whose time has run out," said Nancy Wolf, an official of the Environmental Action Coalition. Photodegradable materials are said to break down through the effect of the sun's ultraviolet rays on chemicals that have been blended with the basic plastic resin, while biodegradable plastics are said to be broken down by microorganisms.</p>
        <p>While some manufacturers had not yet heard of the study, others said the issue of whether such products were truly biodegradable continued to be strenuously debated among scientists and industry officials.</p>
        <p>"We conduct our own testing and have found that these products do break down," said Cindy R. Drucker, manager of environmental policy for Webster Industries , Inc., a maker of Good Sense garbage bags.</p>
        <p>The study comes at a time of growing national concern about solid waste disposal as the popularity of plastic products, particularly for consumer goods, continues to grow. Plastics will account for 10 percent of municipal solid waste by the end of the century, compared with about 3 percent in 1970, Ms. Wolf said. Nearly half of all items packaged in supermarkets are made of plastic.</p>
        <p>Much of the debate has been about whether microorganisms in soil feed not only on cornstarch and sugar additives, but also on the long chains of polymeric plastic.</p>
        <p>The new study found that the amount of mass lost in such products was equal to the amount of cornstarch or sugar that had been added.</p>
        <p>Most of the plastics used in the study were obtained from manufacturers, but others were taken from products available a year ago in supermarkets. They included Hefty garbage bags, Good Sense "photodegradable" garbage bags, and a plastic containing cornstarch made by the Archer-Daniels-Midland Company, a maker of corn products. Hefty garbage bags, which are made by the Mobil Oil Company, are no longer labeled as biodegradable.</p>
        <p>The plastics also underwent a "biochemical oxygen demand" test, which is commonly used to test the oxygen demand that waste will have in a river or stream.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
