<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Noted With Pleasure</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="441573"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5D8113DF93BA15757C0A967958260" item-length="957" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Noted With Pleasure</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Regaining a Shared Culture</p>
        <p>The idea that art forms are either "high" or "low" is a recent invention in American life, and a lamentable one. This is from "Highbrow/Lowbrow: The Emergence of Cultural Hierarchy in America" by Lawrence W. Levine. (Harvard University, paper).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Regaining a Shared Culture</p>
        <p>The idea that art forms are either "high" or "low" is a recent invention in American life, and a lamentable one. This is from "Highbrow/Lowbrow: The Emergence of Cultural Hierarchy in America" by Lawrence W. Levine. (Harvard University, paper).</p>
        <p>When the art forms that had constituted a shared culture for much of the 19th century became less accessible to large segments of the American people, millions of them satisfied their aesthetic cravings through a number of the new forms of expressive culture that were barred from high culture by the very fact of their accessibility to the masses: the blues, jazz or jazz-derived music, musical comedy, photography, comic strips, movies, radio, popular comedians, all of which . . . contained much that was fresh, exciting, innovative, intellectually challenging, and highly imaginative. If there is a tragedy in this development, it is not only that millions of Americans were now separated from exposure to such creators as Shakespeare, Beethoven, and Verdi . . . but also that the rigid cultural categories, once they were in place, made it so difficult for so long for so many to understand the value and importance of the popular art forms that were all around them. Celebrating Work as Work</p>
        <p>Laurence Shames reminds us that the warlike or athletic metaphors used to describe work in America misrepresent -- and devalue -- the realities of earning a living. This is from "The Hunger for More: Searching for Values in an Age of Greed" (Vintage, paper).</p>
        <p>Take away the battlefield imagery, the gridiron metaphors, the barroom slang, and what did you have? A job. A place to go between breakfast time and winter dusk, and, presumably, a way to pay the bills. . . . This wasn't called epic combat or an Olympiad, it was called making a living, and while it had its satisfactions -- even, sometimes, its excitements -- the Super Bowl it was not. . . . Wasn't</p>
        <p>work itself</p>
        <p>sufficiently noble, without making it sound like a guerrilla war or a boxing match? Couldn't the labors that men and women responsibly performed to earn their keep be looked at and respected simply for what they were? What had become of the value of the task itself -- the task construed not as metaphorical sport or metaphorical anything, but simply as the honest and concentrated application of thought, skill, and muscle? The Edge of Freedom</p>
        <p>We'd be more creative, Robert Grudin argues, if we stopped trying to conjure or compel the act and simply let it happen. This is from "The Grace of Great Things: Creativity and Innovation" (Ticknor &amp; Fields, paper).</p>
        <p>We no more "have" ideas than ideas "have" us, and indeed the creative process might be simplified if we stopped searching for ideas and simply made room for them to visit. If anything controls or dominates at the moment of inspiration, it is not the mind but the idea, or rather, the suddenly articulated power of our own inner energies. New ideas capture and possess the mind that births them; they colonize it and renew its laws. . . . For this reason, if for no other, creativity is a classic example of human freedom. We commonly think of freedom as the ability to define alternatives and choose between them. The creative mind exceeds this liberty in being able to redefine itself and reality at large, generating whole new sets of alternatives. Intellectual history is punctuated by such redefinitions, by creative acts that open new reaches of expression and inquiry. In this sense we can call creative vision the edge of freedom, the evolutionary faculty by which, down through history, we have redefined our world and ourselves. Outside Nature, Looking In</p>
        <p>The view from his study at Leiden in the Netherlands stirred Peter Westbroek to reflect on the manner in which nature is being absorbed by our increasingly artificial world. This is from "Life as a Geological Force: Dynamics of the Earth" (Norton).</p>
        <p>Through the windows I can see the street, some gardens, and the houses of my neighbors. My environment is artificial as far as the senses can perceive. The trees on the street have been planted, as have all the woods in this country. Even the air that I breathe has been interfered with by humans. How far must I travel to find pure, unbridled nature, free of human influence? If you take into account our impact on climate, the oceans, and the atmosphere, nothing is unaffected. Even deep in the crust we tap reservoirs of water, fossil fuels, and raw materials on a huge scale. In space, you would have to travel far away to escape the cacophony of radiowaves emitted by civilization. The environmental impact of humanity is ubiquitous. We are immersed in culture, and there is no escape. The Cryptic Professor</p>
        <p>Being a student of Samuel Beckett (he was a lecturer, briefly, at Trinity College in Dublin in the 1930's) was like being trapped in a Beckett story. This is from "Samuel Beckett: A Biography" by Deirdre Bair (Summit, paper).</p>
        <p>He was always present in the classroom before the students, staring out the window, with his back turned. When they had stopped bustling and were silent, he usually continued to stare out the window for a very long time. Finally, he would turn to face them and deliver a sentence perfectly crafted but puzzling. He spoke without notes and never seemed to have anything but the work to be discussed in front of him. Most of his students found they were able to take verbatim notes of his lectures, because when he was finished with the delivery of one sentence, he would turn again to the window, wait another long time, almost as if he had forgotten they were there, and then suddenly turn and speak again.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
