<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Materials to Keep the Refrigerator Cool</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="443909"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFRIGERATORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AEROGELS (INSULATION MATERIAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INSULATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREEZERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLYURETHANE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLUSHA, JOHN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electricity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Polymers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDB1E3BF93BA35756C0A967958260" item-length="978" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Materials to Keep the Refrigerator Cool</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN HOLUSHA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLUSHA, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Researchers are experimenting with a new class of ultralight materials called aerogels that could one day replace polyurethane foams. These foams provide insulation and help hold up refrigerators and freezers, but are considered harmful to the environment.</p>
        <p>Today's refrigerators consist of a metal outside cabinet and a plastic interior. In between is the polyurethane foam, which does more than help keep the contents cool.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Researchers are experimenting with a new class of ultralight materials called aerogels that could one day replace polyurethane foams. These foams provide insulation and help hold up refrigerators and freezers, but are considered harmful to the environment.</p>
        <p>Today's refrigerators consist of a metal outside cabinet and a plastic interior. In between is the polyurethane foam, which does more than help keep the contents cool.</p>
        <p>"The thin steel outer shell provides nothing but some protection against mechanical damage and an esthetically appealing surface to hang the paint on," said Carlo Schwinn, the manager of process engineering at White Consolidated Industries, at a recent conference in New York. "All of the beef is in the foam sandwich between the inner and outer shell."</p>
        <p>But that "beef" includes chlorofluorocarbon gases that have been linked to the decay of the protective ozone layer in the atmosphere. The foams are poured as liquids into a refrigerator cabinet and then gases are used to make the liquid bubble up and fill all the voids with foam. Over the years an appliance is used, the gases tend to leak into the atmosphere. For that reason, most of the world has agreed to stop the production of chlorofluorocarbons by the year 2000.</p>
        <p>In the interim, the refrigeration industry will most likely use a less damaging version of the chemicals, known as hydroclorofluorocarbons, as refrigerants and as foaming agents. But some of the most likely candidates have drawbacks. Some are flammable and others are aggressive solvents that might attack the plastic inner cabinet. They also have a degrading effect on the ozone, although much less than chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, and will almost certainly be phased out as well.  A Better Insulator</p>
        <p>That may be where aerogels come in. They have no ozone-depleting potential, are nonflammable and have twice the insulating value of CFC-based foams. And they are rigid enough to support a refrigerator cabinet; some aerogels can support 1,600 times their own weight.</p>
        <p>They are also the world's lightest solids, consisting of 90 percent empty space; they are only four times as dense as dry air. Some are nearly transparent and look like "frozen smoke," said Sangeeta D. Ramamurthi, a scientist at Battelle Memorial Institute in Ohio, where the materials are being developed. Research into aerogels is also under way at the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory in California.</p>
        <p>Until now the gels have been scientific curiosities, and were used largely to detect high-energy particles emitted from atomic accelerators. High-energy particles racing through the gel give off a bluish light similar to the blue glow seen in pools of water storing nuclear power plant fuel.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ramamurthi said the gels she is experimenting with are based on ceramic materials. They have insulation properities, as measured in "R" values, of 8 to 15 compared with 7.6 for CFC foams when they are new and 3.6 once the gas has leaked out. R values are a measure of a material's insulating ability, with higher numbers representing reduced heat transmission.</p>
        <p>The transparent silica gel is prepared by mixing a silicon-alcohol compound with methyl alcohol, water and a small amount of ammonia hydroxide. All are clear liquids in the unreacted state. When mixed, they form a thick, viscous mass, not unlike Jell-O. It takes about 2 minutes for the gel to form.</p>
        <p>In the reaction, silicon atoms break the chemical bonds of the compound and form a spidery network of silicon dioxide molecules connected to each other throughout the gel. Inside are millions of tiny pores formed by the silicon dioxide in the water and alcohol mixture.</p>
        <p>The trick is to find a way to drive off the liquid without destroying the fine network of solid material that has been formed. Simply heating the gel would cause it to collapse.</p>
        <p>The answer is to increase the pressure on the gel so the alcohol does not boil in a conventional sense and then increase the heat to drive it off, a process known as supercritical drying.</p>
        <p>The size of parts that can be formed by the gels is limited by the size of the pressure cookers, known as autoclaves, now available. "Right now we can do parts that are 3 inches by 3 inches," Dr. Ramamurthi said. Battelle is installing a pilot plant that can handle pieces 6 by 13 inches.  Some Drawbacks</p>
        <p>Scientists acknowledge that the gels may have some drawbacks compared with polyurethane foams, despite their insulating properties. Since they have to be treated under heat and pressure, they would have to be formed as panels and then sandwiched inside refrigerator and freezer walls. That is more difficult than just pouring liquids.</p>
        <p>The aerogels may have applications beyond appliance insulation. Since the silica gel is transparent, it could be used to replace air in the space between a home's inner and storm windows.</p>
        <p>Other gels not as transparent as silica but which have higher R values may be the better choice where the ability to transmit light is not an advantage. Indeed, researchers at Livermore have produced opaque black gels made almost entirely of carbon atoms. They conduct electricity and may find applications in the electronics industry.</p>
        <p>The porous nature of the materials may be used as well. Dr. Ramamurthi notes that ceramic materials can withstand far higher temperatures than the plastics often used in filtration. "Polymers can only be used to 180 to 200 degrees centigrade," she said. "These materials could go as high as 500 degrees."</p>
        <p>There is also interest in using them in the space program. One possible use would be to capture small meteors that otherwise would be smashed to dust against a more substantial material. And their light weight makes them attractive as a construction material in space, since it would cost less to lift them into orbit.  BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
