<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Technology Is Found to Exist To Cut Global Warming Gases</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="421313"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONGRESSIONAL OFFICE OF TECHNOLOGY ASSESSMENT</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDD153FF93BA35751C0A967958260" item-length="646" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Technology Is Found to Exist To Cut Global Warming Gases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Current technologies can sharply reduce gases that scientists say would contribute to global warming, but not without significant expense and dramatic changes in how Americans use energy, a Congressional study reported today.</p>
        <p>The report estimated that substantially cutting emissions of one of the gases, carbon dioxide, could eventually cost the economy as much as $150 billion a year, about what Americans now pay for compliance with all existing environmental laws.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Current technologies can sharply reduce gases that scientists say would contribute to global warming, but not without significant expense and dramatic changes in how Americans use energy, a Congressional study reported today.</p>
        <p>The report estimated that substantially cutting emissions of one of the gases, carbon dioxide, could eventually cost the economy as much as $150 billion a year, about what Americans now pay for compliance with all existing environmental laws.</p>
        <p>The study by the Congressional Office of Technology Assessment comes as delegates from 130 nations are meeting near here to work toward a worldwide treaty on global warming. It also follows pressure from some members of Congress to commit the United States to specific goals to reduce gases that contribute to global warming, something the Bush Administration says should await more study.</p>
        <p>There is division among scientist over the extent, and indeed the existence, of global warming. But many scientists believe that global temperatures will rise because increasing levels of carbon dioxide and other manmade gases will trap and retain heat from the sun in a process similar to what happens in a greenhouse. Such a warming trend could cause sea levels to rise, cause severe droughts and storms and severely disprupt the earth's biological systems.  Number of Gases Involved</p>
        <p>The phenomenon has been attributed to a number of gases, including chlorofluorocarbons and methane. But carbon dioxide, primarily from the burning of fossil fuels, accounts for more than half of the gases identified as creating the greenhouse effect. And scientists believe significant cuts in carbon dioxide emissions will require sharp reductions in the burning of fossil fuels, oil, coal and wood.</p>
        <p>The new study concluded that carbon dioxide reductions of 35 percent are feasible over the next 25 years in the United States with the adoption of stringent energy-saving policies.</p>
        <p>"Such emission reductions will be difficult to achieve and could be costly," said the study, which had been requested by several Congressional committees, but it added that the reductions would require no major technological breakthroughs,</p>
        <p>The report said the cost was difficult to estimate. Energy savings would increase because of conservation and fuel efficiencies, but the cost of appliances, automobiles and houses, would most likely increase.</p>
        <p>The report said predictions on how much it would cost to deal with global warming vary widely, from saving the economy money to costing as much as $150 billion a year to cut carbon dioxide emissions alone by the year 2015.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists have argued that at the very least, industrial nations must reduce carbon dioxide emissions by 20 percent to have any hopes of reversing the trend toward unusual warming of the earth.</p>
        <p>The report said a substantial cut in carbon dioxide emissions would require energy conservation measures to be taken by virtually all sectors of the economy, including construction, manufacturing, transportation and energy industries. Energy Taxes Could Be Needed</p>
        <p>The energy savings most likely would have to be brought about through a mixture of energy taxes, financial incentives and government regulation, the study concluded.</p>
        <p>The Congressional study did not endorse any specific approach or suggest what kinds of energy taxes or incentives might be preferred. But it suggested that tougher energy efficiency standards would have to be developed for commercial buildings as well as for homes, appliances, heating and cooling systems, windows and other elements of construction.</p>
        <p>It cited the need for more energy-efficient transportation systems, including steep increases in automobile fuel economy standards, more incentives toward development of mass transit and perhaps reinstituting the 55-mile-an-hour speed limit nationwide.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
