<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recycling Claim by Biosphere 2 Experiment Is Questioned</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="486462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOSPHERE 2 (ORACLE, ARIZ)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">VILLAGE VOICE (NEWSPAPER)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DA1E3AF931A25752C1A967958260" item-length="612" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recycling Claim by Biosphere 2 Experiment Is Questioned</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CRITICS have long contended that the Biosphere 2 project in the Arizona desert has more to do with showmanship or cultism than science, despite its repeated assertions to the contrary. Now, a newspaper says the $150 million effort is not the environmental experiment it claims to be.</p>
        <p>The project began with much fanfare in September when four men and four women, accompanied by 3,000 species of plants and animals, sealed themselves inside a eight-story, glass structure for a two-year experiment in biological recycling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CRITICS have long contended that the Biosphere 2 project in the Arizona desert has more to do with showmanship or cultism than science, despite its repeated assertions to the contrary. Now, a newspaper says the $150 million effort is not the environmental experiment it claims to be.</p>
        <p>The project began with much fanfare in September when four men and four women, accompanied by 3,000 species of plants and animals, sealed themselves inside a eight-story, glass structure for a two-year experiment in biological recycling.</p>
        <p>The allegations of misrepresentation involve a device that removes carbon dioxide from the air and turns it into a solid for storage inside the biosphere.</p>
        <p>The current issue of The Village Voice says the group secretly installed the device, violating the advertised goal of recycling all materials naturally. Carbon dioxide is exhaled by humans and metabolized by plants. The Voice also said the levels of carbon dioxide in Biosphere 2 were becoming dangerously high, apparently because of the decrease in sunlight and thus a decline in photosynthetic activity by the plants.  Carbon-Dioxide Levels</p>
        <p>Kathleen A. Dyhr, a Biosphere spokeswoman, said in a telephone interview that the group had indeed installed a carbon-dioxide remover. She conceded that it was not "natural" but called it a minor aid to help stabilize the atmosphere during its initial fluctuations. The carbon-dioxide levels were currently fine, she added, though higher than outside the closed environment.</p>
        <p>Ms. Dyhr said the privately financed project had no obligation to disclose all the details of work in progress.</p>
        <p>"If the experiment were formally reported, written up in a publication, and no mention was made of that fact, then that would be fraud," she said. "But I don't know of any research project that would discuss all its methods and techniques" this early in the process. "No experiment would be giving out data to the press."</p>
        <p>From the start, when planning for the Biosphere got under way in the mid-1980's, it was billed as a futuristic experiment in closed recycling where plants and animals would provide each other with all the essentials for life. Most especially, green plants would take human wastes (urine, feces and carbon dioxide) and turn them into oxygen, water and food for human consumption. No mention was made of chemical aids to the process.</p>
        <p>Ms. Dyhr said the carbon-dioxide remover was a last-minute addition, put in after calculations showed the closed environment might go through large swings of its atmospheric chemistry in the first weeks and months after closure. Rather than endanger the whole experiment, she said, the scrubber was added.</p>
        <p>"It was a crutch, for the initial period where large fluctuations were expected," Ms. Dyhr said. She said that the precipitator apparatus could remove up to 4 percent of the carbon dioxide in the air and that it had been turned on a few times.</p>
        <p>The carbon dioxide level of the earth's atmosphere is about 355 parts per million, and levels of 10,000 parts per million or higher can be unhealthy. The levels currently in the Biosphere, Ms. Dyhr said, were about 2,000 parts per million. "That's not considered problematic," she said. "NASA runs the shuttle at 5,000 parts per million."</p>
        <p>Linda Leigh, one of the Biosphere's inhabitants and the botanist in charge of land-based ecosystems for the eight-member crew, said in a telephone interview from inside the glass domes that she and her colleagues were feeling fine and suffering no ill effects from the changing composition of the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>"We've got absolutely no concern about the levels of the CO2," she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
