<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Television; The Grazing of Cattle Vs. Welfare of the Land</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="466591"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIVESTOCK</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC PROPERTY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCUMENTARY FILMS AND PROGRAMS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AUDUBON SOCIETY</org>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEW RANGE WARS, THE (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEW RANGE WARS, THE (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DB1139F931A2575BC0A967958260" item-length="519" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Television; The Grazing of Cattle Vs. Welfare of the Land</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is not hard to understand why cattle ranchers are kicking up dust over "The New Range Wars." The Audubon Society documentary, at 8 tonight on Channel 13, takes aim at the Federal policy of selling grazing rights, at below-market prices, to hundreds of millions of acres of publicly owned land in the Southwest.</p>
        <p>The argument, forcefully advanced by a passel of ecologists and backed up by pictures of devastated areas, is that overgrazing by cattle, which require enormous amounts of forage, has endangered many forms of wildlife, exhausted the soil, polluted waters and possibly harmed the ozone layer. The program jumps around quite a bit as it makes the case that ranchers are being rewarded at taxpayer expense for causing what one scientist calls "an unnatural disaster."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is not hard to understand why cattle ranchers are kicking up dust over "The New Range Wars." The Audubon Society documentary, at 8 tonight on Channel 13, takes aim at the Federal policy of selling grazing rights, at below-market prices, to hundreds of millions of acres of publicly owned land in the Southwest.</p>
        <p>The argument, forcefully advanced by a passel of ecologists and backed up by pictures of devastated areas, is that overgrazing by cattle, which require enormous amounts of forage, has endangered many forms of wildlife, exhausted the soil, polluted waters and possibly harmed the ozone layer. The program jumps around quite a bit as it makes the case that ranchers are being rewarded at taxpayer expense for causing what one scientist calls "an unnatural disaster."</p>
        <p>The ranchers corralled by the program's pleasant narrator and interviewer, Peter Coyote, all seem to be hard-working, enlightened men who lament the depredations of the past, speak of their stewardship of the land and tell how they are trying to operate in more responsible ways, but the pictures weigh heavily against the industry as a whole. How can a grown man, even on a horse, argue with an ecologically enlightened little girl, busy cleaning up a New Mexico river, who tells the camera, "We're out here to help fish"? Pictures of land that has flourished since being barred to cattle are set against those of land turned into desert by years of overgrazing.</p>
        <p>If there are any good reasons, outside of profits for a few thousand businessmen, why ranchers should be subsidized for bringing so much of the Southwest to so sorry a condition -- which is how the dispute is framed -- they are not presented here. Instead, it is pointed out that red meat is not considered a particularly healthy food these days. Assertions of the cattle industry and the Bureau of Land Management that public lands are in relatively good shape and getting better are stampeded.</p>
        <p>Most of the critics are less strident than the biologist Paul Ehrlich, a favorite of public television, who calls the grazing rights "an enormous welfare program for rich ranchers." He is among those who would eliminate all grazing on public lands; other environmentalists would settle for restrictions, and still others are working with ranchers to change their grazing methods. One scientist calls cowboys "a dying breed," but it is not a species the experts here are much interested in protecting. The consensus is in favor of a return to an era before the importation of livestock, which, says Mr. Coyote, can be fed in more efficient ways.</p>
        <p>As to the protests from rancher groups, like past protests from loggers, farmers and others, they run up against television's treatment of environmentalism in any form as a sacred cow. A touch of skepticism would be refreshing now and then, and this hour would have provided more to chew on if it had confronted the opposition arguments. With that caveat, "The New Range Wars" is an effective venture into advocacy that draws critical attention to a Federal policy whose consequences evidently demand it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
