<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="472699"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DB143DF933A2575AC0A967958260" item-length="1156" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-10</p>
        <p>The U.S. naval base in the Philippines may soon lose its lease unless political opinion changes in the next few weeks. Opponents of the base, the largest U.S. military installation in Southeast Asia, won a victory in the Philippine Senate. Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-10</p>
        <p>The U.S. naval base in the Philippines may soon lose its lease unless political opinion changes in the next few weeks. Opponents of the base, the largest U.S. military installation in Southeast Asia, won a victory in the Philippine Senate. Page A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: The Soviet Union is emerging from the three-week storm raised by the coup to face some questions: Who is leading the country? And where? A1</p>
        <p>St. Petersburg fought the Soviet coup in the first hours, with its factory workers and police chief taking leading roles. The city, long called Leningrad, is an example of the extent of reform in the country and how that worked against the coup. A12</p>
        <p>A human rights meeting in Moscow would once have been thought of as another forum for East-West hostility. Instead, the international conference there this week is expected to bring new consensus.  A13</p>
        <p>Soviet military leaders at Harvard are taking a crash course on living with democracy. The classes were planned before the coup, but have taken on new meaning as a more professional military, free from the Communist Party, takes shape. A13 Yugoslavia's fracturing worsened, as election results from the southern republic of Macedonia showed that an overwhelming majority had voted to follow the secessionist republics of Croatia and Slovenia in seeking independence. A1</p>
        <p>Greek court sentences 7 newspaper editors A11</p>
        <p>The odd designs in England's fields, an ever-popular mystery there in recent years, have been partly explained: two local men who trampled out patterns with wooden boards under cover of night have stepped forward. A6</p>
        <p>The home of China's "gulags," Qinghai Province, is a remote area that was once part of Tibet. Little is known about the prisons for political foes and common criminals called "laogai," meaning "reform through labor." A3</p>
        <p>Peace drive survives South Africa strife A3</p>
        <p>Baker sees Mexico as a Soviet model A11</p>
        <p>Palestinian parley stresses role in peace talks A5</p>
        <p>Givat Brenner Journal: Socialism under challenge at kibbutz A4  National A14-17, D19</p>
        <p>Clarence Thomas's nomination to the Supreme Court is largely met with indecision by the American public, a New York Times/CBS News poll shows. Overall, the one-third of the respondents who had an opinion gave very different rationales depending on their race. A1</p>
        <p>The Senate hearing on Judge Thomas begins today before the Judiciary Committee. The hearing is expected to be a hybrid of the rancorous 1987 sessions of Judge Robert H. Bork and last year's calmer questioning of Judge David H. Souter. A17</p>
        <p>Democrats try to carve Gingrich out A14</p>
        <p>Two economic paths in the South are emerging as communities cope -- and fail to cope -- with the loss of manufacturing jobs. In South Carolina, Great Falls and Spartanburg have had widely different success in attracting new businesses. A1</p>
        <p>Chicken processors are under attack over their basic fire safety practices after last Tuesday's fatal blaze at a North Carolina plant. The industry has been questioned about worker injury rates, and critics say infrequent inspections have allowed conditions to worsen. A14</p>
        <p>A plan to limit abuse by the police uses a list of the 25 officers in Kansas City, Mo., who have many citizen complaints and keeps a closer watch on them. The plan is a sign of the recent increased attention given to police brutality.  A1</p>
        <p>Obscene phone caller sentenced to six years A14  Regional B1-4</p>
        <p>Heard a good subway tune lately? Transit officials are considering softening the rumble and screeches heard in New York City's subway stations with piped-in music. It is unclear what music would be selected, but tests have already begun. A1</p>
        <p>Transit leaders to propose cuts approaching $1 billion B3</p>
        <p>Hoboken-Newark rail link opens as part of expansion B2</p>
        <p>Commuters from Staten Island took their ferry to work but faced delays of up to an hour. The day after a devastating fire at the ferry's Manhattan terminal, city officials gave gloomy assessments of the time it would take to repair the damage. B1</p>
        <p>A school snubbed by whites has become a political symbol in New Jersey. Dwight Morrow High School in racially mixed Englewood has a student body that is 90 percent black and Hispanic. Critics contend that a regional school system will correct the imbalance.  B1</p>
        <p>Mayor Dinkins's trip to South Africa, which he will make with several dozen city officials and black busi-ness people, is still planned for Monday though the Mayor has not raised enough money to pay for it. B1</p>
        <p>Dinkins calls Crown Heights killing of a Jew a "lynching" B3</p>
        <p>The campaign in Greenwich Village is likely to produce the first openly homosexual member of New York's City Council. But with no major policy issues to divide the two leading candidates, they are vying for votes in the most personal -- even intimate -- ways. B1</p>
        <p>New group to support insurgents is divided as vote nears B2  Business Digest D1  Science Times</p>
        <p>New thought on how the brain handles language C1</p>
        <p>More psychiatrists find religion helps C1</p>
        <p>Can the world unite against global warming?  C1</p>
        <p>Camera technique may improve lung surgery C3</p>
        <p>Scientists await new data on ozone depletion C4</p>
        <p>Survey faults plan to identify HIV-infected health workers C5</p>
        <p>Women's status and pay still lag in medicine C7</p>
        <p>Science Q&amp;A C2</p>
        <p>Science Watch C5  Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>"Baby-Sitters Club" goes to HBOC11</p>
        <p>Biograph Theater is closing C12</p>
        <p>Theater: "Another Person" C11</p>
        <p>Music: "Cosi Fan Tutte" C11</p>
        <p>Word and Image: "All-Bright Court," a novel C14  Fashion Page B6</p>
        <p>Fete at Saks</p>
        <p>Patterns</p>
        <p>By Design  Obituaries B5</p>
        <p>John Crosby, novelist and columnist</p>
        <p>Brad Davis, actor</p>
        <p>Robert Stoller, theorist on sex- identity problems</p>
        <p>Belinda Mason, AIDS activist</p>
        <p>Nell Donnelly Reed, fashion pioneer Sports B7-12</p>
        <p>Mike Tyson was indicted in Indiana on charges of rape and three other criminal counts. In spite of his legal troubles, the former heavyweight champion will apparently fight Evander Holyfield in a title bout as scheduled. B7</p>
        <p>Baseball: Gooden expects to return in top form B7</p>
        <p>Pirates defeat Cubs B8</p>
        <p>Yanks lose to Orioles B9</p>
        <p>Expos beat Mets B9</p>
        <p>Columns: Anderson on Tyson B7</p>
        <p>Football: How Giants got outsmarted B7</p>
        <p>Coslet accepts part of blame for loss B11</p>
        <p>Hockey: Devils get Barr and McKay B11</p>
        <p>Sports People B10</p>
        <p>Tennis: Power overtakes passion in Open B12  Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials A18</p>
        <p>Food for the Soviet people</p>
        <p>Robbing voters of their rights</p>
        <p>Bush and poverty law panel</p>
        <p>Brent Staples: Judge Thomas</p>
        <p>Letters A18</p>
        <p>A.M. Rosenthal: Absolution for killers A19</p>
        <p>Russel Baker: Capra beats the game A19</p>
        <p>Ivo H. Daalder: Abolish tactical warheads A19</p>
        <p>Regina Schrambling: The curse of culinary convenience A19</p>
        <p>Sally F. Zerker: Another imperfect union A19</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
