<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oil Output Is Raised By OPEC</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="476414"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRODUCTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SAUDI ARABIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ORGANIZATION OF PETROLEUM EXPORTING COUNTRIES (OPEC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">IBRAHIM, YOUSSEF M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DC143FF935A1575AC0A967958260" item-length="1092" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oil Output Is Raised By OPEC</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By YOUSSEF M. IBRAHIM,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">IBRAHIM, YOUSSEF M</byline>
      <dateline>GENEVA, Sept. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries agreed today to a Saudi proposal to increase the group's total production ceiling by more than a million barrels a day, which would keep oil prices at their present moderate range, averaging about $19 a barrel worldwide.</p>
        <p>The accord, calling for a new output of 23.6 million barrels a day, was opposed by several OPEC countries. The stated Saudi aim is to permit the halting recovery of the world economy to continue without any shocks from higher energy prices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries agreed today to a Saudi proposal to increase the group's total production ceiling by more than a million barrels a day, which would keep oil prices at their present moderate range, averaging about $19 a barrel worldwide.</p>
        <p>The accord, calling for a new output of 23.6 million barrels a day, was opposed by several OPEC countries. The stated Saudi aim is to permit the halting recovery of the world economy to continue without any shocks from higher energy prices.</p>
        <p>But the tenacious view of the Saudis was also heavily influenced by Riyadh's decision to retain the commanding share of OPEC production that Saudi Arabia has held since the Persian Gulf crisis, when it raised its output to 8.5 million barrels a day from 5.5 million barrels.  'Got What They Wanted'</p>
        <p>"The Saudis got what they wanted, and the others walked away empty handed," said Bahman Karbassioun, an Iranian oil economist and former OPEC official.</p>
        <p>The OPEC action came as oil consumers moved to discourage fuel use. The European Community proposed to its 12 member nations a clean-energy tax of $10 a barrel on oil by the end of the century to try to curb worldwide emissions of carbon dioxide.  [ Page D3. ]</p>
        <p>Saudi officials have repeatedly said they will not abandon their newly acquired share of world oil markets. Saudi Arabia had argued against the objections of several other OPEC members that producers should continue to pump all the oil they could to protect world markets against shortages in view of the tumbling production of the Soviet Union. It has fallen by more than two million barrels a day over the last three years and continues to deteriorate.</p>
        <p>The Saudi view overwhelmed objections by Algeria, Iran, Libya and Indonesia, which favored a restrained production and higher oil prices. Several OPEC officials conceded they could not stand in the face of the Saudi determination.  'Lot of People Unhappy'</p>
        <p>"It was the maximum we could reach," said Indonesia's oil minister, Ginandjar Kartasasmita. "I am not 100 percent satisfied with it."</p>
        <p>A senior Arab OPEC delegate who asked not to be identified said, "I think they have made a lot of people unhappy, but they have the ability to produce more oil than any of us, and if you can produce, you can dictate the terms."</p>
        <p>The Saudis have emerged from the gulf crisis as the undisputed masters of OPEC, particularly since the elimination of Iraq as an effective member of the organization since it was placed under a United Nations economic embargo in August 1990. The Iraqi oil minister, Osama al-Hiti, left the gathering today before it ended.</p>
        <p>OPEC's last agreement in June had set the ceiling for its members at 22.3 million barrels a day. However the group was in effect producing about 23 million barrels a day, with Saudi Arabia accounting alone for more than a third of that quantity.</p>
        <p>In addition to the Saudis' professed concern for the health of the world economy, OPEC experts here said, their principal goal in addition to regaining dominance of the organization is to wipe out the consequences of the pre-gulf crisis policies of OPEC. Then Iraq, Iran, Algeria and Libya, as well as others, aimed constantly at pushing oil prices up by restraining output, particularly Saudi output.  Forced Cuts in Output</p>
        <p>In July 1990, just before invading Kuwait, Iraq had emerged as the leader of OPEC, forcing Kuwait to cut its production in half, to one million barrels a day, and Saudi Arabia to settle for production of 5.5 million barrels a day, far below its capacity.</p>
        <p>Saudi production capacity could reach nine million barrels a day for limited periods, which is more than any other member of OPEC.</p>
        <p>"I think the Saudis tried to erase the memory of the OPEC meeting of July 1990, which was one in which they lost control and were no longer in charge," said Vahan Zanoyan, senior director of the Petroleum Finance Company of Washington who was observing the meeting and is an OPEC affairs expert.</p>
        <p>Futhermore, Saudi Arabia had said that it would not return to the old and now largely extinct OPEC production quota system adopted in July 1990.</p>
        <p>The Saudi goal, several OPEC officials said, goes beyond today's triumph. It aims, they said, to end an era that began in the 70's, as OPEC attempted unsuccessfully for two decades to set the price of oil by regulating its output and to focus the organization's attention on forging long-term agreements of cooperation with the industrial world.  Iran's Strategy</p>
        <p>The Saudi strategy has not been opposed strongly here by the country's main rival in OPEC -- Iran -- as the Teheran Government has for some time now attempted to normalize its ties with Saudi Arabia in the aftermath of the gulf war. But Iranian officials left little doubt they would continue to pursue their goal of raising oil prices.</p>
        <p>Today's agreement, while supporting the Saudi view that oil prices should remain around the present world average of $19 a barrel, paid lip service to OPEC's so-called minimum reference price of $21 a barrel.</p>
        <p>But Saudi officials said prices could reach that level only through market forces and not through the manipulation of production by OPEC.</p>
        <p>In New York, the market shrugged off the OPEC announcement. The production ceiling is "pretty much what was expected," said Victor Yu, an oil expert at Refco Inc., adding that it "pretty much recognizes reality." On the New York Mercantile Exchange, oil for November delivery closed up 2 cents, at $22.21 a barrel. American prices are generally above the world average, while OPEC's are below it.</p>
        <p>OPEC experts agree the accord will have no impact on oil prices, as oil is plentiful in world markets, and the meeting is widely expected to follow the Saudi blueprint.</p>
        <p>Several OPEC ministers, from Algeria, Iran and elsewhere expressed hope that the organization would eventually return to a fixed production quota system, instead of the present accord, which allows members to produce as much oil as they wish under the umbrella of the new ceiling.</p>
        <p>"It is a little bit difficult to pinpoint a certain time for going back to quotas," said Secretary General Subroto of OPEC, adding that "I cannot say with certainty when it might be revived."</p>
        <p>Mr. Yu said that downward pressure on prices could come from Iraq, which the United Nations has given permission to sell $1.6 billion of oil over six months, and Kuwait, which has resumed exports, at a level of 250,000 to 300,000 barrels a day.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
