<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rule Approved to Extend Nuclear Plants' Licences</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="456176"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LICENSES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NUCLEAR REGULATORY COMMISSION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARR, KENNETH (COMR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DB1E3AF93AA15755C0A967958260" item-length="805" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rule Approved to Extend Nuclear Plants' Licences</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Nuclear Regulatory Commission approved a rule today under which operators of reactors with 40-year operating licenses that are expiring may apply for renewals up to 20 years.</p>
        <p>The commission chairman, Kenneth Carr, said he was determined to approve the rule before his term expires Sunday, so the agency left some details to be worked out by its staff.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Nuclear Regulatory Commission approved a rule today under which operators of reactors with 40-year operating licenses that are expiring may apply for renewals up to 20 years.</p>
        <p>The commission chairman, Kenneth Carr, said he was determined to approve the rule before his term expires Sunday, so the agency left some details to be worked out by its staff.</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for the nuclear industry expressed approval of the commission's action, but opponents of nuclear energy contended that the rule was too vague to insure safety.</p>
        <p>Without such a rule, the country's oldest nuclear plants, which began operation in the 1960's, would have to begin planning to shut down over the next several years.  Critical to Industry</p>
        <p>The new rule is crucial to the industry because all the plants planned since 1974 have been canceled, and only two other plants seem likely to be completed. Some of the older plants are near retirement age; the owners of one, Yankee Rowe, in Rowe, Mass., have already said they planned to apply this year for a 20-year license extension. Yankee Rowe began operation in 1961.</p>
        <p>"License renewal offers America renewable energy that we can count on," said Phillip Bayne, president of the United States Council for Energy Awareness, the industry's public relations arm.</p>
        <p>But a nuclear watchdog group, the Union of Concerned Scientists, complained that the new rule was far too vague in specifying what parts of the plant must be checked to insure that age has not damaged them. Eileen Quinn, a spokeswoman for the group, said the rule had "no requirements that specify what constitutes an effective aging management program."</p>
        <p>Nuclear safety groups say that many plants have parts that have deteriorated with age and that the steel in Yankee Rowe's reactor vessel has become too brittle to insure safe operation. But plant owners say they have replaced worn parts and will step up the inspection and testing of parts vulnerable to age before the reactors exceed the lives for which they were initially licensed. Questions on Current Rules</p>
        <p>A crucial question in the rule issued today was how carefully reactor owners would have to review the adequacy of their equipment and procedures, and compliance with current commission requirements. In preparing the new rule, the commission asserted that existing licensing arrangements assured that the plants were safe, but the four commission members disagreed over how carefully this would have to be re-examined for license extension.</p>
        <p>The problem, said William D. Travers, deputy director of the office in charge of the relicensing rule, is that the current licensing basis is extremely complicated. It includes the original license, all the orders issued by the commission over the plant's lifetime, all the commitments made by license holders to make safety changes and various pieces of equipment and procedures.</p>
        <p>It is, Mr. Trvers said, "a plant-specific beast," differing for each of the 110 reactors in commercial operation.</p>
        <p>Under the rule, utility companies will have to review each part of the license, or state why it is unnecessary to do so. For example, Mr. Travers said, a company might claim there was no need to re-evaluate the emergency evacuation plans just because the plant was older.</p>
        <p>The document approved today does not lay out precisely what must be evaluated, but instructs the commission's staff to draft the final language.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carr, a retired admiral with wide experience in nuclear submarines, said after the session this morning that issuing the rule on renewals was one of the two goals he had for his five-year term.</p>
        <p>"I wanted to do one other thing on my watch I didn't get done, and that was to get somebody to order a plant," said Mr. Carr, who predicted that would happen in his successor's term.</p>
        <p>The new chairman will be Ivan Selin, a former Under Secretary of State for Management, who was confirmed by the Senate on June 21. Mr. Selin, who holds a doctoral degree in electrical engineering from Yale University, is a former chairman of American Management Systems Inc., a computer systems and consulting company.</p>
        <p>While the swearing-in ceremony is next week, Mr. Carr gleefully pulled open his suit jacket, pointed to a small box on his belt and said, "On Sunday night, he's going to have the beeper."</p>
        <p>Whether a new plant is likely in Mr. Selin's term depends in part on the progress of a new licensing procedure now under way. Under the new system, the commission is reviewing reactor designs, with the intention of granting generic certification. The idea is that reactor plans would be pre-approved as meeting Government safety standards the same way as cars, without a separate test on each one. Then the plants could be given permission to operate as long as they were built as designed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
