<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Man of Unspeakable Thoughts</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="439085"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SPENCE, JONATHAN D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LIZHI, FANG</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BRINGING DOWN THE GREAT WALL (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D8123EF932A15757C0A967958260" item-length="2149" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Man of Unspeakable Thoughts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jonathan D. Spence;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SPENCE, JONATHAN D</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BRINGING DOWN THE GREAT WALL</p>
        <p>Writings on Science, Culture, and Democracy in China. By Fang Lizhi. Edited by James H. Williams. Translated by James H. Williams and others. Introduction by Orville Schell. 336 pp. New York: Alfred A. Knopf. $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BRINGING DOWN THE GREAT WALL</p>
        <p>Writings on Science, Culture, and Democracy in China. By Fang Lizhi. Edited by James H. Williams. Translated by James H. Williams and others. Introduction by Orville Schell. 336 pp. New York: Alfred A. Knopf. $19.95.</p>
        <p>Fang Lizhi, the Chinese dissident, likes sometimes to present himself as the very model of the absent-minded intellectual, a man so wrapped up in his own thoughts that he has little consciousness of the world around him. In middle school, he tells us in "Bringing Down the Great Wall," a moving collection of his essays, interviews and speeches, "I was so absorbed with the daydreams that my teachers aroused in me there that at times I would walk right into utility poles on the side of the road." But he at once adds a gloss to this fairly conventional metaphor, one that shows the mischievous and pragmatic side of his character: "So hard did I bump into them, in fact, that I can still remember the numbers that were written on those poles." It is not the pain he wants us to know he remembers, but the numbers.</p>
        <p>As one of China's leading scientists, first in astrophysics and later in cosmology, Mr. Fang is very good indeed both at dreaming and at remembering the numbers. But as an incorrigible freethinker, who has seen with mounting anguish the hopeless state into which Chinese society is drifting, Mr. Fang also has become an accomplished expert at deliberately walking into immovable objects -- in this case, the hard-liners in the upper echelons of the Communist Party's political and educational bureaucracies.</p>
        <p>Fang Lizhi is now one of China's best-known dissidents. He was accused by the Chinese Government of being one of the ringleaders of the huge spring 1989 demonstrations in Tiananmen Square; and, after the mass slaughter of civilians in Beijing on June 4 by the People's Liberation Army, he and his wife sought shelter in the United States Embassy. Allowed to leave the country in the summer of 1990, he has since received academic sanctuary in Cambridge University and in Princeton.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fang's popularity and notoriety have been due in part to his visibility: as an internationally prominent scientist and the vice president of the important University of Science and Technology at Hefei in Anhui Province, he was at the forefront of those trying to train China's youth to participate successfully in the front ranks of the international scientific community. Mr. Fang has also got attention because he has been through a lot: he was purged and deprived of his Communist Party membership in the antirightist campaign of 1957 for his outspoken critique of the sterility of Communist party discussions; he was rehabilitated in 1978, after the Cultural Revolution; he was deprived once more of his party membership in early 1987, as the hard-liners struck back against the late 1986 student demonstrations; and he brought the Government's anger down on himself again in January 1989 when he appealed to the Party to release Wei Jingsheng, the foremost protester of China's long-crushed democracy movement of 1978, who had by then spent 10 years in jail. But, above all, Fang Lizhi has been listened to because he is witty, passionate, tenacious and articulate. Students have loved his speeches; whether he had prepared carefully or spoke off the cuff, he could hold an audience in the palm of his hand.</p>
        <p>The rhythms of Mr. Fang's life as a highly visible protester against his Government's stupidity, greed and cruelty have inevitably led to his being compared to Andrei Sakharov in the Soviet Union and to Vaclav Havel in Czechoslovakia. But in various interviews Mr. Fang has always dodged all parallels with Sakharov, and has explicitly rejected those to Mr. Havel. He emphatically denies that he is a political leader and insists that he does not want to be one. It is one of the weaknesses of China, he explains, that the Chinese reject one leader only to submit themselves to another. It would be far better, he says, for the Chinese "to learn that democracy requires a confrontation of ideas and not a leader who says one thing and everybody follows. . . . If the Chinese people are expecting the appearance of a hero, it had better not be me. This expectation in itself is very unhealthy."</p>
        <p>In "Bringing Down the Great Wall," James H. Williams, a scholar on science and technology in China, and a few of his colleagues have translated and compiled an admirably comprehensive selection of Fang Lizhi's written and spoken words,focusing on his works since 1979 and ending with some of the pieces he wrote after being allowed to leave China in 1990. Mr. Fang's writings are divided into sections corresponding to what they see as four sides of his nature: the cosmologist, the cosmopolitan, the democrat and the dissident. The translations are fluent, and the introductions to each section, along with Orville Schell's long introduction to the book as a whole, are intelligent and pertinent. The Fang Lizhi who is thus introduced to us is humane in an immediately accessible way: decent, courageous, sometimes evasive, sometimes sarcastic, urbane yet emotional, a socialist and an elitist, opinionated and impatient of official cant.</p>
        <p>Readers today are likely to have trouble remembering just how "unsayable" so many of Fang Lizhi's thoughts were in the contexts in which he uttered them. His courage is thus not obvious to an outsider. The fervor of the students' responses came from the fact that they had never heard such words before, certainly not from a senior figure in the establishment. As Mr. Fang says in a beautiful essay, "The End of Forgetting History," this does not mean such things had not ever been said in China -- they had been said spiritedly in 1957 and in 1978 -- but the Chinese state had erased them from the record, replacing the vanished voices with a void that could be filled only with whispers.</p>
        <p>In the mid-1980's, as Mr. Fang hit his stride as a social critic, a host of other Chinese were also trying to give their own versions of truth, not just in essays and speeches but also in films and paintings, novels and poems. But whereas most of them chose to be indirect to some extent, there was little that was indirect about Mr. Fang. He suggested to his audiences that the best global parallels for China were to be found in the zealotry of Iran, the economic stagnation of Poland and the terrible poverty of Chad; he told them "Marxism has become ossified," that the Government's habit of continually shifting its policies was "an infantile way of running an economy," and that the philosophical pronouncements from the Office of National Dialectics in the Chinese Academy of Social Science merely perpetuated "the image of a Chinaman with a long pigtail, clad in a Western suit."</p>
        <p>During the 1980's, Deng Xiaoping and the Chinese Communist Party were trying to make people subscribe to the "Four Upholds," : the Socialist road, the dictatorship of the proletariat, Communist Party leadership and the leading role of "Marxism-Leninism-Mao Zedong Thought." Mr. Fang countered these by saying that he believed a university should have its own four upholds: "a spirit of science, democracy, creativity, and independence." Told by a reporter that his four upholds" might be seen as "a little dangerous," Mr. Fang replied that perhaps he could clarify things by relating his four upholds to what the Government's four really referred to -- namely, superstition, dictatorship, conservatism and dependency. To give some idea of Mr. Fang's bravado, this particular speech was delivered to about 3,000 students and faculty at Tongzhi University in Shanghai in November 1986.</p>
        <p>Commentators on China's various democracy movements, those of 1978, 1986 or 1989, have stated that there never seems to be any content to Chinese discussions of democracy, and that this makes the whole movement seem elusive. Mr. Fang, however, has offered frequent, crisp and intelligent analyses of what he means by democracy -- definitions that even those comfortably raised within such democracies might find hard to improve upon. Democracy, Mr. Fang told his Chinese audiences, means genuine pluralism rather than personalized attacks on the opposition; it means controlling corruption through public scrutiny and accountability; it means upholding the right to complain about injustice of all kinds; it means supporting the fundamental idea of shared human rights; it means governmental responsibility to its citizens; it means not relying on informers and not taking punitive action on the basis of casual suspicions; and it means refusing to quote as wisdom the observations of political leaders who know nothing.</p>
        <p>Chinese and foreign journalists and Mr. Fang's student audiences have often asked how such values might be introduced into China. Mr. Fang has no easy answers. Perhaps change could come from within even if the external structures of government remain the same, he suggests, illustrating his point by using the words of a homely traditional Chinese metaphor: "In front of the shop the sheep's head keeps dangling, but inside the shop one sells dog meat." But, he says, before that happens the people must make it clear to the party that they want change. And that will not be easy, since the Chinese, unsure about what to do, are "like a swarm of headless flies, buzzing around in every direction."</p>
        <p>But Mr. Fang suggests two ways out of this box. First, it is possible that the Government, faced with the strength and determination of the democracy movement in China and abroad, might be forced to change constructively, "just as a bandit gives in when he meets a stronger force." Secondly, it is possible that current global changes themselves might force the issue: "The greenhouse effect, the population explosion, are issues that cannot be solved without a global solution. If China cannot catch up with the rest of the world, the world will make China catch up with it."</p>
        <p>Fang Lizhi may reject comparisons between himself and Andrei Sakharov or Vaclav Havel, but others will continue to make those comparisons for him. As Mr. Williams succinctly puts it in his introduction to one of the sections of this moving and intelligently orchestrated collection, Mr. Fang's great skill is that, "like Sakharov in the Soviet Union, he used the prestige of science to ferry ideas from beyond the margins of political permissibility into the general discourse on reform." We might supplement that comment with an idea that Mr. Havel expressed in his books "Disturbing the Peace" and "Letters to Olga": in the grim world of Communist dictatorship, where optimism seems too facile an idea, there is always a deeper force, something we can term "hope." Hope to Mr. Havel is the power that enables us to keep alive the belief that one day things will again make sense. This making sense of experience is one of the things that gives us courage as we pursue what Mr. Havel calls our "entirely obscure task" on this planet. Mr. Fang, this book shows, has the mental strength to keep that hope alive and to maintain the faith that one day all that he, his contemporaries and his country have gone through during the last half-century will somehow make sense. On the day that happens, the Great Wall will truly come down. INTELLECTUALS UP FRONT</p>
        <p>"For the democracy movement, of course, China needs leaders," said Fang Lizhi, the Chinese astrophysicist and dissident, during a telephone interview from the University of Louisville, in Kentucky, where he was visiting. Yet Mr. Fang refuses to be considered one of those leaders. "I do not like that job," he replied rather wearily. "I like teaching and telling people things. I'm a sparrow leader."</p>
        <p>What Mr. Fang calls a sparrow, Americans call a gadfly. Indeed, it was Mr. Fang's outspokenness that forced him to seek refuge in the United States Embassy in Beijing before going into exile. He is now working on the topology of the universe at the Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton, N.J.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fang may not hope to govern, but he does believe intellectuals belong at the forefront of any functioning democracy -- quite the opposite of the situation in China. There, he said, "the party's first, the intellectuals last."</p>
        <p>Mr. Fang assembled his speeches, letters and essays in "Bringing Down the Great Wall" so they would be on hand for debate. The first step toward reform, he said, is freedom of speech and freedom of the press. But how, aside from the book, does he hope to contribute to the conversation about China while living in New Jersey? "It's difficult," he said. "I am quite far from China. I have joined the Chinese students, I have joined some international organizations for human rights. I can still do something, but it is limited, obviously, to the issue of human rights." -- JUDITH SHULEVITZ  Jonathan D. Spence teaches modern Chinese history at Yale University. His most recent books are "The Question of Hu" and "The Search for Modern China."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jonathan D. Spence teaches modern Chinese history at Yale University. His most recent books are "The Question of Hu" and "The Search for Modern China."</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
