<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>4 Ships to Battle Floes On Polar Explorations</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="460279"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXPLORATION AND EXPLORERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHIPS AND SHIPPING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICEBREAKERS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, WALTER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exploration and Explorers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Icebreakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDA1E3CF935A25754C0A967958260" item-length="591" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>4 Ships to Battle Floes On Polar Explorations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER SULLIVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ICEBREAKERS from four countries are to fight their way through ice floes of the Arctic Ocean this summer in hope of reaching the North Pole. Three, sailing from Tromso in northern Norway, are participating in a six-nation effort whose prime goals are scientific.</p>
        <p>The fourth icebreaker, the Soviet Union's nuclear-powered Sovietsky Soyuz, is to carry tourists as well as scientists to the Pole, then complete history's first surface ship crossing of the entire Arctic Ocean.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ICEBREAKERS from four countries are to fight their way through ice floes of the Arctic Ocean this summer in hope of reaching the North Pole. Three, sailing from Tromso in northern Norway, are participating in a six-nation effort whose prime goals are scientific.</p>
        <p>The fourth icebreaker, the Soviet Union's nuclear-powered Sovietsky Soyuz, is to carry tourists as well as scientists to the Pole, then complete history's first surface ship crossing of the entire Arctic Ocean.</p>
        <p>The icebreakers sailing from Norway will constitute the International Arctic Ocean Expedition -- 1991. Its co-chief scientist, Dr. Leonard Johnson of the United States Office of Naval Research, said the expedition began to develop in 1988 when Sweden said it planned to send its icebreaker Oden to study the ocean beneath the Arctic ice. The Germans proposed adding their ship Polarstern, and the United States then offered to include the Coast Guard icebreaker Polar Star.</p>
        <p>They are scheduled to leave Tromso on Aug. 9, returning on Oct. 10. The timing makes an encounter with the Soviet ship unlikely.</p>
        <p>While the Arctic pack averages 10 feet in thickness, in areas of compression the ice floes buckle into ridges that may be 30 feet high.  Looking at Global Warming</p>
        <p>While the ships hope to reach the Pole, Dr. Johnson said, their success will depend on ice conditions. Their chief goal is to collect data, including evidence for global warming.</p>
        <p>The Arctic is thought to be particularly sensitive to climatic temperature changes. The expedition's other co-chief scientist, Dr. Susumu Honjo of the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution, said a temperature rise should thin the ice, exposing more water and accelerating the warming.</p>
        <p>The international Arctic expedition is considered the most ambitious program ever to fathom the secrets of that ice-covered ocean, the sea floor beneath it and the weather above it.</p>
        <p>In 1977, a Soviet icebreaker became the first surface ship to reach the top of the world. Since the 1930's, exploration of the region has been possible from scientific camps drifting on the ice and from submarines prowling under the ice, but the Arctic Ocean still remains the least known of the world's seas.</p>
        <p>Among the puzzles is the fate of the Mid-Atlantic Ridge, which extends across the Arctic Ocean. It presumably marks a spreading apart of the Arctic Basin. Dredging rocks from the ridge is a high priority. Measuring Ice Thickness</p>
        <p>The expedition plans a variety of elaborate buoys. Chief among them are two developed by Woods Hole and the Japan Marine Science and Technology Center. Each will have 232 sensors to measure phenomena like air and water temperature and ice thickness.</p>
        <p>One major concern is the role of substances carried into the Arctic Ocean by rivers in North America, Europe and Asia. Some experts believe such material then flows into the North Atlantic, feeding the rich fisheries of that region.</p>
        <p>Devices will extract samples of sea floor sediment in an attempt to determine the history of that region for at least the past 100,000 years.</p>
        <p>Aboard the chartered Soviet ship, according to the organizer, Salen Lindblat Cruising Inc., will be some 96 passengers, including 12 scientists sponsored by the National Science Foundation. The ship is to leave Murmansk, on Russia's coast, on July 26.</p>
        <p>Having reached the Pole, it is to continue on to reach the Bering Strait, between Alaska and Siberia, on Aug. 16, then return to Murmansk.  For most the transpolar cost ranges from $25,000 to $29,900.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
