<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>We Didn't Get Into This Ecological Fix by Lack of Technology</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="459790"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DA1F3CF937A25754C0A967958260" item-length="384" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>We Didn't Get Into This Ecological Fix by Lack of Technology</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In "From Brilliant Pebbles to Brilliant Eyes" (Op-Ed, June 23), Edward Teller attempts to link protection of the environment with the construction of a network of 1,000 satellites, whose primary purpose is military. It would be heartwarming indeed were this illustrious American scientist to become a champion of the ecosystem. Alas, a closer reading of Dr. Teller's proposal shows an attempt to hitch the setting star of the "Star Wars" program to ecological awareness. This would not be a match made in heaven.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In "From Brilliant Pebbles to Brilliant Eyes" (Op-Ed, June 23), Edward Teller attempts to link protection of the environment with the construction of a network of 1,000 satellites, whose primary purpose is military. It would be heartwarming indeed were this illustrious American scientist to become a champion of the ecosystem. Alas, a closer reading of Dr. Teller's proposal shows an attempt to hitch the setting star of the "Star Wars" program to ecological awareness. This would not be a match made in heaven.</p>
        <p>The installation and maintenance of a vast fleet of satellites would have potentially dire ecological consequences. Solid-fueled rockets, including the space shuttle, deposit hydrochloric acid in the atmosphere, which destroys ozone. The exact contribution of rocket exhaust to ozone depletion has not yet been determined, but it is a serious concern (as you report in "Some Say the Rockets' Red Glare Is Eating Away at the Ozone Layer," Science Times, May 14).</p>
        <p>Even more disturbing is the linkage of military and environmental goals. The armed services may have made a great contribution to the security and well-being of our country -- but not to environmental health. The United States nuclear weapons industry, to cite just one example, is probably the world's biggest system of toxic-waste production. There is probably no area of government activity where national security and foreign policy have so excused indifference to public health and welfare. Real environmental progress depends on democratic consensus, not the hidden procedures of the military.</p>
        <p>In the final analysis, the roots of our ecological crisis lie not in a lack of technology, but in our alienation from the natural world. It is a personal challenge, not a technical problem. Although technology can assist us, the solution is ultimately to be found in the way we live, not in the machines that we devise. We need to cherish biological diversity, live more lightly upon the earth -- and recycle.</p>
        <p>If we agree to do so, then we will need no sophisticated machinery to save us. However, if we fail to do so, then even the most brilliant tools will not preserve this fragile Spaceship Earth.  CASEY FRANK Jamaica Plain, Mass., July 1, 1991 The writer practices environmental law.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
