<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="468794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D61530F930A1575BC0A967958260" item-length="1174" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After the Coup A8-15</p>
        <p>President Gorbachev said his rescue from the failed coup had taught him that he must join more closely with "democratic forces" and speed the pace of reform. Meanwhile, one of the coup leaders killed himself. Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After the Coup A8-15</p>
        <p>President Gorbachev said his rescue from the failed coup had taught him that he must join more closely with "democratic forces" and speed the pace of reform. Meanwhile, one of the coup leaders killed himself. Page A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: The greatest paradox of the failed coup is that President Gorbachev was saved by the one man he had done his best to destroy, and that Boris Yeltsin rescued a leader whose downfall he had sought. A1</p>
        <p>Mr. Gorbachev described his ordeal, pausing again and again as he recalled the emotions of three days in captivity. His time was spent anticipating the worst and preparing a bootleg videotape. A13</p>
        <p>New faces of new era at Kremlin A8</p>
        <p>Soviet military facing shuffle and reduced independence A14</p>
        <p>Yeltsin reveals new Russian flag A13</p>
        <p>Muscovites savored their triumph over the coup as hordes of anti-Communist residents celebrated by lifting a statue of the founder of the Soviet secret police off its pedestal. A9</p>
        <p>Diplomatic recognition of the Baltics is becoming a real possibility, the Bush Administration and Western governments said. But they said it was still up to the Soviet Union to give sovereignity to the republics.  A9</p>
        <p>Latvians outlaw Communist Party; seek arrest of leader A9</p>
        <p>A new admiration for the Soviets among Americans has replaced lingering feelings of mistrust. More than any time in 50 years, Americans are describing Soviets as kindred spirits with a love of freedom.  A1</p>
        <p>President Bush sent mixed signals to the Soviet Union, reinstating the assistance that he suspended during the coup but saying he would not support major financial aid until he sees significant economic reforms. A15</p>
        <p>Europe resumed giving economic aid to the Soviet Union and expressed hope that President Gorbachev would now step up moves to introduce a full market economy. A15</p>
        <p>Japan is reluctant on more Soviet aid A15</p>
        <p>Chinese express relief at news of Gorbachev's return A14  International A3-6</p>
        <p>Croatia's president issued a warning that his Government would treat the Yugoslav army as an occupying force if its units and rebel Serbs in Croatia did not honor a cease-fire.  A3</p>
        <p>Military authorities in El Salvador have displayed what they said where two guerrilla arms caches, asserting that they were signs of a planned offensive on the capital. A5</p>
        <p>Pocone Journal: Exaltation of alligators in swamp of trouble A4</p>
        <p>Deng Xiaoping turned 87 years old, and the Chinese leader is turning out to be more of an enigma in retirement than he was in power. Mr. Deng's image seems to have undergone reassessment recently. A3</p>
        <p>Palestinians again supported the wrong side, Israelis say A6  National A16-18, D18</p>
        <p>Warnings on dangers of 10 pesticides were overlooked by the Environmental Protection Agency, which is responsible for evaluating scientific studies on possible health dangers of such chemicals. A16</p>
        <p>Jim Bakker sought a lighter sentence in Federal Court. Looking older, grayer and thinner, he asked for a reduction of the 45-year sentence he was given after his fraud conviction in October 1989. A16</p>
        <p>The Cubans who seized a prison unit and 10 hostages in Alabama are worried not only about the stark prospect of deportation. They are also frustrated with the complicated legal process that determines their fate. A16</p>
        <p>Judge is rejected in officers' case in Los Angeles A18</p>
        <p>California eases water curbs A18 Lockheed to pay on water cleanup D18</p>
        <p>Americans back the education plan proposed by President Bush to let children attend public schools of their choice, but balk at using public money for private education, a new poll has found. D18</p>
        <p>Advocates for the disabled are angry over a Los Angeles talk show host who suggested that a pregnant television newscaster was irresponsible in taking the risk of passing a physical abnormality to her child. B18</p>
        <p>White House plans to limit ban on offshore drilling D18</p>
        <p>Oil company to pay $4 million over Texas blast fatal to 23 D18</p>
        <p>Surgeon and wife convicted of killing child D18  Regional B1-5</p>
        <p>Connecticut finally passed a budget. After six months of anguished deadlock, legislators approved Governor Weicker's income tax plan after a 36-hour marathon of deal making and brinkmanship. A1</p>
        <p>The police vowed to crack down on protesters in the racially torn Crown Heights section of Brooklyn as officials scrambled to soothe the tensions of three nights of violence.  B1</p>
        <p>The chasm between blacks and Jews in Crown Heights is heightened by their strikingly different views of the world and each other. But for both groups, the recent clash has become a metaphor for victimization. B1</p>
        <p>Mayor Dinkins expressed frustration that as the city's first black Mayor he should be a miracle worker, capable of solving New York's multilayered social and racial tensions that have eluded solution for years. B3</p>
        <p>The accident that started it all B2</p>
        <p>Examining the legal issues in the crash B2</p>
        <p>An inhabited island on Jamaica Bay is an anomaly in New York City. Broad Channel, which connects Howard Beach to the Rockaways, is home to 2,500 people who fiercely guard their isolation. B1</p>
        <p>The Statue of Liberty's skin problems may not be caused by acid rain, as scientists have long theorized. Now one scientist says the dark patches on the statue's green skin is caused by the harbor's salty water. B1</p>
        <p>U.S. uncovers new failures in nine-mile nuclear disruption B5  Business Digest D1  Weekend</p>
        <p>Making friends with the Met museum C1</p>
        <p>Time for radio (yes, radio) C1</p>
        <p>For Children C21</p>
        <p>Theater: On Stage, and Off C2</p>
        <p>Film: At the Movies C8</p>
        <p>"Dead Again" C1</p>
        <p>"Defenseless" C8</p>
        <p>"Pastime" C13</p>
        <p>"Uranus" C15</p>
        <p>"True Identity" C16</p>
        <p>Music: Sounds Around Town C5</p>
        <p>Pop Jazz: 24-7 Spyz C26</p>
        <p>Dance: Baryshnikov dances Mark Morris C3</p>
        <p>Art: Culture and photography C5</p>
        <p>Art in Review C22</p>
        <p>Evocations of a culture C23</p>
        <p>Restaurants C20</p>
        <p>Word and Image: Novel about a lawyer's torments C25</p>
        <p>TV Weekend C26  Law Page B18</p>
        <p>Canadian high court narrows its rape shield law  Obituaries</p>
        <p>Colleen Dewhurst, an actress D16</p>
        <p>Paul Miller, ex-chairman of Gannett and the Associated Press D17  Sports B10-17</p>
        <p>Baseball: Mets beat Cardinals B11</p>
        <p>Staten Island loses in Little League series B13</p>
        <p>Viola's value dipping B13</p>
        <p>Basketball: Knicks willing to talk trade B11</p>
        <p>Columns: Berkow on Handley, Hostetler and Simms B11</p>
        <p>On Horse Racing B16</p>
        <p>Lipsyte on show biz B16</p>
        <p>Football: Thursday morning quarterbacks B11</p>
        <p>Tennis: Trying to find a practice court B14  Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials A26</p>
        <p>No black magic in the Mayor</p>
        <p>Baltic freedom in a new light</p>
        <p>A breakthrough in Connecticut</p>
        <p>Topics: Upside down in the eye</p>
        <p>Letters A26</p>
        <p>Anthony Lewis: Triumph and decline</p>
        <p>A.M. Rosenthal: From Baltics to Beijing A27  Robert Conquest: Their finest hour</p>
        <p>Richard Burt: Send help - and plenty of it.  A27  Joseph A. Grundfest: Smoking Salomon. A27</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
