<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NOTED WITH PLEASURE</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="456510"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D81E3EF933A05755C0A967958260" item-length="981" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NOTED WITH PLEASURE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Universal Passion</p>
        <p>Octavio Paz, winner of the 1990 Nobel Prize in Literature, reflects in his acceptance speech on the elusive meanings and broad influence of the concept of modernity. This is from "In Search of the Present" (Harvest/Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, paper).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Universal Passion</p>
        <p>Octavio Paz, winner of the 1990 Nobel Prize in Literature, reflects in his acceptance speech on the elusive meanings and broad influence of the concept of modernity. This is from "In Search of the Present" (Harvest/Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, paper).</p>
        <p>What is modernity? It is, first of all, an ambiguous term: there are as many types of modernity as there are societies. Each society has its own. The word's meaning is as uncertain and arbitrary as the name of the period that precedes it, the Middle Ages. If we are modern when compared to medieval times, are we perhaps the Middle Ages of a future modernity? Is a name that changes with time a real name? Modernity is a word in search of its meaning. Is it an idea, a mirage or a moment of history? Are we the children of modernity or are we its creators? Nobody knows for sure. . . . Modernity has been a universal passion. Since 1850 she has been our goddess and our demoness. In recent years there has been an attempt to exorcise her, and there has been much talk of "postmodernism." But what is postmodernism if not an even more modern modernity? Reducing Life to Postcards</p>
        <p>Since the rise of the tourist industry we have often confused foreign lands with the pretty (and unreal) images with which travel is promoted, as Malcolm Andrews reminds us in "The Search for the Picturesque" (Stanford University, paper).</p>
        <p>A rich sunset, a Caribbean beach, a ruined Greek temple, a thatched cottage, a gnarled fisherman mending his net. . . . These have little in common except that, in different ways, each is visually attractive and enriched with sentimental associations. However, the travel-brochure writer would not hesitate to call each one "picturesque." The word is a valuable coin in the currency of tourism. It means "like a picture" and implies that each scene fills some pictorial prescription in terms of subject-matter or composition. The travel-brochure writer is trading on his company's being able to offer access to the living originals of the pictorial stereotypes. . . . There is a peculiar circularity in the tourist's experience. He values the kind of scenery which has been aesthetically validated in paintings, postcards and advertisements; he appraises it with the word "picturesque"; and then he takes a photograph of it to confirm its pictorial value. Simplifying the Primitive</p>
        <p>The idea that tribal art is valuable because it is more unreflective than Western art, and its creators touchingly naive, is, Sally Price argues, condescending and racist. This is from "Primitive Art in Civilized Places" (University of Chicago, paper).</p>
        <p>A widely accepted belief . . . is that, more than any art from the world's Great Civilizations (whether Western or Oriental), Primitive Art emerges directly and spontaneously from psychological drives. Just as children cry when they are hungry and coo when they are content, Primitive artists are imagined to express their feelings free from the intrusive overlay of learned behavior and conscious constraints that mold the work of the Civilized artist. . . . Western enthusiasts of Primitive Art have always argued that its authors are in particularly close touch with the "fundamental, basic, and essential drives of life" -- drives that Civilized Man shares but "buries" under a layer of learned behavior. The view of Primitive Art as a kind of creative expression that flows unchecked from the artist's unconscious is responsible for comparisons between Primitive Art and the drawings of children, and its racist foundation is rather transparent. At Home in the Universe</p>
        <p>We dream of voyaging into space, William E. Burrows writes, not just for knowledge. More important, such exploration helps justify our existence. This is from "Exploring Space: Voyages in the Solar System and Beyond" (Random House).</p>
        <p>Longing to learn is certainly the most valid rationale for undertaking voyages far from the protected precincts of home. Yet in the most basic sense, even the collecting of data -- the stocking of libraries -- is only a supremely honorable excuse to visit new worlds. Rather, the core motivation for human beings to venture where they can, and to send robotic proxies where they cannot, is as sublimated but as real and ultimately unerring as the one that guides snow geese, salmon, and other migrators on their own immense journeys. It is a reason that transcends reason. We go because of a profound urge to leave our imprint on the universe. Doing so, physically as well as spiritually, is the only way we can fundamentally relate to it. Finding Solace in the Moment</p>
        <p>Musing over the growing threats to his garden and the wider world, William Longgood resolves to take strength for the fight from each day's fleeting pleasures in this passage from "Voices From the Earth: A Year in the Life of a Garden" (Norton).</p>
        <p>Everything seems at risk nowadays. It must take some doing to be an optimist. My poor little onion seedlings and others to follow must be ready to withstand assault, acid rain, the greenhouse effect, ultraviolet rays penetrating a diminished ozone layer. . . . The various threats to the environment and life itself do not seem to affect the mockingbird singing so valiantly atop the chimney. . . . His song is unadulterated happiness, the distilled essence of joy in life. The onion seedlings and I can take a lesson from this intrepid troubadour: Live in the moment; do not think about the future and its perils. I read recently about a woman who, after years of depression over the declining environment, put such cares aside and found new pleasure in daily living, concentrating on savoring "those rare moments of grace in an indifferent universe," sound advice for all of us who think too much about the unraveling state of the world.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
