<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Photos by Radar Hint at Ice on Poles of Mercury</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="485330"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MERCURY (PLANET)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MOON</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEED7113AF934A35752C1A967958260" item-length="818" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Photos by Radar Hint at Ice on Poles of Mercury</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the planet nearest the Sun, Mercury bakes in temperatures hot enough to melt lead, but new radar observations have revealed that the planet's polar regions, which get little sunlight, appear to be covered with vast sheets of water ice.</p>
        <p>Scientists said the discovery, announced yesterday, was surprising and exciting and could have important implications for future exploration of the Moon. If Mercury has reservoirs of frozen water, they speculated, the Moon, where conditions are somewhat similar, might also have some polar ice that has gone undetected.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the planet nearest the Sun, Mercury bakes in temperatures hot enough to melt lead, but new radar observations have revealed that the planet's polar regions, which get little sunlight, appear to be covered with vast sheets of water ice.</p>
        <p>Scientists said the discovery, announced yesterday, was surprising and exciting and could have important implications for future exploration of the Moon. If Mercury has reservoirs of frozen water, they speculated, the Moon, where conditions are somewhat similar, might also have some polar ice that has gone undetected.</p>
        <p>And if so, this could make the Moon a more attractive place for human outposts. The lunar polar regions have yet to be examined in any detail by telescope or spacecraft.</p>
        <p>In studies of Mercury in August with powerful radar antennas on Earth, astronomers at the California Institute of Technology and the Jet Propulsion Laboratory, both in Pasadena, Calif., produced the first radar photographs of an entire hemisphere of the planet. They showed an especially bright region at the north pole that, the astronomers said, had all the characteristics of ice reflecting the radar signals.</p>
        <p>Dr. Duane Muhleman, professor of planetary science at Caltech, released the radar photographs and described the findings at a meeting of the American Astronomical Society's Division of Planetary Sciences at Palo Alto, Calif.</p>
        <p>Dr. Muhleman acknowledged that the interpretations were preliminary and that other explanations could be postulated to explain the bright polar structure. "But we regard these alternatives as farfetched," he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bruce C. Murray, a planetary geologist at Caltech who was the chief scientist for the Mariner 10 mission to Mercury in the early 1970's, said, "It's an extraordinary discovery with lots of ramifications."</p>
        <p>Mariner 10 is the only spacecraft to conduct a reconnaissance of Mercury, a planet not much larger than the Moon and slightly smaller than Jupiter's satellite Ganymede and Saturn's Titan.</p>
        <p>On several passages near the planet in 1974, the spacecraft photographed about half of Mercury's surface.</p>
        <p>The radar experiments, conceived by Dr. Muhleman, were able to make images of the other half of Mercury, which has never before been seen except as fuzzy smudges through Earth-based optical telescopes. The powerful radio signal was beamed from the Goldstone antenna in the Mojave Desert of California. The reflected signal was received by 27 radio telescopes near Socorro, N.M. Variations in the surface reflectivity were analyzed to reveal broad topographic features and the apparent ice cap at the north pole. Temperatures of 800 Degrees</p>
        <p>The Goldstone operation was supervised by Dr. Raymond Jurgens of the Jet Propulsion Laboratory. The return signals were processed by Dr. Martin Slade of the laboratory and Bryan Butler, a Caltech graduate student.</p>
        <p>Because the rotational axis of Mercury is completely vertical, and not tilted as in the case of Earth and other planets, the Sun is always exactly overhead on the equator, where the temperature can get as high as 800 degrees Fahrenheit during the planet's closest approach to the Sun every 88 days. This means that there are no seasons on Mercury and some amount of sunlight is always visible from the poles, except perhaps in deep craters very close to the pole.</p>
        <p>Mercury's polar regions are estimated to get as cold as minus 235 degrees Fahrenheit, cold enough to develop and sustain an ice cap.</p>
        <p>Dr. Muhleman theorized that the extremely high temperatures in equatorial regions cook the surface, releasing some chemical substances to create a tenuous atmosphere. Some evidence for an extremely thin atmosphere at Mercury, composed mainly of sodium, was reported in 1985. Most of these gases, which probably include water vapor as well as sodium, escape into space, he said, but some might migrate to the cold polar regions, where they precipitate as a kind of snow.</p>
        <p>"Certainly all water outgassed by the heat of the Sun either escapes or collects at the poles," Dr. Muhleman said.</p>
        <p>The scientists said the brightness patterns of the radar signals from Mercury were similar to those from known ice deposits on Mars and some of the large satellites of the outer solar system. They said they assumed that similar ice sheets would be found at the south pole of Mercury.</p>
        <p>Dr. Slade said some earlier radar studies produced hints of south polar ice. The next observations are to be aimed at that part of Mercury.</p>
        <p>Other features noted in the radar studies of the unphotographed side of Mercury included what appeared to be a large crater as wide as 800 miles. It may be a strong reflector of radar signals because of the presence of vast amounts of sodium on the surface. Another notable feature is the presence of two roughly identical craters that lie on the same longitude meridian and at the same latitude on either side of the equator.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
