<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Now Is The Summer of Discontent</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="469049"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="POP VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROCK MUSIC</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PARELES, JON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DD1538F936A1575BC0A967958260" item-length="1172" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Now Is The Summer of Discontent</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jon Pareles</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PARELES, JON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a balmy, breezy Sunday afternoon deep in the suburbs. Two weeks ago, about 15,000 people, the vast majority between 16 and 25 years of age, gathered in the concert field of bucolic Waterloo Village in Stanhope, N.J. They were nice folks in clean T-shirts, halter tops, shorts, jeans and mass-market punkwear; even the buzzcuts were designer-styled. When someone bumped into someone else, as happens at sold-out rock concerts, polite "Excuse me's" were traded.</p>
        <p>The fans had congregated, however, for nine hours of howling, bawling, shouting and wailing, for denunciations of everything from self-pity to police brutality to parental abandonment, and they yelled affirmation when Trent Reznor of Nine Inch Nails groaned, "I hate everybody!" or Ice-T sang, "I'm a cop killer!"</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was a balmy, breezy Sunday afternoon deep in the suburbs. Two weeks ago, about 15,000 people, the vast majority between 16 and 25 years of age, gathered in the concert field of bucolic Waterloo Village in Stanhope, N.J. They were nice folks in clean T-shirts, halter tops, shorts, jeans and mass-market punkwear; even the buzzcuts were designer-styled. When someone bumped into someone else, as happens at sold-out rock concerts, polite "Excuse me's" were traded.</p>
        <p>The fans had congregated, however, for nine hours of howling, bawling, shouting and wailing, for denunciations of everything from self-pity to police brutality to parental abandonment, and they yelled affirmation when Trent Reznor of Nine Inch Nails groaned, "I hate everybody!" or Ice-T sang, "I'm a cop killer!"</p>
        <p>It was the Lollapalooza Festival, the seven-band package tour headlined by Jane's Addiction, and it is one of the few summer arena tours that's doing good business. Lollapalooza's promoters have found out, as have record stores, that this is the summer of rage -- or, more precisely, the summer when rage sells. It's not rage that supports sweeping political or social movements (though Lollapalooza encourages that possibility, touring with pro-choice, anti-handgun, voter-registration and environmental activists). Nor is it the kind of rage that leads to nationwide riots (although when W. Axl Rose of Guns 'n' Roses got an attack of prima donna-itis, and cut a concert short in St. Louis, fans tore apart the band's stage and equipment).</p>
        <p>It is a rage as inarticulate as it is widespread -- a rage that echoes in outcast music from prison songs to rockabilly to punk, but which has now moved in from the margins. And while observers across the political spectrum worry about sexism or lawlessness or racism or homophobia in various lyrics, they haven't noticed the big picture: audiences gravitate to rage, and most of them don't much care who or what that rage is aimed at. All they want is to feel that someone else is as angry as they are. Compared to the measured doubletalk of politicians and the euphemisms of teachers and other authority figures, uncut rage may seem bracingly sincere.</p>
        <p>To the relief of authorities everywhere, most of the summer's rage is channeled into consumption, into concert tickets and album purchases. N.W.A.'s "Efil4zaggin," a rap album split equally between protests against racist brutality and boasts about sexual brutality against women, zoomed to No. 1 in Billboard magazine's pop charts and sold a million copies in two weeks. It was knocked from the top of the charts by Skid Row, a hard-rock band that spews imprecations at everyone.</p>
        <p>Angry rappers like Ice-T and Ice Cube have emerged as million-sellers and as movie stars in films like "New Jack City" and the anti-violence "Boyz N the Hood." Tours like the Clash of the Titans -- Anthrax, Slayer, Megadeth, all thrash bands, and the slower but equally implacable Alice in Chains -- have drawn sellout crowds who shout along on lines like "Ain't gonna live my life this way!" or the chorus of "Keep It in the Family," a song about how racism is passed from generation to generation: "Hate! Hate! Hate!" Meanwhile, the two long-promised Guns 'n' Roses albums, "Use Your Illusion (I and II)," will include "Double Talkin' Jive," which warns, "I got no more patience."</p>
        <p>For anyone monitoring popular culture, rage as big box office is no suprise. Hostile characters like Roseanne, Bart Simpson and Al Bundy have transformed the happy-family sitcom; slasher and body-count movies have become categories unto themselves. Radio talk-show hosts like Howard Stern and Rush Limbaugh boosted ratings by dispensing nastier and nastier put-downs, cackling with self-satisfaction all the while.</p>
        <p>Rock's major new growth areas in the 1980's included dance music (notably house music), rap, thrash, mope-rock and industrial rock -- one to dance troubles away, four others to throw them back in the world's face. Forget protest songs, with their topicality, their hopeful suggestions and their attempts to convince the uncommitted. In the new genres, hope is rarer than an uplifting melody -- and thrash, rap and industrial rock barely bother with melody at all, proud to be on the other side of a musical generation gap.</p>
        <p>As their elders lightly chide themselves about their yuppie excesses and promise to be kinder and gentler, convenience permitting, a younger generation faces an adulthood that promises nothing but bad news. "In the 1980's," writes Donna Gaines, a sociologist, in her new book "Teenage Wasteland: Suburbia's Dead End Kids," "the great promise of suburbia or the wild urban adventure moved well beyond the grasp of most people. The world out there seems less welcoming than it once was. It has less to offer, and the road is harder. There are fewer free spaces, no buffer zone of affluence, no surplus cushions to fall back on. And your family can't help you out; they're just hanging on themselves."</p>
        <p>For a teen-ager in the 1990's, sex has been contaminated by the threat of AIDS and drugs are associated with oblivion rather than delight. Every heat wave stokes fears about holes in the ozone layer. And, with an economy in which real income hasn't risen since 1973, they can look forward to moving back in with their parents after graduation and competing for low-paying service jobs (it's no wonder Mickey D.'s, a k a McDonald's, figures prominently in so many rap songs). The future seems circumscribed, abstemious. And a self-indulgent megalomaniac like Axl Rose or a latter-day wild-eyed romantic like Perry Farrell of Jane's Addiction draws envious crowds; at least somebody's having a good time.</p>
        <p>Earlier outlets for frustrations have been shut off. Over the last decade, as soundbites and spin-control have replaced substantive discussion of issues, many young people have become convinced that politics is hopelessly out of their control; a survey showed that only 33 percent of 18-to-20-year-olds voted in the 1988 elections, down from 48 percent in 1972. On the job, if there is one, labor unions have taken an economic and ideological beating. So have other vestiges of collective action, which have been atomized by a decade of competitive greed and a revival of self-made-success myths. Struggling people are encouraged to believe they struggle alone.</p>
        <p>At the same time, advertising has helped convince people that they forge an identity through consumption, and that they can fill in that sense that something's missing with the right brand of running shoes or jeans or beer. Or an album.</p>
        <p>So people consume rage as entertainment; they plunk their money down, turn up the volume, and shout themselves hoarse. They shout Public Enemy's black nationalism, Slayer's ambivalent Satanism, Living Colour's warnings of environmental disaster, Nine Inch Nails' self-laceration, Anthrax's moral dialectics, Skid Row's triumphal machismo. For a little while, it feels like actual power -- until the music stops.  POP VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
