<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>7 Arrive With Soviets on Their Minds</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="460050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WHITNEY, CRAIG R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORBACHEV, MIKHAIL S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DA1E31F936A25754C0A967958260" item-length="1371" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>7 Arrive With Soviets on Their Minds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG R. WHITNEY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WHITNEY, CRAIG R</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, July 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Leaders of the seven largest industrialized democracies gathered here today for three days of talks that are expected to focus on ways of encouraging the Soviet Union to move to a market economy without much help from any of them.</p>
        <p>President Mikhail S. Gorbachev of the Soviet Union will present his latest plan for economic change to the leaders here on Wednesday afternoon. That meeting, sought by Mr. Gorbachev for two years, is a recognition of the interdependence of all the world's economies now that the cold war is over.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Leaders of the seven largest industrialized democracies gathered here today for three days of talks that are expected to focus on ways of encouraging the Soviet Union to move to a market economy without much help from any of them.</p>
        <p>President Mikhail S. Gorbachev of the Soviet Union will present his latest plan for economic change to the leaders here on Wednesday afternoon. That meeting, sought by Mr. Gorbachev for two years, is a recognition of the interdependence of all the world's economies now that the cold war is over.</p>
        <p>But a 23-page letter that Mr. Gorbachev sent to all the summit participants last week gave them little reason to believe that he is going to present the kind of detailed, step-by-step plan that could draw aid from Western financial institutions, officials of several countries said today.</p>
        <p>United States officials dismissed the letter as a vague "circular," and one economist said, "It's clear on the aim, but not on the means of getting there." Others said it now appears that it might take decades rather than years for the Soviet Union to switch to a market economy.  Letting Gorbachev Have His Say</p>
        <p>"I think it would be courteous to hear what he says," the host of the summit meeting, Prime Minister John Major of Britain, said today after seeing Prime Minister Brian Mulroney of Canada.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mulroney told reporters, "I don't believe you will see either miracles or blank checks."</p>
        <p>President Bush, who is to meet separately with Mr. Gorbachev on Wednesday, flew in this evening from Paris after talks with President Francois Mitterrand of France and joined Mr. Major for dinner at 10 Downing Street.</p>
        <p>How to respond to Soviet plans for economic change is only one of the pressing issues that will be on the table when the leaders of the United States, Britain, Canada, France, Germany, Italy and Japan -- plus the representative of the European Community -- begin their talks Monday afternoon in Lancaster House, near St. James's Palace.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has been consulting with allies on ways of insuring the destruction of Iraq's capacity to build nuclear weapons as required under United Nations cease-fire resolutions.</p>
        <p>The summit participants are unlikely to endorse military strikes, officials of several countries said, but they could agree on a statement opposing the lifting of United Nations sanctions against Iraq until it complies with all Security Council resolutions connected with its occupation of Kuwait.</p>
        <p>Mr. Major wants the summit participants to back a proposal by the British, Americans and Japanese for a United Nations register of arms sales, which would be aimed at preventing countries like Iraq from amassing vast stocks of offensive weapons. Iraq has successfully played international suppliers off against each other in the past.</p>
        <p>The threat of civil war in Yugoslavia will also be on the minds of the leaders. And Mr. Major, who is presiding over his first summit meeting, wants the heads of government to pledge to attend the international conference on global warming in Rio de Janeiro next year, and to push negotiators toward a a new worldwide trade treaty by the end of this year. Soviets Point to Difficulties</p>
        <p>Some Soviet economists working in London in advance of Mr. Gorbachev's arrival emphasized the difficulty of moving to a market economy while the existing Communist-run system is rapidly deteriorating and people are anxious about scarce supplies of food and consumer goods.</p>
        <p>"In the political sphere, we've made tremendous progress," said Leonid A. Abalkin, a Soviet economist who helped draft Mr. Gorbachev's letter. "But in the economic sphere things remain where they were five or six years ago. The Soviet Union itself has to do the bulk of the work of change."</p>
        <p>He acknowledged that Mr. Gorbachev's latest plan is the 10th one he has reviewed, and that none has been put into action.</p>
        <p>Grigory A. Yavlinsky, who worked with Mr. Gorbachev over the weekend and has been urging him to adopt elements of a radical plan backed by professors at Harvard and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, decided not to come to the summit meeting, a Harvard official said. The official said Mr. Yavlinsky had not explained whether he was forgoing the meeting because Mr. Gorbachev had not gone as far as he wanted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abalkin said the letter from Mr. Gorbachev outlined Soviet plans to privatize 80 percent of the country's light industry by the end of 1992. He acknowledged that Soviet heavy industry, which is mainly related to the military, would take longer. The Western leaders are expected to demand the rapid conversion of plants to civilian use as proof of Moscow's intention to make fundamental changes in the economy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Major, like Mr. Bush and the Japanese Prime Minister, Toshiki Kaifu, whom he also met here today, is skeptical about the usefulness of large financial aid to the Soviet Union while the uncertainty continues.</p>
        <p>"We are very concerned to insure that not only the Soviets pass the legislation for economic reform, but they actually implement the legislation so that the economic reform itself can actually come about," Mr. Major said.</p>
        <p>Germany has provided or pledged $31 billion worth of aid to the Soviet Union over the last year in exchange for Moscow's assent to German unification. The German Chancellor, Helmut Kohl, said in an interview released today that he would argue that helping the Soviet Union to introduce democracy and a market economy would be in the West's interest.</p>
        <p>But "the Germans obviously can't do everything," he told the paper Frankfurter Allgemeine. "Our resources are limited. We have no cash cow." Advice Instead of Money</p>
        <p>Instead of cash, the summit participants are expected to offer the Soviet Union a form of association with the International Monetary Fund. That would enable Moscow to receive technical advice on making the ruble convertible, getting inflation under control and freeing prices on domestic goods.</p>
        <p>"If anybody is looking for anything dramatic in London, they'll be disappointed," one American official said. "But if the Soviet Union comes forward with a real plan, and it's clearly thought through, and lays out a timetable and then keeps to it, I think there will be a response on the part of the West to attempt to underpin it."</p>
        <p>Whatever they decide about the Soviet Union, the Western leaders will seek in the declarations they issue on Wednesday to offer firm support for continuing the flow of aid and capital to Eastern Europe. Most Eastern European countries have gone much further than the Soviet Union in adopting free-market reforms.  THE DOINGS IN LONDON</p>
        <p>TODAY</p>
        <p>Economic summit meetings begin this afternoon at Lancaster House.</p>
        <p>Dinner and the Ceremony of the Keys tonight at the Tower of London. TOMORROW</p>
        <p>Summit meetings continue at Lancaster House.</p>
        <p>Dinner, musical entertainment and laser show with music tonightat Buckingham Palace.</p>
        <p>President Mikhail S. Gorbachev of the Soviet Union arrives at Harrington House, the Soviet Ambassador's residence on Kensington Palace Gardens, later that night.  WEDNESDAY</p>
        <p>Last day of summit meetings at Lancaster House.</p>
        <p>President Bush meets with Mr. Gorbachev over lunch at Winfield House, the United States Ambassador's residence, where Mr. Bush is staying, followed by a news conference.</p>
        <p>Leaders of the seven economic summit nations meet with Mr. Gorbachev in the afternoon at Lancaster House, followed by a news conference with Prime Minister John Major of Britain and Mr. Gorbachev.</p>
        <p>Working dinner with Mr. Gorbachev in the evening at 10 Downing Street, the Prime Minister's residence.  THURSDAY</p>
        <p>Economic summit meeting participants leave London. President Bush leaves London in the morning for visits to Greece and Turkey, before returning to Washington on Monday, July 22.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gorbachev meets with Mr. Major all day at Downing Street.</p>
        <p>In the evening, they go to the Royal Opera House at Covent Garden for the first act of Rossini's "La Cenerentola." FRIDAY</p>
        <p>Mr. Gorbachev meets the British Labor Party opposition leader, Neil Kinnock, and former Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher before departing in the late morning.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
