<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Theater; A History Of the World From Eden To Zaloom</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="414349"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUSSOW, MEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ZALOOM, PAUL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MY CIVILIZATION (SHOW)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DC1331F933A25752C0A967958260" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Theater; A History Of the World From Eden To Zaloom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MEL GUSSOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GUSSOW, MEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To create his theater, all that Paul Zaloom needs is a stage, himself as actor -- and enough trash to fill a month's quota at a recycling center.  In Mr. Zaloom's dextrous hands, the detritus of consumerism is converted into artful subjects for satire. One can imagine him wheeling a cart through a supermarket, shopping for visual puns and metaphors. The result, as demonstrated in his new show, "My Civilization" (at Dance Theater Workshop), is puppetry of a high political priority.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To create his theater, all that Paul Zaloom needs is a stage, himself as actor -- and enough trash to fill a month's quota at a recycling center.  In Mr. Zaloom's dextrous hands, the detritus of consumerism is converted into artful subjects for satire. One can imagine him wheeling a cart through a supermarket, shopping for visual puns and metaphors. The result, as demonstrated in his new show, "My Civilization" (at Dance Theater Workshop), is puppetry of a high political priority.</p>
        <p>The title piece, the first of three monologues, is nothing less than a solipsistic history of the world, from protoplasm through the Garden of Eden and on to the life of Mr. Zaloom, all in 30 minutes. Using an overhead slide projector and an assortment of liquids and solids, both syrupy and spidery, which he sloshes and manipulates on transparent surfaces, he takes us on a jaunty tour back to the beginning of time.</p>
        <p>As these various items are orchestrated into mysterious and comic patterns on screen, he delivers a demented, nonstop play-by-play description of civilization and his insecure place in it. The Zaloom of "My Civilization" is besieged by forces beyond his, or our, ken. Wherever he turns, something is testing his mettle, whether it is a self-corruptive society or unpredictable natural occurrences (a fork suddenly jumps on screen to simulate a bolt of lightning).</p>
        <p>The monologue is a kind of satiric acid rain, insidious and damaging to the accepted order of things. His attitude as author and director is one of abashment, as in his suggestion that either he is going through an early midlife crisis or, as usual, he is indulging in cheap special effects. These effects may be cheap in price, but they are very special. I know of no other performance artist who is working in this idiosyncratic mode.</p>
        <p>In his second sketch, "Phood," he attacks foolishness and faddishness in food, a favorite target of this consumer advocate who is ever ready to warn us not to eat before analyzing content. Employing photographs and other promotional material, he hangs the food industry by its own labels while he pretends to lecture a conference of like-minded individuals who care less about nutrition than about profits.</p>
        <p>At the top of his indictment is the use of artificial ingredients -- the reconstituted made to look like the real thing; additives that preserve a product to perpetuity, unless they happen to explode. There is no short shelf life in this world. Everything lasts forever, or at least until it kills us.</p>
        <p>Having disarmed his audience with laughter, Mr. Zaloom then unveils his finale, a sketch entitled "Meanwhile," a shorter version of which was seen earlier this season in the Dangerous Ideas marathon. Somehow he mixes foreign policy with the savings and loan scandal and the controversy over public support of the arts. Dashing from cluttered table to table like a crazed table tennis player, he animates a tag sale of objects and becomes a quick-change puppetmaster.</p>
        <p>Naturally, some of the remarks are too off the cuff, just as some of the assault moves from wryness to a lesser plane of whimsy, but enough of the humor is derisively on target. Mr. Zaloom's mind and funnybone are synchronized, especially when he is dealing with questions of endangerment to the arts.</p>
        <p>Here comes the National Endowment for the Arts, as represented by a football with a pipe in its mouth, equivocating about awarding grants to performance artists (the grants are frugally distributed from a family-size tin of peanuts -- and are then reclaimed). Private patronage is a tall, thin brand name cigarette and the Internal Revenue Service by two giant screws, marching alongside a large can of squiggly worms. That Senator from North Carolina is personified by a big prop foot and the artists themselves are small tomatoes, easily squashable.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Zaloom's performance, there is a quality of child's play, but it is most inventive gamesmanship. In the years since he began performing, he has grown as a clown and as a social commentator. He has become an ecological antidote to the poisons and pollutants in everyday life. My Civilization</p>
        <p>Researched, written, designed and performed by Paul Zaloom; directed and with additional writing by Donny Osman; lighting design, William Shipley Schaffner. Presented by Dance Theater Workshop, at the Bessie Schonberg Theater, 219 West 19th Street.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
