<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blind on Antarctica</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="456337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DA1F38F933A05755C0A967958260" item-length="434" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blind on Antarctica</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The now-you-see-him, now-you-don't "environment President" has struck again. Last year President Bush promised Congress that he would press for a long-term ban on commercial activity in Antarctica. Last weekend he allowed his negotiators to reject such a ban -- disappointing America's allies and embarrassing himself.</p>
        <p>At issue was a painfully drafted protocol to the Antarctic Treaty that would prohibit mining and drilling in the world's largest wilderness for 50 years. The ban could then be lifted only if all 26 nations with full voting rights concurred.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The now-you-see-him, now-you-don't "environment President" has struck again. Last year President Bush promised Congress that he would press for a long-term ban on commercial activity in Antarctica. Last weekend he allowed his negotiators to reject such a ban -- disappointing America's allies and embarrassing himself.</p>
        <p>At issue was a painfully drafted protocol to the Antarctic Treaty that would prohibit mining and drilling in the world's largest wilderness for 50 years. The ban could then be lifted only if all 26 nations with full voting rights concurred.</p>
        <p>But when treaty members assembled in Madrid, the United States unveiled a surprise counterproposal: At the end of 50 years, any nation that wished to amend the ban could unilaterally withdraw from the agreement if the other nations failed to approve the amendment within three years.</p>
        <p>This "walkout" clause angered not only other delegates but conservationists who had gathered to celebrate the triumph of consensus and common sense. The words "Bush Administration" and "environment," said a Greenpeace spokesman, "shouldn't even appear in the same sentence."</p>
        <p>A bit overwrought, perhaps; Mr. Bush occasionally acts like the "environment President" he promised to be. But in this case he allowed himself to be persuaded that the protocol threatened America's energy supply and its sovereignty.</p>
        <p>That is an empty posture with no serious constituency beyond a few people in the Administration. The oil companies have yet to show any interest in disturbing Antarctica's inhospitable terrain. And if left alone, Antarctica, whose frigid waters absorb carbon dioxide efficiently, will continue to function as an indispensable "sink" for greenhouse gases, a priceless scientific laboratory and a key link in the world's food chain.</p>
        <p>The U.S. position also threatens the principle of unanimity that has held the treaty together since 1961. The treaty, which prohibits nuclear testing and military bases, has been sustained partly by the belief that if everyone goes along, nobody gains unfair advantage -- and nobody loses.</p>
        <p>It's unlikely to happen, but there may come a time when the world's energy needs require a fresh look. The treaty members might thus seek a reasonable compromise that would forsake the principle of unanimity while keeping the threshold for approval very high.</p>
        <p>But Washington's insistence on the right to walk away from any agreement is not reasonable. Any significant invasion of Antarctica will have profound global consequences; any decision to do so ought not to be taken lightly or unilaterally.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
