<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Field Is Still Open, Time Wanes And, as in '88, the Name Gore Arises</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="432709"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="WASHINGTON TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TONER, ROBIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, ALBERT JR (SEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D6123CF936A15750C0A967958260" item-length="1566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Field Is Still Open, Time Wanes And, as in '88, the Name Gore Arises</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN TONER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TONER, ROBIN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fire in the belly is a rare commodity among Democrats these days.</p>
        <p>Senator Sam Nunn of Georgia says he most definitely lacks it. Senator Lloyd Bentsen of Texas has left many Democrats wondering. Even Representative Richard A. Gephardt, the House majority leader and a man with a clear case of Presidential ambition, seems to be trying to dampen speculation about his plans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fire in the belly is a rare commodity among Democrats these days.</p>
        <p>Senator Sam Nunn of Georgia says he most definitely lacks it. Senator Lloyd Bentsen of Texas has left many Democrats wondering. Even Representative Richard A. Gephardt, the House majority leader and a man with a clear case of Presidential ambition, seems to be trying to dampen speculation about his plans.</p>
        <p>The party, as a whole, seems to be struggling to work up its enthusiasm for a Presidential campaign against a popular incumbent coming off a popular war. In such a climate, ambition can seem a virtue and unblinking confidence on an unlined face is not automatically dismissed as hubris. And Senator Al Gore stands out.</p>
        <p>Fire in the belly? "I guess because I ran before, I will always be suspect of having that fire," says the Democrat from Tennessee. "And I will not deny that." No Decision Yet</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, whose 1988 campaign for the Democratic nomination sputtered out in the New York primary, says he has not made a decision on whether to seek the Presidency in 1992. But the interest is clearly there, and some Democrats argue that the moment is ripe for the 42-year-old Senator.</p>
        <p>The field is virtually wide open. The party is slightly panicked as the weeks go by and the most visible standard-bearers are still George S. McGovern, the 1972 nominee who lost 49 states, and Paul E. Tsongas, the former Senator from Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>What particularly intrigues the oddsmakers in Democratic politics is a simple fact: Mr. Gore is inoculated on the one issue that has tormented his party in recent weeks. He was one of just 10 Democratic Senators to vote in favor of the resolution authorizing war in the Persian Gulf. Almost every other potential Democratic contender voted or spoke against it.</p>
        <p>As Carter Eskew, a Democratic political consultant and friend of Mr. Gore, puts it: Mr. Gore could run "without the constant noise, the nyah-nyah-nyah-nyah-nyah, on the gulf."</p>
        <p>No one knows how long the Persian Gulf issue will last in the Presidential campaign. No one suggests it is a rationale for a Presidential candidacy. But for now, at least, the issue that has devastated men like Mr. Nunn has shed an attractive new light on Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>"I think Al is positioned extremely well," said Nathan Landow, chairman of the Maryland Democratic Party and leader of a group of financial contributors who rallied behind Mr. Gore in 1988.</p>
        <p>The question, for many of Mr. Gore's supporters, is whether a candidacy in 1992 would further his goal of being President one day. If an ambitious young Democrat won the nomination but lost the election against Mr. Bush, as is widely expected, would that candidate be repudiated by his party? Or would he emerge well-positioned for 1996, a tested warrior for a grateful party?</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, of course, does not mention such tactical considerations when asked about the factors he weighs. Sipping tea in his office, surrounded by mementoes of a life in politics, including his own "Doonesbury" story line spoofing his privileged background and youthful chutzpah through the character "Prince Albert," Mr. Gore begins with a disclaimer -- that he does not seek to use this interview to sketch campaign themes or advance a candidacy.</p>
        <p>"I have not yet reached the stage where I'm going to make the decision on whether I'm going to run," he says. "But I have very strong beliefs about what this country needs to do, what we as a people need to do."</p>
        <p>He recites the Democratic litany of unmet needs. "On the side of running," he says, "I think this country is feeling the Reagan-Bush years and needs to approach domestic problems like the economy, competitiveness, the environment, crime, with a sense of determination and with leadership and with 'the vision thing.' "</p>
        <p>On the other side of the scales, he says, are personal considerations. Having run before, he says, "It's a lot harder for me to deceive myself about what it really means to make a two-year campaign for President. The last time I fooled myself into thinking that I would see my family one or two days a week, or that the children could take turns coming out on the road. I don't believe that now, because I know that, when the campaign starts, you almost have to say goodbye to your wife and children for the duration." Concerns for Family</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore and his wife, Tipper, who gained her own prominence as a critic of obscenity in rock music lyrics, have three daughters, ages 12, 13 and 17, and a son, Albert 3d.</p>
        <p>"My son, who is the youngest in the family, is only eight years old, and he's already been through one Presidential campaign, and more," the Senator said. Two years ago, while Mr. Gore was attending a Baltimore Orioles baseball game with his son, the boy broke away and was hit by a car. His injuries were serious, his recovery long.</p>
        <p>For all of that, Mr. Gore has long shown all of the symptoms of a common senatorial syndrome: Sooner or later, senators look in a mirror and see a President.</p>
        <p>The Harvard-educated son of a prominent Senator, Albert Gore Sr., Mr. Gore crossed that threshold at the age of 39. He jumped into the 1988 campaign for the Democratic nomination, positioning himself as the Southern candidate in a year when the South was supposed to play a critical role in choosing the nominee. It did not.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore careered from message to message, theme to theme, from Southern populism to Gary Hart-style "new generation" politics. He offered himself as the Democrat who was tough on foreign policy, the favorite son of a proud South, the Democrat who was willing to confront the Rev. Jesse Jackson.</p>
        <p>He did well on Super Tuesday, the round of Southern primaries on March 8, but his campaign seemed to have no coherent strategy for the day after, when the race rolled back into the North. He withdrew after finishing a distant third in New York.</p>
        <p>"He was a very young guy running for President for the first time," said one veteran Democratic strategist.</p>
        <p>His critics, and there were many, said his campaign was all about positioning and a search for short-term tactical advantage. Mr. Gore still bristles at the notion that his national security stance was a matter of campaign positioning: "I had a career in the House for eight years and four years in the Senate before I ran for President."</p>
        <p>But he adds, with a slight laugh, "I've begun to suspect that I made some mistakes in that campaign. And if that hypothesis is proven out, one of them might be that I didn't do a very good job of articulating and staying with the core beliefs that motivated my decision to run."</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore also offers some self-deprecating humor to defuse another charge from the 1988 campaign. "The story I remember from that campaign is: How can you tell Al Gore from a room full of Secret Service agents? And the answer is: He's the stiff one."</p>
        <p>The political damage from his 1988 Presidential campaign was less extensive than many predicted. He retired his debt quickly. He handily won re-election to the Senate last fall. While his rhetoric in New York was hot -- he said of Mr. Jackson, "We're not choosing a preacher, we're choosing a President," and his most prominent supporter in New York, Edward I. Koch, who was then Mayor, denounced Mr. Jackson repeatedly -- Mr. Jackson says today, "We have a good rapport, mutual respect." Experience Will Count</p>
        <p>Democratic strategists say the experience of a past Presidential campaign is invaluable. "What Gore has this time is the greatest single asset someone brings to running for President, and that is that he's run before," one strategist said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore says: "When I run again, whenever that is, assuming that I do, I will spend a lot more time focusing on the priorities that I believe important day in and day out, and a lot less time running from one event to another, keeping in the traveling roadshow that develops in these things."</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has kept working on his pet causes, particularly the environment and global warming. He is writing a book, which he declines to discuss, and has continued to write opinion pieces and guest columns.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's position on the gulf war vote has made him one of the few Democrats able to take the offensive in recent weeks, as Republicans began to hammer the Democrats for their votes. He took the floor of the Senate this month and declared, "Shame on those Republican operatives for playing politics with American lives, for the disservice they do to the brave American soldiers who made the ultimate sacrifice for their country."</p>
        <p>He has begun calling, as he did this morning on the NBC News television program "Meet the Press," for an effort on domestic ills to match the American effort in the gulf, an echo of the old Democratic tradition of aggressive foreign and domestic policy.</p>
        <p>"The world as a whole has chosen, with few exceptions, democracy and capitalism as the wave of the future," he said. "And we need to come out and say, here's how we perfect those. But the Democratic Party, in addition, says, let's fight for those values here at home -- our job isn't finished yet."</p>
        <p>The dance is beginning again.</p>
        <p>"Let's go through a little ritual," said Garrick Utley, the show's host. "I'm going to ask you a question and you're going to give me a straight answer, right? Are you going to run for President?"</p>
        <p>Al Gore smiled and said, "I haven't decided yet."  WASHINGTON TALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
