<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Black Sea, Slow Choking By Pollutants</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="489150"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BLACK SEA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BULGARIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ROMANIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">TURKEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMONS, MARLISE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bulgaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bulgaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDF113DF937A15752C1A967958260" item-length="1688" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Black Sea, Slow Choking By Pollutants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMONS, MARLISE</byline>
      <dateline>VARNA, Bulgaria</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For centuries, the Black Sea produced dolphin skins and caviar and fish so plentiful that no one thought such bounty could ever end. But now this ancient highway between Europe and Asia is suffering extensive changes, the proportions of which are only just becoming fully known.</p>
        <p>All along its 2,500-mile coastline, fishing boats sit in port, idled by the collapse of sturgeon, mackerel, anchovy and other commercial fisheries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For centuries, the Black Sea produced dolphin skins and caviar and fish so plentiful that no one thought such bounty could ever end. But now this ancient highway between Europe and Asia is suffering extensive changes, the proportions of which are only just becoming fully known.</p>
        <p>All along its 2,500-mile coastline, fishing boats sit in port, idled by the collapse of sturgeon, mackerel, anchovy and other commercial fisheries.</p>
        <p>Bathing beaches near Constanta in Romania and Odessa in the Ukraine have been closed for the last two summers because of chemical pollution and the smelly froth of algae blooms. Now scientists warn that this inland sea is rapidly losing its oxygen and its ability to purge itself. Specialists Meet</p>
        <p>The Black Sea and its unusual biological traits, which are still little understood, have long fascinated scientists.  This year, the end of Communism permitted specialists from the whole region to meet and debate the Black Sea's problems freely for the first time at a conference in this Bulgarian city.</p>
        <p>But political turmoil in the Soviet Union is holding up a new international agreement to stop the marine pollution already banned off other coasts, and ships from many nations still clean out their oil tanks, flush their ballast and dump loads of dangerous sludge and toxic waste into the Black Sea.</p>
        <p>Biologists also worry about the growing tide of human, farm and industrial discharge pouring in from the four Black Sea countries -- Bulgaria, Romania, the Soviet Union and Turkey. Newly published surveys show that every town, industry and mine along its shores uses this land-trapped water as dump and sewer.</p>
        <p>More than 60 rivers and streams deliver waste from a catchment area of 160 million people. The four largest are the Danube, the Don, the Dnieper and the Dniester, and they arrive here after sweeping through a region now recognized as one of the most polluted in the world.</p>
        <p>Scientists say that every year these rivers carry many tons of toxic materials -- oil, lead, phosporous, nitrates, chromium, cadmium and others.  Fallout From Chernobyl</p>
        <p>In spring, when the melting snow washes the land, the river waters from the north, especially the Dnieper, carry radioactive fallout from the 1986 nuclear accident at Chernobyl.</p>
        <p>"I know of no other inland sea under such pressure," said Stanislav Konovalov, director of the Soviet Institute for Biology of the Southern Seas at Sebastopol. "This is much more degraded than the Baltic."</p>
        <p>Biologists like Mr. Konovalov who have spent much of their lives exploring the Black Sea say they are shocked and surprised by the collapse of its fisheries and other extraordinary changes in its ecosystems.</p>
        <p>At Vinizi, a small community of summer houses and fishermen on the Bulgarian coast, Atanas Stefanov remembers the time that he and his father hunted dolphins and seals to sell the fat and the skins.</p>
        <p>"Our biggest year, we shot 1,024 dolphins," said Mr. Stefanov, who has been going to sea for 55 of his 68 years. "That was 1947. Everybody did it. Of course it's forbidden now." Only Little Fish Now</p>
        <p>For much of their lives, these fishermen have caught three-foot-long, caviar-laden sturgeon and loads of fat horse mackerel. "Today we get these little things," Mr. Stefanov lamented, showing a pot full of small scad.</p>
        <p>Aboard the Bulgarian research vessel Akademik, Hinko Klisarov said that the crew still spots dolphins, but that the other mammals, the seals, have disappeared altogether. And like creatures in a science-fiction tale, some jellyfish are geting bigger and bigger. "They are now appearing at 30 pounds or more," he said.</p>
        <p>Yuvenaly Zaitsev, a Soviet biologist based in Sevastopol, argues that the sturgeon were finished by overfishing. The total catch, he said, dropped from more than a thousand tons per year in 1950 to less than 10 tons two years ago. Worse than that, he said, of the 26 commercial fish species abundant in 1970, he said, today only five are left in commercial quantities.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zaitsev says a proliferation of jellyfish has caused part of the problem because they eat the eggs and the larvae of other fish. A new arrival is a plague of ribbed jellyfish, a recent intruder that is found on the Atlantic coast of North America and probably arrived here in bilge water.  Anchovy Fleets Paralyzed</p>
        <p>Whatever the cause of the changes, they are far-reaching. Some two million people live directly or indirectly off fisheries. On Turkey's 700-mile Black Sea coast, fishermen have been hit hardest, and anchovy fleets are paralyzed at Trebizond, Sinop, Samsun and other ports. The Ankara Government says that between 1987 and 1989, the Turkish Black Sea catch dropped almost 95 percent, from 340,000 tons to less than 15,000 tons, and it has declared a moratorium on anchovy fishing.</p>
        <p>"Nobody really knows why all this is happening," said Umit Unluata, an oceanographer at the Turkish Institute of Marine Sciences. "It may be a combination of overfishing, pollution, climate change and shifts in the food chain."</p>
        <p>Geologists say the greatest change in these waters happened some 8,000 years ago, when the Black Sea was still a fresh-water lake but the sea level rose and the Mediterranean spilled through the Bosporus.</p>
        <p>As salt water rushed in, geologists believe, it killed the life adapted to fresh water, and this produced the mass of hydrogen sulfide, which remains trapped in the deep waters beneath the thin surface lid of oxygen.  Nine-Tenths Lifeless</p>
        <p>Only the top 100 yards or so is oxygen-bearing water, and more than nine-tenths has such high levels of hydrogen sulfide that it is lifeless.</p>
        <p>"It's really a geological freak," said David Aubrey, a senior scientist at the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution in Massachusetts, which organized the first large international Black Sea conference in October in Varna. "If you put a piece of metal in deep enough, it will come out black. If you turned the Black Sea over, it would smell of rotten eggs."</p>
        <p>"In this fragile setting," Dr. Aubrey added, "man has now created an environmental catastrophe."</p>
        <p>The mass of hydrogen sulfide and methane is sealed off by the lid of oxygenated water. Scientists say that if the sea "turned over" because of an earthquake or a chemical upheaval -- something that they call unlikely but possible -- the escaping gasses could kill people on the shore.  Sea Receives Less Water</p>
        <p>Modern change began 30 years ago with the frantic industrialization along the rivers in Easten Europe that brought toxic chemicals, detergents and fertilizers. Soviet dams and irrigation projects have diverted so much river water that by Soviet estimates, the Black Sea is today receiving almost one-fifth less fresh water and becoming more salty.</p>
        <p>Some scientists believe that the poisonous hydrogen sulfide is welling up, reducing the oxygen layer and thus causing fish kills. But others blame the detergents and fertilizers.</p>
        <p>In the estuary of the Danube, a 70-mile-wide wetland of channels, lakes and swamps, the algae blooms have grown wildly in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>"By the end of the summer, much of the delta is covered in spume," said Mircea Staras, a Romanian biologist. Mr. Staras lives in Tulcia, close to the mouth of the Danube. "When the algae die, everything else is killed," said Mr. Staras, "even the underwater plants. This was an important spawning ground for sturgeon, for carp, for pike. We lost all the big fish." 'An Unexpected Bonus'</p>
        <p>Radioactive fallout from Chernobyl is being monitored by scientists. They say the signals given off by particles like cesium 137 and strontium are traceable and therefore allow monitors to see how pollutants behave, how long they stay on the surface, how fast organisms take them up and how the Black Sea mixes and circulates.</p>
        <p>"It's an unexpected bonus," said Gennadi Polykarpov, a Soviet monitor. "The fallout is a problem in the Dnieper water because it is used for irrigation, but it is not a health hazard in the Black Sea."</p>
        <p>As awareness of the degradation grows, hopes of reversing it are running up against the reality that the Black Sea countries do not have the means or the political will to change their practices in the short run.</p>
        <p>"Even if we stopped all the pollution as if by magic," Mr. Zaitsev said, "it would be impossible to go back to the 1950's. Nature has its own laws."</p>
        <p>Cleaning up many areas would cost a fortune. The large and handsome bay at Burgas, Bulgaria, was a popular beach resort until two decades ago, when chemical plants were built on its shores. Today the bay is off-limits to bathers, and water and air here look equally greasy and opaque with contaminants.</p>
        <p>Farther south, near Chernomoritz, researchers have found hot spots of uranium radiation along the inlets and beaches that they believe was spilled by a nearby mine. Local guesthouse owners, though, have repeatedly taken down signs warning people to keep away due to radioactivity. They say the signs ruined their business.</p>
        <p>But the scientists at the Black Sea conference agreed that even if a cleanup would be too costly or too difficult in the short run, a huge effort should be made to stop the sea from getting worse. A convention to diminish pollution of the Danube, which is fed with sewage and waste from eight nations, was agreed upon in August. But most of the eight nations have not yet signed it.</p>
        <p>A convention to protect the Black Sea has been in the works for two years. While the Soviet military had first held it up, a new complication now is that the Ukraine, Russia and Georgia, caught up in their own domestic political turmoil, will probably have to debate and sign the agreement separately.</p>
        <p>"The two conventions are absolutely essential for any future action," Dr. Aubrey said. "They will help change legislation in the different countries, and they can trigger foreign aid."</p>
        <p>"A new legal framework will be a quantum leap," said Lawrence Mee, of the United Nations Environmental Program. "It made a tremendous difference in cutting back pollution in the Baltic Sea. It showed us that the law can work."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
