<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why the Boom Went Bust</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="416395"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHERNOW, RON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MALABRE, ALFRED L JR</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WITHIN OUR MEANS (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DB1139F933A15752C0A967958260" item-length="1026" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why the Boom Went Bust</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ron Chernow; Ron Chernow is the author of "The House of Morgan," which was awarded the 1990 National Book Award for nonfiction.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHERNOW, RON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITHIN OUR MEANS  The Struggle for Economic Recovery After a Reckless Decade. By Alfred L. Malabre Jr. 167 pp. New York: Random House. $21.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITHIN OUR MEANS  The Struggle for Economic Recovery After a Reckless Decade. By Alfred L. Malabre Jr. 167 pp. New York: Random House. $21.</p>
        <p>No other nation on earth is such an easy sucker for a speculative boom as the United States. Having created a culture of salesmen, small-town boosters and consumers, we are natural denizens of stock exchanges and gambling dens, gulled by our own public relations. But we soon repent of our prodigal ways and gnash our teeth in lamentation. Within a year of the 1929 crash, we were engaged in a national orgy of self-flagellation. The days of easy living, babbittry and bootleg gin soon passed into stoic calls for thrift and sacrifice.</p>
        <p>In "Within Our Means," Alfred L. Malabre Jr. surveys the economic sins of the 1980's and outlines the stations of atonement. Breast-beating has arrived with a vengeance. "If self-indulgence marked the 1980s," he writes, "increased concern about the future seemed the watchword of the new decade." He sees the United States attempting to "regain competitive stature through the neglected avenues of hard work and sacrifice." Time for sackcloth and ashes, folks.</p>
        <p>As the economics editor of The Wall Street Journal and the author of a previous book entitled "Beyond Our Means," Mr. Malabre is ideally positioned to bring us this news. In his skinny front-page columns for The Journal, he was our foremost chronicler of the longest peacetime expansion in American history. He stalked the Reagan boom as doggedly as</p>
        <p>paparazzi</p>
        <p>tail Madonna. For economics buffs, it was a great luxury to have a column devoted to the profile of an expansion.</p>
        <p>Here, Mr. Malabre provides a crushing list of problems that accumulated with prosperity. He doesn't stick to the usual economic suspects: lopsided budgets, exorbitant debt, scanty savings and gargantuan consumption. We must also wade through a Spenglerian catalogue of other ailments neglected by the Reaganites, from AIDS and the hole in the ozone layer to the Exxon Valdez oil spill and crack babies. By about page 10, some readers may find suicide a preferable alternative to completing this book. But if you need a brief polemic to flip onto the stoop of the boastful Reaganite next door, "Within Our Means" should do the trick.</p>
        <p>As a born Cassandra and registered Democrat, I found myself clucking in sympathy as Mr. Malabre proceeded with his grim diatribe. I checked my watch darkly as he informed me that the budget deficit was rising at a rate of $900,000 per minute and that the surviving savings and loans were losing money at the rate of $3 million per hour. I groaned with horror when he forecast a nightmarish deficit of $640 billion at the depth of the recession. I nodded at the injustice of a country so rich in stretch limousines and homeless people. All this Mr. Malabre documents with a stupefying diligence.</p>
        <p>But though I share his bearish forecast and much of his indignation, I found myself increasingly displeased with his approach. I am partial to nice paragraphs of English prose and balk at airless compendiums of facts. Many of Mr. Malabre's pages offer one numbing statistic per sentence. I wish he had framed his abundant facts with an interesting narrative or arresting argument. I don't find the notion of living "within our means" a powerful or original theme, however merited. Ditto for his exhortation that "the situation cries out for bold leadership in the White House and Congress." And his jeremiad about the budget deficit isn't so much wrong as painfully familiar.</p>
        <p>In "Within Our Means," Ronald Reagan and his brand of economics become a shorthand explanation for every ill. George Bush comes off as little more than a weaselly Reagan clone, deaf to the arguments that speak to Mr. Malabre with thunderous conviction. (A characteristic device of the book is to cite a problem, then conclude, more or less, with the finger-wagging refrain "Still, Bush seemed unconcerned.") Mr. Malabre simply rides his hobbyhorse too hard. Many problems that upset him -- from drugs to crime to illiteracy -- didn't originate with Mr. Reagan or Mr. Bush, even if they didn't help matters. Greater fairness would have strengthened the polemic.</p>
        <p>Many of us prefer to believe in Presidential omnipotence when it comes to managing the economy. Yet in retrospect, much of the drift that Jimmy Carter was blamed for would have plagued any President grappling with rising oil prices and global inflation. Similarly, in the 1980's, many things happened to the American economy other than President Reagan -- the globalization of financial markets, for example. The liquidity boom that fed the 1980's owed as much to Paul Volcker's Federal Reserve Board policies as to Ronald Reagan's tax cuts. The easy credit and low interest rates that followed Mr. Volcker's celebrated conquest of inflation led straight to leveraged buyouts, more permissive lending and manic deal making. Some type of Wall Street boom would have occurred even with Walter Mondale in the Oval Office. Where Mr. Reagan erred -- like his Republican predecessors in the 1920's -- was in steadily pumping high-octane tax cuts into a motor already dangerously souped up. And his Administration's disregard of speculative lending, costly takeovers and financial gamesmanship is a governmental scandal that will haunt us for years to come. The current fragility of our financial system is terrifying.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, Mr. Malabre offers a spartan regime of higher taxes, less spending on entitlement programs and more stringent regulation. He proposes a lengthy list of budget cuts, from reducing school lunch programs to paring down small-business loans, and another equally lengthy list for expanded spending, from recruiting an army of savings and loan investigators to repairing our decrepit highways. (At the last moment, Iraq's invasion of Kuwait made him modify his hopes for the "peace dividend.") Again, the lists are sound but not new. Mr. Malabre should have enunciated broad principles of budgetary reform instead of piling up details. By the end, he has not so much persuaded the reader as wrestled him, weary, to the ground.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
