<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Peril Reborn: Mercury in the Environment -- A special report.; Ancient Hazards of Mercury Re-Emerge</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="469428"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Special Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DB1039F935A1575BC0A967958260" item-length="2213" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Peril Reborn: Mercury in the Environment -- A special report.; Ancient Hazards of Mercury Re-Emerge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER,</byline>
      <dateline>DULUTH, Minn.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two decades after the Government thought the problem had been put to rest, mercury is accumulating in fish in thousands of lakes across the United States and Canada, poisoning wildlife and threatening human health.</p>
        <p>Twenty states, including New York and Connecticut, have warned people to limit or eliminate from their diets fish they catch in certain lakes because of dangerous levels of mercury. Canadian scientists have found elevated levels of mercury in fish caught in 95 percent of the lakes tested in Ontario.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two decades after the Government thought the problem had been put to rest, mercury is accumulating in fish in thousands of lakes across the United States and Canada, poisoning wildlife and threatening human health.</p>
        <p>Twenty states, including New York and Connecticut, have warned people to limit or eliminate from their diets fish they catch in certain lakes because of dangerous levels of mercury. Canadian scientists have found elevated levels of mercury in fish caught in 95 percent of the lakes tested in Ontario.</p>
        <p>Scientists say the principal source of contamination is rain containing traces of mercury from coal-burning power plants, municipal incinerators and smelters. Other contamination comes from lake and ocean sediments previously polluted by mercury.</p>
        <p>States and the Federal Government have taken almost no action to reduce releases of mercury, in part because recognition of the problem is recent -- and because Federal energy and state environmental policies are actually part of the problem.  Harm Comes to Animals</p>
        <p>There have been few studies of the extent to which Americans might have been harmed by mercury poisoning, and state health officials say there is no evidence yet of damage to human health in this country.</p>
        <p>But mercury has been confirmed as the cause of deaths of panthers and loons in Florida and is suspected in the reproductive failures seen in eagles, minks, otters and other animals in the Great Lakes region. Contamination is generally not an issue for store-bought fish, which do not come from the lakes most affected, the authorities say.</p>
        <p>"It's a very messy pollutant," said John Bachmann, an engineer in the Environmental Protection Agency's Office of Air Quality. "It's a liquid metal that becomes a gas even at mild temperatures. That makes it difficult to control. We need to know more."</p>
        <p>But state environmental officials and a top Government mercury researcher disagree, saying that enough is known to begin halting mercury's spread. Delays, they say, are a result not of inadequate information but of conflicts.</p>
        <p>Federal energy policy encourages power plants that burn coal, which contains small amounts of mercury. Meanwhile, the states, faced with dwindling landfill space, are encouraging construction of incinerators. Since mercury is used to make batteries, paints, electrical switches and hundreds of other products, incineration of these discarded items releases mercury.</p>
        <p>"Solving this problem means changing our ways and spending money to control emissions -- a lot of money," said Dr. Gary Glass, a chemist at the E.P.A. Environmental Research Laboratory here who is a leading Government researcher and has been studying mercury since 1987 with state support. "It's going to take a very focused effort to cut back on consumer products that contain mercury."</p>
        <p>The Edison Electric Institute, a trade group for utilities, estimated that power plants with equipment to remove mercury from emissions could cost $5 billion nationally. Incinerator builders say curbing mercury emissions could cost $10 million to $30 million per plant.</p>
        <p>Some steps, much less costly, are being taken. Disposal methods that keep discarded batteries and paint from incinerators help reduce mercury in the atmosphere. Battery manufacturers, concerned about possible new regulations, have cut the use of mercury to 250 tons in 1989, from almost 1,200 tons in 1984, the E.P.A. says. Last year, the agency outlawed mercury in interior latex paints.</p>
        <p>But there are still hundreds of millions of batteries, and many old paint cans. And wood that has been covered with latex paint containing mercury still emits mercury when burned.  From the Earth  Ancient Gift, Ancient Peril</p>
        <p>Mercury has been a valuable raw material from the earth's crust for 3,500 years and a recognized hazard for nearly as long. Romans used the bright red sulfide ore of mercury for pigments, and at least one Roman naturalist, Pliny, described how mercury miners died in large numbers.</p>
        <p>In the 19th century, fur that was used in the manufacture of felt hats was dipped in mercuric nitrate solution. Many felt workers absorbed so much mercury through their skin that they became known for slurred speech and uncontrollable shaking.</p>
        <p>In the 20th century, mercury's disinfecting ability make it indispensable to the paper and paint industry in controlling slimes and molds. Chemical companies incorporate mercury in some reactions as a catalyst. Historically, industrial plants poured their mercury waste into rivers or lakes, where it collected in sediments and passed up the food chain, from plankton to minnows to large fish to birds of prey and large mammals -- and human beings.  Tragedy in Japan</p>
        <p>In the 1950's and early 1960's, more than 100 people developed tremors, fell into comas and died in Minamata, Japan. Fish caught in Minamata Bay had mercury levels that measured an average of 11 one-thousandths of a gram for every kilogram (2.2 pounds), comparable to a speck of pepper on a 36-ounce steak. The F.D.A. considers eating a single meal of fish containing one-thousandth of a gram of mercury per kilogram to be dangerous, and bars commercial sales of fish that have more.</p>
        <p>The events in Minamata spurred a global investigation that yielded evidence in the 1960's of rising mercury levels in game fish caught in American waters. In 1972, Congress passed the Clean Water Act, requiring paper companies, smelters, paint factories and other plants to install equipment and prevent mercury from being released into water.</p>
        <p>Before the law, Minnesota sampled its rivers and found adult fish containing a mean mercury level of about one-thousandth of a gram per kilogram in their flesh -- the amount judged by the F.D.A. to be too dangerous. By the late 1970's the mean mercury levels in fish taken in Minnesota rivers dropped to 0.38 thousandths of a gram per kilogram, a level then considered safe.</p>
        <p>But prompted by reports from Sweden of persistent and widespread mercury contamination in fish caught in remote lakes in that country, the Minnesota Department of Health in the 1970's began sampling the state's lakes, particularly those along the wild border with Canada. In 1978, the agency identified mercury at levels of more than one-thousandth of a gram per kilogram in large walleye and northern pike caught in Crane Lake, 130 miles north of here and miles from any industry. The discovery prompted sampling by scientists in Minnesota, Wisconsin, Michigan and in Ontario, which turned up similarly high levels and spurred renewed efforts to identify the sources.  From the Skies  Not So Gentle Falls the Rain</p>
        <p>Scientists now believe they know the culprits. They say mercury is being swept into the upper atmosphere from cement and phosphate plants as well as power plants and incinerators. Mercury also is evaporating from contaminated lake and ocean sediments and falling back to earth as toxic rain.</p>
        <p>"There is a lot of very nasty, unpleasant stuff in rain coming at us from everywhere," said Dr. Terry A. Haines, a fishery research biologist for the United States Fish And Wildlife Service in Maine who has documented evidence of fish contaminated with mercury in the wilds of that state.</p>
        <p>Eliminating mercury and the other compounds from rain is an enormous technical and political problem. For one thing, like the air pollutants that cause acid rain, mercury is released into the atmosphere hundreds of miles from where it is doing the most damage. How far mercury can travel is not known, but in its gaseous form it can linger in the atmosphere up to two years before it falls back to earth.</p>
        <p>Swedish scientists estimate that 930 tons of mercury is circulating in the world's atmosphere at any time, enough to taint rain at levels that average 10 to 50 parts per trillion. That amount, while minuscule, is enough to cause problems.</p>
        <p>In each of the last two years, the Minnesota Legislature rejected legislation that would have made it the first state to enact strict controls on mercury emissions. Industry argued that it would increase the cost of doing business without lowering mercury levels in fish, since most of the mercury falling on Minnesota was coming from outside the state.</p>
        <p>"In a sense, they're right," said Willard Munger, the chairman of the state House Environment and Natural Resources Committee, who proposed the measure. "It's going to take national legislation to solve this problem. But we have to start somewhere." How Safe?  Tainted Fish In the Wilds</p>
        <p>Crane Lake in northern Minnesota is a stepping-off point to one of the largest wilderness regions left in the continental United States. Packs of timber wolves roam the pine forests, otters sun themselves on the rocky shoreline, bears forage for berries and eagles soar across blue skies.</p>
        <p>Yet studies by Dr. Glass, and his colleague, Dr. George R. Rapp Jr., a researcher at the University of Minnesota in Duluth, have found that mercury levels in large adult walleye and northern pike from Crane Lake range from 0.9 to 1.1 thousandths of a gram per kilogram, and that they are rising 3 percent to 5 percent a year. Younger, smaller fish have less mercury.</p>
        <p>The Minnesota Department of Health has set a limit for mercury in fish, 0.16 thousandths of a gram per kilogram, that is thought to be the nation's strictest. New York's limit is one-thousandth of a gram per kilogram, the same as the F.D.A.'s.</p>
        <p>In almost every case, walleye and pike, even young fish 5 inches to 15 inches long, that are caught in Crane Lake and in neighboring Sand Point Lake exceed the state limit. The Minnesota Department of Health has warned Crane Lake anglers not to eat more than one eight-ounce serving of pike or walleye a week. Pregnant women, nursing mothers, women thinking of becoming pregnant, and children under the age of 6 are advised against eating any fish.  Harmless to Visitors</p>
        <p>Businessmen and lodge owners from Crane Lake say the limits are so stringent that they may ruin summertime lodging and fishing. Large fish are recognized as having the most mercury and they are rarely eaten, say homeowners and fishing guides. But smaller fish are staples of the meals that guides prepare, and the guides say they are harmless, especially to visitors who spend only a few days in the region.</p>
        <p>"I've been eating fish here my whole life, and I'm fine," said Arthur (Butch) Eggen, a 38-year-old fishing guide. "The small fish aren't going to hurt you."</p>
        <p>But businessmen recognize that rising levels of mercury in fish in Northern Minnesota lakes represents an economic problem, especially if people conclude that families seeking refuge from citys pollution face a greater risk of exposure to a dangerous toxic compound while on their vacations.</p>
        <p>"We just have to tell people who come here what we know," said David K. Dill, the economic development director in Orr, 28 miles southwest of Crane Lake. "Yes, mercury is here. Yes, it's in the fish. But nobody in Minnesota has ever been diagnosed with mercury poisoning. And as far as the local people are concerned, it's a pressing issue only because if people get scared and go someplace else, it's pressing our pocketbooks." What to Do?  Why Solutions Are Elusive</p>
        <p>Perhaps most distressing about mercury pollution, say scientists, is that even if every industrial source of mercury was shut down today, the problem could get worse in some areas before it gets better.</p>
        <p>First, more than 100 years of reliance on mercury has helped to produce some 45 million tons in the soil, the oceans, the sediment of lakes and rivers and the atmosphere. Second, scientists have found that other pollutants affect how mercury behaves.</p>
        <p>Mercury is most dangerous when it is converted in the environment from its elemental form to methyl mercury, the organic form readily absorbed by fish. One of the disturbing recent findings is that acid in lakes and in clouds, and ozone pollution from cars and power plants, more quickly converts elemental mercury to methyl mercury. Environmental agencies in Minnesota, Wisconsin and New York have noted that the highest levels of mercury were found in fish taken from the most acidified lakes.</p>
        <p>Thomas C. Jorling, the Commissioner of the New York Department of Environmental Conservation, said mercury contamination "can't be solved by one state acting alone, which makes it an appropriate place for the Federal Government to act."</p>
        <p>The Edison Electric Institute estimates that the amount of mercury released from burning coal in the United States each year is 100 tons, a small fraction of the 3,000 to 5,000 tons of mercury that pours into the atmosphere from burning coal around the world. The group argues that, like the destruction of the earth's ozone shield, the mercury problem will be solved only by an international treaty.</p>
        <p>"Maybe we'll decide to go to new ways of generating power," said Dr. Donald B. Porcella, an ecologist at the Electric Power Research Institute, the utility industry's research arm. "Maybe we'll put more controls on incinerators. Maybe we'll cut back on using, or even eliminating mercury in industry. But its a very complicated problem, and we better understand it before we start making decisions."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
