<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trade Focus Has Changed</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="448623"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Economic Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D8103BF93BA15756C0A967958260" item-length="1233" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trade Focus Has Changed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE H. FARNSWORTH,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the United States and Mexico discuss environmental cooperation under arrangements to lower trade barriers at the Rio Grande, they are demonstrating how profoundly the nature of trade policy has changed over the last two decades.</p>
        <p>At one time, tariffs were the primary concern -- something external, remote and without high political visibility.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the United States and Mexico discuss environmental cooperation under arrangements to lower trade barriers at the Rio Grande, they are demonstrating how profoundly the nature of trade policy has changed over the last two decades.</p>
        <p>At one time, tariffs were the primary concern -- something external, remote and without high political visibility.</p>
        <p>But now, trade touches not only pollution control but other sensitive issues like human rights, farm and industrial subsidies, patents and trademarks, government purchasing, industrial standards, investment policies.</p>
        <p>These areas are close to the bone of national economic policy making. Cutting a Vermonter's dairy or a Georgian's peanut subsidies or giving up some "Buy American" preferences in Pentagon purchasing involves political risks.</p>
        <p>As such issues have become the substance of trade talks, the intensity -- and the decibel levels -- of the trade debate have grown year by year.</p>
        <p>There is a striking contrast between the ire and emotionalism of lawmakers debating the trade accords with Mexico and the rest of the world and the placid near-unanimity of those who approved the last major global trade agreement in 1979.</p>
        <p>"In the old days," noted Robert Z. Lawrence, an analyst with the Brookings Institution, "you had a few specialists participating in trade policy, and you knocked a few heads together. But as economies become more globalized, we're moving from shallow to deeper integration, which inevitably involves some pain."</p>
        <p>An illustration of what may lie ahead is the work of the 12 nations of the European Community, which are trying to create a single market by the end of next year.</p>
        <p>The community discovered that even though it had long ago eliminated internal tariffs, its members still had widely differing standards, regulations and rules of competition that were having almost as much of an effect as tariffs in skewing commerce and slowing economic growth.  Restrictions in Canada</p>
        <p>The story is similar in Canada, whose provinces have not applied internal tariffs since 1867. Yet there are any number of other provincial barriers, including quotas, subsidies, discriminatory pricing and import bans that often make it easier for a province to trade with the United States than with its provincial neighbor.</p>
        <p>Americans, for example, can buy beer, bricks and paint from Ontario easier than Quebecers can.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Brian Mulroney, setting out in part to get rid of the provincial barriers, initiated talks with the United States in the mid-1980's that led to a free-trade pact. It took effect in 1989, and the results have been so encouraging that both nations have agreed to accelerate tariff cutting under the agreement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mulroney now seeks to eliminate 500 provincial trade barriers by the mid-1990's. If the program is successful, he says, Canada will reap a reward of billions of dollars of added output and thousands of new jobs.</p>
        <p>With a focus chiefly on cutting tariffs since World War II, global trade liberalization has been remarkably successful. Tariffs today are at sharply reduced levels in all countries and world trade has surged. Trade has now become the engine for American growth.</p>
        <p>But while tariffs have dropped, other less-obvious forms of protection, through direct and indirect subsidies and other aids to industry and agriculture, have increased.</p>
        <p>For instance, the steel industry, a leading employer in many countries, receives hundreds of billions of dollars in subsidies through labyrinthine webs of grants and low-cost loans.</p>
        <p>The free-market-oriented American industry has long complained about the foreign subsidies that undermine its ability to compete throughout the world. Many experts say subsidized industries, often heavy-duty manufacturers, are also damaging the environment.</p>
        <p>"Government-owned or -supported smokestack industries of Japan, Korea, or even Hungary are helping to widen the already gaping hole in the ozone layer that protects us from potentially harmful effects of the sun's unfiltered ultraviolet rays," said William J. Gill in a new book, "Trade Wars Against America."</p>
        <p>While the 1979 international talks to reduce tariffs were a resounding success, the code that spelled out what were acceptable subsidies and what were not has been a big disappointment. Because of its limited coverage and the absence of any backup of international discipline, the code has had practically no effect.</p>
        <p>C. Michael Aho of the Council on Foreign Relations and Jonathan David Aronson of the University of Southern California in their book, "Trade Talks -- America Better Listen!" likened the effort to "trying to put out a forest fire with a handkerchief."</p>
        <p>In effect, while governments were engaging in trade disarmament at the tariff level, they were still quietly responding to the politics of protectionism by re-arming with more sophisticated weaponry.</p>
        <p>President Jimmy Carter's trade chief, Robert S. Strauss, who led the anti-subsidies effort, still believes it was an icebreaker.</p>
        <p>But others fret that it may have been counterproductive, having raised hopes that were not fulfilled and damaging the credibility of the international trading system.</p>
        <p>A new attack on subsidies is being led by Carla A. Hills, the United States trade representative, in the current round of global talks known as the Uruguay Round, after the country in which the first talks were held in 1986.  The Pollution Issue</p>
        <p>While subsidies load the dice, differing standards for cleaning up air and water are another, and growing, source of trade distortion. Industries in countries with lesser standards obtain competitive advantages they are loath to give up.</p>
        <p>Legislation was recently introduced by Senator David L. Boren, an Oklahoma Democrat, that would authorize President Bush to impose duties on imports from countries found to have environmental standards less rigorous than those imposed on American industry.</p>
        <p>Growing concern about environmental problems has also spurred demands for trade sanctions. A 1987 agreement in Montreal to curb global use of chlorofluorocarbons, chemicals believed to be destroying the earth's ozone shield, envisions trade reprisals against countries that do not abide by the new standards. The chronic offenders have been China, Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>At the same time, environmental regulations themselves may be used to restrain trade. Mexico has pending in Geneva a trade case against the United States under the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade, the world agreement on trade. Mexico contends that an American ban on imports of tuna caught with nets that also kill dolphins is unfair trade, aimed chiefly at protecting the American tuna industry.</p>
        <p>Improved protection for intellectual property is another of the objectives of the new global trade talks. American officials say India, Thailand and Brazil are among the countries where the flourishing piracy of pharmaceuticals, books and films, designer jeans, computer softwear and videocassettes costs American industry more than $50 billion a year.</p>
        <p>The United States has long sought what American officials and business leaders like to call a "level playing field." Yet the remaining trade barriers are so close to economic and industrial policy making and sovereignty that it may become more like the search for the Holy Grail.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
