<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Television; Bringing Up Big Guns In Cause of Free Speech</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="426099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, WALTER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">DANGEROUS ASSIGNMENTS (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MOYERS: PROJECT CENSORED (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D81F3CF936A15751C0A967958260" item-length="971" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Television; Bringing Up Big Guns In Cause of Free Speech</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Together for the first time! Starring, in alphabetical order, Tom Brokaw of NBC , Peter Jennings of ABC , Robert MacNeil of PBS, Dan Rather of CBS and Bernard Shaw of CNN ! All in a single hour! This coup of television journalism, tonight at 9 on Channel 13, is in the cause of freedom of speech.</p>
        <p>Most of "Dangerous Assignments," produced in cooperation with the Committee to Protect Journalists, is given to recounting the troubles of three brave reporters. The committee, not tonight's stars, has done the reporting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Together for the first time! Starring, in alphabetical order, Tom Brokaw of NBC , Peter Jennings of ABC , Robert MacNeil of PBS, Dan Rather of CBS and Bernard Shaw of CNN ! All in a single hour! This coup of television journalism, tonight at 9 on Channel 13, is in the cause of freedom of speech.</p>
        <p>Most of "Dangerous Assignments," produced in cooperation with the Committee to Protect Journalists, is given to recounting the troubles of three brave reporters. The committee, not tonight's stars, has done the reporting.</p>
        <p>The first and most serious case, narrated by Dan Rather, tells of the events leading up to the 1988 assassination in Peru of Hugo Bustios, who was gunned down while trying to cover an incident in the atrocity-filled war between the guerrillas of Sendero Luminoso, or Shining Path, and the Peruvian Army. The case made here, with the help of witnesses, puts the blame on the army; the prosecutor assigned to investigate has done nothing. An exasperated judge asks, "How can the police investigate the army?"</p>
        <p>The events are laid out clearly and dramatically. Enrique Zeleri, the editor in chief of Caretas, the publication for which Mr. Bustios wrote, says that when they were shot, Mr. Bustios and a colleague were screaming: "We're journalists. Don't shoot. We're journalists." And he adds, "Of course, that's why they were killed."</p>
        <p>Mr. Jennings tells about the difficulties that Marites Vitug, a reporter in the Philippines, brought on herself with her charges that a millionaire timber tycoon has been using political influence to plunder the rain forest on the island of Palawan. He has filed criminal-libel charges against her, no small matter in a country where, Mr. Jennings notes, in libel cases "you are presumed guilty until proven innocent."</p>
        <p>And Mr. Brokaw is entrusted with the experiences of Max du Preez, who started Vrye Weekblad, the first Afrikaans-language newspaper in South Africa to oppose apartheid, thereby earning him the name "Mad Max." After he published reports about right-wing death squads, Mr. du Preez received death threats of his own and the newspaper office was bombed. Brought to trial under his country's Internal Securities Act, he was found guilty and fined. Several Government officials are now suing Mr. du Preez for libel; their costs are paid by the state. If he loses, he may have to shut down his newspaper, which seems to be the idea.</p>
        <p>In the final segment of "Dangerous Assignments," Mr. Brokaw and Mr. Jennings are joined by Mr. Shaw, with Mr. MacNeil as moderator, to talk about freedom of the press. (They got together in December, when Mr. Rather was off reporting from the Middle East.) The producer might have been better advised to leave well enough alone. For the most part, the conversation of the anchors, although well intentioned, seems anticlimactic after the serious cases recounted here. At moments, as they recall incidents from their own reporting days, they seem to be competing among themselves and, in a discomfiting way, with the admirable subjects of the program.</p>
        <p>Lest anyone come away thinking that journalists in the United States are exposing all the stories that require exposure, "Dangerous Assignments" is followed on Channel 13 by "Project Censored, With Bill Moyers," a report on a few of "the 10 best censored stories of 1990." The list, made public yesterday, is this year's edition of an annual compilation done under the auspices of Sonoma State University in California.</p>
        <p>High among the stories deemed insufficiently covered was the background to the conflict in the Persian Gulf; the multi-billion-dollar bailout of failing savings-and-loan institutions; the origins and consequences of the invasion of Panama, and George Bush's role in the Iran-contra affair.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moyers talks with Tim Weiner, whose reporting for The Philadelphia Inquirer on what he calls the Pentagon's secret budget for arms procurement brought him a Pulitzer Prize, and with Pete Brewton, who has been tracking down the looted savings-and-loan deposits for The Houston Post. In both cases, it is suggested, most of the mass media has fallen down on the job.</p>
        <p>He also talks to Dr. Helen Caldicott, the Australian environmentalist, who contends that the NASA space shuttle is destroying the ozone layer, and to Michael Levine, a former undercover agent of the Drug Enforcement Administration, who seems to be promoting his book, "Deep Cover," about what he calls America's fraudulent war on drugs. The program leaves the impression that the mainstream press has not done their stories justice either.</p>
        <p>Although he notes that some critics call Mr. Brewton's reports "poorly sourced," for the most part Mr. Moyers evidently buys the points of view as delivered. He neglects to note that he was a member of the Project Censored panel that chose the 10 best censored stories in the first place. It's good to have them broadcast, but considering the nature of the program, viewers may miss in the host a touch of the disinterested doubter so useful in the journalist.  Dangerous Assignments  Produced by the Mosaic Group in association with the South Carolina Educational Television Network; Judith Moses and Jan Legnitto, producers; written by Harry Moses, Judith Moses and Jan Legnitto; camera by Alex Zakrzewski, Dewald Aukerra and Scott Ransom; sound by Mark Roy and Tony Bensusan; Harry Moses, executive producer. At 9 tonight on Channel 13. WITH: Tom Brokaw, Peter Jennings, Robert MacNeil, Dan Rather and Bernard Shaw. Moyers Project Censored  Produced by Public Affairs Television; Betsy McCarthy, producer and director; Andie Tucher, co-producer; Michael Collins, editor; Kelly Venardos, researcher; Judith Davidson Moyers, executive producer; Bill Moyers, executive editor. At 10 tonight on Channel 13.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
