<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreign Affairs; Checking It Twice</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="496289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHRISTMAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHRISTMAS GIFTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW YEAR</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GELB, LESLIE H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D6143FF936A15751C1A967958260" item-length="693" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreign Affairs; Checking It Twice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE H. GELB;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GELB, LESLIE H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It turns out that the sweat socks President Bush bought on his recent shopping spree weren't Christmas gifts for Barbara Bush. Mr. and Mrs. Bush have a longstanding policy of not exchanging Christmas presents.</p>
        <p>"They have everything they need, and anything they want they can get," explained Anna Perez, the First Lady's spokeswoman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It turns out that the sweat socks President Bush bought on his recent shopping spree weren't Christmas gifts for Barbara Bush. Mr. and Mrs. Bush have a longstanding policy of not exchanging Christmas presents.</p>
        <p>"They have everything they need, and anything they want they can get," explained Anna Perez, the First Lady's spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>I, too, am blessed with everything I need. So I don't want any gifts. But my wife says I ought to give "gifts" in my column "to those less fortunate who make mistakes."</p>
        <p>"And don't just think your usual way," she continues, warming to the task. "Go beyond male marginalia -- a little of this and that. Escape from the prison you males call reality. Make a wish list. Give things leaders should have but don't because of their narrow sense of realism and lack of imagination and courage."</p>
        <p>"You don't know what you're talking about," I say. "Your political ideas could only be comforting to Martians."</p>
        <p>"Well, it might be that my ideas will get as much reaction as any of the foreign policy columns you write," she insists, bordering on total irrationality.</p>
        <p>"You don't know what you're talking about," I say, suspecting she didn't hear this point a moment ago. "I'll lose all my credibility and effectiveness. (Pause.) But O.K., O.K., if you promise never to ask me again, I'll use my first Christmas column, at the end of my first year in this job, to present your list of miracle gifts."</p>
        <p>What follow are my wife's gifts plus my commentary in parentheses:</p>
        <p>To scientists and economists: the know-how and political backing to plug up the holes in the ozone layer so we don't burn up from ultraviolet rays, and to save the rain forests so we can continue to breathe. No other gifts will mean very much unless this is done, and soon. (I just knew you'd start out with something vaguely reasonable.)</p>
        <p>To American automotive executives: the knowledge to make cars as good as Japan's. And part of making a better car is tying executive salaries to profits. If they don't make any profit, they don't get paid so much, or they even get fired. (You're joking. They'll lay off every plant worker before they take big pay cuts.)</p>
        <p>To U.S. legislators: the guts to flat-out ban all handguns and semiautomatic weapons. Every moron knows there is no constitutional right to have these weapons. Every moron knows a ban will save lives. Anyone who stands in the way of a ban should fry under the ozone hole. (Most politicians will choose the ozone penalty.)</p>
        <p>To all American leaders: the realization that American children are being lost in a tragically inadequate education system, and the dedication to make fixing the system a major national priority. The decline in the ability to read, write, speak, compute and function in the sciences is a national crime. (All right, you've got a point here, but you can't do much without first restoring the American family, fighting teachers' unions, etc., etc.)</p>
        <p>To black American leaders: the good sense to stop abstract battles about "rights" and start concentrating on doing something about community safety, education, teen-age pregnancy and the like -- as a lot of blacks are trying to do in their own neighborhoods. (Not likely.)</p>
        <p>To their white counterparts: the conscience to confront growing prejudice against blacks and other minorities, and the courage -- despite the political winds -- to help those who need help. (Also fat chance.)</p>
        <p>To all who would ban abortion: the decency to remove themselves from other peoples' bodies and beliefs. (They'll put a contract out on you for that one.)</p>
        <p>"Look, I'm running out of space," I say.</p>
        <p>"Well, I've got more . . . Teaching English as the first and must language, using old army bases for the homeless, a cure for AIDS . . ."</p>
        <p>"You've had it," I say.</p>
        <p>"The kids have some ideas for gifts too," she says.</p>
        <p>"They don't know what they're talking about either," say I, recovering my columnist's voice. "And besides, I've had enough of these Christmas miracles."</p>
        <p>"The point is they're not miracles," she says. "The problem is you guys just think they are. Barbara Bush should give George Bush . . . Wait, I'm not finished . . ."  Anna Quindlen is on vacation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Anna Quindlen is on vacation.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
