<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vermont's Broad New Plan on Energy</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="413207"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VERMONT</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">KUNIN, MADELEINE M (GOV)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEED61439F935A35752C0A967958260" item-length="697" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vermont's Broad New Plan on Energy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a sweeping attack on global warming, acid rain and dependence on foreign fuels, the Governor of Vermont has proposed a blueprint for reducing all three through energy taxes and subsidies that would also save large sums of money in the future.</p>
        <p>The energy plan, which experts said was unprecedented in scope, seeks to extend to all forms of energy use a strategy now bearing fruit in the field of electric utilities. The strategy is to tax energy use and earmark the money for new equipment that will do the same work with less fuel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a sweeping attack on global warming, acid rain and dependence on foreign fuels, the Governor of Vermont has proposed a blueprint for reducing all three through energy taxes and subsidies that would also save large sums of money in the future.</p>
        <p>The energy plan, which experts said was unprecedented in scope, seeks to extend to all forms of energy use a strategy now bearing fruit in the field of electric utilities. The strategy is to tax energy use and earmark the money for new equipment that will do the same work with less fuel.</p>
        <p>Gov. Madeleine M. Kunin unveiled the plan on Friday, less than a week before she is to leave office. It is intended by the turn of the century to reduce by 12 percent the emissions of the gases that are believed to cause global warming. It would also cut use of fossil fuel by 29 percent for each Vermont resident and the pollutants in acid rain by 17 percent.</p>
        <p>The plan calls for $21.5 million a year in new fees and taxes, with projected savings of $236 million a year, achieved through higher efficiency.</p>
        <p>The Federal Department of Energy is to announce a national energy strategy soon. While that plan is expected to include efficiency measures, it will probably also call for increased production of energy. Facing 'Tough Choices'</p>
        <p>Mrs. Kunin, who leaves office on Thursday, called the taxes "harsh medicine," but said action was needed in the face of the Persian Gulf crisis and environmental degradation.</p>
        <p>"People really want to delay the tough choices," she said in a telephone interview. "What this plan shows is that there are some long-term benefits to making the tough choices now."</p>
        <p>Since she will not be in office to guide the plan into law, Mrs. Kunin said it would serve as a basis for debate. A spokesman for her successor, Richard A. Snelling, said the Governor-elect would carefully study the plan.</p>
        <p>The spokesman, Michael W. Gilhooly, said Mr. Snelling, who was Governor for eight years in the 1970's and 80's, had a strong interest in energy and the environment.</p>
        <p>Most of the steps recommended in the Vermont plan are within the state's power to accomplish. They include low-cost loans for homeowners and businesses, financial incentives for consumers to buy more efficient cars, and reduction of the speed limit to 55 miles an hour from 65.</p>
        <p>The plan also calls for encouraging the use of wood for fuel in homes and businesses and subsidizing installation of solar water heaters. Other changes would be enforced on utilities supplying electricity and natural gas.</p>
        <p>But the plan also calls for changes that a small state could not enforce on its own, like raising the average fuel efficiency of new cars to 40 miles a gallon from the current Federal standard of 27.5. It also calls for greater use of alcohol and natural gas as transportation fuels, a step that Mrs. Kunin said could be taken by states on a regional basis. 3-Cent-a-Gallon Tax</p>
        <p>Provisions would be paid for with a 3-cent-a-gallon tax on gasoline and diesel fuel, as well as taxes on "nonrenewable" fuels that are now unregulated, like heating oil and propane.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists have long favored spending money to improve efficiency, arguing that the costs would be more than covered by lower energy bills. In addition, they say, there would be a side benefit of reduced pollution because of reduced fuel use.</p>
        <p>That argument has been adopted by many states in regulation of electric utilities, which are often required to subsidize their customers' buying of things like new light fixtures, electric motors and appliances that do the same work with less power. The Vermont plan seeks to expand that model to unregulated fields like home heating and transportation.</p>
        <p>The principle of investing to save energy was endorsed by the New England Fuel Institute, an oil dealers' association in Boston. But Bernard A. Smith, executive vice president of the group, questioned who would pay for the initial efficiency investment. "The cost of energy and energy conservation should be borne by all energy users," he said.</p>
        <p>He said that the use of heating oil had already been cut very sharply through added insulation and storm windows.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
