<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Quick Steps Urged on Warming Threat</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="436514"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DF1339F932A25757C0A967958260" item-length="1032" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Quick Steps Urged on Warming Threat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a report that was welcomed by the White House and environmentalists, the National Academy of Sciences said today that the United States should act promptly to reduce the threat of global warming.</p>
        <p>An academy panel recommended a variety of steps, including raising overall mileage standards for new automobiles to 32.5 miles per gallon from 27.5; increasing Federal support for mass transit and reforestation, and developing a new generation of safe and efficient nuclear power plants. The warming is feared as a result of the steady accumulation of waste industrial gases like carbon dioxide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a report that was welcomed by the White House and environmentalists, the National Academy of Sciences said today that the United States should act promptly to reduce the threat of global warming.</p>
        <p>An academy panel recommended a variety of steps, including raising overall mileage standards for new automobiles to 32.5 miles per gallon from 27.5; increasing Federal support for mass transit and reforestation, and developing a new generation of safe and efficient nuclear power plants. The warming is feared as a result of the steady accumulation of waste industrial gases like carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>The steps necessary to address global warming have been a matter of fierce political contention between the Bush Administration and environmental groups. Even within the Administration, the Environmental Protection Agency has favored quicker action against global warming, which the President's chief of staff, John H. Sununu, has opposed.</p>
        <p>The report from the academy, the leading independent source of scientific advice for the Government, seems intended as an adroit compromise between the various factions, and was praised on all sides.  Rudiments of National Policy</p>
        <p>Although its recommendations are somewhat general, they point the way to a broad-based national program for reducing carbon dioxide emissions. They lay down the rudiments of a national energy policy, which the Administration has long resisted.</p>
        <p>William K. Reilly, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, called the report "a step forward," although he said that he did not necessarily agree with everything in it and that his agency had not yet studied it in detail.</p>
        <p>The study was commissioned by Congress, and many of its recommendations would require Congressional action.</p>
        <p>A senior Administration official, who spoke on the condition of anonymity, said he was pleased the report had not recommended "draconian changes." He also praised the report's cautious stand on the uncertainties of global warming, its cost-benefit analysis, its refusal to propose target dates and quotas for reductions of carbon dioxide emissions, and the importance it places on eliminating another trapper of heat, chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>Dr. D. Allan Bromley, the White House science adviser, said, "I am delighted with the report, as are all my colleagues in the White House." He said actions already taken by the Bush Administration would result in emission reductions on the order of those proposed by the academy.</p>
        <p>The academy report "should put an end to the debate over whether it pays to act to slow global warming," said Dr. Michael Oppenheimer, an atmospheric scientist at the Environmental Defense Fund. "It makes a prima facie case for acting now." 'A Nimble Policy'</p>
        <p>Even though the report does not set targets for reducing carbon dioxide, as environmental groups have long advocated, it was described as "a nimble policy" by a member of the panel, Dr. Jessica Tuchman Mathews, vice president of the World Resources Institute.</p>
        <p>The panel said the prospect of global warming "poses a potential threat sufficient to merit prompt responses," even though it acknowledged that there was great uncertainty about its extent, timing and impact.</p>
        <p>The panel said its proposed measures were all of "low cost," meaning they were cheap ways of reducing carbon dioxide and other waste gases. Low cost was defined as less than $10 per metric ton of heat-trapping gases eliminated per year. The panel did not calculate the total value of the initial investment.</p>
        <p>The panel said the United States "should resume full participation" in international programs to slow population growth. Daniel J. Evans, the chairman of the panel, called population "the biggest single driver of atmospheric pollution." Mr. Evans, a Republican, is a former Governor and Senator from Washington.</p>
        <p>The panel encouraged development and testing of a new generation of safe, efficient nuclear power plants to replace those that burn coal and oil. Its report did not go as far as many environmentalists have advocated in reducing carbon dioxide emissions, concluding that "options requiring great expenses are not justified" now.</p>
        <p>Administration officials say steps already taken will allow overall emissions of "greenhouse" gases in the United States to stabilize in the next decade. But they argue that this is nevertheless consistent with the possible reduction of 10 to 40 percent that the academy said could be achieved if its measures were followed.</p>
        <p>This is because the academy figure represents the reduction that would occur if all the measures were in effect now. By that measure, said Michael Deland, the chairman of the White House Council on Environmental Quality, the actions already taken by the Administration would amount to a 20 to 25 percent reduction.</p>
        <p>The effects of any such measures do not suddenly materialize in one year, but rather come into play over a period of years, in which economic and population growth cause emissions to grow. This is not accounted for in the academy analysis, Mr. Deland said. Mr. Coppock, the director of the academy panel's staff, said that was true.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists say the steps already taken by the Administration are not enough to achieve an absolute reduction in the greenhouse emissions in the United States, but would merely allow them to stabilize in the short term while resuming their growth in the long term.</p>
        <p>They also assert that some of the important steps recommended by the academy have been specifically rejected by the Administration. Among them are the increase in gasoline mileage standards for new cars to 32.5 miles per gallon and stronger Federal support for mass transit.</p>
        <p>Dr. Oppenheimer said the academy's recommendations "go a long way toward meeting the goal of keeping the climate from going haywire."</p>
        <p>The panel did not propose target dates and quotas for carbon-dioxide reductions of the kind that some European countries have adopted and that some environmentalists have urged. Members said that was because rapidly changing knowledge about global warming and climate change was certain to render targets and quotas obsolete.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
