<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Should Stars Set the Agenda?</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="429085"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">CREATIVE COALITION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERNSTEIN, RICHARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D6143DF933A25750C0A967958260" item-length="2163" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Should Stars Set the Agenda?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERNSTEIN, RICHARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The stars were well represented, specifically Holly Hunter, Danny Aiello and Richard Dreyfuss, and there was the usual expensive party afterward. But when "Once Around" opened in New York earlier this year, the premiere was different in one key respect. Just before the lights went out, the actor Christopher Reeve took the stage, and it seemed the audience was going to get just a bit of exhortation, maybe even a touch of enlightenment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reeve was there to ask support for the Creative Coalition, a New York-based group of entertainment-industry figures that promotes certain causes -- and for whose benefit the premiere had been arranged. In his comfortable, unaffected way, but drawing a hushed attention as only a movie star can, Mr. Reeve spoke of the issues the coalition favors -- free choice on abortion, protecting the environment, helping the homeless and "saving" the National Endowment for the Arts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The stars were well represented, specifically Holly Hunter, Danny Aiello and Richard Dreyfuss, and there was the usual expensive party afterward. But when "Once Around" opened in New York earlier this year, the premiere was different in one key respect. Just before the lights went out, the actor Christopher Reeve took the stage, and it seemed the audience was going to get just a bit of exhortation, maybe even a touch of enlightenment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reeve was there to ask support for the Creative Coalition, a New York-based group of entertainment-industry figures that promotes certain causes -- and for whose benefit the premiere had been arranged. In his comfortable, unaffected way, but drawing a hushed attention as only a movie star can, Mr. Reeve spoke of the issues the coalition favors -- free choice on abortion, protecting the environment, helping the homeless and "saving" the National Endowment for the Arts.</p>
        <p>Of course, an appearance like Mr. Reeve's is hardly unusual. Show-business personalities, from Jane Fonda to Bob Hope, Robert Redford to Susan Sarandon, have been speaking out on various causes for years. But there seems to be a new thrust to activities these days. Formerly, stars tended to be part-time activists, at most organizing one or two immense fund raisers, as the Irish rocker Bob Geldof did for Ethiopian famine relief. More commonly, they were content to appear from time to time, to make a statement or issue an endorsement -- in short, to lend the glitter of their names -- and then return to the cloistered world of their stardom.</p>
        <p>But now celebrities, like those in the Creative Coalition, are forming full-time organizations, using the techniques of political lobbies and special-interest groups, becoming board members of associations with executive directors and staffs. The actor Richard Dreyfuss speaks on peace in the Middle East.  The actress Meryl Streep promotes organic food with her organization Mothers and Others for a Livable Planet. The pop singer Sting fights for the South American rain forest.  The rock star Don Henley works to protect Walden Woods in Massachusetts from developers. Mr. Henley and Mr. Dreyfuss have hired full-time aides to coordinate their activities.</p>
        <p>"There is a new trend," said Betsy Kenny, vice president for public affairs of Act III Communications in Hollywood, Norman Lear's production company; the television producer created one of the first major show-business advocacy groups, People for the American Way, in 1983, and Ms. Kenny handles many of his political interests. The newly organized celebrity activists, she said, "came out of the 1988 election." Hollywood's favorite Presidential candidate was the Colorado Democrat Gary Hart. When Mr. Hart's campaign foundered in a sex scandal, some backers wanted to re-energize his suddenly deflated campaign. "And so," Ms. Kenny said, "you started seeing celebrities in Hollywood taking initiatives and creating their own organizations."</p>
        <p>As Hollywoodian politics become less ad hoc and more a permanent presence on the scene, celebrities promise to become more powerful -- and more influential in shaping public opinion. That fact, in turn, raises an obvious question: stars like Christopher Reeve, Richard Dreyfuss, Sting, Barbra Streisand, Don Henley, Ted Danson, Ron Silver, Sinead O'Connor and other new-breed show-business activists may be brilliant performers, but are they qualified to guide Americans on complex political and social questions? And does their presence make a media circus out of what should be sober reflection on complicated problems?</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Connor proclaimed recently, in canceling her appearance at the Grammy Awards, that artists have a duty "to inspire and, in some way, guide and heal the human race." Do they?</p>
        <p>"It's wonderful to do good things in the world, but activism can also become foolish and misguided," said Howard Rosenman, co-president of Sandollar Motion Pictures, a Hollywood production company. "This is still the land of shucksters, hypsters and swashbucklers, and once they become the heads of political organizations, once they start to pontificate about issues they don't know very much about, then it becomes ridiculous. And it dilutes the moral force that they have on the issues that they do know about."</p>
        <p>Paul Fussell, professor of English literature at the University of Pennsylvania and author of "Class" and "A Guide Through the American Status System," worries that the political zeal of the stars poses a particular danger because, as he put it, "people are going to be hoodwinked all the time, deluded by a lot of circuses. Even when it surrounds a cause I like, I don't like it, because I'd prefer a cause to persuade by its own inner argument and not by this kind of magic."</p>
        <p>Celebrities typically reply to these concerns by maintaining that they want to be useful and serious, to understand what they are talking about rather than serve as what Mr. Reeve called "rent a star" -- figures present for window dressing only.</p>
        <p>"We're in a unique position," Mr. Reeve said in an interview. "We have access to politicians who, in fact, need us for their own recognizability. The media need us because they have had sort of a romance with celebrities. At bottom, we're just concerned citizens, but the difference is we have a higher profile, and we want to use that profile intelligently and responsibly."</p>
        <p>Of course, stars have been involved in politics for just about as long as there have been famous people, and that involvement has always generated debate. Years ago, the nuclear physicist Edward Teller cautioned the public against taking too seriously the opinions of famous people, including scientists, when they spoke on subjects outside their areas of expertise. They have the right and perhaps even the duty to speak out, Mr. Teller said, but the public would be mistaken to think they have special insight just because they are well known.</p>
        <p>Those words of wisdom make theoretical sense but seem to have little to do with the way the world works. The fact is, large parts of the public, and certainly the press, treat the views of stars with special respect, and not just the views of movie stars. Albert Einstein was listened to on political matters because he was renowned as a scientist.</p>
        <p>Why does the public listen to stars?  Certainly the political empowerment of celebrities reflects the very star-struck nature of America, its fascination with fame. It reflects the public's urge to imbue a few individuals with a special aura, a power of enchantment, a god- or goddess-like status that renders mere knowledge of a subject almost superfluous.</p>
        <p>But there is a paradox, one connected with the competing images that the public holds of stars. If celebrities are attributed authority on all sorts of questions, they are at the same time viewed as the most pampered members of society, disconnected from the lives of ordinary people. There is something unsettling in the spectacle of these conspicuous consumers, these travelers in private jets, wearers of sequined designer dresses, lecturing the less wealthy on the virtues of recycling, the morality of abortion or the aspirations of Central Americans. The ever-greater presence of stars on the political stage is a sign of the times, an attribute of a culture that stresses image (rather than substance) and glitter (rather than knowledge).</p>
        <p>"A cause by itself is not enough," Professor Fussell said. "People have to have magic. It's the same principle as the beautiful girl pictured on the hood of a car. Her presence there gives the car some magic, but she herself doesn't know anything about cars."</p>
        <p>Once upon a time, people became famous because they were authorities on something -- foreign policy, say, or civil rights. Now it is the reverse. Movie stars start off with fame and they are then attributed authority by a public eager for these visible symbols, for guides they recognize.</p>
        <p>"The main point in a culture of celebrity is that fame is increasingly seen as a form of social power," said Ronald Brownstein, the author of "The Power and the Glitter," a new history of Hollywood's activities on the political scene and the influence of politics on Hollywood, going as far back as the 1930's.</p>
        <p>"In the 1950's," he said, "C. Wright Mills, the sociologist, described celebrity as a dazzling blind that obscures us from the real powers in society, who he thought were shadowy militarists and industrialists. In fact, in a mass-media era, fame is a very tangible form of influence, simply because the ante for any candidate or cause is the ability to attract attention in the media. In the television era, detailed knowledge matters less than the ability to project knowledgeability on the screen, and the stars are the most conspicuous examples of that."</p>
        <p>Given the attention afforded Hollywood's activists, it should come as no surprise that new organizations are springing up like mushrooms. In 1984, the Hollywood Women's Political Committee was formed to support Walter Mondale's Presidential campaign. After the Hart campaign came the Show Coalition, whose board of directors includes Mr. Dreyfuss and Polly Bergen, the director Sydney Pollack and the producer Shawn Daniel.</p>
        <p>"Basically, we educate the entertainment community about political and social issues such as choice, civil liberties and the environment," said Ms. Kenny of the Show Coalition.  "But we also do some lobbying and fund raising."</p>
        <p>Then came the Creative Coalition, spearheaded by the actor Ron Silver.  Ted Danson, whose movie credits include "Three Men and a Baby," formed the American Oceans Campaign to promote environmentalism.  Mr. Henley, a reader of Henry David Thoreau, was upset over plans to develop Walden Woods. He and former Massachusetts Senator Paul Tsongas set up the Walden Woods Project, complete with two full-time staff members and a bevy of volunteers, to oppose the real-estate interests.</p>
        <p>One of the most active and successful Hollywood groups was formed a couple years ago when show-business personalities, reacting to fears of global warming, created the Environmental Media Association, a group that illustrates Hollywood arrayed in all its power. The presidents of four television networks are supporters, as are studio heads and independent producers like Mr. Lear. The idea is to plant pro-environmentalist messages in regular programming. The group's executive director, Andy Spahn, said that some 40 prime-time programs have used material on the environment, including "Thirtysomething," "MacGyver," "Golden Girls," "Knots Landing" and "My Two Dads." According to Mr. Spahn, the association holds briefings with programs' creative staff, does research and provides advice on plot lines.</p>
        <p>"Various shows have done full episodes devoted to environmental themes," he said, citing a "Thirtysomething" scenario in which the character Hope becomes an environmental activist. "Just as important to us, some shows have incorporated incidental dialogue on the environment," Mr. Spahn said. "This is dialogue not central to the plot but that delivers a message about recycling or conservation on an ongoing basis. It's important because our primary interest is to influence life styles."</p>
        <p>But is the insertion of a political message in entertainment a kind of subliminal advertising? Given the entertainment industry's enormous wealth and the magical aura that surrounds it, some people fear that a simplistic, politically correct orthodoxy might be imposed on an impressionable public. After all, few major issues can be understood with a rock-and-roll lyric or some lines of dialogue.</p>
        <p>"It's ironic," Mr. Spahn said, "that some of the people who used to complain of the emptiness of TV and film now complain about the relevance."</p>
        <p>"People identify with the stars and with the characters on a program, so there's great potential to have an impact," he said. "But none of the celebrities are putting themselves in the role of experts. What they're saying is that because of their visibility they have the power to focus attention on the issues. That's generally the role played by fame."</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver of the Creative Coalition argues that today's celebrity activists have made an effort to be informed and responsible.</p>
        <p>"I knew that celebrities would take hits," he said, "that people would say, 'Who are these people? What right do they have to lecture us on politics?' But there's the theoretical abstraction about the way things should work and then there's the way things really do work. And, in the real world, celebrities can attract attention. Then, once you have people's attention, you can expose them to ideas. Without Madonna and Sting, nobody would have heard of the rain forest."</p>
        <p>"To be famous is to have a public voice and to have a public voice is to have influence," Mr. Silver said. "I find uninformed celebrities as reprehensible as uninformed politicians."  FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
