<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush's Energy Plan Emphasizes Gains in Output Over Efficiency</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="421605"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSERVATION OF RESOURCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY EFFICIENCY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D7153EF93AA35751C0A967958260" item-length="1279" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush's Energy Plan Emphasizes Gains in Output Over Efficiency</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The White House has drafted a national energy policy that would encourage the growth of the domestic oil industry and remove obstacles to the construction of nuclear power plants. But the plan calls for only a modest effort to encourage energy efficiency.</p>
        <p>The plan, which is taking final form as war in the oil-rich Persian Gulf has focused new attention on long-term energy supply problems, is intended to make the nation less dependent on foreign sources. Through deregulation and tax breaks, it would encourage the oil, gas and coal industries to begin aggressive programs for increasing the domestic output of fossil fuels in the United States. The Office of Management and Budget circulated a draft of the legislation embodying the policy to Federal departments and agencies this week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The White House has drafted a national energy policy that would encourage the growth of the domestic oil industry and remove obstacles to the construction of nuclear power plants. But the plan calls for only a modest effort to encourage energy efficiency.</p>
        <p>The plan, which is taking final form as war in the oil-rich Persian Gulf has focused new attention on long-term energy supply problems, is intended to make the nation less dependent on foreign sources. Through deregulation and tax breaks, it would encourage the oil, gas and coal industries to begin aggressive programs for increasing the domestic output of fossil fuels in the United States. The Office of Management and Budget circulated a draft of the legislation embodying the policy to Federal departments and agencies this week.</p>
        <p>The proposals include few programs aimed at substantially reducing the consumption of energy. Conservation groups have called for such actions by the Government, but none of the proposals would encourage motorists to reduce their use of gasoline, the largest single use for oil in the United States.</p>
        <p>Copies of the draft were made available to several news organizations today. White House officials said that the draft was receiving a last review from the Energy Department and other agencies and that when those had been incorporated it would be given to President Bush for his signature. James D. Watkins, the Energy Secretary, is scheduled to testify before the Senate Energy Committee and Natural Resources Committee on Feb. 19, and Senator Timothy Wirth, Democrat of Colorado, said Mr. Watkins would present the plan then.</p>
        <p>The draft of a letter accompanying the plan, from Mr. Watkins to Representative Thomas S. Foley, the Speaker of the House, described the policy's purpose. "To secure future energy supplies, we must consider fossil fuels, nuclear power, renewable energy, fusion energy and enhanced R.&amp;D.," the letter said. "As events in the Persian Gulf have demonstrated so aptly, we must reduce our dependence on imported oil from unstable regions. This will require both reducing our overall dependence on oil, particularly in the transportation sector, and increasing domestic production in an environmentally sound manner." Oil Industry's View</p>
        <p>Oil industry executives, who were made aware of its details today, applauded the Administration's aggressive plan to take some restraints off the domestic oil industry. "If this is as described, it certainly sounds very positive, not only for the industry, but for the consumer," said Douglas G. Elmets, a spokesman for ARCO in Los Angeles. "It certainly makes us less reliant on insecure sources of oil."</p>
        <p>But leaders of environmental groups who read the draft today said it was one-sided and would fail to solve the nation's dependence on foreign oil, which supplies more than half the American consumption. "There is no leadership here, no vision for a future of clean, efficient use of energy," said James L. Wolf, executive director of the Alliance to Save Energy, a group in Washington that lobbies for energy conservation measures. "It's very aggressive in ignoring transportation efficiencies, which is the root of the oil problem."</p>
        <p>Democratic lawmakers predicted today that if the legislation proposed by the White House was similar to the draft circulating today, its chances of passage are slim. "It was only a couple of months ago that Admiral Watkins said in an interim report that the single loudest message he heard all across the country was support for energy efficiency in all sectors of the economy, and almost all of these opportunities were ignored," Senator Wirth said.  Opening the Wildlife Refuge</p>
        <p>Among the measures in the 142-page draft is a proposal to open 1.5 million acres of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge in Alaska for oil exploration.</p>
        <p>The Administration wants to put 300,000 acres of the 19-million acre refuge up for bid to oil companies in the first round of oil lease sales; every two years after that, 300,000 more acres would be open for leasing to oil companies. The Interior Department, which owns the refuge and believes as much as 3.6 billion barrels of oil lie below the coastal plain, said this week that new studies show the probability for a successful strike is more than twice what scientists said just four years ago.</p>
        <p>The Administration's proposal includes an array of restrictions and regulations to protect animals and their habitats in the vast refuge, but they are not likely to satisfy environmental groups, including the National Wildlife Federation and Sierra Club, which have been lobbying to keep the oil companies out of the refuge. Oil and Gas Pipelines</p>
        <p>Other proposed programs would aid the oil and natural gas industry, including eliminating requirements that energy companies get approval from the Government to import or export natural gas. Several other proposals would reduce restrictions on owners of oil and natural gas pipelines.</p>
        <p>The formal process of developing the Administration energy policy began in August 1989 with a public hearing in Washington, the first of several around the country, at which Mr. Watkins presided. "This national energy strategy," Mr. Watkins said, "will be a dynamic, living process, not just a document, from this day forward."</p>
        <p>Among the proposals that Mr. Watkins promoted from the start, and that remain in the draft made available today, were new rules for severe limits on the ability of the public to comment on new nuclear power plants before they are started. The proposal is intended to eliminate situations in which new plants are held up or permanently closed because of public protests in the weeks before they are to open.  Concern for the Economy</p>
        <p>Mr. Watkins also said he was interested in conserving energy with new, imaginative programs that would aid the economy as well as the environment. In the draft policy, just a few of the ideas offered at public hearings across the country survived. There are new tax credits for producing energy with the sun, water, and wind, and ideas that could encourage the development of alternative sources of electricity. There is also a proposal to set new standards for making lights more energy-efficient.</p>
        <p>But nearly all proposals for conservation and efficiency, according to lawmakers on Capitol Hill, are likely to be eliminated by the White House over the weekend. The White House has also proposed to weaken an existing regulation requiring automobiles to become more fuel-efficient.</p>
        <p>On Capitol Hill, the White House legislation will compete with several other proposals that have already been introduced.</p>
        <p>Bennett Johnston, a Democrat and chairman of the Senate Energy Committee, has co-sponsored a new bill with Malcolm Wallop, a Republican from Wyoming, that would increase the size of the Strategic Petroleum Reserve and rewrite the nation's principal law that regulates electric utilities.</p>
        <p>Senator Richard H. Bryan, a Democrat from Nevada, has reintroduced a measure that was narrowly defeated last year to increase automobile fuel mileage standards.</p>
        <p>Representative Philip R. Sharp, Democrat of Indiana, would require states to promote energy conservation, calls for Federal power agencies that sell electricity to utilities to require their customers to establish conservation plans, and would call on Federal lending agencies to promote energy efficiency through mortgage incentives for energy-efficient homes. And Senator Frank Murkowski, Republican of Alaska, reintroduced legislation that was withdrawn after the Exxon Valdez in 1989 to open the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge to oil drilling.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
