<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hopeful E.P.A. Report Fans a Debate as Talks on Warming Near</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="414757"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GASES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DB1F39F930A25752C0A967958260" item-length="1149" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hopeful E.P.A. Report Fans a Debate as Talks on Warming Near</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency says that at a time when most other countries have only pledged to take action, the United States has already taken steps that will keep emissions of heat-trapping atmospheric gases at current levels for the next two decades.</p>
        <p>The conclusions are playing a crucial role in the United States' preparations for an international conference in Washington next month to negotiate a treaty to control emissions of the gases, which scientists say could cause a catastrophic warming of the Earth in the 21st century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency says that at a time when most other countries have only pledged to take action, the United States has already taken steps that will keep emissions of heat-trapping atmospheric gases at current levels for the next two decades.</p>
        <p>The conclusions are playing a crucial role in the United States' preparations for an international conference in Washington next month to negotiate a treaty to control emissions of the gases, which scientists say could cause a catastrophic warming of the Earth in the 21st century.</p>
        <p>More than 20 industrialized countries have committed themselves to stabilizing or reducing emissions of carbon dioxide, the gas that would play the largest role in the warming. The Bush Administration has opposed such a target for carbon dioxide, arguing that the extent of the problem is too uncertain. Reliability Is Questioned</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. study is already generating argument. Some critics question its reliability and assail it as a ploy to justify what they see as the Administration's go-slow policy on global warming. They say that even if the findings are reliable, enough of the gases are already in the atmosphere to require stronger action. Scientists say, further, that a substantial reduction in emissions will be required if the global concentration of the gases is to be stabilized at current levels.</p>
        <p>But William K. Reilly, the E.P.A. Administrator, said in an interview that the study showed that the United States had already acted to stabilize its overall contribution to warming. Mr. Reilly has long advocated emissions targets, provided they encompass all the implicated gases, not just carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Atmospheric concentrations of the gases are steadily rising as a result of human activity. Scientists say that because they trap heat much as a greenhouse does, they could cause drastic climatic changes in the next century.</p>
        <p>Some experts on the international politics of global warming say the findings of the agency's report could prompt the United States to drop its objection to targets. In this view, Washington might recapture leadership on the issue of global warming if it proposed an overall target that included all the gases implicated in global warming -- a target that the E.P.A. study suggests it could meet.  Sununu Opposes Targets</p>
        <p>"If they don't do it, they're going to have a very hard time getting back in the game seriously, in terms of playing a leading role in shaping an international approach," said William Nitze, a former State Department official who was responsible for coordinating Government policy on global warming and who represented the United States in international meetings on the subject. He left the Administration last September to become president of the nonprofit Alliance to Save Energy, based in Washington.</p>
        <p>Whether the Administration will now embrace targets in light of the report's finding remains to be seen. The idea has considerable support among officials of Government agencies who are discussing what the United States' stance should be, Administration officials say. But higher officials, including John H. Sununu, the President's chief of staff, have successfully opposed any targets in the past. Mr. Sununu said through an aide that he was aware of the report but would not comment on it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly says that while the study is not yet "fully researched" or scientifically reviewed, "it's the best we have."</p>
        <p>Recently adopted measures that the E.P.A. study says will limit the United States contribution to the greenhouse effect include these measures:</p>
        <p>*Provisions of the new Clean Air Act amendments that will slow carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>*Recent energy-saving measures mandated by the Department of Energy, including efficiency standards for appliances, the development of energy-saving building codes, and initiatives to expand hydroelectric power, promote solar energy and stimulate greater efficiency by the electric-power industry.</p>
        <p>*The phasing out of chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's. These chemicals, used as refrigerants, solvents and propellants, are being abandoned primarily because they destroy the ozone layer that protects living things from ultraviolet radiation. But they also are even more powerful and long-lived heat-trappers than carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>According to a report on the study by Alex Cristofaro, director of the agency's air and energy policy division, researchers calculated the effect of the recent Government measures on emissions of the various greenhouse gases. It converted all the gases to carbon-dioxide equivalents, in terms of heat-trapping capacity.</p>
        <p>It found that the United States contribution to the greenhouse effect, expressed in carbon-dioxide equivalents, would be about the same in 2000 as in 1987, and that it would either drop slightly or show an increase of about 4 percent by 2010. This could change, the study said, if the new Government measures do not materialize as expected or if the economy grows faster than expected.  Can It Be Painless?</p>
        <p>One Government official, who spoke on condition that he not be identified, said that the study's conclusion means that "the problem is possibly less intractable than it might appear at first glance." He said it suggests that "we could quite painlessly" take further action to limit greenhouse emissions over the next few years.</p>
        <p>Environmental skeptics doubt that a United States pledge to stabilize its overall greenhouse emissions by the year 2000 would be a sufficient response. "It would still be a considerably weaker position than that adopted by the Europeans," said Michael Oppenheimer, a senior scientist and expert on global warming at the Environmental Defense Fund, an environmental research and advocacy group.</p>
        <p>He said the Europeans have committed themselves to capping or reducing carbon dioxide emissions. "In addition," he said, "they will do the same as we're doing with CFC's, namely, eliminate them." Most of the world's nations have agreed to halt production of CFC's by the end of this decade.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. study shows that carbon dioxide emissions in the United States would continue to grow over the next two decades, even though this nation's overall contribution to the greenhouse effect would stabilize.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Dr. Oppenheimer said, overall greenhouse emissions by the United States would resume their growth after CFC's have been eliminated if no further action is taken. "In my opinion," said Dr. Oppenheimer, "the U.S. is trying to pull the wool over everyone's eyes under the guise of stabilizing greenhouse emissions."</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly, a career environmentalist before he joined the Bush Administration, has consistently advocated targets to stabilize or reduce overall greenhouse emissions. By setting overall targets, he argues, individual countries are afforded more flexibility.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
