<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TV Weekend; Examining the Scandals at a U.S. Relief Agency</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="496518"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCUMENTARY FILMS AND PROGRAMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NOBEL PRIZES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CABLE NEWS NETWORK</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CBS INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WNET (TV STATION) (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, WALTER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">A.I.D.: UNDER INVESTIGATION (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MADE IN NEW YORK (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">GREAT NOBEL DEBATE, THE (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nobel Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D71E3DF934A15751C1A967958260" item-length="721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TV Weekend; Examining the Scandals at a U.S. Relief Agency</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sunday's edition of "Special Assignment," on CNN at 9 P.M., takes apart the record of the Agency for International Development. If Mark Feldstein's report is reasonably accurate, the agency, which distributes food, medicine and other help to the needy around the world, has been bilked by its own officials and employees. Gene Richardson, its assistant inspector general for investigations, says: "Our crime rate is essentially higher than virtually every other agency in the Government."</p>
        <p>Contractors have squeezed kickbacks out of programs to help feed Pakistan's poor. A deputy director went to prison for accepting nearly $100,000 in payoffs for awarding contracts to Honduras. Three scientists who were supposed to use aid money to find a cure for malaria, that world-class killer, instead made killings of their own. And there's more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sunday's edition of "Special Assignment," on CNN at 9 P.M., takes apart the record of the Agency for International Development. If Mark Feldstein's report is reasonably accurate, the agency, which distributes food, medicine and other help to the needy around the world, has been bilked by its own officials and employees. Gene Richardson, its assistant inspector general for investigations, says: "Our crime rate is essentially higher than virtually every other agency in the Government."</p>
        <p>Contractors have squeezed kickbacks out of programs to help feed Pakistan's poor. A deputy director went to prison for accepting nearly $100,000 in payoffs for awarding contracts to Honduras. Three scientists who were supposed to use aid money to find a cure for malaria, that world-class killer, instead made killings of their own. And there's more.</p>
        <p>Ronald W. Roskens, administrator of the agency, insists that it is "unbefitting" to apply the word "crooks," used by Mr. Feldstein, to even "a very few people, comparatively, at high levels."</p>
        <p>Viewers of "A.I.D.: Under Investigation" may not be much reassured by that vocabulary lesson amid the hour's array of scandals. Instead of sending dry-cleaning fluid to Zimbabwe, a contractor sent toxic waste. Starving Sudanese, who were supposed to receive tons of powdered milk, got animal feed instead. Peruvian children were killed by tainted medicine supplied by the agency. After 13 years of construction and $75 million in aid, a low-income housing project near Cairo is still far from developed.</p>
        <p>The successes of the Agency for International Development (there must be some) are not mentioned in this unsparing report, which will do nothing to improve the prospects for foreign aid in these hard times. 'The Great Nobel Debate'  Channel 13 Tonight at 9</p>
        <p>The main revelation of "The Great Nobel Debate" is that Nobel Prize winners have nothing particularly original to say about puffy questions like "Is mankind on balance harnessing its intelligence to build a better world?" That was the balloon floated before a sizable group of laureates by David Frost a few weeks ago as part of the 90th-anniversary celebration of the Nobel Prizes in Stockholm. You can see how they handled it tonight on Channel 13.</p>
        <p>It is an hour of familiar lamentations, bromides and inspirational tags. Archbishop Desmond Tutu, taking the affirmative position, says he puts his faith in freedom and science. Prof. Henry Kendall, a physicist from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, accentuates the negative with references to global warming, the destruction of rain forests, water problems and overpopulation.</p>
        <p>Everyone sounds intelligent, but the high-mindedness of the occasion evidently kept minds at the idle. Prof. Milton Friedman, the Stanford University economist, sees hope in the collapse of Communism; Octavio Paz puts in a plug for poetry, and Nadine Gordimer, the most recent winner for literature, proposes a marriage of the gods of science and spirituality.</p>
        <p>All these worthies are on their best behavior. The closest attempt at a joke comes late, from Dr. Howard Temin, who won the prize for physiology and medicine in 1975. Drawing attention to the AIDS epidemic, he says, "We must return to love but remind everyone that if you love, use a condom." At the end, Mr. Frost asks for a show of hands on mankind's prospects. If you stay with the program that long, you'll learn the result. 'Made in New York'  Channel 2 Tonight at 9</p>
        <p>"Made in New York" is an hourlong promotion for New York City's movie industry. Agreeable as it is to watch an upbeat program about a beaten-down town, the constant plugs delivered by Ron Silver, playing the host, make for a nonstop commercial. The liveliest scenes are of the movie director Sidney Lumet organizing the crash of a taxicab into a 47th Street jewelry store. (It actually takes place in a Queens studio.) Spike Lee, Paul Mazursky and other movie and television makers contribute to the New York boosterism. There's even a segment on Gary David Goldberg, who created the television series "Brooklyn Bridge," which of course is all about New York and is produced in Hollywood. Special Assignment  Mark Feldstein, reporter; Amos Gelb, producer; Pamela Hill, executive producer. Sunday night at 9 on CNN.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
