<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Not Even Death Ends Anti-Pollution Crusade</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="469707"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUNERALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CEMETERIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEARY, WARREN E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6D81631F934A1575BC0A967958260" item-length="1201" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Not Even Death Ends Anti-Pollution Crusade</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEARY, WARREN E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONCERN about the environment now reaches even beyond the grave and is troubling the cremation and cemetery business.</p>
        <p>More than two million people die each year in the United States. Those responsible for disposing of the remains say their work is increasingly constrained by Federal, state and local laws aimed at protecting air, land and water quality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CONCERN about the environment now reaches even beyond the grave and is troubling the cremation and cemetery business.</p>
        <p>More than two million people die each year in the United States. Those responsible for disposing of the remains say their work is increasingly constrained by Federal, state and local laws aimed at protecting air, land and water quality.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists have questioned the effect of the industry upon the living, wondering, for instance, if buried bodies might contaminate underground water or if cremation could be a source of toxic air pollutants.</p>
        <p>"As an industry, we are concerned because environmental issues generally are the issues of the 90's," said Stephen L. Morgan, executive vice president of the American Cemetery Association. "We don't anticipate any serious environmental problems now, but we follow issues such as reauthorization of the Clean Water Act to see if there are any changes that could affect us." Concerns About Chemicals</p>
        <p>Because of concerns about underground water pollution, questions have been raised about formaldehyde and other chemicals in embalmed bodies seeping into local water tables.  In addition, blood and other body fluids removed during embalming, which may contain infectious agents or toxic chemicals used to treat cancer and other diseases, are usually flushed into the regular sewer system.</p>
        <p>No one is sure how many cemeteries there are in the nation, but Mr. Morgan said industry estimates put the number at 75,000 to 100,000. These vary in size from small churchyard plots to large military and municipal establishments.</p>
        <p>Federal officials have been discussing plans to do test drilling in some cemeteries to check water quality, but industry spokesmen said they did not expect any adverse findings.  Most graves are lined with concrete, brick, metal or other materials that should separate caskets from any ground water in places where it could be a problem, they said. In addition, they said, as yet unpublished findings from test borings done in cemeteries in Canada indicate no ground water problems.</p>
        <p>The cremation industry is facing its biggest environmental challenge from states passing air quality laws that are tougher than Federal standards. California and Florida, states with large death and burial industries because of their large populations of the elderly, have the strictest laws affecting crematoriums, said Roger E. Goodman, a Congressional aide who follows laws affecting the industry.</p>
        <p>"I don't see anything in Federal environmental law that will be a big problem for the industry, but state laws will be the most stringent," said Mr. Goodman, who is legislative director for Representative Bob Wise, Democrat of West Virginia. Dangers of Radioactivity</p>
        <p>Clean Water Action, Greenpeace and other environmental groups raising cautions about emissions from crematorium smokestacks are encouraging tougher monitoring and regulation. Greenpeace, for instance, has accused medical officials and Federal regulators of not keeping close track of people with plutonium-powered heart pacemakers. If people are cremated with those devices, the groups say, dangerous radioactive particles could be released into the air.</p>
        <p>Bob Collins of Clean Water Action, a nonprofit, Washington-based anti-pollution group, said people worried that crematorium emissions might contain mercury from dental fillings, toxic heavy metals from cancer chemotherapy and other dangerous substances. "We would encourage states to pass rigorous laws controlling emissions from crematoriums," Mr. Collins said.</p>
        <p>The Cremation Association of North America, which sponsored a workshop this month on environmental regulations and the cremation industry at its annual meeting in Toronto, says crematoriums comply with air quality laws and are not major sources of pollution.</p>
        <p>But Jack Springer, executive director of the Chicago-based group, said crematoriums were coming under undue pressure from environmental laws in some states because they were being lumped in with other incinerators, particularly those that burn medical wastes, which are being subjected to tighter regulation.</p>
        <p>"Everybody is trying to do something about clean air and there has been a groundswell of activity at the state level," Mr. Springer said. "But crematories are being caught in the same net that is trying to get major air polluters." Burning of Medical Waste</p>
        <p>At its annual meeting, the cremation association passed a resolution calling for its members not to burn hospital waste as a sideline, as some crematoriums have done. Regulated medical waste, which can include plastics, bandages and other materials, including body parts, creates many more pollutants than the cremation of human remains and requires special types of incinerators, Mr. Springer said.</p>
        <p>"To be a member of C.A.N.A., you can't burn regulated medical waste," he said. "It's hard to make an argument that we should not be regulated like medical incinerators if we burn medical waste." The 800 members of the association represent most of the industry in the United States and Canada, including virtually all the larger operators, Mr. Springer said.</p>
        <p>The industry is particularly concerned with restrictions that could hamper cremations because the practice is becoming increasingly popular in this country. Cremation can be less expensive than conventional body preparation and offers more options for either retaining or disposing of the remains, industry spokesmen said. Cremated remains can be placed in a conventional grave, placed in space-saving repositories called columbariums or scattered over land or water, options people find increasingly appealing, they added.</p>
        <p>Cremation is now used in about 17 percent of deaths, compared with 11 percent 10 years ago. The cremation association estimates that the number of operating crematories in the United States will grow from about 1,060 today to 2,600 by the year 2010, when the industry projects that 27 percent of deaths will result in cremation.</p>
        <p>Human remains are cremated in furnaces, called crematories or retorts, that use extreme heat and evaporation to essentially disintegrate all solid material except for the densest bone. After exposure to the 1,600-to-1,700-degree heat of the retort, all that remains of a body is three to nine pounds of bone fragments that are usually pulverized into sand-like grains for storage in a compact urn.</p>
        <p>Kenneth M. Robinson, president of Industrial Equipment and Engineering Company of Orlando, Fla., one of the largest manufacturers of cremators, said the gas-burning furnaces met Environmental Protection Agency emission standards and that the high temperatures produced very little particulate pollution. He said emitted gases, primarily carbon dioxide, carbon monoxide and sometimes chlorides, if plastic containers are used, were well within Federal standards if the cremators were operated properly.</p>
        <p>States, including Florida, have changed regulations to reduce pollution from incinerators, and Mr. Robinson said the resulting rules were difficult for cremators to meet without without reducing the life of the device or requiring expensive modifications.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
