<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LAWMAKERS QUERY PANELIST'S ETHICS</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="491849"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WHITE HOUSE COUNCIL ON COMPETITIVENESS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONGRESS WATCH</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">OMB WATCH</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUBBARD, ALLAN B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WAXMAN, HENRY A (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HILTS, PHILIP J</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CLEAN AIR ACT OF 1990</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DC103AF935A35751C1A967958260" item-length="886" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LAWMAKERS QUERY PANELIST'S ETHICS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP J. HILTS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HILTS, PHILIP J</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The director of the White House Council on Competitiveness, Allan B. Hubbard, helped decide a pollution rule that favored a company in which he owns stock, Representative Henry A. Waxman said today.</p>
        <p>At the same time, two advocacy groups, O.M.B. Watch and Congress Watch, called for Mr. Hubbard's resignation for what they said were conflicts involving the Clean Air Act amendments of 1990. Mr. Waxman, a California Democrat, said Mr. Hubbard's behavior was so flagrant it could be a violation of ethics law.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The director of the White House Council on Competitiveness, Allan B. Hubbard, helped decide a pollution rule that favored a company in which he owns stock, Representative Henry A. Waxman said today.</p>
        <p>At the same time, two advocacy groups, O.M.B. Watch and Congress Watch, called for Mr. Hubbard's resignation for what they said were conflicts involving the Clean Air Act amendments of 1990. Mr. Waxman, a California Democrat, said Mr. Hubbard's behavior was so flagrant it could be a violation of ethics law.</p>
        <p>But David Beckwith, a spokesman for the Competitiveness Council and Vice President Dan Quayle, who is chairman of the Council, called the issue a small matter that was entirely motivated by politics. "This is pathetic," he said. "This is just harassment because it works for them poltically."</p>
        <p>Jeff Nesbit, another spokesman for the Council, said, "This is a thinly disguised attempt by Mr. Waxman to block the Council's efforts to stop excessive regulations that cost Americans jobs and raise prices."</p>
        <p>The incident was the latest in a series that has focused attention on the council, a regulatory review panel that has been accused by Congressional critics of operating in secrecy and as a back door for business to change unwelcome Federal rules. On Nov. 22, the White House backed away from the Council's proposal to tighten the definition of wetlands when scientists said the change would open nearly half of the now-protected areas to development. A few days earlier, the Council refused to turn over documents to several Congresssional committees seeking to determine its role in Federal rule making.</p>
        <p>The White House maintains that the Council is an arm of the President's executive office and as such has all the power to review and suggest regulation that the President gives it. 'Small' Holdings</p>
        <p>The center of the latest incident, Mr. Hubbard, is a wealthy Indiana businessman who owns from 1,000 to 4,000 shares of common stock in PSI Resources, a holding company of 15 utility companies in Indiana, worth from $15,000 to $50,000, according to his financial disclosure statements.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nesbit said: "Mr. Hubbard fully disclosed his holdings in PSI when he joined the government. They are very small."</p>
        <p>PSI's companies, which the Environmental Protection Agency lists as among the largest utility polluters in the nation, sent letters to the Government asking for a relaxation of a proposed pollution rule on acid rain, saying it was a "major concern" that, along with other proposals, would "greatly impact" their business, according to a report by O.M.B. Watch and Congress Watch.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. rejected the company's plea. But when the E.P.A.'s proposal was reviewed by the Council on Competitiveness, at a meeting on Oct. 16 led by Mr. Hubbard, the Council chose a less-restrictive version of the proposal that would, in effect, allow industry not to count its worst days of pollution in measuring smokestack emissions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Waxman, who is chairman of the House Energy and Commerce Subcommittee on Health and the Environment, said he plans to hold a hearing on the matter. Waiver From Conflict Rules</p>
        <p>Federal employees are prohibited by law from participating "personally and substantially" in matters where they have a financial interest. Mr. Hubbard asked Mr. Quayle for a waiver from these conflict of interest rules, which was granted him in June. It permitted him to take part in matters that might affect companies in which he has a financial interest, as long as his interest was not substantial.</p>
        <p>Such waivers are common at the senior levels of government because many such officials come from positions in business. Unless small conflicts can be waived, few would be able to work in government, said members of Mr. Quayle's legal staff.</p>
        <p>Jane Ley, an official of the Office on Government Ethics, an independent Federal agency, said that from a brief reading of the documents involved, Mr. Hubbard's case is not clear. The money involved, between $15,000 and $50,000, may not be a substantial amount to Mr. Hubbard, Ms. Ley said.</p>
        <p>Also, she said, the regulations he was helping to rewrite might be considered to be about pollution in general, and not about the utility industry or his company in particular.</p>
        <p>Representative John Conyers Jr., a Michigan Democrat who is chairman of the House Government Operations Committee, which is investigating Mr. Hubbard's actions, today said that a major question was whether Mr. Hubbard worked on clean air regulations before he got the waiver in June. It is not yet clear what matters he took part in before the waiver was granted.</p>
        <p>An action like Mr. Hubbard's on the pollution rule, if it occurred before the waiver was issued, could possibly be a criminal conflict of interest, Ms. Ley said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Waxman called the waiver "highly questionable." He added, "In any event, Mr. Hubbard's actions in this case appear to be so flagrant that they may not be legal by the waiver."</p>
        <p>He also said that Mr. Hubbard has between $365,000 and $850,000 in the bonds of utility companies, which might increase his financial interest.</p>
        <p>William G. Rosenberg, who directs the E.P.A's air pollution efforts, said that the specific rule considered by the Competitiveness Council would have very little effect on pollution. .</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
