<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PACT IS REACHED TO REDUCE NUCLEAR ARMS; BUSH AND GORBACHEV TO MEET THIS MONTH; 7 POWERS GIVE SOVIETS NEW ECONOMIC ROLE</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="461015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="SUMMIT IN LONDON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">US-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-USSR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMS CONTROL AND LIMITATION AND DISARMAMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">APPLE, R W JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORBACHEV, MIKHAIL S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DE163FF93BA25754C0A967958260" item-length="2112" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PACT IS REACHED TO REDUCE NUCLEAR ARMS; BUSH AND GORBACHEV TO MEET THIS MONTH; 7 POWERS GIVE SOVIETS NEW ECONOMIC ROLE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R. W. APPLE Jr.,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">APPLE, R W JR</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, July 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After nine years of negotiation, the Soviet Union and the United States reached agreement today on a strategic arms treaty, the first to mandate reductions by the superpowers, and President Bush immediately agreed to meet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev in Moscow late this month.</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Gorbachev, the proud leader of the nation where Communism first flowered, sat down with the heads of the seven most powerful capitalist nations and asked them for help in reforming an economic system that has all but collapsed. Almost 75 years after the Bolshevik Revolution, the Soviet President's pleas represented an admission of economic failure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After nine years of negotiation, the Soviet Union and the United States reached agreement today on a strategic arms treaty, the first to mandate reductions by the superpowers, and President Bush immediately agreed to meet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev in Moscow late this month.</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Gorbachev, the proud leader of the nation where Communism first flowered, sat down with the heads of the seven most powerful capitalist nations and asked them for help in reforming an economic system that has all but collapsed. Almost 75 years after the Bolshevik Revolution, the Soviet President's pleas represented an admission of economic failure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gorbachev laid his plans before the Western leaders in what another participant described as "an eloquent performance." Officials taking part in the closed meeting reported that Mr. Gorbachev insisted that Soviet progress toward a market economy and private ownership of property was irreversible, but that he made no new proposals. Gorbachev's Courage Hailed PHE&gt;</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Mr. Gorbachev won praise from the leaders of the seven countries -- the Group of Seven. Mr. Bush said the Soviet leader had shown "enormous courage" in pushing ahead with reforms.</p>
        <p>"It's not going to be quick or easy to implement change in the Soviet Union," Mr. Bush said after the meeting, "but we believe President Gorbachev has made an irrevocable commitment."</p>
        <p>Britain's Prime Minister, John Major, who played host to the group's 17th annual economic summit meeting, said: "This has been a day I believe that history may well see as a landmark. It will be seen as a first step toward helping the Soviet Union become a full member of the world economic community."  [ Excerpts from the Bush-Gorbachev and Gorbachev-Major news conferences, and from the summit's economic declaration, are on pages A10 and A12. ]</p>
        <p>The Moscow meeting was tentatively scheduled for July 30-31.</p>
        <p>Under the provisions of the arms treaty to be signed there, the overall number of nuclear weapons in each side's arsenal will be cut by 25 to 35 percent. The American arsenal will be reduced from about 12,000 warheads and bombs to about 9,000, while Moscow's stockpile is to be reduced from roughly 11,000 to roughly 7,000.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Gorbachev made no specific requests for immediate financial assistance, officials of several nations said, and left little time for questions, he asked the group to "take a step forward" in developing greater cooperation with his country.</p>
        <p>"The ice has started moving; the icebreaker is on its way toward renewal," the Soviet leader told reporters later. But he quickly added, "There is need for movement from the other side," meaning the West.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gorbachev came away with the prospect of a bit more Western aid than had seemed likely a few days ago, including pledges of a "special association" with the International Monetary Fund and the World Bank, extensive programs of technical assistance and an early visit to Moscow by the group's finance ministers to discuss further measures. But he won no promise of major infusions of cash.</p>
        <p>In addition, German officials promised that they would invite the Soviet leader to attend next year's economic summit conference in Munich, and President Francois Mitterrand of France said that he favored ultimately asking the Soviet Union to join the club, making it a Group of Eight.</p>
        <p>At the news conference tonight, Mr. Major said the meeting had established "a partnership with the Soviet Union on a new and better footing," as a first step toward Moscow's integration into the world economic system.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gorbachev called the three-hour session "one of the most important meetings of our time."</p>
        <p>"Today has meant a lot," the seemingly weary Soviet leader said.</p>
        <p>"It's been a good day for the United States," Mr. Bush replied. A Qualified Success</p>
        <p>Merely by winning admission to the forum of capitalist leaders this week, Mr. Gorbachev can claim a victory. But some things that most of the participants would have liked to give him, including full membership now or soon in the International Monetary Fund and greater drawing rights at the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development, were blocked by the United States and Japan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gorbachev had to overcome American opposition and that of hard-liners in his own country to gain an invitation to London. Still, some members of the Gorbachev delegation expressed open disappointment today with what he had achieved. One said that "the Soviet Union doesn't understand Western economics, and the Western nations don't understand Soviet politics."</p>
        <p>Still, the arms accord is likely to help Mr. Gorbachev with his increasingly restive people, as it will free scarce resources for domestic concerns.</p>
        <p>By the time that the strategic arms reduction treaty is carried out, probably in 1999, the number of American warheads on weapons that can reach the Soviet Union will drop by about 25 percent, and the comparable Soviet total will fall by about 35 percent. The treaty puts sub-limits on various weapons systems and is particularly tough on the Soviet SS-18 missile, the most powerful in either arsenal.</p>
        <p>For two days, the prospect of Mr. Gorbachev's arrival here had hung over those attending the conference -- the leaders of Britain, the United States, France, Canada, Italy, Germany and Japan. Today, as his motorcade of Zil limousines flashed across central London from one meeting to another, he utterly dominated the scene, eclipsing and in some cases eliminating debate on other issues.</p>
        <p>The summit conference never really came to grips with the environment, referring discussion of global warming and the rain forests to a United Nations conference next year on the subject and thus avoiding an all-out clash between the United States and the Europeans, especially Britain. Tariff Issue Deferred</p>
        <p>On another difficult matter, described by everyone as crucial, the group merely pledged to complete by the end of the year the current round of talks designed to bring up to date the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade. This is precisely what was promised in Houston a year ago and not delivered.</p>
        <p>Mr. Major, who presided over this week's sessions in a bright and breezy way that contrasted sharply with the stern, hectoring manner of his predecessor, Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher, said it had been "a friendly and very frank summit." He added, "People did speak their minds clearly and comprehensively and on occasions in an unforgettable way."</p>
        <p>Much of the groundwork was laid before today. Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d and Aleksandr A. Bessmertnykh, the Soviet Foreign Minister, had resolved all outstanding questions on the all-important arms treaty, except one technical issue, at a series of meetings in Washington that ended Sunday. That related to the definition of a new missile, in terms of its throw-weight, or destructive capacity, for treaty purposes.</p>
        <p>White House aides said Mr. Bessmertnykh asked this morning for a meeting with Mr. Baker just before Mr. Bush and Mr. Gorbachev were to meet for lunch at the United States Ambassador's residence. A senior American official said the Foreign Minister brought new proposals, and after a flurry of conferences, the President and his advisers agreed that the final obstacle had been overcome. 'Our Hospitality'</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and Mr. Gorbachev spent most of their lunch discussing economic and other matters, then slipped into an adjoining room to ratify what had been agreed to on arms.</p>
        <p>Beaming, the two men met briefly with reporters, Mr. Gorbachev saying that his country was "ready to give our hospitality to the President of the United States and Mrs. Bush." He had sought the Moscow meeting for the last year.</p>
        <p>"Before you change your mind, we accept with pleasure," replied Mr. Bush, who had held out for the treaty as a condition for making the trip.</p>
        <p>Neither side was willing to specify what the final arrangement was, because neither wanted to appear to have made the final concession, lest it be seen as soft by the legislative hard-liners in Washington and Moscow whose backing will be needed if the treaty is to be ratified.</p>
        <p>British and American experts said the difficulties in reaching agreement were more political than military. The Soviet Union is believed to be developing a more advanced, more powerful version of one of its missiles.</p>
        <p>The Administration wanted to head that off, remembering the deployment of the SS-19 after the 1972 anti-ballistic missile treaty. Critics of the 1972 agreement charged that its negotiators had failed to get tight enough language. Gorbachev Explains His Country</p>
        <p>At his meeting with the Group of Seven, Mr. Gorbachev made no specific requests for monetary aid.</p>
        <p>"He really was trying to explain more what was going on inside the Soviet Union, what the pressures were, what he was up against in terms of history, if you will," Mr. Bush reported. "He really stopped short of what some predicted might be on his agenda."</p>
        <p>Mr. Major reportedly opened the meeting by telling the Soviet leader: "You are among well-wishers. The challenges you face are formidable, but the opportunities are limitless."</p>
        <p>He said candidly, however, that the West expected reform in property rights, market prices, the breakup of state monopolies and the establishment of a Western-style legal system.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gorbachev, in turn, spoke of the need to dismantle barriers to the Soviet economy, including trade restrictions and lack of access to loans.</p>
        <p>Daniel Bernard, the French spokesman, described the Russian's presentation as a "particularly rich" 30-minute speech that dealt with the relationship of the Soviet republics to the central Government in Moscow and with his own reform intentions.</p>
        <p>A British official said Mr. Gorbachev's explanation of his economic policies today was not significantly different from the plan detailed in a 23-page letter he sent to the seven leaders last week.</p>
        <p>According to one official, Mr. Gorbachev's one-hour opening statement this afternoon and his remarks at the news conference tonight were not "very specific on details."</p>
        <p>He left unclear, this official said, the answers to such questions as exactly how the Soviets intended to privatize state-owned enterprises and liberalize controlled prices.</p>
        <p>"There was movement in the right direction," an official said, adding that Mr. Major would try to get clarification during his talks with Mr. Gorbachev here Thursday.</p>
        <p>In a briefing tonight, Mr. Gorbachev's chief spokesman, Vitaly Ignatenko, disclosed few details of the private discussions today. He did say that Mr. Gorbachev had discussed the need to create a stabilization fund to bolster the ruble, as a way to more quickly complete the conversion of the ruble on international currency markets. However, he did not seek Western aid for such a fund. "Today was not the occasion" for that, Mr. Major explained. Status of Soviet Republics</p>
        <p>Mr. Ignatenko said Mr. Gorbachev spoke at length about the relationship between the central Government and the republics, and assured Western leaders that he had a mandate to speak for all the Soviet Union in his attempts to press forward with an agenda of economic reform.</p>
        <p>A six-point program of assistance was ultimately agreed on, but some of the points struck economists as imprecise and redundant, an attempt to make a small package look bigger. The Western summit partners committed themselves to these goals:</p>
        <p>*Setting up the special relationship with the International Monetary Fund and the World Bank, leaving it up to the institutions and the Soviet Union to negotiate the terms.</p>
        <p>*Urging other international organizations to make their knowledge and skills available to Moscow.</p>
        <p>*Offering technical assistance to help the Soviets exploit energy resources, improve food distribution, increase nuclear safety, make their transportation system more efficient and convert military industries to civilian ones.</p>
        <p>*Helping expand trade with the West and with Eastern European nations.</p>
        <p>*Sending Mr. Major to Moscow before the end of the year to check on the progress of reform and, if appropriate, to recommend further Western aid.</p>
        <p>*Sending the finance ministers' group to Moscow very soon.</p>
        <p>Chancellor Helmut Kohl of Germany, which has supplied most of the Western aid to the Soviet Union in the last year, had hoped for bolder action. But he spoke of "a good start."</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitterrand said "we must, really must, reach out," and his aides said that he, too, would have liked to do much more to help the beleaguered Mr. Gorbachev than was agreed to in London.  SUMMIT IN LONDON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
