<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OZONE DEPLETION HARMING SEA LIFE</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="487209"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTICA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEILER, C SUSAN (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D91F3CF935A25752C1A967958260" item-length="821" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OZONE DEPLETION HARMING SEA LIFE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A leading marine scientist said today that the thinning of the atmospheric ozone layer over Antarctica had allowed ultraviolet radiation to penetrate much deeper into the ocean than suspected, causing sizable reductions in the productivity of the single-cell organisms that form the base of the oceanic food chain.</p>
        <p>Dr. C. Susan Weiler, a marine ecologist at Whitman College in Walla Walla, Wash., and executive director of the American Society of Limnology and Oceanography, also said that rising ultraviolet radiation in the Antarctic had caused increased genetic damage in the organisms, phytoplankton.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A leading marine scientist said today that the thinning of the atmospheric ozone layer over Antarctica had allowed ultraviolet radiation to penetrate much deeper into the ocean than suspected, causing sizable reductions in the productivity of the single-cell organisms that form the base of the oceanic food chain.</p>
        <p>Dr. C. Susan Weiler, a marine ecologist at Whitman College in Walla Walla, Wash., and executive director of the American Society of Limnology and Oceanography, also said that rising ultraviolet radiation in the Antarctic had caused increased genetic damage in the organisms, phytoplankton.</p>
        <p>The new findings are among the first clear signals that the weakening of the atmospheric ozone shield, which scientists say is caused by chlorine and bromine-based industrial chemicals, is having a measurable effect on marine organisms. Since 1987, scientists in Antarctica have measured reductions in phytoplankton mass of 6 to 12 percent, depending on the depth of the water, Dr. Weiler said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Weiler, a member of a United Nations scientific panel studying the depletion of the ozone layer, said the results of the research in Antarctica raised new concerns about the effect of increased ultraviolet radiation on the oceans, which supply most of the earth's oxygen and much of its food.</p>
        <p>"Increasing ultraviolet radiation could change species abundance and variety of phytoplankton and ripple through the food chain, having effects we really can't predict," she said. Concerns About Cancer</p>
        <p>Dr. Weiler joined nine other top scientists in discussing the ozone depletion problem today at a hearing held by Senator Al Gore, a Tennessee Democrat who is chairman of the Senate Commerce, Science and Transportation Committee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, citing Dr. Weiler's report and several others predicting much higher rates of skin cancer deaths and blindness from cataracts because of ultraviolet radiation, called on the Bush Administration to speed up the removal of chemicals from commerce that deplete the ozone shield. "The evidence is clearer than ever," he said.</p>
        <p>William K. Reilly, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, said later, "The United States will move faster than the treaty obligates us to," referring to the 1987 international agreement that set schedules for gradually eliminating ozone-depleting chemicals. "How much faster is something we have not worked out within the Administration yet, but it will be considerably faster. This latest data should provide a convincing reason for the rest of the world community to move with us."</p>
        <p>Near the top layers of the earth's atmosphere is a belt of ozone that naturally screens harmful ultraviolet radiation and prevents much of it from reaching the earth's surface.</p>
        <p>In the mid-1970's, scientists theorized that chlorofluorocarbons, nearly indestructible chlorine-based industrial chemicals used as refrigerants and solvents, were floating up into the top most layers of the atmosphere and through a multi-step chemical process was dissolving the ozone shield. Other compounds also have been found to be destroying the ozone shield, including the insecticide methyl bromide; methyl chloroform, a chemical used in solvents and adhesives, and halons, which are used in fire extinguishers.</p>
        <p>In the 1980's, scientists discovered a gap in the ozone shield over Antarctica, a finding that helped convince the major industrial nations to sign a treaty in Montreal in 1987 to cut in half production of the destructive chemicals by the year 2000. In 1990 the treaty was amended to require elimination of chlorofluorocarbons and halons by the year 2000, and methyl chloroform by 2005.  Congress Takes Action</p>
        <p>Last year, as part of the Clean Air Act, Congress approved a provision requiring the President to speed the schedule for phasing out the chemicals causing ozone depletion if new evidence warranted it. In October, a United Nations scientific panel said the rate of ozone destruction was increasing and that the shield was weakening over the United States and other temperate zones in the winter and summer. Scientists had previously said that ozone depletion was occurring only over the poles and in middle latitudes in winter.</p>
        <p>The scientists said today that the only region of the earth's ozone shield untouched so far was over the Equator.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robert T. Watson, an upper atmosphere expert at the National Aeronautics and Space Administration in Washington, said even if all ozone-destroying chemicals were outlawed today, thinning would continue for decades because of all the chemicals that had already risen into the upper atmosphere.</p>
        <p>A major worry is the effect more ultraviolet radiation would have on crops. Dr. Alan H. Teramura, a botanist at the University of Maryland, said research in laboratories had found decreases in yield from soybeans and rice exposed to rising levels of ultraviolet radiation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
