<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Champion of the Deep</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="454777"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DIVING AND DIVERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL OCEANIC AND ATMOSPHERIC ADMINISTRATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ORENSTEIN, PEGGY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">EARLE, SYLVIA (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">EARLE, SYLVIA (BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Snorkeling and Diving</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diving and Divers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDE163DF930A15755C0A967958260" item-length="5103" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Champion of the Deep</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PEGGY ORENSTEIN;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ORENSTEIN, PEGGY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A MILE OFF THE Florida Keys, and 80 feet down, the silence is thicker and more majestic than anywhere on land. There is no splash of surf, no whisper of wind, no hum of insect or avian life. There is only the long, rhythmic pull of air from our scuba tanks as we glide past the complicated tangles of coral and gently waving sea fans of Molasses Reef. At this depth, reds and yellows begin to fade and darker colors take on the richness of twilight. Below us, a six-foot-long iridescent green eel blocks the entrance to his coral cave, watching until we are safely out of sight. To the left, the reef rolls down into darkness, into what is literally -- even to the most experienced divers, who generally go no more than about 100 to 150 feet deep -- the unfathomable.</p>
        <p>I try to imagine diving untethered to 1,250 feet, the record-breaking depth to which the woman I am with, Dr. Sylvia A. Earle, has ventured. The recently appointed chief scientist of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration and one of the world's foremost divers, Earle was also one of the first three pilots to take a one-person submersible vessel to a depth of 3,000 feet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A MILE OFF THE Florida Keys, and 80 feet down, the silence is thicker and more majestic than anywhere on land. There is no splash of surf, no whisper of wind, no hum of insect or avian life. There is only the long, rhythmic pull of air from our scuba tanks as we glide past the complicated tangles of coral and gently waving sea fans of Molasses Reef. At this depth, reds and yellows begin to fade and darker colors take on the richness of twilight. Below us, a six-foot-long iridescent green eel blocks the entrance to his coral cave, watching until we are safely out of sight. To the left, the reef rolls down into darkness, into what is literally -- even to the most experienced divers, who generally go no more than about 100 to 150 feet deep -- the unfathomable.</p>
        <p>I try to imagine diving untethered to 1,250 feet, the record-breaking depth to which the woman I am with, Dr. Sylvia A. Earle, has ventured. The recently appointed chief scientist of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration and one of the world's foremost divers, Earle was also one of the first three pilots to take a one-person submersible vessel to a depth of 3,000 feet.</p>
        <p>And now she hopes to reach and explore one day soon the deepest-known point in the ocean, a very, very dark 35,800 feet. This is the depth to which she believes marine science must sink in order to understand, and preserve, this planet.</p>
        <p>While most of us call home the 33 percent of the earth above the shoreline, Sylvia Earle thrives at the lower depths. At 55, she has logged more than 5,000 hours under the sea as an aquanaut and marine biologist, including a two-week continuous stint in 1970, discovering and cataloguing previously unknown species of marine life. Admirers have christened both ocean critters and plants in her name (divers may chance upon the sea urchin</p>
        <p>Diadema sylvie</p>
        <p>or the underwater plant</p>
        <p>Pilina earli</p>
        <p>).</p>
        <p>"People are under the impression that the planet is fully explored," she says of her journeys to inner space, "that we've been to all the forests and climbed all the mountains. But in fact many of the forests have yet to be seen for the first time. They just happen to be underwater. We're still explorers. Perhaps the greatest era is just beginning."</p>
        <p>It is generally accurate to precede Earle's achievements with the label "first woman" -- as in first woman to be chief scientist at the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) -- but that mitigates their significance. For</p>
        <p>anyone</p>
        <p>to have racked up as many laurels as Earle has is remarkable. The fact that she has done so at a time when female scientists continue to be denied research opportunities (and were until recently considered bad luck on a boat) simply gives her success extra resonance.</p>
        <p>It has also given her a public profile, and now Earle's NOAA position, as a liaison between the agency and the public, gives her national clout. A branch of the Department of Commerce, NOAA provides the scientific data for policy-making agencies like the Environmental Protection Agency, predicts the weather (through the National Weather Service) and oversees the nation's fisheries, estuaries and marine mammal program. In the last few years, the agency has increased its prominence by playing a pivotal role in charting global warming trends and in the prosecution of Exxon on grounds of negligence in Prince William Sound.</p>
        <p>EARLE HAD PLANNED TO use her NOAA post to push for more marine sanctuaries, to mediate between industry and environmentalists and to work against the dumping of garbage and toxic waste into the sea. ("People used to think, 'the solution to pollution is dilution.' That's why there's radioactive waste in the Farallones, off San Francisco.") But two months after her appointment, war broke out in the Middle East, and the world's largest oil spill was one of the consequences. NOAA is leading the American end of the international assessment of the damage as well as studying the environmental impact of the oil-well fires that have plunged Kuwait into a greasy twilight. Since March, Earle has been preoccupied with helping to coordinate those efforts.</p>
        <p>"NOAA has a lot of experience responding to oil spills and catastrophes of all sorts," she said a few weeks ago, just before her third trip to the region, "but nothing,</p>
        <p>nothing,</p>
        <p>has prepared anyone for this kind of spill, for this magnitude."</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Deep Ocean Engineering, the company she founded in 1981 with her husband, Graham Hawkes, an engineer, has been making plans to launch Deep Flight, an easy-to-use one-person submersible that Hawkes designed. This summer a pair of the tiny aerodynamic vehicles, constructed on nights and weekends by an all-volunteer crew, will zip down to 4,000 feet and, as Earle says, "do barrel rolls with the whales." Earle and Hawkes plan to be inside.</p>
        <p>But that's just for the maiden voyage. Earle hopes that Deep Flight's ease of operation will someday coax even nondivers into the sea. "Right now so few of us have had the experience of flying through a dark ocean," she says, "of watching the lights of a luminescent creature flash all around us and wondering at their sheer beauty and their influence on the planet as a whole. If a critical mass of people had the opportunity to see the ocean from the inside out there would be far more respect for what we're losing, far more concern."</p>
        <p>WHEN SHE IS WET, SYLVIA Earle is gorgeous. Her Katharine Hepburn cheekbones glow under huge, dark eyes. Her small frame is as agile as a sea nymph's. Dried off and on land, though, she looks a bit like a fish out of water. When we first meet at the San Leandro, Calif., offices of Deep Ocean Engineering, she seems tiny and vulnerable, almost frail in the green sweater, black slacks and down boots protecting against an arctic cold snap gripping the West Coast, her apparent unease betrayed by a slight hunch and a habit of ducking her head when she breaks into her frequent and stunning smile.</p>
        <p>But when Earle starts discussing the motivation behind her work, the amiable shyness disappears. Her voice becomes urgent, and she talks in complete sentences -- sometimes complete paragraphs.</p>
        <p>"Everyone says that they have these childhood memories of blue oceans and green grass and trees and that now things aren't what they used to be," she says as we drive through the groves of drought-browned Eucalyptus covering northern California. "And that's not just the early childhood perspective. There aren't trees where there used to be. Oceans aren't as blue. I grew up in Clearwater, Fla., which doesn't live up to its name anymore.  And it's all happened so fast --</p>
        <p>geological</p>
        <p>time has become something that happens in lifetimes. We've burned through our resources thinking there's always more, but the world has become suddenly small. We have to start recognizing that it's all one system and it's in our own best interests to take care of the place."</p>
        <p>Earle's entire life has been oriented toward the ocean -- she began diving at 17, using a helmet, compressed air and weights to explore the bottom of a Florida riverbed. A few years later, while working toward a degree in marine botany at Florida State, she was among the early devotees of scuba -- which was invented in 1943 -- always with an eye toward going deeper, seeing more and using the information for conservation.</p>
        <p>"Underlying everything Sylvia does is a tremendously deep love of the sea," says Frank H. Talbot, the director of the National Museum of Natural History at the Smithsonian Institution and a former colleague of Earle's at the California Academy of Sciences. "I think Sylvia's strength comes from the sea, from its wildness and beauty."</p>
        <p>Al Giddings, a director-producer of natural-history films, says, "Some people were born with that little blue flame, and she certainly was." Giddings has worked with Earle on a number of projects, including the filming of her record-breaking 1,250-foot dive off the coast of Hawaii in 1979. "We met and she was moving at Mach 10," he says. "When we went off our separate ways, she was still moving at the same speed."</p>
        <p>Earle's home in the hills of Oakland, Calif., is more laboratory than living space, including a test pool to check her submersibles for leaks. Inside the house there is endless ocean memorabilia -- shells, seaweed, pictures of dolphins -- a large number of tailless black cats, a tired black lab named Blue and a group of rare lizards presided over by Elizabeth, Earle's 30-year-old daughter, who is herself nicknamed Lizard. She and her younger brother, John (called Richie), are the offspring of Earle's first marriage, to John Taylor, a zoologist. The marriage ended in 1966. Her youngest child, Gale (or Mouse), 21, is the product of a nine-year marriage to Dr. Giles Mead, a fellow marine scientist; they were divorced in 1976. Earle separated from Graham Hawkes last year, though they continue to work together. When she speaks of the breakup, her voice trembles.</p>
        <p>"I was always trying to combine everything, combine science and traditional expectations," she says. "And I suppose it never occurred to me that there had to be a choice, or at least it didn't until quite recently. I'm beginning now to think I've had choices thrust upon me. In this case it was on Graham's side. He decided he wanted more than I was able to deliver."</p>
        <p>Earle pauses for a long time, staring out the window toward the pool and the equipment surrounding it. "But it's repeatedly been my choice to opt for a career as a scientist -- if you want to call 'being a scientist' a career. A scientist is what I am. It's who and what I am, fundamentally, beyond being a woman, beyond being a wife or beyond being a mother. It's just who I am."</p>
        <p>To underscore her point, she leads me through the house and into a side room, the most important room in the house for someone of her dedication. This is Earle's "plantorium": shelves upon shelves of thick-paged folders in which she has labeled and carefully pressed more than 20,000 plants. It is her lifework.</p>
        <p>One of her goals is to create a complete catalogue of the Gulf of Mexico's plant life. The collection includes plants she pressed 30 years ago, and plants pressed by others as far back as the 16th century. Though a great deal of it is from the Gulf of Mexico, she also has flora from the Indian Ocean, the Tortugas and the Virgin Islands. Earle does what she calls "basic exploration" -- like a 19th-century naturalist who combed the beaches and stalked the Alps with nothing but a walking stick and a notebook. "And it's wonderful," she says. "I prefer using the ocean as a lab to spending much time within four walls, although I've spent a considerable amount of time analyzing material. It's like discovering and cataloguing all the life on a new planet. What are the factors that influence the survival of a species? What nutrients does it need to survive? What is its interaction with predators and prey?"</p>
        <p>Earle has published her discoveries in more than 80 scientific and popular journals, including National Geographic. But she'll need a lot more shelf space if she hopes to complete her cataloguing. "If you study plants you look at everything -- geology, chemistry of the environment," she says. "Plants are the energy base for the whole system. A tree is not a tree all by itself. It hosts jillions of creatures -- birds, insects, fungi. Botany leads to the universe."</p>
        <p>IT WAS IN THE VIRGIN ISLANDS that Sylvia Earle embarked, in 1970, on the project that convinced her of the need to push back the frontier of the ocean's accessibility and gave her the prominence to try.</p>
        <p>Tektite, a government-sponsored program that began in 1969, just as the Apollo astronauts prepared for the lunar landing, offered several teams of scientists the opportunity to live and study for two weeks each on an undersea reef off the coast of the Caribbean island of St. John. Earle headed an all-female team. (The project paved the way for the inclusion of women in the space program.) "It was totally unacceptable for men and women to live together underwater in those days," Earle says. "Out of the question."</p>
        <p>The two-week stay was a revelation. "I wasn't prepared for how valuable the extended time could be," Earle says now. "To be able to watch a whole process in action, to be able to see a fish go through its complete spawning routine, to get to know individual fish,</p>
        <p>that</p>
        <p>eel living over there, not a different eel -- it was like being able to sit and listen to a whole symphony instead of just catching snatches of a piece of music."</p>
        <p>Earle surfaced to an unexpected flurry of fame. The women's team was greeted in Chicago with a ticker-tape parade, written about in Life magazine, featured in Tang commercials and on the "Today" show, celebrated at the White House. "There was this irresistible, almost patronizing inclination to look at the women's team, that women had done this," she says. "So I -- all of us -- tried to twist the women's angle back to the real issue, that the ocean was being noticed."</p>
        <p>But when it came to funds and public support, the country was looking upward. "NASA has had a very vigorous public relations program, whereas the oceans never had that kind of focused voice," Earle explains. "Part of it is you can't watch a submarine launch with the same heart-stopping emotion as a space launch. It doesn't have the same power -- the noise and smoke and all the rest is so exciting. A submarine just slips in the water and that's it. But some of it is more fundamental. We're terrestrial beings and we resist going underwater. We should resist going into space too, but we have as part of our heritage that goodness is skyward. We can see the moon. We can envision walking on it. No one can envision walking on the sea floor the same way."</p>
        <p>While the whole world watched as Neil Armstrong and Edwin (Buzz) Aldrin planted the flag on the moon in 1969, a sole underwater camera recorded the moment, 10 years later, when Sylvia Earle planted the Stars and Stripes on the ocean floor. It was history's deepest untethered dive. Wearing a NASA-like construction called a Jim suit, with a manipulative arm, she descended to 1,250 feet strapped to the front of a submarine."When it got to the bottom," she says, "I stepped off and walked on the ocean floor for two and a half hours. It was a nice parallel: that's about how long Buzz Aldrin and Neil Armstrong were on the moon. It took them longer to get there, of course, and it cost more. But I had the fun of seeing all kinds of critters out there. Like the seven large rays that came gliding by, and the big crabs stalking on the sea floor, or the spiral coral that flashed with blue fire, with luminescence when I touched them. The place was so obviously alive with creatures."</p>
        <p>That magic was laced with danger -- at that depth the 600 pounds of pressure per square inch could have crushed Earle if things had gone awry. Communication between the submarine and Earle sputtered out for several minutes. "That may not sound like a long time," says Al Giddings, who helped coordinate the project and was filming it from inside the submarine, "but at that depth, when you don't know what's going on with the person in the suit, it's very tense."</p>
        <p>But the experience left Earle determined to push deeper, to chart the terrain that is still largely depicted in atlases by an artist's rendering. "There's a sense with the ocean that if you've seen 5 percent, you've seen it all," Earle says. "It's such a fallacy. There are so many variations in terms of systems. Maps of the planet show deserts, forests, all kind of jungles carved up into biological and physical patterns. The oceans are simply blue."</p>
        <p>It was on that record-setting expedition that she met Hawkes, a British engineer who had designed the diving suit she wore. As she and Hawkes fell in love, she pressed him on his own passion for the deep sea. "I wanted to find a way to go to the deepest part of the ocean right now. I would say to him, 'We can go almost anywhere else we want to on the planet, why not there?' "</p>
        <p>Lacking public funds for their project, Earle and Hawkes hatched a scheme for a business venture. In 1981, they founded Deep Ocean Engineering and began constructing an underwater robot that they hoped to sell commercially. (The Phantom, an unmanned submersible equipped with a video camera, was completed in 1985. So far they've sold 215, at a cost of $20,000 to $250,000, depending on the kind of system and accessories chosen.) In 1984, they unveiled Deep Rover, a one-person submersible, whichsoon after set the world's solo dive record -- going to 3,000 feet -- the first time with Hawkes aboard, and two more times immediately after, piloted by Earle and then by Phil Nuytten, the president of Can-Dive Services in Vancouver. Transportable by helicopter, the vehicle is simple to operate, freeing its occupant to concentrate on oceanographic work.</p>
        <p>Deep Rover was designed for inspecting offshore oil rigs, but it has mainly been used for exploring and research. "With Deep Rover, we found a great many more animals in the ocean than we could have measured based on conventional methods like dragging nets," says Bruce H. Robison, senior scientist at the Monterey Bay Aquarium Research Institute in Pacific Grove, Calif., who has been using the craft on and off since 1985. "The nets undersample what we thought we were catching reliably. When you're down there you can see that the water column is an important habitat for gelatinous animals, which are very fragile but abundant. If you drag a net through you turn them into mush. You can't tell how many or what kind they were."</p>
        <p>Neither Deep Rover nor Phantom has made Earle and Hawkes rich. They've sold one Deep Rover, at a cost of $1 million, to Can-Dive Services, which leases it back for projects led by Robison, Earle and others. But the company gave them a base from which to troll for the seed money -- from National Geographic, Television New Zealand and the IMAX film company, as well as their own pockets -- for their next step: Deep Flight.</p>
        <p>IT'S 11:00 ON A TUESDAY night in the airplane-hangar-size back room of Deep Ocean Engineering, and a volunteer group of teachers, engineers, students and nurses who call themselves "the pod squad" are hard at work to the rock beat of the B-52's. They are busily cutting, sanding and smearing fiberglass onto the hull of a transparent 14-foot capsule with stubby wings that looks straight out of the adventures of Tom Swift.</p>
        <p>Deep Flight carries the principles of Deep Rover a step further. The crew compares the vehicle to an airplane, and the submersibles that came before it to dirigibles. Its blunt wings are filled with silicon particles similar to miniature balloons and are fastened like upside-down airfoils to give the vehicle lift while keeping it lean. Its acrylic, pressure-resistant dome affords its pilot a panoramic view. It is small enough to be stowed in the hull of an airplane and, in the event of a disaster, can be on the spot in a matter of hours, ready to plumb for salvageable wreckage. The capsule is also positively buoyant, so that in case of a power failure or other emergency, it bobs back to the surface.</p>
        <p>Earle says Deep Flight's greater speed and maneuverability will make it possible to explore wide areas and to operate in places inaccessible to large vessels. It will "allow the kind of exploration in the sea that has been done in space," she says. Deep Flight may even open up the deep ocean for recreational divers. "You can think where you want to go and just go -- like it's an extension of yourself," says Earle. "There's a wonderful joy in that."</p>
        <p>The pod squad clearly shares her enthusiasm for the project. "This will change the way people look at submersibles," says Mike Hughes, Deep Flight's volunteer coordinator. "It's going to be fun to use. Sylvia's idea is to make people fall in love with the ocean, and this is a great way to do it."</p>
        <p>From a practical standpoint, Deep Flight's innovations seem almost elementary -- as does the very concept of a positively buoyant sub. Even as he points them out, Hawkes, who designed Deep Flight, impatiently dismisses his creation as a Model-T, built in an era that has the technology to build a Maserati. Sitting in the company's conference room, Hawkes rails against the thinking that has kept him from the bottom of the sea. "In aviation there's a tremendous spirit of adventure," he says. "Breaking a record is always a good enough reason to do something. But the subsea people are so stuffy that no one builds crafts just to push a frontier back. Chuck Yeager was totally impractical. Breaking the sound barrier had no use whatsoever when he did it. But a few years later we have the Concorde. We haven't done anything in the sea for 30 years."</p>
        <p>THE NEXT PROJECT for Earle and Hawkes, Ocean Everest, a $10 million cluster of single-person submersibles, will eventually allow aquanauts to travel -- in an almost routine sort of way -- 35,800 feet to the deepest known part of the sea.</p>
        <p>"Round trip," Earle hastens to add when explaining the project. "It's easy to go one way."</p>
        <p>Hawkes is already at work on plans for the vehicle, which he hopes will allow Earle to become the Chuck Yeager of the sea. Ocean Everest will probably be made of transparent ceramic-based materials similar to those used in Deep Flight, and will fly down to the bottom of the Marianas Trench in the Pacific at the rate of 600 feet per minute. That's more than six times faster than the descent rate of larger vehicles like the Sea Cliff, a Navy submersible that can make the trip only partway down. But while the idea has generated some theoretical interest in the deep-ocean research community, it's still on the drawing board. Conventional scientific wisdom holds that there's not enough of significance to see at that depth to warrant the expense of the trip.</p>
        <p>"Basically, you can look at 98 percent of the sea floor if you only dive to 20,000 feet," says Don Walsh, who, with Jacques Piccard, in 1960 made the world's first and so far only trip to the deepest part of the ocean bottom, in the Trieste, a steel-enclosed bathyscaph that was part of a discontinued Navy program. "From an engineering point of view, you have to design for twice the depth to get to only 2 percent of the ocean. As Sylvia says, it's like being told you can climb up 98 percent of the height of the mountains of the planet."</p>
        <p>Walsh and Piccard spent 30 minutes on the ocean floor. Earle hopes not only to go down but also to work with "effective instrumentation" and explore. "We want to have working access to the sea, not just touch bottom and return." She and Hawkes also hope there will be many more than a single trip.</p>
        <p>Hawkes freely admits that his motivation is neither altruistic nor practical: a true engineer, he wants to launch Ocean Everest simply to see if he can. "Why did we go to the moon?" he says. "We went because it was a challenge." But Earle's concerns are also environmental: "I'd like to think that if there were hundreds of Ocean Everests, people would get out in the oceans, get to know the place," she says. "I have to believe that in the process of getting to know the ocean, people would care about it, and be responsible if for no other reason than self-interest."</p>
        <p>There are those who believe that even ecotourism opens the door to degradation of wilderness areas, that rather than loving nature to death we should preserve it simply by leaving it alone. "I know that some people say if you put the tools in the hands of the general public to make the ocean more accessible it just means the damage will occur faster," Earle acknowledges. "But I'm not afraid of that. Maybe if we were building jillions of submersibles.  And we are already causing drastic changes in our ignorance. If people could get out there and see what it means to dump garbage in the ocean, they wouldn't have to make rules. We'd be</p>
        <p>insisting</p>
        <p>on rules to make it stop.</p>
        <p>"The point of Ocean Everest," she continues, "is to not be constrained about where you go but to have free access through the whole range. That way your questions aren't limited by how deep you can go. They're only limited by your imagination."</p>
        <p>FORTY-FIVE FEET UNDER the Atlantic, schools of striped yellow goatfish scoot away from us in uncanny synchronicity. Neon-bright parrot fish, red squirrel fish with coin-size black eyes and electric purple wrasses nibble away at the delicate coral. A sand-covered rock reveals itself to be a paisley flounder and ripples away across the ocean floor.</p>
        <p>A few feet from the seabed, Earle flips over on her back, laces her fingers behind her head and crosses one leg over the other as if she were relaxing on the living-room rug. She hovers happily for a minute, then rolls over to make donkey ears at me, her eyes smiling behind her mask, before flitting behind an outcropping of coral.</p>
        <p>In shallower water, she glides along the bottom, examining the ocean's minutiae: tiny starfish, translucent strings of conch eggs, the shape and variety of the blades of grass and the white bloom of a sea flower. Suddenly she stops to untangle some old fishing line that has become wrapped around plants on the sea floor. Every time Earle dives, she surfaces with a reelful of the stuff, which can mutilate or kill marine life. "Sylvia would follow a piece of fishing line all the way to China if she had to," the sanctuary's manager, Alan Bunn, a NOAA lieutenant commander, told me.</p>
        <p>As I watch her take care of what she calls "our fellow citizens with scales and fins," I remember a conversation we had over dinner back in California, at a restaurant where the specialty of the house turned out to be seafood.</p>
        <p>"I never eat anyone I know personally," she said at the time. "I wouldn't deliberately eat a grouper any more than I'd eat a cocker spaniel. They're so good-natured, so curious. You know, fish are sensitive, they have personalities, they hurt when they're wounded."</p>
        <p>We both ordered the pasta, and Earle beamed.</p>
        <p>"I hope," she said, modulating into a sly smile, "you don't get sick of me thinking like a fish."</p>
        <p>SINCE MARCH, EARLE has been thinking a lot like a fish -- and like sea birds, sea grass and myriad other forms of marine life that are currently imperiled in the Persian Gulf. Under the auspices of NOAA, she has made three trips to the Middle East to help monitor and study the spread of an estimated six million barrels of oil across the water, and even more rolling upward from Kuwait's burning wells. "They're calling this an oil spill in the sky," she says, "because when you stand under those smoky, oily clouds, it isn't long until you find your skin speckled with oil like a fine mist, like rain. Birds are literally falling out of the sky because of it."</p>
        <p>Earle was one of the first officials invited by the Kuwaiti and Saudi Governments to survey the spill, and she is now working with members of NOAA's Hazardous Materials team as well as officials in the Middle East and Europe -- bouncing from Iceland to Holland to Saudi Arabia over the course of three days -- to help coordinate the study of damage to the wildlife and the environment, and to advise local governments on issues such as seafood safety. "The first trip was a shattering experience," Earle says. "We traveled out of Kuwait City in buses, looking at this stark landscape with plumes of fire and smoke all around us. We could feel the searing heat. Just searing. And the smoke everywhere billowing up into this immense black cloud. When the wind blows toward the city it becomes unbearable -- we had to wear surgical masks."</p>
        <p>The scope of the spill off the coast of Saudi Arabia was equally discouraging. "In a matter of weeks, the nature of that place has changed irrevocably," Earle says. "The change was of geological magnitude." The gulf's uniform shallowness -- many areas are only the depth of a swimming pool -- and uniquely high salinity make it home to rich and diverse seagrass meadows. "The grass and sand beds are dense with food for sea creatures and sea turtles," Earle explains. "It's hard to imagine how the turtles will dig through the asphalt on shore to deposit their eggs. Then there are the octopi, the squid, the corals. This area is famous for its pearl oysters. It's also a popular area for migrating birds, and the spill occurred at the peak season, when tens of thousands of sea birds were present. Nobody knows the impact of oil on that incredible assemblage of plants and wildlife."</p>
        <p>The lack of depth, coupled with the lone, narrow passage at the Strait of Hormuz, reduces the chances that nature will quickly begin to right itself, as it has in Prince William Sound. "Prince William Sound is surrounded by a healthy system," Earle explains. "The twice-daily tides flushed the oil away from the shore, which in some ways created a problem, because the oil spread over a wider area. But it also meant the sound itself enjoyed a faster restoration than will likely take place in the gulf, where it takes as much as two years, instead of twice a day, before the water is completely exchanged. And of course, that spill was 250,000 barrels, which was bad enough. This one is in the millions.</p>
        <p>"So how long will it take to clean up?" she continues. "No one knows. It was interesting to see ants bulldozing in their patient grain-by-grain way, bringing up to the surface clean sand to cover the black crust in the desert. All over the desert we could see little hills of clean sand. The desert beetles and other creatures that live underground were doing the same thing, turning things over. But there's no way that all of the oil can be eliminated. It's just an ongoing fact of life now. It can't be changed."</p>
        <p>We were in Florida, far from the damage. Our boat pulled up anchor and we headed toward shore, across the blue, limpid water of Key Largo's marine sanctuary, where, on a day less choppy than this one, the underwater visibility can be 100 feet.</p>
        <p>"The consequences of environmental abuse come into focus so sharply in this kind of hold-in-your-hand package," Earle said of the gulf disaster. "And it has everyone's attention on a top-priority basis. We're still taking for granted these assets that are certainly not free: clean air, water, a habitable environment. Only if we learn from the devastation taking place in a situation like the one in Kuwait will we have a chance not to lose these great assets. We have to understand our dependence on these natural systems."  Peggy Orenstein is the managing editor of Mother Jones magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Peggy Orenstein is the managing editor of Mother Jones magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
