<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Battling Nature in the Sculpture Garden</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="419912"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCULPTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PURCHASE (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PEPSICO INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DECHILLO, SUZANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sculpture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D8173DF930A35751C0A967958260" item-length="1131" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Battling Nature in the Sculpture Garden</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE DeCHILLO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DECHILLO, SUZANNE</byline>
      <dateline>PURCHASE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN her waterproof boots and layers of goose down, wool and fleece, Pamela A. Popeson is an unorthodox sight to those expecting art conservators to wear white gloves and lab coats.</p>
        <p>To be sure, she shares their mission, but Ms. Popeson, the assistant conservator at the Donald M. Kendall Sculpture Gardens at Pepsico, is part of a conservation team facing some unusual problems in maintaining and preserving the 43 works of art along the Golden Path, a yellow stone walkway winding through 112 acres of garden at the corporate headquarters of the food, soft drink and restaurant company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN her waterproof boots and layers of goose down, wool and fleece, Pamela A. Popeson is an unorthodox sight to those expecting art conservators to wear white gloves and lab coats.</p>
        <p>To be sure, she shares their mission, but Ms. Popeson, the assistant conservator at the Donald M. Kendall Sculpture Gardens at Pepsico, is part of a conservation team facing some unusual problems in maintaining and preserving the 43 works of art along the Golden Path, a yellow stone walkway winding through 112 acres of garden at the corporate headquarters of the food, soft drink and restaurant company.</p>
        <p>In November, for example, one conservator pulled on hip waders and climbed into the chilly waters of the lily pond to retrieve a bronze frog that needed a new patina job.</p>
        <p>"Each season brings new problems," explained Ms. Popeson, who monitors the sculptures, making weekly inspections in a golf cart outfitted with brooms, brushes, a ladder, calipers, thermometers and a can of Pepsi. "We constantly battle the effects of weather and pollution. In the spring, birds like to nest in the Nevelson piece, while the chipmunks prefer the mysterious inner spaces of 'Caryatid.' " "Caryatid" is a welded steel sculpture made of automobile parts by Judith Brown. The Birds and the Bees</p>
        <p>With horror she recalled the day the carpenter bees tried to make Swiss cheese out of "Totems," a 45-foot Western red cedar sculpture by Robert Davidson, a Haida Indian from British Columbia.</p>
        <p>"And we're always fighting the guano wars," she said, noting that a flock of Canada geese and other water birds live quite comfortably around the corporate pond, and that the huge model statue of a bear was a favorite target for some of them.</p>
        <p>Trees also deposit their litter on the art works in the courtyard -- sap, leaves, branches, blossoms and berries, each have their season.</p>
        <p>Braving the arctic weather of January, the conservator dusted the snow from "Eve," a bronze nude figure cast by Auguste Rodin in 1881 for his unfinished ensemble "The Gates of Hell." Brushing the snow from Eve's toes and with a silk cloth polishing the wax coating that protects it, Ms. Popeson said, "I love this piece." She conceded that she talked to some of the statues on her rounds. "Not the abstract pieces," she added.</p>
        <p>With a wind-chill factor that made the temperature feel like zero, "Eve" appeared to be shivering this morning on her descent to the Gates of Hell. In warmer weather, the conservator would wash the sculptures or do minor touchups.</p>
        <p>Ms. Popeson said winter is the ideal time to measure the cracking occurring in some of the pieces, and she headed for Richard Erdman's "Passage," a solid block of travertine marble, quarried and sculptured in one piece, which is now slowly cracking and splitting. Using calipers she measured the visible cracks, noting all in her reports. Each week Ms. Popeson writes a report on each sculpture piece in the garden.</p>
        <p>"The most important thing I do is to look," she said. "A lot of work is preventive, watching to see if the coatings are starting to break down. Then I report it before there is any damage." The Team Effort</p>
        <p>Ms. Popeson is also a sculptor and spends part of the week making dinosaur models at the American Museum of Natural History.</p>
        <p>As the eyes of the conservation team, Ms. Popeson works for Douglass Kwart, a freelance objects conservator who oversees the conservation program at Pepsico. They work with two Pepsico employees, Katherine F. Niles, the art program director, and Flavio Rodrigues, an engineer in charge of buildings and grounds.</p>
        <p>The idea of the sculpture garden was conceived by Donald M. Kendall, former chairman and chief executive of Pepsico, who still oversees the growing collection. Mrs. Niles said of the corporate headquarters, "The building was dedicated in 1970 when eight works of art sculpture were put in a small garden, and people were excited about it. At the time Mr. Kendall said, 'If everyone likes it this much, we're going to keep this garden open forever.' "</p>
        <p>The gardens are free and open to the public during daylight hours  A Fight Against Entropy</p>
        <p>One can't just plunk down 43 works of art outdoors and walk away -- metals tarnish, bronze corrodes and marble and even resin crack.</p>
        <p>"What we're dealing with here, I think, is what everyone deals with in every action of their daily life and that is entropy -- things want to go to hell, and we're fighting that tendency," Mr. Kwart said.</p>
        <p>"These materials will rust or tarnish, and we're fighting that tendency. I think we're winning the battle in this case. The way you overcome entropy is, you pump a lot of energy into the system."</p>
        <p>In the garden, conservators battle precipitation, humidity, temperature changes, ultraviolet light degradation, acid rain, and environmental and chemical dangers, as well as wildlife and insect damage.  120 Degrees to 40, All in a Day</p>
        <p>"Our job's a lot harder than the museum conservators, working to maintain a piece on a wall," Mr. Kwart said. "Compare the museum environment to a garden, where the temperature ranges dramatically every day.</p>
        <p>"For example, the big black marble bear out there is a rather delicate piece. When the sun hits that black rock during the day the temperature can go up to 120 degrees on the surface, and drop to 40 degrees at night. That change puts the stones through tremendous stress, because of contraction. Water is absorbed into the stone and driven out, absorbed and driven out again."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Niles said, "Our battle is based on research on each piece and working with the living artists if possible." Each piece has a yearly treatment plan, and the conservators use all kinds of protective coatings, like paints, lacquers and waxes.</p>
        <p>"Alexander Calder was alive when we purchased his piece," Mrs. Niles said, describing "Hats Off," a hard-edged Calder stabile, welded of steel plates and painted orange-red. "Calder sited the piece and was able to tell us what to do with it."  The Wages of Enthusiasm</p>
        <p>As a conservator, Mr. Kwart balances art and science in preserving those outdoor works of art that sometimes have an overly enthusiastic public audience. "People adore the George Segal piece," he said, talking about "Three People on Four Benches," which sits on the front lawn.</p>
        <p>"But this presents problems for us. George Segal likes the fact that people routinely plant big red lipstick kisses on the piece, but we have to deal with it." This year the piece is scheduled for a major cleaning and patination, or new coating. treatment.</p>
        <p>While preserving the sculpture can be a challenge, "you can't just dip these pieces in plastic," Mr. Kwart pointed out. "They'd look like paperweights. You really have to let the art speak for itself."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
