<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Energy Bill Is Derailed In Senate</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="484232"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FILIBUSTERS AND DEBATE CURBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXPLORATION OF RESOURCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALASKA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARCTIC NATIONAL WILDLIFE REFUGE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KRAUSS, CLIFFORD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska/Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exploration of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D8103EF931A35752C1A967958260" item-length="837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Energy Bill Is Derailed In Senate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KRAUSS, CLIFFORD</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Senate derailed a major bill intended to reduce the nation's dependence on foreign oil today, effectively defeating the Administration's plan to open a vast Alaskan wildlife refuge to oil drilling.</p>
        <p>Most Congressional officials said they thought an energy bill was likely to return to the floor in some form this year, but without the significant wildlife-refuge drilling provision.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Senate derailed a major bill intended to reduce the nation's dependence on foreign oil today, effectively defeating the Administration's plan to open a vast Alaskan wildlife refuge to oil drilling.</p>
        <p>Most Congressional officials said they thought an energy bill was likely to return to the floor in some form this year, but without the significant wildlife-refuge drilling provision.</p>
        <p>The bill turned aside today would have encouraged increased domestic drilling and dropped some regulations that hinder the nuclear energy industry in building new reactors. The legislation also included measures intended to increase conservation by encouraging the use of alternative energy sources and offered incentives to promote greater efficiency in buildings and appliances. It would also have required the Government to set new fuel-efficiency standards for cars, although it did not set specific targets. Home to Caribou Herds</p>
        <p>Many of these measures had been proposed or actually tried after the Arab oil boycott of the early 1970's.</p>
        <p>But the heart of the bill, and the provision opposed most strongly by environmental groups, would have opened drilling along a 1.5-million-acre coastal plain of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge in Alaska, one of the country's last unspoiled wilderness regions. The refuge is home to one of the world's largest migratory herds of caribou, which give birth in precisely the area where developers had hoped to drill. In addition, many polar bears and rare species of sea mammals live in the area.</p>
        <p>Proponents of drilling argued that the reserve could have potentially provided the country more than a half million barrels of oil a day.</p>
        <p>After opponents blocked an effort to end debate on the bill, supporters said they feared it was dead. Sixty votes were needed to avert a threatened filibuster on the bill and move it toward Senate passage. But the vote to shut off debate was 50 to 44, effectively ending consideration. Nine Republicans joined 35 Democrats to block the cloture vote.</p>
        <p>Environmental activists, who mobilized a letter-writing campaign to defeat the bill, also cited a potential danger of increased sulfur and nitrogen oxide emissions, which contribute to acid rain.</p>
        <p>Small and medium-sized utility companies also opposed the bill, saying deregulation would put them at a financial disadvantage to larger companies, and automobile company lobbyists joined the varied coalition, because they oppose automobile mileage standards.</p>
        <p>The action today was a defeat for Energy Secretary James D. Watkins and Interior Secretary Manuel Lujan Jr., who had both urged passage.</p>
        <p>The Persian Gulf war, which underlined the instability of the Middle East, had given impetus to the legislation. But the urgency weakened in the last several months, as oil prices remained stable and supplies appeared to be ample.</p>
        <p>Senator Timothy Wirth, Democrat of Colorado and leader of the opposition forces, said that once the Arctic drilling provision was eliminated, he hoped the Senate could reconsider the energy bill before Thanksgiving. Call for a New Policy</p>
        <p>He called for a new energy policy based on "efficiency, alternative fuels, new sources of renewable energy and the abundant, clean supplies of natural gas" from "places like my home state of Colorado."</p>
        <p>But supporters of the legislation suggested it could be dead.</p>
        <p>"OPEC is going to take the message of this vote, and they will grab more of our market," said Senator Frank H. Murkowski, Republican of Alaska. "And after they have made us captive, then they are going to start raising their prices and then it will be too late."</p>
        <p>A similar bill without the Arctic drilling provision is advancing in the House. Representative Philip R. Sharp, Democrat of Indiana and a ranking member of the House Energy and Commerce Committee, predicted that Congress would eventually pass a comprehensive energy package without tampering with the Arctic zone. He said the House bill would conserve the equivalent of five million barrels of oil and other fuels each day by the year 2010.</p>
        <p>He added that "these numbers are five times greater" than the 600,000 barrels a day that he estimated the Arctic zone could produce.</p>
        <p>The American Petroleum Institute called the Senate vote "a serious setback" and declared Arctic oil drilling "the key to increased domestic oil production."</p>
        <p>Ronni Lieberman, a spokeswoman for the Sierra Club, praised the Senate action, calling it a "body blow to President Bush's energy strategy." Her group would continue to oppose the legislation -- even if it is stripped of the Arctic drilling measure -- she said, because it encourages increased use of nuclear power, does nothing to promote solar and wind energy, and does too little to insure greater automobile fuel efficiency.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lieberman said her group preferred a bill sponsored by Senator Richard H. Bryan, Democrat of Nevada, that would require that new automobiles sold in the United States travel no less than 40 miles to a gallon.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
