<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How the West Was (Almost) Lost</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="418396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LIMERICK, PATRICIA NELSON</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SON OF THE MORNING STAR (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5D61231F934A15752C0A967958260" item-length="1531" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How the West Was (Almost) Lost</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA NELSON LIMERICK; Patricia Nelson Limerick, a history professor at the University of Colorado, is the author of "The Legacy of Conquest: The Unbroken Past of the American West."</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LIMERICK, PATRICIA NELSON</byline>
      <dateline>BILLINGS, Mont.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON A Montana battlefield, 114 years after the death of George Armstrong Custer, the atmosphere abounds in good intentions. On this summer day, after a long morning of warfare, Indian warriors and white soldiers paused for a hard-earned lunch. They do form separate lunch queues: half-clothed, long-haired Indians in one; blue-coated cavalrymen in the other. Good will, nonetheless, crosses the lines.</p>
        <p>"I hope I didn't hurt you out there," a soldier says to a warrior.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON A Montana battlefield, 114 years after the death of George Armstrong Custer, the atmosphere abounds in good intentions. On this summer day, after a long morning of warfare, Indian warriors and white soldiers paused for a hard-earned lunch. They do form separate lunch queues: half-clothed, long-haired Indians in one; blue-coated cavalrymen in the other. Good will, nonetheless, crosses the lines.</p>
        <p>"I hope I didn't hurt you out there," a soldier says to a warrior.</p>
        <p>"Don't worry about it," the Indian answers. "Every cavalryman out there shot me at least 10 times."</p>
        <p>Indian and cavalryman, producer and director, scriptwriter and wardrobe designer -- all the people involved in the production of this four-hour television version of Evan S. Connell's 1984 book-length historical essay, "Son of the Morning Star," seem united in their determination to do it right. They want to present, in the words of the producer, Preston Fischer, a "fair, balanced and accurate" version of the legendary event at the Little Bighorn on June 25, 1876.</p>
        <p>Starring in "Son of the Morning Star," which will be broadcast on ABC next Sunday and Monday night at 9, Gary Cole (of NBC's Friday night drama "Midnight Caller") follows in a long tradition of film Custers. In "The Flaming Frontier" (1926), Hoot Gibson played Custer as "the bravest man that ever lived," as the movie's ads put it. "They Died With Their Boots On" (1941), was the climax of Custer's career as a hero, according to Paul Hutton, a historian at the University of New Mexico. Seven years later, in "Fort Apache," Henry Fonda played Custer as an arrogant, stiff-backed officer, contributing to his own defeat. He finally landed in Arthur Penn's hands; the Custer in "Little Big Man" (1970)as "vain and ambitious, but also insane," says Professor Hutton.</p>
        <p>Martyred hero of a conquering nation, or self-destructive symptom of a sick society, the filmic Custer has been shaped more by the needs of the film makers' times than by the record of history.</p>
        <p>The creators of "Son of the Morning Star" hope to break loose from the swinging of this pendulum and to put Custer in his context; thus they are awarding equal attention to the cavalry and the Indians. Gary Cole's impulsive Lieut. Col. Custer will have David Strathairn's foresighted and cautious, but complex, Captain Frederick Benteen as a counterweight, and, the film's voice-over narration will alternate between the perspective of Custer's wife, Libbie, and the perspective of Kate Bighead, a Cheyenne woman who witnessed many key events of the Plains Wars.</p>
        <p>Kimberly Norris, a Flathead Indian and recent Native American studies major at the University of California at Los Angeles, plays the adult Kate Bighead. She says she can understand Libbie Custer's point of view. And Rosanna Arquette, who plays Libbie, laments the "horrible" campaigns against the Indians, and appraises the love between George and Libbie as "romantic, because they were madly in love, and tragic, because he was such a jerk."</p>
        <p>All the Indian parts are played by Indian actors, and the cultural encounters, both on and off camera, are striking. During breaks in the battle, an Indian man arrayed for war drinks a Coke, eats a Snickers bar, and smokes a Marlboro; makeup people freshen war paint. Asked what it is like to provide first aid at the Battle of the Little Bighorn, the paramedics standing by from Arrow Medical Services say that limbs, but not lives, are at risk. The ground is pocked; a lot of horses are falling, puncture wounds and sprained ankles are common.</p>
        <p>Lightly dressed, the Indians are reporting in with bad sunburns. "I asked one Indian man, 'Did you guys get sunburned like this 100 years ago? ' " one paramedic reports. "He told me, 'I think it has something to do with the change in the ozone layer.' "</p>
        <p>For an observer of this cross-cultural film making, which echoes the spirit of the production of Kevin Costner's recent hit "Dances With Wolves," a cheerful fantasy starts to gather strength. This fantasy is as improbable as hundred of others directed at the American West. Maybe, at the end of the 20th century, the epic of the conquest of Western America has taken an unexpected turn. After all the bitterness, injury, lost territory and lost morale, maybe Indians and whites have at last found a common ground -- in the making of films.</p>
        <p>Evan Connell's "Son of the Morning Star" seems an unlikely text to provide the occasion for pipe dreams of reconciliation. A hypnotic study of Custer's last stand, the book looks unflinchingly at the jarring violence of war. The romance of the "colorful Indian wars" dissolves in repeated encounters with the facts of what happens to human bodies under the pressure of bullets or knives, as well as what happens to human minds in contact with a brutal reality. Mr. Connell, who had advised the screenwriter, Melissa Mathison (whose credits include "E.T., the Extraterrestrial"), on the mini-series, was a commanding presence on the set.</p>
        <p>Steeped in the literature of Indian-white violence, Mr. Connell insisted on capitalizing just one sentence in his book. The words were carved by a French deserter on the wall of an abandoned fort: "NOUS SOMMES TOUS SAUVAGES."</p>
        <p>Watching the filming of the battles provides impromptu support for Mr. Connell's point. Each scene takes ages to set up: cavalrymen, Indians, horses, cameras to be positioned, much correcting of this and changing of that. Only the privileged have chairs.</p>
        <p>The smoke machines start up, sounding like lawn mowers and smelling of kerosene; the 19th century and the real smoke of battle seem farther and farther away.</p>
        <p>And the battle starts.</p>
        <p>The Indians are in the grass in the low ground; the cavalrymen are trying to form a line where the hill starts to rise. The guns sound like cap pistols. But then, as the Indians steadily advance, as the soldiers retreat, as Army horses lose their riders and retreat in a panic (and there is no Method actor as good as a panicked horse), the watcher's detachment begins to erode.</p>
        <p>The soldiers are defending the hillside where caterers, production company staffers, friends and observers are clustered, and they are obviously not doing a very good job. For a minute and a half, all one's carefully cultivated cultural relativism -- the stock in trade of the professional Western American historian -- goes on leave. Sure, it was an invasion; sure, the Indians are legitimately defending their homeland -- but the white folks are</p>
        <p>losing</p>
        <p>, and they had better do whatever it takes to start winning, and save our hillside</p>
        <p>and us.</p>
        <p>War between whites and Indians was only one part of the struggle in 1876. A quieter, but nearly as savage version of psychological warfare went on within the ranks of the Army. With deep jealousies and resentments dividing the officers, Custer's Seventh Cavalry was a regiment with a nightmarish staffing plan. The two men who disliked Custer most bitterly were Sergeant Marcus Reno and Captain Frederick Benteen. Benteen had tried repeatedly to temper Custer's impulsiveness and had been as often rebuffed.</p>
        <p>Ask Evan Connell whom he would be if he were going to play a character in this mini-series, and there is no hesitation. "Benteen," says the taciturn author. "I like Benteen."</p>
        <p>On June 4, 1990, on another site near Billings, the Custers are having a party at Fort Abraham Lincoln, just before the regiment departs for the fated 1876 campaign.</p>
        <p>Couples dance and, in the manner of the 19th-century West, some of the couples are made up of two officers, one officer wearing a white hankerchief on his sleeve to signify temporary status as a lady. The Custers are dancing with considerable charm and intensity, his golden hair flying while at the edge of the dancing zone.</p>
        <p>While the dancing is filmed over and over, and the dancers remain relentlessly festive, the actors playing Benteen and Reno do a magnificent job of maintaining stances of continuous contempt. David Strathairn says that he has made no effort to make Benteen sympathetic. "He was cantankerous, gruff, rude, frustrated," Mr. Strathairn says. "But he did make one decision that saved some people's lives."</p>
        <p>On June 25, 1876, at the Little Bighorn, Benteen held back. Eventually besieged on a hill, Benteen and most of his men stayed alive.</p>
        <p>"Benteen was a bitter, mean, vindictive, wise and foresighted man," Mr. Connell says. "He was my favorite."</p>
        <p>There is one thing clear in Montana in June 1990: Benteen bears close watching. Without him, inevitability governs the story: the Civil War ends, Custer heads West toward his last stand. "This," Mr. Connell says, "was a disaster that a lot of people sensed was about to happen. But they couldn't stop the machinery."</p>
        <p>Army recruiting posters show "guys having a wonderful time, not a drop of blood," Mr. Connell says. "This has always exasperated me." The book "Son of the Morning Star" was a kind of hopeless reminder, he says, that "we have one war after another, and there are always some excuses manufactured for it.</p>
        <p>"I hope the movie is controversial," he says. "It would be disappointing for people to say, 'So what.' "</p>
        <p>TELEVISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
