<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Opposes Antarctic Mining Ban Now</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="454887"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINES AND MINING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOHLEN, CURTIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DC1F3FF930A15755C0A967958260" item-length="661" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Opposes Antarctic Mining Ban Now</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>MADRID, June 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An agreement to protect the Antarctic from mineral exploitation for at least 50 years suffered a setback today when the United States said it would not endorse such a ban now.</p>
        <p>Among the 26 Antarctic Treaty nations with full voting rights that had subscribed to the agreement when it was drafted here in April, only the delegation from the United States returned to the Spanish capital this week without Government approval. That disappointed many of the 39 treaty members and environmental delegates who had hoped for a formal signing on Sunday, the 30th anniversary of the coming into force of the Antarctic Treaty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An agreement to protect the Antarctic from mineral exploitation for at least 50 years suffered a setback today when the United States said it would not endorse such a ban now.</p>
        <p>Among the 26 Antarctic Treaty nations with full voting rights that had subscribed to the agreement when it was drafted here in April, only the delegation from the United States returned to the Spanish capital this week without Government approval. That disappointed many of the 39 treaty members and environmental delegates who had hoped for a formal signing on Sunday, the 30th anniversary of the coming into force of the Antarctic Treaty.</p>
        <p>"June 23d is a totally artificial date as far as a decision is concerned," said the chief American delegate, Curtis Bohlen. "It would be a mistake to rush into one."</p>
        <p>"My Government has decided that this is such an important question that it needs more time to consider," Mr. Bohlen said, adding that the delay does not necessarily imply that the accord will ultimately be rejected by the United States.</p>
        <p>The chief Spanish delegate, Carlos Blasco, cautioned that "we can't speak of failure."  Mining Moratorium Sought</p>
        <p>The draft accord, which would become a protocol to the Antarctic Treaty, would impose a 50-year moratorium on all mining in the world's largest wilderness. After that the ban could be reconsidered, but only with the consent of all 26 treaty signers with full voting rights.</p>
        <p>The Antarctic Treaty, which went into effect in 1961, was originally signed by 12 nations, of which 7 still claim territorial rights to the region. It prohibits any military bases or nuclear and other weapons tests and insured freedom of scientific research.</p>
        <p>When the meeting opened on Monday, the American delegation submitted a proposed amendment allowing any country to dissociate itself from the ban if an amendment it proposed was not put into effect within three years.</p>
        <p>Environmental organizations expressed dismay over what they called the "walkout" clause, which they said undermined the principle of consensus.</p>
        <p>"The whole basis of the Antarctic Treaty is consensus," said James Martin-Jones, representing the World Wide Fund for Nature. "The U.S. demands strike at the heart of the treaty."</p>
        <p>The Australian delegate, Lyn Goldsworthy, expressed fears that the United States could undermine the delicate consensus achieved in April.  Undoing of Negotiation Feared</p>
        <p>"We're incredibly concerned that the U.S. may undo a very carefully negotiated position," she said. "You must remember that countries with important differences on other issues, such as Britain and Argentina, buried those differences in April for the common good."</p>
        <p>The chief French delegate, Jean-Pierre Puissochet, said of the Americans today: "They were alone. I heard no voice sharing the U.S. view."</p>
        <p>Mr. Puissochet also accused the United States of trying to railroad the delegates by waiting until this week to propose the amendment.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bohlen denied taking a unilateral stance, adding that the United States could not accept the April text because it did not guarantee the right to modify the mining ban in future.</p>
        <p>"We want to be sure there is a fail-safe amendment process," he said. "Besides, our policy has been very consistently opposed to a permanent mineral activity ban."</p>
        <p>Environmentalists' reactions to the outcome of this week's meeting ranged from anger to despair.</p>
        <p>"I presume Mr. Bush will call for a victory parade to celebrate the destruction of Antarctica," said David McTaggart, chairman of Greenpeace.</p>
        <p>"The U.S. got 99 percent of what they wanted this week," said Paul Bogart, a Greenpeace official. "The fact that they didn't accept it shows the Administration is not interested in protecting the enviroment. The two shouldn't even be in the same sentence."</p>
        <p>"What we're seeing is a foreign-policy extension of domestic policy on energy: the continued reliance on and addiction to fossil fuels," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
