<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World; Experts Say Oil Shocks Are Unlikely To Go Away</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week In Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="416693"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5D6153EF933A15752C0A967958260" item-length="981" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World; Experts Say Oil Shocks Are Unlikely To Go Away</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE oil price fever that has burned since August -- the industrial world's third bout with the malady since 1973 -- was broken last week when traders concluded that the intense air raids on Iraq had eliminated the threat to Saudi installations. The price of crude fell by more than $10 overnight and ended the week at a level lower than before Saddam Hussein invaded Kuwait.</p>
        <p>No one is sure what will happen to prices in the weeks ahead. Government officials went to great pains to argue that this was not a case, as demonstrators keep chanting, of "blood for oil." But attention inevitably turned to techniques other than carpet bombing for assuring access to oil or, better yet, reducing the economy's dependence on a commodity that can jump in price by 150 percent in a few weeks, and fall by 33 percent in a few hours.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE oil price fever that has burned since August -- the industrial world's third bout with the malady since 1973 -- was broken last week when traders concluded that the intense air raids on Iraq had eliminated the threat to Saudi installations. The price of crude fell by more than $10 overnight and ended the week at a level lower than before Saddam Hussein invaded Kuwait.</p>
        <p>No one is sure what will happen to prices in the weeks ahead. Government officials went to great pains to argue that this was not a case, as demonstrators keep chanting, of "blood for oil." But attention inevitably turned to techniques other than carpet bombing for assuring access to oil or, better yet, reducing the economy's dependence on a commodity that can jump in price by 150 percent in a few weeks, and fall by 33 percent in a few hours.</p>
        <p>The case for making the world safe for oil-importing countries is clear, said Joseph Stanislaw, a Paris-based oil expert for Cambridge Energy Research Associates. Even if Iraqi forces occupying Kuwait never marched on to Saudi Arabia, "the intimidation would have been enough to have given them effective control of OPEC pricing," he said, "putting not only the American economy, but the industrialized world, at the mercy of one man."</p>
        <p>No matter how successful the war against Mr. Hussein, however, energy security will be far from assured. The American oil industry would like to produce more at home. But when it comes to oil, geology is destiny. The United States has about 26 billion barrels of proven reserves in the ground, of a global total of one trillion barrels. And the oil is getting harder to find; since the oil price crash of 1986, domestic daily oil production has shrunk by an amount larger than Kuwait's normal production.</p>
        <p>"It's clear that U.S. production of those reserves will have a very limited impact on the world oil market," said Robert K. Watson, an energy specialist at the Natural Resources Defense Council, which has fought hard against drilling in parts of Alaska and the outer continental shelf. The reason is the volume elsewhere, including 650 billion barrels in the Persian Gulf. Iraq and Kuwait each have roughly quadruple the reserves of the United States; Saudi Arabia's are 10 times larger.</p>
        <p>But the United States is an oil giant of another kind; last year it consumed 16.96 million barrels a day, or about 28 percent of world production. So the country is addicted to imports, 46 percent of supply last year. After the oil shocks of 1973 and 1979, industry and consumers switched to other fuels or simply used less. Americans used .27 metric tons of oil per $1,000 in gross domestic product in 1970, but by 1989 the figure was down to .18 tons, a drop of 33 percent. In the same period, Japan improved by 46 percent.</p>
        <p>With domestic production declining 5 percent last year and probably more this year if low prices prevail, the United States will have to run hard just to stay in place in terms of imports. That means, said Mr. Watson and others, "the only way we can really affect the amount of oil available to provide energy services is by getting a handle on demand."</p>
        <p>The United States has been at a disadvantage in weaning itself from oil, partly because it relies on market forces, which do not reflect the cost of war. Despite three oil shocks, oil is still easy to find, cheap to buy, and easy to use. Oil may be depletable in theory, but because of exploration and better technology reserves have nearly doubled since 1970. And, fever aside, the price is usually low. Cambridge Energy Research Associates calculates that prices in 1989 were one-fourth lower than in 1980, adjusting for inflation, and the price has stayed consistently below the price of oil from shale or tar sands.</p>
        <p>Supply is a prominent issue when it is threatened, but almost always, moving oil is very easy. It generally does not require long pipelines, as does natural gas, and when refined and delivered for use it is an extremely compact energy package. Two efficiency experts, Amory B. Lovins and Hunter B. Lovins, calculated in their book "Brittle Power" that a gasoline station with 20 pumps running is delivering as much energy as a medium-sized nuclear plant.</p>
        <p>For months, the Energy Department has been developing a National Energy Strategy, presenting the White House with a menu of steps to increase supply or cut demand. But experts outside government think the former is more likely.</p>
        <p>The chairman of the Council on Environmental Quality, Michael R. Deland, said, "It will be extremely difficult to lessen our dependence on imported -- and hence Middle Eastern -- oil." The economy can switch to other technologies, but the most important will not be in wide commercial use until the next century, he said. A new generation of more economical, publicly acceptable nuclear power plants, photovoltaic cells and other "renewable" energy sources, including batteries to run vehicles, will be needed, he said, along with a general improvement in efficiency.</p>
        <p>At Citizen Action, a Washington-based nonprofit group, Ed Rothschild, an energy expert, called for a plan stressing efficiency. But he added, "The decline in oil prices may have a perverse effect, taking the pressure off to have a national energy strategy."</p>
        <p>Others argue that no energy strategy is good energy strategy. Fereidun Fesharaki, an oil analyst at the East-West Center, a research center in Honolulu, defined energy policy as "taking my tax dollars and subsidizing something uneconomic."</p>
        <p>"It creates industries which do not deserve to be created," he said, referring to synthetic fuels and other failed efforts. When oil rises in price, he said, alternatives will emerge on their own.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, he suggested, events like Iraq's invasion of Kuwait or other triggers for oil shocks are "something we may face every 10 or 15 years."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
