<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Is So Rare as a Day In May? July Before June</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="449420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORTHEASTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HINDS, MICHAEL DECOURCY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D71E39F932A35755C0A967958260" item-length="1161" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Is So Rare as a Day In May? July Before June</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL deCOURCY HINDS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HINDS, MICHAEL DECOURCY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A dome of very hot, humid air parked itself 20,000 feet over the northeastern United States about 20 days ago and just hung around, making the month of May the hottest that New York, Philadelphia, Baltimore, Washington and many other cities have experienced in meteorological memory.</p>
        <p>And while the East sweltered, temperatures dropped to record-breaking lows in Southern California, and unseasonable snw fell in the Sierra Nevada.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A dome of very hot, humid air parked itself 20,000 feet over the northeastern United States about 20 days ago and just hung around, making the month of May the hottest that New York, Philadelphia, Baltimore, Washington and many other cities have experienced in meteorological memory.</p>
        <p>And while the East sweltered, temperatures dropped to record-breaking lows in Southern California, and unseasonable snw fell in the Sierra Nevada.</p>
        <p>"For the season it's weird," Daniel H. Graf, a meteorologist at Pennsylvania State University in State College, said yesterday. 'Very Exciting' Weather</p>
        <p>"It is not unusual to have areas that are very hot and others that are very cold, but the oddest part is that a summer weather pattern has persisted here for three weeks in the spring," he said. "These are the kind of severe weather patterns that meteorologists live for. It's very exciting."</p>
        <p>In New York, the heat drove many homeless people from their temporary resting spots in the subway system to new resting spots on the street, said Robert E. Slovak, a Transit Authority spokesman. "Since it's hot outside, it's obviously hotter in the subway system, and that is not a very desirable place to live."</p>
        <p>For those with more desirable shelter -- the air-conditioned kind -- power companies seemed to have no trouble meeting demand for electricity. Consolidated Edison in New York and other utility companies in the region reported no power surges or equipment failures and no operational problems from the heat.</p>
        <p>Temperatures were expected to moderate in the Northeast over the weekend. Matthew Tauber, a meteorologist with the National Weather Service in New York, said a cold front would move in from Canada today, lowering temperatures in the city by about 10 degrees by this evening.</p>
        <p>But the buildup of oppressive heat and humidity took its toll yesteday, driving thousands of students and teachers from their classrooms.</p>
        <p>Many school districts closed early yesterday, observing a novelty: a heat day. Among them were schools in south and central New Jersey, in Philadelphia and its suburbs and in Washington.</p>
        <p>"This is the first time the D.C. public schools have ever totally shut down because of the heat," said Cheryl Johnson, a spokeswoman for the Washington school system.</p>
        <p>The temperature reached 99 degrees yesterday, the eighth day of over 90-degree heat. Less than one-fourth of the District's 175 schools are fully air-conditioned, and the rest were not designed for summer use.</p>
        <p>"You just sit and sweat," said Steven Davis, a dance student at the Ellington School of the Arts.</p>
        <p>Schools began reporting problems on Thursday. In Washington, 25 of the 35 teachers in Rabaut Junior High School could no longer stand their airless chambers, and took emergency sick leave in the middle of the day. Group Guards Fire Hydrants</p>
        <p>In Philadelphia, the Ferguson Elementary School had little tap water above the basement level because overheated Philadelphians had turned on so many fire hydrants. Yesterday, a community group guarded the hydrants near Ferguson.</p>
        <p>"Things like this bring people together, kind of like when the lights went out in New York," said Barbara Tucker, the school's principal.</p>
        <p>In New York City, temperatures eached 90 degrees on Thursday and 91 yesterday, pushing the average temperature for May to a record high of 68.1 degrees. The previous average high for the month was 67.9.</p>
        <p>Philadelphia, the hottest city in Pennsylvania, had the hottest days in May on record on Thursday and again yesterday, when the temperature reached 97 degrees on both days.</p>
        <p>Coastal Maine had nine days over 80 degrees this month, breaking the previous record of seven for May. Norfolk, Va., set a record for May with 100 degrees yesterday. Baltimore's 81-degree low yesterday was higher than the average high at this time of year. Concern About Global Warming</p>
        <p>Every time it gets unseasonably warm, concerns about global warming increase. But Dr. Frederick B. House, professor of physics and atmospheric science at Drexel University in Philadelphia, said significant effects of atmospheric pollution on the earth's temperature would not be seen for 10, 20 or 30 years. "It's just abnormally hot," he said yesterday.</p>
        <p>James P. Friend, a professor of atmospheric chemistry at Drexel, theorized that the heat wave was caused by a Bermuda high pressure system, named for the location of its center off the Carolina coast.</p>
        <p>"What happens is the whole Northeast becomes very stagnant and allows a concentration of heat and pollutants to build up," he said. "That's why it feels so awful."</p>
        <p>But in Los Angeles, yesterday was the coldest day in May ever recorded, with 62 degrees. And in the Sierra Nevada nighttime temperatures fell below freezing, another rarity. Keeping Warm in Arizona</p>
        <p>In unseasonably cool Arizona, snakes and other reptiles have been exercising more than usual to keep warm, said Gary G. Williams, a spokesman for the Arizona-Sonora Desert Museum in Tucson. "The desert animals are just a tad more active," he said in a telephone interview. A moment later he added, "My, it's just started raining, and it's coming down hard."</p>
        <p>In New York, unusually large crowds gathered to catch a breeze on Coney Island's Cyclone Roller Coaster, said a spokesman, Milt Berger. Free air shows by the Army's Golden Knights earlier in the week drew "a solid phalanx of people for the full two and three-quarter miles of boardwalk," he added.</p>
        <p>On Long Island, about 900,000 people visited Jones Beach State Park in May, up from the usual May crowd of 500,000 to 700,000, said Joseph F. Lescinski, the park's superintendent.</p>
        <p>"What we're winding up with is July crowds in May," he said. "We're dealing with many more cases of heat exhaustion and sunburn than we would normally be handling now."</p>
        <p>And it has been about 10 to 15 degrees cooler at Jones Beach than in New York City. Elephant Cooling Systems</p>
        <p>The heat makes everybody's work a bit harder. Peter Cimini, for example, has to care for 22 elephants, 40 horses, 4 bison, 2 llamas, 4 ponies, 3 cows, 4 pigs and 17 ducks, not to mention 24 lions and tigers. He is stable master for the Ringling Brothers and Barnum &amp; Bailey's Circus, which has been in Philadelphia during most of the heat wave.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cimini says he suffers much more than the animals, most of which were born for the heat. "African elephants have great cooling system: it's the veins in their ears, and when it gets hot they turn on the fans," he said.</p>
        <p>The Philadelphia Magic Company has another solution, supposedly created by the magician Merlin in the days of King Arthur. It is an odorless powder called oxiperciety, popularized by knights who used it to cool themselves while encased in their armor, said Danny Archer, the company's magician.</p>
        <p>"It works if you believe it does," he said. "Anyway, we've had a rush last week, and we're sold out." An ounce and a half of the powder cost $5.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
