<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Audubon Society Pursues An Identity Beyond Birds</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="451376"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AUDUBON SOCIETY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAVER, ANNE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERLE, PETER A A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D61E3DF93AA35755C0A967958260" item-length="1661" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Audubon Society Pursues An Identity Beyond Birds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAVER, ANNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The National Audubon Society is worried about its old-fogy image. So it asked some California conultants to find out what came to mind when people heard the word Audubon. The bad news: "Birds."</p>
        <p>And there was worse to come. The consultants reported that the society, 105 years old, was regarded as "old-fashioned and exclusive," not "compelling." Many, the consultants said, thought it had a narrow "bird oriented" focus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The National Audubon Society is worried about its old-fogy image. So it asked some California conultants to find out what came to mind when people heard the word Audubon. The bad news: "Birds."</p>
        <p>And there was worse to come. The consultants reported that the society, 105 years old, was regarded as "old-fashioned and exclusive," not "compelling." Many, the consultants said, thought it had a narrow "bird oriented" focus.</p>
        <p>Bummer. That is if you're Peter A. A. Berle, president of the Audubon Society, competing with so many environmentalist groups for money and support. Greenpeace, the outfit that runs rafts in front of Soviet whalers, was given much higher marks.  But No Parachutes</p>
        <p>"We want to be Greenpeace but we don't want to parachute off bridges," said an editor of Audubon, the society's magazine, who spoke on the condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>The new image is more than bird-deep. The magazine's top editor, Les Line, who held the job for 25 years, was dismissed in early March. He was replaced with an interim editor, Malcolm Abrams, the former managing editor of The Star, a national tabloid.</p>
        <p>The very word "bird" is now under assault in memorandums signed by Mr. Berle. Since the 1990 consultants' report from Landor Associates of San Francisco, members of the staff have been asked to refrain from overusing "bird images."</p>
        <p>How then to report on fund-raising birdathons? One directive suggested that when someone said: "Audubon -- that's all about birds, isn't it?" a reply might be: "We're much more than birds. Our scientists, lobbyists, and grass-roots activists work on a variety of issues, including ancient forests, wetlands, the Platte, and the Arctic National Wildife Refuge."</p>
        <p>Even the society's logo, the beloved egret, has been blown off course. It's been replaced on National Audubon stationery by a plain blue flag. (Chapter members are still allowed to use the egret.)</p>
        <p>What is happening to the National Audubon Society, one of the nation's oldest and esteemed environmental groups?</p>
        <p>Oops. Scratch "oldest." A January 1990 memo from Mr. Berle about the society's "old-fogy description" tells the staff in Audubon's New York office to eliminate phrases like "one of the nation's oldest and largest environmental groups" and substitute "one of the nation's largest and most effective."</p>
        <p>Mr. Berle (pronounced BUR-lee), in addition to being the society's president, is also the publisher of Audubon, the magazine.</p>
        <p>"What's wrong with being old?" said Mr. Line, its former editor, on a recent afternoon at his home in Amenia, N.Y. "Why does everything have to be new? It's like selling more boxes of Tide. Just put 'NEW!' on them."</p>
        <p>He recalled one slogan that Landor suggested early last year: "Audubon -- Responding to Nature's Cry." That's cry, not call. Reminder of Roach Killer?</p>
        <p>"The egret is a symbol of the organization's greatest campaign, stopping the killing of plume birds for hats, and it's served us well for 90 years," Mr. Line said. He said the blue flag reminded him of the symbol for Black Flag roach killer.</p>
        <p>"Peter has expressed a desire to have 2 million members rather than the 500,000 we now have, and he feels those new members have to come from the twentysomething, thirtysomething crowd," Mr. Line said, adding that the average age of Audubon members is in the mid-40's.</p>
        <p>There was a problem when people saw the egret, Mr. Berle said in a recent interview. "They didn't say, 'Aha, Audubon!' Landor found that people had very little understanding of who we were and what we did, but everybody knew the name."</p>
        <p>Mr. Berle went on: "The other problem is we don't own the name. You could have an Audubon nursery or an Audubon used-car lot or an Audubon housing project or whatever. The concept of the flag, whether you like it or not, is that Audubon is a cause. That distinguishes it from a used-car lot."</p>
        <p>The Audubon Society was formed by a big-game hunter, George Bird Grinnell, in 1886, to fight the slaughter of birds for ornamental feathers. The society's namesake, John James Audubon, probably killed more birds than he painted, but the very birdness of his pictures apparently transcended that fact. Adding Causes</p>
        <p>Over a century later, the Audubon Society has a $42 million budget. Its causes are multiplying: from birds and wildlife habitats to toxic waste and population control. The old guard says the society is losing its focus. The new guard talks about redefining nature.</p>
        <p>At the interview in his office, Mr. Berle, who has a law degree from Harvard, was pressed for time because he was preparing to represent the society before the Supreme Court, as Nebraska and Wyoming battle over water rights on the Platte River.</p>
        <p>The states want to take water out of the Platte; the environmentalists want to keep it in, for the birds and the ecosystem. The Audubon Society is defending the birds. (It is fine to use bird images, society guidelines say, when they're "indicators of health of large ecological systems.")</p>
        <p>Mr. Berle, who has been president of the society for six years, has strong environmental credentials. He founded Berle, Kass &amp; Case, the New York law firm that initiated a suit against the Union Carbide Corporation for the pollution of underground water on Long Island with pesticides. He served three terms in the New York Legislature, 1968-74, and then headed the State Department of Environmental Conservation from 1976 to 1979, when the state was faced with the toxic wastes of Love Canal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berle talks of a wide spectrum of concerns: mapping old forests in Oregon; nature programs in the Everglades for inner-city children; increased foreign aid for family planning; keeping the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge free of oil drilling.</p>
        <p>The society, he said, "is trying to take all these pieces and be an effective force for change."</p>
        <p>And Mr. Line, it appears, is too much of a conservationist for Mr. Berle's vision.</p>
        <p>"Berle told me that the primary reason I had to go was my interest in nature and natural history and natural resources, and that that was not where the action was," said Mr. Line, watching a swallowtail butterfly hovering over his pansies. Switch Is Odd, to Some</p>
        <p>This is an odd turn of events to those who say that Mr. Line ran a magazine whose writers led the way in exploring subjects like toxic waste, pesticides and the destruction of the Everglades.</p>
        <p>"Les Line took a birdwatcher's magazine and broadened its scope to problems on ecology and the environment," said George Plimpton, a longtime society member who has written for the magazine. "He did exactly what the new crowd is trying to do. There was the hue and cry that we should stick to birds. Now there's another hue and cry that he's not gone far enough."</p>
        <p>Mr. Berle would not comment on Mr. Line's dismissal, other than to refer to his March 7 press release that praised Mr. Line's work but said it was time "for fresh leadership," for "an editor who can take the magazine into the 21st century."</p>
        <p>The change is welcomed by others.</p>
        <p>"The magazine is a little stodgy," said Ann Botshon, who edited Garden, the New York Botanical Garden's magazine, for nine years before it folded. "It's beautiful, but has a static quality that makes it almost impregnable."</p>
        <p>Mr. Line agreed that things have changed. But the society, he said, has lost its bearings.</p>
        <p>"In the 60's, we were fighting the big fight over hard pesticides, all the chlorinated hydrocarbons, like DDT," he said. "Now there's far more concern for the human environment: solid waste, energy, population control, toxic waste, acid rain. All these issues relate, of course, to habitat and wildlife, but the society has moved away from its historic mission.</p>
        <p>"There's tremendous competition out there for money among all these environmental groups. And we've gotten top-heavy with bureaucrats and accountants and fund-raisers who are all good professionals, but I don't think you'd catch them sloshing through a marsh."</p>
        <p>The ornithologist and wildlife artist Roger Tory Peterson agrees. "Audubon is losing its identity," he said. "It's trying to do too many things. We're getting away from the original thing, which is wildlife, and getting into the human thing, which is pollution and birth control and all that sort of thing."</p>
        <p>In his 82 years, Dr. Peterson has written 15 books on wildlife and edited 40. He saw his first flicker at the age of 11.</p>
        <p>"He had his head under his wing and I thought he was dead," Dr. Peterson said. "So I touched him with my finger, and he woke up and looked at me, startled. Ever since then, birds seemed to me the most vivid expression of life."</p>
        <p>This awe of nature is what Mr. Line fears is disappearing from the very group that nurtured it. And what stands in its place is flag waving. Stories Are Changed</p>
        <p>At Audubon magazine, staff members fear not only losing their jobs, but the end to a long tradition of literary nature writing. "Accessible," "new," "compelling" and "upbeat" are the buzzwords now.</p>
        <p>Articles for coming issues -- more than $130,000 worth, editors estimate -- have been jettisoned or put on hold.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abrams, the interim editor, killed the July issue's cover article, about a study of the effects of the Persian Gulf war on the environment, and substituted one about the society's participation in an American-Soviet effort to establish an international park across the Bering Strait. Staff members say the change is a perfect example of what they most fear: that Audubon will become the society's house organ.</p>
        <p>"If the Kiwanis Club was doing it, I'd run it the same way," Mr. Abrams said.</p>
        <p>The identity crisis may have more casualties. But the egret is "still alive and well," Mr. Berle said. Local chapters can use it, or a muskrat, or a kingfisher if they want.</p>
        <p>"But when we write our name, the Audubon Society, you'll see the blue flag," he said.</p>
        <p>The question is, members ask, does the flag stand for everything, or nothing?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
