<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Mother, a Little Something for the Garden</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Consumer's World Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="444666"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTHER'S DAY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAVER, ANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mother's Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFD81730F932A25756C0A967958260" item-length="615" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Mother, a Little Something for the Garden</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAVER, ANNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Unless you're a perfect child, you probably forgot that tomorrow is Mother's Day. You have no present, no book that will change her life and make you her favorite and you have no dinner reservation at the unforgettable, undiscovered restaurant. So you'll probably dash out to the corner for a bouquet of flowers -- a lovely gift, but temporary. It will fade within the week.</p>
        <p>A plant might be a better choice, one that will grow year after year in her garden, or on a sunny window. Some lucky mothers have whole yards full of such plants, living histories of the thoughtful people who brought them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Unless you're a perfect child, you probably forgot that tomorrow is Mother's Day. You have no present, no book that will change her life and make you her favorite and you have no dinner reservation at the unforgettable, undiscovered restaurant. So you'll probably dash out to the corner for a bouquet of flowers -- a lovely gift, but temporary. It will fade within the week.</p>
        <p>A plant might be a better choice, one that will grow year after year in her garden, or on a sunny window. Some lucky mothers have whole yards full of such plants, living histories of the thoughtful people who brought them.</p>
        <p>So take an hour or two today or tomorrow to ramble about your favorite nursery. If it only stocks the usuals, like impatiens and Whopper tomatoes, you'll have to go elsewhere. But before you leave ask to see the manager, and ask about more interesting plants. Show enough interest, and the stock may change so that you won't have to go far afield next time. And remember, Father's Day is June 16, and it's perfectly acceptable to give him flowering plants, too.</p>
        <p>Here are a few ideas, for shade and sun, indoors and out.</p>
        <p>ASTILBES AND HOSTAS: A large pot of astilbes and hostas is fine for a shady terrace. These indestructible perennials are good companions thanks to their contrasting foliage and flowers. Astilbes have deep green or bronze, finely cut foliage (shaped sort of like Italian parsley) and feathery blooms of pink, white, or deep red. Hostas are grown for their bold sculptural leaves -- some blue green, some grass-green with gold edging -- but they also have subtle, lily-like flowers, and Royal Standard is sweet-scented.</p>
        <p>CLIMBING HYDRANGEA: Unlike the big blowsy hydrangeas so familiar at beach houses, this elegant creature will scramble 40 feet up a tree, or lounge over an old stone wall, putting out lateral branches of white flowers that look like lace doilies. It loves sun, but tolerates light shade.</p>
        <p>CHERRY TOMATOES: And for the mother who loves tomatoes, a dwarf cherry tomato plant can be ideal. Red Robin is a luscious, hearty producer; Yellow Canary a golden cousin. These and other container varieties can be grown all summer in a hanging basket or large pot, as long as they have plenty of sun.</p>
        <p>HERBS: A windowbox or hanging basket of four herbs is something your mother can plant herself and it's a quite inexpensive gift. Choose basil, thyme, rosemary, chives, oregano, mint, or any favorite; select an interesting container and bring along the potting soil. Plant at least four inches apart. Sun is a must.</p>
        <p>GERANIUMS: A scented geranium or two or three in a pot is a joy for a sunny window. Every time you brush past these plants, the scent of lemon, or rose, or cinnamon fills the air.</p>
        <p>CLEMATIS: A clematis is another climber perfect for a wall or fence. These romantic flowers may well be the beginning of a collection, because they come in all colors -- deep purple, white, pink with rosy stripes, deep red. They bloom at all different times, some in shade, some in sun. The English train them to grow among their old roses.</p>
        <p>And there are always garden tools you can pick up at the last minute.  How about a sturdy trowel if Mom's an avid gardener? A good pair of anvil pruners might also make her forget the gift you forgot last year.</p>
        <p>And there are always garden tools you can pick up at the last minute. How about a sturdy trowel if Mom's an avid gardner? A Panama hat to protect her from the ultraviolet rays streaming through the thinning ozone layer (add some No. 15 sunscreen, a must these days for every gardener). A pair of goatskin, puncture-proof workgloves (the longer, the better) for pruning thorny rose bushes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
