<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Songs of the 50's and 60's in Bridgeport</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="472391"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DOWNTOWN CABARET THEATER (BRIDGEPORT, CONN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KLEIN, ALVIN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BEEHIVE (REVUE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D91F30F93BA3575AC0A967958260" item-length="594" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Songs of the 50's and 60's in Bridgeport</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KLEIN, ALVIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"BEEHIVE" (the hairdo) is a symbol of, and a sincere salute to, girl groups (the Shirelles, the Shangri-Las) and the girls without groups (Brenda Lee, Leslie Gore) who, with their songs, shamelessly brought the inanities of the 1950's right into the next decade -- that is, until the cause-inspired music of the 60's put all that to rest, for a time.</p>
        <p>Now, with the recurring psychological ramifications and the increasing commercial lure of nostalgia, it appears that the B-word and all it represents never quite went away. It was simply intimidated by guitars and streams of long hair. And even if it did go away for a while, it keeps coming back with a vengeance, and with more cans of hairspray, no matter the ozone layer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"BEEHIVE" (the hairdo) is a symbol of, and a sincere salute to, girl groups (the Shirelles, the Shangri-Las) and the girls without groups (Brenda Lee, Leslie Gore) who, with their songs, shamelessly brought the inanities of the 1950's right into the next decade -- that is, until the cause-inspired music of the 60's put all that to rest, for a time.</p>
        <p>Now, with the recurring psychological ramifications and the increasing commercial lure of nostalgia, it appears that the B-word and all it represents never quite went away. It was simply intimidated by guitars and streams of long hair. And even if it did go away for a while, it keeps coming back with a vengeance, and with more cans of hairspray, no matter the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>At long as the revue at the Downtown Cabaret Theater in Bridgeport sticks to the songs it can handle ("I Sold My Heart to the Junkman," "Judy's Turn to Cry"), it is painless, no matter the eardrums, and at times ingratiating.</p>
        <p>As an added fillip for audience members who are keen on a participatory assault, and all too eager to heed the invitation to "carry on," twist, stomp and clap along in the aisles, "Beehive" is some night out.</p>
        <p>Not that serious themes are in short supply. Self-assertiveness comes up ("You Don't Own Me," "It's My Party"), and so does the cautionary song ("Don't Sleep in the Subway.") Nor was the show's creator, Larry Gallagher, unmindful of the importance of events of the era. We learn, for example, that J. F. K. got into the White House and that Elvis Presley got out of the Army. The dialogue among the six high-voltage singers, though spare, is succinct, proving that the period's concerns were not just cosmetic ("Michelle Has Acne") but cosmic ("Why Wars?").</p>
        <p>And the lyrics, which reveal an unending mastery of extended syllabication ("Why Do I Love You Like I Doooooooo?") are, throughout, emotionally wrought, filled with references to repairing or retrieving broken hearts. Or they wistfully wonder about the future: "Tonight the light of love is in your eyes, but will you still love me tomorrow?".</p>
        <p>After a rousing, infectious "You Don't Have to Say You Love Me," the first act of what should have been a one-act show is over.</p>
        <p>After intermission the audience hears about music reflecting "political and social changes." It is unreasonable to expect a cast that's been just fine at transmitting the generic dopiness of those earlier years of the decade to convey the complex talents, essence and authority of Tina Turner, Aretha Franklin and Janis Joplin. Such radically different and distinctive energies are not to be reduced to a bump here, a tic there, a few high-decibel yelps and endless jumping and gyrating. A slew of tacky imitations follow.</p>
        <p>It becomes the burden of the performer doing Miss Franklin to represent both the "voice of black pride and women's expression." And another cast member is saddled with an overextended -- and this is no longer painless -- medley of three songs associated with Janis Joplin. It is meant to be a high point. Yes, Woodstock is mentioned, if incorrectly. The assassinations of Robert F. Kennedy and Martin Luther King Jr. are not.</p>
        <p>But wait. There's a retrogressive finale. The girls come back, handwaving and swaying, just like old times, to deliver "Make Your Own Kind of Music," the evening's real message song. Gosh, just when we thought it was really over.</p>
        <p>"Beehive," at the Downtown Cabaret Theater, 263 Golden Hill Street, Bridgeport. 576-1636. Performances Fridays and Saturdays at 7:30 and 10 P.M. through Nov. 9.  THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
