<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Compromise Clears Way for Virginia Power Plant</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="449894"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VIRGINIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SHENANDOAH NATIONAL PARK (VA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL PARK SERVICE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">AYRES, B DRUMMOND JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WAXMAN, HENRY A (REP)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia/Shenandoah National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DE153FF931A35755C0A967958260" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Compromise Clears Way for Virginia Power Plant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By B. DRUMMOND AYRES Jr.,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">AYRES, B DRUMMOND JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The National Park Service and two electrical power companies announced Friday an unusual environmental compromise that will help clear the way for construction of a coal-fired power plant in Virginia, provided that an existing plant reduces air pollution that is threatening the Shenandoah National Park.</p>
        <p>Park Service officials and Interior Secretary Manuel Lujan Jr., along with power company officials, hailed the compromise as a "significant new pollution-reduction agreement" that would protect the environment and still permit industrial development.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The National Park Service and two electrical power companies announced Friday an unusual environmental compromise that will help clear the way for construction of a coal-fired power plant in Virginia, provided that an existing plant reduces air pollution that is threatening the Shenandoah National Park.</p>
        <p>Park Service officials and Interior Secretary Manuel Lujan Jr., along with power company officials, hailed the compromise as a "significant new pollution-reduction agreement" that would protect the environment and still permit industrial development.</p>
        <p>But Representative Henry A. Waxman, the California Democrat whose House Subcommitee on Health and Environment monitors pollution issues, called the compromise "an outrageous paper sham." He said it was vaguely written without any enforcement teeth and asserted that the Park Service had been forced to accept it by White House officials more concerned with company profits than the environment.</p>
        <p>An environmental group that has opposed the plant, the Southern Environmental Law Center of Charlottesville, Va., questioned whether the agreement was broad enough. Center officials warned that they would challenge the compromise in court if it proved to have shortcomings. Park Service Took Tough Stand</p>
        <p>The agreement, reached with the Virginia Power company and the Old Dominion Electric Cooperative, provides that the utilities may construct a new coal-fired generating plant in south-central Virginia so long as there is a reduction in pollution flowing from an old plant situated north of Shenandoah Park in West Virginia. The reduction is to be 1.1 times greater at the old plant than emissions from the new plant, and discussion may be reopened if Park Service officials conclude that the reduction is not achieved.</p>
        <p>The agreement came about after the Park Service took an aggressive anti-pollution step and decided to actively oppose construction of the $1.2 billion electric plant rather than simply express concerns about pollution.</p>
        <p>Park officials argued that the plant would add to industrial and urban pollution that is slowly killing the northern Virginia park that stretches 85 miles along the Blue Ridge Mountains and is famed for its cliff-hugging Skyline Drive. They said the pollution, much of from sulfur dioxide emissions from coal-fired power plants that falls to the earth as acid rain, was poisoning trout streams, searing trees and shrubs, clouding vistas and endangering the health of park visitors.</p>
        <p>An agency of the Interior Department, the Park Service had previously expressed concern about air pollution in a number of its parks, including Shenandoah, the Great Smokies on the Tennessee-North Carolina border and the Grand Canyon. But until it opposed the Virginia plant, it had avoided taking a stand that could affect the pace of industrial development, leaving such portentous action to the Environmental Protection Agency. White House Pressure Denied</p>
        <p>The agreement is the kind encouraged by the Clean Air Act and the Bush Administration on the theory that trade-offs in pollution emissions achieve both environmental and economic goals. Spokesmen for the Interior Department and the power company said the White House kept close watch on the negotiations that led to the agreement. But they denied that there was any undue pressure on the Park Service to reach a compromise so that the power companies could avoid costly construction delays.</p>
        <p>"The agreement resulted from negotiations, not pressure," said Carl F. Baab of Virginia Power.</p>
        <p>Power company officials said they hoped work could start on the plant shortly. But they expressed concern over delays, should the agreement with the Park Service be challenged in court.</p>
        <p>David W. Carr Jr., a lawyer for the Southern Environmental Law Center, said his organization would study the details of the agreement over the weekend and then determine whether there would be a challenge.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
