<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>We'll Need More Than a Water-Saving Drive</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="492022"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHORTAGES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAJOR, DAVID C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DE133CF934A35751C1A967958260" item-length="341" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>We'll Need More Than a Water-Saving Drive</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>"What to Do About Water" (editorial, Nov. 19), on the drought warning for New York City's water supply system, shows little understanding of the complexity and seriousness of the water management and planning problems facing New York City and the communities upstate served by the city's system. The relatively minor conservation measures you advocate are helpful but inadequate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>"What to Do About Water" (editorial, Nov. 19), on the drought warning for New York City's water supply system, shows little understanding of the complexity and seriousness of the water management and planning problems facing New York City and the communities upstate served by the city's system. The relatively minor conservation measures you advocate are helpful but inadequate.</p>
        <p>The demand now exceeds the safe yield of the system by 200 million to 300 million gallons a day. The city's mathematical simulations show that under these conditions a drought emergency, with mandatory restrictions on water use, will occur on average every nine years.</p>
        <p>The Mayor's intergovernmental task force on New York City water supply needs, whose final report is due early next year, has it right. The city needs to follow a two-fold planning path.</p>
        <p>First, it needs to implement expeditiously all reasonable conservation measures to manage demand, especially completion of the universal metering program. Second, the city should commence immediately studies of ways to increase system capacity, should that be required. Despite a well-managed conservation program, overall demands may rise in the long run. There may be upward pressures on demand from consumers in the city and upstate, from new upstate service areas with the legal right to take water from the city's system and because of larger state-mandated reservoir releases for environmental and other purposes.</p>
        <p>There may also be a need to supplement Long Island's supply through New York City's system. Global warming, and the resulting rise in sea levels and intrusion of salt water, will further complicate the supply situation. The task force has seen correctly that New York City needs both to manage demand effectively and to think carefully now about the future capacity of its exceptional water supply system.  DAVID C. MAJOR New York, Nov. 25, 1991 The writer is former chief of water resource planning, New York City Dept. of Environmental Protection.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
