<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Disk of Death</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="487410"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDING EQUIPMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KEAN, PATRICIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recording Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DB1F38F934A25752C1A967958260" item-length="690" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Disk of Death</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Patricia Kean;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KEAN, PATRICIA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The world used to be a pretty secure place. We grew up taking things like the ozone layer and the record album for granted, and assumed that like our parents before us, the tanner we were and the more records we bought, the better off we'd be.</p>
        <p>But the unthinkable happened. A nasty hole appeared in the atmosphere. The cassette came along. Then the final straw: the imperialistic compact disk, bent on nothing less than world domination. Encased in anti-nostalgic, don't-touch-me-unless-you-mean-business plastic, the CD pays lip service to cover art, liner notes and lyrics by reproducing them on the head of a pin. Worst of all, it offers sound so pure it has no place in our fallen world. As it turns out, a little perfection can be a dangerous thing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The world used to be a pretty secure place. We grew up taking things like the ozone layer and the record album for granted, and assumed that like our parents before us, the tanner we were and the more records we bought, the better off we'd be.</p>
        <p>But the unthinkable happened. A nasty hole appeared in the atmosphere. The cassette came along. Then the final straw: the imperialistic compact disk, bent on nothing less than world domination. Encased in anti-nostalgic, don't-touch-me-unless-you-mean-business plastic, the CD pays lip service to cover art, liner notes and lyrics by reproducing them on the head of a pin. Worst of all, it offers sound so pure it has no place in our fallen world. As it turns out, a little perfection can be a dangerous thing.</p>
        <p>Need proof? Take a look at the first generation of record-deprived teenagers who will soon reach adulthood, their psyches warped beyond repair. Small wonder they lack self-esteem. Their CD's are perfect -- and they are not. Yes, they have experienced Axl Rose's rage in the clear ringing tones the gods intended. But they've never known the peace, serenity and sense of well-being that flows from being the proud owner of shelf after shelf of scruffy, dog-eared, alphabetized albums. If someone had taken away your LP's when you were 16, you might also be sporting a postmodern hairdo, dabbling in Satanism and protesting things like fur.</p>
        <p>In the halcyon days of the 1970's, albums were refreshingly flawed. The needle made an impression and we lived with the consequences. As a result, when I play a record today, Marvin Gaye sings in the middle of what sounds like a driving rain and a chorus of adders. Yet these imperfections speak volumes of personal history; skips and hums bring back fond memories of playing "Mercy, Mercy Me" until the neighbors cried out for some.</p>
        <p>Like a good argument, there were two sides to every record, and like good novels, many had a tale to tell. By eliminating the distinctions between sides one and two, and encouraging us to edit an artist's work, the programmable CD player shatters the album's narrative integrity and takes us back to the pre-Sgt. Pepper age when records were choppy collections of hit singles. Until your bank offers CD conversion loans, it makes perfect economic sense to submit to the tyranny of the Top 40 and replace a dozen worn Elvis Costello albums with a single compact disk promising only his "Greatest Hits."</p>
        <p>Next to a CD, an album appears laughably oversized, like a '57 Chevy parked alongside a baby Benz. But when you held a record in your hands, the music became an all-enveloping activity. In effect, album covers made possible an MTV of the mind, a channel through which an individual could use her imagination to make Ringo come alive.</p>
        <p>But now all of us, old and young, Sinatra buff and Morrissey acolyte alike, are merely pawns in a high-stakes game of planned obsolescence. Somewhere, behind closed doors, the leaders of the shadowy multinational conspiracy that signed the record's death warrant are helpless with laughter as we shell out $15 a pop for music that is already as up to date as the rotary dial. Like the album before it, the CD will go the way of all eight-track tapes. Maybe not today, maybe not tomorrow, but soon, and for the rest of our lives.</p>
        <p>In fact, rumor has it that the best minds in the business are putting the finishing touches on a system informally known as YAT, short for "You Are There." YAT fits snugly into the palm of your hand, offers typically transcendent sound but also projects a stunning, life-size laser image that takes requests, destroys a piece of your furniture and allows you to say, truthfully, that you have partied with Megadeath in your own living room.</p>
        <p>Amid the chaos, only one thing is certain. You can bet your last Monkees album that whatever form the next audio sensation takes, it will be smaller, shinier, awesomely aerodynamic and terribly, terribly digital. But rather than make us happy, our pursuit of the cutting edge will leave its scars -- a glut of faux-walnut cabinetry and a perpetual state-of-the-art anxiety. Mercy, mercy me.</p>
        <p>Patricia Kean is writing a book of essays.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Patricia Kean is writing a book of essays.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
