<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Equation For Saving Energy</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="435484"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="BLACKBOARD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNION OF CONCERNED SCIENTISTS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WAITE, TERESA L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMPSON, WALTER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DF1738F934A35757C0A967958260" item-length="403" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Equation For Saving Energy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Teresa L. Waite</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WAITE, TERESA L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MIX together a dedicated group of people with authority from the top, whip up awareness and support at the bottom and add a generous amount of dough. The result, according to Walter Simpson, is energy conservation a la mode.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simpson, the energy officer at the State University of New York at Buffalo, is the creator of this formula, called "Recipe for an Effective Campus Energy Conservation Program," which outlines the ingredients necessary for universities to cut waste, save money and protect the environment. The report was recently published by the Union of Con&lt;ll37cerned Scientists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MIX together a dedicated group of people with authority from the top, whip up awareness and support at the bottom and add a generous amount of dough. The result, according to Walter Simpson, is energy conservation a la mode.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simpson, the energy officer at the State University of New York at Buffalo, is the creator of this formula, called "Recipe for an Effective Campus Energy Conservation Program," which outlines the ingredients necessary for universities to cut waste, save money and protect the environment. The report was recently published by the Union of Con</p>
        <p>Nine years ago Mr. Simpson was an ambitious graduate student of philosophy and a concerned environmentalist looking for a job. As he recalled: "I told the administrators that there was so much energy waste on this campus that even if I were incompetent, I couldn't help but save the university more money than they would pay me."</p>
        <p>The administrators bought the argument, and last year Mr. Simpson helped save the school about $3 million on utility bills.</p>
        <p>With such success, Mr. Simpson said he wanted to share his findings with other schools, especially at a time of increasing concern about global warming and the depletion of natural resources. "Most schools, institutions and homeowners will find they can reduce their energy consumption by 50 percent," he said.</p>
        <p>He is currently working with the National Organization of Physical Plant Administrators to send the report to its university members. The Union of Concerned Scientists in Cambridge, Mass., is also distributing the report to scientists and campus environmental groups.</p>
        <p>While many of the report's 21 steps seem obvious, not all are easily accomplished.</p>
        <p>Leading the list is the need for an enthusiastic group of people -- a cross-section of campus representing maintenance and housing, students and faculty -- to coordinate a conservation program. This group, the guide says, must have the support of the university administration.</p>
        <p>With such authority, it can then start an awareness campaign, with posters, publications and seminars, to garner campus support. "Seize the moral ground," Mr. Simpson said. "Administration officials may be concerned about line item budgets, but more people can be turned on by how conservation can protect wilderness areas, mitigate the greenhouse effect or even reduce the risk of going to war over oil."  BLACKBOARD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
