<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Receding Ice on Arctic Sea Hints at Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="457376"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ONTARIO (CANADA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES GEOLOGICAL SURVEY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GLOERSEN, PER (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CAMPBELL, WILLIAM J (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Ontario</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DE163DF937A35754C0A967958260" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Receding Ice on Arctic Sea Hints at Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the latest indication that a warming climate has significantly affected the northernmost regions of the earth, scientists reported today that the extent of ice in the Arctic Sea declined about 2 percent from 1978 to 1987.</p>
        <p>Three separate studies in the last year have found that the part of the Northern Hemisphere covered by snow has been shrinking, that sea ice near Greenland has become substantially thinner and that Alaskan snow melted two weeks earlier in the 1980's than in the 1940's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the latest indication that a warming climate has significantly affected the northernmost regions of the earth, scientists reported today that the extent of ice in the Arctic Sea declined about 2 percent from 1978 to 1987.</p>
        <p>Three separate studies in the last year have found that the part of the Northern Hemisphere covered by snow has been shrinking, that sea ice near Greenland has become substantially thinner and that Alaskan snow melted two weeks earlier in the 1980's than in the 1940's.</p>
        <p>A fourth study found that a warmer climate has profoundly disrupted ecosystems in northwestern Ontario, threatening lake trout fisheries, cutting the flow of water into lakes and making them more fertile but less able to flush out pollutants.</p>
        <p>Now the latest study, appearing in today's issue of the British journal Nature, shows that sea ice in the Arctic receded slightly toward the North Pole in the 1980's. The finding is based on an analysis of measurements made every other day from October 1978 to August 1987 by a sensing instrument aboard a satellite.  No Ice Change in Antarctic</p>
        <p>The analysis was performed by Dr. Per Gloersen of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration's Goddard Space Flight Center at Greenbelt, Md., and by Dr. William J. Campbell of the United States Geological Survey Ice and Climate Project at the University of Puget Sound in Tacoma, Wash.</p>
        <p>In contrast to the Arctic, the study found no significant changes in the extent of Antarctic Sea ice. The authors of the study said they did not know the reason for this difference. But there is more ocean in the Southern Hemisphere, other scientists say, and the ocean absorbs heat and tends to delay warming.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gloersen and Dr. Mitchell note in their report that computerized simulations of the atmosphere's workings show that the Southern Hemisphere warms more slowly than the Northern Hemisphere when atmospheric concentrations of carbon dioxide are doubled. Carbon dioxide, which traps heat in the atmosphere, causing the earth to warm, is increasing because of the burning of fossil fuels like coal and oil.</p>
        <p>Many scientists believe that growing amounts of the gas in the atmosphere will cause the global climate to warm significantly, perhaps even catastrophically, over the next few decades. The last decade, on the whole, was the world's warmest since people began keeping temperature records in the latter part of the 19th century. But scientists disagree on whether this recent warming was caused by the increase in heat-trapping gases or is a result of the climate system's natural variability.</p>
        <p>"The smoking gun has not been identified yet," Dr. John E. Walsh, an atmospheric scientist at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, said in an interview. Nevertheless, he noted in a commentary in Nature, computer simulations suggest that the warming would be noticed sooner in the Arctic than elsewhere in the Northern Hemisphere.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gloersen said in an interview that the observed decrease in Arctic Sea ice could be an indicator of long-term climatic change and consequently "bears close scrutiny" for the next 10 to 20 years.</p>
        <p>In looking at all the recent studies involving warming and the northern latitudes, Dr. Walsh said, "You begin to think that something's really going on, but if you look closer, there's usually a caveat that goes with each one." For example, he said, the Gloersen-Campbell study shows that although the area of sea ice receded toward the poles, the area of open water within the ice area has also decreased. Retreating Ice Fills Holes</p>
        <p>"The position of the ice edge has gone north," he said, "but north of that ice edge, some of what used to be open water is filled in with ice. So you can't say we've lost 2 percent of the ice on the basis of their results. We've lost some, but a little less than 2 percent."</p>
        <p>Dr. Gloersen's explanation is that as the ice retreats, its distribution becomes more compact.</p>
        <p>There is a further puzzle. Computer simulations show that with global warming, Arctic areas should warm more than temperate areas, Dr. Walsh said, adding, "But the Arctic has not warmed any more than the rest of the Northern Hemisphere."</p>
        <p>Despite all the qualifications, Dr. Walsh said, "there's certainly some evidence accumulating" of an Arctic impact of a warming trend.</p>
        <p>If what is happening in the Arctic is a sign of a global warming trend, scientists say, that trend could be interrupted by the eruption last month of the Mount Pinatubo volcano in the Philippines. Climatologists expect that sulfur dioxide spewed into the stratosphere by the eruption will react with water to produce a long-lasting global haze. The haze is expected to reflect and scatter some sunlight for perhaps three or four years, cooling the earth and largely counteracting any further warming in that period.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
