<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Many Competing Bills Chase the Energy Problem</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="433221"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY EFFICIENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSERVATION OF RESOURCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXPLORATION OF RESOURCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXCISE TAXES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exploration of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Excise Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DC1239F93BA15750C0A967958260" item-length="1214" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Many Competing Bills Chase the Energy Problem</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawmakers have responded to the Bush Administration's national energy strategy with a flurry of competing proposals to raise gasoline taxes, improve automobile mileage, raise energy efficiency in businesses and homes, open sensitive regions to oil exploration, and spend hundreds of millions of dollars for research on conservation and renewable sources of energy.</p>
        <p>At last count, the House Energy and Commerce Committee was reviewing 68 proposals for revamping Federal energy policy, and, in the Senate, four main bills and more than a dozen others have been introduced.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lawmakers have responded to the Bush Administration's national energy strategy with a flurry of competing proposals to raise gasoline taxes, improve automobile mileage, raise energy efficiency in businesses and homes, open sensitive regions to oil exploration, and spend hundreds of millions of dollars for research on conservation and renewable sources of energy.</p>
        <p>At last count, the House Energy and Commerce Committee was reviewing 68 proposals for revamping Federal energy policy, and, in the Senate, four main bills and more than a dozen others have been introduced.</p>
        <p>Despite the intense energy expended in making proposals, some of the most influential lawmakers have expressed doubts that Congress will resolve fierce regional, economic and environmental issues and reach a consensus on a final package. The reason: Oil supplies are steady and prices have fallen since the end of the Persian Gulf war.  No Shortages, No Brownouts</p>
        <p>"At the moment, there are no gasoline lines or brownouts," Representative John D. Dingell, Democrat of Michigan, chairman of the House Energy and Commerce Committee, said last month. "I wonder if we are serious enough about energy to solve the problem at long last."</p>
        <p>Even if a bill emerges, staff experts in both houses say it is likely to take five or six months to reach the House and Senate floors. The conference to resolve differences between the bills will take more time and, if successful, a final measure may be ready before the election in 1992.</p>
        <p>Few members of Congress disagree that there is an energy problem. Low prices discourage domestic oil and gas production, economists say, while also encouraging people to waste energy. The United States is importing nearly half its oil, accounting for half the $108 billion international trade deficit in 1990, according to the Department of Commerce.</p>
        <p>Most important, higher imports are vulnerable to costly disruptions of supply. Though the Bush Administration insists the Persian Gulf war was primarily a response to Saddam Hussein's aggression, few in Congress doubt that it was also prompted by oil.</p>
        <p>What nobody in Congress knows is whether the public views the Persian Gulf war as a call to action on energy policy or as the price a nation must periodically pay to preserve its oil-based way of life.</p>
        <p>"Regrettably, we were not wise enough 10 years ago to continue the energy security measures enacted after the oil crises of the 1970's," said Representative Leon E. Panetta, chairman of the House Budget Committee, who introduced an energy proposal last month that called for establishing a minimum price for oil. "Our dependence has tragically resulted in war. How many times do we have to learn this lesson?"</p>
        <p>The debate in Congress will be framed by two issues: whether to open the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, a 17.9-million-acre wilderness in Alaska, to oil and gas exploration, and whether to raise fuel mileage standards on automobiles by 40 percent. Drilling in the Refuge</p>
        <p>The opening of the refuge was proposed on Feb. 20 by the Bush Administration in its national energy strategy and was included in several Congressional bills, including one introduced by Senators J. Bennett Johnston, Democrat of Louisiana, and Malcolm Wallop, Republican of Wyoming, the chairman and ranking minority member of the Senate Committee on Energy and Natural Resources.</p>
        <p>The President's plan also includes removing obstacles to the constructon of nuclear power plants, reducing restrictions on utilities that generate electricity for the wholesale market and simplifying licensing for hydroelectric power plants, along with a modest conservation effort, including encouraging the use of alternative fuels in vehicle fleets.</p>
        <p>The nation's largest environmental groups, among them the Sierra Club and the National Wildlife Federation, have vowed to block any effort to drill in the Arctic refuge. Energy Secretary James D. Watkins promised Senator Johnston in a hearing earlier this month that the President would veto any bill that did not include opening the refuge to oil exploration.</p>
        <p>Increasing fuel efficiency in cars was offered by Senators Richard H. Bryan, Democrat of Nevada, and Slade Gorton, Republican of Washington. It calls for raising average fuel economy in cars from 27.5 miles a gallon currently to nearly 40 miles a gallon, an increase that could save 2.8 million barrels of oil daily, about nine times as much oil as the Arctic Refuge is expected to produce daily, Senator Bryan says.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups support the bill. But Samuel K. Skinner, the Secretary of Transportation, said on Tuesday that raising fuel mileage standards would destroy the domestic auto industry and he would urge the President to veto any bill that contained such a provision.</p>
        <p>Having watched two of the most important groups in the debate stake out their positions, members of Congress and their top staff experts now wonder how much the White House or the environmental community will compromise or whether either the White House or the environmentalists can afford to be accused of derailing a substantive energy bill.</p>
        <p>"The question for Congress is, do you lose people by putting both controversial items in a comprehensive bill or do you gain people by tackling the issues and putting both items in," said Jack Riggs, director of the House Energy and Commerce Committee's Subcommittee on Energy and Power. "That's what we're going to spend a year finding out."</p>
        <p>Other proposals are attracting considerable attention as well.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups are fond of the bill introduced last week by Senators Timothy E. Wirth, Democrat of Colorado, and James M. Jeffords, Republican of Vermont. It seeks to improve the energy efficiency of homes, businesses and the Federal Government but does not mention opening the Arctic Refuge.</p>
        <p>In the House, Representative Panetta proposed to control supplies of oil by price strategies. Mr. Panetta's bill would set a price floor of $16 a barrel for domestic oil. It would also raise gasoline taxes.</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Panetta's plan, if oil prices increased and then fell back, the Government would be able to collect half of the retreat as an additional tax on gasoline. The Administration has said it opposes any new motor fuel taxes.</p>
        <p>Representative Norman F. Lent, Republican of Long Island, the ranking minority member of the House Energy and Commerce Committee, has proposed an energy bill with other House Republicans that is similar to the White House energy strategy. It would make it easier for utilities to license nuclear power plants with streamlined procedures. The bill would provide tax credits for utilities that generate electricity with renewable energy sources including the sun, wind, and hot water from deep wells. It also seeks to make it easier for pipeline companies to build interstate natural-gas pipelines.</p>
        <p>And Philip R. Sharp, Democrat of Indiana, introduced five proposals that would require the Government to set new fuel-efficiency standards for utilities, expand the Strategic Petroleum Reserve from a billion to 1.5 billion barrels, streamline regulations for building gas pipelines, and provide tax breaks for utilities that generate electricity with renewable sources of energy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
