<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amazon Forest Loss Is Sharply Cut in Brazil</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="432815"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRAZIL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AMAZON JUNGLE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AMAZON RIVER BASIN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL SPACE RESEARCH INSTITUTE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKE, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru/Amazon Basin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEED71638F935A15750C0A967958260" item-length="751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amazon Forest Loss Is Sharply Cut in Brazil</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKE, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOREST rangers were murdered, and sugar was poured in the fuel tanks of patrol helicopters during the Amazon's fractious "burning season," but the deforestation rate dropped sharply last year, according to new figures gathered by satellites.</p>
        <p>Sparing an expanse of rain forest the size of Delaware, Brazilian farmers and ranchers burned 27 percent less forest in 1990 than in 1989, according to a study by the National Space Research Institute.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOREST rangers were murdered, and sugar was poured in the fuel tanks of patrol helicopters during the Amazon's fractious "burning season," but the deforestation rate dropped sharply last year, according to new figures gathered by satellites.</p>
        <p>Sparing an expanse of rain forest the size of Delaware, Brazilian farmers and ranchers burned 27 percent less forest in 1990 than in 1989, according to a study by the National Space Research Institute.</p>
        <p>By comparing Landsat satellite images, researchers found that the annual rate of forest clearing dropped to 5,334 square miles in 1990 from 7,273 square miles in 1989.</p>
        <p>"The drop is very clear and very real," said Luiz Gylvan Meira, director of land observation for the Brazilian institute.  Global Effects of Losses</p>
        <p>With world concern high over potential global warming from deforestation, the Brazilian figures are eagerly anticipated by scientists and environmentalists every year. After several years of controversy, a consensus has emerged among scientists that figures by the Space Research Institute are the most accurate yardstick for measuring the loss of the Amazon's forest cover.</p>
        <p>The institute's data analysis techniques are highly accurate, said Compton J. Tucker, an American biologist who has been using satellites to study Brazil's deforestation for the last decade, most recently for NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center in Maryland.</p>
        <p>Next month in Puerto Rico, the Brazilians plan to train teams from six other Amazon Basin nations in the skills of tracking rain forest deforestation. For the project, the Pan Amazon Deforestation Study, NASA has purchased regional satellite data from the Space Research Institute in Sao Jose dos Campos.</p>
        <p>While photographs from space show a slowing of deforestation, people on the ground disagree on the causes.</p>
        <p>"I attribute the drop to rain and to the economic recession -- not to the Government of Brazil," said Fabio Feldmann, an opposition legislator who was recently elected chairman of the environment committee of Brazil's Chamber of Deputies. Other critics say that Operation Amazonia, the Government's campaign against deforestation, was begun in late August, well after the annual six-month burning season had started.</p>
        <p>Raimundo Deusdarah, who saw several of his forest rangers and helicopters shot at last year, believes otherwise. Mr. Deusdarah, director of fire control operations for Brazil's state environmental agency, recently listed the successes of last year's campaign: agents seized 20,000 illegally cut logs and issued $9 million in fines to 3,500 violators of burning and cutting regulations.</p>
        <p>One measure of the program's impact was the violent response by landowners: 4 of the agency's 324 agents were shot to death and 2 of its 6 helicopters were struck by gunfire.</p>
        <p>Next month, the authorities plan to begin a more intensive "Operation Amazonia," with a $4 million budget, four times last year's budget.</p>
        <p>It is to start with public information campaigns targeted at rural unions, schools and landowners in Para, Mato Grosso and Rondonia, states that accounted for three-quarters of last year's Amazon deforestation. About 12 percent of the original 1.35-million-square-mile forest has been lost, up from 4.4 percent in 1978.</p>
        <p>This year, Operation Amazonia plans to enlist the services of military and civil aviation pilots who frequently crisscross remote areas of the forest. Brazil's army has trained 18 environmental agents to plot fire coordinates radioed from aircraft.</p>
        <p>Under an agreement reached last September, the Space Institute will transmit by computer modem daily reports on fire sightings read from photographs taken by satellites of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, which pass over Brazil four times a day.</p>
        <p>But in a country where the economy last year suffered its sharpest contraction in 40 years, environmental officials say they do not know whether budget officials will actually release the $4 million needed for the Amazon preservation campaign.</p>
        <p>With saving the rain forest a popular cause in Europe and the United States, Brazil has been showered recently with low-interest loans and outright gifts. But virtually all the money is designated for Amazon research or park preservation projects.</p>
        <p>"There is a lot of talk about preserving the Amazon, but very few resources actually arrive for the control side," said Mr. Deusdarah. "We need to buy helicopters, boats, jeeps. Any foreign aid is welcome."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
