<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peace Now?; There's a New Era. Then There's the Mideast.</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week In Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="463546"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRIEDMAN, THOMAS L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDA1730F93BA15754C0A967958260" item-length="1963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peace Now?; There's a New Era. Then There's the Mideast.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRIEDMAN, THOMAS L</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONSIDERING this week's American-Soviet summit in Moscow, where the first treaty reducing long-range nuclear arms will be signed, and considering the breakthrough in efforts to convene a Middle East peace conference, it is tempting to wonder whether peace isn't breaking out all over.</p>
        <p>Peace is a word that evokes images of handshakes and bear hugs, of treaties and toasts and of enmities forgotten for a spirit of live and let live. But as every statesman knows, peace in the real world of diplomacy is usually born of very different stuff.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CONSIDERING this week's American-Soviet summit in Moscow, where the first treaty reducing long-range nuclear arms will be signed, and considering the breakthrough in efforts to convene a Middle East peace conference, it is tempting to wonder whether peace isn't breaking out all over.</p>
        <p>Peace is a word that evokes images of handshakes and bear hugs, of treaties and toasts and of enmities forgotten for a spirit of live and let live. But as every statesman knows, peace in the real world of diplomacy is usually born of very different stuff.</p>
        <p>That is worth remembering in this season of political global warming -- not only in order to appreciate the limits of the peace now developing in Europe and between the superpowers, but also to understand why peace across the Atlantic will not automatically be translated into peace along the Jordan as well.</p>
        <p>The lamb only lies down with the lion in the Old Testament's vision of peace. Peace in the real world usually comes about by the lion's eating the lamb. The progress in East-West relations in the last five years -- whether it was the reunification of Germany, the withdrawal of the Soviet Union from Eastern Europe, the lessening of East-West competition or a nuclear arms reduction treaty favoring the West -- all derived from a single fact: the triumph of capitalism over Communism. In Defeat, Clarity</p>
        <p>Not only was there a clear victor and a clear vanquished, but, equally important, the vanquished understood they had been vanquished. The Soviet Union understood it would have to change its system and behavior; Mr. Gorbachev's genius has been to do this with a style and flair that enabled him to get the most out of a defeat. The cold war may not have ended with a single Appomattox, but if the conventional arms treaty and the German unification agreement of last November are put together with the dissolution of the Warsaw Pact last month and Mr. Gorbachev's trashing of Marxism-Leninism before the Soviet Communist Party last week, they add up to the diplomatic equivalent of a conditional surrender. Still, from such lemons Mr. Gorbachev has made lemonade. When before in history has a defeated commander in chief won the Nobel Peace Prize?</p>
        <p>The fundamental difference about the Middle East -- and this is why a peace there will be much harder to arrange -- is that there is no clear-cut, acknowledged victor or vanquished. Either the defeated won't admit their defeat and behave accordingly, or someone from the outside always intervenes to spare the defeated the full consequences of folly.</p>
        <p>Consider the proposed peace conference. Syria has agreed to come not because it has been defeated in a recent battle by Israel, but because its patron, the Soviet Union, was defeated by America. The Syrians feel that by agreeing to attend an American-inspired conference now they can, at a minimum, build a new relationship with Washington, and perhaps even exploit America's leverage to regain some of the Golan Heights. In President Hafez al-Assad's vision, he will be paid either by Washington or by Israel. To keep himself ideologically pure, he probably prefers to be paid by Washington.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shamir, of course, understands this perfectly. He will maneuver to be paid retail by Washington for simply going to the peace conference, but says he will offer the Arabs nothing at the actual bargaining table.  "Shamir has no ambition to be Churchill, or to go down as a great statesman," remarked the Israeli philosopher David Hartman. "He sees himself as having a very simple mandate to honor -- preserving Eretz Israel, the land of Israel. He can do without the book contract and the Nobel Peace Prize."</p>
        <p>The Palestinians have not only been vanquished by the Israelis; they managed to come out losers in the gulf war as well, by siding with Iraq and thereby provoking the Saudis to cut off their funding. Yet they have been refusing to accept the diplomatic consequence, which is that they can only come to the peace conference on Israeli terms: as part of a joint Jordanian-Palestinian delegation, with no representatives from East Jerusalem or the Palestinian diaspora.  Avoiding Reality</p>
        <p>The Palestinians are now asking France to press Washington to press Israel not to force the Palestinians to abandon everything they ever stood for just for a seat at a conference that most likely will give them nothing.</p>
        <p>The situation recalls the passage in the Lebanese novelist Amin Maalouf's allegory of Palestine, "Leo Africanus," in which seven years after the 15th-century Muslim expulsion from Spain a Muslim father says to his son: "You see, Hassan, all those men still have hung up on their walls the key to their houses in Granada . . . The only reason for their existence is the thought that soon, thanks to the Great Sultan or to Providence, they will find their house once again . . . They live like this, they will die like this, and their sons will do so after them. Perhaps one day it may be necessary for someone to dare to teach them to look unflinchingly at their defeat, to explain to them that in order to get on one's feet again one must first admit that one is down on the ground."</p>
        <p>Another contrast between Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d's diplomacy in Europe and his diplomacy in the Middle East is that in the Middle East the means has become the end. Mr. Baker appears to have no plans for what comes after a peace conference, no concept even for what tradeoffs can or should be made at the bargaining table between Arabs and Israelis. This could be risky, if one accepts the principle that a diplomatic conference cannot be an end in itself, but can only ratify power relationships that have already been worked out on the ground. The proposed Middle East peace conference could easily turn into a forum for each side to present its aspirations and expect the United States to deliver the other side's concessions. It would be as though, at last year's "two plus four" conference on German unification -- which Mr. Baker also organized -- the Soviets had been allowed to come still refusing to concede the loss of East Germany, the West Germans to come demanding Alsace-Lorraine and the Americans and British to come insisting on remaining in Berlin forever.</p>
        <p>The deal over Germany was already pre-arranged because "Gorbachev admitted failure -- but here nobody will ever admit defeat, not Arafat and not even Saddam Hussein," said the Israeli historian Meron Benvenisti. "So the diplomatic game never really gets going." In other words, the Israelis always win and the Arabs always make sure that they never enjoy it. Hidden Motives</p>
        <p>Not only does no one in this neighborhood acknowledge defeat; often they won't even acknowledge their real interests or motives. Take the Saudis. They have been quietly ridding their kingdom of thousands of Palestinians and replacing them with Egyptians; but last week, there was King Fahd pleading with Mr. Baker in public to help ease the plight of Palestinians. Everyone in the region knows the Saudis much prefer the Israelis over Yasir Arafat or Jordan's King Hussein for controlling the progressive, potentially radical Palestinians in the West Bank and Gaza Strip. Israel is a more efficient policeman, and can be blamed. But in the shadow dance of Middle East diplomacy the Saudis say just the opposite. The really scary thing -- for the Saudis -- is that President Bush seems to believe their public posturing.</p>
        <p>Finally, the United States and the Soviet Union can conclude arms control agreements because each society has an intuitive sense about the other's solidity and ability to honor the agreement. Even if the Soviet Union splits apart there will always be a Russia, and Russia in the mind of America is as permanent as the Kremlin walls. So it was between Egypt and Israel. Egypt in the mind of Israel is a nation, a people as old as the Jewish people. Egypt is the pyramids, and with such a people one can trade land for peace. Syria in the mind of Israel evokes something very different. Damascus is intrigue; it is a minority Alawite clique ruling by conspiracy. Syria is shifting sands, and with such a country it will be hard to convince Israelis to conclude anything more than an elaborate armistice. THE ARAB-ISRAELI QUESTIONS</p>
        <p>The American plan for Middle East peace talks envisions an international conference that would break after two days into one-on-one sessions between Israel and individual Arab parties. The goal as stated by Americans would be an exchange of land occupied by Israel for Arab recognition of Israel's right to exist in peace, although Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir of Israel still rejects the land-for-peace formula. Syria, Lebanon and Jordan have agreed to attend and Jordan has agreed to take part in a joint delegation with Palestinians, although no Palestinians have yet agreed to join in. Egypt and Saudi Arabia would take part in matters of general concern to the Middle East. Here is a look at territorial and security questions expected to figure in any such talks.</p>
        <p>With Jordan and the Palestinians:</p>
        <p>The Camp David agreements of 1979 foresaw a period of Palestinian autonomy, and the nature of this autonomy would be the principal question. The final status of land under occupation by Israel since 1967 would be worked out only later, but maneuvering for advantage on this question figures in all the preliminaries. Even conciliatory Israeli officials reject the notion of an independent Palestinian state, favoring instead an entity tied tightly to Jordan. The fate of about 100,000 Jewish settlers -- most in the West Bank near Jerusalem -- would also have to be negotiated. Three areas are involved:</p>
        <p>- West Bank: This, as well as the Gaza Strip, was part of the larger Arab state envisioned in the 1947 United Nations plan to partition Palestine; it was annexed by Jordan after Israel drove back attacking Arab forces in the first Middle East war in 1948, and has been administered by Israel since the 1967 war. Most Israelis consider control of the West Bank a strategic asset to be bargained away only for the firmest guarantees against a new military threat. At the same time, many religious and nationalist Israelis also see it as part of the biblical Land of Israel and are reluctant to give back any of it. - Gaza Strip: This came under Egyptian military administration after 1948 and has been administered by Israel since 1967. It contains some of the most embittered Palestinian refugee camps. Arrangements for military security and for linking Gaza and the West Bank would have to be negotiated.</p>
        <p>- Jerusalem: Israel is adamant that its reunification of Jerusalem as Israel's capital after the 1967 war is not subject to negotiation; this clashes with Arab assertions that East Jerusalem should be treated as part of the West Bank. Among the bitterest of memories for Israelis is that they were prevented from visiting Jewish holy places in the Old City while Jordan controlled the eastern half of Jerusalem from 1948 to 1967. After the 1967 fighting, Israel proclaimed Jerusalem irrevocably reunited and extended its boundaries. With Syria:</p>
        <p>The Golan Heights was wrested from Syria in the 1967 Middle East war; Israel in effect annexed it in 1981, and 11,000 Jews have settled there. Syria has made recovery of this strategic high ground a major goal; Israelis fear that Syria might again shell northern Israel from the heights, as it often did before 1967. With Lebanon:</p>
        <p>The chief issue here is the presence of Israeli forces in a narrow border strip of Lebanese territory that they have patrolled, with the aid of a proxy Lebanese militia, since 1985 to prevent cross-border guerrilla raids.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
