<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Paint, New Cars, Acid Rain: Often, They Don't Mix</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="54" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Consumer's World Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="485716"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PAINTS AND PAINTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PROTECTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SULFURIC ACID</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MEIER, BARRY</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CONSUMER'S WORLD PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Motoring</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DB163CF93AA35752C1A967958260" item-length="1083" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Paint, New Cars, Acid Rain: Often, They Don't Mix</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARRY MEIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MEIER, BARRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Acid rain, already blamed for killing lakes and trees, has found another target -- the paint of some late-model cars.</p>
        <p>The problem is a result of both increasing pollution and the widespread use in recent years of a high-gloss car paint technology known as clear coat. The finish, which creates a mirrorlike sheen, is used on most cars today. Auto producers and paint companies say the finish is particularly susceptible to marring by acid rain and other pollutants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Acid rain, already blamed for killing lakes and trees, has found another target -- the paint of some late-model cars.</p>
        <p>The problem is a result of both increasing pollution and the widespread use in recent years of a high-gloss car paint technology known as clear coat. The finish, which creates a mirrorlike sheen, is used on most cars today. Auto producers and paint companies say the finish is particularly susceptible to marring by acid rain and other pollutants.</p>
        <p>"It tends to highlight all the defects," said John P. Gallagher, a product manager in the automotive finish division of E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company, a major producer of car paint.</p>
        <p>The scope of the paint problem is unclear. But spokesmen for the Ford Motor Company, General Motors Corporation, the Chrysler Corporation and Honda Motor Company all said that acid rain was posing a problem. At the same time, they all declined to release data concerning recent warranty claims for pollution-related paint damage.</p>
        <p>Acid rain is largely created when sulfur dioxide and nitrogen dioxide are discharged by factories and power plants. The compounds turn into sulfuric acid and nitric acid in the atmosphere and can travel hundreds of miles before they fall to earth as rain or snow.</p>
        <p>When acid rain falls on a vehicle, the moisture evaporates but the acid remains. Concentrated by sunlight, the sulfuric acid can become so strong that it will eat through or etch a car's finish.</p>
        <p>The blemish that results looks like a splattered raindrop. Once the damage occurs, it cannot be removed by washing, and it is particularly noticeable on vehicles that have dark or metallic finishes, auto industry officials said.</p>
        <p>"It's like you put a wet glass on a table," said Thaddeus Lasko, a manager for paint development at General Motors. "If it is really severe you need to have the car refinished."</p>
        <p>Some industry officials suggest that modern car paints are more blemish-prone because Federal air-pollution regulations bar the use of certain chemicals that once provided hardness to paints. But others, while agreeing that acid rain can damage a car, say the problem is compounded because cars look better than ever and consumers have higher expectations.</p>
        <p>"Nowadays, any little blemish that might occur is disconcerting to the customer," Mr. Lasko said. A New Option</p>
        <p>Whatever the case, many car companies and their suppliers are seeking finishes more resistant to pollution. And some car dealers are adding $200 to $600 to the price of new vehicles by adding or offering as an option sealants that claim to protect car finishes against acid rain and other pollutants.</p>
        <p>For example, Mark Herega, the sales manager at George Lucas Chevrolet/Geo in Carteret, N. J., said every new car that arrives at that dealership is immediately coated with a such sealant.</p>
        <p>"We protect all our cars both for our convienience and our customer's peace of mind," he said.</p>
        <p>But other auto industry officials and dealers disputed whether such sealants worked and called them a sales gimmick.</p>
        <p>"I don't even offer it," said Anthony Pace, a salesman at Drew Chevrolet in Elizabeth, N. J. Mr. Pace said that while acid rain staining was a significant problem at his dealership two years ago, car finishes have been improved since then.</p>
        <p>In the United States, the acid rain problem for cars appears most severe in the Northeast and Southeast, although problems have been reported elsewhere, said Mr. Gallagher, the Du Pont official.</p>
        <p>"It varies in severity depending on time of the year, weather and location," he said. "One day you could have a problem, one year you could have a problem and other times you won't."</p>
        <p>Jim Tidwell, the owner of Jim Tidwell Ford in Kennesaw, Ga., said he received a rash of complaints last year from customers about marring of new car paint finishes because of pollution.</p>
        <p>"After someone has spent $10,000 to $15,000 for a new car they don't want to come back here to have it repainted after 30 days," Mr. Tidwell said, "because they know we can't do as good a paint job as the factory."</p>
        <p>He said the problem was diminishing because Ford is now coating new cars with a temporary acryliclike compound to protect vehicles against pollutants while in transit to dealerships. Nonetheless, Mr. Tidwell said he was still receiving complaints from customers.</p>
        <p>"It is still a problem," Mr. Tidwell said. "They don't have the technology in the paint as I see it." Primer, Color, Clear Coat</p>
        <p>Clear-coat car paints were introduced 20 years ago. But it was only in the mid-1980's that most car markers began to use them.</p>
        <p>In the clear-coat process, a car is painted with a primer coat, then a color coat and, finally, a clear coat, which gives the finish a high-gloss sheen.</p>
        <p>While defending the technology as superior, several car producers and paint suppliers said that as the popularity of these paints grew, so did the number of complaints from dealers and customers.</p>
        <p>As a result, at least three major paint producers, Du Pont, PPG Industries and BASF A.G., have developed tougher clear-coat finshes that are more resistant to pollution, according to their spokesmen.</p>
        <p>But the better paints are typically being used only on the more expensive models.</p>
        <p>"We are working as fast as we can and they are switching as fast as they can," Mr. Gallagher said, referring to car producers. WHEN IT RAINS, GET YOURSELF TO A CAR WASH</p>
        <p>Paint finishes are susceptible to damage from factors as diverse as industrial discharges and bird droppings.</p>
        <p>But in the case of acid rain damage, most car industry experts say the best defense is a simple one: try to wash the car after it rains.</p>
        <p>Not all pollution damage requires repainting. In the case of acid rain spotting, the damage is most troublesome on dark-colored cars or those with metallic finishes. And a car is most prone to damage in its first few months of life, when factory-applied paint is hardening.</p>
        <p>A number of car dealers are offering special sealants as protection against pollution at a cost of $200 to $600. But some experts believe that while such sealants can help retain a car's appearance, they are of little or no value against acid rain.</p>
        <p>For example, Marilyn Perchard, of the Ford Motor Company, said Ford had tested, without success, more than 100 commercial sealants for their ability to resist acid rain.</p>
        <p>"There may be products out there that I don't know about," Ms. Perchard said. "But everything that I've seen so far doesn't work."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
