<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Still Hooked on Oil</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="428168"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSERVATION OF RESOURCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSIAN GULF WAR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MIDDLE
EAST-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, ALBERT JR (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUSSEIN, SADDAM (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910306T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DC173CF935A35750C0A967958260" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Still Hooked on Oil</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Al Gore; Al Gore, Democrat of Tennessee, is the chairman of the Senate subcommittee on science, technology and space.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GORE, ALBERT JR (SEN)</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WASHINGTON</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration's new national energy strategy proposes to deal with our energy crisis the way we dealt with Saddam Hussein before he invaded Kuwait: by pretending the problem will go away if we humor it. What we need instead is the resolve and leadership with which President Bush dealt with Saddam Hussein after he invaded Kuwait.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WASHINGTON</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration's new national energy strategy proposes to deal with our energy crisis the way we dealt with Saddam Hussein before he invaded Kuwait: by pretending the problem will go away if we humor it. What we need instead is the resolve and leadership with which President Bush dealt with Saddam Hussein after he invaded Kuwait.</p>
        <p>I voted to authorize force in the Persian Gulf, and I agree with the President that this conflict has been about values far more important than oil, but I do not want to see an increase in our dependence on the oil underneath that chronically unstable region. Yet according to bipartisan analysis, the Bush strategy will result in an overall increase in U.S. oil imports, from approximately 50 percent to 60 percent when the plan is fully implemented by 2030.</p>
        <p>The Administration argues that we will be better off than we would be otherwise, but that ignores alternative policies -- energy efficiency, conservation and renewable sources -- that could dramatically reduce our dependence on imported oil and fossil fuels generally. Mr. Bush proposes instead sacrificing one of our last, most pristine wilderness areas -- the Alaska National Wildlife Refuge -- for an uncertain oilfield that would provide, at best, a few months' supply at our current rate of consumption.</p>
        <p>And while President Bush claims that the answer is the marketplace, and that the unaided forces of supply and demand can solve the problem for us, his plan offers not a single proposal for addressing the enormous hidden costs of burning and wasting such vast quantities of fossil fuels. What about the cost to our national security of increased dependence on Middle Eastern oil? Where is it addressed in the market?</p>
        <p>What about the hidden costs that burning more oil imposes on the environment? Where are they addressed in the market? Global warming may be hard to think about, but it is rapidly being recognized as one of the most serious problems humans face. The White House effort to pretend it does not exist reminds me of the point made by scientist Carl Sagan, when he quotes a song by Dire Straits: "Denial ain't just a river in Egypt."</p>
        <p>Cheap oil and energy conservation are not naturally linked. The new energy marketplace -- itself distorted by the billions we have just correctly invested in restoring stability to the world's largest reserves of oil -- will discourage investment in alternative energy sources and dampen consumer interest in greater energy efficiency.</p>
        <p>The victory of capitalism over Communism in the philosophical war of the last 75 years has been as decisive as the victory by the coalition against the forces of Saddam Hussein. In the aftermath of both victories, we need to focus on what comes next. As for the economic system we advocate for ourselves and all the world, it is time to address forthrightly what economists call the "externalities" -- those hidden costs we would rather forget.</p>
        <p>With oil prices dropping, there is no better time for a bolder energy policy. We should ask the President for political leadership and the kind of courage he showed in the gulf in order to accelerate the development of energy alternatives, confront our addiction to fossil fuels, especially foreign oil, and measure the full costs of the energy choices we make.</p>
        <p>The President's skills, personal experience and most trusted advisers are in the realm of foreign policy. Thus far, he has not shown corresponding strength in meeting the pressing needs of this country closer to home. Perhaps that is why his domestic policy decisions seem to be so vulnerable to short-term political considerations. Whatever the reason, he discarded the recommendations of his own Energy Secretary and adopted a proposal driven above all by the desire to avoid discomfiting the voters for the next 20 months. But what about the next 20 years?</p>
        <p>On energy policy, the President misreads the mood of the nation. In the Persian Gulf, we showed our remarkable ability as a nation to pull together in a crisis. Americans will show the same determination to avoid another Middle East crisis if their leaders address these issues forcefully, honestly and now.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
