<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="483741"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D61531F933A05753C1A967958260" item-length="610" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>The economy expanded in the third quarter for the first time in a year, the Government reported. But the Commerce Department's chief economist acknowledged that the recovery had started to lose momentum by Labor Day.  [ Page A1. ]  Consumer confidence fell sharply this month, the Conference Board said.  [ D13. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>The economy expanded in the third quarter for the first time in a year, the Government reported. But the Commerce Department's chief economist acknowledged that the recovery had started to lose momentum by Labor Day.  [ Page A1. ]  Consumer confidence fell sharply this month, the Conference Board said.  [ D13. ]</p>
        <p>A former senior White House aide said he had terminated a $600,000 contract to represent the former head of Saudi intelligence who is under scrutiny in the B.C.C.I. investigation.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>The White House threatened to veto any banking measure that contains a compromise by two key Democratic chairmen.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>Nine Eastern Governors and Washington's Mayor agreed to adopt California's program to require cars that pollute less.  [ A1. ]  The E.P.A. proposed rules to cut in half the kind of air pollution that is mainly responsible for acid rain.  [ A23. ]</p>
        <p>Automatic dialing is under fire by regulators, and Congress is poised to either ban or severely restrict it.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>State governments are reducing their services, despite tax increases of $25 billion in the last 15 months.  [ A16. ] Companies</p>
        <p>Salomon Brothers announced a $110 million cut in the bonuses it planned to pay employees, largely because it did not believe many of its traders and investment bankers deserved so much.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Chrysler agreed to sell its 50 percent stake in Diamond-Star to Mitsubishi for nearly $100 million.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>Time Warner signed an agreement for Toshiba and C. Itoh to invest $1 billion for a stake in Time Warner Entertainment.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>USX said its third-quarter earnings from steel dropped 93.8 percent. A rival, LTV, said it had turned a profit.  [ D1. ]  HomeFed lost $485.7 million, making a Government takeover more likely.  [ D2. ]  Warner-Lambert announced drastic cost-cutting measures.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>K-III Magazines said Harry A. McQuillen would fill the top posts of the group that acquired eight Murdoch magazines.  [ D1. ]  James Silberman is ending his career as president and editor in chief of Summit Books, a Simon &amp; Schuster imprint.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>Dial announced a proposal to complete its transformation from a bus company to a soap company.  [ D4. ] Markets</p>
        <p>Bond prices exploded and long-term rates fell well below 8 percent after the Government reported a decline in inflation.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>The dollar plunged in heavy worldwide trading on the assumption that interest rates are headed lower.  [ D18. ]  Yields on C.D.'s and money market accounts dropped slightly in the last week.  [ D7. ]</p>
        <p>Stocks managed to hold onto their gains. The Dow closed up 16.32, at 3,061.94.  [ D10. ]  Grain and soybean futures rallied.  [ D18. ] International</p>
        <p>The British Prime Minister is not prepared to sign a pledge for a "swift transition" to the final stage of monetary union.  [ A3. ]</p>
        <p>The U.S. announced a strict ban on trade with Haiti.  [ A3. ] Business Technology</p>
        <p>Technological advances are making gyroscopes smaller, lighter and cheaper, moving them beyond sophisticated military and aerospace instruments and into consumer products.  [ D9. ]  American Express plans to purchase two new massively parallel supercomputers from Thinking Machines.  [ D9. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>A dean of urban planning suggests a transportation policy that exploits opportunities to privatize, asks users to pay their way and subsidizes transit patrons. Peter Passell: Economic Scene.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>Gambling industry stocks may not be as risky as they are generally regarded. Market Place.  [ D10. ]</p>
        <p>Some leading advertisers say they are beginning to see glimmers of light amid the gloom. Stuart Elliott: Advertising.  [ D21. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
