<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="439849"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DF1639F937A15757C0A967958260" item-length="581" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Companies</p>
        <p>The Air Force selected a team led by Lockheed to build a new generation of agile, radar-evading fighter planes. Also on the winning side are General Dynamics and Boeing; the losers are Northrop and McDonnell Douglas.  [ Page A1. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Companies</p>
        <p>The Air Force selected a team led by Lockheed to build a new generation of agile, radar-evading fighter planes. Also on the winning side are General Dynamics and Boeing; the losers are Northrop and McDonnell Douglas.  [ Page A1. ]</p>
        <p>By betting on Bank of New England, J. Terrence Murray is turning Fleet/Norstar into New England's biggest bank at a time of one of the region's worst downturns.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>The involvement of Kohlberg, Kravis, Roberts in the Bank of New England deal is certain to be widely debated.  [ D7. ]</p>
        <p>I.B.M. slashed PC prices, introduced models based on Intel's latest microprocessor and said it would outpace its rivals.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>RJR Nabisco announced a small profit, its first since going private in 1989. It posted net income of $5 million.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Barclays de Zoete Wedd has abandoned its move into the American equities business after a little more than a year.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>American Express reached an agreement with Sumitomo Bank to issue charge cards and other consumer loans in Japan.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>NCR and A.T.&amp; T. seemed to move closer to a deal, as NCR said it would accept A.T.&amp; T.'s offer on certain conditions.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>A panel of Prudential directors reportedly approved offering Hardwick Simmons the top job at Prudential Securities.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>Texaco's net rose 26.5 percent, Chevron reported a gain of 17.8 percent, and Phillips Petroleum was off 38.2 percent.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>Morgan Stanley, Salomon, Alex. Brown and Piper Jaffray all reported sharply higher earnings.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>MCI said net income in the quarter fell 20.6 percent, to $130 million, despite strong revenue growth.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>Bethlehem Steel reported a first-quarter loss of $39.2 million, saying the recession had diminished demand for steel sheet.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>Times Mirror, the Tribune Co. and the Washington Post Co. reported large declines in earnings.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>NEC said it was negotiating with Bull about buying shares in the faltering French computer giant.  [ D9. ]</p>
        <p>E.D.S. and Continental signed a 10-year agreement under which E.D.S. will take over a large part of System One.  [ D4. ] The Economy</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court upheld a regulation that will make it easier for unions to organize at community hospitals.  [ A1. ]</p>
        <p>Greenspan said the economy's slide was drawing to an end and the central bank needed to be especially cautious on rate cuts.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>The fund that protects bank deposits is in far worse shape than has been reported, the G.A.O. has found.  [ D1. ] Business Technology</p>
        <p>The bar code is being groomed for a more demanding role after years of playing a bit part in the information revolution.  [ D1. ] Markets</p>
        <p>Stock prices moved slightly higher, ending a three-day losing streak. The Dow gained 2.73, to 2,930.45.  [ D10. ]</p>
        <p>Prices of long-term Treasury bonds posted a moderate recovery, pushing interest rates down slightly.  [ D16. ]</p>
        <p>Soybean futures prices surged after a Brazilian agency slashed its forecast for the soybean harvest.  [ D17. ]  The dollar fell.  [ D17. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>The latest report on the greenhouse effect is the first to bridge the canyon between alarmist science and what-me-worry economics. Peter Passell: Economic Scene.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>The rise in Texscan's stock appears to have been prompted by a firm's recommendation. Floyd Norris: Market Place.  [ D10. ]</p>
        <p>Roger Livingston and Paul Keye have rejected the comfortable life, choosing to form an agency in Los Angeles. Advertising.  [ D18. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
