<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Forgive Debt, Finance Nature</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="460382"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSERVATION OF RESOURCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LATIN AMERICA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AMAZON JUNGLE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D61531F935A25754C0A967958260" item-length="553" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Forgive Debt, Finance Nature</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Latin America owes the world billions of dollars -- much of which it can't repay. The world wants Latin America to stop destroying its priceless rain forests, ancient nurseries of life that also serve as a natural sink for greenhouse gases. These two conditions invite a deal -- debt-for-nature swaps that would channel some of Latin America's debt into conservation.</p>
        <p>Swaps involving more than $100 million owed to private banks have already been arranged. And just a few weeks ago, Brazil gave the debt-for-nature idea a huge boost when it agreed to devote $100 million each year to saving the Amazon rain forest if banks would discount its debt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Latin America owes the world billions of dollars -- much of which it can't repay. The world wants Latin America to stop destroying its priceless rain forests, ancient nurseries of life that also serve as a natural sink for greenhouse gases. These two conditions invite a deal -- debt-for-nature swaps that would channel some of Latin America's debt into conservation.</p>
        <p>Swaps involving more than $100 million owed to private banks have already been arranged. And just a few weeks ago, Brazil gave the debt-for-nature idea a huge boost when it agreed to devote $100 million each year to saving the Amazon rain forest if banks would discount its debt.</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration likes the idea and is backing a bill that would add money owed the Federal Government to the debt-for-nature pot. The bill is floundering in the Senate, and needs a timely push from the White House.</p>
        <p>Debt-for-nature swaps sound complicated, but the mechanism is simple: Conservation groups, using private funds, buy foreign debt owed to banks. Since the debt may be uncollectible, the banks are happy to unload it at a fraction of its face value. The conservation groups then turn around and offer to forgive all or part of the debt in exchange for a pledge by the debtor nation to use the windfall for environmental purposes.</p>
        <p>In the first swap, in 1987, Conservation International paid $100,000 to Citicorp for an uncollectible $650,000 owed to Citicorp by Bolivia. Conservation International then agreed to forgive the entire debt in return for Bolivia's promise to protect four million acres of tropical forests. Since then, 15 similar swaps have been carried out with a half-dozen countries.</p>
        <p>These private ventures are modest in global terms. That's why Mr. Bush included debt-for-nature swaps in his 1990 "Enterprise for the Americas" initiative, an effort to pare debt, liberalize trade and boost investment in Latin America. Under his plan, a slice of $12 billion in Latin America's foreign aid debt would be forgiven; interest payments on the rest would flow to local environmental projects instead of the U.S. Treasury.</p>
        <p>The payments would be made in local currency, enabling debtor countries to use their scarce hard currency for imports. The payoff for the U.S.? Debtors would have to streamline their economies, pledge to reduce their debts with other big creditors like the World Bank and open their borders to outside investors on favorable terms.</p>
        <p>The House passed a bill similar to the Bush plan last month. The problem is in the Senate. A bill sponsored by Christopher Dodd, Democrat of Connecticut, includes the swap idea but dilutes the potential impact by allowing debtor countries to spend the money on child nutrition, anti-drug efforts and secondary education.</p>
        <p>These are worthy causes. But the Administration argues that they are already financed by existing A.I.D. programs, whereas environmental causes are not. Unless conservation is specifically targeted, debtor nations are likely to spend the money on projects with a quicker political payoff.</p>
        <p>Still, the Dodd bill is better than no bill at all -- and it could be reshaped in a House-Senate conference. But first the Senate must act. At stake is a promising extension of an innovative way to reduce debt -- and enrich the planet in the bargain.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
