<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Using Bacteria to Control Pollution</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="429736"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BACTERIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ODORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOG</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLUSHA, JOHN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Odors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910313T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDF123AF930A25750C0A967958260" item-length="1113" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Using Bacteria to Control Pollution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN HOLUSHA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLUSHA, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bacteria may be better than chemicals or absorbent materials at controlling emissions of volatile solvents that contribute to low-level smog and at eliminating the odors of sewage treatment plants and composting operations, experts in the field say.</p>
        <p>Although the use of bacteria to clean up pollution on land and in water is still in the experimental stage, at least two dozen biological filters are in use in this country, scrubbing out odors and breaking foul organic compounds into more benign carbon dioxide and water.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bacteria may be better than chemicals or absorbent materials at controlling emissions of volatile solvents that contribute to low-level smog and at eliminating the odors of sewage treatment plants and composting operations, experts in the field say.</p>
        <p>Although the use of bacteria to clean up pollution on land and in water is still in the experimental stage, at least two dozen biological filters are in use in this country, scrubbing out odors and breaking foul organic compounds into more benign carbon dioxide and water.</p>
        <p>Biofilters or soil bioreactors, as they are called, take advantage of bacteria's ability to adapt themselves to feed on whatever material is available, from tree leaves to propane.</p>
        <p>The filters are decidedly low tech and appear from the outside to be little more than a mound of dirt. But they can control air emission problems without consuming the chemicals used in scrubber systems or without the regeneration systems needed with activated carbon treatment.</p>
        <p>S. C. Johnson &amp; Son Inc. uses a biofilter to treat emissions of pentane and butane that escape from its aerosol can filling operations in Racine, Wis. "We lose from 30 to 100 tons from the aerosol filling line a year," said Timothy Lafond, the environmental manager at Johnson's Waxdale manufacturing plant. "On average we get 90 percent-plus control efficiency" from the biofilter, he said. The bacteria present in the soil break the relatively simple hydrocarbons into carbon dioxide and water, which are vented into the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Since volatile organic compounds like pentane and butane contribute to low-altitude smog, emissions are being progressively restricted by Federal and state regulations. The Johnson filter has been in continuous operation since December 1988 with little maintenance other than watering in dry periods.  Key Ingredient Is Dirt</p>
        <p>Like most biofilters, the principal ingredient is dirt. Air from around the aerosol filling is collected and blown into a grid of perforated pipes laid in a bed of gravel. The gravel diffuses the air-solvent mix, which rises into the three-foot-deep dirt filter.</p>
        <p>In it, the hydrocarbon molecules are adsorbed on droplets of water and then broken down by microbes that obtain energy and elements necessary for their survival and growth in the process. The oxygen-rich atmosphere insures that the offensive compounds will be converted chemically to oxides before leaving the filter.</p>
        <p>The Johnson filter occupies an acre between two factory buildings. It is covered with grass and looks like an open field. The performance of the filter fluctuates with the seasons because it is based on living organisms. Mr. Lafond says that 99 percent of the hydrocarbons are destroyed in warm weather, but that the breakdown rate drops to 65 percent in severe cold as the bacteria become less active.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lafond said it was not necessary to develop special strains of bacteria to make a soil filter work. "The bugs are already there," he added. But he said there was a "learning curve" when it was first used, as the bacteria adapted to feed on the hydrocarbons. "We started at 30 to 40 percent efficiency and gradually took that up to over 90 percent," Mr. Lafond said, as the solvent-eating bacteria increased in number.  Looking for Green Grass</p>
        <p>Since moisture in an important part of the treatment process, the water content of the filter is monitored. "If the grass is green, then we assume the water is O.K.," Mr. Lafond said. "If it starts to turn brown, then we get concerned." Lawn sprinklers are used until the grass is green and lush again.</p>
        <p>Since the bacteria feed on the wastes they are treating, the filters can be operated for years with little attention. Maintenance is sometimes limited to cutting the grass. The one exception is in cases where the chemical products of the breakdown process tend to acidify. Many of the bacteria that best remove odor-causing compounds are sensitive to acidity of the soil. Once again, though, the solution is simple.</p>
        <p>For example, in Gainesville, Fla., a soil filter is used to remove hydrogen sulfide -- a toxic gas with a rotten-egg smell -- from a sewage treatment plant. Although the filter removes more than 99 percent of the offensive gas, according to Eric R. Allen, a professor of environmental engineering at the University of Florida, the sulfur oxides produced by the breakup of hydrogen sulfide tend to combine with the moisture in the earth to form sulfuric acid.</p>
        <p>"We have to add lime to offset the acidity," Professor Allen said.  'Very, Very Cheap'</p>
        <p>He said the low-tech nature of biofilters had made it difficult to convince engineers accustomed to chemical treatment systems of their value. But he said economics might increase their attractiveness. "They are very, very cheap to operate," he said.</p>
        <p>A report produced by Geoffrey A. Kuter of International Process Systems, which uses biofilters to control odors from composting operations, indicated that the annual operating cost would be 44 percent less than a chemical scrubbing system and 75 percent less than activated carbon -- which is highly adsorbent because of its large surface area.</p>
        <p>One drawback is the amount of land required for a biofilter. Not every industrial site has an acre or more to set aside to treat emissions. "If you have a lot of area, then you can use a biofilter," said Sam Cha, a chemist with TRC Environmental Engineering in East Hartford, Conn. "But if you do not, they you would probably want a carbon system, because they are very compact."</p>
        <p>There are a variety of formulas for the composition of biofilters, depending on the compounds to be treated. Ordinary soil, compost and peat provide the microorganisms, and other materials, like volcanic ash, sand and bark, are used to make the pile porous. Mr. Kuter said the ideal filter had 40 to 60 percent empty space to allow air to circulate.</p>
        <p>He said biofilters were merely an engineered version of a technique practiced for centuries: covering foul-smelling materials with soil to control odor. Some examples are the soil covers typically found over septic systems and garbage landfills.</p>
        <p>But he said the effectiveness of this approach had been limited by the amount of oxygen present in the soil. By controlling the amount of air being mixed with the substance to be treated, biofilter operators can insure an abundant supply of oxygen.</p>
        <p>Biofilters have been widely used in Europe and Japan, and are gradually attracting more interest in this country. "We did our project before it became popular," Mr. Lafond said. "Now a lot of people are very interested in biological systems."  BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
