<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Company Is Finding The Good in Pollution</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="414000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FERTILIZER</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MORRISON, GARRETT (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fertilizer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DE133BF93AA35752C0A967958260" item-length="1295" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Company Is Finding The Good in Pollution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>THOMASTON, Me., Jan. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A radically different approach to air pollution -- converting harmful combustion waste products into something useful -- is being tested here at New England's only cement plant. A geochemist has found a way to combine the acid and ash emissions from the plant to produce fertilizer, distilled water and limestone for the cement plant, and hardly anything else.</p>
        <p>The system's designers think the process will have wide application in other industries trying to cope with pollutants, including paper mills, trash-to-energy plants and some coal plants. In addition to producing a product that can be sold, the proceedure eliminates the problem of disposing of chemicals filtered out of the smokestack and the need to buy neutralizing materials for a "scrubber." It also allows the use of cheap but dirty high-sulfur fuel, even while reducing air pollution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A radically different approach to air pollution -- converting harmful combustion waste products into something useful -- is being tested here at New England's only cement plant. A geochemist has found a way to combine the acid and ash emissions from the plant to produce fertilizer, distilled water and limestone for the cement plant, and hardly anything else.</p>
        <p>The system's designers think the process will have wide application in other industries trying to cope with pollutants, including paper mills, trash-to-energy plants and some coal plants. In addition to producing a product that can be sold, the proceedure eliminates the problem of disposing of chemicals filtered out of the smokestack and the need to buy neutralizing materials for a "scrubber." It also allows the use of cheap but dirty high-sulfur fuel, even while reducing air pollution.</p>
        <p>Factories that want to cut pollution have long had the option of installing scrubbers, which capture sulfur dioxide that causes acid rain by spraying the smoke with a limestone solution, chemically locking up the sulfur. But that is expensive, and merely transforms acid that would have gone into the air into a solid that can poison groundwater and must be disposed of.  Half the Problem</p>
        <p>And sulfur dioxide is only half the problem for many fuel-burning factories. They also produce ash, which is highly alkaline and can include heavy metals that can easily dissolve in underground water.</p>
        <p>In contrast, the "recovery scrubber" here -- a small chemical reactor -- combines the sulfur dioxide and ash to make fertilizer. The process begins with capturing in filters the waste dust leaving the concrete kiln and dissolving it in water. The dust includes ash, limestone that has been contaminated with sulfur, and potassium, which in cement-making is a contaminant. The water is pumped into a tank, and the exhaust gases that passed through the filter, which contain sulfur dioxide, are allowed to bubble through the water.</p>
        <p>In the tank, the calcium-sulfur compounds are broken apart, and the sulfur and potassium combine to produce potassium sulfate, a fertilizer. Waste heat from the smoke is then used to distill away the water and recover the fertilizer. The distilled water is used in the kiln. At the same time, the calcium combines with carbon dioxide, and is turned back into limestone.</p>
        <p>The inventor, Dr. Garrett Morrison, a geochemist, first tried the chemical reaction in a trash barrel. Then he persuaded the Passamaquoddy Indian tribe, which then owned the cement company, to put up $250,000 for a larger experiment.</p>
        <p>The tribe, which had bought the plant in 1983 with the proceeds of a land settlement, has since sold it, but owns the rights to the process and hopes it will be commercialized and applied to a variety of industries.</p>
        <p>Proponents of the system say sales of the fertilizer and savings on waste disposal will more than pay for the recovery scrubber.  In addition, under the Clean Air Act, a factory that cuts acid emissions can sell the "right" to emit the same amount of pollution. This raises the possibility that some companies will install this kind of scrubber even if they already meet clean air rules, just to increase their profits.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, many plants must buy an alkali to neutralize the sulfur dioxide, and also pay to haul away the resulting solids as well as ash, said Thomas N. Tureen, chairman of Tribal Assets Management, the Passamaquoddy's Portland-based company. The recovery scrubber can use that ash in place of the alkali.  Prototype Is Tested</p>
        <p>An $11 million full-scale prototype began tests late last month, with the cost split evenly between the Department of Energy's Clean Coal Technology program and CDN-USA, a Spanish consortium that now owns the cement company, called the Dragon Products Company.</p>
        <p>The recovery scrubber has special value for cement plants because it also rescues for re-use the 20 percent of the raw material, limestone, that ordinarily escapes from the kiln up the stack or into the filters.</p>
        <p>Dr. Joseph P. Strakey, the associate director for clean coal technology at the Energy Department's Pittsburgh Energy Technology Center, called the scrubber "extremely promising."</p>
        <p>"Usually, you don't scrub at a profit," he said, adding that in power plants, scrubbers can drive up the cost of electricity by 10 to 15 percent. Mr. Tureen pointed out that all other scrubbing technologies release carbon dioxide, a gas believed to cause global warming, as the limestone reacts with the sulfur. But this technology consumes carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Dr. Strakey and others think the scrubber can probably be adapted to a wide variety of industries, but say it seems especially valuable for cement. At a cement plant, a mixture of limestone and a few other ingredients is roasted with a blast of flame, generally from oil or coal.</p>
        <p>Most of the mixture goes on to be cement, but the kiln also produces prodigious amounts of "kiln dust," a pollutant. Collected in filters, millions of tons of this kiln dust can pile up in scarce landfill space, and threaten groundwater. The waste also shortens the useful life of limestone quarries, which usually determines the life of the cement plant.  Extending Limestone Supply</p>
        <p>Dragon has about 85 years of limestone left at 80 percent efficiency; recovering the 20 percent will make it last even longer. But Dragon also has a 50-foot mountain in back, a waste pile known as Dragon Mountain, that used to be an 80-foot-deep quarry. It is full, and establishing a new dump could cost $2 million.</p>
        <p>Now the mountain can be slowly recycled by the recovery scrubber.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the scrubber is producing potassium sulfate, a fertilizer. (When backyard gardeners buy 6-10-4 at the lawn and garden center, the "4" is potassium.)</p>
        <p>But one problem is that the reaction works only at a cool temperature, so the exhaust gases must be sprayed with water first. And the potassium sulfate concentration in water is only about 2 percent. Most industries would dump potassium sulfate in such low concentrations, Dr. Morrison said, but he added, "That is not only environmentally unsound, but economically unsound."  Solution in a Pump</p>
        <p>The scrubber uses waste heat from the stack to distill the water. But the stack gas is only about 245 degrees Fahrenheit, and once it is run through two heat exchangers, to prevent contamination, it is only 100 degrees, far below the boiling point. The solution is a vacuum pump, which lowers the air pressure so that the water boils at 100 degrees.</p>
        <p>Apart from reversing the buildup of waste and making a marketable byproduct, the scrubber assures that the remaining exhaust has been stripped of 97 percent of its sulfur. The former system took out only 58 percent. Dragon was already using high-sulfur coal, but a plant that had been on expensive coal or oil that is 1.5 percent sulfur and that had installed such a scrubber could switch to cheaper fuel that is 3 percent sulfur and still cut emissions by 90 percent.</p>
        <p>In a paper mill or waste-to-energy incinerator, where there is no kiln dust, the sulfur dioxide would be put in a reaction tank with the alkaline ash to produce the potassium sulfate.</p>
        <p>Another advantage: Trash incinerators produce ash with high concentrations of heavy metals, but the reaction in the recovery scrubber makes them insoluble in water, so disposal is safer.</p>
        <p>Ordinary coal-burning plants do not produce enough ash to sustain the reaction, but those in Eastern Europe, which use poor quality coal with high ash content, would be suitable, the designers say.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tureen, the chairman of Tribal Assets, describes the scrubber as "a mixture of Indian environmentalism and Yankee frugality."  BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
