<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Save Gasoline a Better Way</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="428455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSERVATION OF RESOURCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXCISE TAXES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Excise Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDA1431F934A35750C0A967958260" item-length="478" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Save Gasoline a Better Way</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The best way to reduce the use of fuel and clean up the atmosphere is for Congress to pass a stiff energy tax. But the Administration's national energy strategy virtually ignores tax hikes or any other conservation measure, an omission that many in Congress rightly want to reverse.</p>
        <p>Yet Congress, too, seems determined to duck taxes. Senator Richard Bryan of Wisconsin has won considerable support for a different approach, a bill that would raise average fuel-efficiency standards for new cars from 27.5 miles per gallon to 40. Mr. Bryan's regulatory approach is tempting, but it won't work as well as higher taxes. That's because fuel-efficiency standards -- known as CAFE standards -- lower only fuel use</p>
        <p>per vehicle</p>
        <p>for new cars. But CAFE has not significantly lowered</p>
        <p>total</p>
        <p>fuel use. In recent years, fuel use per vehicle has gone down, and total fuel use has gone up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The best way to reduce the use of fuel and clean up the atmosphere is for Congress to pass a stiff energy tax. But the Administration's national energy strategy virtually ignores tax hikes or any other conservation measure, an omission that many in Congress rightly want to reverse.</p>
        <p>Yet Congress, too, seems determined to duck taxes. Senator Richard Bryan of Wisconsin has won considerable support for a different approach, a bill that would raise average fuel-efficiency standards for new cars from 27.5 miles per gallon to 40. Mr. Bryan's regulatory approach is tempting, but it won't work as well as higher taxes. That's because fuel-efficiency standards -- known as CAFE standards -- lower only fuel use</p>
        <p>per vehicle</p>
        <p>for new cars. But CAFE has not significantly lowered</p>
        <p>total</p>
        <p>fuel use. In recent years, fuel use per vehicle has gone down, and total fuel use has gone up.</p>
        <p>Compared with a tax, CAFE standards affect a much smaller segment of the energy market. They apply only to new cars, which account for less than 10 percent of gasoline consumption. Worse yet, they hold down driving costs. And Congress treats CAFE as a substitute for a stiff gasoline tax, keeping gas prices down.</p>
        <p>These lower driving costs encourage people to drive more miles, which offsets part of the impact of higher fuel economy. CAFE also works against itself in another way. Manufacturers may be forced to adopt expensive technologies, making new cars more expensive, encouraging drivers to keep old gas-guzzlers.</p>
        <p>Safety is also a serious issue. To meet CAFE, manufacturers sell smaller cars. According to studies by Robert Crandall of the Brookings Institution, 1989 cars were 500 pounds lighter than they would have been without CAFE. That will boost fatalities in these cars by about 2,500 and serious injuries by 25,000. True, higher gas taxes would also make small cars more attractive, but less so. Taxes primarily encourage everyone to drive less.</p>
        <p>Over all, the fuel savings generated by CAFE standards are small, according to studies by Prof. Robert Leone of Boston University. Energy taxes would be more effective. A higher gas tax would encourage everyone to drive less, buy more fuel-efficient cars, share rides and, eventually, live closer to work. According to some studies, a gasoline tax as small as 5 cents per gallon would achieve as much conservation as Mr. Bryan's bill, but at a fraction of the cost to the economy. A broad tax applying to all fossil fuels would fight pollution and global warming even better.</p>
        <p>Congress, fearful of voter wrath over tax increases, could offset a higher gas tax with lower payroll taxes. That way the Federal deficit would be unaffected, one regressive tax would replace another and the nation's needs for energy, and clean air, would be protected. That's the core of a sensible national energy strategy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
