<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Dinosaur Extinction Theory, A 'Smoking Gun'</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="421073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PALEONTOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMETS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTEROIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DINOSAURS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAITI</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMIT, JAN (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIGURDSSON, HARALDUR (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asteroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFD91430F934A35751C0A967958260" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Dinosaur Extinction Theory, A 'Smoking Gun'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After more than a decade of global searching and spirited debate, geologists say they have found the clearest evidence yet that a massive object from outer space smashed into Earth 65 million years ago, at the time of the mass extinction of the dinosaurs and many other forms of life.</p>
        <p>Analysis of tiny glass fragments from Haiti, presumably produced in the extreme heat of an asteroid or comet impact, has encouraged geologists to proclaim the issue all but settled. An extraterrestrial impact, not widespread volcanic eruptions as others have hypthesized, must have left the telltale geochemical traces in 65-million-year-old sediments, the geologists conclude, and so could have caused or at least contributed to the ecological catastrophe at the time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After more than a decade of global searching and spirited debate, geologists say they have found the clearest evidence yet that a massive object from outer space smashed into Earth 65 million years ago, at the time of the mass extinction of the dinosaurs and many other forms of life.</p>
        <p>Analysis of tiny glass fragments from Haiti, presumably produced in the extreme heat of an asteroid or comet impact, has encouraged geologists to proclaim the issue all but settled. An extraterrestrial impact, not widespread volcanic eruptions as others have hypthesized, must have left the telltale geochemical traces in 65-million-year-old sediments, the geologists conclude, and so could have caused or at least contributed to the ecological catastrophe at the time.</p>
        <p>A team of geologists led by Dr. Haraldur Sigurdsson of the University of Rhode Island is reporting today in the journal Nature that the glass particles are completely free of small crystals and almost free of gas or water, characteristics that virtually ruled out volcanic origin. Their chemical composition also reflected nonvolcanic origin. Significance Is Stressed</p>
        <p>In an accompanying commentary, Dr. Jan Smit, a geologist at the Free University in Amsterdam who is a strong proponent of the impact hypothesis, said the new findings were significant because, despite growing circumstantial evidence that a cosmic impact was associated with the extinctions, there was "no 'smoking gun' in the form of a crater or of products formed by an impact."</p>
        <p>The glass drops, called tektites, "supply the missing evidence," Dr. Smit said, and "seem to provide the final riposte to the volcanic eruption mechanism."</p>
        <p>The new evidence has enabled geologists to fix their sights on the most probable location of ground-zero, the point of impact. They think the impact very likely occurred in the area of the Gulf of Mexico or the Caribbean Sea, probably on the Yucatan Peninsula of Mexico. A crater there long since covered by sediment may be the place where the object hit and scattered glassy debris at least as far as Haiti.</p>
        <p>But other geologists and many paleontologists complain that proponents of the impact hypothesis are jumping to unwarranted conclusions. Opponents Unconvinced</p>
        <p>"I concede them no victory whatsoever," Dr. Charles B. Officer, a geologist at Dartmouth College and a leading advocate of the volcanic hypothesis, said yesterday in an interview.</p>
        <p>Like many paleontologists, Dr. Robert Bakker of the University of Colorado Museum in Boulder said the evidence might favor an impact by an asteroid or comet at the end of the Cretaceous period of geologic time, when the mass extinction occurred, but it has not been proved that this was primarily responsible for the extinctions.</p>
        <p>"I'm still an agnostic about the cosmic event being so decisive," Dr. Bakker said in an interview. "There could have been an impact, but the terrestrial victim profile is totally wrong. If the extinctions were instantaneous, from acid rain and global cooling due to a dust cloud, then the frogs and salamanders in the tropics should have been the first to die off. They survived, and so did the tropical and temperature turtles. The least vulnerable should have been the big land animals, but they were the hardest hit."</p>
        <p>The idea that an asteroid impact could have killed off the dinosuars followed the discovery of an unusual abundance of the rare element iridium in sediments deposited worldwide at the end of the Cretaceous period 65 million years ago. The iridium, more common in meteorites, was found in clay that was virtually free of fossils and marked the boundary between the last dinosaurs of the Cretaceous and the proliferation of mammals in the Tertiary period that followed.</p>
        <p>The first discovery was made in 1978 by Dr. Walter Alvarez, a geologist at the University of California at Berkeley. He and his father, Dr. Luis Alvarez, a Nobel Prize-winning physicist at Berkeley, deduced that the iridium was the residue of an impacting asteroid that created a worldwide cloud of dust that blocked out sunlight, causing temperatures to plummet and more than half the Earth's species to die off. Geologists Search for Crater</p>
        <p>Strong support for the impact hypothesis came when geologists began finding glassy particles that appeared to have been formed in the heat of impact, and minerals of that time that seemed to have been shattered by such an impact. The distribution of such clues suggested that the impact, if indeed there was one, had occurred somewhere in the Americas. But where was the crater?</p>
        <p>Several prospects have been examined and rejected. Another site, underwater off the coast of Colombia, is being investigated.</p>
        <p>Dr. Sigurdsson's team, which included other scientists from the universities of Rhode Island, North Carolina, Michigan and Florida, found that the chemical composition of the glass found at Beloc, Haiti, suggests the melting of continental crustal rocks and limestone sediments. The large size of the fragments and their occurrence in a relatively thick deposit may indicate "close proximity of this outcrop to the source region," the researchers wrote.</p>
        <p>Scientists from the University of Arizona and Intera Technologies Inc., an oil exploration company in Houston, have identified a buried crater near Merida, Yucatan, that is more than 100 miles wide, extending out under the Gulf of Mexico.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
