<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Newest Parental Nightmare: Eco-Smart Child</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="458922"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SLESIN, SUZANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D6163AF932A25754C0A967958260" item-length="1229" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Newest Parental Nightmare: Eco-Smart Child</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE SLESIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SLESIN, SUZANNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the old days, the children were the sneaky ones -- smoking in the bathroom and doing other things they shouldn't. Now, it's the parents who are afraid of being caught by their environmentally aware, health-conscious and "politically correct" children, some of whom are barely out of kindergarten.</p>
        <p>They march around in unbleached cotton T-shirts that proclaim, "When You Buy Ivory Someone Else Pays," "Save the Earth" or "Oceans in Question." And they carry their sports equipment in tote bags emblazoned with dancing dolphins and the message, "Don't Let Their Song Be Silenced."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the old days, the children were the sneaky ones -- smoking in the bathroom and doing other things they shouldn't. Now, it's the parents who are afraid of being caught by their environmentally aware, health-conscious and "politically correct" children, some of whom are barely out of kindergarten.</p>
        <p>They march around in unbleached cotton T-shirts that proclaim, "When You Buy Ivory Someone Else Pays," "Save the Earth" or "Oceans in Question." And they carry their sports equipment in tote bags emblazoned with dancing dolphins and the message, "Don't Let Their Song Be Silenced."</p>
        <p>These vociferous children are harassing their parents to save water, forget about diet soda, keep away from red meat, abandon fur coats, stop smoking and shut off the lights. They also insist on paying attention to the new recycling laws, no matter what.</p>
        <p>No wonder there are quite a few parents who, having put their little darlings on the bus to summer camp, are breathing a sigh of relief.</p>
        <p>"As soon as the bus left, I immediately went home and put a few bottles into the trash," admitted Cynthia Nachmani, whose 11-year-old son, Jacob, left for camp on June 24. "When he's around, all the cans and bottles -- we go through a case of club soda a week -- go straight back to the store. But when he's gone, I throw them away.</p>
        <p>"I guess now I'm rebelling against Jacob's sternness," continued Ms. Nachmani, an associate museum educator at the Museum of Modern Art who met her husband at a peace march in Washington Square in 1961. "And Jacob's ecology extends to eating. So usually he doesn't eat bacon because of the nitrates. But the last weekend before he goes off to camp, he has two breakfasts, with bacon at each of them. That's become a tradition in our family."</p>
        <p>Children like Jacob call themselves "eco-smart," and when faced with the cornucopia of ice cream vendors at Fifth Avenue and 59th Street in Manhattan make a beeline for Ben &amp; Jerry's. "See?" said one 8-year-old recently, ripping open a Rainforest Crunch Peace Pop. "It says '1% for Peace.' The others are just ice cream."</p>
        <p>The parents who were peaceniks, or otherwise politically active and socially conscious, in the 60's seem to be on the shortest fuses. Paula Rubinstein, a New York antiques dealer and avowed "sympathizer to the antiwar movement" hates that she cannot take a bath in peace.</p>
        <p>"I share a bathroom with my daughter Hillary, who is 17," she said. "If I happen to turn on the water in the tub but happen to step into my bedroom for a minute to take off my watch or get a robe, by the time I get back, Hillary has already turned the tap off. She tells me I'm wasting water. It drives me crazy."</p>
        <p>Smoking is a long-running big deal. For years, children as young as 4 have been hiding the ashtrays, crooking their fingers and yelling "Yuck" whenever they are within three feet of a cigarette. Some even start their haranguing at an earlier age.</p>
        <p>William Van Carpels showed his displeasure at 5. "Grandma, I didn't know you did drugs," he wailed when he saw his grandmother lighting up on the porch outside his house.</p>
        <p>Where does this all come from? Everywhere, one could answer -- even from the parents.</p>
        <p>Starting in nursery school -- and continuing inexorably through high school -- children learn the ways and means of environmental politics. They get into the habit of rounding up soda cans and recycling all sorts of materials into artwork. As soon as they can read, they sit up in bed at night poring through "Fifty Simple Things Kids Can Do To Save the Earth" (Andrews and McNeel, 1990, $6.95) a popular birthday gift from their peers. And their science projects focus on saving the rain forest, rather than discovering the mysteries of electricity.</p>
        <p>"Kids are better informed and instinctively more tied in, more connected," said Randi Hacker, the publisher and editor in chief of P3, which calls itself "the Earth-based magazine for kids," in Montgomery, Vt. In her magazine, children read about fossil fuel, acid rain and leopard jeopardy.</p>
        <p>They also read books like "Let's Talk Trash: the Kids' Book About Recycling" (Waterfront Books, $14.95), where they are told to "keep things until they're all used up," and "fix things when they break instead of throwing them out."</p>
        <p>Socially conscious children are apt to jump on their soapboxes in a flash. One of Earl Pierce Jr.'s consciousness-raising tactics is to leave environmentally sound literature around his house in Lawnside, N.J.</p>
        <p>"I hide some of the books," said the 12-year-old's mother, Joyce Gilchrist-Pierce, a teacher of language arts and social studies. "It just makes me feel too guilty."</p>
        <p>Absolutely no plastic is an unwritten law in the household. "If something is in plastic, I have to hide if I want to use it," Ms. Gilchrist-Pierce said.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, she admires her son's zeal. "Earl torments me to do the right thing," she said. "He wants me to have an environment for him and his children that they will be able to live in."</p>
        <p>But sometimes, especially when mother and son go grocery shopping, she finds it a bit trying when he puts the kibosh on her buying Styrofoam cups. "It's hard," she said, "especially when he's giving me a lesson as we walk down the aisle."</p>
        <p>And what about aerosol cans, many children's pet peeves? "Don't even mention them," Ms. Gilchrist-Pierce said. "I have to use a pump."</p>
        <p>Jane Bevans, a lawyer, said: "It's bad enough when your mother did it to you. Now the kids are on to us."</p>
        <p>Her 6-year-old daughter, Maggie Bevans Tauranac, is on the alert when she suspects that diet soda is making an appearance in the family's New York apartment. "She feels that the worse thing we could do would be to actually drink it," Ms. Bevans said. "She's very persistent."</p>
        <p>Maggie also insists that as soon as anyone gets into the family car, that all seat belts should be on and all doors locked. "We've always done the seat belts," Ms. Bevans said. "But I absolutely hate to lock the doors. She drives us crazy."</p>
        <p>And the harassment doesn't stop when the children get a little older.</p>
        <p>As soon as Sherrill N. Musty's sons, Andrew, 22, and Jamie, 16, are out of the house, she goes straight to the refrigerator, makes two butterscotch sundaes and eats them one after the other. "I'd never do it in front of them," said Ms. Musty, a publisher in Burlington, Vt. "They'd rag me too much about it.</p>
        <p>"They used to go on and on and on about smoking. I stopped in 1985. But my husband is still smoking. But he is reducing it a little bit under pressure."</p>
        <p>When Ginger Barber's daughter Anna, who is now 22, left for college, her mother, a New York literary agent got on the telephone with her butcher. "It was an S.O.S. call," she said. "I ordered a leg of lamb. We had to do without red meat for years, because Anna had been a vegetarian since she was 10 years old."</p>
        <p>But Ms. Barber did concede that Anna had permanently affected their family's eating habits. "We eat a lot less red meat these days, although we'd been brought up on a healthy portion of it," she said.</p>
        <p>And Anna is back from college this summer, working in New York at an environmental law firm, so she is keeping her mother on her toes.</p>
        <p>"Now I have to go grocery shopping carrying my string bag," Ms. Barber moaned. "If I forget and come home with a plastic bag my name is on the environmental criminal list for the evening."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
