<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From a Pollutant, a Cleaner Fuel</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="468349"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DIESEL POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARBAGE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHANE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NAPHTHA</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PUEBLO (COLO)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">RENTECH INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D8143FF932A1575BC0A967958260" item-length="1252" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From a Pollutant, a Cleaner Fuel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite recurring energy crises, the world has plenty of fuel. The problem is, it is in the wrong place or the wrong form. Coal does not run cars and trucks, and natural gas, because it is hard to ship, often runs nothing at all.</p>
        <p>From time to time, desperate governments and venturesome capitalists try to produce diesel fuel and gasoline, the cream of the hydrocarbons, from natural gas or surplus coal. But usually these efforts are uneconomical.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite recurring energy crises, the world has plenty of fuel. The problem is, it is in the wrong place or the wrong form. Coal does not run cars and trucks, and natural gas, because it is hard to ship, often runs nothing at all.</p>
        <p>From time to time, desperate governments and venturesome capitalists try to produce diesel fuel and gasoline, the cream of the hydrocarbons, from natural gas or surplus coal. But usually these efforts are uneconomical.</p>
        <p>Next month, a group will try a new method. A new refinery in Pueblo, Colo., will turn methane gas, a pollutant given off by decaying garbage, into diesel fuel. The fuel will be far cleaner, but no more expensive, than what is now available at filling stations. More important, the plant's builder, Rentech Inc., expects to make money.  Broad Expansion Sought</p>
        <p>Other landfills have burned methane to produce steam for powering factories or generating electricity, neither of which is needed in Pueblo. For the new plant -- called Synhytech, for synthetic hydrogen technology -- Rentech developed a patented catalyst that performs a key step of the operation. The new method could also be used to convert natural gas into diesel fuel in locations like Alaska that are too remote to justify building a natural gas pipeline.</p>
        <p>At 240 barrels of products a day -- enough to fill one tanker truck -- the Pueblo plant is "a boutique refinery," said Rentech's president, Dennis L. Yakobson. But Rentech, based in Denver, believes that 100 landfills around the country could use the process. Rentech, which went public earlier this year and trades over the counter, hopes to license its technology to companies around the world. The stock, which is lightly traded, closed yesterday at $2.50.</p>
        <p>The new plant's construction cost, $16 million, was put up by Fuelco, an unregulated subsidiary of the Public Service Company of Colorado.</p>
        <p>Along with the diesel fuel, the Pueblo plant will produce naphtha and wax. Naphtha is used to make other chemicals; the wax, of a type mostly imported from South Africa, is used in everything from adhesives to lipsticks. The total value is about $60 a barrel, providing a satisfactory rate of return, Mr. Yakobson said.  52 Percent Methane</p>
        <p>Situated above Pueblo's 110-acre municipal landfill, the Rentech plant collects a gas that is 52 percent methane -- the main component of natural gas -- plus carbon dioxide, nitrogen and water vapor.</p>
        <p>The technology disposes of a hazardous pollutant; the methane is flammable and adds to global warming. The United States Environmental Protection Agency in May proposed regulations that would force controls on methane emissions at more than 10 percent of the 6,000 landfills now operating.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yakobson said the technology would prove valuable in converting natural gas to liquid fuels in remote areas, where there is gas but no market for it.</p>
        <p>In these cases, the gas has to be cheap to make conversion economical. If a pipeline is available to ship gas to a conventional customer, the gas price becomes too high for the Rentech process to be competitive. The Pueblo plant will pay $50,000 a year for its gas, which is found money for the local government but only about 60 cents a barrel of product.</p>
        <p>Another group interested in the new method includes companies that drill offshore, where gas can be a nuisance or even an impediment. Some have found gas associated with oil, but the gas cannot be economically shipped by tankers, and pipelines would be too costly.</p>
        <p>Normally, in such circumstances, the gas is reinjected underground, but in some formations this is difficult because pressures are too high. Marathon Oil, a subsidiary of USX, initially rejected the Rentech process but is reconsidering it because of recent improvements.  From Decay of Trash</p>
        <p>The Rentech process involves taking the carbon and hydrogen atoms that emerge in small molecules from the decay of trash, in this case as methane gas, and stringing them together into the giant hydrocarbon molecules found in diesel fuel.</p>
        <p>Rentech mixes the methane, or CH , and water, or H 0, at high temperature and low pressure, producing two gases, carbon monoxide, or CO, and hydrogen, or H  . These are fuels also, because they burn readily.</p>
        <p>Some carbon dioxide that is also produced in the process, and some that is naturally present in the landfill gas, is removed using standard industrial methods.</p>
        <p>Then the remaining gases are sent to a synthesis reactor, where an iron-based catalyst a little coarser than talcum powder absorbs the carbon monoxide and the hydrogen and strings them together in straight-line hydrocarbon fuel molecules. The company says the catalyst, embedded in molten wax, represents an improvement on the Fischer-Tropsch process developed in the mid-1920's and used by the Nazis.</p>
        <p>The diesel fuel that results has several advantages over what is made from crude oil, according to Mr. Yakobson. It has no sulfur, a component that the Environmental Protection Agency is struggling to remove from conventional diesel fuel with progressively stricter limits. It also has no aromatics, which are harder to burn and thus are a source of pollutants, some of them cancer-causing.</p>
        <p>The fuel is pale champagne-colored, with very little smell. Commercial diesel fuel is amber and has a smell well known to anyone who has visited a truck stop. More Nitrogen Oxide</p>
        <p>The Detroit Diesel Corporation tested the fuel recently in a transit bus engine and compared it to No. 1 diesel fuel, an off-the-shelf formulation cleaner than the No. 2 diesel now sold in truckstops. It found substantial decreases in particulate matter, hydrocarbons and carbon monoxide, but an increase in nitrogen oxide, an ingredient of smog. Nitrogen oxide rises with combustion temperature, and the Rentech diesel burns hotter.</p>
        <p>If the plant turns a profit, it will be standing on the shoulders of giants that collapsed before it. The biggest coal-to-liquids project to date was run by the Nazis, to provide fuel for the Luftwaffe and the Wehrmacht during World War II. South Africa, in response to international sanctions, also makes gasoline from coal, at costs that are secret but believed to be high.</p>
        <p>Other efforts to make diesel from coal or gas are under way or planned. The Department of Energy announced on July 30 that it would put $5 million over the next two years into research on making liquid fuel from coal. The goal is to reduce the cost to $30 a barrel over five to ten years.</p>
        <p>New Zealand, to reduce its vulnerability to international crises, heavily subsidized a plant that turns natural gas into methanol and the methanol into 900,000 barrels of high-octane gasoline a year. Opened in 1985, the plant has operated smoothly, "like a Rolls-Royce," said Bruce Wallace, a spokesman for Fletcher Challenge, a company that owns 75 percent of it.  Not a Commercial Success</p>
        <p>The rest is held by Mobil, which runs the plant. But the project is hardly a commercial success; it cost $1.2 billion to build. The New Zealand Government paid Fletcher Challenge to take the 75 percent stake.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wallace said that given the amount the Government had invested, it would not have turned a profit for New Zealand until oil prices rose to $50 or $60 a barrel, more than triple current levels. If prices do go that high, someone might build another plant as a profit-making venture, he said. But as to when that would be, he said, "we probably wouldn't even ask ourselves."  BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
