<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lay Off 'Thelma and Louise'</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="453143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="FILM VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MASLIN, JANET</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">THELMA AND LOUISE (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6D7153CF935A25755C0A967958260" item-length="1675" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lay Off 'Thelma and Louise'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Janet Maslin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MASLIN, JANET</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Because he didn't smile when he said it. Because he stole, cheated or lied. Because he wasn't lucky. Because it was a good day to die.</p>
        <p>Those are traditional reasons for which characters in outlaw movies are disposed of, sometimes only in the wink of an eye. It's a list to which a new one can now be added: because he tried to rape and beat a woman whose best friend had once been the victim of a sex crime, and the best friend went berserk while watching history repeat itself. And because he was smug instead of sorry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Because he didn't smile when he said it. Because he stole, cheated or lied. Because he wasn't lucky. Because it was a good day to die.</p>
        <p>Those are traditional reasons for which characters in outlaw movies are disposed of, sometimes only in the wink of an eye. It's a list to which a new one can now be added: because he tried to rape and beat a woman whose best friend had once been the victim of a sex crime, and the best friend went berserk while watching history repeat itself. And because he was smug instead of sorry.</p>
        <p>"Thelma and Louise," the film in which this new pretext for killing turns an Arkansas waitress and an Arkansas housewife into ebullient runaways, is obviously a crime story of a different stripe. Though it takes much of its inspiration from the road movies of 20 years ago, its style and attitudes are thoroughly up to date. Though it tells a tale of violence, its spirit could not be more benign. Though it employs certain conventions of the buddy-film genre, it feels unfamiliar in the best possible way. In viewing the desperado's life through the eyes of two suddenly adventurous women, it sees something other movies have not seen.</p>
        <p>It also raises new hackles, having been tarred as a kind of she-"Rambo" by those who deem it mindlessly violent and uncharitable to men. The charge that this is "toxic feminism" has been leveled by sources as diverse as John Leo of U.S. News &amp; World Report and the columnist Liz Smith. "Nobody in 'Thelma and Louise' worries about AIDS, using condoms or encountering a serial killer," Ms. Smith noted, and that's true; nobody worries about the greenhouse effect or wears seat belts, either. But what is it that really rankles about "Thelma and Louise"?</p>
        <p>Not the violence: the amount of violence seen here is remarkably small, especially in view of the casual flare-ups with which male-oriented road movies are often loaded. Out for a weekend's fishing trip, mischievously stealing away from Thelma's husband and Louise's boyfriend, the two heroines first get into trouble in an Arkansas honky-tonk, where a man who makes a pass at Thelma mistakes her high spirits and alcoholic haze for sexual availability. This leads to the shooting incident that turns Thelma and Louise into outlaws and also gives the story its momentum. It's a legal and moral lapse, but also a plot necessity. Without events like this, the heroes of most road movies would have to pack up and go back home.</p>
        <p>Later on, Thelma and Louise have their run-ins with a truck driver, a police officer and a storeful of customers at a grocery, none of whom is injured by their behavior. The truck driver does incur property damage, the grocery store customers are robbed, and the policeman becomes the victim of a potentially dangerous prank; but these events deserve to be seen in some kind of perspective. Last summer was the season of the sky-high body count, with Arnold Schwarzenegger blasting his way across Mars in "Total Recall," all of whose female characters were prostitutes. In "Another 48 Hours," a buddy film tailored to more conventional tastes, Eddie Murphy and Nick Nolte killed enemy after enemy without batting an eye. So, once again, what's so egregious about "Thelma and Louise"?</p>
        <p>The heroines of this story happen to look quite innocent by comparison with the road movie characters of the late 1960's and early 1970's, when the genre was in full bloom. Compared with the stoned, messianic drug dealers of "Easy Rider," who traveled the highways fueled by condescension and paranoia and took it as their sexual due to visit a whorehouse in New Orleans, Thelma (Geena Davis) and Louise (Susan Sarandon) seem infinitely more level-headed and kind. (Anyone who remembers "Easy Rider" fondly but has not watched it since its 1969 release should be reminded that Billy and Captain America visit a commune that has its own resident mime troupe, complete with stage. Timeless it's not.)</p>
        <p>And compared with Bonnie Parker, who got a sexual thrill out of the way Clyde Barrow announced, "We rob banks" in Arthur Penn's "Bonnie and Clyde" in 1967, Thelma and Louise have no real taste for crime. Furthermore, compared with the wandering sex offenders of Bertrand Blier's "Going Places" in 1974, their feelings about the opposite sex are positively friendly. They are mobilized not by hostility or anomie but by a sudden, unexpected glimpse of what life might have been like for them without a bad marriage (Thelma's) and a dead-end job (Louise's). Their dissatisfaction with their everyday lives is something anyone in the audience will understand.</p>
        <p>While it's true that criminal behavior plays a role in this story, it requires extraordinary blinders to regard "Thelma and Louise" solely as an account of antisocial depravity. Besides, criminal behavior on screen can be as well used in the service of virtue as in glorification of crime. "The Silence of the Lambs," for example, can be seen as a grisly film, but it is much more persuasively a film in which the saving of a single life becomes all-important, in which a fundamental decency prevails. The heroism of its central character, Clarice Starling, emerges in stark relief against the horrors she has battled.</p>
        <p>In the case of "Thelma and Louise," a violent and tragic mistake becomes the crucible in which character is formed. One of the most invigorating things about this film is the way its heroines, during the course of a few brief but wildly eventful days, crystallize their thoughts and arrive at a philosophical clarity that would have been unavailable to them in their prior lives. By the end of the film, the director Ridley Scott and the screenwriter Callie Khouri are ready to allow Thelma and Louise the opportunity to take full charge of their lives and full responsibility for their missteps, too. The film's bracing ending has a welcome toughness.</p>
        <p>In fact, throughout the course of the story, Thelma and Louise have been seen learning to take charge of their own lives. And there may lie the problem: it's something that goes beyond Thelma and Louise's aggressiveness, their politics, their cavalierness about condoms (a matter not remotely addressed by the movie, by the way) or any other aspect of the film that strikes some small segment of the audience as hotheaded. It's something as simple as it is powerful: the fact that the men in this story don't really matter.</p>
        <p>They are treated as figures in the landscape through which these characters pass, and as such they are essentially powerless. For male characters, perhaps, this is a novelty, but women in road movies have always been treated in precisely the same way.</p>
        <p>The men in this story may be boors or charmers, but in neither case do they have much effect on what Thelma and Louise do. These women become thoroughly independent in a way that is commonplace for male movie heroes but still a novelty where heroines are concerned. The freedom they embrace is remarkably complete, and not even particularly sexual (sexual liberation is the one realm in which women on screen have always been free to exercise their independence). No wonder they've ruffled a few feathers.</p>
        <p>The men in the story, ranging from Louise's conciliatory boyfriend (Michael Madsen) to a flirty young hitchhiker (Brad Pitt) and a sympathetic police detective (Harvey Keitel), do a lot to engage Thelma and Louise's respective interests, just as incidental female characters might in a movie about two footloose men. And the film draws the different ways in which Thelma and Louise each view men with particular clarity.</p>
        <p>Louise, the older and more stern of the two, may be noticeably gun-shy as a result of her past, and she is well beyond reach of her onetime beau, even when he proposes marriage. The more sheltered Thelma is, by comparison, positively boy crazy. Having been tied to the same dull, disloyal mate since she was 14, she yearns for adventure. But if on paper this rebelliousness sounds like militancy, in effect it is played with feistiness and wry humor. When Thelma runs off, she doesn't leave an angry manifesto pinned on the wall with a dagger; she leaves a note for her husband in the microwave, together with dinner and a beer.</p>
        <p>Consider this within the context of several other recent films that involve women who pose some kind of a threat. Anyone who doubts that style and mood make a big difference in the way aggressive heroines are perceived might well see "La Femme Nikita," about a woman transformed from an angry, antisocial punk into a trained assassin. She might indeed seem threatening, were it not for the fact that she also learns to wear makeup and performs at least one of her violent acts wearing a little black evening dress and pearls.</p>
        <p>The husband-killing New Jersey women in "Mortal Thoughts" are less elegant but almost as lulling, since they leaven their deadly activities with a strain of dizzy humor, and the man they kill (played by Bruce Willis) is a comical lout. In terms of misdeeds and motives, both "La Femme Nikita" and "Mortal Thoughts" are much darker than "Thelma and Louise." And in terms of antipathy toward men, Thelma and Louise can't hold a candle to the Madonna of "Truth or Dare."</p>
        <p>But it is Thelma and Louise who tease each other about admiring the physique of that male hitchhiker, who give up all ties to home and hearth, who take issue with a truck driver who has been outstandingly rude and who otherwise exercise what in the past have been male prerogatives on the screen. The aspects of this film that have raised the greatest furor are features that would be virtually routine in a comparable movie about men.</p>
        <p>So it requires the use of a double standard to feel that "Thelma and Louise" fails to depict exemplary behavior when the masculine road movie has never pretended to do anything of the kind. This road movie's brand of escapism offers transcendence, not instruction -- and it rises above both the everyday and the limits of its genre. "Thelma and Louise" is transcendent in every way.  FILM VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
