<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Seltzer Once Thrived, A Few True Fizzes Remain</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="458716"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="DE GUSTIBUS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEVERAGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HAVANA DRY BEVERAGES INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'NEILL, MOLLY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOWELL, GEORGE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DE113BF933A25754C0A967958260" item-length="1044" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Seltzer Once Thrived, A Few True Fizzes Remain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MOLLY O'NEILL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'NEILL, MOLLY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the world according to seltzer connoisseurs, this is the year 20 A.P.</p>
        <p>Two decades have elapsed since plastic bottles with screw caps began to replace the blue or green glass bottles with hand-operated siphons that are to a lively seltzer what a flared cork is to a proper bottle of Champagne. In the years B.P. (Before Plastic), sales held their own. After Plastic (A.P.), sales of sparkling water geysered. There are now high-priced imports. There is orange, lemon, lime and raspberry seltzer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the world according to seltzer connoisseurs, this is the year 20 A.P.</p>
        <p>Two decades have elapsed since plastic bottles with screw caps began to replace the blue or green glass bottles with hand-operated siphons that are to a lively seltzer what a flared cork is to a proper bottle of Champagne. In the years B.P. (Before Plastic), sales held their own. After Plastic (A.P.), sales of sparkling water geysered. There are now high-priced imports. There is orange, lemon, lime and raspberry seltzer.</p>
        <p>But there isn't the same sparkle. At least not for seltzer cognoscenti, who grew up at a table set with a siphon bottle as certainly as it was set with napkins.</p>
        <p>"Before plastic you could rely on a fresh seltzer -- by that I mean good bubble activity," said Sam Steinberg, past president of the Good Health Seltzer Association, a trade group in New York that was founded in the 1930's and grew to 501 members, B.P. "There's one guy left," said Mr. Steinberg, who is now retired.</p>
        <p>The survivor is George Howell, owner of Havana Dry Beverages in the Bronx. Mr. Howell, who is called "Sweet George," because, he says, "maybe people appreciate that somebody still delivers real seltzer," began working for Havana Dry when he was 17 years old. Forty-two years later, he still runs his business, delivering fresh seltzer to about 400 customers.</p>
        <p>His career has always been more like a calling. "It wouldn't let me go," he said. His product starts with the city's own artesian spring -- tap water. It is filtered through charcoal and paper to remove salt and additives, and then infused with carbon dioxide, hosed into glass bottles and capped with a siphon that customers cannot remove. "You can never open him, he can never go flat," Sweet George said.</p>
        <p>That was New York seltzer, B.P. Like the mineral water from bucolic sources that lines grocery store shelves today, the local elixir has a venerable past.</p>
        <p>Named for Niederselters, a village near Frankfurt, Germany, that began producing carbonated tonics in the 16th century, the elixir was introduced to New York "by a Frenchman after the revolution," Mr. Steinberg said. But it wasn't until 1809 that Joseph Hawkins patented the machinery for carbonating spring water, and the hermetically sealed bottles became part of the well-set table.</p>
        <p>"Every block had a milkman, a laundry man, a seltzer man," Mr. Steinberg recalled.</p>
        <p>But by the late 1960's, imported water started to make a dent in the local market, though seltzer connoisseurs aren't sure why. "It's just seltzer that bubbles up from the ground and is more expensive," Mr. Steinberg said. "Seltzer is pure H2 O plus CO2 , which makes it H2 CO3 : mildly acidic, no salt, no sugar.</p>
        <p>"The water from the spring in Saratoga had hydrogen sulfite. We hated that smell."</p>
        <p>The purity of seltzer, he said, makes it "the basis of all soda that is sold now; everything is just seltzer with flavoring." When New York seltzer purists vary their own beverage intake, they tend to stay local.</p>
        <p>Dr. Brown's Cel-Ray Soda is one respectable alternative. The tonic -- an infusion of celery seeds, sugar and, of course, seltzer -- is said to have been invented in 1869 by a doctor treating immigrant children on the Lower East Side. Dr. Brown's is now owned by the Canada Dry Bottling Company of New York, and is made and bottled in College Point, Queens. It continues to serve a faithful following.</p>
        <p>"We are no threat to Pepsi," said Harry Gold, marketing director of Dr. Brown's, "but people who grew up in New York never lose a taste for Cel-Ray."</p>
        <p>About a million bottles and cans of Dr. Brown's are sold a year. About that many bottles of another local seltzer derivative, Manhattan Special, are also sold annually. That beverage, a blend of espresso, cane sugar and a splash of seltzer, was invented by Dr. Theresa Cimino in 1895.</p>
        <p>"It's a low-carbonated drink," said the inventor's great-granddaughter, Aurora Passaro, now the president of the Brooklyn company, "but the fizz is essential to the refreshment."</p>
        <p>The fizz is equally indispensable to a classic New York egg cream, a mix of milk and chocolate syrup that is spritzed to a fine foam with seltzer. "I don't know how it got its name because it has no egg, no cream," Mr. Steinberg said. "But I know it's nothing without fresh seltzer."</p>
        <p>David Fox, owner of Fox's U-Bet Chocolate Flavor Syrup , the other egg-cream essential, concurs. "You need the forceful jet for the distinctive foam," he said. "But the siphon bottles are antiques and that's getting to be a problem."</p>
        <p>People like to make lamps out of the bottles, said Mr. Howell of Havana Dry Beverages. More than increased imports or other changes in the marketplace, he battles the flea-market value of his container, he said. The bottles, which were recycled by seltzer companies, are not made anymore.</p>
        <p>In the early years, A.P., people began looking for "a souvenir of glass times," Mr. Howell said. Now, the best of the handblown Czechoslovakian siphon bottles can fetch up to $10. He has "bottle locators" in Philadelphia and New Jersey who snatch up cases of 10 for $3.20 to $3.50.</p>
        <p>But he can't deliver these valuables to just anyone. "We try to keep the bottles to where they don't disappear," Mr. Howell said. Only the thirsty need apply. "We can't go lugging 50-pound cases to walk-ups for people to make lamps," he said.</p>
        <p>Such activity would be inconsistent with his calling. So would flavored seltzers. "I can't tie up bottle inventory with something like that," he said.</p>
        <p>He stood between the spigot and the clanking machine that can turn city water into seltzer at the rate of 1,250 bottles an hour -- that's blue bottles, green bottles, real siphon bottles, Sweet George was quick to add.</p>
        <p>He didn't sound like the kingpin of a venerable commodity. He sounded like an anointed guard at an ancient spring. "I get a wonderful feeling to know I stuck around after plastic," he said. Classic New York Egg Cream (Adapted from David Fox) 1 cup milk  1/4 cup seltzer 2 tablespoons Fox's U-Bet chocolate flavor syrup.</p>
        <p>Pour milk into a tall, chilled glass. Spritz in the seltzer until a white head reaches the top of the glass. Spoon in the syrup with a little wrist action. Relax and enjoy.</p>
        <p>Yield: 1 serving.  DE GUSTIBUS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
