<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Nation; Kuwait Still Burns</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="463324"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WICKER, TOM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D6153AF93BA15754C0A967958260" item-length="744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Nation; Kuwait Still Burns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM WICKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WICKER, TOM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Those oil wells in Kuwait are still burning -- more of them than at first reported, with unknown final effects, and probably for a longer period than officially projected.</p>
        <p>Not just "about 500," as generally reported, but 732 Kuwaiti oil wells were set afire by retreating Iraqi forces last winter. A Senate subcommittee, chaired by Joseph Lieberman of Connecticut, received that hard figure on July 11 from Kuwait's Ambassador to the U.S., Sheik Saud Nasir al-Sabah, and E. L. Shannon Jr., chairman of Santa Fe International, an oil drilling company owned by Kuwait.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Those oil wells in Kuwait are still burning -- more of them than at first reported, with unknown final effects, and probably for a longer period than officially projected.</p>
        <p>Not just "about 500," as generally reported, but 732 Kuwaiti oil wells were set afire by retreating Iraqi forces last winter. A Senate subcommittee, chaired by Joseph Lieberman of Connecticut, received that hard figure on July 11 from Kuwait's Ambassador to the U.S., Sheik Saud Nasir al-Sabah, and E. L. Shannon Jr., chairman of Santa Fe International, an oil drilling company owned by Kuwait.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shannon testified that by July 8, "some 199 wells had been extinguished or capped," which means that more than 500 still were burning four months after the desert war ended.</p>
        <p>In fact, the overall problem may have gotten worse, owing to huge oil lakes being formed by wells that are still gushing but no longer afire. James George, a former Canadian Ambassador to Kuwait and an environmental scientist who led a Friends of the Earth inspection team to Kuwait in June, told the subcommittee that now these lakes are catching fire, causing more pollution than a well fire, and will be harder to extinguish.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shannon said the Kuwaiti Government had set a goal of 500 wells "secured" by the end of the year, and all by March 1992. But Mr. George, in much more pessimistic testimony, said his F.O.E. team had concluded that the fires "will not be controlled for years -- perhaps four or five years -- as Red Adair told the committee a month ago." Mr. Adair is one of the world's leading oil-well firefighters.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Shannon and Mr. George agreed that the work in Kuwait is being complicated by the hazard of unexploded allied and Iraqi munitions, some of them now submerged in the oil lakes.</p>
        <p>Various scientific teams have reached differing conclusions as to the regional and global consequences of the fires. Most now believe that they will cause neither a widespread "nuclear winter" effect (falling temperatures as smoke blocks the sun's rays) nor a major increase in global warming (from the "greenhouse effect" of carbon dioxide emissions).</p>
        <p>But within those extremes, there's much disagreement. Data are still scarce and there are no useful precedents; the largest previous oilfield blaze -- only five fires -- was in Libya in 1965. Some evidence indicates that the Kuwaiti fires could become a far-reaching environmental catastrophe.</p>
        <p>John Horgan of Scientific American has reported that levels of soot -- believed to be from Kuwait -- above the Mauna Loa Observatory in Hawaii were five times higher in March than in the three previous Marches. The Environmental Protection Agency, for unexplained reasons, briefly suppressed this finding.</p>
        <p>Balloon observations at the University of Wyoming, Mr. Horgan reported, suggest that Kuwaiti smoke has passed over the continental U.S. Particle concentrations in the troposphere above Wyoming increased by a factor of 10 or more from early February to late March 1991.</p>
        <p>By far the most apocalyptic speculation -- much disputed -- is that smoke from Kuwait may have worsened the gigantic typhoon that killed over 100,000 persons in Bangladesh on May 1. This theory holds that the smoke warmed the atmosphere and increased the customary monsoon rains. Tiruvalam Krishnamurti of Florida State University, a monsoon expert, told Mr. Horgan that floods in Bangladesh rose two feet higher than ever before recorded, and that rains after the storm were unusually severe.</p>
        <p>The visible smoke plume from Kuwait would cover most of the coastal U.S. from New York to Florida. Kuwaiti soot has been detected in northern Japan. Soviet scientists already have measured unprecedented levels of acid rain in regions of the Soviet Union and similar fallout is expected in areas 2,000 kilometers from Kuwait, possibly as far away as China.</p>
        <p>Temperature drops of up to 10 degrees Celsius are predicted for a radius of hundreds of kilometers around Kuwait; drops of 1 or 2 degrees may be felt for 1,000 kilometers. Nearby Bahrain has just had its coolest May in 35 years. These effects could produce crop failures and famine; and soot falling on snowy regions -- already seen in the Himalayas -- may cause rapid melting, followed by flooding.</p>
        <p>If the fires are extinguished on Kuwait's official schedule, such consequences may be brief and manageable. But suppose the fires burn for years? The cumulative effect would be disastrous.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
