<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Global Warming: Search for the Signs</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="418736"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GASES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D7173AF93AA15752C0A967958260" item-length="2040" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Global Warming: Search for the Signs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AN ever-lengthening string of extraordinarily warm years has renewed fears of the greenhouse effect -- the trapping of the Sun's heat by gases that a rapidly industrializing world is pouring into the atmosphere. Responding to the alarm, delegates from around the globe will gather next week outside Washington to negotiate a treaty limiting the gases.</p>
        <p>But as the delegates converge, most scientists are far from ready to announce that greenhouse warming has arrived, since the warming recorded over the last decade could also be part of a natural climatic change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AN ever-lengthening string of extraordinarily warm years has renewed fears of the greenhouse effect -- the trapping of the Sun's heat by gases that a rapidly industrializing world is pouring into the atmosphere. Responding to the alarm, delegates from around the globe will gather next week outside Washington to negotiate a treaty limiting the gases.</p>
        <p>But as the delegates converge, most scientists are far from ready to announce that greenhouse warming has arrived, since the warming recorded over the last decade could also be part of a natural climatic change.</p>
        <p>Instead, they are struggling to answer a crucial question: how can a greenhouse warming of the climate be recognized and distinguished from natural warming? They are focusing their detective efforts on various subtle changes that a greenhouse warming would be expected to induce. These signs are known collectively as the greenhouse "fingerprint."</p>
        <p>The task, climatologists say, is by no means as easy and straightforward as it might seem.</p>
        <p>They know that certain gases, chiefly carbon dioxide, chlorofluorocarbons and methane, admit the Sun's energy but block heat from escaping back to space. They know that the gases are steadily building up, largely through the burning of fossil fuels. And they know that the average surface temperature of the Earth has indeed been rising for the last decade. In 1990, at a shade under 60 degrees Fahrenheit, it was the highest since global measurements began in the late 19th century.</p>
        <p>But as provocative as all this evidence is, the scientists believe, it in no way establishes a cause-and-effect relationship between the greenhouse gases and the recent rise in the average global temperature. The rise is consistent with greenhouse warming, they say, but not enough to prove a connection.</p>
        <p>If the greenhouse effect is indeed warming the planet as scientists predict it will, this will ultimately become so obvious that "a kid on the street can tell what's going on," said Dr. Tim P. Barnett, a climatologist at the Scripps Institution of Oceanography in La Jolla, Calif. It will become obvious, scientists say, because the rate of warming is expected to outstrip that of any climatic change in the last 10,000 years.</p>
        <p>But the greenhouse "signal," if in fact it is there now, is still so small on a global scale that it is obscured by the "noise" of the many other factors that influence climate. These other factors, the climatologists say, could well be the cause of the overall global warming observed in the last decade.  Or, equally possibly, they could have produced an overall cooling that partly offset an even larger greenhouse warming than the rise in average global temperature might suggest.</p>
        <p>To help resolve these uncertainties, the climatologists are trying to develop a diagnostic set of features that would indicate a greenhouse-caused warming.</p>
        <p>No single climatic feature can be relied on as the proof of greenhouse-induced warming. "You want to look for it in a number of places so you don't get tricked by one," said Dr. Barnett, a leader in the effort to develop a reliable detection strategy. Possible Greenhouse Fingerprints</p>
        <p>Scientists have identified a number of promising candidates to be included in the greenhouse fingerprint.  Among the leading ones are these:</p>
        <p>Global temperature patterns. In greenhouse warming, scientists believe, the continents would warm more than the oceans. Subarctic latitudes are expected to warm more than tropical latitudes in the Northern Hemisphere, but not in the Southern Hemisphere. The lower part of the atmosphere, or troposphere, would become warmer while the stratosphere would become cooler.</p>
        <p>Sea surface temperatures. They are expected to rise fairly uniformly with greenhouse warming, while naturally occurring changes vary more from one part of the globe to another.</p>
        <p>Water vapor in the atmosphere. The vapor would not only increase with the warming but, in a classic feedback effect, would also intensify the warming by amplifying the effect of the greenhouse gases. Moisture content would be expected to increase more in the tropics than in higher latitudes like the temperate and sub-arctic zones.</p>
        <p>Changes in seasonality. Greenhouse warming is expected to be more evident in winter than in summer, particularly at high latitudes.</p>
        <p>From computer simulations of the Earth's climate, scientists believe these indicators of the greenhouse signal are so distinguished from natural, internal fluctuations of the climatic system as to be characteristic of greenhouse warming. One example of the natural fluctuations is the phenomenon of El Nino, in which periodic changes in sea surface temperatures in the tropical Pacific Ocean affect global temperature and rainfall patterns. Previous Periods of Warming</p>
        <p>On a geological time scale, the Earth has undergone periods of substantial natural warming. Between 5,000 and 6,000 years ago, scientists believe, temperatures in various parts of the world were about 2 to 5 degrees warmer than benchmark levels in the late 19th century. By comparison, the average global temperature has increased by about half a degree to one degree in the last century.</p>
        <p>There were other warm periods about 125,000 years ago, when parts of the globe were 3.5 to 14 degrees warmer than the benchmark temperatures, and 3.3 million to 4.3 million years ago, when they were 3.5 to 35 degrees warmer, depending on location and season.</p>
        <p>These warm periods were presumably caused by natural factors originating outside the ocean-atmosphere climate system. These include changes in solar radiation, changes in the Earth's position relative to the Sun, naturally occurring increases in greenhouse gases and changes in relationships between the land and the ocean. These latter changes, brought about by the movement of the Earth's crustal plates, are thought to have altered patterns of ocean circulation that play a critical role in shaping climate.</p>
        <p>A modern cause of non-greenhouse climate change may be pollutants, apart from greenhouse gases, that humans are throwing into the atmosphere. Many of these can affect temperature, moisture and atmospheric functioning, complicating efforts to detect greenhouse warming. 'Junk in the Atmosphere'</p>
        <p>"We've put a lot of junk in the atmosphere" in addition to greenhouse gases, said Dr. Barnett, "and it seems to be pretty well dispersed.</p>
        <p>"What would that do to the climate?" he asked. "I don't think that's been computed, but it could have a large-scale effect."</p>
        <p>For example, climatologists say, fine pollution particles emitted by industry cause clouds to form, and these can have warming or cooling effects, depending on the type of clouds and their location. These effects are uneven from one part of the globe to another, further complicating matters.</p>
        <p>Another source of distortion, said Dr. James E. Hansen, a climatologist at the Goddard Institute of Space Studies in New York, is the depletion of the Earth's ozone layer because of the release of chlorofluorocarbons into the atmosphere, a change that causes cooling at some levels of the atmosphere in northern regions of the globe. This may affect the expected temperature difference between latitudes and even between land and ocean, for instance, obscuring the greenhouse signal.</p>
        <p>"As soon as you start looking at these kinds of details you're in trouble," Dr. Hansen said, adding that detecting greenhouse warming depends on observing all the competing external influences on climate.</p>
        <p>Climatologists say the effort to rule out all the greenhouse effect's possible competitors as causes of global warming is slowed and frustrated by a lack of observational data in many key areas and by the state of the art of climatic science.</p>
        <p>"Whenever you try to do this quickly, you run up against our ignorance and the quality of the data," said Dr. Michael E. Schlesinger, a climatologist at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, who has worked closely with Dr. Barnett.</p>
        <p>An especially significant indicator of greenhouse warming would be any increase in atmospheric water vapor. It is "the first thing you'd expect," said Dr. Veerabhadran Ramanathan of the University of California at San Diego, who has studied the matter extensively. In greenhouse warming, more water would change into vapor. This vapor is critical to greenhouse warming because it would amplify by five times the relatively small initial warming impulse provided by carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>"You should clearly be seeing that in the observations," said Dr. Ramanathan. "If that's not there, you'd know it's not greenhouse. If it is there, the case would be compelling that it is greenhouse."</p>
        <p>But "we don't have the answer to that question," he said, "because we don't have the observational records." Satellite observations provided such data from 1984 to 1989, but the satellite has stopped working. No measurements have been made since then, although the Department of Energy plans to establish a series of ground-based observation stations that could fill the gap. New satellites are also expected to help fill it later in the decade, and Dr. Hansen and others are pressing for an earlier date.</p>
        <p>In this and some other areas, scientists say, existing records are too short to discern either trends in natural variability or signs of greenhouse warming. The best and most complete climatic observations are those of surface temperature. Scientists trying to develop a reliable fingerprint are comparing observed temperature patterns in these records with those expected to result from greenhouse-induced warming.</p>
        <p>Climatologists at the Max Planck Institute in Hamburg, Germany, and at the University of East Anglia in Britain, for example, have analyzed the globally observed pattern of surface temperatures and are measuring it against model predictions.</p>
        <p>Developing reliable signs of the greenhouse model depends heavily on improving the computer models of the atmosphere that predict greenhouse-induced changes. The models are continually being refined, but are still imperfect representations of the real world.</p>
        <p>"Some things, the models don't simulate so well," Dr. Barnett said. "Other things, they seem to simulate quite well." He said scientists would first have to "isolate the best model and the best of the observations" before they were set to do their detecting.</p>
        <p>Some climatologists think that refining the models is more important at this point than the accumulation of data. "I don't think more data is going to reduce uncertainties in the next few years," said Dr. Phil Jones, a climatologist at the University of East Anglia. The short-term answer, he said, "is going to be in improvement of the models and better agreement between models."</p>
        <p>For the next few years, the public and policy makers will have to rely on all these efforts to tell them what is happening.</p>
        <p>"We'd better find out as soon as we can," Dr. Hansen said. If action to reduce emissions of greenhouse gases is delayed, "either the climate changes are going to be larger and the impacts on people are going to be greater, or we will have to make more painful and expensive efforts," he said, adding, "The earlier we know, the easier it is to minimize the impacts or to adapt to them."</p>
        <p>A reliable fingerprint could also make it easier not only to detect the human-induced greenhouse effect but also to measure its future magnitude with some assurance. Since the ocean absorbs and holds much of the heat before ultimately releasing it back into the atmosphere, there is a lag of up to several decades between the emission of greenhouse gases into the air and their full effect on climate.  Waiting for Answers</p>
        <p>Given all the obstacles, when can answers be expected? Some scientists say in a decade or so, but Dr. Barnett says nobody has really made a good estimate.</p>
        <p>"Some of my colleagues say detection is premature because the models aren't good enough," he said. "Others say, 'Detection is a red herring -- let's do something about the greenhouse effect right now because the consequences are so bad.'</p>
        <p>"I think we're going to be forced in the next 5 or 10 years to take what we have and make some decision."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
