<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Energy Bill Held Unlikely Soon</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="486519"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KRAUSS, CLIFFORD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D9163EF931A25752C1A967958260" item-length="762" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Energy Bill Held Unlikely Soon</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KRAUSS, CLIFFORD</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite optimistic predictions by proponents of conservation and renewable fuels that major new energy legislation would be on the Senate floor by Thanksgiving, Congressional officials say it may be impossible to pass anything more than a limited alternative for months.</p>
        <p>Ten days ago, liberal Democrats and an unlikely coalition of environmental groups, small utilities and the automobile industry derailed the Bush Administration's energy bill. Building a coalition for a substitute will be much more difficult.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite optimistic predictions by proponents of conservation and renewable fuels that major new energy legislation would be on the Senate floor by Thanksgiving, Congressional officials say it may be impossible to pass anything more than a limited alternative for months.</p>
        <p>Ten days ago, liberal Democrats and an unlikely coalition of environmental groups, small utilities and the automobile industry derailed the Bush Administration's energy bill. Building a coalition for a substitute will be much more difficult.</p>
        <p>"It's going to be a tall order to come up with a new energy bill," said Senator Frank H. Murkowski, an Alaska Republican who is a member of the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources. "The birth pains that came with the last one were extensive."</p>
        <p>The old energy bill, which was backed by the White House and the oil industry, tried to stitch together a grab bag of provisions that addressed off-shore and Arctic oil drilling, conservation, incentives to promote greater efficiency in buildings and appliances, deregulation of the utility industry and alternative energy sources like nuclear and hydroelectric power.</p>
        <p>Without the impetus of a crisis, like the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait last year, which gave the old energy bill a push, Congress is likely to change its approach and deal with such issues individually, in a fashion that will fail to establish a coordinated strategy, analysts say.</p>
        <p>"It's out of sight, out of mind," said Senator J. Bennett Johnston of Louisiana, a Democrat who is the chairman of the Committee on Energy and Natural Resources. He had sponsored the defeated legislation.</p>
        <p>"The price of gasoline is O.K. now, so there must not be a problem," he said. "A Gallup poll shows that nearly a majority of the American people don't know that we import any oil." Nearly half the oil consumed in the United States is imported. Several Bills Under Way</p>
        <p>A few alternative bills are now in play, but none appears to have a chance of passage until late next year, at least.</p>
        <p>One, sponsored by Senator Richard H. Bryan, a Nevada Democrat, would mandate an increase in automobile fuel efficiency from the current 27.5 miles a gallon to 40 over the next decade. The Senate Commerce Committee passed the measure, which environmentalists say would conserve 2.5 million barrels of oil a day, but lobbying by the auto industry has so far helped impede action by the full Senate.</p>
        <p>The auto industry helped defeat the original energy package because executives feared liberals would add amendments on the floor to mandate fuel efficiency. With the industry reeling from decreased sales, several senators who helped Mr. Bryan sink the original bill are now opposing his efforts to raise mileage standards.</p>
        <p>Representative John D. Dingell, the Michigan Democrat who heads the House Committee on Energy and Commerce and is one of the strongest advocates of the auto industry in Congress, is working to keep anything similar to the Bryan measure from being considered in the House.</p>
        <p>Daniel Becker, a lobbyist for the Sierra Club and a primary strategist for the environmental movement on energy legislation, said Mr. Dingell could stop his committee from considering the Bryan bill, but he would be unable stop the full House from adding it as an amendment to a House energy bill next year.</p>
        <p>But a number of House staff members who monitor energy policy are not as confident.</p>
        <p>"Dingell is a very formidable adversary," Mr. Bryan said.</p>
        <p>But even if both Congressional chambers do pass the bill, the White House has threatened to veto any legislation that includes stricter fuel-economy standards, arguing that the country cannot afford to burden the industry with more costs. Alaska Drilling Measure</p>
        <p>The House Merchant Marine Committee is considering legislation that would allow oil drilling in the Alaskan National Wildlife Refuge. It was the strong opposition by environmental groups to opening up one of the country's last virgin preserves that sank the old energy bill, and the House measure is not considered any more passable.</p>
        <p>Representative Philip R. Sharp, an Indiana Democrat who is chairman of the Energy and Power Subcommittee, is sponsoring legislation that would promote the construction of natural gas pipelines, seek reductions of carbon-dioxide emissions that cause global warming and encourage the development of renewable energy sources like wind, solar and geothermal power.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharp's panel overwhelmingly approved his measure, but not before it carved out several of his most ambitious proposals.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
