<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Day 3: Remarks in Congress During the Last Hours of Debate</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19910115T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="414765"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="CONFRONTATION IN THE GULF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY ACTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONGRESS (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DE1738F930A25752C0A967958260" item-length="3532" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Day 3: Remarks in Congress During the Last Hours of Debate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the debate in Congress Friday night and today on President Bush's request for support for military action in the Persian Gulf, as transcribed by The New York Times: Senator Robert C. Byrd Democrat of West Virginia</p>
        <p>Now Mr. President, a superpower has claws and it has teeth. The superpower, as against this third world power, doesn't have to be impatient or impetuous. A superpower doesn't have to feel rushed. We can afford to be patient and let sanctions work. They say the morale of our soldiers will suffer. Mr. President, we should have thought about this before we proceeded to double our forces and terminate the rotation policy in the Middle East. Nothing damages morale more than early large losses of life. . . .</p>
        <p>Mr. President, the two economic giants of Germany and Japan have hardly spoken eloquently with their pocketbooks. They have only opted to hold our coats while we take on Hussein. Mr. President, I think this is a shame and a disgrace that Germany and Japan, two countries which will benefit far more than will the United States, two countries whose need for the oil of the Middle East far exceeds our need, will stand by and cynically watch American men and women shed their blood in the sands of the Arabian desert and refuse to help to finance in their treasury the costs of this effort.</p>
        <p>I think, Mr. President, I have difficulty finding the words to express my feelings that other nations would stand by. It's a monstrous disgrace and the American people will remember it.  Representative Ted Weiss</p>
        <p>Democrat of Manhattan</p>
        <p>Speaker, when we take those 30 seconds to take the oath of office and we raise our right hands and we puff out our chests, that's not just a formula that we're going through. We swear to preserve and protect and defend the Constitution of the United States.</p>
        <p>When we do that, we do it in the particular. And for the last 10 years at least, there has been such a tremendous erosion of our commitment to protecting and defending and preserving the Constitution.</p>
        <p>And this institution has played a role in that. We've abdicated. When we think that it's O.K. to wage small wars ourselves, whether it's Grenada or Panama, without the prior approval of the Congress, it seems to me that we're eroding the Constitution.</p>
        <p>And when we try to depend on international law, having set that kind of example, we erode the Constitution and our leadership role.</p>
        <p>The Bennett-Durbin Resolution should be adopted, because it reasserts that which the founders of this nation intended -- that the people make that fateful decision. And it should be done at this time. It is being done; it wouldn't have been done if the Secretary of State or the President had been left to their own. This body made that happen. Let's adopt this resolution to make it absolutely clear.  Senator Bob Graham  Democrat of Florida</p>
        <p>We make a basic mistake, I suggest, if we think that what we are dealing with is one man -- Saddam Hussein. I see Saddam Hussein not as the cause of those fundamental events, but rather as the guileful person who has taken advantage of those and other fundamental factors occurring in this region.</p>
        <p>We also, drastically, have contributed to the past. We have accommodated Iraq over a period of more than a decade, accommodated in terms of covertly assisting them in the war with Iran, within the shadow of the invasion of Kuwait, continuing to extend substantial economic assistance to Iraq.</p>
        <p>We also have contributed to the past by our failure to have a sustained commitment to a rational national energy policy, failure which has made us increasingly hostage to the circumstances in the Middle East and the personalities of today's and tomorrow's Saddam Husseins.</p>
        <p>Looking to the future, I would suggest that as we attempt to assess how we should respond to the current crisis today, we should ask ourselves what do we want to have as some of the consequences not just of the next 10 or 60 days but over the next decade in this region and what do they say about U.S. policy around the world in this new post-cold-war era.</p>
        <p>I am going to support the resolution which will give the President of the United States the authority to use force. I am going to do so because I believe that the President of the United States deserves to have a presumption of correctness of his actions, and that he especially deserves to have a presumption of correctness as it relates to matters of our national security and relations with other nations.</p>
        <p>I am reluctant to draw universal conclusions from a short visit to the Middle East, but that reluctance will be overcome to this extent: that I came away with the sense that this was an an extremely complex fabric of interrelated and divergent issues, factors, personalities, history and culture that we were dealing with in this crisis. It is not just the simple issue of a large and powerful state invading, pillaging and occupying a weak neighbor. And that the institution of the Presidency was in the best position to integrate, evaluate, assess options and implications of those options, and reach a judgment which was in the national interest.</p>
        <p>Representative Thomas S. Foley Democrat of Washington</p>
        <p>I would not feel it right as a Speaker to stand behind the usual custom not to vote and not to speak on the question of this importance. I do not ask anyone to follow me but I do as you feel so often I think, the need to explain to my constituents, to those who have sent me here why I will cast a vote for Hamilton-Gephardt and against the Michel-Solarz amendment.</p>
        <p>Those who believe that the President must now be armed with what is unquestionably . . . a virtual declaration of war, those who believe that that must be done, should not hesitate to vote that way, should not hesitate to give him that power.</p>
        <p>But let me suggest to you one thing. Do not do it under the notion that you merely hand him another diplomatic tool, another quiver of economic leverage or international leverage.</p>
        <p>The President has had no doubt about this. He has said again and again that if given that power he may well use it and perhaps sooner than we realize. If that is your judgment vote honorably and calmly and securely.</p>
        <p>But if you feel that more can be done, if you feel that the sanctions have not yet wasted their opportunity, if you believe that Saddam Hussein is growing weaker everyday under their impression, if you believe the international coalition will hold, if you believe that this nation's leadership is best expressed in this body and in the other body and in the coalition of constitutional consent, then vote for Hamilton-Gephardt.</p>
        <p>But however you vote, as the majority leader has said, let us come together after the vote with the notion that we are Americans here, not Democrats and not Republicans, all anxious to do the best for your country without recrimination as to motive, without anything but the solemn cry that on this great decision day we voted as our conscience and judgment told us we should. And then though our opinion may change over the years, we will not bear the burden of a harsh judgment on our honor and our actions at this moment.  Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato</p>
        <p>Republican of New York -</p>
        <p>Mr. President, Saddam Hussein is like a glutton, a geopolitical glutton. He's sitting down at the banquet table overflowing with goodies. And let me tell you, like every glutton, he's going to have them all. Kuwait is just the appetizer. He's gobbling it up. But it's not going to satisfy him. After a noisy belch or two, he's going to reach across the table for the next morsel. Now what's it going to be -- Saudi Arabia? Could be. The U.A.E? Who knows? I don't.</p>
        <p>But I do know two things with absolute certainty: he's going to keep grabbing and gobbling, and the main course somewhere on that menu is the State of Israel. The Israelis know that and that's one big reason that Prime Minister Shamir within the past 48 hours has again stated his unequivocal support for President Bush's policy.</p>
        <p>What's a little hard for me to understand is how some of Israel's strongest supporters in this body have joined into this chorus of "Let's give Saddam more time." Saddam has already had too much time. And I'm not talking about just these past five months, Mr. President. I'm talking about the years and years in which we, the United States, ignored his brutality, condoned his repeated aggressions against both his neighbors and many of his own people, and actually subsidized him with American taxpayers' money. It's time, Mr. President, to blow the whistle on Saddam Hussein. It is time to let him know, this grisly glutton, that the free lunch is over. It's time for him to pay the bill.  Senator Charles S. Robb  Democrat of Virginia</p>
        <p>We can and should take the President to task if we disagree with him on a whole variety of matters here at home -- from the budget to the rest of the domestic agenda.</p>
        <p>But in the great issues of war and peace, I believe we ought to make every effort possible to speak with one voice, or at least with the strongest majority voice possible.</p>
        <p>On balance, the majority of us would give the President very high marks for the way he has handled the gulf challenge to date. Yet now that we have reached the truly critical stage, I believe it would be a fundamental mistake to give even the appearance of withdrawing our trust and support.</p>
        <p>There is no question that the risks are great. I don't want to minimize the potential consequences if we're wrong. We can't escape responsibility for the actions we are about to authorize, and we shouldn't. We are risking thousands of American lives, and that fact weighs on the conscience of every member here -- particularly on those who have known the unhumane brutality of combat firsthand. And maybe future Saddam Husseins will act rationally when they look back on how the free world responded to the first real challege to the concept of collective security in the post-cold-war era.</p>
        <p>Let's give peace a chance by giving the President the authority he believes he needs to achieve it.</p>
        <p>And if Saddam Hussein understands that we have not only the capability but the will to carry out such an attack if necessary, maybe he'll act rationally in the first instance and we'll be able to bring the troops home soon.</p>
        <p>Representative Charles E. Bennett  Democrat of Florida</p>
        <p>When I first came to Congress, I wore a ribbon, the Silver Star. I did it partly for apology for being crippled. I haven't been wearing it recently. I'm not quite sure why I'm not wearing it. But I do know this, that when I was given that, I was given that with a citation that said, "Gallantry in Action." Friends, there's no such thing as gallantry in action.</p>
        <p>I don't want to run down anybody else's award. But action -- military action -- is a horrible experience. There's no gallantry in it. There's no beauty in it. It's a horrible experience. It's up to us in Congress to bite the bullet ourselves and to do something about seeing to it that peace is secured, if it can be secured, for the benefit of everybody, and it can be done.</p>
        <p>There are things that are unmentionable, things that can't be linked, for instance, that antagonizes a lot of people. But the world knows if this war ends the way it's now going, we're going to have a worse war in the future, a much worse war which may last for thousands of years.</p>
        <p>So this question of settling the Palestine problem, protecting Israel in its boundary and things like that are things that can be met. That takes courage because it can defeat us to do anything about it. But that's why we were elected. We were elected to make this kind of decision. We weren't elected to stay here forever. We were not elected for our salaries. We were elected to take a responsible position of government when the opportunity came -- comes to take it, and that's what we're not doing it unless we pass some way to see to it this process of trying to find a solution to this, other than combat, takes place. That's our responsibility. That's the courage that we must show today, and this is the place it has to be. It's not in Saudi Arabia. It's here in Washington, D.C., in this chamber today.</p>
        <p>I'm 80 years of age. I've been in this chamber for 43 years. Out of the 17,000 votes I've cast, the only one I really regret was the one which I cast for the Bay of Tonkin resolution. I particularly regret it because I knew that it was a declaration of war, and just as is the Solarz measure before us today, it's a declaration of war. And if you pass it, you make a compliance with the thing that I'm now asking you to vote for, which is to say you ought to decide ----</p>
        <p>. . . it means that a vote ought to be cast on the basis of what you think is best for our country, not best for the Democratic or Republican Party, not best for the President, not best for you, but what's best for our country and what's best for the world.</p>
        <p>So take that in your heart. Hold it close to you and realize this is a tremendously important opportunity you have here today, and cast your vote on that basis.</p>
        <p>Representative Nancy Pelosi  Democrat of California</p>
        <p>The King of Jordan last night on "Nightline" said that if we go to war, we could have an ecological disaster of the first order. Some of the consequences could be -- and this is according to the United Nations Environment Program -- oil spills equal to a dozen Exxon Valdez spills coursing through gulf waters; oil fires raging for weeks and perhaps months; smoke and debris blocking sunlight, causing temperatures to drop and altering crop seasons which could result in widespread famine; toxic plumes ascending to the upper atmosphere and falling as acid rain; millions of fish, dolphins, sea birds and other marine life wash onto Gulf shores; chemical contamination of air, water and vegetation; the Persian Gulf as a dead sea.</p>
        <p>The point has already been made how important it is for us to have an energy policy to avoid such conflicts in the future. The point is already made how we have to have a better policy toward nuclear disarmament. I hope the point will be made that we take very seriously the environmental consequences of our actions.</p>
        <p>Senator Robert J. Dole  Republican of Kansas</p>
        <p>I think everyone would agree that sanctions without a credible military threat would never have any severe impact on Iraq or Saddam Hussein.</p>
        <p>Now I've said to the President of the United States in a meeting with Republicans and Democrats that we need to pursue every avenue for a peaceful solution. I've said to the President of the United States, when I look into the eyes of a young man in the desert in Saudi Arabia I see his parents, maybe his children, his spouse. And if we talk about burden-sharing as we have in the dollar terms, wait until we start counting the deaths, how many Egypitans, how many Americans, how many Saudis, how many British. This is the real burden-sharing.</p>
        <p>And I've implored the President, who also has been there in World War II, that what we are attempting to do in the Congress of the United States is to strengthen his hand for peace, not to give him the license to see how fast we can become engaged in armed conflict.</p>
        <p>As far as this Senator knows, nothing in the United Nations resolution says that on the 15th you have to do something. But I think on the 15th, Saddam Hussein will understand that if he wants peace he can have it.</p>
        <p>So Mr. President, I know that everyone in this chamber wants Saddam Hussein to get out of Kuwait, and some have additional demands they would make on Saddam Hussein. I believe that the resolution we're about to vote on does exactly the wrong thing. As I've indicated, it actually gives Saddam Hussein a holiday from the threat that we might use force. . . .</p>
        <p>It would seem to me that the pending resolution wipes out this credible threat unless we're going to maintain 400,000 men there and all the military threat we have up until some day in the future, maybe this year or next year or the next year. And I've always thought that if he had sort of a holiday, as Saddam Hussein would have, that he probably wouldn't just take the holiday, he'd probably dig in deeper and make preparations so he can inflict even more casualties on the United States and on our young men and our young women and other forces from other allied nations in this period. So it's a two-edged sword.</p>
        <p>So it seems to me we have to think about the ultimate result. Do we save lives by waiting six months or waiting a year? Or do we by our votes today indicate to Saddam Hussein that now it's up to you? . . .</p>
        <p>So I would hope, Mr. President, that we're going to demonstrate today that the President of the United States is the Commander in Chief. The Congress of the United States certainly has a role to play. I said last November and December we ought to have been here debating then, when the policy was being formulated instead of coming in at the 11th hour after having been AWOL for three or four months and trying to change the direction of the policy President Bush has so patiently and successfully put together. This is not the United States versus Iraq. It's the entire international community with just a few exceptions versus Saddam Hussein and Iraq.  Representative Thomas M. Foglietta  Democrat of Pennsylvania</p>
        <p>I sit on the Armed Services Committee and we have heard experts come in and talk to us about the number of casualties, the number of young American men and women who will come back to us in body bags. Those estimates have ranged from as low as a thousand on up to 40 or 50 thousand. I say to you that we should do all we can to seek peace, to prevent those body bags from coming back to this country. So far, we have negotiated. We had one meeting -- one meeting, which lasted for six hours, during which time our representatives, our Secretary of State, issued an ultimatum: either you do what we say or else.</p>
        <p>Don't you believe that those 10 to 40 or 50 thousand young men and women deserve more? Deserve more time, more consideration and more negotiation? I do.</p>
        <p>Senator Al Gore  Democrat of Tennessee</p>
        <p>My decision today is the product of an intense, may I say excruciating, effort to find my way to a place as close to a sense of the ultimate truth in this matter as I am capable of getting.</p>
        <p>I've struggled to confront this issue in its bare essence -- to separate what I think is fact, or at least highly probable, from what I think is false, or at least highly improbable -- to strike a balance and to take my stand.</p>
        <p>We've all made that journey, regardless of where it has lead us. Each of us has stood here to describe it. And now it is my turn. I stood in a different place halfway through last year, when men and women from my home town in Carthage, Tenn., joined the units of many other towns across this country, leaving their loved ones, saying goodbye to husbands and wives and children and parents and preparing to become part of this army now massed in the desert of Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>I felt, up until recently, especially after the hearings in which I played an active role, questioning, probing, searching for the truth, I felt that I would support a move to continue the sanctions and hold open the option of force at a later time. As I searched my heart on this issue over the last few days with special intensity after we all heard the Secretary of State enunciate the word regrettably in Geneva, I found myself feeling that if I voted for the Mitchell nonresolution I would do so hoping that it did not prevail. I found myself feeling even late last night that since it now appears that there is a majority in favor of the other point of view that it would pass and will pass regardless of how I vote.</p>
        <p>I found myself pulled once again to support the Mitchell nonresolution, speaking only of the process I've gone through.</p>
        <p>And, Mr. President, I feel that I owe it to those who are there prepared to make the ultimate sacrifice, to give the best judgment of my head and my heart on what this nation should now do. I cannot reconcile myself to a point of view and a vote that says in effect, we will let this deadline come and go and try the sanctions perhaps until the next window, next August when military operations would again become feasible.  Representative Bud Shuster  Republican of Pennsylvania</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, we're asked, what's the hurry? Well, after five months of rebuffed diplomacy, every day that this Congress procrastinates Saddam's factories are producing more chemical and biological weapons; more anthrax, more botulism, more sarin, which is a lethal nerve gas, and yes, more progress on nuclear weapons.</p>
        <p>And make no mistake about it, my colleagues, if we must resort to military force, those factories of death and destruction and terrorism will surely be targets.</p>
        <p>So today, not next week, not next month, but today, we must give the President the authority to remove this scourge or the face of history will pass judgment upon us as the Congress that failed to do its duty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the debate in Congress Friday night and today on President Bush's request for support for military action in the Persian Gulf, as transcribed by The New York Times: Senator Robert C. Byrd Democrat of West Virginia</p>
        <p>Now Mr. President, a superpower has claws and it has teeth. The superpower, as against this third world power, doesn't have to be impatient or impetuous. A superpower doesn't have to feel rushed. We can afford to be patient and let sanctions work. They say the morale of our soldiers will suffer. Mr. President, we should have thought about this before we proceeded to double our forces and terminate the rotation policy in the Middle East. Nothing damages morale more than early large losses of life. . . .</p>
        <p>Mr. President, the two economic giants of Germany and Japan have hardly spoken eloquently with their pocketbooks. They have only opted to hold our coats while we take on Hussein. Mr. President, I think this is a shame and a disgrace that Germany and Japan, two countries which will benefit far more than will the United States, two countries whose need for the oil of the Middle East far exceeds our need, will stand by and cynically watch American men and women shed their blood in the sands of the Arabian desert and refuse to help to finance in their treasury the costs of this effort.</p>
        <p>I think, Mr. President, I have difficulty finding the words to express my feelings that other nations would stand by. It's a monstrous disgrace and the American people will remember it.  Representative Ted Weiss</p>
        <p>Democrat of Manhattan</p>
        <p>Speaker, when we take those 30 seconds to take the oath of office and we raise our right hands and we puff out our chests, that's not just a formula that we're going through. We swear to preserve and protect and defend the Constitution of the United States.</p>
        <p>When we do that, we do it in the particular. And for the last 10 years at least, there has been such a tremendous erosion of our commitment to protecting and defending and preserving the Constitution.</p>
        <p>And this institution has played a role in that. We've abdicated. When we think that it's O.K. to wage small wars ourselves, whether it's Grenada or Panama, without the prior approval of the Congress, it seems to me that we're eroding the Constitution.</p>
        <p>And when we try to depend on international law, having set that kind of example, we erode the Constitution and our leadership role.</p>
        <p>The Bennett-Durbin Resolution should be adopted, because it reasserts that which the founders of this nation intended -- that the people make that fateful decision. And it should be done at this time. It is being done; it wouldn't have been done if the Secretary of State or the President had been left to their own. This body made that happen. Let's adopt this resolution to make it absolutely clear.  Senator Bob Graham  Democrat of Florida</p>
        <p>We make a basic mistake, I suggest, if we think that what we are dealing with is one man -- Saddam Hussein. I see Saddam Hussein not as the cause of those fundamental events, but rather as the guileful person who has taken advantage of those and other fundamental factors occurring in this region.</p>
        <p>We also, drastically, have contributed to the past. We have accommodated Iraq over a period of more than a decade, accommodated in terms of covertly assisting them in the war with Iran, within the shadow of the invasion of Kuwait, continuing to extend substantial economic assistance to Iraq.</p>
        <p>We also have contributed to the past by our failure to have a sustained commitment to a rational national energy policy, failure which has made us increasingly hostage to the circumstances in the Middle East and the personalities of today's and tomorrow's Saddam Husseins.</p>
        <p>Looking to the future, I would suggest that as we attempt to assess how we should respond to the current crisis today, we should ask ourselves what do we want to have as some of the consequences not just of the next 10 or 60 days but over the next decade in this region and what do they say about U.S. policy around the world in this new post-cold-war era.</p>
        <p>I am going to support the resolution which will give the President of the United States the authority to use force. I am going to do so because I believe that the President of the United States deserves to have a presumption of correctness of his actions, and that he especially deserves to have a presumption of correctness as it relates to matters of our national security and relations with other nations.</p>
        <p>I am reluctant to draw universal conclusions from a short visit to the Middle East, but that reluctance will be overcome to this extent: that I came away with the sense that this was an an extremely complex fabric of interrelated and divergent issues, factors, personalities, history and culture that we were dealing with in this crisis. It is not just the simple issue of a large and powerful state invading, pillaging and occupying a weak neighbor. And that the institution of the Presidency was in the best position to integrate, evaluate, assess options and implications of those options, and reach a judgment which was in the national interest.</p>
        <p>Representative Thomas S. Foley Democrat of Washington</p>
        <p>I would not feel it right as a Speaker to stand behind the usual custom not to vote and not to speak on the question of this importance. I do not ask anyone to follow me but I do as you feel so often I think, the need to explain to my constituents, to those who have sent me here why I will cast a vote for Hamilton-Gephardt and against the Michel-Solarz amendment.</p>
        <p>Those who believe that the President must now be armed with what is unquestionably . . . a virtual declaration of war, those who believe that that must be done, should not hesitate to vote that way, should not hesitate to give him that power.</p>
        <p>But let me suggest to you one thing. Do not do it under the notion that you merely hand him another diplomatic tool, another quiver of economic leverage or international leverage.</p>
        <p>The President has had no doubt about this. He has said again and again that if given that power he may well use it and perhaps sooner than we realize. If that is your judgment vote honorably and calmly and securely.</p>
        <p>But if you feel that more can be done, if you feel that the sanctions have not yet wasted their opportunity, if you believe that Saddam Hussein is growing weaker everyday under their impression, if you believe the international coalition will hold, if you believe that this nation's leadership is best expressed in this body and in the other body and in the coalition of constitutional consent, then vote for Hamilton-Gephardt.</p>
        <p>But however you vote, as the majority leader has said, let us come together after the vote with the notion that we are Americans here, not Democrats and not Republicans, all anxious to do the best for your country without recrimination as to motive, without anything but the solemn cry that on this great decision day we voted as our conscience and judgment told us we should. And then though our opinion may change over the years, we will not bear the burden of a harsh judgment on our honor and our actions at this moment.  Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato</p>
        <p>Republican of New York -</p>
        <p>Mr. President, Saddam Hussein is like a glutton, a geopolitical glutton. He's sitting down at the banquet table overflowing with goodies. And let me tell you, like every glutton, he's going to have them all. Kuwait is just the appetizer. He's gobbling it up. But it's not going to satisfy him. After a noisy belch or two, he's going to reach across the table for the next morsel. Now what's it going to be -- Saudi Arabia? Could be. The U.A.E? Who knows? I don't.</p>
        <p>But I do know two things with absolute certainty: he's going to keep grabbing and gobbling, and the main course somewhere on that menu is the State of Israel. The Israelis know that and that's one big reason that Prime Minister Shamir within the past 48 hours has again stated his unequivocal support for President Bush's policy.</p>
        <p>What's a little hard for me to understand is how some of Israel's strongest supporters in this body have joined into this chorus of "Let's give Saddam more time." Saddam has already had too much time. And I'm not talking about just these past five months, Mr. President. I'm talking about the years and years in which we, the United States, ignored his brutality, condoned his repeated aggressions against both his neighbors and many of his own people, and actually subsidized him with American taxpayers' money. It's time, Mr. President, to blow the whistle on Saddam Hussein. It is time to let him know, this grisly glutton, that the free lunch is over. It's time for him to pay the bill.  Senator Charles S. Robb  Democrat of Virginia</p>
        <p>We can and should take the President to task if we disagree with him on a whole variety of matters here at home -- from the budget to the rest of the domestic agenda.</p>
        <p>But in the great issues of war and peace, I believe we ought to make every effort possible to speak with one voice, or at least with the strongest majority voice possible.</p>
        <p>On balance, the majority of us would give the President very high marks for the way he has handled the gulf challenge to date. Yet now that we have reached the truly critical stage, I believe it would be a fundamental mistake to give even the appearance of withdrawing our trust and support.</p>
        <p>There is no question that the risks are great. I don't want to minimize the potential consequences if we're wrong. We can't escape responsibility for the actions we are about to authorize, and we shouldn't. We are risking thousands of American lives, and that fact weighs on the conscience of every member here -- particularly on those who have known the unhumane brutality of combat firsthand. And maybe future Saddam Husseins will act rationally when they look back on how the free world responded to the first real challege to the concept of collective security in the post-cold-war era.</p>
        <p>Let's give peace a chance by giving the President the authority he believes he needs to achieve it.</p>
        <p>And if Saddam Hussein understands that we have not only the capability but the will to carry out such an attack if necessary, maybe he'll act rationally in the first instance and we'll be able to bring the troops home soon.</p>
        <p>Representative Charles E. Bennett  Democrat of Florida</p>
        <p>When I first came to Congress, I wore a ribbon, the Silver Star. I did it partly for apology for being crippled. I haven't been wearing it recently. I'm not quite sure why I'm not wearing it. But I do know this, that when I was given that, I was given that with a citation that said, "Gallantry in Action." Friends, there's no such thing as gallantry in action.</p>
        <p>I don't want to run down anybody else's award. But action -- military action -- is a horrible experience. There's no gallantry in it. There's no beauty in it. It's a horrible experience. It's up to us in Congress to bite the bullet ourselves and to do something about seeing to it that peace is secured, if it can be secured, for the benefit of everybody, and it can be done.</p>
        <p>There are things that are unmentionable, things that can't be linked, for instance, that antagonizes a lot of people. But the world knows if this war ends the way it's now going, we're going to have a worse war in the future, a much worse war which may last for thousands of years.</p>
        <p>So this question of settling the Palestine problem, protecting Israel in its boundary and things like that are things that can be met. That takes courage because it can defeat us to do anything about it. But that's why we were elected. We were elected to make this kind of decision. We weren't elected to stay here forever. We were not elected for our salaries. We were elected to take a responsible position of government when the opportunity came -- comes to take it, and that's what we're not doing it unless we pass some way to see to it this process of trying to find a solution to this, other than combat, takes place. That's our responsibility. That's the courage that we must show today, and this is the place it has to be. It's not in Saudi Arabia. It's here in Washington, D.C., in this chamber today.</p>
        <p>I'm 80 years of age. I've been in this chamber for 43 years. Out of the 17,000 votes I've cast, the only one I really regret was the one which I cast for the Bay of Tonkin resolution. I particularly regret it because I knew that it was a declaration of war, and just as is the Solarz measure before us today, it's a declaration of war. And if you pass it, you make a compliance with the thing that I'm now asking you to vote for, which is to say you ought to decide ----</p>
        <p>. . . it means that a vote ought to be cast on the basis of what you think is best for our country, not best for the Democratic or Republican Party, not best for the President, not best for you, but what's best for our country and what's best for the world.</p>
        <p>So take that in your heart. Hold it close to you and realize this is a tremendously important opportunity you have here today, and cast your vote on that basis.</p>
        <p>Representative Nancy Pelosi  Democrat of California</p>
        <p>The King of Jordan last night on "Nightline" said that if we go to war, we could have an ecological disaster of the first order. Some of the consequences could be -- and this is according to the United Nations Environment Program -- oil spills equal to a dozen Exxon Valdez spills coursing through gulf waters; oil fires raging for weeks and perhaps months; smoke and debris blocking sunlight, causing temperatures to drop and altering crop seasons which could result in widespread famine; toxic plumes ascending to the upper atmosphere and falling as acid rain; millions of fish, dolphins, sea birds and other marine life wash onto Gulf shores; chemical contamination of air, water and vegetation; the Persian Gulf as a dead sea.</p>
        <p>The point has already been made how important it is for us to have an energy policy to avoid such conflicts in the future. The point is already made how we have to have a better policy toward nuclear disarmament. I hope the point will be made that we take very seriously the environmental consequences of our actions.</p>
        <p>Senator Robert J. Dole  Republican of Kansas</p>
        <p>I think everyone would agree that sanctions without a credible military threat would never have any severe impact on Iraq or Saddam Hussein.</p>
        <p>Now I've said to the President of the United States in a meeting with Republicans and Democrats that we need to pursue every avenue for a peaceful solution. I've said to the President of the United States, when I look into the eyes of a young man in the desert in Saudi Arabia I see his parents, maybe his children, his spouse. And if we talk about burden-sharing as we have in the dollar terms, wait until we start counting the deaths, how many Egypitans, how many Americans, how many Saudis, how many British. This is the real burden-sharing.</p>
        <p>And I've implored the President, who also has been there in World War II, that what we are attempting to do in the Congress of the United States is to strengthen his hand for peace, not to give him the license to see how fast we can become engaged in armed conflict.</p>
        <p>As far as this Senator knows, nothing in the United Nations resolution says that on the 15th you have to do something. But I think on the 15th, Saddam Hussein will understand that if he wants peace he can have it.</p>
        <p>So Mr. President, I know that everyone in this chamber wants Saddam Hussein to get out of Kuwait, and some have additional demands they would make on Saddam Hussein. I believe that the resolution we're about to vote on does exactly the wrong thing. As I've indicated, it actually gives Saddam Hussein a holiday from the threat that we might use force. . . .</p>
        <p>It would seem to me that the pending resolution wipes out this credible threat unless we're going to maintain 400,000 men there and all the military threat we have up until some day in the future, maybe this year or next year or the next year. And I've always thought that if he had sort of a holiday, as Saddam Hussein would have, that he probably wouldn't just take the holiday, he'd probably dig in deeper and make preparations so he can inflict even more casualties on the United States and on our young men and our young women and other forces from other allied nations in this period. So it's a two-edged sword.</p>
        <p>So it seems to me we have to think about the ultimate result. Do we save lives by waiting six months or waiting a year? Or do we by our votes today indicate to Saddam Hussein that now it's up to you? . . .</p>
        <p>So I would hope, Mr. President, that we're going to demonstrate today that the President of the United States is the Commander in Chief. The Congress of the United States certainly has a role to play. I said last November and December we ought to have been here debating then, when the policy was being formulated instead of coming in at the 11th hour after having been AWOL for three or four months and trying to change the direction of the policy President Bush has so patiently and successfully put together. This is not the United States versus Iraq. It's the entire international community with just a few exceptions versus Saddam Hussein and Iraq.  Representative Thomas M. Foglietta  Democrat of Pennsylvania</p>
        <p>I sit on the Armed Services Committee and we have heard experts come in and talk to us about the number of casualties, the number of young American men and women who will come back to us in body bags. Those estimates have ranged from as low as a thousand on up to 40 or 50 thousand. I say to you that we should do all we can to seek peace, to prevent those body bags from coming back to this country. So far, we have negotiated. We had one meeting -- one meeting, which lasted for six hours, during which time our representatives, our Secretary of State, issued an ultimatum: either you do what we say or else.</p>
        <p>Don't you believe that those 10 to 40 or 50 thousand young men and women deserve more? Deserve more time, more consideration and more negotiation? I do.</p>
        <p>Senator Al Gore  Democrat of Tennessee</p>
        <p>My decision today is the product of an intense, may I say excruciating, effort to find my way to a place as close to a sense of the ultimate truth in this matter as I am capable of getting.</p>
        <p>I've struggled to confront this issue in its bare essence -- to separate what I think is fact, or at least highly probable, from what I think is false, or at least highly improbable -- to strike a balance and to take my stand.</p>
        <p>We've all made that journey, regardless of where it has lead us. Each of us has stood here to describe it. And now it is my turn. I stood in a different place halfway through last year, when men and women from my home town in Carthage, Tenn., joined the units of many other towns across this country, leaving their loved ones, saying goodbye to husbands and wives and children and parents and preparing to become part of this army now massed in the desert of Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>I felt, up until recently, especially after the hearings in which I played an active role, questioning, probing, searching for the truth, I felt that I would support a move to continue the sanctions and hold open the option of force at a later time. As I searched my heart on this issue over the last few days with special intensity after we all heard the Secretary of State enunciate the word regrettably in Geneva, I found myself feeling that if I voted for the Mitchell nonresolution I would do so hoping that it did not prevail. I found myself feeling even late last night that since it now appears that there is a majority in favor of the other point of view that it would pass and will pass regardless of how I vote.</p>
        <p>I found myself pulled once again to support the Mitchell nonresolution, speaking only of the process I've gone through.</p>
        <p>And, Mr. President, I feel that I owe it to those who are there prepared to make the ultimate sacrifice, to give the best judgment of my head and my heart on what this nation should now do. I cannot reconcile myself to a point of view and a vote that says in effect, we will let this deadline come and go and try the sanctions perhaps until the next window, next August when military operations would again become feasible.  Representative Bud Shuster  Republican of Pennsylvania</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, we're asked, what's the hurry? Well, after five months of rebuffed diplomacy, every day that this Congress procrastinates Saddam's factories are producing more chemical and biological weapons; more anthrax, more botulism, more sarin, which is a lethal nerve gas, and yes, more progress on nuclear weapons.</p>
        <p>And make no mistake about it, my colleagues, if we must resort to military force, those factories of death and destruction and terrorism will surely be targets.</p>
        <p>So today, not next week, not next month, but today, we must give the President the authority to remove this scourge or the face of history will pass judgment upon us as the Congress that failed to do its duty.</p>
        <p>CONFRONTATION IN THE GULF  Correction:  January 15, 1991, Tuesday</p>
        <p>Because of a transcription error, excerpts on Sunday from a speech about the Persian Gulf by Senator Al Gore, Democrat of Tennessee, rendered the name of a resolution incorrectly. The passage should have read, "I found myself feeling that if I voted for the Mitchell-Nunn resolution, I would do so hoping that it would not prevail." The Senator did not say "Mitchell nonresolution."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 15, 1991, Tuesday</p>
        <p>Because of a transcription error, excerpts on Sunday from a speech about the Persian Gulf by Senator Al Gore, Democrat of Tennessee, rendered the name of a resolution incorrectly. The passage should have read, "I found myself feeling that if I voted for the Mitchell-Nunn resolution, I would do so hoping that it would not prevail." The Senator did not say "Mitchell nonresolution."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
