<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; Device to Save Infants Lifts Medical Hope, and Investors</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="493515"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIRTH DEFECTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NELLCOR INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">POLLACK, ANDREW</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Birth Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birth Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D6173FF931A25751C1A967958260" item-length="1132" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; Device to Save Infants Lifts Medical Hope, and Investors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">POLLACK, ANDREW</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Dec. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A small California medical-equipment company is stirring hopes both in the medical community and on Wall Street. It is developing a device that could reduce the risk that babies will be born with brain damage because of oxygen deprivation during delivery.</p>
        <p>The device, known as a fetal oximeter, would measure the oxygen content in fetal blood during labor and delivery. It might also allow women to avoid Caesarean sections that are performed because it appears the fetus is suffering from lack of oxygen, although in some cases they are not.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A small California medical-equipment company is stirring hopes both in the medical community and on Wall Street. It is developing a device that could reduce the risk that babies will be born with brain damage because of oxygen deprivation during delivery.</p>
        <p>The device, known as a fetal oximeter, would measure the oxygen content in fetal blood during labor and delivery. It might also allow women to avoid Caesarean sections that are performed because it appears the fetus is suffering from lack of oxygen, although in some cases they are not.</p>
        <p>The company, Nellcor Inc. of Hayward, Calif., is still testing the device and has not published any scientific data that prove it works or that it is useful in preventing problem births or unnecessary Caesareans. But investors, in furious anticipation, have bid up the company's stock to triple the price of a little more than a year ago. Today, the stock closed at $28.50, unchanged, in over-the-counter trading.</p>
        <p>"The sizzle in the stock is the fetal oximeter," said Lorraine Schwarz, an analyst with Wertheim Schroder &amp; Company in New York, who recommends the stock. "There's nothing like it on the market."</p>
        <p>But other analysts expressed more caution. "I don't like to see companies talk early in the development stage when it's not certain there's clinical significance," said Gene T. Gargiulo of the First Boston Corporation, who calls the stock overvalued.</p>
        <p>Dr. David B. Swedlow, Nellcor's vice president of medical affairs and technology development, said the company had solved the technical problems "to our satisfaction," adding that Nellcor hoped to apply by June for approval to market the device.</p>
        <p>Nellcor, founded in 1981, is a pioneer in pulse oximetry, which provides a painless and continuous measurement of the oxygen content of a patient's blood. Oximeters are now standard equipment in operating rooms. They have greatly reduced the number of deaths that occur from lack of oxygen in patients under anesthesia and have led to sharply reduced malpractice insurance rates for anesthesiologists.</p>
        <p>In pulse oximetry, a sensor is wrapped around or clipped to a finger, toe, earlobe or nose of the patient. In simple terms, red light from a small diode shines through the skin, and a detector on the other side measures how much of the light gets through. When blood is rich in oxygen, it is bright red, and most of the light will get through. Oxygen-poor blood is dark red and absorbs the light.</p>
        <p>Pulse oximetry was developed by a Japanese engineer in 1976, but Nellcor was the first to commercialize the idea, in 1983 -- a rare reversal of the usual Japanese-American pattern.</p>
        <p>Nellcor is a leader in pulse oximeters, which sell for $2,000 to $5,000 apiece. Its main competitors are Criticare Systems of Waukesha, Wis. and Ohmeda, a division of the BOC Group of Britain, formerly British Oxygen.</p>
        <p>But Nellcor's main business is not the razor but the blades. More than 50 percent of revenues and profits comes from selling millions of the disposable sensors, which resemble small bandages, for about $15 apiece. Nellcor also licenses some competitors to use Nellcor sensors on their oximeters.</p>
        <p>In its last fiscal year ended July 7, Nellcor had net income of $16.2 million, or $1.05 a share, on revenues of $158.9 million. This fiscal year analysts project the company will earn about $1.25 a share on revenues of close to $190 million.</p>
        <p>Nellcor is benefiting from the spread of pulse oximetry beyond operating rooms to monitor patients in intensive care units and those who receive narcotics while recovering from surgery. The company has also been buying companies and licensing technology in an attempt to expand into new areas, like monitors for carbon dioxide, anesthesia gases and blood pressure.</p>
        <p>But analysts say the biggest opportunity lies in applying pulse oximetry to fetuses during delivery. Fear of malpractice suits from problem births has led many doctors to stop delivering babies.</p>
        <p>"This is at the top of the wish list" for obstetricians, said Tina Rizopoulos, an analyst with Paine Webber. "Essentially, you can use one sensor on every baby born in the U.S. and abroad."</p>
        <p>Currently, doctors usually measure the heart rate of a fetus using a monitor that rests on the mother's abdomen. In about 20 to 25 percent of births an electrode is attached to the fetus's scalp to get more detailed heart rate data.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Swerdlow said that heart rate was only an indirect measure of the important oxygen level in the blood. In many cases, he said, the heart rate can slow even if the baby is not experiencing a problem. In such cases, a Caesarean is often performed to be safe.</p>
        <p>The company's fetal sensor, Dr. Swerdlow said, is inserted into the cervix and held against the side of the baby by the pressure of the uterine wall. The company has obtained what it believes are reliable readings of oxygen level, which is difficult given the baby's movements in delivery, and has not experienced safety problems. Some babies have emerged from the womb holding the sensor in one hand, he said.</p>
        <p>Michael P. Downey, Nellcor's chief financial officer, said the big market would again be in disposable sensors, which could sell for about $50 apiece. If such a device were used in all four million births each year in the United States, sales would be $200 million a year, large for a company of Nellcor's size. While competitors are also believed to be looking at fetal oximeters, analysts say Nellcor appears to be far ahead.</p>
        <p>But some analysts are cautious. Len Yaffe of Montgomery Securities in San Francisco, while praising Nellcor as an excellent company, said he thought that fetal oximeters would be used only for a fraction of births, not for all of them because doctors would not want to insert something into the birth canal unless it was necessary.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gargiulo of First Boston said that Nellcor had been over-optimistic about the sales potential or manufacturability of other products in the past. The company concedes sales of its anesthesia gas monitor have been disappointing. It also had severe problems in manufacturing its carbon dioxide sensing product.</p>
        <p>Such problems depressed earnings a few years ago and led to a shakeup in management. The four founders eventually left the company and C. Raymond Larkin Jr., who had been in charge of sales and marketing, became chief executive.</p>
        <p>Even assuming the fetal oximeter works, it is not clear how quickly the Food and Drug Administration will approve its use. Nellcor is hoping the agency will decide that the fetal oximeter is merely a new use for an approved technology and will approve it in a matter of months. But if the F.D.A. decides a more complete review is needed, approval could require an additional two years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
