<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q&amp;A</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="463911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAY, C CLAIBORNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D9103FF933A05754C0A967958260" item-length="406" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q&amp;A</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. CLAIBORNE RAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAY, C CLAIBORNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Red Clay  Q.</p>
        <p>What makes red clay red?</p>
        <p>A.  The famous soil found in Georgia, South Carolina and elsewhere in the southern Piedmont region is mainly a grayish-white clay called kaolin colored by a small amount of iron oxides, said Bill R. Smith, a soil scientist at Clemson University in Clemson, S.C.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Red Clay  Q.</p>
        <p>What makes red clay red?</p>
        <p>A.  The famous soil found in Georgia, South Carolina and elsewhere in the southern Piedmont region is mainly a grayish-white clay called kaolin colored by a small amount of iron oxides, said Bill R. Smith, a soil scientist at Clemson University in Clemson, S.C.</p>
        <p>"It doesn't take a lot of red paint to paint a barn red, and it doesn't take a lot of these iron oxides to color the soil red," he said. The oxides can be magnetically separated or chemically reduced in the laboratory, leaving a light-colored residue, he said.</p>
        <p>The Piedmont clays were mostly formed in place, not washed there from somewhere else by ancient seas or rivers, he said. The oxides, which are very finely divided particles, come from iron-bearing minerals in deposits of solid crystalline igneous or metamorphic rocks, he said. These minerals spend thousands and thousands of years under rainfall in well-drained conditions that promote oxidation.</p>
        <p>The color is tenacious in clothes, possibly because the particles are so fine and dusty, he suggested. "Soaps emulsify oils, and this is not an oily dirt at all," he said.</p>
        <p>In many parts of the South, many of the nutrients have been leached out of the clay by millennia of rain, Dr. Smith said, but the warm, well-watered red-clay regions are actually fairly green, and the clays will support grass, trees and shrubs. Some of the soils are extensively eroded, so that the red clay subsoil is much closer to the surface and the topsoil is thin or missing.  Beer Through a Straw</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>Does drinking beer through a straw make a person drunk faster?</p>
        <p>A. There is no evidence to support the idea that people get drunk faster if they drink alcoholic beverages through a straw, according to the National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism.</p>
        <p>However, the carbonation of beer is itself a factor in intoxication, according to "Loosening the Grip: a Handbook of Alcohol Information," by Kinney and Leaton, published by the C.V. Mosby Company. The book notes that carbon dioxide, which makes beer and other carbonated beverages bubble, hastens the passage of alcohol from the stomach and has the effect of increasing the speed of absorption. It is the rate of absorption that is largely responsible for the feeling of intoxication; other factors besides carbonation include the amount of food in the stomach and the type of beverage consumed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
