<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>COMPANY BRIEFS</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="485518"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DE103BF93BA35752C1A967958260" item-length="350" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>COMPANY BRIEFS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>* American Southwest Mortgage Investments Corp., Tucson, Ariz., a mortgage finance investment company, acquired most of the assets of Residential Mortgage Investments Inc., Fort Worth, for $1.1 million in cash and about 1.8 million new American shares. * Angeion Corp., Plymouth, Minn., a maker of medical components, received approval from the Japanese Government to begin marketing two additional lines of accessory devices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>* American Southwest Mortgage Investments Corp., Tucson, Ariz., a mortgage finance investment company, acquired most of the assets of Residential Mortgage Investments Inc., Fort Worth, for $1.1 million in cash and about 1.8 million new American shares. * Angeion Corp., Plymouth, Minn., a maker of medical components, received approval from the Japanese Government to begin marketing two additional lines of accessory devices.</p>
        <p>* BTR P.L.C., London, a conglomerate, raised its hostile offer for Hawker Siddeley Group P.L.C. by about 3 percent, to $2.76 billion. Hawker Siddeley, an industrial group, rejected the sweetened offer as a "token increase." * CalFed Inc., Los Angeles, a financial services holding company, will sell its institutional investment management company, TSA Capital Management, to Mitchum, Jones &amp; Templeton Inc., Los Angeles, an investment banking and management firm, and a group of TSA executives. Terms were not disclosed.  * Dow Corning Corp., Midland, Mich., a joint venture of Dow Chemical Co. and Corning Inc., plans a four-year, $262 million expansion of its manufacturing plants in Barry, Wales. * General Motors Corp., Detroit, started vehicle assembly at its joint venture operation in Tunisia. * Hanson P.L.C., London, said the Federal Trade Commission had requested additional information on its $625 million proposed merger with Beazer P.L.C. * Mobil Corp., New York, has made two more discoveries off Nigeria, of an estimated 450 million barrels of recoverable oil. Mobil has a 40 percent interest in the discoveries. The remaining 60 percent is held by Nigerian National Petroleum Corp. * Union Carbide Corp., Danbury, Conn., said it had developed a technology, called Cansolv, to removes up to 99 percent of sulfur dioxide, which causes acid rain, from industrial and utility plant emissions.  * Zenith Electronics Corp., Glenview, Ill., and American Telephone and Telegraph Co. said their all-digital high-definition television system was certified for testing by the Federal Communications Commission.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
