<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>American and Pilots Brace for Strike</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="419597"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WAGES AND SALARIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PILOTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN AIRLINES INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ALLIED PILOTS ASSN</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAYES, THOMAS C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CRANDALL, ROBERT L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pilots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D91238F931A35751C0A967958260" item-length="1195" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>American and Pilots Brace for Strike</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS C. HAYES, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAYES, THOMAS C</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS, Feb. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pilots at American Airlines started passing the hat a year ago to build a strike fund. The dollar count has swelled into the millions and, with contract talks bogged down, cockpit crews at the nation's largest airline are bracing for a walkout as early as March.</p>
        <p>"Nobody wants it for personal reasons and financial reasons," said Steve Roach, a co-pilot based in San Francisco. "But all the past promises from management have been broken. The company is accusing us of everything except causing holes in the ozone layer, and we're just fed up."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pilots at American Airlines started passing the hat a year ago to build a strike fund. The dollar count has swelled into the millions and, with contract talks bogged down, cockpit crews at the nation's largest airline are bracing for a walkout as early as March.</p>
        <p>"Nobody wants it for personal reasons and financial reasons," said Steve Roach, a co-pilot based in San Francisco. "But all the past promises from management have been broken. The company is accusing us of everything except causing holes in the ozone layer, and we're just fed up."</p>
        <p>This high-level feud over money, power and pride has pitted the aggressive management of Robert L. Crandall, American's chairman and chief executive, against a pilots' union whose ranks have surged with the airline's growth but whose pay and benefit levels lag behind some rivals.</p>
        <p>Directors of the Allied Pilots Association, the in-house union for the company's 8,900 pilots, rejected a third contract offer late Wednesday, this time after a Federal mediator supervised bargaining in Washington that began Jan. 7.</p>
        <p>American executives concede that just the threat of a strike will cost bookings, but the airline is banking on customer loyalty inspired by the frequent-flier discounts it pioneered. Some travel agents have said that if a strike deadline drew near, they would back up American reservations by booking a second seat on another carrier.  Two-Level Pay Scale</p>
        <p>The pilots are taking aim at another American innovation: the pay system that gives lower wages for the same work to pilots with fewer years at the airline. This "two-tier" wage scale played an important part in American's growth and its success against upstart low-fare rivals like People Express. One measure of the company's success was its adding 5,000 pilots since 1983; it also more than doubled the number of highly paid captains, to more than 3,400.</p>
        <p>The lower pay scale applies to two-thirds of American's pilots and it has inflamed many of them. "The system is grossly unfair," said Wally Pitts, a first officer on American's international flights who is in the lower-paid group. "We feel that as an industry leader in profits and executive compensation, that all of the employees at American should directly benefit in a like manner, and therefore be compensated at the top of the industry," said Mr. Pitts, 33 years old, who was hired six years ago.</p>
        <p>In addition to wanting higher pay, union members oppose the airline's demand that pilots begin paying an average of about $1,000 a year as their share of medical insurance costs. Most other company employees make such payments.</p>
        <p>More than a year of talks in Fort Worth, where American is based, collapsed at the end of December with harsh accusations from both sides. Before the talks broke down, a period of abnormally high pilot absences had snarled American's schedules and disrupted 60,000 passengers during the Christmas holiday.</p>
        <p>Within days, American, a unit of the AMR Corporation, said it would eliminate 250 of its 2,300 daily flights, including the intensely competitive Los Angeles-San Francisco route. The airline said it could not risk another episode like the December "sick-out," but union members said the pilots were being made scapegoats for cuts that American was forced into because of overly aggressive expansion. The route cuts became completely effective today.  More Talks Scheduled</p>
        <p>The Federal negotiators from the National Mediation Board decided Thursday to resume the bargaining in Washington on Monday. If the renewed talks break off, the board declares an impasse and both sides reject binding arbitration, a 30-day cooling off period would begin, and American's pilots could be on strike sometime in March.</p>
        <p>In the event of a strike, the airline's strategy is to hire replacements. American has hired and trained 700 to 900 pilots a year since 1983 and company officials say any new pilots could be flying within five weeks of the day they are hired.</p>
        <p>"There are plenty of pilot candidates in the marketplace who would love to fly for American Airlines," said Robert W. Baker, American's executive vice president for operations. "For every pilot we hire, there are 16 applications. When you consider the Eastern pilots who suddenly find themselves on the park bench, that puts another 3,000 pilots into the pool of potential candidates." Eastern Airlines Inc., in bankruptcy and out of cash, stopped flying on Jan. 18.</p>
        <p>While American would suffer from a strike, its survival would not be threatened. The expansion that Mr. Crandall set in motion in 1983, at an estimated cost of $20 billion through 1995, has catapulted American ahead of all of its major competitors in passengers and, until last year's fuel cost increases, in profits.</p>
        <p>In addition, People Express and other low-cost competitors have failed, merged or changed strategies, and many major carriers like Continental Airlines, Pan American World Airways and Trans World Airlines are in financial trouble.  Effects of Recession and War</p>
        <p>Still, the pilots say circumstances are on their side. They say recession, slack winter travel and fears of terrorism brought on by the war in the Persian Gulf have combined to reduce airline passenger loads by 20 percent from a year ago. Moreover, American's operations have been strained since the Pentagon last year called up 400 of the 1,700 American pilots who are active in the military reserves.</p>
        <p>The American pilots want the airline to match the industry-leading pay levels that Delta Airlines granted its pilots last summer. If that scale were approved, the salary for a captain who had flown 15 years on a mid-sized Super 80 class of aircraft would rise to $135,954 from $118,557.</p>
        <p>The highest paid pilots, the captains of the wide-bodied jumbo jets, would make $176,130 after 12 years, as against their current $145,368 after 15 years. The pay of a flight officer, the junior crew member, on a Boeing 727-200, would rise to a range of $58,482 to $96,525, depending on experience, from the current $31,995 to $75,519.</p>
        <p>American's management has been holding out for a pay package that would essentially match the scale pilots at Northwest Airlines accepted last year. That scale is next highest after Delta's.</p>
        <p>But American also is offering a bonus formula that would be tied to the airline's profit. In good years, the base pay and bonus would exceed the pay of Delta's pilots, the company said. But some pilots oppose such profit sharing because the amount is unpredictable and vulnerable to manipulation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baker, the company vice president, said he still hoped for a solution. "In an industry in the midst of turmoil, American has made our pilots a very rich offer." he said. "We think we have done everything possible to avoid confrontation and are astounded that the A.P.A. is unwilling to reach a reasonable agreement."</p>
        <p>Mr. Pitts of the union said: "There is not one pilot on the property of American Airlines that wants to see the airline fail. We are tied directly to American's success and we truly believe the contract we are seeking allows American an adequate rate of return."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
