<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; Cheap Oil, Expensive Cartel</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="431384"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ADELMAN, M A</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ECONOMIC SCENE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DD103DF933A15750C0A967958260" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; Cheap Oil, Expensive Cartel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SAUDI ARABIA, the muscle behind the international oil cartel, made no secret of its aims at the meeting of OPEC ministers in Geneva last week: keeping the price of a barrel high enough to replenish its war-depleted treasury -- but not high enough to weaken the magic kingdom's grip on the market.</p>
        <p>America, the muscle behind Saudi Arabia, is of two minds about the price of oil. On the one hand, policy makers worry that low prices would discommode their friends from Abu Dhabi to Houston. On the other, they fret that high prices would slow recovery from the recession and anger voters who believe deep down that Gen. Norman Schwarzkopf was fighting to make the world safe for unleaded regular at $1.06 a gallon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SAUDI ARABIA, the muscle behind the international oil cartel, made no secret of its aims at the meeting of OPEC ministers in Geneva last week: keeping the price of a barrel high enough to replenish its war-depleted treasury -- but not high enough to weaken the magic kingdom's grip on the market.</p>
        <p>America, the muscle behind Saudi Arabia, is of two minds about the price of oil. On the one hand, policy makers worry that low prices would discommode their friends from Abu Dhabi to Houston. On the other, they fret that high prices would slow recovery from the recession and anger voters who believe deep down that Gen. Norman Schwarzkopf was fighting to make the world safe for unleaded regular at $1.06 a gallon.</p>
        <p>None of this surprises M. A. Adelman, professor emeritus of economics at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and perennial gadfly to the energy establishment, who argues that Washington's views on oil have been muddled by a mix of "high policy and low politics." To Mr. Adelman, the right price to pay for oil is the lowest price that would assure an adequate supply for the foreseeable future. And that, he estimates, is a startlingly low $6 to $10 a barrel.</p>
        <p>If oil were sold in competitive markets, like cameras or computers, no single producer could hope to influence the price by raising or lowering output. Over the long term, the price would equal the cost to the highest-cost producer able to find a market for its crude.</p>
        <p>But plainly, the oil market is not competitive. Roughly one-quarter of the world's production -- and more than half the known, low-cost reserves -- comes from a handful of Persian Gulf states. Production decisions by Saudi Arabia (and, in the future, perhaps Iraq and Kuwait as well) affect the price of oil. That has not, however, stopped Mr. Adelman from calculating the "efficiency price" of oil, the price that would emerge from a competitive market.</p>
        <p>Over a period of weeks or months, he notes, it would pay producers to deliver oil as long as they could cover their operating costs. The competitive price floor, then, would be the price below which the world's high-cost producers -- notably Americans -- would be better off leaving the oil in the ground. And that price, Mr. Adelman reckons, may be as low as $5 a barrel and is certainly no more than $10.</p>
        <p>In the long run, of course, output from high-cost regions would be bound to decline unless producers believed prices would be sufficient to cover both operating costs and the cost of developing new reserves. But in a competitive market the loss could easily be filled by production from low-cost regions, notably the Persian Gulf. The OPEC nations alone, Mr. Adelman estimates, could profitably produce more than 60 million barrels a day through the 1990's (and perhaps beyond) at just $6 a barrel -- three times the quantity they currently deliver at one-third the current price.</p>
        <p>George Bush's new world order is not likely to include a blueprint for a competitive oil market. Mr. Bush, a former oilman, has never shown much enthusiasm for cheap fuel. Indeed, as Vice President, he pressed the Saudis to curb their inclination to prove their power over the cartel by driving the price toward the competitive floor. And in any case, nothing short of carving Saudi Arabia, Iraq and Iran into a dozen small oil-producing states and then applying America's antitrust laws to OPEC would do the trick. Nonetheless, the Adelman calculations do cast a different light on some current policy questions.</p>
        <p>His cost estimates for OPEC make clear that most of the cash going to oil exporters is pure windfall. Squeezing the cartel would thus not be likely to reduce the supply. And it is hard to think of such a policy as unfair, unless one happens to believe that Saudi Arabia, Norway and Alaska deserve to be rich at the expense of Brazil, Poland and Oregon.</p>
        <p>By the same token, the calculations suggest the magnitude of economic waste created by OPEC's continuing financial grab. High prices have created perverse incentives to drain America first: If Mr. Adelman's numbers are in the ball park, little or none of the billions of dollars spent annually on oil development in North America could be justified in purely economic terms.</p>
        <p>There are environmental implications here, too. Environmentalists correctly argue that the ecological damage from burning carbon fuels -- local air pollution, global warming -- ought to be factored into the price at the pump. What they rarely acknowledge, though, is that OPEC already assesses a "carbon tax" that triples the price of crude.</p>
        <p>Washington does have an oil policy. The only catch, it seems, is that the policy is made in Houston and Riyadh.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
