<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Grown-Ups; A Few Drinks, a Few Laughs, A Few Momentous Decisions</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week In Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="461636"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">APPLE, R W JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORBACHEV, MIKHAIL S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DF1539F932A15754C0A967958260" item-length="1602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Grown-Ups; A Few Drinks, a Few Laughs, A Few Momentous Decisions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R. W. APPLE Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">APPLE, R W JR</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY began 17 years ago at Rambouillet, just outside Paris, these annual summer gatherings, with a handful of national leaders gathered in relative obscurity to talk about economic problems. But they have turned into the annual meetings of the Board of Directors of the Planet Earth, where political and military questions often dominate, where reputations and alliances and friendships are formed, and where great policy questions are pushed up or down the international agenda. Which is, of course, why Mikhail S. Gorbachev wanted so badly to come here last week, even if it did expose him to derision as a Bolshevik beggar.</p>
        <p>Critics complain that the G-7 summit conferences have become too elephantine and elaborate (this year's spectacular was a mini-tattoo, complete with lasers, fireworks and bands, in the courtyard of Buckingham Palace). All the important decisions are made in advance, the critics say, and all the rough edges of real debate are smoothed away so the 3,000 or so journalists who now attend can concentrate on image-building for domestic politics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY began 17 years ago at Rambouillet, just outside Paris, these annual summer gatherings, with a handful of national leaders gathered in relative obscurity to talk about economic problems. But they have turned into the annual meetings of the Board of Directors of the Planet Earth, where political and military questions often dominate, where reputations and alliances and friendships are formed, and where great policy questions are pushed up or down the international agenda. Which is, of course, why Mikhail S. Gorbachev wanted so badly to come here last week, even if it did expose him to derision as a Bolshevik beggar.</p>
        <p>Critics complain that the G-7 summit conferences have become too elephantine and elaborate (this year's spectacular was a mini-tattoo, complete with lasers, fireworks and bands, in the courtyard of Buckingham Palace). All the important decisions are made in advance, the critics say, and all the rough edges of real debate are smoothed away so the 3,000 or so journalists who now attend can concentrate on image-building for domestic politics.</p>
        <p>But that misses the point. Much of what happens at these meetings may indeed be political theater, but theater is an integral part of all politics, from the staging of American presidential campaigns to debate in the House of Commons. It may sometimes mask for the moment what is actually going on, but it helps propel the story forward, toward climaxes and denouements that are very real.</p>
        <p>So it was here, where even the impasse that had prevented the completion of the momentous treaty to reduce strategic nuclear arms was finally broken. The debate about whether the West would provide massive, immediate financial assistance to the Soviet Union to ease its slide toward economic chaos and to help it begin the arduous march toward a free-market system had been decided weeks before the first outriders arrived at the summit. A Finely Tuned 'Maybe'</p>
        <p>But if there was to be "no blank check," as President Bush said, no "limousines full of cash," as one of the Russians put it, would the West fully commit itself to the process of change in the Soviet Union? Would the West co-sponsor the Westernization of Russia and the republics so tenuously attached to it, thereby committing its prestige and some of its treasure -- and to a degree its security interests -- to an enterprise as dubious, in terms of cost and consequence, as it was when Peter the Great set out to pull it off three centuries ago?</p>
        <p>Those questions were in fact debated here, and a decision of sorts was taken: not yes, not no, but maybe. Even before the summit meetings began, Mr. Gorbachev had of course won his much-coveted invitation to the ball, which was a major victory for him and a tribute to the military strength and the sheer size of the Soviet Union; no matter how much of a shambles its economy is in, the country bulks too large to be excluded any longer. Indeed, he was assured of a repeat performance next year in Munich, perhaps attending the main meeting instead of a postscript, and a separate annual meeting between the chairman of the G-7, who is the leader of each year's host country, and the leader of the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gorbachev did not get to dance with the fairy princess, although he did get invited to visit the Queen. Even President Francois Mitterrand of France, a staunch Gorbachev backer, said it was a bit too early to make it the G-8, though he said he strongly supported doing so a bit later; for now, we are left with a G-7 1/2 or perhaps a G-7 plus 1, which in itself represents a major advance for Mr. Gorbachev over last year, when the leaders discussed him and his country's fate in Houston without him.</p>
        <p>The full engagement of the West will have to wait until Mr. Gorbachev has given more evidence that he is making progress in implementing what Mr. Bush called his "irrevocable commitment" to reform. What the Soviet leader told the Western heads of government in a letter earlier in the month, and what he added in his rambling but by all accounts gripping presentation at Lancaster House, was not enough to persuade Mr. Bush and Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu of Japan to go beyond a parcel of good intentions wrapped in pretty words. They remained immovable even though Mr. Gorbachev came through with the final concession, whose shape is still unknown, that made it possible to conclude the negotiations on a strategic arms reduction treaty and schedule a Bush-Gorbachev meeting at the end of the month.</p>
        <p>As Gianni de Michelis, the Italian Foreign Minister, said as the struggle raged, it had to do with the brightness of the signal to be sent by the meeting. A more brilliant one was wanted by his delegation, by the French, by the Germans above all, with their fear of the consequences of social unrest in Russia for their eastern provinces, and even by the British, who on this question acted more like Europeans and less like members of an Anglo-Saxon entente. The Americans and Japanese, with Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d reportedly one of the most cautious voices, chose to concentrate not on Mr. Gorbachev's good intentions, however sincere, but on the difficulties he faces, and to go slow. A Murky Future</p>
        <p>The Western leaders hope that the process they have launched here will link the Soviet bureaucracy with those of the International Monetary Fund and the World Bank and the G-7 treasuries in a tutorial on the conditions and procedures for turning a failed command economy into a thriving market economy, and doing it in a country that has known nothing but the fiercest autocracy for a thousand years. That is what Prime Minister John Major of Britain, for whom the summit conference provided a valuable launching pad into world politics, meant when he said it might be seen in years to come as a major turning point.</p>
        <p>But it might not. It is by no means certain that Mr. Gorbachev has the ability, given the entrenched opposition of conservative elements, to make the kinds of changes that the international financial organizations have always endorsed for countries struggling to rebuild their economies and enter the system that links the developed nations. And even if he somehow persuades the army and the reactionary forces in the Communist Party to let him try, even if he overcomes the residual reflexes of the cold war, it is by no means certain that it will work. It is one thing to drag the Taiwanese economy into the 20th century or to reform an African or Latin American one, quite another to turn around anything as massive and clumsy as the Soviet economy. Nothing remotely like that has ever been attempted before.</p>
        <p>There was a lot of talk during this meeting about revitalizing the United Nations, which was the legacy of its newfound utility in dealing with the crisis in the Persian Gulf. But as things now stand the world organization can act boldly only when the interests of the five permanent members of the Security Council, including the Soviet Union and China, happen to coincide, and there is no reason to believe that this will now happen more or less automatically. Nor is there any sign of a concerted effort to rewrite the charter, eliminating or softening the veto, bringing Japan and Germany and perhaps India and Brazil into the inner circle, adapting in some way to the emergence of Europe as a more solid political entity. And NATO, for its part, is much too exclusive both in membership and in subject matter.</p>
        <p>So the G-7 1/2 is the nearest approximation available, at this moment of seemingly ceaseless flux, to an international tribunal where the powerful nations of the world can thrash out their differences, set change in motion or respond to it. A little of that got done this week, despite all the usual sweeping under the table and papering-over and double-talk. But the topic of reform in the Soviet Union and the argument about how to foster it and cope with it will be back on the agenda for many summers to come, long after the current actors have left the stage. A SCORECARD FROM LONDON</p>
        <p>Accomplishments -- The United States and Soviet Union announced agreement on a strategic arms reduction treaty and scheduled their own summit. -- The seven leading industrialized democracies heard President Mikhail S. Gorbachev outline plans to reform the Soviet economic system and request help; they promised technical aid and advice, but not much money, and invited Moscow to become an associate member of the International Monetary Fund and World Bank. -- The meeting's political declaration, among other things, called for a strengthened United Nations, pledged to maintain sanctions against Iraq and expressed support for efforts to start Israeli-Arab peace negotiations and for progress toward ending apartheid in South Africa. The meeting also supported founding a United Nations registry of arms sales to monitor the international trade in munitions. Unfinished Business -- The democracies failed to reach agreement on standards for allowable carbon dioxide emissions. European countries pressed for stricter standards; the United States resisted. -- The participants failed to resolve a dispute over farm subsidies that stands in the way of agreement on new rules for trade in farm goods, financial services, textiles and other areas -- the subject of the so-called Uruguay Round of trade talks, which have been under way for five years and which broke down in December. Americans are pressing Europeans to cut farm subsidies; the Europeans proposed a compromise, but agreement was not reached.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
