<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Television; Exploring the Beauty of Ancient Maps</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="434293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PUBLIC BROADCASTING SERVICE (PBS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, WALTER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SHAPE OF THE WORLD, THE (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D7103CF932A35757C0A967958260" item-length="576" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Television; Exploring the Beauty of Ancient Maps</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Take a helping of simple curiosity; add practical needs, political aspirations, religious faith and abiding superstitions, and prepare with mathematical calculation, careful observation, intuition and imagination, and you have the makings of what an ambitious new PBS series calls "The Shape of the World." The six-parter, which begins at 9 tonight on Channel 13 and at 10 on Channel 21, explores the history of map-making with elegance and intelligence.</p>
        <p>The opening hour, "Heaven on Earth," tells of the strivings to comprehend the globe on which humans found themselves long before they had the instruments to figure out where precisely they were. The centuries of effort are traced to ancient Egypt, whose rulers needed to fix boundaries of farms so they could collect taxes efficiently. That required some arithmetic, which was embellished with speculative leaps on why the sun appears and disappears every day. Was it the gods rolling it up and down, or a giant beetle?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Take a helping of simple curiosity; add practical needs, political aspirations, religious faith and abiding superstitions, and prepare with mathematical calculation, careful observation, intuition and imagination, and you have the makings of what an ambitious new PBS series calls "The Shape of the World." The six-parter, which begins at 9 tonight on Channel 13 and at 10 on Channel 21, explores the history of map-making with elegance and intelligence.</p>
        <p>The opening hour, "Heaven on Earth," tells of the strivings to comprehend the globe on which humans found themselves long before they had the instruments to figure out where precisely they were. The centuries of effort are traced to ancient Egypt, whose rulers needed to fix boundaries of farms so they could collect taxes efficiently. That required some arithmetic, which was embellished with speculative leaps on why the sun appears and disappears every day. Was it the gods rolling it up and down, or a giant beetle?</p>
        <p>Leave it to the Greeks to ask what tonight's polished narrator, the British actor Patrick Stewart, calls the right question: What was the world made of and what does it look like? Since it would be a long time before astronauts could fly high enough to see the shape of the world for themselves, Greek scientists had to use their ingenuity. Inspired by the varied pitches of strings of different lengths on a lyre, Pythagoras created an ideal universe, with the heavens moving around the earth: the harmony of the spheres.</p>
        <p>In the second century A.D. came the great "Geography" of Ptolemy, filled with errors (for centuries explorers went in search of the Mountains of the Moon, from which the Nile supposedly flowed) yet remarkable for bringing together odds and ends of information picked up by travelers and organizing them in ways that continue to serve map-makers today. The scientific spirit was at work.</p>
        <p>In capturing the beauty of the ancient maps, the program also suggests the beauty of the minds and dreams that went into them. Efforts in the medieval world to adjust what was reported of the world outside of Europe to biblical accounts might result in what is described here as a crazy cosmos: the centuries-long quest for the precise location of paradise is smiled away as "the greatest wild goose chase of Christendom." And yet creations like the 13th-century mappae mundi remain glowing expressions of mankind's striving to understand as well as to believe.</p>
        <p>The history is delivered with a light touch and enlivened with curiosities, such as the efforts as late as the 19th century by Charles Gordon, a Christian fundamentalist and a surveyor as well as a famous British general, to track down the Garden of Eden. Tonight's hour ends with the rediscovery, in Constantinople, of Ptolemy's "Geography" and the revival of classical learning, which opened the way to the explorations of the Renaissance that brought back more accurate maps from once fabled lands.</p>
        <p>It's a rich story, admirably told, of people looking ever outward to satisfy inner cravings. Even when they produced maps that placed the center of the universe in Jerusalem, their minds were ranging into the mysterious beyond. The last program emphasizes that maps are helping defend the shape of the world from all manner of perils, including floods, earthquakes and global warming, even as they have helped guard against dangers and take advantage of opportunities down the millennia.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
