<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Film; Ulcers and the Other Prices Of Being a Pint-Sized Prodigy</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="479368"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CANBY, VINCENT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FOSTER, JODIE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LITTLE MAN TATE (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEED7133EF93AA35753C1A967958260" item-length="1045" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Film; Ulcers and the Other Prices Of Being a Pint-Sized Prodigy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT CANBY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CANBY, VINCENT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fred Tate (Adam Hann-Byrd) is like any other 7-year-old. He's not especially handsome but, aside from his introspective manner, he is the kind of kid you might see in a television commercial for a ghastly new multi-colored breakfast cereal. His height is average; his face is still fleshed with baby fat.</p>
        <p>His mind, though, is something else. It's moving at the speed of light.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fred Tate (Adam Hann-Byrd) is like any other 7-year-old. He's not especially handsome but, aside from his introspective manner, he is the kind of kid you might see in a television commercial for a ghastly new multi-colored breakfast cereal. His height is average; his face is still fleshed with baby fat.</p>
        <p>His mind, though, is something else. It's moving at the speed of light.</p>
        <p>Fred paints in both oils and watercolors and, at the moment, is going through a Picasso-influenced Cubist period. He plays the piano at what is said to be competition level. He takes telephones apart, not to fix them but to make them work more efficiently.  As a birthday present for his mother, Dede (Jodie Foster), he writes an opera.</p>
        <p>Taking the story of Dede, a militantly independent, unmarried mother, a waitress who once wanted to be a dancer, and Fred, a child prodigy hanging onto sanity as if it were a tiger's tail, Ms. Foster makes a terrifically self-assured debut as a motion-picture director with "Little Man Tate."</p>
        <p>The material is congenial for someone as special as she is. The actress has grown up in the adult world of movies, having been first nominated for an Oscar in 1976 for "Taxi Driver," made when she was 13. Later the same year she played a femme fatale in "Bugsy Malone."</p>
        <p>By the time she won her Oscar in 1989 for "The Accused," she had been in the business longer than most of the older people she was working with. It's now apparent that she also knows exactly what she's doing behind the camera. "Little Man Tate" is a small-scale, very engaging comedy that dares to suggest that intelligence, so often mocked in movies, can also be celebrated.</p>
        <p>Along with his remarkable gifts, Fred has his problems, ulcers among them. When he sees a tabloid headline, "Mother Earth Meltdown," he lets out an involuntary "Oh, my God," which is both funny and, in light of his age, scary. In addition to the greenhouse effect, Fred worries about environmental pollution and the proliferation of nuclear arms.</p>
        <p>He would also like to have someone to eat lunch with.</p>
        <p>Fred is not exactly the most popular kid in his class. You don't make friends by knowing all the answers, either with the other students or with the teacher. The grotesquely cheerful Miss Nimvel (Celia Weston) at first thinks he's retarded, then suggests he might be able to skip elementary school entirely.</p>
        <p>"Little Man Tate" is about the battle for Fred's future. On one side is the protective, tough-talking Dede, who doesn't want Fred turned into an exploited pint-sized freak. She tries to ignore his brilliance, while feeling her own increasing inadequacy in dealing with him.</p>
        <p>On the other side is Jane Grierson (Dianne Wiest), a former child prodigy herself, an adult who knows the problems first-hand and who is now an educator of such children. She's still brilliant, but almost completely out of touch with real life.</p>
        <p>When boiled down to this central conflict, and when seen in light of its resolution, "Little Man Tate" is a lot more conventional than its characters would seem to demand. The same story might well have been turned into a Movie of the Week.</p>
        <p>Yet, as directed by Ms. Foster, the film has a kind of purity of purpose and control that is very rare in mass-market movies. It avoids a lot of sentimental nonsense. It is also sparely (and well-) written by Scott Frank, the man who wrote the screenplay for Kenneth Branagh's "Dead Again."</p>
        <p>"Little Man Tate" has a good deal of fun at the expense of "The Odyssey of the Mind," a sort of cross-country "mental Olympics" in which Fred participates at Jane Grierson's request. These are a series of contests at which gifted children display their skills to the amazement of academe.  At one point the kids are seen trying the case of Goldilocks, charged with breaking and entering.</p>
        <p>The movie never explores the biological roots of such special gifts, though it understands that terrible prices may have to be paid by the children themselves. This awareness gives the film its tension.</p>
        <p>There is tension, too, in the principal women's roles. Though Ms. Wiest's Jane Grierson is initially an object of ridicule, she also knows what she's talking about in her criticism of Dede's handling of Fred.</p>
        <p>Ms. Foster's Dede is an even more complicated character, mostly for everything that is left unexplained.  Fred's father is never identified.  That, says Dede, is something she doesn't talk about. It's as if she had conceived through the cooperation of an anonymous sperm donor.</p>
        <p>Whatever the explanation, Dede is a determinedly, obsessively free spirit, fierce in her relations with everyone except Fred. She seems to be just the kind of woman who might well produce a child as singular in his way as she is in hers.</p>
        <p>Ms. Foster is particularly good in her handling of young Mr. Hann-Byrd. This is not the standard American movie's kid performance. There is never that sinking feeling that he's trying to act, to give a performance as the word is understood by adult actors. Instead, he responds to the people and events around, remaining always a figure of some mystery.</p>
        <p>Other notable members of the cast are Harry Connick Jr., as the university student who teaches Fred how to play pool; Josh Mostel, as Fred's professor of quantum physics, and George Plimpton, who appears briefly as a fatuous host of a television talk show.</p>
        <p>"Little Man Tate" is a modest movie in the best sense. Its head is not stuffed with half-baked ambitions that cannot be realized. Like Dede, it is cool, bright, always aware of its limitations and, from time to time, unexpectedly rewarding in its turn of mind.</p>
        <p>"Little Man Tate," which has been rated PG (Parental guidance suggested), has some vulgar language. Little Man Tate Directed by Jodie Foster; written by Scott Frank; director of photography, Mike Southon; edited by Lynzee Klingman; music by Mark Isham; production designer, Jon Hutman; produced by Scott Rudin and Peggy Rajski; released by Orion Pictures Corporation. Running time: 99 minutes. This film is rated PG. Dede Tate . . . Jodie Foster Jane Grierson . . . Dianne Wiest Eddie . . . Harry Connick Jr. Garth . . . David Pierce Gina . . . Debi Mazar Damon Wells . . . P. J. Ochlan Fred Tate . . . Adam Hann-Byrd</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
