<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Defying the Wisdom for '92, Ex-Senator Tsongas Dives In</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="436364"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TONER, ROBIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TSONGAS, PAUL E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DA173AF933A25757C0A967958260" item-length="923" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Defying the Wisdom for '92, Ex-Senator Tsongas Dives In</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN TONER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TONER, ROBIN</byline>
      <dateline>LOWELL, Mass., April 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The heavyweights in the Democratic Party are temporizing, stalling, waiting for the odds to improve before making any commitment to enter the 1992 Presidential campaign. Paul E. Tsongas, the former Senator from Massachusetts, has simply plunged in, calmly defying the collective wisdom of the Capital Beltway.</p>
        <p>He knows that after the party's experience with Michael S. Dukakis, the 1988 Democratic nominee, a campaign by another Greek-American liberal from Massachusetts is "fodder for Jay Leno and 'Saturday Night Live,' " as Mr. Tsongas puts it. He knows that the view of much of Washington is that President Bush is all but unbeatable and would certainly not be beatable by someone off the national political scene since 1984, when Mr. Tsongas left the Senate with a diagnosis of cancer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The heavyweights in the Democratic Party are temporizing, stalling, waiting for the odds to improve before making any commitment to enter the 1992 Presidential campaign. Paul E. Tsongas, the former Senator from Massachusetts, has simply plunged in, calmly defying the collective wisdom of the Capital Beltway.</p>
        <p>He knows that after the party's experience with Michael S. Dukakis, the 1988 Democratic nominee, a campaign by another Greek-American liberal from Massachusetts is "fodder for Jay Leno and 'Saturday Night Live,' " as Mr. Tsongas puts it. He knows that the view of much of Washington is that President Bush is all but unbeatable and would certainly not be beatable by someone off the national political scene since 1984, when Mr. Tsongas left the Senate with a diagnosis of cancer.</p>
        <p>He also knows that every time he has a chest cold, as he does now, someone will probably ask him about his health, five years after he underwent a successful bone marrow transplant for the treatment of lymphoma.</p>
        <p>Paul Tsongas, now 50 years old, knows all these things, talks about them blithely on the veranda of his gracious old hilltop home here in Lowell -- and remains convinced that he wants to run.</p>
        <p>He was struggling on this gentle morning with a speech he would deliver later in the week to the National Press Club in Washington. "It's hard to make people understand how I think these days," he said.</p>
        <p>Were he thinking today as he did back in his days as an ambitious young lawmaker who considered himself a potential Presidential contender, he might make the same calculated decision that many Democrats are now making: "Decide that it's not probable," he said, "and save myself for '96."</p>
        <p>But he is no longer a 33-year-old freshman Congressman or a 37-year-old freshman Senator. His battle with cancer, and six years working as a lawyer and businessman, have changed him, Mr. Tsongas said. He is convinced that the nation faces a serious economic decline and that neither Democrats nor Republicans are addressing it as they should. He wanted to get his ideas out. And so he runs. 'Pro-Business Liberal'</p>
        <p>Mr. Tsongas is often termed a "pro-business liberal," and he does not object to the description. His campaign white paper, "A Call to Economic Arms," paints a grim picture of "America's manufacturing base under attack," buffeted by outmoded policies and intensifying foreign competition. "Both political parties," the paper argues, "are going to have to abandon the rusty core elements of their economic philosophies and head off in new directions."</p>
        <p>Republicans, he asserts, must accept the notion that the United States needs an industrial policy in which the Federal Government is actively involved in helping businesses develop new technologies. "American companies need the U.S. Government as a full partner if they are to have any hope of competing internationally," Mr. Tsongas wrote.</p>
        <p>Democrats, Mr. Tsongas said, must reject the politics of "class warfare" and help spur economic growth through measures like a carefully aimed cut in the tax on capital gains. "Class warfare is certainly good politics," he wrote, "but it's good politics at the expense of the nation's industrial base."</p>
        <p>Mr. Tsongas also breaks with the orthodoxy of many Democrats by supporting nuclear power as a means of easing the country's dependence on fossil fuels, a stance that he adopted several years ago but that he says is all the more urgent now, given the furor over global warming.</p>
        <p>The Tsongas campaign has printed 40,000 copies of "A Call to Economic Arms," and Mr. Tsongas said he is cheered by the response. "I know the usual political analysis is that Bush is unbeatable and we should just have a coronation and skip the election, but that's Washington," he said. "Outside, people really know that the ground is trembling."</p>
        <p>This is not a mega-campaign. Its first major fund-raising event will be Thursday night in Boston; Dennis Kanin, Mr. Tsongas's law partner and longtime political adviser, said the campaign expected to raise $250,000 that night. The Tsongas campaign hired a press secretary this week, its first paid staff member, and will open a headquarters in Boston shortly. Mr. Tsongas is expected to officially announce his candidacy on April 30, with appearances in Lowell, Manchester, N.H., and Des Moines.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tsongas said he had sought and had received a go-ahead from his physicians before deciding to make the race. Dr. Tak Takvorian, a senior staff physician at Dana-Farber Cancer Institute and Mr. Tsongas's physician, said the candidate had shown no evidence of the disease since he underwent the bone marrow transplant in 1986. 'Could Not Be Better'</p>
        <p>Mr. Tsongas, who has three daughters with his wife, Nicola, a lawyer, said, "On a personal level, our life could not be better than it is now."</p>
        <p>He said he was urged to enter the race for governor of Massachusetts last year, but, "It just wasn't me." He said he wanted his ideas on national economic policy to be heard; some Democrats, including the poll taker Geoffrey Garin, suggest that he could play a role similar to that played by Bruce Babbitt, the former Governor of Arizona, in 1988: raising ideas, challenging orthodoxy.</p>
        <p>"But the fact of the matter is, nobody's turned that into a successful model yet for winning the nomination," Mr. Garin said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tsongas said, with a smile, that he is ready to press on. "Besides," he said after outlining the rationale for his candidacy, "it's also fun. There's a magic to it."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
