<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.P.A. Urging Electricity Efficiency</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="415687"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT BULBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY EFFICIENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIGHTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light Bulbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lighting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDF113CF935A25752C0A967958260" item-length="728" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.P.A. Urging Electricity Efficiency</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a rare Federal venture into electricity efficiency, the Environmental Protection Agency began a campaign yesterday to convince the nation's 1,000 largest businesses that they can reduce pollution, and increase profits, by buying better lights.</p>
        <p>The voluntary program will seek to persuade chief executives that investments in more efficient lighting in offices, stores and factories will return bigger profits than any other use of the money, while providing better working conditions and good public relations. The agency even plans to hand out "environmental hero" awards to executives who take part in the program, called Green Lights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a rare Federal venture into electricity efficiency, the Environmental Protection Agency began a campaign yesterday to convince the nation's 1,000 largest businesses that they can reduce pollution, and increase profits, by buying better lights.</p>
        <p>The voluntary program will seek to persuade chief executives that investments in more efficient lighting in offices, stores and factories will return bigger profits than any other use of the money, while providing better working conditions and good public relations. The agency even plans to hand out "environmental hero" awards to executives who take part in the program, called Green Lights.</p>
        <p>If all businesses adopted commonly available high-efficiency lighting techniques, the agency said that about 11 percent of all the electricity used in this country would be saved and costs would drop by $18.6 billion a year. It also said, the national output of sulfur dioxide, the prime cause of acid rain, would fall 7 percent, and output of carbon dioxide, which is believed to cause global climate change, would fall 5 percent. A Different Approach</p>
        <p>"This is a completely different way of approaching environmental problems," John S. Hoffman, director of the Global Change Division of the Environmental Protection Agency, said in an interview. When the Government wants to clean up the air, he said, it usually orders car makers to install catalytic converters or utilities to build scrubbers for smokestacks.</p>
        <p>The idea of saving money through efficiency has largely been a province of the utilities and the states that regulate them, and while many utilities have reported progress, most say they are only scratching the surface.</p>
        <p>Last week, the New York Power Authority, the largest state-owned power agency, announced a $50 million program to improve the efficiency of its electricity customers, which are other government agencies and nonprofit institutions.</p>
        <p>For the utilities, the goal has been to avoid having to build multibillion-dollar power plants -- keeping a growing customer population satisfied with a fixed amount of electricity -- by squeezing more light, more heat and more mechanical power from each kilowatt-hour. State utility commissions, eager to avoid the rate increases that often come with new power plants, have been prodding the utilities to do more, and concern over the environment has been cited as a side benefit.  Raising Energy Efficiency</p>
        <p>The Federal Government, which does not regulate utilities at the retail level, has focused its energy attention elsewhere. Washington's biggest efficiency push came in the last decade in cars, with new rules forcing higher gasoline mileage. The Department of Energy's biggest effort in the electric field has been the promotion of nuclear power. And after years of reluctantance, the Reagan White House agreed to a Congressional initiative that set standards raising the efficiency of new consumer appliances like refrigerators. But lighting was largely ignored.</p>
        <p>Since the Iraq invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2, the Department of Energy has been on a short-term campaign to save energy, especially gasoline, led by James D. Watkins, the Energy Secretary.  'Not Tokenism'</p>
        <p>Charles Komanoff, an efficiency consultant based in New York, said in an interview, "This is genuine efficiency, not tokenism."</p>
        <p>But he added that those who need to improve efficiency the most and who will have the most trouble doing it are not the country's thousand largest corporations, but small businesses, nonprofit groups and individuals. The E.P.A. plan is to focus on big companies first, because they use the most power.</p>
        <p>The technologies the E.P.A. is recommending include compact fluorescent lights, which screw into a standard socket but provide four times the efficiency; improved fluorescent tubes that give substantially more light; electronic ballasts, which do the same work as conventional magnetic ballasts in controlling the flow of electricity to fluorescent tubes but use only half the power and eliminate hum and flicker, and control devices that automatically shut off lights in a vacant room, or dim and brighten them to balance the amount of light entering through windows.</p>
        <p>Green Lights has already signed up 24 corporations, including Bell Atlantic, Citicorp, Johnson &amp; Johnson, Phillips Petroleum and Whirlpool.</p>
        <p>COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
