<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; Greenhouse Gamblers</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="453643"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL DEFENSE FUND</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ECONOMIC SCENE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D61438F93AA25755C0A967958260" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; Greenhouse Gamblers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF the experts don't really know how fast the atmosphere is warming or what the consequences of warming could be, what should Washington do to slow it down? To the Environmental Defense Fund, the answer seems obvious: Buy some insurance against catastrophe, and buy it as cheaply as possible.</p>
        <p>The defense fund wants electric utilities to reduce emissions of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases at least to the extent that their new plants are adding them. And it wants Uncle Sam to keep the cost down by creating a market for greenhouse gas "offsets," allowing a utility in, say, Virginia or Texas to meet its obligation by paying to plant trees in Costa Rica or to trap methane from garbage dumps in Ohio.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF the experts don't really know how fast the atmosphere is warming or what the consequences of warming could be, what should Washington do to slow it down? To the Environmental Defense Fund, the answer seems obvious: Buy some insurance against catastrophe, and buy it as cheaply as possible.</p>
        <p>The defense fund wants electric utilities to reduce emissions of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases at least to the extent that their new plants are adding them. And it wants Uncle Sam to keep the cost down by creating a market for greenhouse gas "offsets," allowing a utility in, say, Virginia or Texas to meet its obligation by paying to plant trees in Costa Rica or to trap methane from garbage dumps in Ohio.</p>
        <p>The plan is bound to receive a mixed reception in the White House. President Bush's economists championed a similar market-based plan for coping with acid rain, which is the centerpiece of last year's amendments to the Clean Air Act. But Administration skeptics, notably John Sununu, have yet to concede that anyone should be asked to spend money to solve an environmental problem that may never materialize.</p>
        <p>Commercial power plants emitting 100,000 tons of carbon annually are by no means the only important sources of greenhouse gases. But they are prime targets for reformers because their emissions are relatively easy to monitor, and their pollution-control costs can be passed on to a broad base of customers.</p>
        <p>The bill introduced yesterday by two Democratic Congressmen, Jim Cooper of Tennessee and Mike Synar of Oklahoma, would require utilities to save a ton of carbon (or its equivalent in other greenhouse gases) for every additional ton they pump into the air. Renovated plants would have to meet the same requirement after 1995. Plants might meet the standard by switching from coal to natural gas, which produces more watts per pound of carbon emitted, or by encouraging consumers to conserve energy. But the architects of the plan hope and expect utilities to go farther afield.</p>
        <p>Dan Dudek, an Environmental Defense Fund economist, thinks offsets could be harvested at very low cost from dozens of sources. For example, huge amounts of methane, a far more potent greenhouse gas than carbon dioxide, are currently vented from coal mines. And most of the chlorofluorocarbon gases, the most destructive of all greenhouse chemicals, are now lost when refrigerators and air-conditioners are scrapped.</p>
        <p>Utilities might not wish to collect waste gases from mines or abandoned appliances. But they certainly could pay others to do the collecting. And if there were an active market for offsets, they could simply buy as many tons as they needed, the way General Mills buys wheat on the commodity exchanges.</p>
        <p>The oldest objection to markets for pollution offsets -- that sinners should not be permitted to buy indulgences -- no longer carries much weight among economically sophisticated environmentalists. But other qualms are not so easily dismissed.</p>
        <p>One is cost. Almost everyone agrees that offsets represent the cheapest and least intrusive way to buy insurance against greenhouse warming. But there is wide disagreement over how cheap the insurance would be.</p>
        <p>Drawing on a report published last month by the National Academy of Sciences, Mr. Dudek estimates that utilities could meet the bill's requirements through the year 2005 at a cost of $10 billion to $20 billion. Bush Administration economists fear the academy is too optimistic. They doubt, for example, that higher-mileage cars would pay for themselves in savings at the pump.</p>
        <p>But the most fundamental objection is the most imponderable: How much should be spent on a greenhouse solution before it is certain there is a greenhouse problem? The White House is in no mood to purchase a $10 billion o $20 billion insurance policy on the strength of current science. It is holding out for a far more cautious "no regrets" policy, curbing greenhouse gases only to the extent that the limits can be justified on other grounds. The prime target: chlorofluorocarbons, which are also the chief culprits in thinning the atmosphere's protective layer of ozone.</p>
        <p>President Bush surely has the muscle to block legislation this year. But with Europe pressing for a greenhouse fix, and big business afraid to be caught on the politically incorrect side of the debate, delay is becoming less tenable.</p>
        <p>Sooner or later -- probably sooner -- Washington is likely to leap into the unknown. When it does, an offsets plan is going to look better to the free marketers in the White House than heavy taxes on carbon emissions or the direct regulation of polluters.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
