<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Volcano's Eruption in Philippines May Counteract Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="456475"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VOLCANOES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MOUNT PINATUBO (PHILIPPINES)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PHILIPPINES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Philippines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Philippines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DB153EF933A05755C0A967958260" item-length="1193" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Volcano's Eruption in Philippines May Counteract Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A global warming trend that began in the 1980's and has continued into 1991 could be offset over the next few years by atmospheric cooling caused by the eruption this month of the Mount Pinatubo volcano in the Philippines, scientists say.</p>
        <p>The major factor at work in the climatic effect is not the familiar dust cloud, but a chemical reaction. Volcanic eruptions spew out vast quantities of sulfur dioxide gas that later combine with water to form tiny supercooled droplets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A global warming trend that began in the 1980's and has continued into 1991 could be offset over the next few years by atmospheric cooling caused by the eruption this month of the Mount Pinatubo volcano in the Philippines, scientists say.</p>
        <p>The major factor at work in the climatic effect is not the familiar dust cloud, but a chemical reaction. Volcanic eruptions spew out vast quantities of sulfur dioxide gas that later combine with water to form tiny supercooled droplets.</p>
        <p>The droplets constitute a long-lasting global haze that reflects and scatters sunlight, causing the earth to cool. This last occurred in 1982, when haze from the eruption of El Chichon volcano in Mexico depressed global temperatures for about four years before a warming trend that began around 1980 resumed in late 1986.  Decline Seen for Several Years</p>
        <p>The cloud of sulfur dioxide from the June 15 eruption in the Philippines is roughly twice as large as that of El Chichon, scientists have now determined, making Mount Pinatubo perhaps the biggest eruption of the 20th century.</p>
        <p>Experts believe that the haze it is producing could lower the average global temperature by more than half a degree Fahrenheit for three or four years, countering the global warming. A number of scientists expect the warming of the last few years to resume after the mid-1990's, once the haze disperses.</p>
        <p>An average global cooling of half a degree would scarcely be noticed by people on the street. But it is important in the context of the global warming problem, and it could reduce, for a time, the odds in favor of milder winters and hotter summers.</p>
        <p>Many scientists expect that by the end of the next century the earth's temperature will rise 2 to 9 degrees above a global average that is now just shy of 60 degrees. A warming in the high end of that range would bring catastrophic disruptions in climate, ecology and agriculture.</p>
        <p>Some climatologists say the pronounced warming that began about a decade ago is caused by an increase in heat-trapping gases like carbon dioxide that are being poured into the atmosphere by industries and motor vehicles. Others say it is too soon to tell whether the warming is caused by the gases or by natural variabilities.</p>
        <p>But they agree that Mount Pinatubo promises to change the picture substantially at a time when temperatures have been at or near record levels, both globally and in many parts of the United States.</p>
        <p>Through May, 1991 has been one of the world's warmest years since people began keeping records more than a century ago. Now, "it looks like there will be some cooling for the next few years," said Dr. Alan Robock if the University of Maryland, a meteorologist specializing in volcanoes and climate.</p>
        <p>But there is an added complication: Other scientists predict that sea surface temperatures in the tropical Eastern Pacific will increase some time in the fourth quarter of this year in an event that has come to be known as El Nino. Powerful westward-blowing trade winds weaken, allowing warm water to slosh back eastward from the Western Pacific.</p>
        <p>This shift produces widespread changes in climate and weather; climatologists believe that El Nino caused global temperatures to rise in 1983, overriding the cooling brought about by El Chichon's eruption. They also believe that the coming El Nino, even though it is expected to be milder than the one in 1982-83, may do the same for a few months next year, after which cooling induced by the Philippine eruption is expected to resume.</p>
        <p>There is a large element of uncertainty in all this, since El Nino might not develop as scientists expect, and since they have only begun to measure the huge cloud of sulfur dioxide from the volcano. Its leading edge raced westward through the stratosphere across the Atlantic Ocean last week, and it was expected to reach the southern United States this weekend.</p>
        <p>Its arrival will be announced, scientists say, by unusually spectacular sunsets, produced by the same light scattering that causes atmospheric cooling.</p>
        <p>Using sensors aboard satellites, scientists have determined that the 15-million-ton sulfur dioxide cloud from Mount Pinatubo is about twice the size of the one emitted by El Chichon, said Dr. Arlin J. Krueger, an atmospheric physicist at the National Aeronautics and Space Administration's Goddard Spaceflight Center at Greenbelt, Md.</p>
        <p>Dr. M. Patrick McCormick, an atmospheric scientist at the NASA Langley Research Center at Hampton, Va., who analyzes volcanic clouds, said the Mount Pinatubo eruption "could be the biggest of the century."</p>
        <p>The cloud from Mount Pinatubo stretches across a latitude band ranging from 15 degrees to 25 degrees, said Mike Matson, an interpreter of satellite images at the National Atmospheric and Oceanic Administration site at Camp Strings, Md. By contrast, he said, El Chichon's cloud covered 5 degrees in its initial path around the globe.</p>
        <p>By October or November, Dr. McCormick said, "it'll go global." The light-scattering droplets "will be around a long time," he said, some of them lasting 8 to 10 years. But they gradually fall to earth, and they do not affect climate that long. Story Told in Temperatures</p>
        <p>The record of average global temperature from the earth's surface to an altitude of four miles, as measured by satellite instruments from 1979 to the present, neatly dovetails with El Chichon's eruption and El Nino of 1982-83. In 1980 and 1981, temperatures were above an average measured from 1982 through 1990. In 1982, the year of El Chichon's eruption, there was a sharp drop below the average. In 1983, immediately after El Nino, there was a sharp rise above average.</p>
        <p>But the next three years, with El Chichon's haze still permeating the atmosphere, temperatures were below average. Then there was another sharp rise, followed in 1989 by a sharp drop linked to unusually low sea-surface temperatures caused by the event known as La Nina, a shift in ocean waters that represents the flip side of El Nino in a continuing climatic oscillation. Then the warming resumed.</p>
        <p>This pattern is paralleled by data from other sets of global temperature measurements, some made at the surface of the earth and some from balloons in the atmosphere, the type that have been made over the last century. Those showed 1990 to be the warmest year on record globally, with an average for the year of nearly 60 degrees.</p>
        <p>But the satellite data, supplied by Roy Spencer of the NASA Marshall Space Flight Center at Huntsville, Ala., diverged from the other figures. The satellite data showed 1990 as the fourth warmest year in the 12 years of satellite measurements, after 1987, 1988 and 1980. The variation in findings is attributable to different methods of measurement and sets of data.</p>
        <p>Dr. James E. Hansen of the NASA Goddard Institute for Space Studies in New York, who has consistently forecast that global warming induced by emissions of heat-trapping gases will become apparent in the 1990's, said that even with the cool period that is likely to result from the Philippine eruption the 1990's were still likely to be warmer, as a whole, than the 1980's.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
