<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="442575"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5D61531F931A35756C0A967958260" item-length="1183" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-19</p>
        <p>The security zone in northern Iraq is scheduled to be expanded roughly 70 miles at dawn to enable Kurdish refugees in remote mountain camps to join the return home.  Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-19</p>
        <p>The security zone in northern Iraq is scheduled to be expanded roughly 70 miles at dawn to enable Kurdish refugees in remote mountain camps to join the return home.  Page A1</p>
        <p>Iraq should pay for the relief effort to help Kurdish refugees, the Administration said. It is seeking to link approval of resumed Iraqi oil exports to such payments. A16</p>
        <p>Book says Powell voiced doubts on strategy against Iraq A16</p>
        <p>For Iraqis, a slow return to normality A16</p>
        <p>15 top journalists see Cheney and object to gulf war curbs A17</p>
        <p>Lebanese troops were deployed in areas south, east and north of the capital, taking another big step toward reuniting Muslim and Christian parts of a country that was partitioned by civil war. A3</p>
        <p>Kemp sees Ariel Sharon, despite State Department resistance A14</p>
        <p>A cease-fire was agreed to in Angola by the leftist Government and United States-backed rebels after 16 years of civil war. They also agreed to hold the nation's first free election in the second half of 1992. A1</p>
        <p>Pretoria shifting attention to local apartheid A11</p>
        <p>U.S. team seeking exodus of Ethiopian Jews A15 The lives of ordinary Cambodians remain bleak, and their future offers little promise. A U.N. plan to unite the land's factions is faltering on 20 years of hatred and intrigue. A1</p>
        <p>Seoul aches from 3d day of protests and tear gas A19</p>
        <p>News analysis: China-U.S. ties: frosty to icy A13</p>
        <p>The death toll in Bangladesh wrought by a devastating cyclone is about 3,000, the Government confirmed, but it is expected to climb sharply as communications are restored to affected areas. A9</p>
        <p>The May Day rally on Red Square, formerly the premier Communist rite of spring, was a joyless event, as President Gorbachev listened stoically to litanies of woe and accusations of misrule. A3</p>
        <p>Earthquake buries Soviet village, killing all A8</p>
        <p>The dream of a united Ireland is one that many residents in the southern Republic say they could postpone if it would help bring about an internal political settlement in British-controlled Northern Ireland. A5</p>
        <p>Britain moving to allow trials of suspected Nazis A6</p>
        <p>London Journal: Sharpton arrives, and makes waves A4</p>
        <p>Door opens a crack for Colombia's Indians A10  National A20-23, B10-12</p>
        <p>Prime lending rates were reduced by most of the nation's largest banks to 8 1/2 percent, from 9 percent, a move that may help reduce borrowing costs for small businesses and consumers, and stimulate the economy. A1</p>
        <p>Banking on a comeback in Boston D1</p>
        <p>General Dynamics said it will cut at least 27,000 jobs from its 90,000-person work force over four years, in another stark illustration of the painful shrinkage facing the military contracting industry. D1</p>
        <p>News analysis: Health care may pose the supreme political test of the 1990's for Congress. Many are calling for change; many agree on the goals. But there is still no consensus on how to restructure the system. A1</p>
        <p>Report lists 161 hospitals with high death rates B11</p>
        <p>Hospitals cited in New York City B11</p>
        <p>A muscular dystrophy experiment will take place amid controversy over whether it is ethical and effective. The treatment involves the injection of normal muscle cells into a boy's diseased leg muscles.  B10</p>
        <p>Satellite problems delay "star wars" shuttle test B10</p>
        <p>NASA says it is time to build the space station B10</p>
        <p>Ragu agrees to take "fresh" off sauce labels A23</p>
        <p>Shenandoah National Park is being threatened by air pollution that is obscuring its vistas and, in the form of acid rain, is poisoning its trout streams and killing its forests. A20</p>
        <p>The nuclear plant fire and explosion in Maine occurred while the plant's operators were running the reactor at record power levels, plant officials said. A20</p>
        <p>Two killed and at least 120 hurt in Louisiana explosion A21</p>
        <p>The Brady bill is being threatened by a procedural dispute with the House leadership, the measure's sponsor said. The bill would impose a seven-day waiting period on handgun purchases. A22</p>
        <p>Washington Talk: Split on gun bill reflects geography A22</p>
        <p>Military jet used for a Quayle trip A21  Regional B1-8</p>
        <p>A plan for the new political map of New York City was released. Under it, black or Hispanic New Yorkers might win as many as a third of the seats on the City Council.  A1</p>
        <p>John Santucci plans to retire from the Queens District Attorney post in June, after 14 years in which he went from relative obscurity to almost constant controversy. A1</p>
        <p>A prosecutor whose reach seldom left Queens B2</p>
        <p>Woman and son, 7, die in leap B2</p>
        <p>44 percent of the local school budgets were rejected by New Jersey voters in one of the most politicized school elections in years. B1</p>
        <p>New York City and other localities could default on payments for their borrowing if the state's budget impasse lasts through June, Governor Cuomo said in a strident attack on the Legislature. B1</p>
        <p>Liberal Party is expected to back Abrams for Senate B3</p>
        <p>Tenants are beginning to fume as the building workers' strike is starting to affect them in dozens of ways, from the simply annoying to the serious. The state of the negotiations to end the strike is unclear. B1</p>
        <p>Charity work by the Japanese living in America, from fund-raising to renovating shelters, is growing as they begin to rethink their relationship with this nation, its people and its problems. B1</p>
        <p>Clinton Hill Journal: Towering broken angel fulfills a dream B3</p>
        <p>Bloomingdale's is closing store in Queens B4  Business Digest D1  The Home Section</p>
        <p>And plant by the light of. . . .  C1</p>
        <p>Great idea for baby-sitters: clubs C1</p>
        <p>Making a small studio seem bigger C1</p>
        <p>Parent &amp; Child C2</p>
        <p>Design Notebook C10</p>
        <p>A Gardener's World C11</p>
        <p>A quilt festival at Pier 92 C12  Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>Brooklyn Academy plans festival despite money fears C17</p>
        <p>Art auction fever breaksC17</p>
        <p>Networks may revert to cliches, after all C17</p>
        <p>Theater: "The Will Rogers Follies" C17</p>
        <p>Dance: Jose Limon troupe C19</p>
        <p>Word and Image: Novel with a werewolf C22</p>
        <p>Home video C24  Health Page B14</p>
        <p>Therapists say a single session may be enough  Obituaries B15</p>
        <p>Frank N. Ikard, ex-Congressman and oil lobbyist Sports B16-22</p>
        <p>Baseball: Ryan pitches 7th no- hitter B17</p>
        <p>Henderson does it B17</p>
        <p>Yanks lose to A's again B19</p>
        <p>Viola and Mets lose, 8-7 B19</p>
        <p>Basketball: MacLeod going to Notre Dame B17</p>
        <p>Does Knick future include Ewing?  B22</p>
        <p>Celtics take 2-1 lead against Pacers B22</p>
        <p>Column: Anderson on Pat Riley B17</p>
        <p>Hockey: Bruins defeat Penguins B23</p>
        <p>Horse Racing: Strike the Gold takes a stroll B20</p>
        <p>Soccer: Many applicants for World Cup sites B24  Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials A24</p>
        <p>Cowering before medical costs</p>
        <p>City's loss is Albany's gain</p>
        <p>Still a Wonderful Town</p>
        <p>Karl E. Meyer: Kurds</p>
        <p>Letters A24</p>
        <p>Anna Quindlen: The human condition A25</p>
        <p>William Safire: Going after them A25</p>
        <p>Mario M. Cuomo: Hollow rhetoric from the unions A25</p>
        <p>Hans A. Bethe: Chernobyl -- it can't happen here A25</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
