<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Simple, Sober Town</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19910310T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="424068"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIQUOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WHISKEY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LYNCHBURG (TENN)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">JACK DANIELS DISTILLERY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDB123CF934A25751C0A967958260" item-length="1509" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Simple, Sober Town</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT; FLORENCE FABRICANT writes the Food Notes column for The Times.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LYNCHBURG, a horse-and-buggy village tucked into the hollows of southern Tennessee, is all charm -- and irony. This town, which essentially owes its existence to Jack Daniel's Tennessee Whisky, made in the distillery just beyond the town square, is dry. The company that owns Jack Daniel's owns not only the distillery but also the major restaurant and general store. But nothing stronger than lemonade, coffee or tea is sold or served in Lynchburg, or surrounding Moore County, which voted to continue to ban alcohol after the repeal of Prohibition in 1933.</p>
        <p>But you don't need a drink to enjoy Lynchburg. A visit for a morning or afternoon, planned to include a tour of the distillery, one of the few in the country opened to visitors, and lunch at Miss Mary Bobo's Boarding House, is a diverting stopover on the route to or from Nashville, Memphis or Chattanooga or even Huntsville, Ala.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LYNCHBURG, a horse-and-buggy village tucked into the hollows of southern Tennessee, is all charm -- and irony. This town, which essentially owes its existence to Jack Daniel's Tennessee Whisky, made in the distillery just beyond the town square, is dry. The company that owns Jack Daniel's owns not only the distillery but also the major restaurant and general store. But nothing stronger than lemonade, coffee or tea is sold or served in Lynchburg, or surrounding Moore County, which voted to continue to ban alcohol after the repeal of Prohibition in 1933.</p>
        <p>But you don't need a drink to enjoy Lynchburg. A visit for a morning or afternoon, planned to include a tour of the distillery, one of the few in the country opened to visitors, and lunch at Miss Mary Bobo's Boarding House, is a diverting stopover on the route to or from Nashville, Memphis or Chattanooga or even Huntsville, Ala.</p>
        <p>Beyond the movie set facade of the 19th-century courthouse square, in the giant, multimillion-dollar working whisky factory, the visitor is given an extremely thorough yet anecdotal first-hand look at how whisky is made. And at Miss Mary Bobo's there are tables groaning with wonderful honest, down-home food, a taste of a simpler and immensely satisfying era.</p>
        <p>Lynchburg is a company town, population about 400, dominated by the distillery, which was re-established after repeal. It took a special bill in the Tennessee legislature to allow liquor to be made in Moore County.</p>
        <p>The plant, with 350 permanent employees, is spread over 500 acres on the other side of Mulberry Creek. Its trio of large, industrial green warehouses, which hold more than a million gallons of whisky in barrels, looms on the neighboring hilltop.</p>
        <p>In 1983, shortly after Mary Bobo died at 102 years of age, Jack Daniel's, now owned by Brown-Forman of Louisville, Ky., even bought Miss Mary Bobo's Boarding House from her heirs. She ran it until she died. "She never thought of herself as old," said Lynne Tolley, who began managing it when it reopened in 1984. Miss Tolley, a native of Lynchburg, is a great-grandniece of the eponymous Jack Daniel.</p>
        <p>The boarding house, opened by Miss Mary in 1908 in what had originally been a traveler's hotel, the Salmon Hotel, built in 1867, is a white clapboard building just off the town square. The 60 or so guests who assemble when Miss Tolley rings the dinner bell at 1 P.M. every day except Sunday are ushered from the parlor into a series of rooms with long set tables. They seat themselves, boarding house style, and always pass the food clockwise. The 9 or 10 dishes are served in simple crockery bowls and casseroles.</p>
        <p>The food is rib-sticking country fare that is more than a mere exercise in nostalgia because it's downright delicious.</p>
        <p>In spring the menu might include creamed cabbage casserole, old fashioned macaroni and cheese, country ham, fried okra, scalloped apples, stewed chicken with pastry and cornbread muffins. A cranberry relish often served is labeled intoxicating because it is laced with a heavy dose of Jack Daniels (permitted in cooking).</p>
        <p>Fresh green beans are cooked to utter tenderness and an unfashionably drab color and are a revelation for anyone who has grown accustomed to the bright, nouvelle crunch of vegetables today. Served doused with melted butter, they are irresistible.</p>
        <p>There has never been a bottle of olive oil in Miss Mary Bobo's kitchen. Nor a sun-dried tomato.</p>
        <p>But, by midsummer, slices of scarlet sun-ripened tomatoes from the garden in back grace the table. Corn, squash, peaches, apples, pickles and relishes are added to the menu, depending on the season.</p>
        <p>Guests refill their plates at will, invariably forgetting about counting calories. In the iced tea poured throughout the meal, some opt for sugar substitute, the singular nod to modern taste. Perhaps it's necessary with the dense, sweet chess square with whipped cream or the other rich cobblers or pies served for dessert.</p>
        <p>THE kitchen is operated by local women and each table has a hostess who leads the guests in introductions and explanations of why their travels brought them to Lynchburg. Snippets of family history and such come up in what evolves into lively conversation.</p>
        <p>After dinner, a much-needed half-mile stroll through the town and over the bridge leads to the Jack Daniel's headquarters. The visits are run about every half hour as groups assemble in the large, barnlike reception area decorated with antique tools relating to whisky making. The tour begins with a film about the region and the whisky.</p>
        <p>Visitors are then taken by bus to one of the warehouses to see the whisky stored in barrels where it ages, then to the rick yard where sugar maplewood is burned to make the charcoal that is used to filter the whisky. Like bourbon, Tennessee whisky is made from corn, but its distinctive mellowness comes from being passed through beds of charcoal. Used charcoal from the distillery is now turned into charcoal briquettes and sold for barbecuing.</p>
        <p>The tour then stops at Jack Daniel's original office with its old prints and the so-called "killer safe" that Mr. Daniel kicked in frustration after losing the combination, leading to the gangrene that killed him in 1911.</p>
        <p>Jack Daniel's distillery was founded in 1866 by Jasper Newton Daniel, nicknamed Jack, who acquired a still at the age of 13 from a Lutheran preacher, Dan Call. He moved the still from nearby Louse Creek to Lynchburg and registered it in 1866, making it the oldest registered distillery in the country. It is now on the National Register of Historic Places.</p>
        <p>One reason he picked this spot is that the Cave Spring provided a source of cold, iron-free water essential for making good whisky. In 1907 Mr. Daniel assigned the ownership of the distillery to his nephew, Lem Motlow, and his cousin, Richard Daniel, who subsequently sold his interest to Mr. Motlow. It was Mr. Motlow, a State Senator, who arranged for the State Legislature to pass the bill allowing Jack Daniel's to be made once again in Lynchburg. When Mr. Motlow died in 1947 his four sons took control.</p>
        <p>After being filled in with this bit of company history, visitors are led to a complex of brick and iron buildings including silos where the corn for making the whisky is stored and, finally, into the buildings where the corn mash is cooked and fermented, then distilled and charcoal filtered. It is in this area that the basics of whisky making are explained.</p>
        <p>The stops on the tour are not in the order of production. Yet, after the hour or more that the tour takes, it becomes clear what is involved. One sees the corn mash bubbling away, actually feels the heat of the fermentation as the natural sugar in the grain is converted to alcohol, and smells the carbon dioxide being given off in the process.</p>
        <p>When the four-day fermentation is completed, the mash is distilled in tall column stills, not the round alembic stills used for making Scotch. The clear distillate, drawn off at 140 proof, or 70 percent alcohol, is filtered through beds of charcoal for 24 hours, then cut with water to 110 proof before being stored in oak barrels.</p>
        <p>It is in the barrels that the whiskey acquires its characteristic amber color. Before bottling, more water is added, bringing the proof down to 86.8. The bottling plant is not open to visitors but a brief video shows that step.</p>
        <p>A visit to Lynchburg can begin with dinner at Miss Mary Bobo's and follow with a tour of the distillery, or vice versa. At some point inbetween there should be time for a stroll around the town and shopping for gifts or souvenirs.</p>
        <p>Most of what is sold in Herb Fanning's Old Time Hardware and General Store, now also owned by Jack Daniel's, is essentially a Jack Daniel's souvenir: hats, mugs, T-shirts, sweatshirts, glassware and the like.</p>
        <p>There are a number of shops around the town square. The Lynchburg Ladies Handicrafts Shop is a cooperative that sells quilts, toys and other crafts priced from $6 to $500 and signed by the makers. Linbaugh's Tennessee Emporium has assorted gifts typical of shops catering to tourists as well as some lovely furnishings and baskets made from bent willow. IF YOU GO TO TENNESSEE  Getting There</p>
        <p>Lynchburg is on Route 55, 27 miles west of Interstate 24, 70 miles south of Nashville and 80 miles northeast of Chattanooga. It is also about 45 miles north of Huntsville, Ala.  Where to Eat</p>
        <p>Miss Mary Bobo's Boarding House, Lynchburg, Tenn. 37352, is open for dinner at 1 P.M. Monday through Saturday. According to the demand, a dinner may also be scheduled for 11 A.M. The cost is $9.50 for adults, $5 for children 12 and under. Tipping is not permitted. Reservations are necessary and can be made until 11 A.M. on the day of the visit. Telephone: 615-759-7394. What to Do</p>
        <p>Tours of the distillery are conducted every day except Thanksgiving, Christmas and New Year's from 8 A.M. to 4 P.M. They are free of charge.</p>
        <p>An international barbecue cookoff run by the distillery is held in the town in the fall.  -- F. F.</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 10, 1991, Sunday</p>
        <p>A map on Feb. 17 with an article about Lynchburg, Tenn., mislabeled the state to the west. It is Arkansas, not Kansas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 10, 1991, Sunday</p>
        <p>A map on Feb. 17 with an article about Lynchburg, Tenn., mislabeled the state to the west. It is Arkansas, not Kansas.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
