<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New &amp; Noteworthy</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="439157"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D91731F932A15757C0A967958260" item-length="927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New &amp; Noteworthy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAUREL GRAEBER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOUL MURDER: The Effects of Childhood Abuse and Deprivation, by Leonard Shengold. (Fawcett Columbine, $10.95.) The term in the title was used in the 19th century by an author writing about Kaspar Hauser, a German boy who had spent 15 years chained in a cellar. Dr. Shengold applies his psychoanalytic training to the boy's modern-day counterparts, patients whose individuality has been brutally destroyed. Our reviewer, F. Robert Rodman, said in 1989, "The tension between his devotion to his patients and his adherence to a highly disciplined method gives this book an immense dignity and beauty."</p>
        <p>THE MANDARINS, by Simone de Beauvoir. (Norton, $12.95.) First published in France in 1954, this novel won the country's highest literary honor, the Prix Goncourt. Its chronicle of postwar Paris, with allusions to members of Simone de Beauvoir's own circle, earned a more mixed reception in the United States. But our reviewer, Elizabeth Janeway, said in 1956 that it "is much more than a</p>
        <p>roman a clef</p>
        <p>. . . and more also than the presentation of an intellectual dilemma. It is, in its own right, a moving and engrossing novel."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOUL MURDER: The Effects of Childhood Abuse and Deprivation, by Leonard Shengold. (Fawcett Columbine, $10.95.) The term in the title was used in the 19th century by an author writing about Kaspar Hauser, a German boy who had spent 15 years chained in a cellar. Dr. Shengold applies his psychoanalytic training to the boy's modern-day counterparts, patients whose individuality has been brutally destroyed. Our reviewer, F. Robert Rodman, said in 1989, "The tension between his devotion to his patients and his adherence to a highly disciplined method gives this book an immense dignity and beauty."</p>
        <p>THE MANDARINS, by Simone de Beauvoir. (Norton, $12.95.) First published in France in 1954, this novel won the country's highest literary honor, the Prix Goncourt. Its chronicle of postwar Paris, with allusions to members of Simone de Beauvoir's own circle, earned a more mixed reception in the United States. But our reviewer, Elizabeth Janeway, said in 1956 that it "is much more than a</p>
        <p>roman a clef</p>
        <p>. . . and more also than the presentation of an intellectual dilemma. It is, in its own right, a moving and engrossing novel."</p>
        <p>MEN AT WORK: The Craft of Baseball, by George F. Will. (Harper Perennial, $9.95.) This is very much a book about men at play -- the teams who have given America its national pastime. It examines four key elements of baseball -- managing, pitching, hitting and defense -- and profiles several of its major figures. "They talked with full and fine intelligence about their artful labors to a man who knew what questions to ask," Barbara Grizzuti Harrison said here last year. Another timely volume, PLAYING FOR KEEPS: A History of Early Baseball, by Warren Goldstein (Cornell University, $9.95), is "rich in delicious information," our reviewer, Robert Pinsky, said in 1990.</p>
        <p>LONDON FIELDS, by Martin Amis. (Vintage International, $11.) We have already survived 1984, but this novel of the future promises horrors just as vast in 1999: impending nuclear apocalypse, solar storms and the greenhouse effect run rampant. Against this backdrop, Samson Young, an American writer, is concocting a three-character murder mystery. Last year our reviewer, Bette Pesetsky, called the novel "a virtuoso depiction of a wild and lustful society. In an age of attenuated fiction, this is a large book of comic and satirical invention." Along more wild and lustful lines, Vintage International is reissuing two of Mr. Amis's earlier novels: SUCCESS ($10), which, Jay Parini said here in 1987, "holds our attention quite skillfully . . . yet is, finally, a distasteful book," and DEAD BABIES ($10), of which Margaret Drabble said in The Book Review in 1976, "One might want to forget it, but it won't be easy."</p>
        <p>RADICAL SPIRITS: Spiritualism and Women's Rights in Nineteenth-Century America, by Ann Braude. (Beacon, $12.95.) Although links between seances and suffragism may not be immediately apparent, the author presents spiritualism as an occult means of giving women the voice that society had denied them. It became historically intertwined with women's rights, "a remarkable example of how a movement constantly infiltrated by charlatans can nonetheless lead to socially valuable developments," our reviewer, Milton Rugoff, said last year.</p>
        <p>MY LOVE, MY LOVE: Or, The Peasant Girl, by Rosa Guy (Owl/Henry Holt, $8.95.) This retelling of the Hans Christian Andersen tale "The Little Mermaid" is set in the Caribbean, where the peasant heroine, Desiree Dieu-Donne, bargains away her own life to save that of a young aristocrat. The Trinidad-born Rosa Guy, whose book inspired the Broadway musical "Once on This Island," is as concerned with political realities as fairy tales. "Her new fable captures the spirit of the Caribbean as unforgettably as  [ her earlier novel ]  'A Measure of Time' did jazz-age Harlem," Angeline Goreau said here in 1985.</p>
        <p>THE NEW AGE: Notes of a Fringe Watcher, by Martin Gardner. (Prometheus, $15.95.) Here is spiritualism's modern-day side: if Shirley MacLaine and psychic phenomena leave you cold, you'll find a sympathetic voice in the author. Mr. Gardner writes about pseudo-science for The Skeptical Inquirer, a journal based in Buffalo, which first published half of the pieces in this collection. Karen Ray said here in 1988, "Mr. Gardner always maintains a firm grasp of the subject, and a tone that is skeptical without being snide."</p>
        <p>THE HILL OF EVIL COUNSEL: Three Stories, by Amos Oz. (Harvest/Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, $7.95.) Translated by Nicholas de Lange in collaboration with the author, these three interwoven stories by the acclaimed Israeli writer take place in Jerusalem on the eve of the country's birth. The tales are linked by the character of Uri, an Israeli boy who becomes involved in the lives of several political conspirators. "The three stories maintain a superb unity of time and place, echoing and enriching one another as they go along," our reviewer, Morris Dickstein, said in 1978. The publisher is also reissuing Mr. Oz's 1974 novel TOUCH THE WATER, TOUCH THE WIND ($7.95), the story of a Polish refugee.</p>
        <p>BURY MY HEART AT WOUNDED KNEE: An Indian History of the American West, by Dee Brown. (Owl/ Henry Holt, $14.95.) This new edition of the seminal historical work, detailing the demise of Native American culture and society from 1860 to 1890, comes upon the 20th anniversary of its first publication and a century after the Wounded Knee massacre. In 1971 our reviewer, N. Scott Momaday, called it "a whole narrative of singular integrity and precise continuity."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
