<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Commodity to Be Traded: Government Permits for Pollution</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="460508"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUTURES TRADING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SULFUR DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMMODITIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CHICAGO BOARD OF TRADE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5D8123BF934A25754C0A967958260" item-length="1242" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Commodity to Be Traded: Government Permits for Pollution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER PASSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ever searching for new ways to make markets and money, commodity exchanges have broadened their horizons from familiar products like soybeans and wheat to concepts like Eurodollar futures contracts that only a business school graduate could love. Now the nation's largest commodity mart has gone a step further, approving trading in Government permits to pollute.</p>
        <p>The Chicago Board of Trade voted yesterday to create a private market for rights to emit sulfur dioxide. The rights are to be issued to electric utilities by the Environmental Protection Agency as part of Washington's strategy to reduce acid rain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ever searching for new ways to make markets and money, commodity exchanges have broadened their horizons from familiar products like soybeans and wheat to concepts like Eurodollar futures contracts that only a business school graduate could love. Now the nation's largest commodity mart has gone a step further, approving trading in Government permits to pollute.</p>
        <p>The Chicago Board of Trade voted yesterday to create a private market for rights to emit sulfur dioxide. The rights are to be issued to electric utilities by the Environmental Protection Agency as part of Washington's strategy to reduce acid rain.</p>
        <p>Besides providing a service to the electric power industry, such a market would allow trading by individuals, letting them stake investment money on a rise or fall in the value of pollution rights, much as they now speculate on stocks and bonds.  Offshoot of Clean Air Act</p>
        <p>Such a market was made possible by the Clean Air Act of 1990. In a departure from traditional regulatory practices, Congress gave polluters the right to meet sulfur emissions standards by buying and selling allowances that the Environmental Protection Agency will allot to individual plants.</p>
        <p>While Federal officials are unwilling to comment on the Board of Trade initiative before they examine the details, there is every reason to believe the Bush Administration will hail the board's action.</p>
        <p>Free-market proponents say they think the new market will make it cheaper and easier for utilities to do their part in reducing acid rain. "We are anxious to establish a bona fide private market," said William G. Rosenberg, an assistant administrator at the E.P.A. Initially, no Government approval is required for the trading. Could Serve as a Model</p>
        <p>Many environmental analysts say, moreover, that the new market could serve as a model for least-cost controls on other pollutants -- notably the smog-producing chemicals that bedevil most American cities. And it could presage a far more ambitious effort to limit emissions of gases that are widely thought to be warming the earth's atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The Clean Air Act limits total emissions of sulfur dioxide gas from 110 power plants in 1995. Five years later, a much more stringent limit will force the industry to reduce emissions to less than half of the 1991 level. Dan Dudek, an economist at the Environmental Defense Fund who helped to draft the rules, argues that by allowing polluters to trade their emissions allowances, individual utilities in different markets with different types of power plants will not be locked into a single cleanup strategy.</p>
        <p>One company may find that it pays to install smokestack scrubbers on aging coal-fired boilers, bringing its emissions below the requirements, and then sell the surplus allowances. Another may leave untouched a heavy sulfur polluter that is otherwise efficient, and will buy allowances to cover the excess emissions. Still another may subsidize customers' purchases of energy-efficient appliances and lighting equipment, thereby cutting electricity demand and permitting it to shut down its offending boilers.</p>
        <p>But Richard Sandor, an executive managing director of Kidder, Peabody &amp; Company, notes that the freedom to buy and sell allowances will not yield the maximum possible benefits unless utilities have an easy way to exchange them at a price that reflects the lowest possible cost of removing sulfur from the air. That is where the Chicago Board of Trade's initiative fits in. Trading to Start in 1993</p>
        <p>Under the plan, the exchange will begin trading "cash forward" contracts in 1993 -- simple agreements to deliver allowances after they are issued in 1995. It will also ask the Commodity Futures Trading Commission for permission to establish a continuing "futures" market, permitting anyone to gamble on emissions rights in standardized 25-ton allotments up to three years in advance.</p>
        <p>A utility might, for example, buy 100 contracts due in 1997, thereby nailing down the right to spew an extra 2,500 tons of sulfur dioxide that year. The seller might be another utility that is planning to close down an old coal plant in 1997. Or it might be a mutual fund run by a brokerage house, whose manager thinks the price of allowances will fall, and is prepared to risk clients' money on the bet.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sandor estimates that contracts will initially trade at about $400 a ton and will fluctuate with factors ranging from the demand for electricity to the state of scrubber technology. The price could not rise above $2,000 because utilities always have the option of exceeding their legal emissions and paying a fine of $2,000 a ton.</p>
        <p>Not everyone is convinced that the plan will work smoothly. John Palmisano, the president of Aer-X, a Wash ington firm that is a pioneer in the private trading of local pollution allowances for smog-creating chemicals, says he thinks the market will be hard to establish. Most of the exchanges in sulfur allowances, he suspects, will be made directly between utilities, in large blocks. He worries, moreover, that some state regulators will balk at allowing utilities to participate in a national market for pollution rights.</p>
        <p>The volume of trading may be light by the standards of the Board of Trade, acknowledges Mr. Sandor, who drafted the proposal along with Philip Senechal, chief executive of the Bellefonte Lime Corporation in Bellefonte, Pa. On a typical day, futures representing 200,000 bushels of corn and 150,000 bushels of soybeans are traded on the exchange.</p>
        <p>But computerized trading could be used to match buyers and sellers at low cost. And in any case, notes Jim Thompson, the former Governor of Illinois who, along with Mr. Sandor, served as co-chairman of the exchange committee analyzing emissions allowances, noted that "the Board of Trade has social benefits as well as members' profits in mind."</p>
        <p>Those benefits could spill into market-based approaches to environmental regulation that are just now reaching the public agenda. Southern California regulators are pondering the wisdom of creating a computerized market for business permits to emit volatile organic chemicals. Dozens of other cities, hard-pressed to meet Federal air-quality standards, will also be seeking the least intrusive ways to regulate emissions of these smog-producing gases.  A Head Start</p>
        <p>Mr. Sandor said the Board of Trade's venture might prove invaluable both in designing these local markets for emissions permits and gaining legitimacy for the concept with local regulators. It would also give them a head start in producing computer software for operating such markets cheaply and fairly.</p>
        <p>The experience could pay even greater dividends, should Washington decide to limit emissions of greenhouse gases as part of a global commitment to slow atmospheric warming. The principal greenhouse gases -- carbon dioxide, methane and refrigeration chemicals -- are emitted in large quantities by thousands of businesses. The possible means of mitigating their effects, everything from energy conservation to planting trees that trap carbon, are many and varied.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dudek of the Environmental Defense Fund says that strategies for controlling greenhouse gases that try to second-guess private efforts are bound to be wasteful. His group is now pressing for legislation to limit utilities' emissions of carbon dioxide -- which could become more fodder for the Board of Trade.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
