<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="485627"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDA1739F93AA35752C1A967958260" item-length="1038" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International 2-6  SANCTIONS AGAINST YUGOSLAVIA</p>
        <p>Frustrated at its failure to halt Serbian-led attacks on Croatia, the European Community imposed broad economic sanctions on Yugoslavia and urged the United Nations to order an oil embargo.  Page 1  CIVIL WAR BATTERS DUBROVNIK</p>
        <p>Dubrovnik, the city on the Adriatic widely recognized as an international cultural treasure, has become a casualty of the civil war that has torn Yugoslavia apart.  1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International 2-6  SANCTIONS AGAINST YUGOSLAVIA</p>
        <p>Frustrated at its failure to halt Serbian-led attacks on Croatia, the European Community imposed broad economic sanctions on Yugoslavia and urged the United Nations to order an oil embargo.  Page 1  CIVIL WAR BATTERS DUBROVNIK</p>
        <p>Dubrovnik, the city on the Adriatic widely recognized as an international cultural treasure, has become a casualty of the civil war that has torn Yugoslavia apart.  1</p>
        <p>HONG KONG EXPELS 59 BOAT PEOPLE</p>
        <p>A plane carrying 59 Vietnamese boat people left Hong Kong for Hanoi under a new agreement on forced repatriation. Some of the refugees wept and struggled as they were pushed aboard the plane.  1  NATO WARNS SOVIET REPUBLICS</p>
        <p>NATO ended a two-day summit meeting with a warning to the Soviet Union and its restive republics to bring their nuclear arsenals under central control and curb the spread of conventional forces.  6</p>
        <p>St. Petersburg Journal: The victorious but burdened church.  2  POLISH PRIME MINISTER NAMED</p>
        <p>President Lech Walesa asked Bronislaw Geremek, once his mentor in the Solidarity movement and more recently his critic, to form Poland's next government.4  KOREAS SHOULD BAN BOMB, ROH SAYS</p>
        <p>President Roh Tae Woo of South Korea declared that his country will no longer have American or any other nuclear weapons on its soil, and called on North Korea not to build a nuclear bomb.  3  U.N. ASKS FUNDS FOR CAMBODIA ROLE</p>
        <p>In a bid to speed the end of the Cambodian civil war, the United Nations is pressing for start-up funds for peacekeeping.4  MAXWELL'S AMERICAN BUSINESSES</p>
        <p>The American operations of the Maxwell Communication Corporation have performed solidly, but the debt incurred to acquire them has undermined the company.  39</p>
        <p>The body of Robert Maxwell was flown to Israel for burial.  51  U.S. TO SELL SAUDIS MORE MISSILES</p>
        <p>The United States plans to sell 14 more Patriot anti-missile batteries to Saudi Arabia to reinforce its defenses, Pentagon officials said. 3</p>
        <p>The American University of Beirut's main building was bombed. 3  National 8-11 A WAR OF WORDS RAGES ON</p>
        <p>President Bush paused between a summit session of the Atlantic alliance and economic talks in the Netherlands to renew his increasingly defensive battle with Congress. Had it been up to Democrats, he said, America would be sitting "fat, dumb and happy with Saddam Hussein maybe in Saudi Arabia." 1  Gephardt attacked the President's foreign policy.  9</p>
        <p>A Washington battle is looming over tax cuts as well.  9  CAN COMPUTERS THINK?</p>
        <p>Addressing a question that many scientists believe will become a central issue of the information age, a group of human judges in Boston engaged in a three-hour battle of wits with a number of computer programs.  1  WHAT BLACKS THINK OF DUKE</p>
        <p>To many black Louisianans, David Duke's big following in the campaign for governor is a sign of deep racial and economic problems that threaten black progress.  8  MICHIGAN WELFARE RULING</p>
        <p>In a decision that could prompt further evictions of thousands of poor tenants, a Michigan appeals court declined to restore benefits under a welfare program that the state killed last month.  8  TITLE INSURERS IN TROUBLE</p>
        <p>The title insurance industry, which provides protection to millions of property owners, may not have enough money in reserve to meet a surge in claims.39  CRITICISM FOR A.T.&amp;T.</p>
        <p>Using unusually harsh language, the Federal Communications Commission said the A.T.&amp; T. phone disruption in September resulted from management oversight and outdated equipment.  39  TURN IN CHEERLEADER CASE</p>
        <p>The Texas woman convicted of trying to hire a killer to improve her daughter's chances of becoming a cheerleader won a new trial.  8</p>
        <p>U.S. to speed approval of drugs.  10</p>
        <p>Tritium contamination found outside weapons plants.  10</p>
        <p>In Texas, deaths by gunshot outnumber traffic fatalities.  10</p>
        <p>Sexual-harassment suit faults an ad campaign.  11</p>
        <p>A Chicago family of 10 killed, apparently by carbon monoxide.  11  Metropolitan -- Digest, 25 EXPANSION FOR KENNEDY</p>
        <p>The first new terminal for Kennedy International Airport in 30 years has been proposed by three of the biggest international airlines. The expansion comes as Kennedy tries to maintain its pre-eminence as the country's largest international gateway.  1</p>
        <p>Business -- Digest 39</p>
        <p>Sports 31-37</p>
        <p>STUNNED ABOUT MAGIC</p>
        <p>The news that Magic Johnson is infected with the AIDS virus left teen-agers across New York and the nation shocked, saddened and touched as if never before by the knowledge that the disease strikes indiscriminately.  1  Few heterosexuals tested for AIDS. 32  Advertisers indicate support.  32  Johnson continues to be frank.  33  Help for lobbying efforts on AIDS.  33  Leagues remain cautious on AIDS testing.  33  A shock shared by the world.  33  Basketball: Lakers go on.  31  Fitch unhappy with Nets' transactions.  31  Column: Rhoden on Kenny Anderson.  31  Football: Giants Notebook.  37  Jets rookie is hoping to make an impact.  37  Notre Dame's defense is more confident.  37  Hockey: Devils defeat Canadiens.  36  Rangers tie Maple Leafs.  36  Sports Leisure 37  Obituaries 12  Charlotte Moorman, cellist.  Consumer's World 54  "After Christmas" sales, now. New cars and acid rain. A versatile ax. Flu shots for flu season. Arts/Entertainment  Broadway's future audience.  13  Germany recovers 3 tassels, a possible clue in a vast theft.  14  Music: Fats Domino.  13  City Opera revives "Brigadoon". 13 Roy Gershen plays Louis Jordan. 15  Music in Review16  Dance: Judith Ren-Lay.  17  Editorials/Op-Ed  Editorials 22  Magic Johnson  A trick on poor women. Voters' anguish on death. Jail spending. Letters 22  Russell Baker: Will he? Won't he? Will he?  23  Anna Quindlen: Believe in Magic. 23  Tom McMillen: Magic, now and forever. 23  Steven D. Gold: Taxes aren't fatal. 23  David Holahan: The whining state of Connecticut. 23</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
