<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Television; On the Baltics and the Persian Gulf</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="455115"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, WALTER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BALTIC REQUIEM, A (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LEGACY OF WAR (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEED71E30F937A15755C0A967958260" item-length="647" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Television; On the Baltics and the Persian Gulf</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In "A Baltic Requiem," the Latvian movie maker Juris Podnieks gets at the heart of the resurgent nationalism of Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania. The 90-minute work, at 9 tonight on Channel 13, sets last summer's folk festivals, in which the Balts celebrated their national identities, against the power that has dominated them since before World War II. The patriotic songs, banned for half a century, the flowers, crosses, candles, costumes and high emotions of the festivals are contrasted with the grayness imposed by the guns and tanks of the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>Few of the singers are old enough to remember their nations' brief spell of independence between the two world wars or to have had any experience of democracy, yet they seem imbued with a culture that has managed to survive centuries of repression. The memories of elderly people of the arrests and deportations during the Nazi occupation in World War II and the Soviet takeover after the war are followed by pictures from last year's votes for independence in the Latvian and Lithuanian parliaments. Among the powerful images are those of a hill of crosses in Lithuania, thousands upon thousands of them, planted and replanted by the faithful after being bulldozed by the Russians, and hard-to-take scenes of Soviet soldiers chasing and clubbing civilians last winter in Vilnius.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In "A Baltic Requiem," the Latvian movie maker Juris Podnieks gets at the heart of the resurgent nationalism of Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania. The 90-minute work, at 9 tonight on Channel 13, sets last summer's folk festivals, in which the Balts celebrated their national identities, against the power that has dominated them since before World War II. The patriotic songs, banned for half a century, the flowers, crosses, candles, costumes and high emotions of the festivals are contrasted with the grayness imposed by the guns and tanks of the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>Few of the singers are old enough to remember their nations' brief spell of independence between the two world wars or to have had any experience of democracy, yet they seem imbued with a culture that has managed to survive centuries of repression. The memories of elderly people of the arrests and deportations during the Nazi occupation in World War II and the Soviet takeover after the war are followed by pictures from last year's votes for independence in the Latvian and Lithuanian parliaments. Among the powerful images are those of a hill of crosses in Lithuania, thousands upon thousands of them, planted and replanted by the faithful after being bulldozed by the Russians, and hard-to-take scenes of Soviet soldiers chasing and clubbing civilians last winter in Vilnius.</p>
        <p>The last half hour is a tribute to two of Mr. Podnieks's cameramen who were killed in the military's attack in January on unarmed people guarding the parliament and television station in Riga. Through the men's cameras, you see the nighttime assault by the Soviet black berets; then, suddenly, things go out of focus, and then other cameras show the dying men. "Film me," one cries as he falls.</p>
        <p>Throughout there is the music of what the evening's host, Hedrick Smith, calls the "singing revolution," which he says has forced President Mikhail S. Gorbachev to soften his opposition to independence for the Baltic countries. Mr. Podnieks appears on screen to affirm his allegiance to his people's struggle, but of course his film has already done that.</p>
        <p>There's good news at 10 tonight, maybe, on the Discovery Channel. "Legacy of War," the first program of a weeklong look at "State of the Natural World," concludes that the damage done by the Iraqis to Kuwait is merely a disaster, not a catastrophe. Experts say the first accounts of what the narrator of this BBC production calls "the most wanton act of destruction since the Vandals sacked Rome" were exaggerated.</p>
        <p>Although the pictures above and under water of the enormous oil spill are ominous, the result is described as of purely local consequence for the Persian Gulf itself. Estimates of the loss are now between one and four million barrels, much less than at first feared, and so far the world's climate does not seem to have been affected by the fires. In the open waters of the gulf, fish still flourish; green turtles are still laying their eggs, and the program reports that only one-half of 1 percent of the birds in the gulf have died. No one can be sure of the long-term effects, but the documentary leaves the impression that expensive though the cleanup must be, it is manageable.</p>
        <p>The second half of tonight's hour tells of the American military's plans for destroying its stock of outdated chemical weapons, a parlous enterprise. The series continues through the week with reports on birth control in Mexico and environmental concerns in Siberia, the decline of Canada's singing white beluga whales and Japan's use or misuse of the oceans, and more. It concludes with "The Greenhouse Conspiracy," a two-hour documentary that challenges the global warming hypothesis, followed by a discussion by scientists on both sides of the controversy. It would not be surprising if tonight's upbeat assessment of Kuwait's oil fires produced some controversy, too.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
