<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="471919"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D71731F934A3575AC0A967958260" item-length="1176" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Soviet Turmoil 4-7</p>
        <p>The Baltic states became indepedent during deliberations at the first meeting of the Soviet Union's new ruling council. The act formally freed Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia, which were incorporated forcibly in the Soviet Union in 1940.  Page 1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Soviet Turmoil 4-7</p>
        <p>The Baltic states became indepedent during deliberations at the first meeting of the Soviet Union's new ruling council. The act formally freed Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia, which were incorporated forcibly in the Soviet Union in 1940.  Page 1</p>
        <p>Latvia must decide who is a citizen, a complex question fraught with political, historical and even philosophical tension. But the question must be settled before its first Parliamentary elections in the next year or two. 1</p>
        <p>New Latvian newspaper struggling to do it right 5</p>
        <p>Very quietly, Leningrad is St. Petersburg 7</p>
        <p>St. Petersburg finds a name so familiar and, well, czarist 7</p>
        <p>Reporter's notebook: The astronauts aboard the Soviet space station Mir, who journeyed weightlessly above the coup, beamed down an urgent question: Was it true, they asked, that the space station was for sale? 1</p>
        <p>TV critic's notebook: Soviet odd couple makes U.S. debut 7</p>
        <p>International 2-3, 8</p>
        <p>A bitter political fight over Israel took shape as some Congressional supporters ignored President Bush's appeal to delay a request for $10 billion in loans and said they would push for quick approval. 1</p>
        <p>France warned Gen. Michel Aoun, the exiled Christian general who battled the Lebanese Government, to tone down his calls for rebellion in Beirut to prevent French-Lebanese relations from worsening.  3</p>
        <p>The Yugoslav peace conference will still be held today in the Hague, despite the continuing ferocious fighting between Serbs and Croats, the foreign ministers of the European Community have decided. 3</p>
        <p>Ex-East German chief quits politics 3</p>
        <p>Access to the European Community for Eastern European countries was blocked by France, which torpedoed an agreement in an effort to protect its own cattle producers. 35</p>
        <p>One hundred are killed as two trains crash in Congo 2</p>
        <p>Argentine prosecutor sees trials of generals winding down 8</p>
        <p>Ranomafana Journal: Whose forest is it?  2  National 9-12</p>
        <p>An ex-C.I.A. spymaster was indicted on 10 felony charges of perjury, false statements and obstruction of inquiries into the Iran-contra affair. Clair E. George had been the agency's third ranking official. 1</p>
        <p>The indictment challenges the C.I.A. and the culture of the agency that Mr. George personified -- a culture of secrecy that for decades has successfully resisted efforts to penetrate and change it. 10</p>
        <p>The first white man to be executed for killing a black in the United States since 1944 was put to death in Columbia, S.C. Donald (Peewee) Gaskins was convicted of the 1982 killing-for-hire of a fellow inmate. 1</p>
        <p>A swath of broadcasting frequencies is being shifted from Government to commercial use as many experts inside and outside the Government say the system for awarding licenses has broken down. 1</p>
        <p>Officials are trying to find out if Salomon chief misled U.S.  35</p>
        <p>The economy showed no clear trend in August, with the unemployment rate remaining at 6.8 percent and a second straight rise in factory payrolls countered by job shrinkage elsewhere, the Government said. 35</p>
        <p>White House Memo: The decision by two conservatives to defy a request from George Bush to cancel an ad attacking three Democratic Senators reflects the long tension between the President and the right wing. 9</p>
        <p>Judge in Noriega trial bars records on Bush 11</p>
        <p>U.S. judge is given prison sentence 12</p>
        <p>Milwaukee police officers are dismissed 12</p>
        <p>A witness in the Florida rape case against William Kennedy Smith said in a document that Senator Edward Kennedy discussed a rape allegation a day before he told the police he knew nothing about the incident. 9</p>
        <p>Worry about cancer in Los Alamos is beginning to rise after a sculptor said he found a "cluster of cases of brain tumors" in the New Mexico community where the atomic bomb was first developed. 9</p>
        <p>Fire victims died trying to shut exits 9</p>
        <p>Costs of adapting to global warming in the nation should still be reasonable, a panel of scientists said. They were optimistic about the ability of farming and industry to adapt to climate change. 12  Regional 25-28</p>
        <p>A contractor with suspected mob ties was barred last November from bidding on a school project but awarded a $884,000 contract in May with the Sanitation Department. 25</p>
        <p>The celebration of Rosh ha-Shanah is is being greeted with a mix of hope and apprehension in Crown Heights, where thousands of Jews are expected to gather this weekend to celebrate their New Year. 25</p>
        <p>The records of the grand jury that declined to bring charges against a Hasidic man in Crown Heights will not be released, a judge said, rejecting an extraordinary request by the Brooklyn District Attorney. 27</p>
        <p>Prof. Leonard Jeffries of City College has not had a traditional rise as a scholar and demonstrated a penchant for controversy long before the current furvor over a speech he gave that has been attacked as racist. 25</p>
        <p>A well-heeled City Council candidate running in the East Village was unknown until his advertisements began appearing everwhere. The campaign of Philip K. Howard, a lawyer, is a testament to the power of money in the race. 25</p>
        <p>Jacob Riis beach seems forgotten these days. Attendance on the stretch of sand on the Rockaway Peninsula is down, despite a promotional campaign and local residents' opinion that it is the area's best beach. 26</p>
        <p>Body found in box in midtown 27</p>
        <p>A bomb hoax closes Madison Avenue for 2 1/2 hours 27</p>
        <p>Six youths admit guilt in Queens cemetery case 28</p>
        <p>New Jersey could take center stage in the national abortion debate now that a Superior Court judge has said he is willing to consider a lower judge's ruling that human life begins at conception. 26</p>
        <p>Parking investigator charges cover-up of bogus ticketing 26</p>
        <p>Cuomo seeking bill to restrain insurance costs 28  Business Digest 35  Sports 29-34</p>
        <p>Baseball: Mets lose to Braves 31</p>
        <p>Tapani and Twins beat Yanks 31</p>
        <p>Column: Berkow on Navratilova 29</p>
        <p>Football: Notre Dame is missing a few people 29</p>
        <p>Hockey: Notebook 32</p>
        <p>SportsLeisure: Blind golfers tee it up 33</p>
        <p>Tennis: Navratilova and Seles reach Open final 29</p>
        <p>Connors has crowd; Courier has cap 32  Consumer's World 50</p>
        <p>Using laser to catch speeding motorists</p>
        <p>Short-term beeper rental</p>
        <p>Gripe water for babies</p>
        <p>New suspension bar for bikes</p>
        <p>Guidepost  Obituaries 13</p>
        <p>Francis Turner, an educator</p>
        <p>Hallie Burnett Zeisel, a novelist  Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>Dracula in the subway 15</p>
        <p>MTV video awards 48</p>
        <p>Theater: "Skin of Our Teeth" 14</p>
        <p>Music: "The Death of Klinghoffer" 15</p>
        <p>Dance: Kristin Jackson Dance 15  Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials 22</p>
        <p>Bridgeable gap in South Africa</p>
        <p>Breaking the scroll cartel</p>
        <p>Justice in Crown Heights</p>
        <p>Few choices for Civil Court</p>
        <p>Letters 22</p>
        <p>Russell Baker: Oh, what joys impend 23</p>
        <p>Anna Quindlen: The graffiti on the wall 23</p>
        <p>Alan Tonelson: Put America first 23</p>
        <p>Hershel Shanks: Scholars, scrolls, secrets and "crimes" 23</p>
        <p>Mark Paslawsky: Recycle military bases 23</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
