<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SUMMERTIME HARM TO OZONE DETECTED OVER BROADER AREA</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="482175"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CANCER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SKIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HALONS (CHEMICAL)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Skin Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DE1139F930A15753C1A967958260" item-length="1014" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SUMMERTIME HARM TO OZONE DETECTED OVER BROADER AREA</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Oct. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the first time, scientists have found the earth's protective ozone shield to be weakened over the United States and other temperate-zone countries in summer, when the sun's harmful ultraviolet rays are the strongest and pose the greatest danger to people and crops.</p>
        <p>Since this summertime depletion of the ozone shield was not known until now, predicted increases in skin cancers and crop damage are too low, an international panel of scientists convened by the United Nations said here today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the first time, scientists have found the earth's protective ozone shield to be weakened over the United States and other temperate-zone countries in summer, when the sun's harmful ultraviolet rays are the strongest and pose the greatest danger to people and crops.</p>
        <p>Since this summertime depletion of the ozone shield was not known until now, predicted increases in skin cancers and crop damage are too low, an international panel of scientists convened by the United Nations said here today.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, they said, the rate of ozone depletion has accelerated and will continue at the higher rate in the 1990's, requiring a more rapid phasing out of chlorofluorocarbons, halons and other manmade chemicals that destroy ozone high in the atmosphere. Stricter Controls to Be Sought</p>
        <p>United Nations officials said they would seek to reopen international discussions next year in an effort to speed up abandonment of the ozone-eating chemicals for the second time since controls on them were first adopted in 1987. As of now, developed countries have agreed to phase them out by the year 2000 and developing countries by 2010.</p>
        <p>Until recently, scientists believed on the basis of measurements from satellites that ozone depletion was taking place only over the poles, and in the middle latitudes in winter. The depletion is worse nearer the poles, and worst of all over the Antarctic, with its ozone "hole."</p>
        <p>"We now see a significant decrease of ozone both in the Northern and Southern Hemispheres not only in winter, but in spring and summer, the time when people sunbathe, putting them at risk for skin cancer, and the time we grow crops," said Dr. Robert Watson, a National Aeronautics and Space Administration scientist who is co-chairman of an 80-member group of scientists from 80 countries who have been assessing ozone trends. He said the situation was "extremely serious."</p>
        <p>Chlorofluorocarbons and other ozone-destroying chemicals are used in a wide variety of industrial and consumer applications, including refrigration and air conditioning, and halons are used in fire extinguishers.</p>
        <p>The chemicals take years to waft up to the upper atmosphere. There, they touch off chemical reactions that lead to the destruction of the ozone, which screens out harmful frequencies of ultraviolet radiation. Unscreened, the rays can cause cancer and cataracts, harm some crops and other plants and, scientists fear, disrupt the feeding patterns of marine life.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mostafa K. Tolba, executive director of the United Nations Environment Program, called the findings "very disturbing" and said there was "definitely a need for a quick response" and for a reopening of international talks on the subject. They spoke at a news conference here today.</p>
        <p>Besides destroying ozone, chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, are among several gases that trap heat in the atmosphere. In another new finding, the scientists reported that the ozone depletion may have a cooling effect, offsetting part of the global warming trend that some scientists fear may already have begun. If this finding is confirmed, restoring atmospheric ozone levels could increase global warming.</p>
        <p>The finding could undercut the Bush Administration's position on global warming. The Adminstration has sought to avoid making possibly costly cuts in carbon dioxide emissions by insisting that actions it is taking to reduce CFC's are sufficient for the next decade or more. Dr. Tolba, under whose leadership the ozone and the climate talks are taking place, said that these findings showed clearly that "the main emphasis should be on carbon dioxide." Administration Defends Policy</p>
        <p>But William K. Reilly, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, said today that unexpected findings vindicated the Administration's policy of emphasizing research rather than immediate action on global warming. "What had been thought was a major greenhouse gas turns out in fact to be having a cooling effect," he said.</p>
        <p>The United States, along with other industrialized countries, has agreed to phase out CFC's by the end of this decade, and Mr. Reilly said the country was ahead of schedule. And today, the Du Pont Company, the world's largest manufacturer of CFC's and halons, announced that in response to the new scientific report it was accelerating its phaseout of the chemicals by three to five years. In 1988 the company pledged to eliminate them by 2000.</p>
        <p>In April, the Environmental Protection Agency reported that over the previous decade, ozone declined by 4.5 to 5 percent over the United States and other Northern Hemisphere countries in the winter and early spring. Agency analysts calculated that as a result, some 12 million Americans would develop skin cancer, and more than 200,000 of them would die, over the next 50 years.</p>
        <p>The United Nations analysis, which includes more recent data and independent information from satellites and ground-based instruments, shows that from May through August, high-atmosphere ozone in the Northern Hemisphere temperate zones decreased by about 3 percent in the 1980's. This is about triple the rate of the 1970's. Similarly, the analysis showed a decrease of about 5 percent in the Southern Hemisphere summer, from December through March.</p>
        <p>Because CFC's are still rising slowly to the ozone layer and will be for some years, Dr. Watson said, "we believe there will be an additional 3 percent ozone loss between now and the end of the century" in the northern latitudes, which include Europe and North America, and in the Southern Hemisphere's temperate zones. Only in the tropics was no significant increase detected.</p>
        <p>The scientists did not calculate how many additional cancer deaths might result from the summer ozone depletion. But Dr. Watson said that with the form of skin cancer called melanoma, which is often fatal, there would be about a 1 percent increase in cases for every 1 percent of ozone depletion. For other skin cancers, which are less often fatal, each 1 percent of ozone depletion brings a 3 percent increase in cases, he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
