<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Nation; A Time to Move</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="437033"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DE113EF930A25757C0A967958260" item-length="709" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Nation; A Time to Move</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM WICKER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The central proposition of the new National Academy of Sciences report on global warming is that it's time to get a move on. Something has to be done, and the sooner the better.</p>
        <p>So tactfully is the report worded, however, and so moderate and affordable are its specific recommendations that even the Bush Administration managed to find words of welcome. Dr. D. Allen Bromley, the White House science adviser, said he was "delighted with the report, as are all my colleagues."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The central proposition of the new National Academy of Sciences report on global warming is that it's time to get a move on. Something has to be done, and the sooner the better.</p>
        <p>So tactfully is the report worded, however, and so moderate and affordable are its specific recommendations that even the Bush Administration managed to find words of welcome. Dr. D. Allen Bromley, the White House science adviser, said he was "delighted with the report, as are all my colleagues."</p>
        <p>A prospective buyer for the Brooklyn Bridge might take that at face value -- if he could overlook some flagrant and obvious divergences between White House policies and the academy report:</p>
        <p>* The Administration does not support an increase from 27.5 to 32.5 miles per gallon, as recommended, in the fuel efficiency of new autos.</p>
        <p>* The White House has not advocated or provided more Federal support for mass transit, as the report urges.</p>
        <p>* Population growth is the "biggest single driver of atmospheric pollution," said Daniel Evans, the former Republican Governor and Senator from Washington, who headed the academy panel that prepared the report. But President Bush opposes abortion and refuses to permit U.S. support for some population-control programs in other countries.</p>
        <p>* The report urged a sharp increase in emphasis on fuel efficiency and conservation in Federal energy research, and greater effort to develop alternative energy sources. But the Reagan and Bush Administrations have systematically dismantled the conservation and alternative-source programs of Presidents Nixon and Carter; and in the so-called "energy policy" Mr. Bush announced in February, he asked for no conservation at all and little real reduction in consumption of either domestic or foreign oil, but instead urged opening the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge to oil drilling and production.</p>
        <p>* The academy panel clearly said that prompt action should be taken to reduce the threat of global warming; but it's no secret that the most powerful voice in Mr. Bush's ear, that of his chief of staff, John Sununu, has been saying that the threat is not conclusively established and more study is needed before taking stronger action.</p>
        <p>The report tacitly gives that attitude the back of its hand, citing a 25 percent increase in the atmospheric concentration of carbon dioxide in the last century and a continuing increase of about 0.5 percent a year (a figure bound to go up as a result of the huge and intense oil-well conflagration that was a price of the liberation of Kuwait).</p>
        <p>Global average temperatures were reported to have risen by 0.5 to 1.1 degrees Fahrenheit in the last century; and if nothing is done to reduce emissions of "greenhouse" gases like carbon dioxide, average global temperatures were projected to go up at least another 1.8 and as much as 9 degrees.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists, too, expressed themselves as pleased with the Academy of Sciences report, but probably few of them really welcomed its call for development of a new generation of nuclear power reactors. The panelists did offer the important reservations that these reactors should be safe to operate and that their waste should be safely disposable, in order for nuclear power to regain public acceptability.</p>
        <p>That's a tall order, especially nuclear waste disposal. That's been shown to be less a technical than a</p>
        <p>political</p>
        <p>problem, since few if any states or localities want to accept storage of this dangerous stuff under any conditions of regulation or safety.</p>
        <p>Publicly acceptable nuclear power, moreover, can hardly be achieved by leaving its development again to the largely discredited supervision of the private utilities; nor do many of them want to take on the financial and regulatory burdens that would be required. Countries with thriving nuclear power programs have attained them under strict government development and management; but in the U.S. the Bush Administration, the utilities industry and the public's free-market theology may oppose that.</p>
        <p>But the essential value of the National Academy of Sciences report is not in its sometimes debatable details, but in its clear overall meaning.The hour is late and the need is urgent, as even Mr. Sununu now will find it harder to deny.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
