<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's a Rain Forest Out There</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="495474"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="ON LANGUAGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENGLISH LANGUAGE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ON LANGUAGE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D71139F931A15751C1A967958260" item-length="1190" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's a Rain Forest Out There</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT'S HAPPENED to the</p>
        <p>jungle</p>
        <p>?</p>
        <p>It's disappearing. This once-popular word was first used in 1776 in Nathaniel B. Halhed's translation of a code of Hindu laws: "Land Waste for Five Years . . . is called Jungle." It is respectably rooted in the Hindi</p>
        <p>jangal</p>
        <p>and the Sanskrit</p>
        <p>jangala</p>
        <p>, "wasteland, desert." After a century of use in this dry sense, the word was applied to uncultivated tropical land, overgrown with grasses and teeming with snakes and creepily wet wildlife; Thomas Macaulay wrote in 1849 of "a vast pool . . . overhung with rank jungle."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT'S HAPPENED to the</p>
        <p>jungle</p>
        <p>?</p>
        <p>It's disappearing. This once-popular word was first used in 1776 in Nathaniel B. Halhed's translation of a code of Hindu laws: "Land Waste for Five Years . . . is called Jungle." It is respectably rooted in the Hindi</p>
        <p>jangal</p>
        <p>and the Sanskrit</p>
        <p>jangala</p>
        <p>, "wasteland, desert." After a century of use in this dry sense, the word was applied to uncultivated tropical land, overgrown with grasses and teeming with snakes and creepily wet wildlife; Thomas Macaulay wrote in 1849 of "a vast pool . . . overhung with rank jungle."</p>
        <p>As recently as a generation ago, the word was doing fine. Rudyard Kipling wrote "The Jungle Book" in 1894, and coined</p>
        <p>the law of the jungle</p>
        <p>, cruel but fair in its way. A children's play structure was called a</p>
        <p>jungle gym</p>
        <p>in 1923;</p>
        <p>jungle warfare</p>
        <p>was taught in all the best military schools after World War II, and the metaphor was extended to "</p>
        <p>The Asphalt Jungle</p>
        <p>," a 1950 John Huston movie (which brought Marilyn Monroe to prominence) about the fierce city, while Evan Hunter's 1954 novel about city schools was titled "</p>
        <p>The Blackboard Jungle</p>
        <p>." Harried executives told the joke of Tarzan swinging on a vine into his treehouse and telling Jane, his mate: "Whew! It's a jungle out there."</p>
        <p>All gone.</p>
        <p>Jungle</p>
        <p>is no more, at least not in sophisticated usage. The</p>
        <p>rain forest</p>
        <p>has taken over.</p>
        <p>It started to grow slowly. The German botanist Andreas Franz Wilhelm Schimper first used</p>
        <p>Regenwald</p>
        <p>in 1898; William Rogers Fisher translated it literally in this 1903 publication in English: "The</p>
        <p>Rain-forest</p>
        <p>is evergreen, hygrophilous in character, at least thirty meters high, but usually much taller, rich in thick-stemmed lianes, and in wood as well as herbaceous epiphytes."</p>
        <p>That was what used to be a</p>
        <p>jungle</p>
        <p>; in those days, a somewhat drier woodland that attracted lumberjacks was a</p>
        <p>forest</p>
        <p>. Now they're both forests; the dripping one with the quicksand and weird birdcalls is a</p>
        <p>tropical rain forest</p>
        <p>while the nice woods with reasonable rainfall that Hansel and Gretel would go trooping through is a</p>
        <p>temperate rain forest</p>
        <p>.</p>
        <p>This is the environmentalists' greatest linguistic triumph. Because a</p>
        <p>jungle</p>
        <p>was fearsome, nobody would want to preserve it. But a</p>
        <p>forest</p>
        <p>has a nice ring to it -- there was Robin Hood with his merry men robbing the rich in Sherwood Forest -- and the word lent itself to persuasion for preservation. If a pollster asks, "Is it O.K. to mow down the</p>
        <p>jungle</p>
        <p>?" the answer will be "Sure, who needs it?"; if the same pollster asks, "Do you approve of destruction of the</p>
        <p>rain forest</p>
        <p>?" the answer will be "No, it will lead to global warming or a new ice age."</p>
        <p>Get off that jungle, Jim. When they colorize that John Huston movie for television, we will see Marilyn Monroe in "The Asphalt Rainforest." IF BY WHISKY</p>
        <p>THE GREAT POLITICAL straddle exemplified by the</p>
        <p>if-by-whisky</p>
        <p>speech was attributed here to Gov. Fuller Warren of Florida in the 1950's. An earlier and richer formulation was submitted by Norman L.  Simpson of Syracuse, who found an undated and unattributed clipping in his family archives; he dates it to the 1920's, during discussions of the repeal of the Volstead Act prohibiting the sale of liquor:</p>
        <p>"I'll take a stand on any issue at any time, regardless of how fraught with controversy it may be. You have asked me how I feel about whisky; well, Brother, here's how I stand.</p>
        <p>"If by whisky, you mean the Devil's brew, the Poison scourge, the bloody monster that defies innocence, dethrones reason, creates misery and poverty, yea, literally takes the bread out of the mouths of babes; if you mean the Evil Drink that topples men and women from pinnacles of righteous, gracious living into the bottomless pit of despair, degradation, shame, helplessness and hopelessness -- then certainly I am against it with all my power.</p>
        <p>"But if by whisky, you mean the oil of conversation, the philosophic wine and ale that is consumed when good fellows get together, that puts a song in their hearts, laughter on their lips and the warm glow of contentment in their eyes; if you mean that sterling drink that puts the spring in an old man's steps on a frosty morning; if you mean that drink, the sale of which pours into our treasury untold millions of dollars which are used to provide tender care for our little crippled children, our pitifully aged and infirm and to build our highways, hospitals and schools -- then, Brother, I am for it. This is my stand."</p>
        <p>The</p>
        <p>if-by-whisky</p>
        <p>technique is still in active use. Asked by Jonathan Alter of Newsweek if he was not too sensitive to criticism, Gov. Mario M. Cuomo of New York replied:</p>
        <p>"If by thin-skinned you mean very, very quick to respond -- that's what I've done for a lifetime. I'd been a lawyer for more than 20 years. You can't let the comment from the witness pass.</p>
        <p>"If  [ by thin-skinned ]  you're talking about being personally sensitive to criticism, that's a lot of  [ expletive ] ." NO PICNIC</p>
        <p>WHAT IS THE LATEST putdown of a person who is</p>
        <p>not all there</p>
        <p>-- whose</p>
        <p>elevator does not go all the way to the top</p>
        <p>, whose</p>
        <p>oars are not both in the water</p>
        <p>?</p>
        <p>Sally Quinn, whose latest novel is the entertaining "Happy Endings," reports this sighting:</p>
        <p>his belt does not go through all the loops</p>
        <p>. A variant formulation, describing inadequacy in a situation rather than in an individual (and probably based on</p>
        <p>an hour late and a dollar short</p>
        <p>), is</p>
        <p>one sandwich short of a picnic</p>
        <p>.</p>
        <p>These are transient phrases; the definition of dottiness that has shown generational staying power is</p>
        <p>out to lunch</p>
        <p>. It is, of course, taken from the sign on an establishment's door meaning "temporarily gone"; although the more officious signs state, "Open 9-12, 2-5," with the new sense of fogginess, those signs more often say cheerfully, "Be right back," or for the less industrious proprietors, "Gone fishin'."</p>
        <p>But in its sense of "gone bonkers,"</p>
        <p>out to lunch</p>
        <p>has achieved a place in the slang Hall of Fame. "Members of Congress who support these bills are</p>
        <p>out to lunch</p>
        <p>," Tom Schatz of Citizens Against Government Waste charged last month; in 1984, candidate Walter Mondale told a Michigan labor group, "The Reagan Administration is</p>
        <p>out to lunch</p>
        <p>." The earliest use so far sighted/cited is in Science Digest in August 1955: " '</p>
        <p>Out to lunch</p>
        <p>' refers to someone who, in other years, just wasn't 'there' -- and he is told immediately to 'Get with it!' " This phrase, which may have originated in the scientific community, was adopted in its sense of "crazily distant; profoundly out of touch; once removed from reality" in Britain. "Dostoyevsky notwithstanding," wrote The Times Literary Supplement in 1983 about a crime novel, "it's not always a good idea to have a central character who's</p>
        <p>out to lunch</p>
        <p>most of the time."</p>
        <p>This is by way of advertising for the coiner of the slang phrase now achieving the stature of a classic. If you have a pre-1955 written citation, send it to Safire Out to Lunch, at The New York Times, 1627 Eye Street N.W., Washington, D.C. 20006. I'll be in.</p>
        <p>ON LANGUAGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
