<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; More Green For Less Gold</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="443888"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STAVINS, ROBERT</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ECONOMIC SCENE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D8153BF93BA35756C0A967958260" item-length="778" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; More Green For Less Gold</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS many a candidate for public office has discovered, green is beautiful: Voters much prefer their air pristine, their water potable and their garbage somewhere else. What elected officials are also discovering is that green can be expensive: According to the Environmental Protection Agency, Americans spend $100 billion annually to comply with Federal environmental rules.</p>
        <p>That is why Washington now seems almost as interested in how to clean up as what to clean up -- and why the initial Project 88 report, released on the eve of President Bush's inauguration, caught the political wave.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS many a candidate for public office has discovered, green is beautiful: Voters much prefer their air pristine, their water potable and their garbage somewhere else. What elected officials are also discovering is that green can be expensive: According to the Environmental Protection Agency, Americans spend $100 billion annually to comply with Federal environmental rules.</p>
        <p>That is why Washington now seems almost as interested in how to clean up as what to clean up -- and why the initial Project 88 report, released on the eve of President Bush's inauguration, caught the political wave.</p>
        <p>The brainchild of two ambitious Senators, Tim Wirth of Colorado and the late John Heinz of Pennsylvania, Project 88 made a case for market-based incentives as a cheaper, less intrusive alternative to traditional pollution regulation. Round 2 of the project, released this week, offers more specific advice for environmentalists eager to tame the capitalist beast without rendering it lame.</p>
        <p>Before the mid-1980's, environmental politics was about us versus them. They were chopping down our rain forests, poisoning our rivers and coating our sea otters in crude oil. Government's job was to stop them.</p>
        <p>Now the battle lines are blurred. Companies are scrambling to become greener-than-thou: products once touted as "new and improved" are now "recyclable" or "biodegradable." By the same token, there is greater public recognition that the environmental lunch is not free; sometimes the price of clean is higher taxes and higher prices.</p>
        <p>Political momentum for environmental change has not ebbed. But it is dawning on Democrats, as well as Republicans, that the greatest political rewards may well be reaped by those who worry about the costs as well as the benefits.</p>
        <p>The first Project 88 report, written by Robert Stavins of the Kennedy School of Public Policy at Harvard, offered ways to think about a laundry list of problems from radon pollution to wetland conservation. The message, that market-linked financial incentives could be a cheap, effective alternative to "command" regulation, was no revelation to economists. But it did impress the target audience, environmental professionals and lawmakers who want the job done with minimal disruption to business, consumers and the Government budget.</p>
        <p>One area where the report apparently influenced votes was in the acid-rain provisions in last year's amendments to the Clean Air Act. The "get the bad guys" approach of the original act set standards for sulfur emissions from power plants. Rather than merely tightening those standards, forcing older plants to be rebuilt at great expense, the new law limited total sulfur emissions and gave polluters discretion in how to comply collectively.</p>
        <p>Rights to pollute can now be traded, giving polluters an incentive to close exceptionally dirty plants and sell their emissions rights to those who value them more. In some cases, it may even pay utilities to subsidize customer conservation rather than build cleaner plants or buy the right to pollute from someone else. The estimated savings to utility stockholders and electricity consumers will run to about $1 billion a year.</p>
        <p>Round 2, again drafted by Mr. Stavins, digs a little deeper than the original report. The chapter on greenhouse warming, drawn largely from the work of Dan Dudek of the Environmental Defense Fund, Lawrence Goulder of Stanford University and Ralph Cavanagh of the Natural Resources Defense Council, is particularly intriguing.</p>
        <p>International limits on greenhouse gases, it suggests, would be more cheaply carried out if emissions rights could be traded among nations. This would allow countries to buy rights from others that are prepared, say, to switch to nuclear power or to plant trees. Poor countries might be compensated with a disproportionate share of rights in the initial allocation, giving them the choice of polluting more or raising capital by selling their permits.</p>
        <p>The report makes a case for fuel taxes in proportion to the amount of carbon dioxide the fuels put into the air. The revenue, the report suggests, could be used dollar-for-dollar to reduce other taxes, offsetting the regressive nature of carbon taxes and perhaps reducing market distortions that impair economic efficiency.</p>
        <p>There is too little detail here to weigh the merits of these policy prescriptions. But it would be a mistake to think of Round 2 as simply a cookbook, to be judged by the completeness of the recipes. Project 88 is a sign of the growing economic savvy of the environmental movement, recognition that there is more to good environmental policy than just saying no.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
