<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Bangladesh's Storms, Poverty More Than Weather Is the Killer</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19910514T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="444650"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CYCLONES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BANGLADESH</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KRISTOF, NICHOLAS D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bangladesh</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Bangladesh</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cyclones</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DB1631F932A25756C0A967958260" item-length="1098" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Bangladesh's Storms, Poverty More Than Weather Is the Killer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS D. KRISTOF,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KRISTOF, NICHOLAS D</byline>
      <dateline>DHAKA, Bangladesh, May 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Behind the immediate horror of the cyclone that killed more than 100,000 people last week lies a painful truth: It is not so much weather that is killing people as it is poverty.</p>
        <p>The loss of life on such a scale would be preventable, relief experts and Bangladeshi officials say, if only there were enough money to build more cyclone shelters and higher embankments against the sea. But money is short, and so the next big cyclone will also kill tens of thousands of destitute villagers forced by population pressures to live in dangerous areas.  Vulnerable to Any Storm</p>
        <p>"I will stay here," said Abdulkarim, an 18-year-old man on Gomatali Island, which barely rises a few feet above the Bay of Bengal and is vulnerable to any storm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Behind the immediate horror of the cyclone that killed more than 100,000 people last week lies a painful truth: It is not so much weather that is killing people as it is poverty.</p>
        <p>The loss of life on such a scale would be preventable, relief experts and Bangladeshi officials say, if only there were enough money to build more cyclone shelters and higher embankments against the sea. But money is short, and so the next big cyclone will also kill tens of thousands of destitute villagers forced by population pressures to live in dangerous areas.  Vulnerable to Any Storm</p>
        <p>"I will stay here," said Abdulkarim, an 18-year-old man on Gomatali Island, which barely rises a few feet above the Bay of Bengal and is vulnerable to any storm.</p>
        <p>Nobody needs to tell Mr. Abdulkarim that life on the island is dangerous. He lost both parents and all six of his brothers and sisters to the cyclone, which struck on April 30 with winds of 145 miles an hour. But like nearly every other islander interviewed, he said he had no alternative but to accept the risk.</p>
        <p>"Where would I go?" asked Aminsharif, a 27-year-old Gomatali resident who also lost his entire family to the cyclone. "I have land here, and it's all I have. I have no choice but to stay."</p>
        <p>Mr. Aminsharif, who like most rural Bangladeshis has just one name, fervently hopes that the Government or foreign aid donors will build a cyclone shelter on the island. And it seems probable that the devastation last week will lead to new shelters along the coast, though not enough of them.</p>
        <p>But while such shelters offer good protection from cyclones, it is not clear that building new ones is the most efficient way of saving lives in a country so desperately poor.</p>
        <p>The cyclone's toll -- put at 125,000 by the official, but not overly reliable, count -- has captured international attention and spurred an outpouring of aid. But each year, without attracting much notice, about 870,000 Bangladeshi children under the age of 5 die routinely, a third of them from diarrhea caused by impure water. The cyclone has merely added a large increment of anguish to a grief that is chronic.</p>
        <p>Small amounts of aid, spread around efficiently, could save lives as effectively as storm shelters. United Nations officials say the aid would greatly enhance mundane projects like measles-vaccination campaigns or water purification systems.</p>
        <p>But it is also clear that cyclone shelters save lives. The reason so many people died is that they lived in crude huts that offered little protection from the elements. Those who lived in concrete homes had a far greater chance of surviving.</p>
        <p>In the Banskhali district, south of the port of Chittagong, virtually every hut within a few miles of the ocean was destroyed, and perhaps half the people in those houses died.  One Structure Was Spared</p>
        <p>But one remaining structure, battered but still looming over the bare mud flats once speckled with thatched-hut villages, is the two-floor concrete home of Abdulmobin, one of the most prosperous men in the area.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abdulmobin said that 30 people took refuge in his home during the cyclone, and that all survived except one man who was swept away when he opened the door during the storm.</p>
        <p>Despite an effort to build a string of shelters after a cyclone in 1970 in which 300,000 to 500,000 people died, there are not nearly enough. The island of Sandwip, for instance, has just 10 cyclone shelters, providing protection to 15,000 people even though 300,000 people live there.</p>
        <p>In all, Bangladesh has 302 cyclone shelters, while 5,000 to 10,000 are needed. But each shelter costs $50,000 to build, and Bangladesh already had a budget deficit before the cyclone. If more is spent on shelters, less must be spent on other forms of relief.</p>
        <p>There has been some progress over the decades. The latest cyclone was more intense than the one in 1970, yet this time far fewer people seem to have been killed. The unreliability of the death toll makes it difficult to be precise, but cyclone shelters and an early-warning system probably saved many lives.  Progress Is Slow</p>
        <p>Still, the pace of such progress is painfully slow.</p>
        <p>Bari Talukdar, executive engineer of the Bangladesh Water Development Board, said that with enough money the death toll from severe cyclones could be reduced to the hundreds from the hundreds of thousands. The money would go toward building more cyclone shelters and higher embankments to protect the shoreline and the islands from storm tides.</p>
        <p>"Now the time has come for rebuilding the embankment to protect against cyclones," Mr. Talukdar said. The old embankments, which were badly damaged by the wall of water that accompanied the cyclone, were intended to protect against high tides and modest squalls rather than cyclones. The old embankments were 12 to 15 feet high, but should be 18 to 25 feet to provide protection from major cyclones, he said.</p>
        <p>The problem is that construction of such embankments, when fortified with concrete or boulders, would cost about $25,000 per 100 feet. Kutubdia Island, one of the worst hit by the cyclone, is more than 30 miles in circumference. It would cost tens of millions of dollars to build an adequate dike around the perimeter of just that one island.</p>
        <p>In an ideal world, Kutubdia Island -- with an average elevation of only about five feet above sea level -- might simply be abandoned to the ocean. But population pressures in Bangladesh are such that people flock to any bit of land that peaks above the sea, for there is no room for them on the mainland.</p>
        <p>Bangladesh has a population of 118,000 million, and is growing by 2.4 million each year. At that rate, it takes just two or three weeks for the population to make up for the loss of 125,000 cyclone victims. As the population soars, more and more peasants move to the coastal areas and the islands, searching for work and for some earth to cultivate, whatever the risks.</p>
        <p>The American-financed project of the 1960's to reclaim agricultural land on Kutubdia by building protective embankments led to a big increase in the number of people living there. The result is that more people than ever are now at risk from cyclones.</p>
        <p>In the longer term, low-lying Bangladesh faces a grave threat from a rising sea level. Higher sea levels resulting from global warming could be catastrophic for Bangladesh. In 1988, severe flooding left nearly two-thirds of the country briefly under water; rising sea levels could increase the frequency of inundation and the risks to islanders and coastal dwellers alike.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 14, 1991, Tuesday</p>
        <p>Because of a transmission error, a front-page article on Saturday about Bangladesh misstated its population. It is 118 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 14, 1991, Tuesday</p>
        <p>Because of a transmission error, a front-page article on Saturday about Bangladesh misstated its population. It is 118 million.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
