<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Homeowners Revive Interest In Solar Power</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="469275"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOLAR ENERGY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIERDEN, ANDI</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D61E3CF936A1575BC0A967958260" item-length="1546" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Homeowners Revive Interest In Solar Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDI RIERDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RIERDEN, ANDI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN Berta Nelson's backyard in Norwich, past a cluster of pink phlox and a pyramid-shaped greenhouse that she designed and built, sits an array of blue solar panels facing south. As the sunlight streams down, the panels' photovoltaic cells convert the light to electricity. The current is then carried into the house and stored in eight batteries. The system, installed in June, supplies enough power to run Ms. Nelson's refrigerator, lights, television, typewriter and other appliances.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nelson said that even before she considered installing a solar electric system in her five-room house, which is shaded by two large oak trees, she had already cut her electric bill by 80 percent after buying a low-voltage refrigerator and by conserving energy as much as possible. After a month of receiving power from the sun, Ms. Nelson's electric bill was less than $5. Though Ms. Nelson may be an exception, an increasing number of people share her concerns, said advocates for solar power. They added that recent events like the Persian Gulf war and the debate over where to store the state's low-level radioactive waste have spurred interest in alternative energy sources, particularly the sun. "One of my dreams is to get off the grid for good," said Ms. Nelson, who is the house manager at a women's group home. For now, her solar electric system is automatically connected to the outside transmission network when she needs more electricity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN Berta Nelson's backyard in Norwich, past a cluster of pink phlox and a pyramid-shaped greenhouse that she designed and built, sits an array of blue solar panels facing south. As the sunlight streams down, the panels' photovoltaic cells convert the light to electricity. The current is then carried into the house and stored in eight batteries. The system, installed in June, supplies enough power to run Ms. Nelson's refrigerator, lights, television, typewriter and other appliances.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nelson said that even before she considered installing a solar electric system in her five-room house, which is shaded by two large oak trees, she had already cut her electric bill by 80 percent after buying a low-voltage refrigerator and by conserving energy as much as possible. After a month of receiving power from the sun, Ms. Nelson's electric bill was less than $5. Though Ms. Nelson may be an exception, an increasing number of people share her concerns, said advocates for solar power. They added that recent events like the Persian Gulf war and the debate over where to store the state's low-level radioactive waste have spurred interest in alternative energy sources, particularly the sun. "One of my dreams is to get off the grid for good," said Ms. Nelson, who is the house manager at a women's group home. For now, her solar electric system is automatically connected to the outside transmission network when she needs more electricity.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nelson said she bought the system through a dealer in California for $4,100 and paid another $1,500 for installation. To many people that might seem a major expense, she said, "but when you think about what we are paying in terms of air pollution and nuclear waste, deciding to go solar is really out of the domain of money."</p>
        <p>Judi Friedman, the president of People's Action for Clean Energy, which promotes energy alternatives and sponsors tours of solar-powered homes around the state, said that the group has received more inquiries since January than it did following the 1970's oil shortages. During that time fuel prices soared, and the Federal Government adopted an aggressive energy-conservation plan that included educating the public and offered tax breaks to encourage the purchase of solar-energy devices. But when the price of oil dropped in the early 1980's, so did the interest in solar power, she said.</p>
        <p>"In the last several years fuel has remained so cheap that the public has been lulled into not thinking about alternative energy," Mrs. Friedman said. "Now, however, many people are seriously considering if our dependence on fossil fuels and nuclear power is really worth all of the risk." Though solar equipment remains too expensive for the average homeowner, its advocates said, technological advances and new approaches to home design have made solar power more affordable and cost effective.</p>
        <p>Devices that contain photovoltaic cells like those purchased by Ms. Nelson are getting cheaper. Developed in the 1950's by Bell Telephone Laboratories as a possible power source for remote telephone systems, the cells concentrate sunlight, then reflect it back and forth between thin layers of silicon, dislodging electrons to form an electrical current.</p>
        <p>Photovoltaic cells can supply power for a host of small-scale applications. For several years Mrs. Friedman, who lives in Canton, has used a photovoltaic panel to supply electricity to a 12.5-volt engine that operates a pump to carry water from a pond uphill to her vegetable garden. The cells can also be used to power irrigation pumps as well as water heaters, calculators, electric cars and refrigerators.</p>
        <p>Another factor that has made solar power more attractive is the trend away from so-called active technologies that require panels, fans and pumps to collect and distribute heat, to "passive solar," which relies on a home's design and position in relation to the sun. To achieve the maximum benefits from the sunlight during the winter, Mrs. Friedman and her husband, Lou, cover their house's north-facing windows with quilted shades and leave those on the south side of the house undraped. The south windows are covered at night to keep in the warmth.</p>
        <p>The house also has an overhang above the south windows to prevent the warmth of the summer sun from overheating the house while allowing the full light from the low winter sun to come in.</p>
        <p>"We're an illustration of how even a traditional home can incorporate solar principles," said Mrs. Friedman. She added that combining passive solar methods with the use of fluorescent lightbulbs, energy-efficient appliances, energy-saving windows and heavy insulation enables homeowners to cut energy costs by at least 60 percent.</p>
        <p>Another example of passive solar is the Earth Shelter House owned by Henry and Betsy Noble in New Canaan. The house was designed by Donald Watson, the dean of the School of Architecture at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute in Troy, N.Y., a specialist in energy-conserving homes. Its north side is built into a hill, with the south side containing several energy-efficient windows and a large skylight. The average year-round temperature inside a house of this design is 60 to 70 degrees, said Mr. Watson, who has designed more than 50 solar homes in Connecticut. Living With the Sun</p>
        <p>To make better use of the daylight, Mr. Watson said, he devised a shading system around the windows that bounces light up to the ceiling and farther into the interior. The system reduces glare yet allows the Nobels to extend the use of natural light.</p>
        <p>"Living here with the motion of the sun is just dreamy," said Mrs. Nobel, whose husband is a former First Selectman of New Canaan.</p>
        <p>Solar homes built during the 1960's and 70's typically used roof-mounted solar collectors to take in the sun's heat, which was then transferred to other parts of the house with fans. Mr. Watson designed one of the first solar homes in Connecticut for Dorothy Eames of Groton in the late 1970's. The system includes 18 solar collectors and cost around $15,000. It provides for around 85 percent of the home's year-round energy needs and requires little maintenance, she said, adding that she uses a wood stove for backup heating.</p>
        <p>Around the time that the house was built, the Federal Government created tax breaks that cut 40 percent off the cost of solar equipment. Connecticut offered $600 grants, cutting the price even further. While those incentives lasted, thousands of people bought solar water heaters, said Ed Butler of Sunrise Solar Services in Winsted.</p>
        <p>"People who had no real commitment to solar would ask me to install a heater just because their accountant said it would be a good idea," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Butler was among a team of solar experts from Connecticut who were hired during the Carter Administration to install 32 solar collectors on the West Wing of the White House to heat water for the kitchen. The panels came down soon after Ronald Reagan was elected President and were put into storage.  Systems Built to Last</p>
        <p>In 1985, as part of the Reagan budget cuts, the Federal tax credits ended, and the solar-power industry immediately went into a deep slumber. "It was a real blow to business," Mr. Butler said.</p>
        <p>Today he mainly does general plumbing work and maintains existing solar-power systems, he said. "It's primarily changing antifreeze and that sort of thing," he said. "Solar water heaters just don't break down that often."</p>
        <p>He said the water in the solar heater in his plumbing shop gets up to 100 degrees in the winter. Depending upon how much water is used, the systems can generally provide more than 70 percent of hot water year-round. Since the Persian Gulf crisis began, said Mr. Butler, requests for new installations have picked up, but they have not yet reached the tempo of the 1970's and early 80's.</p>
        <p>Though state grants for solar energy are no longer available, qualified home buyers and owners of some residential buildings can obtain low-interest loans through the State Department of Housing for the purchase of alternative energy devices. Legislators are also scheduled to decide this fall whether to renew a law that exempts residents from paying a sales tax on solar equipment.</p>
        <p>Solar-power advocates said they would like to see the government develop a more aggressive energy-conservation policy that would include educating consumers about the advantages and cost-effectiveness of solar energy as well as reinstating the tax breaks to homeowners and to industries that develop such alternatives. Without incentives, they said, this latest surge of interest may fizzle, too.</p>
        <p>As for Ms. Nelson of Norwich, she said she is planning to increase her solar power by buying more photovoltaic panels as well as a solar-electric water heater. She has acquired the funds to purchase her system from money left to her by her mother, a longtime conservationist and solar-energy supporter who died last year.</p>
        <p>Flipping through an alternative energy catalogue that contained everything from wind generators to solar toys, she talked about having an open house in the fall to demonstrate how her system operates.</p>
        <p>"I've dreamed about going solar for such a long, long time," she said. "And now that it's done, boy does it feel good."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
