<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Perils of Pig Farming Touch Man and Beast</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="469379"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PIGS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDUSTRIAL AND OCCUPATIONAL HAZARDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FARMERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESPIRATORY DISEASES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AMMONIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHANE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HYDROGEN SULFIDE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IOWA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLDERNESS, DEAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KILBORN, PETER T</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Iowa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Respiratory Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Iowa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Farmers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Respiratory Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrogen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DF1531F936A1575BC0A967958260" item-length="1637" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Perils of Pig Farming Touch Man and Beast</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER T. KILBORN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KILBORN, PETER T</byline>
      <dateline>IOWA CITY</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the hot nursery, where the temperature is kept around 80 degrees, pigs are raised from weaning to a weight of 40 pounds, and in the adjacent, cooler nursery they grow to 100 pounds. As Dean Holderness, who raises the pigs, steps out of the building, the doorknob rattles.</p>
        <p>"Door knobs last a year, year and a half," Mr. Holderness says. Gases produced by the pigs' urine and feces corrode metal, he explains.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the hot nursery, where the temperature is kept around 80 degrees, pigs are raised from weaning to a weight of 40 pounds, and in the adjacent, cooler nursery they grow to 100 pounds. As Dean Holderness, who raises the pigs, steps out of the building, the doorknob rattles.</p>
        <p>"Door knobs last a year, year and a half," Mr. Holderness says. Gases produced by the pigs' urine and feces corrode metal, he explains.</p>
        <p>The ammonia, carbon dioxide, carbon monoxide, methane and hydrogen sulfide that collect in buildings like this are no better for the farmers who work there than they are for the door knobs.</p>
        <p>Lately, some farmers have been alarmed to learn that the gases, along with the dust of pig dander, particles of feed and of dry manure, cause unusually high incidences of respiratory ailments, from coughing and sniffles to lung scarring and pneumonia, conditions that many have long attributed to weather or allergies.</p>
        <p>Such facts poke another hole in the mythology of American farming. For all the surface serenity of places like the Holderness farm, about 15 minutes from downtown Iowa City where the horizon shimmers with green and dun-colored waves of rolling corn and soybean fields, Grant Wood homesteads and grazing livestock, agriculture is and always has been a perilous business.</p>
        <p>Farmers lose limbs and lives to accidents with machinery. They get bitten, kicked and sometimes killed by livestock. They can be poisoned by chemicals.</p>
        <p>The National Safety Council in Chicago reports that last year, 42 of every 100,000 agricultural workers were killed, just one fatality below the rate for miners and six times the rate for manufacturing.</p>
        <p>While all farmers face peril, pig farmers face more than most. Because they raise the corn and often the soybeans they feed their pigs, they are as vulnerable to planting and harvesting dangers as other farmers. Those who raise swine indoors also have to contend with fouler air than that of Rust Belt factories.</p>
        <p>Studies at the University of Iowa here suggest that more than half of the roughly 240,000 farmers who produce the nation's pork, predominantly on family farms, contract a variety of maladies. The health problems are largely a result of the shift most farmers have made in the last 20 years to raising pigs in confined indoor spaces instead of outdoors in barnyards and pastures.  Lethal Gas</p>
        <p>At the extreme, 19 American farmers died instantly in the 1980's from inhaling hydrogen sulfide produced by the decomposing hog waste, said Dr. Kelly J. Donham, a professor of agricultural medicine at the Univerity of Iowa. The gas, he said, is as lethal as the hydrogen cyanide that some states use to execute criminals.</p>
        <p>Pigs, the source of hot dogs and ham, sausage and bacon, are raised on one in eight American farms. Pig farming is particularly important to Iowa, the nation's top pork producer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Holderness, who has spent 20 of his 30 years working on his family's farm, raises 3,500 pigs a year and has been doing the work alone since his father retired a few years ago.</p>
        <p>"Every fall I get pneumonia," he said. "Walking pneumonia. I go to the doctor and take X-rays and get penicillin, and back I have to go." He also has two penny-sized splotches on his lungs, which are evidently benign, and in the winter he said he gets rashes on his arms, probably from handling the feed or moldy hay.  'Down You Go'</p>
        <p>He has broken a knuckle, damaged a knee and has had a quarter of an inch of each of his two big toes removed. He said 600-pound pregnant sows bucked him and stomped on his shoes, crushing the steel-reinforced tips. "They go up between your legs and down you go, like football," he said.</p>
        <p>Respiratory ailments like those suffered by hog farmers also afflict dairy farmers whose cows spend part of the winter indoors. They also afflict workers called chicken catchers who collect poultry in huge enclosed sheds, according to studies by Stephen Lenhart and other scientists at the National Institute of Occupational Safety and Health.</p>
        <p>Most of the ailments associated with the confinement of livestock subside when farmers stay out of the buildings and can usually be prevented if farmers install better ventilation and wear respirators.</p>
        <p>But respirators that filter out both dust and toxic gases are cumbersome to wear, and effective ventilation is costly for farmers, who typically earn $20,000 to $40,000 a year raising pigs, so few take such precautions. "Farmers are disabled by respiratory disease more than any other occupational group," said Dr. Donham.</p>
        <p>Pig farmers in the United States and Europe were driven to indoor pens by the need to keep production prices down, to raise more pigs that are uniformly lean and to maintain production through the winter. Dale Shires, director of the office of the Iowa State Agricultural Extension Service here, said year-round production helped farmers earn steadier incomes.</p>
        <p>In this part of Iowa, experts say, about two-thirds of the pig farmers use some confinement methods. Some use partial confinement, moving the pigs outdoors after the nursery stage. Some confine as many pigs as they have room for and raise the overflow outdoors. Skimpy Statistics</p>
        <p>Statistics on disease and injury among farmers are notoriously skimpy because farmers do not have to report them as most other employers must. While the Occupational Safety and Health Administration reports high rates of some agricultural accidents and illnesses, it keeps no record of respiratory diseases.</p>
        <p>What data the agency does collect come from only the 3 or 4 percent of the nation's 2.1 million farms that have more than 10 employees. Congress, reflecting farmers' discomfort with regulation, bars the agency from all but those bigger farms.</p>
        <p>So Dr. Donham's study is among the most comprehensive works on disease in agriculture. He monitored 207 swine confinement workers at 108 farms in Iowa from 1985 to 1990. In an interview, he said that at the start of the study, 25 percent were found to have chronic bronchitis, twice the rate of other farmers.</p>
        <p>He said about 25 percent had asthma-like reactive airways disease, 20 percent suffered from mucous membrane irritation and 30 percent had something he calls organic toxic dust syndrome. "That's like a real bad case of the flu," Dr. Donham said. There was overlap in the groups that had those ailments, he said, but 60 percent had at least one of them.</p>
        <p>In general, farmers will hear nothing of the Government regulations that have helped improve safety in other businesses.</p>
        <p>"If you get hurt by something, it's your fault," said Randy Lackender, who is taking over an eastern Iowa farm from his father.  'Hog Knees'</p>
        <p>Mr. Lackender said his father has a pair of "hog knees," artificial knee joints that were implanted after years of injuries caused by temperamental sows.</p>
        <p>On another farm near here, John Wall and his son Tom raise about 1,500 pigs a year without hired help on 800 acres where they also grow corn and soybeans. They have improved ventilation in their confinement buildings, and they wear masks in winter.</p>
        <p>But Tom Wall said: "In the winter I'll still be short of breath and cough for three days if I stay more than two hours in there. I'm 31 years old; I have two kids; I want to be around."</p>
        <p>Some bigger pork producers have made ambitious investments to guard against the hazards of confinement. Richard Oberman of rural Iowa City and his son Chuck have 440 sows, 25 boars and produce about 10,000 young pigs a year. They raise these "feeder" pigs to 40 pounds and sell them to farmers who will feed them to a finished weight of about 240 pounds, when they are slaughtered. Advanced Ventilation</p>
        <p>The Obermans last year built an enormous confinement unit, covering half an acre. Its walls can be rolled partly down in good weather, and it has an advanced ventilation system that draws air through the roof, mixes it with the air in the building, then pulls it down to the waste pits and expels it from the lower level of the building.</p>
        <p>"It's very efficient," Richard Oberman said. "It's an intensively managed production unit." People entering the building must take a shower and put on clothes that are kept on the site. The Obermans insist on this to protect the pigs from diseases that might be brought in from outside.</p>
        <p>The men wear heavy earmuffs because of the racket the pigs make with their metal feed bins, and when the weather cools and the walls are closed, they wear dust-filtering face masks.  Chuck Oberman said he and his one employee spend 40 hours a week in the building.</p>
        <p>How much pigs suffer from the air and the crowding in confinement units is a matter of debate among farmers and animal welfare groups. Farmers say sows produce litters in confinement that are as least as large as those produced outdoors and cite this as evidence of the pigs' good health.  Stresses of Confinement</p>
        <p>But the stresses of confinement do show. Confined hogs nervously leap to their feet when someone enters the buildings, and some studies have shown high incidences of their biting one another's tails, a problem farmers combat by removing their sharpest teeth.</p>
        <p>Some studies have found pneumonia in the lungs of slaughtered swine, Dr. Donham said. But the cumulative damage of the dust and gas they breathe is probably minor. A market animal's "farrow-to-finish" lifetime is only six months, so exposure to foul confinement air before being trucked to the packing plant is relatively short.</p>
        <p>Larry Noel of Rockford, Iowa, raises 8,000 hogs a year in a system similar to that of the Obermans. He installed the system after two bouts of pneumonia. He sees signs of boredom and stress among the pigs and says he is looking for ways to counter it. Bowling balls make good toys, he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
