<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oil's Inconvenient Bonanza</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="418370"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PROFITS (INDUSTRY-WIDE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY ACTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSIAN GULF WAR</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAYES, THOMAS C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D71731F934A15752C0A967958260" item-length="1832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oil's Inconvenient Bonanza</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS C. HAYES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAYES, THOMAS C</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In almost any industry, a batch of quarterly earnings reports heralding huge profit gains would bring on buoyant appraisals from gleeful executives. But not Big Oil. Despite vigorous profit gains in the fourth quarter announced last week by several oil giants, few industry executives were celebrating.</p>
        <p>In releasing 1990 results, leaders of the nation's largest, international oil companies took pains to stress that their stunning profits from the last three months of 1990 were a solitary event, a bonanza from high oil prices that was unlikely to be repeated anytime soon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In almost any industry, a batch of quarterly earnings reports heralding huge profit gains would bring on buoyant appraisals from gleeful executives. But not Big Oil. Despite vigorous profit gains in the fourth quarter announced last week by several oil giants, few industry executives were celebrating.</p>
        <p>In releasing 1990 results, leaders of the nation's largest, international oil companies took pains to stress that their stunning profits from the last three months of 1990 were a solitary event, a bonanza from high oil prices that was unlikely to be repeated anytime soon.</p>
        <p>Oil prices have indeed dropped since war broke out in the Persian Gulf and an oversupply of crude is expected to depress prices further when the conflict ends, taking oil industry profits with them.</p>
        <p>And oil companies say their earnings from the last quarter were dramatic in large part because the corresponding 1989 period against which they are compared was the worst in a decade for the industry. Analysts expect the fourth-quarter operating profits for the 12 largest oil producers to increase by an average of 70 percent over the same period in 1989.</p>
        <p>The oil executives' somber tone is intended in part to blunt populist opposition in Congress. Given the public anger over high prices at the gas pump since the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait last August and the anticipated wild increases in oil company earnings, some representatives drafted bills earlier this month proposing that oil companies be taxed on windfall profits made from the high price of crude.</p>
        <p>The breathtaking collapse in crude prices immediately after war flared in the Persian Gulf on Jan. 16 -- prices fell by $10.56 a barrel the next day -- may help muffle opposition on Capitol Hill for now. The closing price on Friday for the March contract of domestic light, sweet crude, was about $21.35 per barrel, far below the average crude price of nearly $30 a barrel in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>But some longstanding adversaries of Big Oil may not back off so readily. "It is very disturbing to conservationists that the oil companies have profited so greatly by the war and the runup in oil prices," said Sharon Newsome, vice president for resources conservation at the National Wildlife Federation, one environmental group urging the oil companies to put profits into alternative energy sources.</p>
        <p>The airline industry, which consumes huge quantities of jet fuel to power its 19,000 flights a day in the United States, is also up in arms and has appealed to Washington for help. It suspects that oil companies kept jet fuel prices high in the last months of the year to recapture profits lost when competition stiffened and demand lapsed in gasoline sales after the initial jump in prices this fall.</p>
        <p>While the price of jet fuel was 8 cents a gallon below that of wholesale gasoline when Iraq invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2, it has ranged between 9 and 40 cents per gallon above gasoline since mid-August, according to the Energy Department.</p>
        <p>"We have borne far more of the crude-oil price increase," said Edward A. Merlis, vice president of policy and planning at the Air Transport Association, the airlines' trade group in Washington.</p>
        <p>Expecting newspaper headlines telling of huge, fourth-quarter profit increases that would soon appear, Kenneth T. Derr, Chevron's chairman, two weeks ago told reporters : "I would hope that we don't end up with a major political problem over a quarter that I would refer to as an anomaly. Today, we are earning at a significantly lower rate than the fourth-quarter average."</p>
        <p>The quarterly gains reported by Exxon, Mobil, Texaco, Chevron, Amoco and Shell -- the nation's six largest companies ranked by sales -- were nevertheless dramatic. Net income for the world's largest oil company, Exxon, soared more than threefold, to $1.56 billion. Mobil's profit rose 45.6 percent. Texaco was up 35 percent, and Amoco, by 68.6 percent. Chevron earned $633 million, after a loss of $883 million in the period a year ago, which was caused by write-offs and other charges totaling $1.2 billion. Shell Oil's earnings jumped by 68.9 percent.</p>
        <p>In fact, these quarterly profits might have been much larger. But each of the top five lowered their reported profits with bookkeeping tactics that oil giants often employ legally to pare taxes in periods when profits -- and public resentment -- are on the rise.</p>
        <p>The five companies settled legal and tax disputes, wrote down the values of aging or unwanted oilfields, tallied losses from jettisoned refineries and plants and added millions to reserves for cleaning up oilfields and refineries.</p>
        <p>But the oil companies point out that the write-offs were even heftier in last year's final quarter, another reason the final 1990 quarter appeared so prosperous. Exxon, for instance, wrote off $800 million in the last quarter a year ago for costs to clean up the Exxon Valdez oil spill in Alaska. With that expense removed, Exxon's profit in the quarter a year ago was $1.29 billion, and its percentage gain in the 1990 fourth quarter was 21 percent, not 221 percent.</p>
        <p>In the fourth quarter of 1990, all of the majors reported spectacular profit increases in their exploration units because crude prices in the averaged about $10 a barrel more than in the last three months of 1989. Mobil's profit in its domestic exploration unit rose more than fivefold, to $68 million, and in its larger foreign unit by 72 percent, to $505 million. The average global price for its crude was $27, compared with $17 in the similar period a year ago.</p>
        <p>Because the five companies each refine much more crude oil than they produce, they must buy vast supplies on global crude markets. Exxon, for example, refined an average of 3.3 million barrels of crude a day in the fourth quarter, while producing half as much from its own oilfields, or an average of 1.6 million barrels a day.</p>
        <p>Because the price of crude was falling for most of the quarter while retail prices remained steady, profit margins rose for refining operations in most companies. Crude costs moved lower through November and much of December, after rising the previous quarter, and that cut refiners' expenses. Profit margins increased because prices for wholesale and retail gasoline prices drifted lower at a slower rate than crude prices. Those condition were ideal for refining units of most big oil companies.</p>
        <p>Despite the spectacular final quarter, the profit picture for all of 1990 was mediocre. That is because world oil prices averaged about $20 a barrel in the first three months of 1990, before slipping below $16 a barrel in the spring quarter. Analysts estimate that year-to-year gains were in a range of 10 percent to 12 percent. Exxon's net income, excluding the huge Valdez expense, rose 7.6 percent. Mobil's profit rose 6.7 percent and Amoco's, by 19 percent.</p>
        <p>And contrary to a survey by Chevron showing that most Americans believe oil is more profitable than most businesses, the oil industry has been a weak sister. The industry earned an average of about $12.50 on every $100 of capital invested during the last 20 years, compared with $13.40 for the average industry. Several industries like software, beverages, pharmaceuticals, hotels, gaming and publishing did much better during the 80's.</p>
        <p>The surge in crude prices in the last half of 1990 pushed Chevron and Exxon to a rate of return on equity above $15 for every $100. In Chevron's case, it was the first time since 1981.</p>
        <p>But that kind of return may be short-lived. The world is awash with oil, a result of rising output, mainly from Saudi Arabia since the Persian Gulf flare up, and slumping demand for crude. And Saddam Hussein has not appeared able to disrupt supplies: Tankers have moved safely from Saudi loading ports on the Persian Gulf since war erupted, apparently out of the reach of Iraqi forces.</p>
        <p>"The world has ample crude inventories now, and it is going to have more," said Richard J. Kruizenga, Exxon's vice president for corporate planning. He said global crude supplies amounted to 150 million barrels, and that the surplus was rising by 500,000 barrels a day. Consumption outside the Soviet Union is 54.1 million barrels a day.</p>
        <p>Analysts agree that if it were not for trader fears about Saddam Hussein's potential for havoc on oilfields in the Middle East, crude would be selling for far less than $20 a barrel. Dillard P. Spriggs, president of Petroleum Analysis Ltd., in New York, said crude prices could easily fall below $15 if the war ends in a few months.</p>
        <p>William L. Randol, an oil analyst at the First Boston Corporation, said oil prices should average a little more than $20 a barrel in 1991 if war ends before summer -- a prospect that means the industry's quarterly gains would not be nearly as spectacular as for the last quarter of 1990.</p>
        <p>"It is impossible to forecast what conditions we may face," Mr. Derr of Chevron said this week. THE OPTIONS IN ENERGY PATHS</p>
        <p>The prospects of bloodshed in distant oilfields vital to the American economy is certain to intensify the call from Washington for reduced reliance on Middle East oil.</p>
        <p>Large oil companies say they want new supplies, too, but will be unable to find them without improvements in profitability, which despite impressions to the contrary, have lagged behind other manufacturers.</p>
        <p>A Texaco-sponsored survey showed that the public opposes the use of taxes to finance the search for oil and natural gas in places other than the Middle East, as well as other forms of energy like geothermal, synthetic fuels and methanol, according to a William K. Tell Jr., a company executive. "They want to see the money come from industry investments," he said. "But I don't see how they can expect that if they are critical of the earnings of an industry that is looking at such moderate rates of return."</p>
        <p>Many environmentalists fault oil companies for devoting most of their capital budgets to extending their search for oil, preferring that they spend more on renewable energy sources like wind and solar power. "Oil companies have resisted those changes," said Sharon Newsome, of the National Wildlife Federation. "Their alternatives to oil, like oil shale, coal gasification and synfuels, are damaging to the environment and have an enormous impact on global warming."</p>
        <p>Yet environmentalists and oil executives have found some common ground in recent years by promoting a cleaner-burning fuel: natural gas. The United States is nearly self-sufficient in natural gas, with known reserves much larger than for oil.</p>
        <p>The problem is raising billions of dollars needed to shift a gasoline-reliant economy toward using more natural gas.</p>
        <p>Some oil companies have formed partnerships with natural-gas distributors. "If they make a profit doing so, so be it and more power to them," said Jeffrey Seisler of the Natural Gas Vehicle Coalition in Washington. "In terms of national security and energy security, this is a very positive move forward."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
