<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Exxon Plans Additive for Cleaner Fuel</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="472656"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHYL TERTIARY BUTYL ETHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHORTAGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">EXXON CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAYES, THOMAS C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DB123BF933A2575AC0A967958260" item-length="805" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Exxon Plans Additive for Cleaner Fuel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS C. HAYES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAYES, THOMAS C</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS, Sept. 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Exxon Corporation today became the latest refiner to announce plans to invest millions of dollars in new plants to produce an essential component of cleaner-burning fuel.</p>
        <p>Analysts say the component, methyl tertiary butyl ether, could be in short supply for the next few years as tougher laws take effect to limit smog-related pollution, raising demand for cleaner fuels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Exxon Corporation today became the latest refiner to announce plans to invest millions of dollars in new plants to produce an essential component of cleaner-burning fuel.</p>
        <p>Analysts say the component, methyl tertiary butyl ether, could be in short supply for the next few years as tougher laws take effect to limit smog-related pollution, raising demand for cleaner fuels.</p>
        <p>Exxon U.S.A., a Houston-based subsidiary of the big oil company, said it expected to spend more than $100 million to build plants to make the compound, known as M.T.B.E., at its three largest American refineries.  Plans for This Year</p>
        <p>Construction on the first plant is to begin this year at Exxon's refinery in Baton Rouge, La., with work on another planned for 1993 in Baytown, Tex. Plans for a third plant, at Exxon's refinery in Benicia, Calif., north of San Francisco, are under study.</p>
        <p>The Clean Air Act, passed by Congress in 1990, requires cleaner-burning gasoline to be sold beginning in the fall and winter next year in 41 metropolitan areas, including most of the nation's largest cities. The anti-pollution standards for gasoline will be toughened again in 1995 and further in 2000.</p>
        <p>Several large gasoline marketers, including ARCO, Shell and Exxon, began testing sales of cleaner-burning premium gasoline blends using M.T.B.E. more than a year ago. The oil companies are depending on these reformulated blends to blunt campaigns by some environmentalists to restrict gasoline sales sharply in the years ahead.</p>
        <p>"The Exxons of the world are trying to protect themselves from a shortage situation," said Urvan Sternfels, president of the National Petroleum Refiners Association, a trade group based in Washington. "There is a really serious question as to whether there is going to be enough oxygenates available to meet all of the new demand that we anticipate."</p>
        <p>William I. Ludlow, vice president of DeWitt &amp; Company, a consulting firm in Houston, said current supplies of M.T.B.E. appeared adequate to meet demand in the next few years, but could become tight when regulations are stiffened in 1995.</p>
        <p>M.T.B.E. includes an oxygen molecule that permits more thorough combustion of fuel by engines and reduces carbon monoxide and other exhaust emissions. The chemical compound had been used since the mid-1980's to raise octane levels in premium gasoline blends, but refiners have promoted it in the last few years as a way to reduce pollutants.</p>
        <p>The Clean Air Act mandates higher oxygen levels in gasoline next year in areas where carbon dioxide pollution produces a brown haze during the winter months, especially in high-altitude areas like Denver.  Practical Components</p>
        <p>M.T.B.E. and ethanol are considered the two most practical components available to refiners to raise oxygen levels to at least 2.7 percent of the gasoline mixture. Aromatics like benzene and toluene, once used to raise octane levels, have been restricted because of concerns that they help to create smog and may contribute to cancer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sternfels of the refiners association said many refiners favored M.T.B.E. because ethanol was more costly and could not be blended into gasoline transported through pipelines. Also, the building blocks of M.T.B.E., the common chemical feedstocks isobutylene and methanol, can be easily supplied.</p>
        <p>Total consumption of M.T.B.E. increased to 96,000 barrels a day last year, from 30,000 barrels a day in 1985, and will probably triple again to more than 300,000 barrels a day by 1995, said Joe Leonard, a petrochemical industry analyst at Chem Systems Inc., a consulting firm in Tarrytown, N.Y.</p>
        <p>"As more and more gasolines are reformulated for more cleaner-burning characteristics, M.T.B.E. will go into all gasolines, not just premium blends," he said.</p>
        <p>As recently as a year ago, few refiners produced their own M.T.B.E.; ARCO Chemical, which is 83 percent owned by ARCO Inc., accounted for 40 percent of the world's supply. Since then, Chevron, Conoco, Shell, Unocal, Amerada Hess and Mobil have announced plans to build plants within existing refineries.  Big Plants Planned</p>
        <p>Most of these plants will produce fewer than 5,000 barrels of M.T.B.E. a day for use within the same gasoline refineries. But Tenneco Inc. and Phillips Petroleum are building plants to produce more than 10,000 barrels a day and plan to sell much of the output to other gasoline refiners.</p>
        <p>With M.T.B.E. becoming a more important cost factor in gasoline output and future supplies uncertain, refiners want captive supplies, Mr. Sternfels said.</p>
        <p>Exxon U.S.A. currently buys M.T.B.E. from a sister company, Exxon Chemical, and from other suppliers. A spokesman for Exxon U.S.A., Henry Beathard, said the company decided to build its new plants because "we can produce it more cheaply than we can purchase it."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
