<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q&amp;A</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="578137"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTAINERS AND PACKAGING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD CONTAMINATION AND POISONING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAY, C CLAIBORNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DE1539F931A15751C1A964958260" item-length="540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q&amp;A</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. CLAIBORNE RAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAY, C CLAIBORNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cans Gone Bad</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>Why do spoiled cans of food swell?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cans Gone Bad</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>Why do spoiled cans of food swell?</p>
        <p>A. Cans of spoiled food may swell, and it is usually taken as a sign of spoilage, but canned food may be spoiled even if the can does not swell, said Dr. Joseph Hotchkiss, associate professor of food science at Cornell University in Ithaca, N.Y.</p>
        <p>If cans do swell, he said, it can be for two reasons, one chemical and one biological.</p>
        <p>Acid foods, like tomato juice, canned pineapple or almost any canned fruit, may attack the lining of a metal can, he said, and one of the byproducts of the chemical reaction is hydrogen gas. The gas exerts pressure inside the can, causing it to swell.</p>
        <p>"What food scientists call a hydrogen swell poses very little health risk, and you could probably eat the food, though it might taste metallic," he said, "but don't take a chance, because the other cause of swelling could be fatal, and a consumer has no reliable way of telling the difference."</p>
        <p>The second reason for swelling, Dr. Hotchkiss said, is that inadequate processing of the canned food could have left behind living microorganisms that are capable of reproducing, especially anaerobic organisms, which can live in the absence of oxygen. The organisms give off gases, mostly carbon dioxide, that can cause the can to swell.</p>
        <p>"This swelling can be a sign of very serious food spoilage that could cause illness or even death," he said. Botulism is of primary concern, he said. Other less dangerous microbes can also cause swelling, but to tell the difference, lab tests would be needed.</p>
        <p>"A rule of thumb for consumers is not to use cans that have pressure in them, on the chance that it might be of microbiological origin," Dr. Hotchkiss said. "When in doubt, throw it out."  Red-Blooded Fish</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>Do fish have blood, and if so what color is it? Why don't I see blood when I clean a fish?</p>
        <p>A.Fish do have blood, and it is red, said H. J. Walker, senior museum scientist in the marine vertebrates collection of the Scripps Institution of Oceanography in La Jolla, Calif.</p>
        <p>Other cold-blooded animals, like amphibians and reptiles, also have red blood, he said.</p>
        <p>Fish have a circulatory system with blood and a heart as the pump just like that of humans, Mr. Walker said, and just like that of humans, fish blood is red because it contains hemoglobin, the iron compound that carries oxygen.</p>
        <p>If a fish is fresh and is cut near major vessels, you will see blood, said Mr. Walker. In muscle tissue, which becomes filets, the vessels are so small that the blood may not be evident, he said, or if the fish is not fresh, the blood may have coagulated or collected in one part of the body.</p>
        <p>Fish from the fish market may have already been gutted and beheaded and so may be drained of most blood. Even so, Mr. Walker said, you might see blood around the spine, because a major blood vessel goes right under the arches of the vertebral column.</p>
        <p>Readers are invited to submit questions about science to Questions, Science Times, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036. Questions of general interest will be answered in this column, but requests for medical advice cannot be honored and unpublished letters cannot be answered individually.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
