<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="562497"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DD1431F931A25753C1A964958260" item-length="961" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-9  NEW SMOG ALARMS SCIENTISTS</p>
        <p>A vast pool of pollution over the South Atlantic is causing alarm among scientists, who say it may harm people and contribute to global warming. The cloud is also calling attention to the complex role of theozone as villain and blessing.  A1  SARAJEVO MOURNS ITS CHILDREN</p>
        <p>The death of three children in a mortar blast deepened Sarajevo's sense of desperation and bitterness. Numbed residents appear convinced that hope is finally lost.  A7</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-9  NEW SMOG ALARMS SCIENTISTS</p>
        <p>A vast pool of pollution over the South Atlantic is causing alarm among scientists, who say it may harm people and contribute to global warming. The cloud is also calling attention to the complex role of theozone as villain and blessing.  A1  SARAJEVO MOURNS ITS CHILDREN</p>
        <p>The death of three children in a mortar blast deepened Sarajevo's sense of desperation and bitterness. Numbed residents appear convinced that hope is finally lost.  A7</p>
        <p>PALESTINIAN PROTESTS GAIN VIGOR</p>
        <p>A prison hunger strike has breathed new life into the Palestinian uprising in the Israeli-occupied lands. Inmates have now agreed to suspend the strike in return for a pledge to study their living conditions.  A6  CASTRO'S ISLAND IN VIGIL</p>
        <p>President Castro has begun warning Cubans of a fateful confrontation with global capitalism. Among the more ominous preparations are a crackdown on dissent and calls for military preparedness.  A3  FIGHTING IN ANGOLAN CAPITAL</p>
        <p>Fighting broke out between police officers and opposition party soldiers in the worst breach yet of Angola's 18-month-old cease-fire.  A9  ANXIOUS ELECTION IN GEORGIA</p>
        <p>Anxious people stood in long lines in Georgia to give Eduard Shevardnadze their ballots and their hopes. The former Soviet Foreign Minister said his task was tougher than any he faced in the Kremlin.  A7  INVESTIGATING THE INVESTIGATORS</p>
        <p>The Justice Department found itself in a dispute with the F.B.I. over how the Government should determine whether evidence was concealed in a sensitive case involving Iraq.  A6  The Shining Path kills 44 people in an Andean village.  A8  Will Chinese Communists abolish a bastion of aging hard-liners?  A7  Germans watch the ascent of Chancellor Kohl's heir-apparent.  A4  Italy's Government survives an economic vote of confidence.  A6  National A10-17  RIVALS MEET FOR FIRST DEBATE</p>
        <p>With his Presidency in jeopardy, George Bush asked the American people tonight for more time to right the economy, but his economic stewardship came under fire from Bill Clinton and Ross Perot.  A1  ASSESSING THE DEBATE</p>
        <p>News analysis: Did the Presidential candidates do what they needed to do? Measured by that standard, the first of the three Presidential debates was a fair night for Clinton and Ross Perot and less than a triumph for the President.  A1  When great things are at stake, petty things matter.  A13  HEARD ANY JOKES LATELY?</p>
        <p>The searcher for trenchant political humor finds slim pickings during this election season -- "The recession has hit our business, too," one comic says -- but a troupe of comedians performing in a Manhattan basement stands out. A13  A WARNING FROM I.B.M.</p>
        <p>I.B.M. has warned its workers and other companies that two chemicals widely used in manufacturing semiconductor chips and in other industries may significantly increase the risk of miscarriage.  A1  'I WAS RECKLESS'</p>
        <p>Her backers said Lena Guerrero, the young, talented Hispanic chairwoman of the Texas Railroad Commission, would go far in politics. Nobody is making those predictions anymore after she resigned her post and apologized for falsifying her resume.  A10  REWRITING ESKIMO HISTORY</p>
        <p>Eskimos in Alaska see an unusual archeological dig that experts say could rewrite the history of Eskimo culture as a bargaining chip to push a multimillion-dollar deal to preserve some of North America's most extraordinary wildlife habitat.  A10  HELPING PROBLEM PRIESTS</p>
        <p>While priests who have sexually abused minors make up only a small fraction of the nation's Roman Catholic clergy, a series of criminal cases and lawsuits in recent years has focused attention on the church's handling of this problem.  A11  Metro Digest B1  LAST-DITCH FIGHT AGAINST TB</p>
        <p>As cases of drug-resistant tuberculosis increase, medical experts scramble to find new ways of treatment. Some of the nation's most desperate cases end up at the National Jewish Center in Denver. There, aggressive treatment combining drugs, shots and surgery gives them literally their last chance at a cure.  A1  A NEW, CRUELER, COLUMBUS</p>
        <p>On the 500th anniversary of Christopher Columbus's arrival in the New World, students across the nation are learning everything from skepticism to contempt for the explorer's exploits. And amid the revisionist wave, textbooks have played an important role in the changing perceptions.  A1  Business Digest D1  Arts/Entertainment C11-20  Thyssen art collection opens in Madrid.  C11  The 'Glengarry' math: Add stars and money, then subtract ego.  C11  Theater: Ann Magnuson.  C11  "Regina" at City Opera.  C11  From Joan Manuel Serrat.  C16  National Orchestra of Spain.  C18  Word and Image: "The Young Indiana Jones Chronicles." C18  Obituaries B8  Sports C1-9  Baseball: Jays rally for 3-1 series lead.  C1  Pirates afloat as Bonds awakens.  C1  Eckersely shows he's mortal.  C4  Eckersely shows he's mortal.  C4  Columns: Vecsey on Sanders C2  Football: Giants defeat Cards.  C1  Colts top Jets in overtime.  C1  Missed opportunity for Jets.  C5  Hockey: Devils have numbers to deal with.  C9  Horse Racing: Pleasant Tap horse to beat.  C9  Editorials/Op-Ed A18-19  Editorials  Only only answer deep.  Columbus, then and now.  Derek Walcott's embrace. Curbing violence in the schools.  Letters  Anthony Lewis: No knockouts.  William Safire: Clinton doesn't lose.  Deborah Tannen: The real Hillary factor.  Daniel M. Kasper: The sky is not the limit.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
