<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="557093"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2D6163BF93BA2575AC0A964958260" item-length="1101" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-10  CURRENCY MARKETS STEADY</p>
        <p>A day after Europe's system of economic coordination nearly collapsed, currency markets stabilized. But few ideas emerged to address the roots of the crisis.  A1  THE U.S. CAN DO LITTLE</p>
        <p>News analysis: American policies and actions contributed relatively little to the monetary crisis, and there is little Washington can do to alleviate it, economists said.  A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-10  CURRENCY MARKETS STEADY</p>
        <p>A day after Europe's system of economic coordination nearly collapsed, currency markets stabilized. But few ideas emerged to address the roots of the crisis.  A1  THE U.S. CAN DO LITTLE</p>
        <p>News analysis: American policies and actions contributed relatively little to the monetary crisis, and there is little Washington can do to alleviate it, economists said.  A1</p>
        <p>Many in Europe sense imports and travel will cost more.  D4  Despite hopes, Germany's central bank did not cut interest rates.  D5  A 'no' vote on unity means more chaos, France told its people.  D5  No apologies from Prime Minister Major of Britain.  D5  TESTIMONY TO BRUTALITY</p>
        <p>It is a grisly scene even for the Balkans' landscape of war: four charred, putrid bodies, sprawled by a road in Bosnia. They were said to be victims of an attack on a group of Serbian civilians.  A3  THE MIDEAST ROLLER COASTER</p>
        <p>One day after declaring progress with Israel, Syria said talks were deadlocked and could be saved only by American intervention.  A6  IRAQ BANK SCANDAL WON'T DIE</p>
        <p>At a hearing in which a former bank official was to be sentenced, his lawyer moved to withdraw the guilty plea and set the stage for a trial featuring accusations that the Bush Administration ignored the multibillion-dollar fraud.  A6  LESS FEAR OF NORTH KOREA</p>
        <p>The President of South Korea said that while he remained suspicious of North Korea, he was convinced that its drive to develop atomic weapons "had become weaker." A8  THAT'S NOT HITLER, RUSSIAN SAYS</p>
        <p>Although Hitler's jaw and parts of his skull are stored in Moscow, the body shown in a Soviet archive film is not that of the Nazi leader, a Russian historian said. He said Hitler's charred remains were found by Soviet troops in 1945.  A10  GREEN LIGHT FOR U.N. IN SUDAN</p>
        <p>With civilians cut off from food and medicine in war-torn southern Sudan, both sides in the civil war have agreed to let in aid flights, a United Nations official said.  A10  U.S. PLAN FOR SOMALIA</p>
        <p>After criticism of relief efforts in Somalia, the United States offered a six-point plan for fighting hunger there, but the United Nations fears Washington is undercutting the new relief coordinator's office.  A10  GUZMAN DOWN, FUJIMORI UP</p>
        <p>The arrest of the leader of the Shining Path insurrection has caused a surge in the political fortunes of President Fujimori, poll takers and politicians said.  A8  Amsterdam Journal: Women make a splash in Dutch politics.  A4  National A12-21  OPENING TELEPHONE SERVICE</p>
        <p>The Federal Communications Commission gave small telephone companies more opportunity to compete in local telephone service. Consumers moved closer to the day when they can choose a local telephone company like they now choose a long-distance carrier.  A1  IRAN-CONTRA INQUIRY ENDS</p>
        <p>More than five years after he began, the independent prosecutor investigating the Iran-contra affair said he was ending his inquiry and had no plans to seek other indictments.  A1  MAN VS. NATURE: SOME LESSONS</p>
        <p>South Carolina, ravaged by Hurricane Hugo three years ago, offers a lesson to residents of Florida, Louisiana and Hawaii in how much man can and cannot do to repair a world that nature blew apart.  A1  In Hawaii, visits to hurricane-ruined homes take an emotional toll.  A16  JUDGE'S IMPEACHMENT SET ASIDE</p>
        <p>A Federal judge overturned the impeachment verdict against Alcee Hastings, a former Federal district judge, saying he did not receive a fair trial in the Senate because a 12-member committee rather than the full Senate conducted the trial.  A1  LIMITED AGENDA FOR CONGRESS</p>
        <p>Democrats in Congress have decided to scale back their agenda, in part to forestall vetoes by President Bush and in part because they were unable to agree on health-care and abortion-rights legislation.  A12  HOUSE POST OFFICE DISCLOSURE</p>
        <p>A Federal grand jury investigating the House post office has reportedly been told that a member of Congress used the post office to cash at least one campaign check.  A12  PSYCHIATRIST OFFERS TO RESIGN</p>
        <p>Dr. Margaret Bean-Bayog, the Harvard psychiatrist accused of sexually abusing a patient and contributing to his suicide, offered to resign her medical license. But the state medical board refused to accept the letter and turned the matter over to an administrative judge.  A12  CARBON DIOXIDE'S ILL EFFECTS</p>
        <p>New evidence suggests that the rising carbon dioxide content of the earth's atmosphere may be even more damaging to plants than many scientists had believed.  A14  CONTEST FOR URBAN ETHNIC VOTES</p>
        <p>The end of the cold war has set off a new competition for conservative, anti-Communist voters, many of whom have been among the staunchest "Reagan Democrats." A20  A KINDER, GENTLER CLINTON?</p>
        <p>In the days before he had a lead over George Bush, Gov. Bill Clinton made a point of talking tough. Now, his speeches have a softer edge.  A20  President Bush pointedly attacks the Clinton economic plan.  A21  A CONQUERING UNDERDOG</p>
        <p>Outspent by two primary opponents, Russell D. Feingold made a stunning virtue in the recent Democratic Senate primary in Wisconsin of mocking the major cliches of modern American politicking.  A20  The role of Mark Gearan, campaign manager for Al Gore.  A21  Law Page A22  Three years after a Texas school bus crash, the legal frenzy continues.</p>
        <p>At the Bar  Metro Digest B1  DINKINS ASSAILS POLICE UNION</p>
        <p>Mayor Dinkins openly criticized the police union and some of its members, arguing in an emotional appearance that their rowdy demonstration at City Hall showed why minority communities lack confidence in some officers.  A1  ZUCKERMAN CLOSE TO NEWS DEAL</p>
        <p>Mortimer B. Zuckerman, the New York real-estate developer and owner of U.S. News &amp; World Report, became all but assured of acquiring the bankrupt Daily News, though a final understanding will probably not be reached until next week.  A1  Editorials/Op-Ed A34-35  Editorials  Europe, one way or another.  New York's finest mob.  A first step in Haiti.  The paper that won't drop dead.  Letters  A. M. Rosenthal: The drug papers.  Anthony Lewis: When reality strikes.  Matthew L. Lifflander: Switch, don't fight, Mr. Perot.  James P. Mooney: Watch cable TV rates rise. Business Digest D1  Weekend C1-35  Sports B8-14  Obituaries A26</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
