<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: The Environmental Debate; Gore Says Bush Is Hypocritical on Ecology Issues</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="547622"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLMES, STEVEN A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, ALBERT JR (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DD1E3CF937A3575BC0A964958260" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: The Environmental Debate; Gore Says Bush Is Hypocritical on Ecology Issues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN A. HOLMES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLMES, STEVEN A</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, Calif., Aug. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Giving full voice to an issue that has been muted in the early stages of the Presidential campaign, Senator Al Gore today sharply criticized President Bush for his environmental record, saying he had been hypocritical on those issues.</p>
        <p>In stops at a factory in Irvine, Calif., that makes environmentally safe intravenous bags for hospitals and at a plant here that recycles used motor oil, Mr. Gore sought to highlight his own credentials as an environmentalist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Giving full voice to an issue that has been muted in the early stages of the Presidential campaign, Senator Al Gore today sharply criticized President Bush for his environmental record, saying he had been hypocritical on those issues.</p>
        <p>In stops at a factory in Irvine, Calif., that makes environmentally safe intravenous bags for hospitals and at a plant here that recycles used motor oil, Mr. Gore sought to highlight his own credentials as an environmentalist.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, the Democratic Vice-Presidential nominee, used an appearance at the Evergreen Oil plant to underscore contrasts with Mr. Bush, who visited the same plant in June just after the United Nations Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro. The Tennessee Senator said the company was struggling to survive primarily because the Bush Administration had failed to promulgate regulations that would encourage the recycling of oil.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Evergreen is a member of the Hazardous Waste Treatment Council, an industry group that is suing the Environmental Protection Agency for its failure to draft regulations that company officials say would lead to more oil recycling. Currently, 90 percent of used motor oil is either burned or dumped in landfills. 'The Hypocritical President'</p>
        <p>"The American people trusted George Bush when he said he was going to be the environmental President," Mr. Gore told a crowd of employees and their families. "When George Bush came to Evergreen, he was the hypocritical President."</p>
        <p>Today's comments mark the first time Mr. Gore has made detailed criticism of the Administration's environmental record. His nomination was cheered by many environmentalists, who said it would mean that matters like pollution and global warming would receive more attention in the campaign. But until today, Mr. Gore had mainly articulated the broad outlines of the party's message and attacked the Administration's handling of the economy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's reluctance to speak on the environment is a marked contrast to criticism in his book, "Earth in the Balance: Ecology and the Human Spirit," of politicians -- including himself -- for not boldly addressing ecological issues.</p>
        <p>In the book's introduction he wrote that he had "become very impatient with my own tendency to put a finger to the political winds" when it came to environmental issues. Hitting Back</p>
        <p>Yet, as Mr. Gore steps up his comments on the environment, the Republicans have already begun to hit back, at times using Mr. Gore's book to try to portray him as an environmental extremist.</p>
        <p>Last week, after Mr. Gore spoke at a Washington clinic on women's health issues, Republican campaign workers circulated several pages from Mr. Gore's book that dealt with the harvesting of Pacific yew trees, whose bark yields the chemical taxol, which has shown promise as a treatment for ovarian, lung and breast cancers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore took no position on whether the trees should be harvested, but the message the Republicans intended to convey was that he cared more about trees than cancer victims. Jobs vs. the Environment</p>
        <p>Democrats acknowledge that Mr. Gore must proceed carefully, in the face of Republican charges that environmental proposals will cost jobs. The task for Democrats, these officials say, is to sell environmental protection as a job-creating program.</p>
        <p>"We've got to do a clear job of saying that the choice George Bush lays out there of the environment or jobs is an absolutely false one," said Senator Tim Wirth, a Colorado Democrat who is coordinating the campaign's environmental policy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's visits to both Evergreen Oil and McGaw Inc. in Irvine were intended to highlight the Democrats' message of creating jobs while saving the environment. McGaw manufactures an intravenous bag for hospitals that contains no polyvinyl chlorides and can therefore be recycled.</p>
        <p>Larry Watts, a company vice president, said McGaw had revenues last year of about $300 million, with $200 million of that coming from recyclable intravenous bags.</p>
        <p>In his speech to the company's employees, Mr. Gore said: "This demand in the marketplace for new, more environmentally efficient products is a worldwide demand. And if we are going to enjoy the kind of economic advantage in the 90's and in the next century that we want for our kids, we really should be leading this environmental revolution in all industries, the way you're leading it in your industry."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
