<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>California Proposal Would Let Industry Sell Pollution Rights</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="504402"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENSON, RICHARD W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DC133DF933A05752C0A964958260" item-length="1247" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>California Proposal Would Let Industry Sell Pollution Rights</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENSON, RICHARD W</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Jan. 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Southern California's air-quality regulators said today that they planned a radical new approach to controlling air pollution, allowing companies to purchase the right to pollute if they could not or chose not to reduce emissions on their own.</p>
        <p>The new approach, which is still subject to formal approval, would supplant the current system of tight company-by-company regulation and would be the largest and most ambitious attempt yet to clean up the air by replacing regulatory fiat with free-market forces.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Southern California's air-quality regulators said today that they planned a radical new approach to controlling air pollution, allowing companies to purchase the right to pollute if they could not or chose not to reduce emissions on their own.</p>
        <p>The new approach, which is still subject to formal approval, would supplant the current system of tight company-by-company regulation and would be the largest and most ambitious attempt yet to clean up the air by replacing regulatory fiat with free-market forces.</p>
        <p>Specific elements of the plan have brought opposition from business, labor and environmental groups as the proposal has been drafted in recent months, but regulators said they were confident that the basic concept would be approved by the board of the regulatory authority, allowing it to go into effect by 1994.</p>
        <p>Based on a long-debated concept known as emissions trading, the plan would dictate to polluters the amount by which they would have to reduce their emissions each year, but would not tell them how to do it. Businesses that developed techniques or technologies to reduce their emissions below the required levels would generate credits they could sell on the open market to other companies that were unable to meet the requirements or found it uneconomical to do so.</p>
        <p>The idea is to reduce the costs to companies while providing them with an economic incentive to cut emissions as much as possible and to develop antipollution processes. The concept, long advocated by economists, was endorsed in the Clean Air Act passed by Congress last year, and has been used to limited degrees within particular industries. Utilities are moving toward adopting it in their efforts to reduce acid rain, but it has yet to be applied across an entire region or on a scale envisioned by the California plan.</p>
        <p>Because the Southern California regulatory body, the South Coast Air Quality Management District, is extremely influential in policy circles throughout the country, many people involved in the issue said they expected the approach to spread to other regions with air-quality problems linked to factories, oil refineries, auto body shops and other stationary sources of pollution. The plan does not affect the regulatory approach to reducing emissions from automobiles. 'A Model for the Nation'</p>
        <p>"It's a tremendous departure in the sense that in the past the district has mandated regulations that specify a technology or a process or a housekeeping rule for how things should be done," said Joel Schwartz, a staff scientist for the Coalition for Clean Air, an environmental group. "Now the district is going to take its hands off and say that as long as you can prove you're getting real reductions you can do anything you want to reduce emissions, or you can buy permits from other companies that have proven they have reduced their emissions. This will be a model for the nation."</p>
        <p>The air-quality district has been drafting plans for the shift for nearly a year against a backdrop of growing pressure by the business community and elected officials to reduce the industrial costs of complying with Southern California's strict air pollution regulations. The air-quality district for many years was resistant to what is called the "marketable permits system," but its executive officer, James Lents, said in an interview today that achieving further improvements in the region's air required a new approach.</p>
        <p>"We have some of the world's strictest air-quality regulations in California, but it has not been enough to solve the air-quality problem here," Mr. Lents said. "We feel this will be a better system than the traditional command-and-control approach," he said, by giving businesses incentives to make additional improvements. Further Debate Likely</p>
        <p>While there is general consensus that the board of the air-quality district will approve the proposal, there will almost certainly be changes to specific elements of it as public debate on the issue intensifies between now and March 6, when the board is scheduled to vote. There also appears to be a minority on the board that is not yet convinced the program will work.</p>
        <p>"I have a real problem gambling on economic theory," said Larry Berg, a board member and the director of the Institute for Politics and Government at the University of Southern California.</p>
        <p>Representatives of environmental groups have been pushing the regulators to adopt a go-slow approach. They advocate limiting the program in the beginning to sources of nitrogen oxides, such as oil refineries and utilities, which can be monitored and measured relatively easily and accurately. The groups want the regulators initially to retain their traditional tight regulation of sources of reactive organic gases, such as those contained in paints, coatings and solvents, which are far more difficult to track.</p>
        <p>"We're concerned that the district not go forward with such a big plan and give up the whole regulatory structure until they've learned to make it work," said Mr. Schwartz of the Coalition for Clean Air. "They haven't proven to us that they'll be able to enforce the program." Why Labor Groups Worry</p>
        <p>Labor groups are also expressing some reservations about the concept. They say they fear that by allowing companies to sell their pollution rights the system will reward companies that choose to close plants in the region and move elsewhere, taking jobs with them. So labor groups are pushing for limits on the ability of companies that are leaving the area to sell their credits.</p>
        <p>"We don't want to deny companies the right to leave, but we don't want them packing off to Mexico with a sackful of money from selling their credits, either," said Kelly Candaele, a political representative for the Los Angeles Federation of Labor.</p>
        <p>Business groups have generally supported the concept as a way of making it more economical to stay and expand their operations in California. Although some smaller companies have expressed fears that larger competitors might benefit inordinately from looser regulation, most industries see emissions trading as giving them greater flexibility in dealing with the basic regulatory requirement of reducing pollution by a mandated percentage each year. Citing an Example</p>
        <p>A study conducted last month by the Regulatory Flexibility Group, a coalition of corporations in the Los Angeles area, cited the example of a small electronics firm that faced huge costs in reducing emissions of reactive organic gases from its semiconductor operations. To make the reductions on its own, the company would have to pay $200,000 per ton of annual emissions.</p>
        <p>But a company that paints or coats ships spends only $2,000 a ton to reduce its emissions of the same gases. Under an emissions trading program, the electronics company might be able to buy pollution credits from the ship-painting company for a price much closer to $2,000 a ton than $200,000, sharply reducing its expenses.</p>
        <p>As proposed by the air quality district, the plan would initially apply to the 2,000 companies in the region that account for 85 percent of the smog-forming hydrocarbons emitted by the businesses that the district monitors, and to the 700 businesses that account for 95 percent of nitrogen oxide emissions. The plan calls for smaller companies to be added to the program later, with only a handful of businesses, including restaurants and dry cleaners, likely to be exempted, Mr. Lents said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
