<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Supermarket Experiments With Ozone-Saving Coolant</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19920325T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="516446"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFRIGERATORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUPERMARKETS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GLENS FALLS (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">STOP 'N SAVE SUPERMARKET</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HANNAFORD BROTHERS CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920324T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DF123EF937A15750C0A964958260" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Supermarket Experiments With Ozone-Saving Coolant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>GLENS FALLS, N.Y., March 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Almost everyone agrees that chlorofluorocarbons, the chemicals destroying the earth's protective ozone layer, will have to be replaced, and President Bush recently moved to ban their manufacture after the end of 1995.</p>
        <p>But CFC's, as they are known, run nearly every refrigerator in the nation's 35,000 supermarkets, which account for about 20 percent of refrigeration in this country. What will be used next to keep the milk from spoiling and the ice cream from melting?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Almost everyone agrees that chlorofluorocarbons, the chemicals destroying the earth's protective ozone layer, will have to be replaced, and President Bush recently moved to ban their manufacture after the end of 1995.</p>
        <p>But CFC's, as they are known, run nearly every refrigerator in the nation's 35,000 supermarkets, which account for about 20 percent of refrigeration in this country. What will be used next to keep the milk from spoiling and the ice cream from melting?</p>
        <p>No one is sure, and the deadline is looming. But at a lectern in front of the bok choy, kale and spinach in the produce department here today, Government and industry officials introduced what they said was the nation's first "ozone friendly" supermarket. The store, a 63,000-square-foot Stop 'n Save that opened on Sunday, provides the first large-scale test of an alternative refrigerant.</p>
        <p>CFC's "are chemicals we all take for granted in our modern life," said William D. Cotter, the chairman of the State Energy Research and Development Authority, one sponsor of the $1.5 million test.</p>
        <p>But replacing CFC's is more complicated than it looks; apart from one fatal flaw, destruction of the ozone, CFC's are cheap, efficient, relatively nontoxic and inert. Substitutes have proven incompatible with piping and other equipment and sometimes have been less efficient, a big issue for an industry that uses 4 percent of the nation's electricity.</p>
        <p>The new store here, the 89th opened by Hannaford Brothers Company of Scarborough, Me., uses a refrigerant called 134a, which has no chlorine and therefore does not break up ozone in the stratosphere. The ozone at that level of the atmosphere provides the earth with partial protection from the most dangerous form of ultraviolet radiation. Scientists predict that increasing damage to the ozone layer will cause increases in cases of skin cancer and damage to crops.</p>
        <p>The chemical 134a is not new, but many companies have stayed away from it because tests of its toxicity are incomplete. It does have another problem besides ozone destruction: it contributes to global warming by increasing the trapping of solar heat by the atmosphere. But it is only about one-tenth as bad in that respect as chlorofluorocarbons, which are believed to be responsible for as much as 25 percent of global warming. Supermarket With a Difference</p>
        <p>The Stop 'n Shop, which looks from the outside just like any newly opened supermarket, down to the giant inflatable man on the roof, in green overalls holding a sack of groceries. But inside it is different in many ways.</p>
        <p>This store's refrigerator cases and air-conditioners all run on 134a. Both have computer controls to try to cut energy use, operating at variable speeds rather than cycling on and off, as a home refrigerator does, which is less efficient. In addition, all the cases, including the ones that hold milk and beer, have doors. Vendors have long resisted doors, but they cut energy use by up to 60 percent.</p>
        <p>The freezers, at least temporarily, run on a compound related to CFC's, which will eventually be banned as well. Hannaford would like to replace that too, but 134a cannot chill freezers effectively. For that reason, 134a has already found its way into some prototype auto air-conditioners, but is probably not going to work in home refrigerator-freezers.</p>
        <p>The new compound sells for about $11 a pound now, but Hannaford expects the price to come down to $6 with volume production. The old CFC refrigerant, R-12, used to sell for 60 cents a pound, but it is now $3.60, and will reach $6 as supplies get more scarce, said Thomas Mathews, Hannaford's refrigeration specialist.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the refrigeration market only seems to grow, especially in supermarkets. "Everyone in the family is working, and eating more prepared foods," said Raymond J. Albrecht, the senior project manager at the State Energy Research and Development Authority. "We want more choices," he said, so the refrigerator cases get longer and longer. Closely Watched Experiment</p>
        <p>Many store chains are watching this experiment closely. In addition to Hannaford, 15 companies contributed equipment to this experiment, and Allied-Signal Inc., which has its headquarters in Morristown, N.J. and a research lab in Buffalo, donated the refrigerant itself. The Electric Power Research Institute, a national research consortium, and the Empire State Electric Energy Research Coroporation, its New York counterpart, also chipped in. The test includes three different types of compressors, the devices that squeeze the heat out of the refrigerant; each type will run the whole system for a week to see which works best.</p>
        <p>The system was built with careful attention to the piping, with bigger pipes and fewer joints, to hold down leaks. A typical supermarket can leak hundreds of pounds of refrigerant a month, which was not important at 60 cents a pound but means more at $6. Among the techniques to be used here are fluorescent dyes in the refrigerant, so that leaks can be spotted easily with an ultraviolet light.</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 25, 1992, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day yesterday about a supermarket in Glens Falls, N.Y., that is experimenting with refrigerants to replace chlorofluorocarbons misstated its name. The store is Shop 'n Save.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 25, 1992, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day yesterday about a supermarket in Glens Falls, N.Y., that is experimenting with refrigerants to replace chlorofluorocarbons misstated its name. The store is Shop 'n Save.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
