<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Fight Smog, 8 Northeast States Adopt New Curbs on Power Plants</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="518793"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOG</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NITROGEN OXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW HAMPSHIRE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MAINE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">VERMONT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RHODE ISLAND</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MASSACHUSETTS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Rhode Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DA1E3FF930A35757C0A964958260" item-length="1461" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Fight Smog, 8 Northeast States Adopt New Curbs on Power Plants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A coalition of eight Northeastern states announced an agreement yesterday to impose extensive controls on electric generating stations to cut the emission of nitrogen oxides, thus opening a new front in the drive to reduce smog.</p>
        <p>Nitrogen oxides, which are among the chemicals created during combustion, play a major part in the formation of smog.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A coalition of eight Northeastern states announced an agreement yesterday to impose extensive controls on electric generating stations to cut the emission of nitrogen oxides, thus opening a new front in the drive to reduce smog.</p>
        <p>Nitrogen oxides, which are among the chemicals created during combustion, play a major part in the formation of smog.</p>
        <p>While technically the controls agreed to are recommendations, subject to approval by regulatory agencies in each state, it is those very state regulators who have now unanimously backed the proposal.  Spurred by Clean Air Act</p>
        <p>The action by New York, New Jersey and the New England States was spurred in part by the Federal Clean Air Act amendments of 1990, which call for controls but give few details. It comes amid growing scientific evidence that while regulators have concentrated on the other main precursor of smog, volatile organic chemicals, the effect of their work was limited because they had not paid enough attention to nitrogen oxides.</p>
        <p>Volatile organic chemicals are compounds of hydrogen and carbon, mostly from products derived from oil, including gasoline, paints and solvents.</p>
        <p>Also propelling state officials into action was frustration that the changes already made in cars, which include devices to limit nitrogen oxides but have given greater emphasis to control of the organic chemicals, have not eliminated dangerous levels of smog, which is known technically as ground-level ozone.</p>
        <p>At least for the next three years, the effect on a typical consumer's utility bill is expected to be measured in pennies. Utilities were not certain yesterday how much compliance would cost, but the announcement by the states indicated an annual cost of more than $100 million in the 1990's, and more in the next decade.</p>
        <p>The proposal is "a recognition of the increasing scientific evidence that volatile organic chemical controls alone will not cut the mustard," said Barbara A. Kwetz, director of air quality control at the Massachusetts Division of Environmental Protection. "It's an attempt by the states to actually implement what is in the Clean Air Act."</p>
        <p>The new regulations would require extensive changes to dozens of utility generating stations that use oil, coal and natural gas, and would have to be completed by May 1995. A second phase, requiring an additional reduction in nitrogen oxides, is scheduled to take effect in May 1999 but will be subject to review when new studies of smog formation are completed in 1994.</p>
        <p>"It's certainly a major undertaking," said Charles F. Carlin Jr., the senior engineer in the environmental compliance department at Northeast Utilities, the largest utility in New England. "This may turn out to be the most expensive portion of the new Clean Air Act for us."</p>
        <p>The Clean Air Act imposes extensive requirements for control of sulfur emissions, which cause acid rain, but Northeast, like many utilities in the New England and Middle Atlantic regions, has already eliminated most sulfur emissions.</p>
        <p>The latest move comes as the Bush Administraton is trying to reduce new regulations on business. The day before the announcement by the Northeast states, the Environmental Protection Agency issued a long-awaited guidance document to the states on how they should carry out the Clean Air Act changes, but it was silent on nitrogen oxides. States Take Action on Their Own</p>
        <p>State officials say the Environmental Protection Agency told them earlier this year that the guidance would call for weak controls, because of White House pressure. The states asked for no guidance, so they could proceed on their own.</p>
        <p>So yesterday, the Northeast States for Coordinated Air Use Management, an organization made up of the environmental commissioners of New York, New Jersey, Connecticut, Rhode Island, Massachusetts, Vermont, New Hampshire and Maine, announced unanimous approval of a pact that seeks to cut the utility emissions of nitrogen oxides by more than 50 percent.</p>
        <p>Utilities have been scrutinized for years because of their emissions of sulfur, which lead to acid rain, but experts said that outside California, regulators had rarely considered fighting smog with controls on existing electric generating stations.</p>
        <p>California already controls nitrogen oxide emissions by utilities, and Connecticut already has some controls in place.</p>
        <p>Another group, the Ozone Transport Commission, which includes all the members of the Northeast States group plus Pennsylvania, Maryland, Delaware, Virginia and Washington, D.C., has also called for controls, but has not been specific.</p>
        <p>The Northeast States group has successfully used the state-by-state approach on several occasions. In the late 1980's, the group required oil companies to make changes in gasoline to reduce hydrocarbon emissions. Last year the organization agreed to adopt California's strict standard on new cars, including cars powered by new fuels and by electricity, although the states have not completed adopting those regulations and some face substantial opposition.</p>
        <p>The effort to transplant the California vehicle standard to the Northeast is related to yesterday's announcement in two ways. First, those cars will emit smaller amounts of nitrogen oxides. Second, one argument raised by opponents of importing the California car standard was that the auto industry was being called on to do more than its fair share while other pollution sources got off easy.</p>
        <p>In a way, the Northeast States group acknowledged that yesterday, saying that thus far the utility emissions had been uncontrolled. They said that the first-phase changes, to be completed over the next two years, would cost less than $1,000 per ton of nitrogen oxides removed at most plants, and that the second-phase controls, the ones that take effect in 1999, would cost "in the range of $5,000 per ton" of emissions removed.</p>
        <p>In contrast, the organization said, other industries have been ordered to take emission control steps on hydrocarbons that cost more than $5,000 a ton, "and are anticipated to increase to the level of $10,000 per ton during the 1990's."</p>
        <p>The new rules on utilities have been in the works for months, but were delayed because of extensive consultations with the electric companies, Michael Bradley, the group's executive director, said. Some of those utilities said they faced substantial costs, but others, which rely on non-combustion sources of electricity like hydroelectric and nuclear plants, will have a smaller challenge.  Some Utilities Hope for Changes</p>
        <p>Some utilities are hoping for changes in the Northeast States agreement, which now calls for measuring the nitrogen oxide output hour by hour.</p>
        <p>At Con Edison, Dominick J. Mormile, the manager of air quality control, said the company's boilers tended to produce far lower levels of nitrogen oxides when they ran at partial capacity, as they do at night, than at full capacity, which is typical during the day.</p>
        <p>The average over 24 hours could probably be brought within the new limits, he said, but bringing the average each hour within the new limits would be difficult. He said the cost of compliance would range from $10 million to $50 million, depending on which average was used.</p>
        <p>"It's territory we haven't regulated before," said William J. O'Sullivan, an engineer with the Department of Environmental Protection and Energy in New Jersey. "As a consequence, there are some very large emitters, primarily in the utilities, with completely uncontrolled emissions that can be controlled very cost effectively."  Smog a Problem in the Summer</p>
        <p>A spokesman for one of New Jersey's major utilities, Public Service Electric and Gas, said his company was still hoping for more "flexibility" in the rules. Smog is a summer problem, he pointed out, and rather than make expensive equipment changes that would cut nitrogen oxide output all year long, his company could cut summertime nitrogen oxide production by switching from coal to natural gas, which is cleaner-burning.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Sullivan said such arrangements might still be worked out.</p>
        <p>The major population centers in the eight-state region, and even some rural parts of the area, violate Federal standards for ozone concentrations on hot summer days, when the sun cooks hydrocarbons and nitrogen oxides, producing smog.</p>
        <p>The Clean Air Act amendments of 1990 established new deadlines for compliance, with the metropolitan New York-New Jersey-Connecticut area, classified as a "severe" area, having until 2007. Most of the rest of Connecticut, along with most of Massachusetts and all of Rhode Island, was classified as having a "serious" ozone problem and was given until 1999; southern Maine, with a "moderate" problem, must comply by 1996.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
